<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6346095</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">37070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-37070-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Immunoinformatic and systems biology approaches to predict and validate peptide vaccines against Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus (EBV)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Arif</given-names></name><address><email>arif_sjtu@sjtu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8349-5181</contrib-id><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Abbas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>Aman Chandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yanjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Syed Shujait</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Junaid</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>Shoaib</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>William C. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Xueying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4200-7502</contrib-id><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Dong-Qing</given-names></name><address><email>dqwei@sjtu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0368 8293</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16821.3c</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Microbial Metabolism, and College of Life Sciences and Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Shanghai Jiao Tong University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449683.4</institution-id><institution>Center for Biotechnology and Microbiology, </institution><institution>University of Swat, </institution></institution-wrap>Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1771 451X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.415499.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Clinical Oncology, </institution><institution>Queen Elizabeth Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Kowloon, Hong Kong </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2323 5732</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.39436.3b</institution-id><institution>Qianweichang College, </institution><institution>Shanghai University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>720</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus (EBV), also known as human herpesvirus 4 (HHV-4), is a member of the Herpesviridae family and causes infectious mononucleosis, Burkitt&#x02019;s lymphoma, and nasopharyngeal carcinoma. Even in the United States of America, the situation is alarming, as EBV affects 95% of the young population between 35 and 40 years of age. In this study, both linear and conformational B-cell epitopes as well as cytotoxic T-lymphocyte (CTL) epitopes were predicted by using the ElliPro and NetCTL.1.2 webservers for EBV proteins (GH, GL, GB, GN, GM, GP42 and GP350). Molecular modelling tools were used to predict the 3D coordinates of peptides, and these peptides were then docked against the MHC molecules to obtain peptide-MHC complexes. Studies of their post-docking interactions helped to select potential candidates for the development of peptide vaccines. Our results predicted a total of 58 T-cell epitopes of EBV; &#x000a0;where the most potential were selected based on their TAP, MHC binding and C-terminal Cleavage score. The top&#x000a0;most peptides were subjected to MD simulation and stability analysis. Validation of our predicted epitopes using a 0.45&#x02009;&#x000b5;M concentration was carried out by using a systems biology approach. Our results suggest a panel of epitopes that could be used to immunize populations to protect against multiple diseases caused by EBV.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>This work is supported by the Key Research Area Grant 2016YFA0501703 from the Ministry of Science and Technology of China, and Ph.D. Programs Foundation of Ministry of Education of China (Contract No., 20120073110057).</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus (EBV), also known as human herpesvirus 4 (HHV-4), is a member of the Herpesviridae family and is one of the&#x000a0;eight known types of human herpesvirus. EBV is the most common human virus in the world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> and was isolated in 1964 from tumor cells (Burkitt&#x02019;s lymphoma) by Epstein&#x02019;s group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. EBV is related to distinct forms of cancer, such as Burkitt&#x02019;s lymphoma, stomach cancer, Hodgkin&#x02019;s lymphoma and nasopharyngeal carcinoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. A&#x000a0;High number of cases are usually reported. In the United States and other developing countries, most people are infected with EBV<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> as 90% of the adults in the United States have been formally diagnosed with EBV infection. EBV infection can be asymptomatic or symptomatic, and the latter case includes mild fatigue, fever, enlarged spleen, swollen liver, swollen lymph nodes, inflamed throat, or rashes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. From 2006 to 2015, several clinical trials were conducted to develop vaccines; however, an EBV vaccine, phase 2 trial, from gp350 protein has been testified. This vaccine reduced the rate of Infectious Mononucleosis (IM) but not virus infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Precautionary measures, such as avoiding direct contact with patients (including refraining from using a patient&#x02019;s toothbrush, sharing food, or exchanging bodily fluids), can help reduce the risk of infection. EBV can infect host B cells and booms via a nonlytic mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. EBV viral proteins play important roles in lymphoproliferative disease. For example, viral membranous proteins, such as LMP-1, may induce tumorigenic replication in infected B cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. There are two types of EBV; Epstein and Yvonne Barr identified EBV in tumor tissue associated with Burkitt&#x02019;s Lymphoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Glycoprotein 42 (gp42), Glycoprotein H, Glycoprotein L, and Glycoprotein B aid in the entrance to the host cell. Glycoprotein 42 binds to the HLA class II molecule because it is required for B cells, which inhibit epithelial cell fusion. For epithelial-cell fusion, the GH receptor protein interacts with GP42<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and GL is transported to the cell surface, which is essential for the correct folding of GH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">EBV glycoprotein B is important for viral fusion events with B cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The human immune system precisely targets EBV glycoprotein 350 (gp350), which is an example of a lytically expressed gene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The attachment of GP350 to the MHC-II molecules in the cell is aided by the already attached GP42 protein of EBV virus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. The fusion of the B-cell membrane and the outer viral envelope of the EBV virion requires functional spicule glycoproteins such as GH, GL, and gp42<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Previous studies suggest that glycoproteins such as GB complement membrane fusion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Vaccination is a significant approach to improve the standard of public health and provide an effective way to control the growing infections. In nature, plants act as bioreactors, which have been used to express efficient vaccine antigens against viral, bacterial and protozoan infections. Besides, we know that antibody epitope prediction using computational tools, one of the crucial steps of vaccine design<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Recent advancement in vaccine design has aimed for the expansion of conventional assays designed to quantify T-cell responses against various vaccine candidates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Immunoinformatic approaches have made great contributions to predicting B-cell and T-cell epitopes in the development of subunit vaccines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. For subunit vaccine development, identification of continuous B-cell or nonlinear also known as non-continuous and cytotoxic T-lymphocyte (CTL) epitopes are essential. Among B-cell epitopes, &#x0003e;90% are noncontinuous<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. The use of computational tools contribute greatly in biology designing <italic>in silico</italic> vaccine, prediction of T-cell epitope is crucial which does not only reduce the cost but also the necessity for experimental results<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Epitopic vaccine against HIV, malaria and tuberculosis resulted in&#x000a0;promising outputs and maintained the defensive and beneficial potential therapeutic uses of the developed vaccines candidates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Immunoinformatics plays an upright role in antibody and immunodiagnostic agents development, and vaccine design. The early phases of vaccine and other therapeutics agents developments were based on solely immunological experimentations. These early developmental techniques were tedious and costly too. The use of bioinformatics such as computational techniques greatly reduces the time and cost of developing such agents for therapeutic purposes. Khan <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, used multiple bioinformatics tools to predict vaccine against multiple HPV viruses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Thus the development of modern therapeutic medicines and vaccines greatly rely on such tools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Systems medicine emphases significantly on the components of pathway kinetics to probe different conditions. Systems medicine could be also utilized to investigate interaction mechanisms between microbes. Metagenomics data could be utilized for such analysis. Rather than whole cell interaction, an insight onto proteins interaction could be also comprehended through systems biology approaches (Singh, P. K. <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. These latest techniques widely expand the circle of new drugs development. Overall, it is known that multidisciplinary aspects of the production of therapeutic proteins that has gained much more attention (Dangi, A. K. <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Structural modelling using computational resources led to success in the development of computer assisted drugs. Likewise molecular docking algorithms scoring functions of different conformers to design new drug candidates.</p><p id="Par7">In the present study, potential B-cell and T-cell epitopes (as effective vaccine candidates) were identified with the help of immunoinformatic approaches. T-cell immunogenicity is associated with epitope binding strength to the MHC molecule<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Molecular modelling tools were applied to peptide-MHC complexes to investigate their post-docking interaction in order to select potential candidates for the development of peptide vaccines.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Epstein-Barr Virus Sequence</title><p id="Par8">The sequences of EBV proteins, including GH, GL, GB, GN, GM, GP42 and GP350, were retrieved from the Universal Protein knowledgebase (Uniprot) database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>). The sequence retrieval accession numbers along with other information are provided in the (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The 3D coordinates of all the selected proteins were predicted by using online webserver phyre2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk/phyre2/html/page.cgi?id=index">http://www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk/phyre2/html/page.cgi?id&#x02009;=&#x02009;index</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The overall workflow of the work is shown in the Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Detailed information, including individual protein sequence length, and region and accession number is shown in the table below.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>S. No</th><th>Uniprot Accession Number</th><th>Protein Name</th><th>No of Amino Acids</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1.</td><td>P0C763</td><td>Glycoprotein B</td><td>857</td></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>P03231</td><td>Glycoprotein H</td><td>706</td></tr><tr><td>3.</td><td>P03212</td><td>Glycoprotein L</td><td>137</td></tr><tr><td>4.</td><td>P03215</td><td>Glycoprotein M</td><td>405</td></tr><tr><td>5.</td><td>P03196</td><td>Glycoprotein N</td><td>102</td></tr><tr><td>6.</td><td>P03205</td><td>Glycoprotein 42</td><td>223</td></tr><tr><td>7.</td><td>P68343</td><td>Glycoprotein 350</td><td>886</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The figure above is showing the pipeline of the study. Resources, methods, and each step is discussed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e588"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Prediction of Linear B-Cell Epitopes</title><p id="Par9">After interacting with antigens (such as B-cell epitopes), B-lymphocyte cells differentiate into memory cells and antibody secreting plasma cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. B-cell epitopes have a hydrophilic nature and are accessible for flexible regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. IEDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iedb.org/">http://www.iedb.org/</ext-link>) online analysis resources were used to obtain the Parker hydrophilicity prediction values<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, Emini prediction values of surface accessibility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, Kolaskar and Tongaonkar&#x02019;s antigenicity scale values<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, and Karplus and Schulz Flexibility Prediction values. B-cell epitopes were predicted using ElliPro (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tools.immuneepitope.org/toolsElliPro/">http://tools.immuneepitope.org/toolsElliPro/</ext-link>) using both protein sequences and structural information<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. ElliPro utilizes the Protrusion Index (PI) of residues, protein shape approximation, and the final neighbouring residues clustering, which rely on PI.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Prediction of Potential Cytotoxic T-lymphocyte (CTL) Epitopes</title><p id="Par10">CTL epitopes were predicted using the NetCTL.1.2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetCTL/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetCTL/</ext-link>) server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. NetCTL accepts the FASTA sequence format to perform different analyses, such as prediction of MHC class I binding affinity, TAP transport efficiency and C-terminal cleavage. The artificial neural network and weight matrix were used for the prediction of MHC-I binding and proteasome-dependent C-terminal cleavage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Peptide Library Construction and Molecular Docking</title><p id="Par11">All of the predicted epitopes were modelled using the online webserver PEP-FOLD3 using 200 simulation runs to sample the conformations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> and sOPEP energy function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Subsequently, we have docked the best ranked peptide models to the selected class I MHC molecules HLA-A (PDB ID: 2GIT) using the PatchDock docking server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. The algorithm of the PatchDock server uses structural geometry to find docking transformations with good molecular shape complementarity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The resulting complexes were refined through the FireDock server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. High energy complexes were subjected to interaction analysis and molecular dynamics simulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Molecular Dynamics Simulations</title><p id="Par12">The accepted complexes were subjected to Molecular Dynamic simulations using the AMBER 14 molecular dynamics package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. The system was neutralized using Na<sup>+</sup> ions using tleap. Each system was solvated in a rectangular box with buffer distance of 8.0&#x02009;A&#x000b0; using TIP3P water molecules. A two-stage energy minimization of the complexes, using the SANDER module of AMBER 14, was performed to relieve the atomic clashes. An initial minimization of 6,000 steps, followed by another round of minimization (6,000 steps), were used to restrain the positions of all atoms in the systems, except those from the water molecules in the first minimization. The <italic>pmemd.cuda</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> software was used to simulate the minimized complexes. The SHAKE algorithm and the Particle-Mesh Ewald (PME) method were used to include the long-range interactions, and a non-bonded interaction cutoff radius of 10&#x02009;A&#x000b0; was considered. For equilibration, 10,000&#x02009;ps time was applied, followed by a 50&#x02009;ns simulation carried out at 310&#x02009;K using the Langevin temperature coupling scheme at constant pressure (1&#x02009;atm) with isotropic molecule-based scaling. Sampling of the MD trajectories was carried out every 2.0&#x02009;ps. RMSD and hydrogen bonding analysis were carried out using the integrated CPPTRAJ and PYTRAJ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> modules in AMBER 14 and were visualized using the online server PDBePISA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, UCSF Chimera<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> and PyMOL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Antigenic and Allergenic behaviour the predicted Epitopes</title><p id="Par13">To confirm the allergenic and non-allergenic properties of all the designed epitopes, B-cell and T-cell epitopes, AlgPred<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/algpred/">http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/algpred/</ext-link>), which is an online web tool was employed with accuracy of 85%. Primary amino acid sequences were used of all the selected proteins for this purpose. The antigenicity of all the epitopes was predicted by using ANTIGENpro<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/">http://scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/</ext-link>) using different machine learning algorithms to process the amino acids sequences.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>PKPD Modeling</title><p id="Par14">The design and execution of the EBV signalling cascade was performed based on a literature survey within a virtual cell. Proposed peptides were chosen for kinetic analysis of EBV, where a concentration of 0.45&#x02009;&#x000b5;m was assigned based on previous literature. Modelling of chemical reaction networks was applied for the analysis of this pathway.</p><p id="Par15">This nonlinear kinetics scheme follows the Michaelis&#x02013;Menten equation as below:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{V}}=\frac{({\rm{Vmax}})\,\cdot \,({\rm{S}})}{{\rm{Km}}+{\rm{S}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Vmax</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Km</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par16">This equation can be transformed to,<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{C}}=\frac{({\rm{Cmax}})\,\cdot \,({\rm{D}})}{{\rm{Km}}+{\rm{D}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Cmax</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Km</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>or<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{V}}=\frac{{\rm{d}}[{\rm{P}}]}{{\rm{dt}}}=\frac{({\rm{Amax}})\,\cdot \,({\rm{D}})}{{\rm{Km}}+{\rm{D}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Amax</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-.25em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Km</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par17">Here,</p><p id="Par18">C&#x02009;=&#x02009;steady state concentration;</p><p id="Par19">C<sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;theoretical maximum for C;</p><p id="Par20">A<sub>max</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;theoretical maximum for A;</p><p id="Par21">D&#x02009;=&#x02009;dose.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Sequence retrieval and analysis</title><p id="Par22">Uniprot was used to retrieve the primary amino acid sequences of the selected proteins (glycoprotein B, glycoprotein L, glycoprotein N, glycoprotein H, glycoprotein M, glycoprotein 42 and glycoprotein 350) of EBV as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Information about the protein source, accession number, number of active residues, and other information is given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The 3D structures of the selected proteins. The Phyre 2 online server was used for B-cell and T-cell epitope prediction. (<bold>A</bold>) Glycoprotein B (<bold>B</bold>) Glycoprotein H (<bold>C</bold>) Glycoprotein L (<bold>D</bold>) Glycoprotein M (<bold>E</bold>) Glycoprotein N (<bold>F</bold>) Glycoprotein 42 (<bold>G</bold>) Glycoprotein 350.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e938"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Allergenicity and antigenicity prediction</title><p id="Par23">The allergic and nonallergenic behaviours of EBV species were predicted using AlgPred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imtech.res.in/raghava/algpred/">http://www.imtech.res.in/raghava/algpred/</ext-link>). Allergenicity prediction of known protein sequences is based on similarity. We checked if the epitopes are antigenic or not using the online server AntigenPro (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/">http://www.scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. All of the proteins were found to be nonallergenic, while they possess antigenic properties (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Antigenic and allergenic results of the selected proteins.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>S.NO</th><th>Proteins</th><th>Allergenicity</th><th>Antigenicity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1.</td><td>Glycoprotein B</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>Glycoprotein H</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr><tr><td>3.</td><td>Glycoprotein L</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr><tr><td>4.</td><td>Glycoprotein M</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr><tr><td>5.</td><td>Glycoprotein N</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr><tr><td>6.</td><td>Glycoprotein 42</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr><tr><td>7.</td><td>Glycoprotein 350</td><td>Non-Allergic</td><td>Antigenic</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>B-cell epitope prediction</title><p id="Par24">The BCPred server predicted 58 B-cell epitopes: five epitopes were for GP 42, eight for GP H, nineteen for GP B, one for GP L and GP N, five for GP M, and nineteen for GP 350. However, epitopes with scores above 0.99 were selected as the most potentially antigenic epitopes. Therefore, only one epitope each from GP42, GL, GM, GN and GH; four epitopes from GB; and fifteen epitopes from GP350 were found to meet the threshold value. B-cell epitopes, along with their scores, are tabulated in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>B-Cell epitopes predicted by BCPred.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Protein</th><th>Position</th><th>Epitope</th><th>Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>GP42</td><td>43</td><td>TWVPKPNVEVWPVDPPPPVN</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>GH</td><td>623</td><td>DEKEGLETTTYITSQEVQNS</td><td>0.994</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">GB</td><td>21</td><td>GAQTPEQPAPPATTVQPTAT</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>400</td><td>TTPTSSPPSSPSPPAPSAAR</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>430</td><td>RRRDAGNATTPVPPTAPGKS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>257</td><td>YKIVDYDNRGTNPQGERRAF</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>GL</td><td>18</td><td>LPTWGNWAYPCCHVTQLRAQ</td><td>0.674</td></tr><tr><td>GM</td><td>357</td><td>TPSPGRNRRRSSTSSSSSRS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>GN</td><td>25</td><td>TGVLPAGASSPTNAAAASLT</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="15">GP350</td><td>514</td><td>TTPTPNATSPTPAVTTPTPN</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>535</td><td>TSPTPAVTTPTPNATSPTLG</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>474</td><td>TSPTPAGTTSGASPVTPSPS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>598</td><td>TSPTSAVTTPTPNATGPTVG</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>720</td><td>PAPRPGTTSQASGPGNSSTS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>577</td><td>TSPTSAVTTPTPNATSPTLG</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>556</td><td>TSPTSAVTTPTPNATSPTLG</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>423</td><td>KAPESTTTSPTLNTTGFADP</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>835</td><td>TSPPVTTAQATVPVPPTSQP</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>647</td><td>TSAVTTGQHNITSSSTSSMS</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>243</td><td>GILTSTSPVATPIPGTGYAY</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>452</td><td>THVPTNLTAPASTGPTVSTA</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>626</td><td>TNHTLGGTSPTPVVTSQPKN</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>746</td><td>NVTKGTPPQNATSPQAPSGQ</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>767</td><td>TAVPTVTSTGGKANSTTGGK</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Surface accessibility of EBV</title><p id="Par25">Threshold values &#x0003e;1 were set to predict the surface probability values. Amino acids with higher surface probability values (&#x0003e;1) have greater probability to be present on protein surfaces<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The maximum surface probability scores for Glycoprotein B (RRRRRD<sub>428&#x02013;433</sub>), Glycoprotein H (EREDRD<sub>520&#x02013;525</sub>)<sub>,</sub> Glycoprotein L (KNGSNQ<sub>68&#x02013;73</sub>), Glycoprotein M (RNRRRS<sub>362&#x02013;367</sub>), Glycoprotein N (TEAQDQ<sub>44&#x02013;49</sub>), Glycoprotein 42 (TKKKHT<sub>199&#x02013;124</sub>), and Glycoprotein 350 (PRPRYN<sub>810&#x02013;815</sub>) were 9.415, 9.265, 4.395, 9.054, 4.777, 5.691 and 4.859, respectively. The minimum surface probability scores were 0.032 (VVILVI<sub>745&#x02013;750</sub>), 0.033 (CVFCLV<sub>5&#x02013;10</sub>), 0.071 (LAICLV<sub>8&#x02013;13</sub>), 0.067 (IIPILC<sub>309&#x02013;314</sub>), 0.07 (LVLVII<sub>76&#x02013;81</sub>), 0.054 (VIVLLL<sub>18&#x02013;23</sub>), and 0.058 (AALLVC<sub>3&#x02013;8</sub>). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> (Supplementary Materials) shows the graphical representation of the predicted surface accessibility of EBV. Moreover, for all of the other proteins which have maximum and minimum accessibility scores are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> (Supplementary Materials).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Surface flexibility of EBV selected proteins</title><p id="Par26">The Karplus and Schulz flexibility method was used to calculate the motions of atoms (back and forth, considering temperature or B factor). Low B-factor values indicate a highly systematic structure, and high B factors indicate a distorted structure 32. The graphical representation of the surface flexibility results for EBV is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>. Maximum flexibility scores for Glycoprotein B, Glycoprotein H, Glycoprotein L, Glycoprotein M, Glycoprotein N, Glycoprotein 42, and Glycoprotein 350 were 1.13, 1.094, 1.121, 1.157, 1.071, 1.091, 137 for heptapeptides EQNQEQK<sub>803&#x02013;809,</sub> VITQGPN<sub>346&#x02013;442</sub>, PKNGSNQ<sub>67&#x02013;73</sub>, STSSSSS<sub>368&#x02013;374</sub>, GASSPTN<sub>31&#x02013;37</sub>, VRGGGRV<sub>31&#x02013;37</sub>, PGNSSTS<sub>733&#x02013;739</sub>, respectively. Minimum flexibility scores were 0.88, 0.872, 0.904, 0.866, 0.862, 0.897, and 0.894 for the peptides QAIMLAL<sub>795&#x02013;801</sub>, LAAMLMA<sub>351&#x02013;357</sub>, FLAICLV<sub>7&#x02013;13</sub>, FLWWVVF<sub>193&#x02013;199</sub>, IYLMYVC<sub>85&#x02013;91</sub>, VAAAAIT<sub>37&#x02013;43</sub>, and LLVMADC<sub>877&#x02013;883</sub>, respectively. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> (Supplementary Materials) shows a graphical representation of the predicted surface flexibility of EBV. Moreover, for all of the other proteins which have maximum and minimum flexibility scores are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> (Supplementary Materials).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Parker Hydrophilicity Prediction for EBV</title><p id="Par27">Hydrophilicity of the predicted epitopes was calculated using the Parker hydrophilicity approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. The graphical illustration of the predicted Parker hydrophilicity of EBV is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> (Supplementary Materials). From all of the predicted EBV peptides, the maximum hydrophilicity calculated was 6.843 for Glycoprotein 350 at the amino acid positions DNGTESK<sub>496&#x02013;502</sub>. These regions were predicted to act as active T-cell epitopes. The minimum hydrophilicity score calculated was &#x02212;7.857 for Glycoprotein M at the amino acid positions FLWWVVF<sub>193&#x02013;199</sub>. Moreover, for all of the other proteins which have maximum and minimum hydrophilicity scores are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> (Supplementary Materials).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>T-cell epitope identification</title><p id="Par28">Epitope predictions for all seven proteins were conducted on NetCTL, an online epitope prediction server. MHC-I binding prediction using the SMM method resulted in many potential epitopes against one allele, HLA-A*24:02. The weight matrix and artificial neural network was used for the prediction of MHC-I binding and proteasome dependent C-terminal cleavage. The MHC binding affinity, the TAP score, and the C-terminal cleavage score were considered to select the most promising epitopes among those predicted. The top three epitopes (as shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) for glycoprotein B (ETDQMDTIY, QMDTIYQCY, PTTVMSSIY), glycoprotein L (MTAASYARY, LTSAQSGDY, ATSVLLSAY), glycoprotein H (ALENISDIY, LLTTLETLY, SSSALTGHL), glycoprotein N (IADCVAFIY, FLALGNSFY, TTDSEEEIF), glycoprotein M (LTEAQDQFY, IASAIYLMY, ASAIYLMYV), glycoprotein 42 (CAELYPCTY, HTFQVPQNY, NTREYTFSY), and glycoprotein 350 (PTNTTDITY, FLGNNSILY, HAEMQNPVY) were selected for docking.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>List of the total peptides T-cell vaccines predicted by NetCTL.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>S.NO</th><th>Peptide Sequence</th><th>MHC Binding Affinity</th><th>Rescale Binding Affinity</th><th>C-terminal Cleavage Affinity</th><th>Transport Affinity</th><th>Prediction Score</th><th>MHC-I Binding</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3">GB</td><td>131</td><td>ETDQMDTIY</td><td>0.7945</td><td>3.3733</td><td>0.6371</td><td>2.4710</td><td>3.5924</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>134</td><td>QMDTIYQCY</td><td>0.7028</td><td>2.9841</td><td>0.9533</td><td>2.7440</td><td>3.2643</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>502</td><td>PTTVMSSIY</td><td>0.5331</td><td>2.2633</td><td>0.6136</td><td>2.5280</td><td>2.4817</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">GL</td><td>256</td><td>MTAASYARY</td><td>0.7300</td><td>3.0993</td><td>0.6470</td><td>2.9770</td><td>3.3452</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>216</td><td>LTSAQSGDY</td><td>0.7246</td><td>3.0764</td><td>0.6687</td><td>2.9570</td><td>3.3245</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>396</td><td>ATSVLLSAY</td><td>0.6201</td><td>2.6327</td><td>0.9581</td><td>3.0130</td><td>2.9271</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">GH</td><td>41</td><td>ALENISDIY</td><td>0.4625</td><td>1.9636</td><td>0.9238</td><td>2.9920</td><td>2.2518</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>107</td><td>LLTTLETLY</td><td>0.3076</td><td>1.3059</td><td>0.9638</td><td>2.7450</td><td>1.5877</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>96</td><td>SSSALTGHL</td><td>0.1437</td><td>0.6103</td><td>0.9131</td><td>1.1760</td><td>0.8060</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">GN</td><td>86</td><td>IADCVAFIY</td><td>0.6262</td><td>2.6588</td><td>0.9587</td><td>2.7190</td><td>2.9385</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>225</td><td>FLALGNSFY</td><td>0.5351</td><td>2.2720</td><td>0.8655</td><td>2.9130</td><td>2.9385</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>396</td><td>TTDSEEEIF</td><td>0.4510</td><td>1.9148</td><td>0.2635</td><td>2.3520</td><td>2.0719</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">GM</td><td>43</td><td>LTEAQDQFY</td><td>0.7612</td><td>3.2319</td><td>0.6749</td><td>2.8170</td><td>3.4740</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>81</td><td>IASAIYLMY</td><td>0.5205</td><td>2.2100</td><td>0.7658</td><td>3.0050</td><td>2.4752</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>82</td><td>ASAIYLMYV</td><td>0.1686</td><td>0.7159</td><td>0.5794</td><td>0.5250</td><td>0.8291</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">GP42</td><td>132</td><td>CAELYPCTY</td><td>0.4738</td><td>2.0117</td><td>0.9710</td><td>2.9460</td><td>2.3047</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>86</td><td>HTFQVPQNY</td><td>0.4422</td><td>1.8777</td><td>0.9494</td><td>2.9720</td><td>2.1687</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>103</td><td>NTREYTFSY</td><td>0.3707</td><td>1.5740</td><td>0.9745</td><td>2.9820</td><td>1.8693</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">GP350</td><td>316</td><td>PTNTTDITY</td><td>0.5572</td><td>2.3659</td><td>0.9498</td><td>2.3650</td><td>2.6266</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>274</td><td>FLGNNSILY</td><td>0.4340</td><td>1.8426</td><td>0.9710</td><td>2.8180</td><td>2.1291</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>143</td><td>HAEMQNPVY</td><td>0.4028</td><td>1.7103</td><td>0.7631</td><td>2.7190</td><td>1.9607</td><td>Yes</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Peptide modelling and docking studies for HLA-A*24:02 and epitope interaction analysis</title><p id="Par29">The selected top three epitopes from all proteins were docked against HLA-A*24:02 using Fire dock. The epitope QMDTIYQCY (glycoprotein B) was docked to understand the interaction pattern between peptide-MHC complexes. The global docking energy and van der Waals (vdW) energy were reported as &#x02212;35.20 (kcal/mol) and &#x02212;25.12 (kcal/mol), respectively. Residues Gln7, Cys8 and Asp3 from the docked peptides and Thr143, Tyr116, Thr80 and Lys146 from the MHC molecules were involved in binding. Peptide MTAASYARY (glycoprotein H) was reported to share a global energy of &#x02212;34.27 (kcal/mol), with &#x02212;29.12 (kcal/mol) vdW energy. On the other hand, peptides from Glycoprotein M (TTDSEEEIF), Glycoprotein N (LTEAQDQFY), Glycoprotein 42 (CAELYPCTY), and Glycoprotein 350 (PTNTTDITY) contributed global energies of &#x02212;36.20 (kcal/mol), &#x02212;34.25 (kcal/mol), &#x02212;40.20 (kcal/mol), and &#x02212;30.48 (kcal/mol), respectively. The vdW interaction energies for these complexes ranged from &#x02212;29.71(kcal/mol) to &#x02212;18.80 (kcal/mol). Residues Lys66, Arg97, Tyr99, Gln155, His114, and Thr163 from these complexes were uniformly involved in hydrogen bonding interactions. The Chimera interaction analysis tool predicted the interactions between peptide and MHC-I molecules within 3&#x001fa;. Overall, the stability was supported by the variable amounts of hydrogen bonding. The molecular interaction patterns are depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, while the interacting atoms are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Interaction pattern of the docked peptides against MHC I molecules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2138"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Molecular Docking analysis of the final peptides.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Peptide</th><th rowspan="2">Global Energy (kcal/mol)</th><th rowspan="2">vdW Energy (kcal/mol)</th><th rowspan="2">H-Bond Energy (kcal/mol)</th><th colspan="2">H-Bond Interaction</th></tr><tr><th>Peptide-MHC atom pair</th><th>d<sub>init</sub> (&#x000c5;)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>QMDTIYQCY</td><td>&#x02212;35.20</td><td>&#x02212;25.12</td><td>&#x02212;1.09</td><td>GLN7 NE2-THR143 OG1</td><td>3.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="4">Glycoprotein B</td><td>CYS8 N-TYR116 OH</td><td>3.77</td></tr><tr><td>ASP3 OD1-THR80 OG1</td><td>2.62</td></tr><tr><td>ASP3OD2-LYS146 NZ</td><td>3.95</td></tr><tr><td>MTAASYARY</td><td>&#x02212;34.27</td><td>&#x02212;29.12</td><td>&#x02212;3.82</td><td>GLN5 NE2-GLU63 O</td><td>3.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="4">Glycoprotein H</td><td>GLN5 NE2-GLU63 OE2</td><td>3.60</td></tr><tr><td>SER6 N-TYR99 OH</td><td>3.47</td></tr><tr><td>TYR9 N-GLN155 OE1</td><td>2.42</td></tr><tr><td>THR2 O-THR73 OG1</td><td>3.56</td></tr><tr><td>THR2 O-ARG97 NH1</td><td>3.63</td></tr><tr><td>SER3 OG-HIS70 NE2</td><td>3.01</td></tr><tr><td>GLN5 OE1-TYR99 OH</td><td>3.77</td></tr><tr><td>ASP8 OD2-HIS114 NE2</td><td>3.79</td></tr><tr><td>ASP8 OD2-ARG97 NH2</td><td>3.76</td></tr><tr><td>MTAASYARY</td><td>&#x02212;34.26</td><td>&#x02212;18.80</td><td>&#x02212;1.36</td><td>GLN5 NE2-THR163 OG1</td><td>2.74</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="4">Glycoprotein H</td><td>SER6 O-TYR99 OH</td><td>2.56</td></tr><tr><td>GLY7 O-ARG7 NH1</td><td>2.22</td></tr><tr><td>TYR9 OH-TRP147 NE1</td><td>3.52</td></tr><tr><td>TTDSEEEIF</td><td>&#x02212;36.20</td><td>&#x02212;29.71</td><td>&#x02212;4.82</td><td>THR1 OG1-GLU63 OE2</td><td>3.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="4">Glycoprotein M</td><td>THR1 O-LYS66 NZ</td><td>2.89</td></tr><tr><td>GLU7 OE1-ARG97 NH2</td><td>3.72</td></tr><tr><td>GLU7 OE2-ARG97 NE</td><td>3.69</td></tr><tr><td>GLU7 OE2-ARG97 NH2</td><td>3.02</td></tr><tr><td>GLU7 OE2-HIS114 NE2</td><td>3.24</td></tr><tr><td>LTEAQDQFY</td><td>&#x02212;34.25</td><td>&#x02212;24.49</td><td>&#x02212;3.30</td><td>LEU1 N-ARG65 O</td><td>3.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="4">Glycoprotein N</td><td>GLU3 OE2-TYR99 OH</td><td>2.17</td></tr><tr><td>ASP6 O-LEU156 N</td><td>3.88</td></tr><tr><td>GLN7 OE1-HIS70 NE2</td><td>3.04</td></tr><tr><td>GLU3 OE1-LYS66 NZ</td><td>3.60</td></tr><tr><td>GLU3 OE2-HIS70 NE2</td><td>3.32</td></tr><tr><td>CAELYPCTY</td><td>&#x02212;40.20</td><td>&#x02212;23.44</td><td>&#x02212;1.23</td><td>CYS7 N-THR163 OG1</td><td>3.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="4">Glycoprotein 42</td><td>THR8 OG1-THR163 O</td><td>2.95</td></tr><tr><td>TYR9 N-TYR159 OH</td><td>3.74</td></tr><tr><td>GLU3 O-GLN155 NE2</td><td>3.13</td></tr><tr><td>PRO6 O-THR163 OG1</td><td>2.03</td></tr><tr><td>THR8 O-LYS66 NZ</td><td>2.02</td></tr><tr><td>PTNTTDITY</td><td>&#x02212;30.48</td><td>&#x02212;29.45</td><td>&#x02212;3.12</td><td>THR5 OG1-THR143 OG1</td><td>3.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8" colspan="4">Glycoprotein 350</td><td>ASN3 OD1-TRP147 N</td><td>3.54</td></tr><tr><td>THR4 O-THR80 OG1</td><td>3.58</td></tr><tr><td>THR4 OG1-LYS146 NZ</td><td>2.53</td></tr><tr><td>ASP6 O-TRP147 NE1</td><td>3.57</td></tr><tr><td>ASP6 OD2-ARG97 NH2</td><td>3.50</td></tr><tr><td>ASP6 OD1-ARG97 NH2</td><td>3.89</td></tr><tr><td>ASP6 OD2-ARG97 NH2</td><td>3.50</td></tr><tr><td>ASP6 OD2-HIS114 NE2</td><td>3.27</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>PKPD modelling-based validation</title><p id="Par30">In a time-course simulation with the shortlisted peptides (obtained from the screening), the initial concentration of the top-listed peptides was set at 0.45&#x02009;&#x000b5;m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, and after 20&#x02009;seconds, all of the interactions of the EBV mechanism in the cell signalling cascade were stabilized given in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. EBV is a Baltimore Class I virus of the Herpesviridae family and plays a crucial role in lymphoproliferative disease. During tropic EBV infection, EBV binds to the HLA class II molecule, and B cells inhibit epithelial cell fusion, while the GH receptor protein interacts with GP42, and GL is transported to the cell surface where it is essential for the correct folding of GH. EBV GB is important for viral fusion events with B cells. Glycoprotein 350 binding is supported by the binding of EBV gp42 to B-cell MHC-II, while fusion of the B-cell membrane and the outer viral envelope of EBV virion must have functional spicule glycoproteins, such as GH, GL and gp42. Vaccines development requires the identification of extremely competent B-cell linear or nonlinear and CTL epitopes, where T cells act as mediators.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Model of the biochemical pathway of MDS in the presence of peptides.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2631"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The time-course simulation with screened peptides against relation of interacting EBV.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2640"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">A systems biology approach is useful to investigate T-cell epitopes in peptide sequences, and earlier reports have accelerated research leading to the development of immune biology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Root Mean Square Deviation (RMSD)</title><p id="Par32">Molecular dynamics simulation was conducted to confirm the post-docking stability of the complexes. Trajectories were obtained after 50&#x02009;ns and subjected to backbone stability using RMSD. RMSD of the selected complexes after 50&#x02009;ns revealed that all of the complexes were stable and that the peptides had occupied the binding grooves of MHC-I molecules. RMSDs of all the complexes were calculated and plotted on the graph shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. The RMSDs of all of the complexes ranged from 0.08 to 0.2&#x02009;nm. These results show that small fluctuations were observed during the simulation time, but these fluctuations are likely because some of the peptides are modelled as loop structures.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Root mean square deviation (RMSD) of the peptide-MHC complexes showing the stability of the peptides in the binding cavity of the MHC molecule.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2659"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par33">Vaccination is one of the best options for providing immunity against different pathogenic organisms, thus delivering protection against different diseases. Different types of vaccines, such as peptide, conjugated, subunit, and DNA vaccines, can be used to provoke the immune response. However, in this postgenomic and proteomic era, researchers prefer peptide or subunit vaccines over the whole pathogenic agent due to the availability and accessibility of huge data sets for different pathogens. These data can be systematically analyzed through the use of computational tools. Presentation of MHC-Antigen on the surface of T-cells provide a way to kill the infected cell. This presentation of MHC-antigen complex direct apoptosis or self-eating process of the infected cell. The antigenic element of the pathogen provoke the immune response by activating a signalling process. The peptide fragment bound to MHC molecule is primarily presented T-cell which significantly rely on different factors including proteasome cleavage and transport with the aid of ER. TAP which transporting channels or proteins help in the transport to the surface of the cell. Therefore, considering the c-terminal cleavage activity and TAP efficiency greatly help in the selection of effective vaccine candidates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Immunoinformatic approaches have contributed greatly to the development of vaccines. Therefore, we employed these tools to design peptide vaccines against EBV to provide a means to protect humanity from the multiple diseases caused by EBV, such as infectious mononucleosis, Burkitt&#x02019;s lymphoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, Hodgkin&#x02019;s lymphoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>, stomach cancer, laryngeal carcinoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, multiple sclerosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup> and lymphomatoid granulomatosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Additional diseases that have been linked to EBV include Giannotti&#x02013;Crosstie syndrome, erythema multiform, acute genital ulcers, and oral hairy leukoplakia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>; furthermore, hypersensitivity to mosquito bites has been associated with EBV infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. EBV has been implicated in disorders related to alpha-synuclein aggregation (e.g., Parkinson&#x02019;s disease, dementia with Lewy bodies, and multiple system atrophy)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. The proteome of EBV has many important functional proteins involved not only in its pathogenesis but also in the maintenance of the pathogenic condition. EBV has been reported to use its glycoproteins, such as glycoprotein B, glycoprotein L, glycoprotein H, glycoprotein N, glycoprotein M, glycoprotein 42, and glycoprotein 350, to attach to and infect its host cell. Therefore, predicting and validating both B-cell and T-cell epitopes from these proteins are important steps to provide immunity against these various diseases. Based on MHC binding affinity, TAP score, C-terminal cleavage score, molecular docking and MD simulation, we propose Glycoprotein B (QMDTIYQCY<sub>134&#x02013;142</sub>), Glycoprotein L (MTAASYARY<sub>256&#x02013;264</sub>), Glycoprotein N (TTDSEEEIF<sub>396&#x02013;404</sub>), Glycoprotein M (LTEAQDQFY<sub>43&#x02013;52</sub>), Glycoprotein 42 (CAELYPCTY<sub>132&#x02013;140</sub>), and Glycoprotein 350 (PTNTTDITY<sub>316&#x02013;324</sub>) as the final T-cell epitopes that could provoke the immune response in the host cell. The systems biology approach with pharmacokinetic/dynamics modelling validated that these epitopes significantly activates the immune response pathway and, thus, provide a strong basis for the testing of these epitopes under <italic>in vivo</italic> conditions. Structural stability analysis of the peptide-MHC complexes also revealed the stability of these immunogenic complexes. Antigenic and allergenic profiles also confirmed that these epitopes are strong candidates. Furthermore, B-cell epitopes were reported as the primary choice for the development of a B-cell immune response.</p><p id="Par34">This study provides a means for the development of peptide-based vaccines against EBV infection that could prevent many important diseases. To date, no such computational meta-analysis integrated with dynamics has been reported for the purpose of developing a peptide vaccine for EBV. This multiple step process has noticeably increased the scope and precision of this study. Our results will facilitate efficient subsequent experimental efforts, as the specified regions from Glycoprotein B (QMDTIYQCY<sub>134&#x02013;142</sub>), Glycoprotein L (MTAASYARY<sub>256&#x02013;264</sub>), Glycoprotein N (TTDSEEEIF<sub>396&#x02013;404</sub>), Glycoprotein M (LTEAQDQFY<sub>43&#x02013;52</sub>), Glycoprotein 42 (CAELYPCTY<sub>132&#x02013;140</sub>), and Glycoprotein 350 (PTNTTDITY<sub>316&#x02013;324</sub>) could be used for the development of candidate CTL epitopes. This study will aid in the progress of peptide vaccines against EBV.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par35">It is well known that EBV causes many human diseases, including cancer. This study integrated multiple approaches to elucidate possible effective peptide vaccines that could provide protection against multiple infections. This study provides insight into the disease-causing factors of EBV virus and, thus, finalized potential B-cell and T-cell epitopes that will aid in the development of effective vaccines. Despite the prediction and validation of such peptides computationally, testing of our predicted epitopes should be carried out in animal models.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_37070_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-37070-z.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Part of our computations was carried out at the High Performance Computing Center of Shanghai Jiao Tong University. This work is supported by the Key Research Area Grant 2016YFA0501703 from the Ministry of Science and Technology of China, and Ph.D Programs Foundation of Ministry of Education of China (Contract No., 20120073110057).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>A.A. has made contribution in the acquisition, analysis and interpretation of the data and drafted the manuscript. A.K., A.C.K. and M.J. involved in the design of the study. D.Q.W. is the academic supervisor and involved in the supervision of the study. W.C.C. and S.S.A. for the critical evaluationof the manuscript. S.S., X.M. and Y.W. is involved in the revision proofreading of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chesnokova</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutt-Fletcher</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fusion of epithelial cells by Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus proteins is triggered by binding of viral glycoproteins gHgL to integrins &#x003b1;v&#x003b2;6 or &#x003b1;v&#x003b2;8</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>20464</fpage><lpage>20469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0907508106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) and its associated human cancers&#x02013;genetics, epigenetics, pathobiology and novel therapeutics</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2672</fpage><lpage>2713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16720343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spectrum of Epstein-Barr virus-related diseases: a pictorial review</article-title><source>Japanese journal of radiology</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11604-008-0291-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19373526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nasopharyngeal carcinoma: molecular biomarker discovery and progress</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-6-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17199893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17199893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Asymptomatic primary infection with Epstein-Barr virus: observations on young adult cases</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2017</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>e00382</fpage><lpage>00317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00382-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28835490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odumade</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogquist</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Balfour</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress and Problems in Understanding and Managing Primary Epstein-Barr Virus Infections</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><year>2011</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/cmr.00044-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21233512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21233512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein&#x02014;Barr virus vaccines</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>1992</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0264-410X(92)90434-L</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1323899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rickinson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus: 40 years on</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Cancer</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>757</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc1452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15510157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebowitz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An EBV membrane protein expressed in immortalized lymphocytes transforms established rodent cells</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1985</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(85)90256-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3000618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Achong</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virus particles in cultured lymphoblasts from Burkitt&#x02019;s lymphoma</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><year>1964</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>702</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(64)91524-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jardetzky</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) glycoprotein B cytoplasmic C-terminal tail domain regulates the energy requirement for EBV-induced membrane fusion</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2014</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>11686</fpage><lpage>11695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01349-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25100836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutt-Fletcher</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) BZLF2 gene product associates with the gH and gL homologs of EBV and carries an epitope critical to infection of B cells but not of epithelial cells</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1995</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>3987</fpage><lpage>3994</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7539502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7539502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Buranathai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grose</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutt-Fletcher</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chaperone functions common to nonhomologous Epstein-Barr virus gL and Varicella-Zoster virus gL proteins</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1997</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1667</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8995697?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8995697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Backovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jardetzky</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of Epstein-Barr virus glycoprotein B functional domains via linker insertion mutagenesis</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2009</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01817-08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khyatti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanescu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) glycoprotein gp350 expressed on transfected cells resistant to natural killer cell activity serves as a target antigen for EBV-specific antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1991</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1846213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1846213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borza</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutt-Fletcher</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternate replication in B cells and epithelial cells switches tropism of Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>594</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm0602-594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12042810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Omerovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jardetzky</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soluble Epstein-Barr virus glycoproteins gH, gL, and gp42 form a 1: 1: 1 stable complex that acts like soluble gp42 in B-cell fusion but not in epithelial cell fusion</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2006</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>9444</fpage><lpage>9454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00572-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16973550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spear</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Longnecker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herpesvirus entry: an update</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2003</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>10179</fpage><lpage>10185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.77.19.10179-10185.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12970403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dubey, K. K. <italic>et al</italic>. Vaccine and antibody production in plants: developments and computational tools. <italic>Brief Funct Genomics</italic>, 10.1093/bfgp/ely020 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ip</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijman</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Daemen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epitope prediction assays combined with validation assays strongly narrows down putative cytotoxic T lymphocyte epitopes</article-title><source>Vaccines</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines3020203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26343185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional heterogeneity and high frequencies of cytomegalovirus-specific CD8+ T lymphocytes in healthy seropositive donors</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>8140</fpage><lpage>8150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.74.17.8140-8150.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10933725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doering</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsudaira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cysteine scanning mutagenesis at 40 of 76 positions in villin headpiece maps the F-actin binding site and structural features of the domain</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>12677</fpage><lpage>12685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi9615699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8841111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Regenmortel</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping epitope structure and activity: from one-dimensional prediction to four-dimensional description of antigenic specificity</article-title><source>Methods (San Diego, Calif.)</source><year>1996</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.1996.0054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Florea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epitope prediction algorithms for peptide-based vaccine design</article-title><source>Proc IEEE Comput Soc Bioinform Conf</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16826643?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16826643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic bioinformatics approach for selection of epitope-based vaccine targets</article-title><source>Cellular immunology</source><year>2006</year><volume>244</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cellimm.2007.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17434154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational identification, characterization and validation of potential antigenic peptide vaccines from hrHPVs E6 proteins using immunoinformatics and computational systems biology approaches</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0196484</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0196484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29715318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brusic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunoinformatics and its relevance to understanding human immune disease</article-title><source>Expert review of clinical immunology</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/1744666X.1.1.145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20477662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Large-scale validation of methods for cytotoxic T-lymphocyte epitope prediction</article-title><source>BMC bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>424</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-8-424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17973982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systems biology as an approach for deciphering microbial interactions</article-title><source>Briefings in Functional Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bfgp/elu023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24994863?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24994863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dangi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x00026; Shukla, P. Cell Line Techniques and Gene Editing Tools for Antibody Production: A Review</article-title><source>Frontiers in Pharmacology</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>630</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2018.00630</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29946262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29946262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazarski</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The kinetic stability of MHC class II: peptide complexes is a key parameter that dictates immunodominance</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2005.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16039577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kelley, L. A., Mezulis, S., Yates, C. M., Wass, M. N. &#x00026; Sternberg, M. J. E. The Phyre2 web portal for protein modeling, prediction and analysis. <italic>Nature Protocols</italic><bold>10</bold>, 845, 10.1038/nprot.2015.053<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk/phyre2/html/page.cgi?id=index">(http://www.sbg.bio.ic.ac.uk/phyre2/html/page.cgi?id&#x02009;=&#x02009;index)</ext-link> (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epitope recognition by diverse antibodies suggests conformational convergence in an antibody response</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><year>2002</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>2371</fpage><lpage>2382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.168.5.2371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11859128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fieser</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tainer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Geysen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghten</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of protein flexibility and peptide conformation on reactivity of monoclonal anti-peptide antibodies with a protein alpha-helix</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>1987</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>8568</fpage><lpage>8572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.84.23.8568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New hydrophilicity scale derived from high-performance liquid chromatography peptide retention data: correlation of predicted surface residues with antigenicity and X-ray-derived accessible sites</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1986</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>5425</fpage><lpage>5432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00367a013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2430611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emini</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of hepatitis A virus-neutralizing antibody by a virus-specific synthetic peptide</article-title><source>Journal of virology</source><year>1985</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2991600?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2991600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolaskar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tongaonkar</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A semi-empirical method for prediction of antigenic determinants on protein antigens</article-title><source>FEBS letters</source><year>1990</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(90)80535-Q</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1702393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponomarenko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ElliPro: a new structure-based tool for the prediction of antibody epitopes</article-title><source>BMC bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>514</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19055730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lamiable, A. <italic>et al</italic>. PEP-FOLD3: faster de novo structure prediction for linear peptides in solution and in complex. <italic>Nucleic acids research</italic>, gkw329 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maupetit</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuffery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Derreumaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A coarse&#x02010;grained protein force field for folding and structure prediction</article-title><source>Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.21505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Duhovny, D., Nussinov, R. &#x00026; Wolfson, H. J. In <italic>International Workshop on Algorithms in Bioinformatics</italic>. 185&#x02013;200 (Springer).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneidman&#x02010;Duhovny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Taking geometry to its edge: fast unbound rigid (and hinge&#x02010;bent) docking</article-title><source>Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.10397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrusier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FireDock: fast interaction refinement in molecular docking</article-title><source>Proteins: Structure, Function, and Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.21495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mashiach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneidman-Duhovny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrusier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussinov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfson</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FireDock: a web server for fast interaction refinement in molecular docking</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>W229</fpage><lpage>W232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chazelle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solving and analyzing side-chain positioning problems using linear and integer programming</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1028</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15546935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Case, D. A. <italic>et al</italic>. Amber 14 (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salomon-Ferrer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Grand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Routine microsecond molecular dynamics simulations with AMBER on GPUs. 2. Explicit solvent particle mesh Ewald</article-title><source>Journal of chemical theory and computation</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3878</fpage><lpage>3888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct400314y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26592383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheatham</surname><given-names>TE</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>PTRAJ and CPPTRAJ: software for processing and analysis of molecular dynamics trajectory data</article-title><source>Journal of chemical theory and computation</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3084</fpage><lpage>3095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct400341p</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26583988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krissinel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference of macromolecular assemblies from crystalline state</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2007.05.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17681537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UCSF Chimera. A visualization system for exploratory research and analysis. Resource for Biocomputing, Visualization, and Informatics (RBVI), UCSF. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rbvi.ucsf.edu/chimera/">http://www.rbvi.ucsf.edu/chimera/</ext-link> (2004).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The PyMOL molecular graphics system. Schr&#x000f6;dinger, Inc. https://www.pymol.org/ (2002).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AlgPred: prediction of allergenic proteins and mapping of IgE epitopes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>W202</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl343</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16844994?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16844994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweredoski</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SCRATCH: a protein structure and structural feature prediction server</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W72</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki396</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15980571?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)-encoded protein kinase, EBV-PK, but not the thymidine kinase (EBV-TK), is required for ganciclovir and acyclovir inhibition of lytic viral production</article-title><source>Journal of virology</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>4534</fpage><lpage>4542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02487-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20181711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Flow cytometric analysis of herpes simplex virus type 1 susceptibility to acyclovir, ganciclovir, and foscarnet</article-title><source>Antimicrobial agents and chemotherapy</source><year>1997</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>2686</fpage><lpage>2692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.41.12.2686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9420039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saijo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzutani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Niikura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurane</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of C&#x02010;terminus of herpes simplex virus type 1 thymidine kinase for maintaining thymidine kinase and acyclovir&#x02010;phosphorylation activities</article-title><source>Journal of medical virology</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.2157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11793392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alberts, B. <italic>et al</italic>. <italic>Molecular Biology of the Cell, Sixth Edition</italic> (Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brusic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bajic</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovsky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational methods for prediction of T-cell epitopes&#x02014;a framework for modelling, testing, and applications</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2004</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2004.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15542369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundegaard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke&#x0015f;mir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the proteasome in generating cytotoxic T-cell epitopes: insights obtained from improved predictions of proteasomal cleavage</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00251-005-0781-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15744535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15744535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Malley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benign lymphadenopathies</article-title><source>Modern pathology: an official journal of the United States and Canadian Academy of Pathology, Inc</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S88</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/modpathol.2012.176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pannone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of EBV in the pathogenesis of Burkitt&#x02019;s Lymphoma: an Italian hospital based survey</article-title><source>Infectious agents and cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-9378-9-34</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25364378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25364378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mechelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epstein-Barr virus genetic variants are associated with multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2015</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1362</fpage><lpage>1368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000001420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25740864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ascherio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein-barr virus infection and multiple sclerosis: a review</article-title><source>Journal of neuroimmune pharmacology: the official journal of the Society on NeuroImmune Pharmacology</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11481-010-9201-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20369303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tagliavini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lymphomatoid granulomatosis: a practical review for pathologists dealing with this rare pulmonary lymphoproliferative process</article-title><source>Pathologica</source><year>2013</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24466760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24466760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Lernia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epstein-Barr virus and skin manifestations in childhood</article-title><source>International journal of dermatology</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1177</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-4632.2012.05855.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24073903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24073903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyriakidis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Primary EBV infection and hypersensitivity to mosquito bites: a case report</article-title><source>Virologica Sinica</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12250-016-3868-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27900557?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27900557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woulfe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoogendoorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarnopolsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibodies against Epstein-Barr virus cross-react with alpha-synuclein in human brain</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2000</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1398</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.55.9.1398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11087792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGrath, P. Cancer virus discovery helped by delayed flight. <italic>BBC World Service.&#x02013;2004. Available at</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bbc.com/news/health-26857610">http://www.bbc.com/news/health-26857610</ext-link> (2015).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>