<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Damages.</div>
 <p id="P15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Damages as a percent of GDP were calculated by multiplying a constant by the square of the temperature change since the baseline period. For example, 
  <span class="italic">D</span>(2050) = 
  <span class="italic">a</span> · Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>(2050)
  <span class="sup">2</span>· GDP. The net present value is then calculated using the discount rate such that NPV(
  <span class="italic">D</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>)) = 
  <span class="italic">D</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>)/(1+
  <span class="italic">r</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">t</span>–2010
  </span>. 
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">Hsiang et al. (2017)</a> present a recent justification for using a quadratic function for damages. For the sensitivity analysis, damage exponents of 1.5 or 3 were considered. Other formulations of the damage function have been considered in the literature. The first alternative is explicit calculation of damages within integrated assessment models. Another alternative is to include a higher-power term in addition to the square exponent so that at low temperatures damages rise quadratically, but at high temperatures damages accelerate (
  <a rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" href="#R63">Weitzman, 2010</a>). Finally, some analyses account for the impact of climate change on the economic growth rate, finding substantially higher damages (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">Dell et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">Moore and Diaz, 2015</a>). The damage constant (
  <span class="italic">a</span>) (which cancels out in this particular application) and the GDP pathway are taken from the Nordhaus DICE model (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">Nordhaus, 2017</a>). Sensitivity analyses used a growth of 0.5 and 1.5 times that of the baseline growth for each 5-year time period in the Nordhaus scenario. The GDP growth rates over the 21st century from DICE (2.5 %) and the high and low growth rate scenarios (1.3% and 3.8 %) are consistent with the estimate of 21st century per capita GDP growth from 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">Christensen et al. (2018)</a> of 2.1% (with a standard deviation of 1.1 %), when added to the population growth rate of 0.4% from DICE (see the 
  <a rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#SD1">Supplement</a> for a graph of the GDP scenarios). A temperature offset was also used because it is not clear what baseline temperature should be used for the damage function. A central value of 0.6 °C (the temperature change from 1951– 1980 compared to 2011 based on the NASA GISSTemp surface temperature record; 
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">GISTEMP, 2017</a>) is used, with sensitivities of 0 °C as a lower bound and 0.8 °C (the temperature change from 1880 to 2012 from the 2014 National Climate Assessment) as an upper bound. For the RCP3PD scenario, some future years (fewer than 1 out of 1000 of the total years considered across all sensitivities and generally only for years near the end of the analysis) are cooler than the baseline temperature; in those years the net temperature change is set to zero to avoid numerical problems.
 </p>
</sec>
