<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Future climate change and its impacts on air quality in China are estimated from numerical simulations with a regional coupled climate-chemistry modeling system established using the dynamical downscaling technique. The description of the modeling system is detailed in a previous paper (
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In the modeling system, the regional 2-way coupled WRF-CMAQ model with aerosol direct effects is used to dynamically downscale the global climate from the CESM-NCSU (
 <xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
 <xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr"/>
 <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr"/>
 <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr"/>
 <xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr"/>
 <xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr"/>–
 <xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) for a high-resolution regional climate and air quality simulation under a changing climate. The dynamical downscaling technique takes full advantage of global climate-chemistry models that can accurately predict large-scale global changes and regional models that can better represent regional phenomena. The current year simulations of the CESM-NCSU and WRF-CMAQ have been evaluated against observations to validate the model’s simulation of global (
 <xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>) and regional (
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) climate and air quality. A comprehensive evaluation indicates that the CESM-NCSU provides a reasonable representation of the current global atmosphere, making it suitable for future climate simulations (
 <xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). In general, most meteorological variables are accurately simulated in the CESM-NCSU. The regional WRF-CMAQ model also performed well under the multiyear climatological application for both major meteorological variables and chemical variables and, in particular, outperformed global models in predicting the high PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> concentrations in urban areas as well as the surface ozone concentrations in China (
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Thus, it can better support a high-resolution health impact assessment. The regional WRF-CMAQ model reproduced the spatial distributions and seasonal and daily variations of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and ozone concentrations well (
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Comparisons of future climate changes projected by the CESM-NCSU with an ensemble of Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) (
 <xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) models are provided in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic>SI Appendix</italic>, 
  <italic>SI Text</italic> and Fig. S7
 </ext-link>). In summary, despite some discrepancies with CMIP5 models, the CESM-NCSU generally captures the sign and magnitude of future climate trends, thus providing a reasonable representation of future climate change.
</p>
