<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Policy conclusions and limitations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this work we tackled a policy relevant problem in the realm of energy economics and energy analytics using a novel technique, namely Functional Data Analysis (FDA). FDA has that helped identifying drivers of electricity consumption, its derivative and the impacts of having received a real time in-home display on the whole daily, temporal load. Results have revealed time varying patterns of energy consumption and their relation with ownership of three different clusters of electric appliances. Depending on the time of day, ownership of appliances belonging to different clusters drives electricity consumption and its instantaneous change. We also use the fact that the households in our sample have received a display providing real time information on their consumption to determine whether appliance ownership has determined a change in daily use of electricity. Comparing pre- and post- intervention consumption, the analysis indicates that despite we observe a statistically significant drop in electricity use, this doesn’t appear to be related with the structure of ownership of appliances. This is an important and novel insight, given the policy request to understand who should be the to target of these behavioural and informational interventions [
  <a rid="pone.0218702.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218702.ref040">40</a>] and the absence of this kind of analysis in the current literature [
  <a rid="pone.0218702.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218702.ref041">41</a>]. Previous research has documented significant heterogeneity in aggregated energy demand response to energy efficiency programs [
  <a rid="pone.0218702.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218702.ref042">42</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0218702.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218702.ref044">44</a>], with socio-demographics and historical consumption showing up as important mediators. Despite our sample showing a large distribution of energy consumption as well as of ownership of appliances, the statistical results point to a limited role of energy-using technology on the effectiveness of providing residential users with real time information about energy use and costs. The context of a regulated market with limited price differentiation between times of the day might help explain this absent correlation. Further studies carried out with state of the art randomized controlled trials should help investigate these issues further. Only by deepening our understanding of the levers which can enable smart technologies to work, we can fully evaluate their cost effectiveness and the case for specific policy support.
 </p>
</sec>
