<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The CCASE experiment consists of six plots (each 11 X 13.5 m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>), each centered on a minimum of three mature red maple trees (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0171928.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). Two plots serve as reference (hereafter referred to as “
 <italic class="italic">reference</italic>”), two have soils warmed 5°C throughout the snow-free season (hereafter referred to as “
 <italic class="italic">warmed</italic>”), and two others have soils warmed 5°C throughout the snow-free season with soil FTCs induced in winter (hereafter referred to as “
 <italic class="italic">warmed + FTC</italic>”). All six plots are dominated by mature red maple trees, which make up 63.1 ± 6.9% basal area with an understory composed of mostly American beech (
 <xref rid="pone.0171928.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The depth of the organic layer is on average 5.2 ± 0.3 cm and soils in this experiment are classified as sand and loamy sands (M. Vadeboncoeur, 
 <italic class="italic">personal communication</italic>). We purposefully located the plots to have similar basal area of individual tree species and total basal area across all tree species among plots (
 <xref rid="pone.0171928.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). We did not randomly assign treatments across the six plots because of logistical constraints associated with electrical infrastructure. Future studies should take into account the trade-offs between replication of experimental treatments and size of individual plots given the high cost of both infrastructure and energy required to heat the plots. It would have been ideal in this experiment to have a greater number of plots per treatment. Because our goal was to evaluate both below- and aboveground responses to changes in temperature in this tall statured ecosystem, we chose to have relatively large plots that were replicated only twice.
</p>
