<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study tested the impact of experimentally manipulated food availability on the reproductive performance of the northern wheatear, a long-distance migratory insectivorous bird, with implications for the potential effects of climate- and land-use-driven changes in food in the breeding areas. The experimental increase in food availability increased the annual reproductive output of the wheatears breeding on Fair Isle by increasing the frequency of pairs raising second broods and males raising broods with more than one female (polygyny). The experimental increase in food availability had no detectable effect on clutch size or the number of fledglings produced from first broods.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As well as leading to an increase in the production of fledglings produced over the breeding season, food supplementation also advanced hatching date of first broods and increased chick quality (as measured by body size). Specifically, increased food availability led to an advance in hatching date of first broods by approximately 3 days, an increase in the wing length of chicks measured at 7 and 8 days of age in 2009 (but not in 2010) (which could either represent a larger fledging size or more rapid growth towards an unaltered fledging size).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The advance in hatching dates of first broods of food-supplemented wheatears relative to controls indicates that the timing of breeding was constrained by natural food availability on Fair Isle. Food supplementation within a territory was initiated only once a pair was seen to have formed by their behaviour. This was necessary to avoid a situation where birds arriving on Fair Isle in the spring chose those territories with supplementary food, which could have led to the feeding treatment being distributed unevenly with respect to individual quality and arrival dates and confounded the experiment. Clutches of fed pairs were initiated approximately 17 days after feeders within their territories were deployed. The result of designing the experiment in this way means that food supplementation likely occurred over only part of the adult female developmental phase of reproduction, which occurs before egg laying 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Wingfield1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Wingfield1">[37]</a>. Despite this, we observed a 3-day advance in hatching dates (highly correlated with laying dates) of fed wheatears relative to unsupplemented controls. Advances in breeding date from food supplementation at the breeding site are also widely reported in resident and short-distance migratory songbirds 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Martin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Martin1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Robb1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Robb1">[11]</a>. The extent of advance in breeding date in response to increased food was similar to our study for some of these species (e.g. 2 days for jackdaws 
  <span class="italic">Corvus monedula</span> and 5 days for great tits 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Soler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Soler1">[14]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Kllander1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Kllander1">[38]</a> but much greater in others, such as 18 days in song sparrows (
  <span class="italic">Melospiza melodi</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Arcese1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Arcese1">[15]</a>. The timing of initiation of supplemental feeding relative to laying dates may influence the extent of advance in laying dates, but the link is not clear; in the three examples above, experimental provisioning began much earlier in the jackdaw study than in the great tit or song sparrow studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The earlier date of first clutches induced by food supplementation may have contributed to an increased reproductive output by increasing the time available for females to lay a second clutch following fledging of their first. Additional breeding attempts were very rare by control pairs, however, even by those that began breeding early, suggesting that the increase in the number of breeding attempts was likely to depend on food availability in combination with early breeding, and not just on early breeding 
  <span class="italic">per se</span>. Wheatears that initiated their first brood earlier and had access to supplemental food were more likely to have second broods (and, in the case of males, have simultaneous broods). A higher proportion of pairs that initiated a first brood subsequently initiated second broods in 2009 (6.5%) than in 2010 (1.9%), which is consistent with the earlier start to breeding in 2009 (hatch date in 2009 was 8 days earlier than in 2010). The proportion of males initiating simultaneous broods was, however, higher in 2010 (9.6%) than in 2009 (4.3%), but simultaneous brooding will be less time-limited than second brooding. Consistent with our findings, experimental and natural changes in food availability led to changes in numbers of breeding attempts in black-throated blue warblers (
  <span class="italic">Dendroica caerulescens</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Nagy1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Nagy1">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Rodenhouse1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Rodenhouse1">[39]</a> and song sparrows 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Arcese1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Arcese1">[15]</a>. In support of our finding that earlier breeding alone does not increase rates of multiple brooding, food-supplementation of resident breeding birds during pre-laying and laying stages only resulted in advanced laying dates but no impact on number of clutches initiated 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Smith1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Smith1">[40]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Bolton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Bolton1">[41]</a>. In an observational study of wheatears 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Tye1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Tye1">[42]</a>, earlier breeding was associated with greater fledging success of first broods and with a higher probability of second brooding, but in the absence of food manipulation it is not certain whether food availability (as breeding timing is likely related to territory quality) underpinned these results. In a long-term Swedish study, older male wheatears had higher reproductive success than yearling males, probably because older birds arrive on breeding grounds earlier, allowing them to commence breeding sooner as well as potentially gain the best territories 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Prt1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Prt1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Prt2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Prt2">[25]</a>. In our experimental study, high quality early-arriving males with supplementary food may be able to expend more energy on defending larger territories and attracting additional mates compared to lower quality late-arriving males that may be more constrained in their territory choice.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The low rates of total nest failure in this study are in stark contrast with other studies of wheatears. Only about 8% of first clutches in the current study failed to produce any fledglings, while total failure rates of about 41%, 30% and 21% were recorded in East Anglia 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Tye1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Tye1">[42]</a> and two studies in Sweden 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Arlt1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Arlt1">[22]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Moreno1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Moreno1">[28]</a>, respectively. It is therefore possible that increases in food availability have a greater effect on the reproductive parameters measured on Fair Isle than among wheatears living in areas where predation risk is a greater determinant of breeding success. This would be an interesting avenue of future research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The supplemented food in our study also resulted in increased chick (and therefore probably fledgling) quality, as measured by chick size at age 7–8 days. These results are consistent with those of natural and experimental food reduction, which led to decreased nestling growth rates of black-throated blue warblers 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Rodenhouse1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Rodenhouse1">[39]</a>. The magnitude of the effect in our study did, however, vary between years, suggesting that food availability is not always equally limiting to chick growth.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although food supplementation had measurable effects on hatching date, the number of breeding attempts and chick growth, other reproductive parameters appeared to be unaffected. There was no difference in clutch size or hatching success of first broods, which explains why food-supplementation also did not increase the number of chicks fledged from first broods. It is possible that our sample size was not large enough to detect an effect. In support of our results, however, food supplementation had no effect on the number of fledglings from first broods in black-throated blue warblers 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Nagy1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Nagy1">[8]</a>, while clutch size was higher in food-supplemented pairs in only five of 14 species (comprising non-migratory and short-distance migrant species) reviewed by Arcese and Smith 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Arcese1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Arcese1">[15]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study provides evidence that the number of breeding attempts that can be fitted into each breeding season is currently limited both by food availability, and by the date of initiation of the first brood. Our food supplementation was uniformly high across the whole breeding season, yet high altitude and high latitude moorland habitats typically have short growing/breeding seasons, with highly peaked food availability 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Both2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Both2">[43]</a>. Phenological changes associated with climate change are, indeed, already resulting in earlier spring arrivals of migratory songbirds. The timing of autumn departures are also advancing, however, leading to a shift in the breeding season with no increase in its duration 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Cotton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Cotton1">[44]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0111180-VanBuskirk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-VanBuskirk1">[46]</a>. The variation between years in the frequency of second broods in our study suggests that other factors (e.g. weather and availability of key prey taxa), as well as overall food availability, may affect multiple brooding. As well as environmental conditions at the breeding grounds, breeding date of migratory birds depends on spring arrival date and arrival body condition, both of which are affected by environmental factors at the wintering grounds and migration routes 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Studds1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Studds1">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Coppack1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Coppack1">[47]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Rockwell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Rockwell1">[48]</a>. Breeding close to the wintering grounds, resident and short-distance migrants may be less time-constrained in their response to environmental change than long-distance migrants 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Berthold1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Berthold1">[49]</a>. Temperature changes may also have direct impacts on bird reproduction that may have consequences for duration of the breeding season. For example, great tits kept at higher temperatures began laying at the same time as controls but terminated laying, regressed their testes and started post-breeding moult earlier, despite food being provided ad libitum 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Visser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Visser1">[50]</a>. To understand the implications of our finding that food availability may affect fledgling production in wheatears via changes in breeding attempts, it is important to understand how climate change will affect the timing and shape of food peaks, food abundance and the direct impact on wheatear behaviour and physiology of factors such as temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study has shown that food supplementation increased fitness of northern wheatears by providing resources needed for second broods. In addition, while no additional chicks were fledged from first broods, the chicks were larger which may aid post-fledging survival 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Seward1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Seward1">[27]</a> and increase fitness as an adult. This has clear implications for the impact of changes in food availability due to environmental change, although caution is always required in extrapolating results to other populations, species or even to other years 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Both2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Both2">[43]</a>. There may also be independent, direct effects of environmental variables such as temperature and rainfall on breeding parameters 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Salvante1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Salvante1">[51]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Visser2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Visser2">[52]</a>. Much of the literature on the impacts of climate change on birds has focussed on the issue of mismatches between timing of breeding and the timing of peaks in food availability 
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Both3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Both3">[53]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0111180-Reed1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0111180-Reed1">[55]</a>. By increasing food availability uniformly across the whole breeding season, we have been unable to address the impact of changes in the timing of peaks in the food supply of wheatears. Instead, our experiment measured the degree of phenotypic plasticity in a range of breeding parameters, revealing the extent to which individual birds can respond instantly to changes in environmental conditions. If the range of climate (and thus food) variability that the birds' phenotypic plasticity encompasses is exceeded, then there will be selective pressure for evolutionary change.
 </p>
</sec>
