<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The simulations analyzed come from the CESM‐LME project (Otto‐Bliesner et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), made available via the Earth System Grid (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.earthsystemgrid.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.earthsystemgrid.org</ext-link>). The CESM version 1.1 (Hurrell et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) was integrated with the land carbon‐atmosphere system coupled at a spatial resolution of roughly 2°×2°, and the ocean and sea ice system at approximately 1°×1° (the CESM grid is encoded as 1.9x2.5_gx1v6). The land component of the ESM is the Community Land Model version 4 coupled with carbon‐nitrogen cycle (CLM4CN) including key biophysical, biogeochemical processes, and human‐made disturbances on terrestrial ecosystems (Hurrell et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Lawrence et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Oleson et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Thornton et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). The CESM‐LME simulations were shown to reproduce interannual variability and decadal mean values of land and ocean carbon sinks comparable to other ESMs of the Coupled Model Inter‐Comparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) when compared to observational estimates during the late twentieth century (Hoffman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Hurrell et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Lehner et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). The CMIP5 forcing (Schmidt et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) prescribed to the CESM includes solar irradiance, changes from Earth's orbital parameters, solar variability with an 11 years periodicity, volcanic eruptions, LULCCs, and atmospheric concentrations of long‐lived and well‐mixed greenhouse gases (GHGs; namely, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O). The temporal evolution of these major external forcings has been shown in Fig. 2 in Otto‐Bliesner et al. (
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The variation in this record of GHGs (derived from ice cores in Antarctica) relates not only to natural feedback in the carbon and nitrogen cycles to changes in climate but also to some early anthropogenic perturbations, such as from land use change due to agriculture (Gasser &amp; Ciais, 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Gerber et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Schmidt et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). The imposed LULCC is the only forcing applied to land areas; this was derived from a historical mapping of agricultural areas and population‐based proxies for agricultural activity. The resulting LULCC affects the surface albedo, surface roughness, soil characteristics, water cycling, and carbon turnover. The CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions due to land use change are not considered in LULCC, since they are implicitly incorporated in the reconstructed GHG record. We noticed that there is a small step‐change in the LULCC data at the year 1500, which is an artifact from the merger of two different land‐cover datasets (Otto‐Bliesner et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), scaling the Pongratz reconstruction (Pongratz et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) to match the Hurtt dataset (Hurtt et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) at the year 1500 at each land grid cell. Our calculation shows that this artificial change at 1500 of the LULCC forcing has led to a large emission of the CESM‐LME modeled D and significant influence on NBP at that year (Figure 
 <xref rid="jame20902-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref> in the 
 <xref rid="jame20902-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">supporting information</xref>). To avoid its potential effect to our results, we replaced the values at the year 1500 of all variables (NBP, NPP, RH, D, and all carbon pools) from all simulations with an average of 5 years (1495‐1499) before and 5 years (1501‐1505) after 1500.
</p>
