<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A degree of specialization in utilization of habitats during breeding and non-breeding stages of life is variable among animals, including birds 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Morrison1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Morrison1">[1]</a>. Species that are not strictly associated with a very special habitat can settle in different habitats, varying in suitability and quality, which enforces individuals or breeding pairs to decide where to settle to maximize benefits and minimize costs in fitness 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Fretwell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Fretwell1">[2]</a>. In addition, ecological conditions in settlement habitats differ also among years, which may change profitability of settlement decisions. In the case of breeding habitats, settlement decisions are directly translated into offspring numbers and quality 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Fretwell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Fretwell1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Chalfoun1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Chalfoun1">[3]</a>. Inter-habitat and inter-annual differences in clutch size and other components of reproductive success have long been found in population studies 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Kluijver1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Kluijver1">[4]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Mgi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Mgi1">[10]</a>. Such differences have also been revealed in our study system 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Marciniak1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Marciniak1">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura1">[12]</a>. Breeding habitat preferences seem to result from variation in availability of nesting sites and food in interaction with the risk of predation and parasite infestations 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Chalfoun1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Chalfoun1">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins1">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Martin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Martin1">[13]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Wilkin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Wilkin1">[16]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unfortunately, variation in habitat quality is notoriously difficult to assess in the field 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Morrison1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Morrison1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-VanBalen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-VanBalen1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Mgi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Mgi1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Wilkin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Wilkin1">[16]</a>. Such an assessment is important for population ecology, but also for conservation biology, especially in association with human-induced changes in habitats. Because different hematological and physiological characteristics of birds have been found to consistently differ among habitats in relation to habitat properties 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Gavett1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Gavett1">[17]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura2">[25]</a>, an idea has been developed that ecological physiology could support conservation by providing some tools for assessing habitat quality 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Wikelski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Wikelski1">[26]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Ellis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Ellis1">[29]</a>. Both ecological physiology and conservation biology are especially interested in physiological stress reaction of organisms in response to detrimental factors (stressors) occurring in the environment at different spatio-temporal scales 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Marra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Marra1">[30]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Payne1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Payne1">[34]</a>. Stress reaction is adaptive because it adjusts physiological functions to compensate for potentially harmful disturbances of homeostasis 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Bradshaw1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Bradshaw1">[35]</a>, but obviously allocation of resources in stress response is traded-off with other functions, especially immunity, and, therefore, costly 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Lochmiller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Lochmiller1">[36]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Romero1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Romero1">[38]</a>. As a result, prolonged stress responses developed under the influence of chronic stressors lead to fitness costs; habitats that produce chronic stressors are considered as low-quality environments 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Albano1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Albano1">[28]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Ellis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Ellis1">[29]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Maron1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Maron1">[33]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Busch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Busch1">[39]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As mediators in vertebrate stress response, glucocorticoid hormone concentration in blood provides direct metrics of stress 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Siegel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Siegel1">[40]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Johnstone1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Johnstone1">[42]</a>. Because handling of birds for taking a blood sample as well as a capture method may constitute a strong stressor in response to which glucocorticoid level changes very rapidly, alternative indicators of stress have also been analyzed, including heterophil-to-lymphocyte ratio (H/L ratio, hereafter) and stress proteins (see 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Johnstone1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Johnstone1">[42]</a> for review). The H/L ratio turned out to be a reliable indicator of chronic stress that develops over a longer time 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Ots1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Ots1">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Vleck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Vleck1">[41]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Gross1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Gross1">[43]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Davis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Davis1">[45]</a>. In nestlings of different bird species, the H/L ratio is sensitive to different stressors, especially factors associated with food conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Suorsa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Suorsa1">[32]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-HoiLeitner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-HoiLeitner1">[46]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Muller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Muller1">[49]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura6" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura6">[60]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nestlings of hole-nesting altricial birds grow in nests that are relatively safe and well isolated from external factors, which is considered to be the reason for a relatively long time of their post-hatching development 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Ricklefs1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Ricklefs1">[50]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-OConnor1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-OConnor1">[51]</a>. Therefore, the outside environment influences nestlings mostly indirectly through their parents, especially through variable quality of parental care, including nest sanitation, brooding, and, first of all, food amount, quality and delivery frequency. In blue tits 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span> and great tits 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> the involvement in parental care differs between the sexes but participation of both parents in feeding nestlings is essential for nestling growth and survival 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins2">[52]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura5" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura5">[54]</a>. Amounts of food, preferably caterpillars, and regularity of its delivery to nestlings depends on its abundance and spatial distribution, which may differ between habitats and years 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins1">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Marciniak1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Marciniak1">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins2">[52]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura4">[53]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins3">[55]</a>. Human-induced changes in habitat structure and function, such as forest fragmentation and management, are known to negatively influence insect abundance and bird foraging 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Burke1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Burke1">[56]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Hinsley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Hinsley1">[58]</a>, leading to physiological stress in birds 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Suorsa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Suorsa1">[32]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Suorsa2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Suorsa2">[59]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Busch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Busch1">[39]</a>. Moreover, exposure to human visitors may disturb the regularity of feeding nestlings by parental birds 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura2">[25]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura6" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura6">[60]</a>. All this suggests that stress indicators of nestling tits may indeed be used as indicators of habitat quality and should display some predictable patterns of variation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blue tits and great tits belong to the commonest and most numerous passerines in the Western Palearctic 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins2">[52]</a>. Although they evolved as forest species, adapted to conditions of deciduous and mixed forests, in contrast to other species of parids, blue tits and great tits also regularly nest in various tree patches, even in city centers 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins2">[52]</a>. This suggests that they are more ecologically plastic than other parids. In spite of this general plasticity, great tits are more generalist than blue tits with respect to the food of the breeding period, with blue tits being more specialized in foraging on tree canopy caterpillars as key food of nestlings 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Perrins2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Perrins2">[52]</a>, . Being strictly dependent on leaf-eating caterpillars, blue tits are also likely to be more sensitive than great tits to human-induced changes in the structure of habitats 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Nour1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Nour1">[57]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Hinsley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Hinsley1">[58]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main idea of this paper is that the environment subjects nestling tits to stress mostly through the food delivered by parental birds. Since trophic conditions differ among habitats and years, variation in physiological indicators of stress is expected to display a consistent pattern. Because blue tits are a little different from great tits in their degree of dependence on caterpillars, an inter-species difference in stress indices is also expected. General physical conditions, which constitute a background for nestling development, may also impact nestlings independently of food. Particularly, high temperature is a potential stressor that might induce elevated H/L ratios in nestlings and might differ between study sites.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consequently, the aim of this study was to examine the following predictions concerning the H/L ratio variation in nestling blue tits and great tits:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">- because of higher ecological sensitivity of blue tits in comparison with great tits, we expected that a corresponding difference should occur in chronic stress response, reflected in the H/L ratio,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">- because trophic conditions for growing nestlings are better in the forest site than in the parkland site, we predicted that the H/L ratio of nestlings should be higher in the parkland,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">- because food abundance and weather conditions during the nestling period tend to differ among years, we expected that the H/L ratio should also be variable between years,</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">- in addition, since the study sites differ in tree cover and the degree of insolation, we checked if maximal temperatures differ between the sites.</p>
</sec>
