<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The individual H/L ratios were ln-transformed (ln (1+H/L)) to meet assumptions of analyses, but are presented in a non-transformed form in the figures and the text. Because the H/L ratios of nestlings from the same brood are not independent, the ln-transformed H/L ratios were analyzed using mixed linear models, with brood Id included as a random factor controlling for clustering; degrees of freedom were estimated by the Satterthwaite method 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Heck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Heck1">[64]</a>. Effects of different factors on the H/L ratio were modeled in an ANCOVA style by first fitting a model that included wing length as an age-controlling covariate and all factors of interest. We previously confirmed that wing length is a reliable and precise measure of age in average trophic conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Babura3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Babura3">[48]</a>. The covariate was removed from the model when non-significant or retained when significant to produce the final model presented in the paper 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Crawley1">[65]</a>. The comparison of the H/L ratios between first-brood nestling blue tits and great tits did not include the wing-length covariate because of a distinct difference in body size between these species; species identity was the main factor in this comparison, with year and site providing only a background. The year and site factors were basic factors in within-species analyses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat-specific temperatures recorded with DS1921G Thermochron iButton loggers in 2012 were compared between the parkland site and the forest site using t-test, with average May temperatures for individual loggers being unit data points. Peak annual frassfall values during 2005–2012 were compared between the sites using paired t-test.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analyses were performed using IBM SPSS 20 software 
  <a rid="pone.0074226-Heck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0074226-Heck1">[64]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
