<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fledging and recruitment success</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The negative effect of rainfall on fledging success was stronger in the later part of the nestling period when the overall energy demands of the nestlings are expected to be the highest. This suggests that food shortages during the period with highest net energy demand for offspring (because of growth, body size, and endothermic metabolism) may reduce their condition below a threshold from which they cannot recover. Younger nestlings, on the other hand, are ectothermic and hence may be able to reduce their metabolism to low levels during periods of adverse weather conditions. Furthermore, young nestlings are often brooded by the female (Conder 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">1989</a>), and during poor weather conditions, females may increase their time spent brooding to protect the young (Radford et al. 
  <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2001</a>; own observations).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By contrast, recruitment success was related to the number of days of rainfall during the first half of the nestling period. Rainfall effects may not only increase the risk of mortality for nestlings but may also reduce growth rates (Conder 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">1989</a>; Keller and van Noordwijk 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1994</a>; Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>; Veistola et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">1997</a>; Dawson and Bortolotti 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2000</a>). Fledgling body condition has been shown to strongly affect probability of juvenile survival to the next year (Sullivan 
  <a rid="b56" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56">1989</a>; Lindén et al. 
  <a rid="b23" ref-type="bibr" href="#b23">1992</a>; Naef-Daenzer et al. 
  <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">2001</a>; Low and Pärt 
  <a rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24">2009</a>). As the ability to compensate reduced growth during adverse weather may be lower for young as compared to old nestlings (Geiser et al. 
  <a rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17">2008</a>; but see Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>), it is possible that effects of rain during the early nestling stage may be manifested as reduced survival after fledging.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results also indicate a stronger effect of rainfall for nests hatched early than late in the breeding season (Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2A</a>). Fledging and recruitment success is generally lower for nests hatched late in the breeding season (Öberg et al. 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>) and thus, effects further reducing reproductive performance may be more difficult to detect (lower statistical power). However, nestlings hatched early in the season may also be more sensitive to rainfall. Early breeding individuals produce on average larger clutches and have larger broods than late breeders (Öberg et al. 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>), potentially requiring an effort beyond the parent's capacity when feeding young during poor environmental conditions thus causing brood reduction through nestling mortality (Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>). If this is true, difference in fitness between early and late breeders may disappear in years with heavy rain early in the season, reducing the advantages of early breeding.
 </p>
</sec>
