<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recent focus on the response of organisms' phenologies to increasing spring temperatures (Crick and Sparks 
  <a rid="b13" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13">1999</a>; Sparks 
  <a rid="b53" ref-type="bibr" href="#b53">1999</a>; Parmesan and Yohe 
  <a rid="b39" ref-type="bibr" href="#b39">2003</a>; Lehikoinen et al. 
  <a rid="b21" ref-type="bibr" href="#b21">2004</a>; Visser et al. 
  <a rid="b60" ref-type="bibr" href="#b60">2004</a>; Chambers et al. 
  <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">2013</a>) has largely been because of expected temperature-associated changes in reproductive output and population growth rates (exemplified by studies on birds: Visser et al. 
  <a rid="b59" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59">1998</a>; Both et al. 
  <a rid="b8" ref-type="bibr" href="#b8">2006</a>; Møller et al. 
  <a rid="b31" ref-type="bibr" href="#b31">2008</a>; but see Reed et al. 
  <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2013</a>). However, predicted changes in rainfall patterns (IPCC 
  <a rid="b19" ref-type="bibr" href="#b19">2013</a>) may also have potential consequences for phenology through delays in breeding in wet springs (Senapathi et al. 
  <a rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" href="#b50">2011</a>), or more directly for reproductive output (Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>; Franklin et al. 
  <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2000</a>; Arlettaz et al. 
  <a rid="b1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1">2010</a>). This is likely to occur via changes in prey activity (i.e., food availability; Avery and Krebs 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">1984</a>), altered foraging patterns (Veistola et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">1997</a>; Dawson and Bortolotti 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2000</a>; Radford et al. 
  <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2001</a>), and/or increased energy demands (Keller and van Noordwijk 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1994</a>; Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>; Veistola et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">1997</a>). Further, persistent or heavy rainfall may reduce juvenile growth rates (Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>; Veistola et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">1997</a>; Dawson and Bortolotti 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2000</a>) and increase offspring mortality (e.g., Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>; Dawson and Bortolotti 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2000</a>; Franklin et al. 
  <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2000</a>; Rodríguez and Bustamante 
  <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">2003</a>; Arlettaz et al. 
  <a rid="b1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1">2010</a>). Thus, predictions of how populations respond to on-going climate change will also require information on relationships between rainfall and vital rates for many species. One such potential group of species are insectivorous birds breeding in northern temperate regions, where mean precipitation and extreme precipitation events are predicted to increase with future climate change (IPCC 
  <a rid="b19" ref-type="bibr" href="#b19">2013</a>). Insectivores may be particularly affected by changing rainfall patterns because their main prey are less active, during adverse weather, resulting in reduced food availability (Avery and Krebs 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">1984</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In birds, the risk of rainfall-related nestling mortality could differ depending on the developmental stage of the nestlings (c.f. Low and Pärt 
  <a rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24">2009</a>). This is because of a number of age-related changes that occur during nestling development that affect energy demand of altricial nestlings, including: (1) a change from an ectothermic state at hatching to an endothermic metabolism before fledging (Whittow 
  <a rid="b61" ref-type="bibr" href="#b61">2000</a>), (2) feathers grow and the surface area to volume ratio of individuals changes, reducing exposure and surface heat transfer (Whittow 
  <a rid="b61" ref-type="bibr" href="#b61">2000</a>), (3) body size and growth-rate changes during growth (e.g., Low et al. 
  <a rid="b27" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27">2012</a>), and (4) the time spent brooding nestlings decreases with nestling age (e.g., Conder 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">1989</a>). As the direction of changes in energy demand is likely to differ for these factors – for example, chicks become more robust to exposure with time (i and ii above; and see Arlettaz et al. 
  <a rid="b1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1">2010</a>), but potentially more susceptible to energy limitation with time (iii and iv above; and see Siikamäki 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">1996</a>) – there are no simple predictions concerning nestling age and rainfall-related mortality.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Negative effects of rainfall on reproduction may not only be expressed as nestling mortality. Reduced foraging opportunities during rainfall (especially for insectivorous species) are likely to influence the condition of both young and their parents; thus, examinations of population impacts of rainfall patterns needs to consider long-term effects on individuals, such as reduced juvenile survival to the next year (Lindén et al. 
  <a rid="b23" ref-type="bibr" href="#b23">1992</a>; Naef-Daenzer et al. 
  <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">2001</a>; Low and Pärt 
  <a rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24">2009</a>) and increased costs of reproduction in adults (Linden and Møller 
  <a rid="b22" ref-type="bibr" href="#b22">1989</a>; Stearns 
  <a rid="b54" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54">1992</a>). Weather effects on adult survival come from evolutionary studies during periods of adverse weather conditions (e.g., Boag and Grant 
  <a rid="b7" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7">1981</a>), or studies investigating effects of annual breeding season rainfall or large-scale weather patterns on adult survival, revealing negative effects of rainfall in some studies (Franklin et al. 
  <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2000</a>; McDonald et al. 
  <a rid="b30" ref-type="bibr" href="#b30">2004</a>; Cowley and Siriwardena 
  <a rid="b12" ref-type="bibr" href="#b12">2005</a>), or no effects in other studies (Stokke et al. 
  <a rid="b55" ref-type="bibr" href="#b55">2005</a>; Robinson et al. 
  <a rid="b46" ref-type="bibr" href="#b46">2008</a>; Salewski et al. 
  <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">2013</a>). Clearly, if weather influences fledging success, recruitment success, and/or adult parental survival, estimates of effects need to consider multiple fitness components to avoid underestimating the impact of weather variables on population growth. At present, however, studies specifically linking rainfall during the nestling period with juvenile survival (e.g., recruitment success) and adult parental survival for species breeding in the northern temperate regions are largely lacking.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigate the effects of rainfall during the nestling period on reproductive success and parental survival probability in a population of northern wheatears (
  <span class="italic">Oenanthe oenanthe</span>). First, we test whether rainfall is related to fledging success, recruitment success and apparent survival for male and female parents to the next year, while accounting for effects of temperature that otherwise may confound effects of rainfall. Second, we examine whether relationships between nestling mortality and rainfall are age dependent, that is, whether the strength of the effect of rainfall on fledging success, recruitment success, and apparent parental survival is limited to a specific period during nestling/fledgling development. Third, we investigate whether environmental or individual conditions such as habitat quality or timing of breeding may buffer individuals from effects of rainfall (Franklin et al. 
  <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2000</a>). We expect individuals breeding in high-quality habitats to be less affected by rainfall than those in poorer quality habitats. Similarly, late breeding individuals may be more affected by rainfall than early breeders, as late breeders generally encounter deteriorating environmental conditions (e.g., reduced food availability; Perrins 
  <a rid="b42" ref-type="bibr" href="#b42">1965</a>; Öberg et al. 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>) or are poor quality individuals (de Forest and Gaston 
  <a rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15">1996</a>; Morbey and Ydenberg 
  <a rid="b32" ref-type="bibr" href="#b32">2000</a>). Finally, we look at how parental nest feeding visits vary with rainfall as a possible mechanism explaining relationships between rainfall and fitness.
 </p>
</sec>
