<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rainfall and subsequent parental survival</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The step 1 rainfall analysis on male parental survival to the next year showed support for declining survival as number of days with rain increased during the nestling stage (NumDays
  <sub>NestFull</sub>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1" href="#sd1">Table S1</a>; Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1C</a>). This model was closely followed by the equivalent model containing rainfall during the first part of the nestling period (NumDays
  <sub>Nest1</sub>), suggesting that much of the rainfall effect on male survival is during the earlier nestling period (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1" href="#sd1">Table S1</a>). For female parental survival, no model containing rainfall substantially improved model fit (ΔAIC &gt; 2) as compared to the base model (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1" href="#sd1">Table S1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the step 2 covariate analyses, there was little support for an effect of average temperature on male parental survival as models containing temperature always had less support than the equivalent model without it (Table
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>). However, there was substantial support for an interactive effect between rain and number of fledged young on male parental survival (Tables
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl2" href="#tbl2">2</a>). In contrast to our prediction, for males who fledged a smaller number of offspring, there was a steeper decline in apparent survival with increasing numbers of days with rainfall, than for those with more fledglings (Table
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl2" href="#tbl2">2</a>; Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2B</a>). There was little support for interactive effects between rainfall and field layer height or egg-laying date on male parental survival (Table
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
