<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 1 – Assessing rainfall-fitness correlations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each fitness component, we created a candidate model set, where we varied rainfall variables while holding constant variables known to be important in influencing each respective fitness component (based on Öberg et al. 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a> where relative variable importance weights were &gt;0.60), which included: (1) for fledging success – field layer height (short/tall), female age (yearling/older), egg-laying date (the date the first egg was laid relative to 1 May), and an age*egg-laying date interaction, (2) for recruitment success – field layer height, female age, nest type (roof vs. ground), and egg-laying date, and (3) for female and male parental survival – field layer height, nest success (successful/failed), and egg-laying date. Although egg-laying date does not appear to influence adult survival (Öberg et al. 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>), we included this factor in the base models because any seasonal pattern in rainfall may hide a potential relationship between survival and egg-laying date. Similarly, age did not appear to influence adult survival (Low et al. 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">2010</a>), but due to a higher proportion of young breeders in tall habitats (tall vs. short; females: 48 vs. 35%, 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 11.7, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001; males: 39% vs. 26%, 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 12.2, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001), we included age to avoid any confounding effects of this variable on parental survival. For both fledging and recruitment success, female age was unknown in ∼20% of the breeding attempts, so we used the known male age in these cases because male and female age is highly correlated in this population (likelihood ratio, 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 79.44, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 820; see also Öberg et al. 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>). For female parental survival analyses, we only used females of known age. In all models, we included year and individual identity as random effects; except for the fledging success analysis where the individual random effect resulted in some models not converging and so it was excluded. This omission was unlikely to have influenced our overall results, as the term did not improve AIC (Akaike's information criterion) in less complex fledging success models where convergence occurred.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the variables known to influence each respective fitness component as a base, we created models for each rainfall measure (see above) during periods of different nestling ages: the entire nestling period (when chicks were 0–15 days of age), the first half of the nestling period (0–7 days), and the second half of the nestling period (8–15 days); for recruitment success and parental survival, there was one additional model for each rainfall measure during the early postfledging period (16–25 days). Thus, the candidate model set contained 13 models for fledging success (base + 4 rain variables x 3 periods) and 17 models for recruitment success and parental survival (base + 4 rain metrics x 4 periods). The initial analyses included the rainfall measure only as a linear term, as visualization of the raw data showed no obvious nonlinear relationships between rainfall and the fitness components of interest (not shown). All models in the candidate set were then ranked by AIC, with the highest ranked model (smallest AIC; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1" href="#sd1">Table S1</a>) used as the base model for the next step in the analyses of each fitness component providing the addition of a rainfall variable improved AIC by &gt;2 (Burnham and Anderson 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2002</a>). For female parental survival, the effect of rainfall on model fit was extremely weak (ΔAIC &lt; 2; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1" href="#sd1">Table S1</a>); thus, we concluded that there was little support for an effect of rainfall on female parental survival and did not perform any further analysis on this fitness component.
 </p>
</sec>
