<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 2 – Disentangling temperature and rainfall and assessing rainfall–covariate interactions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We built new candidate model sets for each fitness component based on the highest ranked model from step 1. First, to account for potential effects of temperature on variation in fitness components, we included mean temperature during the same time period as for the rain variable. Temperature and rainfall were correlated but Pearson's correlation coefficients never exceeded 0.4, and the variance inflation factor (VIF) for our fixed effects was always &lt;1.7 (a VIF &gt; 2 suggests problems with collinearity; Zuur et al. 
  <a rid="b62" ref-type="bibr" href="#b62">2009</a>). Second, we included an interaction between field layer height and rainfall to investigate whether habitat quality may buffer individuals from effects of rainfall. Third, we included an interaction between egg-laying date and rainfall to investigate whether rainfall-related effects on fitness differ for early and late breeding individuals. Finally, we included the interaction between number of fledged young and rainfall in models of male parental survival. If rainfall effects on survival are mediated through an increase in effort, individuals with many young (i.e., higher effort) should be more vulnerable to rainfall. Including all combinations of those additional covariates resulted in candidate sets of nine models for fledging and recruitment success, and 17 models for male parental survival. Models were compared based on AIC values and AIC weights (Burnham and Anderson 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2002</a>). As a validation for the model selection in step 1, we then reran all of the top-ranked models in step 2 with the different rainfall parameters from step 1; in no cases did the model fit improve with other rainfall data, supporting the step 1 model selection procedure. We then also checked our assumption that the relationship between rainfall and fitness was linear by comparing the full model with a model that included a quadratic rainfall term; with the exception of fledging success, the quadratic term did not improve model fit. We report the quadratic rainfall effect for fledging success below.
 </p>
</sec>
