<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although we did not observe any effects of climate change on RCW as simulated here, it is important to note that our study only addressed two potential ways in which climate change could affect the population. The empirical relationship between April precipitation and reproduction from Ft. Benning that we used in our simulations has been noted elsewhere and it is hypothesized that it is driven by decreases in the number of foraging bouts by adults (Neal et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>). If the overall increase in precipitation projected for the area reduces the number of foraging bouts such that individual body condition declines, mortality rates in adults or young may increase in addition to the decrease in fecundity that has been observed. There are myriad potential effects that climate change may have on this and other species. For example, climate change may affect the population dynamics of cavity competitors, diseases, and parasites, or the distribution or abundance of nest predators. The interaction among insects and plants may also be influenced by climate change (DeLucia et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). If insect abundance decreases or the timing of insect population growth (i.e., larval development for many species) changes as a result of climate perturbations, then food availability for animals such as the RCW may be negatively influenced. Furthermore, our models did not include the well‐documented phenomenon of loblolly pine decline observed at Fort Benning. In a recent study, loblolly decline was related to water stress (Ryu et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), suggesting that loblolly pines might be more susceptible to decline under changing climates. Thus, climate change should not be discounted as a threat to this species, and future work should focus on how climate change will influence the entire ecosystem upon which this species depends.
</p>
