<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Other studies have also indicated losses in diversity, especially when it remains confined to specific areas, mainly due to effects of habitat fragmentation and climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref079" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>]. Thus, the effectiveness and functionality of long-term environmental preservation/conservation areas is something very questionable, and that was also what we found out from our results. For example, only in relation to 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aurita</italic>, environmental preservation/conservation areas currently comprise 48.24% of the total distribution of this species, and official data indicate that the Atlantic Forest is under an accelerated rate of destruction [
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>], including within its own ecological reserves, because of illegal deforestation [
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref081" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref082" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. This suggests the possibility that by the second half of the twenty-first century all endemic species of the Atlantic Forest (and those that there are distributed) are in serious risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref079" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0202813.ref084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>], including 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aurita</italic>. With this in mind, one of the challenges will be to know with relative certainty, what would be the appropriate minimum distribution size to provide viability, in this case Ceratophryidae populations, and ensure the future of their species. This question can only be answered by studies in population dynamics.
</p>
