<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model Simulations.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global modeling studies with intermediate complexity models have shown bistability of the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) in response to oscillatory or stochastic freshwater forcing in the North Atlantic (
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>). However, this behavior does not always appear in fully coupled 3D GCMs (
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>, 
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>). Recently, however, one such model (Community Earth System Model 1) has been shown to predict significant nonforced oscillations in the strength of the AMOC and North Atlantic temperatures when subject to last glacial maximum (LGM) boundary conditions (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>). This behavior has been termed a “kicked” salt oscillator. At the start of a DO-type warming, a large northward North Atlantic flux of salt occurs. This is associated with abruptly increased northward delivery of ocean heat and the melt of substantial areas of North Atlantic sea ice (
  <a rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" href="#r5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>). A gradual external forcing related to orographic change of the North American Laurentide ice sheet or a small freshwater perturbation can also trigger similar oscillations (
  <a rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" href="#r4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>). A version of the GCM called GFDL CM2Mc also exhibits nonforced oscillations of the AMOC, although only for a certain combination of background climate conditions (
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>). Here, we use a forced salt (or hosing) oscillation approach for setting up our suite of DO-type simulations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulations are set up using an isotope-enabled version of the Hadley Center Coupled Model general circulation model (HadCM3). This GCM consists of a coupled atmosphere, ocean, and sea ice model and has been widely used to study past, present, and future climates (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). HadCM3 can also be run for hundreds of years on modern supercomputers (
  <a rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" href="#r24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>, 
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). The ocean component of HadCM3 is a rigid lid model, with a fixed volume and water conservation through a time-invariant surface salinity flux that represents iceberg calving. Ref. 
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a> has the implementation of water isotope code in HadCM3. Ice sheets and sea ice in the model are initialized with 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i145" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O values of −40 and −2‰, respectively. Using this model, salinity fluxes are applied in opposing directions to the North Atlantic vs. the rest of the global ocean surface. Simulations are set up using LGM ice sheets, orbital forcing, and greenhouse gas composition; additional details are in ref. 
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>. Every DO simulation is continued from the same standard 1,000-y glacial period (LGM) spin-up simulation. In the first instance, each DO-type simulation is then run for 500 y using an identical stadial-type forcing: a negative salinity flux, equivalent to 0.25 Sv of freshwater, is applied across the North Atlantic between 50
  <span class="sup">○</span> N and 70
  <span class="sup">○</span> N. To balance the global salt (freshwater) budget, a coincident equivalent-sized positive salinity flux is also applied to the rest of the global ocean, ensuring a net global salt flux of zero. This generates a 1,500-y spin up of a stadial-type climate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A suite of DO simulations is branched from this initial spin-up 1,500 stadial-type simulations. To generate the suite of stadial-type climates, a range of salt fluxes is then applied to the 1,500 spin ups from the equivalent of 0.1- to 1.0-Sv North Atlantic freshwater. The salt flux increments are equivalent to freshwater fluxes of 0.1, 0.25, 0.5, and 1.0 Sv (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807261116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>). Later interstadial negative salinity fluxes are applied using the same range of magnitudes. Each of these stadial-type simulations is branched off from a different year of the spin-up simulation. For each of the salt flux experiments, the surface layer of the ocean is freshened across the North Atlantic at a rate equivalent to the addition of between 0.1 and 1 Sv of freshwater, while the rest of the surface layer of the ocean is salinified at a rate equivalent to the loss of between 0.1 and 1 Sv (i.e., from −0.1 to −1 Sv) of freshwater. The suite of simulations is run using this stadial-type forcing for between 100 and 500 y, yielding a wide range of stadial climates. In each case, the North Atlantic (negative) salt forcing is always balanced by an equivalent-sized (positive) salt forcing applied across the rest of the global ocean; therefore, the net global freshwater (or salt) flux is always zero.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To generate a switch between stadial-type and interstadial-type climate states, a reversed salinity forcing, with positive salinity forcing over the North Atlantic and negative values over the remaining global ocean, is then applied. All forcings are between 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i146" class="math">
    <span class="mo">±</span>
   </div>
  </div>0.1 and 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i147" class="math">
    <span class="mo">±</span>
   </div>
  </div>1 Sv. The net global salinity flux is always zero. When we calculate stadial–interstadial difference, we use 50 y of data in each case: the 20 y on either side of the salt flux switch are excluded.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Greenland is represented by 80 grid points in HadCM3; thus, some smoothing of the surface topography is required to run the simulation (
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). The modeled surface elevation is thus lower than the observed elevation. For the northern ice core sites, our modeled surface elevations are generally within 500 m of the present day surface elevations: NEEM: 2,450 vs. 2,341 m above sea level (observed vs. modeled, respectively). Similarly, NGRIP is 2,917 vs. 2,788 m above sea level (observed vs. modeled, respectively), and GISP2 is 3,216 vs. 2,832 m above sea level (observed vs. modeled, respectively). Because Greenland is somewhat narrower in the south, the elevations at DYE3 are 2,480 vs. 1,240 m for observed vs. modeled surface elevation, respectively. Thus, while all modeled sites are somewhat too low, the discrepancy is most significant in the south at DYE3. This may account for some, but not all, of the larger sensitivity of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i148" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O at DYE3 during DO events.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The suite of simulations shows a range of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i149" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O values and sea ice states (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807261116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>). At NGRIP, the stadial climate 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i150" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O varies from −37.5 to −29‰. Of 32 initial simulations, 15 exhibit DO-type abrupt warming over Greenland with 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i151" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O increases of 2.0‰ or more, where a 2.0‰ threshold could be considered representative of the minimum for a small DO-type abrupt warming (
  <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>). Each simulation with a significant 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i152" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O jump starts from 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i153" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O values at NGRIP of −32‰ or below (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807261116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>). Most of the larger 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i154" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O jumps occur under an interstadial-type salt flux (i.e., a return of salt to the North Atlantic) of size equivalent to 0.25 Sv or larger. This magnitude of salt oscillation is also in agreement with the size of salt flux required to induce significant AMOC variations in HadCM3 under present and future forcing scenarios (
  <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>). Note that there is a mean offset in Greenland between the mean model and mean data in 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i155" class="math">
    <div class="msup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">δ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">18</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>O of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i156" class="math">
    <span class="mo">+</span>
   </div>
  </div>8‰ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1 
   <span class="italic">C</span>–
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>). This offset is in the same direction as in earlier isotopic simulations alongside a similar warm model bias in the temperature and a wet bias in the precipitation (
  <a rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" href="#r21">21</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
