<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">QTLs related to salinity resistance in plants were studied by using GWAS. Kumar et al. (2015) reported various genes regulating the salinity tolerance in rice by using infinium high-throughput SNPs arrays. Six thousand genotype-based SNP were constructed for genes related to stress and linkage among SNPs and phenotypic data were interpreted. QTLs for salt tolerance by genomic regions were mapped on chromosome numbers 1, 4, 6, and 7. A novel QTL present on chromosome number 1 was reported and was called “Saltol” which is associated with salt tolerance at seedling stage [
 <xref rid="B153-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">153</xref>]. Lafarge et al. (2017) performed GWAS for genotyping 167 rice varieties for spikelet sterility (SPKST), and panicle micro-nutrient by applying 3 techniques of haplotype regression, single marker regression, and co-fitting of all markers to analyze the impact of heat during anthesis process. A significant association was present between SPKST, secondary traits, and 14 loci. These loci were investigated for functions related to heat shock proteins, controlling plant responses, development of gametophyte, cell division, and detecting abiotic stresses [
 <xref rid="B149-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">149</xref>]. Chopra et al. (2017) reported various stress-tolerant genes in 
 <italic class="italic">Sorghum bicolor</italic> associated with heat and cold stresses. GWAS was conducted for genotyping and phenotyping analysis. Thirty SNPs were identified for genes related to anthocyanin expression and carbohydrate metabolism, which are powerfully associated with cold stress at the seedling growth phase of sorghum. Similarly, 12 SNPs were discovered for heat stress at the seedling stage and controlled by the genes having functions in ion transport mechanism and sugar metabolism [
 <xref rid="B154-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">154</xref>]. In another study Chen et al. (2017) examined 
 <italic class="italic">Sorghum bicolor</italic> for heat tolerant traits such as leaf firing (LF) and leaf blotching (LB) at the vegetative phase of growth. To identify the association among SNPs with genotype and heat tolerance, GWAS was performed. Nine SNPs were closely linked with LF and five SNPs were identified for LB traits. Furthermore, 14 genes associated with SNPs were discovered that have stress-responsive expression to abiotic stresses [
 <xref rid="B155-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">155</xref>].
</p>
