<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-ijerph-13-00438" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <sec id="sec1dot1-ijerph-13-00438" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.1. Mediterranean Climate Type Regions and Their Vulnerability to Climate Change</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Mediterranean climate is characterized by a hot and dry season in summer and mild temperatures associated with rainfall in winter. Despite the apparent uniformity of the Mediterranean climate, there are differences between sub-areas, for example in the length of the dry season or a variance in precipitation amounts [
   <a rid="B1-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-13-00438">1</a>]. The Mediterranean climate type is found in five areas of the world including the Mediterranean Basin, the western United States (California) and Mexico (northwest Baja), central Chile, the Cape region of South Africa, and south and southwestern Australia [
   <a rid="B2-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-13-00438">2</a>]. These five areas are renowned for high levels of biological richness [
   <a rid="B3-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-13-00438">3</a>,
   <a rid="B4-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-13-00438">4</a>]. The mild Mediterranean climate and the proximity to the sea make it attractive to people, resulting in a disproportionately high conversion of ecosystems for agriculture, development, and other human uses. As a result, the Mediterranean climate regions are characterized by high population density and growth, as well as the extension of urban areas [
   <a rid="B5-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-13-00438">5</a>,
   <a rid="B6-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-13-00438">6</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the Mediterranean climate is determined by the interaction between mid-latitude and sub-tropical circulation regimes and a complex morphology of mountain chains and land–sea contrasts, the Med-regions are vulnerable to climatic changes [
   <a rid="B7-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-13-00438">7</a>,
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-13-00438">8</a>]. In fact, the Mediterranean ecosystems are among the most vulnerable to the global warming impacts [
   <a rid="B9-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-13-00438">9</a>]. Recent studies show that these changes have already been observed: for instance, since the 1960s, the Mediterranean basin has become warmer with a significant increase in the frequency, intensity and duration of heat waves. It is also characterized by a reduction in the availability of potable water as a result of a decrease in the total amount of precipitation, changes in rainfall patterns and water overuse by the growing population, mainly in urban areas [
   <a rid="B10-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-13-00438">10</a>,
   <a rid="B11-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-13-00438">11</a>]. In California the mean temperature has increased across all regions [
   <a rid="B12-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-13-00438">12</a>], and projected average temperatures are expected to rise dramatically in future decades, greatly exceeding the warming that has occurred to date since the late 19th century [
   <a rid="B13-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-13-00438">13</a>]. In recent years, California has experienced extreme drought [
   <a rid="B14-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-13-00438">14</a>]. According to Williams 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
   <a rid="B15-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-13-00438">15</a>] anthropogenic warming has intensified the recent droughts as part of a chronic drying trend that is becoming increasingly detectable and is projected to continue growing throughout the rest of this century. In the Western Cape region of South Africa significant warming trends were found and very warm days have become warmer or have occurred more regularly [
   <a rid="B16-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-13-00438">16</a>]. Under climate change projections, serious reductions in water supply and increases in the frequency of intense wildfires are expected for this region [
   <a rid="B17-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-13-00438">17</a>]. In southwestern Australia, the mean temperature has risen by more than 1 °C since 1910 and declines in rainfall have been observed in recent decades [
   <a rid="B18-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-13-00438">18</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec1dot2-ijerph-13-00438" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.2. Climate Change Impacts on Health in Mediterranean Cities</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent climatic changes and future projections have resulted in growing attention to the health effects on all human populations, both urban and rural [
   <a rid="B19-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-13-00438">19</a>]. These overall negative health effects impact in direct ways (e.g., heatwaves, flooding, and drought) and in indirect ways (e.g., food availability). The risks and the number of people exposed to them are influenced by social and economic development, technology, and health service provision. Consequently, urban areas where people, resources and infrastructure are concentrated are especially vulnerable to the health impacts of the changing climate [
   <a rid="B20-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-13-00438">20</a>,
   <a rid="B21-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-13-00438">21</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Urban populations are increasing in absolute numbers and are also relative to rural populations in every part of the world. According to the UN [
   <a rid="B22-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-13-00438">22</a>], 54% of the world population lives in urban areas. Because cities concentrate populations, extreme weather events (such as severe heatwaves or flooding) affect a much larger number of people. Cities also concentrate poor populations who are especially vulnerable to the effects of climate change because of the conditions in which they live and the fact that they often lack adequate shelter or access to health services [
   <a rid="B23-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-13-00438">23</a>]. Another crucial factor is relating to the increasing proportion of the older population. This worldwide growing group is highly vulnerable (more than others) to health risks associated with extreme temperatures, infectious diseases and air pollution [
   <a rid="B19-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-13-00438">19</a>,
   <a rid="B21-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-13-00438">21</a>,
   <a rid="B24-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-13-00438">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-13-00438">25</a>]. The population density in cities tends to lengthen the supply lines for essentials such as water, food, and energy sources. Extreme temperatures, storms or droughts that disrupt these urban lifelines can have serious consequences for the health of city residents [
   <a rid="B26-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-13-00438">26</a>]. In addition, the ways in which cities are constructed—reducing vegetation, covering large areas with impermeable surfaces, and obstructing natural drainage channels—make many city inhabitants more vulnerable to heatwaves, heavy precipitation, and other extreme weather events whose occurrence is found to be increasing [
   <a rid="B9-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-13-00438">9</a>,
   <a rid="B20-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-13-00438">20</a>]. The ways in which the changing climate affects the health of city inhabitants are detailed below:
   <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Extreme high air temperatures contribute directly to deaths from cardiovascular and respiratory disease, particularly among elderly people and those with chronic diseases. The impacts are worsened by the “urban heat island” effect, which results from greater heat retention of buildings and paved surfaces in urban areas.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Direct physical injuries and deaths from extreme weather events such as intense rainfall, winds and floods. Extreme events may also damage homes, create dangerous transport conditions and disrupt the supply of medical and health services.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Increasingly variable rainfall patterns (drought, floods) affect the supply of fresh water. A lack of safe water can compromise hygiene and increase the risk of water-borne diseases.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Worsening air quality related to changes in temperature and precipitation resulting in the formation of smog may cause respiratory illnesses. High temperatures also raise the levels of ozone and other pollutants in the air that exacerbate cardiovascular and respiratory diseases. Pollen and other aeroallergen levels are also higher in extreme heat conditions.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Illnesses and deaths occur from the spreading and expanded range of vector-borne infectious diseases.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Food-borne diseases resulting from bacterial growth in foods exposed to higher temperatures.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Unstable nutritional security among the urban poor who have reduced access to food (
      <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, shortages and rising prices) as a result of extreme events (extreme temperatures, drought, floods) [
      <a rid="B19-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-13-00438">19</a>,
      <a rid="B20-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-13-00438">20</a>,
      <a rid="B21-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-13-00438">21</a>].
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In cities with a Mediterranean climate (Med-cities), people have to deal with cold in winter, which can be either dry or wet, and heat in summer, with high or low humidity. In the transitional seasons, over short periods of time, the climatic conditions can change from one extreme to another. Therefore, dealing with bioclimatic comfort and weather conditions in a Mediterranean climate may be more complicated than in more extreme environments [
   <a rid="B27-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-13-00438">27</a>]. These challenges are increasing since the Mediterranean climate-type regions are among the most vulnerable to the impacts of the changing climate [
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-13-00438">8</a>]. In the Mediterranean basin itself, since many cities are old, they are compact and densely populated [
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-13-00438">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-13-00438">29</a>]. Furthermore, Med-cities often lack shading in public places, and when shading elements exist they are often designed in ways that do not provide sufficient shade during the hot hours, nor is their potential to reduce heat stress fulfilled [
   <a rid="B30-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-13-00438">30</a>]. Although air conditioning is essential in the long hot season, it is mainly used in areas with higher socio-economic standing while poor populations have less access to air conditioning [
   <a rid="B31-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-13-00438">31</a>]. In Med-cities, as a part of the local mentality, windows remain open for most of the hot months. Many activities, particularly social gatherings, occur in outdoor locations such as shaded balconies, courtyards, and outdoor restaurants [
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-13-00438">29</a>]. These cultural behaviors increase the potential for contact with mosquitoes that may be vectors for infectious diseases. All the characteristics above make the residents of the Med-cities susceptible to the impacts of climate change.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec1dot3-ijerph-13-00438" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.3. The Importance of Adaptation Policy at the City Level</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is a global phenomenon; and national governments have a crucial role to play in both mitigation and adaptation. Nevertheless, the local level is as important for protecting public health from this emerging threat: as was mentioned above, cities are vulnerable to climate change due to their population and infrastructure density. Med-cities are particularly susceptible since they are located at the hot-spots (areas of high biodiversity under threat from humans) of some of the strongest climate change effects [
   <a rid="B9-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-13-00438">9</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation at the city level can prevent or significantly reduce vulnerability, including improvement of housing, building resilient infrastructure and strengthening the adaptation capacity of the general community and of low-income and vulnerable groups [
   <a rid="B32-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-13-00438">32</a>,
   <a rid="B33-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-13-00438">33</a>]. For example, modifications to vegetation cover and surface albedo can “offset projected increases in heat-related mortality by 40%–99%” ([
   <a rid="B34-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-13-00438">34</a>], p. 7). Indeed, implementation of a heatwave plan alongside public awareness and readiness of public health services were estimated to prevent 4000 cases of access mortality in France in 2006 [
   <a rid="B35-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-13-00438">35</a>]. Adaptation measures can have more than one health benefit. For example, improving the thermal efficiency of housing has two co-benefits: reducing electricity bills and reducing emissions of air pollutants thereby decreasing respiratory diseases. Also, increasing tree canopy cover has the co-benefits of reducing heat stress, and improving the living environment and one’s sense of wellbeing [
   <a rid="B36-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-13-00438">36</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The current study aims to highlight health impacts of climate change in cities with Mediterranean climate, and to analyze in detail local climate adaptation plans in cities with Mediterranean climate-type (which are highly vulnerable to health risks as a result of the changing climate), in order to identify the climate change-related health impacts addressed in the plans, as well as the policy measures developed to adapt to these health impacts. Finally, adaptation policy recommendations for the city level in Mediterranean climate regions are proposed.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
