<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recommendations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent years, major international organizations have put forward recommendations for adaptation to climate change. For example, the United Nations International Strategy for Disaster Reduction launched the global campaign “Making Cities Resilient—My City is Getting Ready!” to promote increased understanding and commitment by cities and local governments to risk reduction and to build cities that are resilient to disasters and climate change. The overall target of the campaign is to get as many cities as possible committed to disaster risk reduction and to span a global network of engaged cities and municipalities of different sizes, characteristics, risk profiles, and locations that can help and learn from one another [
  <a rid="B85-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-ijerph-13-00438">85</a>,
  <a rid="B94-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94-ijerph-13-00438">94</a>,
  <a rid="B95-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95-ijerph-13-00438">95</a>,
  <a rid="B96-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96-ijerph-13-00438">96</a>]. Based on these recommendations, and on the health risks in Mediterranean urban environments, we suggest that Med-cities may consider adopting the following fields depending on their local needs and vulnerability chalenges: 
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Assessment of health risks</span>: conduct risk assessments in order to identify the main threats to urban public health in a Mediterranean climate, and to maintain up-to-date data on risks and vulnerabilities, transparent to the citizens.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Extreme events management</span>: prepare comprehensive plans for extreme events, including early-warning systems. These plans should be cross-sectoral with a focus on vulnerable populations.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Long-term adaptation</span>: go beyond short-term preparedness for extreme events, and prepare for the longer-term changing climate over a 20 to 50-year span, although this is a challenge due to much shorter political time frames. Specifically: 
     <div list-type="alpha-lower" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>
        <span class="italic">Strategic urban planning</span>: based on risk assessments—building regulations, land-use planning, revising master plans.
       </p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>
        <span class="italic">Micro-climate</span>: long-term adaptation for a hotter climate is a special opportunity for Med-cities, which can contribute to the wellbeing of the urban population throughout the hot Mediterranean climate. Cities should increase the amount of shaded public spaces, using trees both with wide canopies and other shading elements. The shaded areas should include public squares, playgrounds, bus stops, pavements on main streets and rest areas in parks [
        <a rid="B30-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-13-00438">30</a>].
       </p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>
        <span class="italic">Social resilience</span>: strengthen communities and improve social networks.
       </p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>
        <span class="italic">Physical resilience</span>: adapt water infrastructure for floods and drought, improve buildings, e.g., encourage homeowners to reduce risks of extreme weather.
       </p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Risk communication</span>: raise awareness of the expected health risks, and promote opportunities for better understanding of adaptation health benefits (and co-benefits) among the general public, politicians, professionals in the municipality and city health system, local civil society organizations in the public sector, and schools.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Collaborative governance</span>: design adaptation policies collaboratively across the different municipality departments, between the municipality and the public, local civil society organizations and local businesses, and across levels of government: local, national and international.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Multi-level, global network governance</span>: to deal with health risks as a result of climate change, collaboration and coordination could be carried out not only at the county and/or state levels, but also with other cities dealing with similar challenges. An initial step toward collaboration between Med-cities has been taken recently with the establishment of the “Mediterranean City Climate Change Consortium (MC-4)” [
     <a rid="B97-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B97-ijerph-13-00438">97</a>] that aims to coordinate efforts across political borders and disciplines to bring more resources and knowledge to building solutions for cities in the five Mediterranean-climate regions.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Health systems</span>: build capacity and resilience in local public health agencies for short-term and long-term adaptation. The U.S. CDC developed a framework for Building Resilience against Climate Effects (BRACE) to facilitate the process in public health agencies [
     <a rid="B98-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98-ijerph-13-00438">98</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Ecosystems and natural buffers</span>: protect these resources to reduce the impact of climate change, including mitigation of floods and storms.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Vector-, water- and food-borne diseases</span>: improve surveillance and control of climate-sensitive diseases.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Research</span>: conduct local research to improve assessments of health risks, identification of locally-appropriate adaptation measures and evaluation of the implementation and outcomes of health-related climate action plans.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This current study examined in detail health aspects in climate change adaptation plans in five Med-cities. Although this is a preliminary step, our results and recommendations may serve as a basis for future preparedness in similar cities with a Mediterranean climate.</p>
</sec>
