<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although global interconnectivity ensures a continued risk for importations of Chikungunya into regions with competent mosquito vectors, until very recently there were no global distribution models for this viral disease, and comparatively little research identifies global regions of climatic suitability for Chikungunya transmission. It is, however, well known that climate affects growth, survival and abundance of the two primary vectors for Chikungunya, 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. Both field and laboratory experiments demonstrate that survival of both of these mosquito species is affected by lower and upper temperature thresholds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Precipitation is another important factor influencing the availability of microhabitats for oviposition and larval development: heavy rainfalls – which are increasing in frequency due to climate change in some areas – have increased the abundance of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic>, thereby increasing the risk of Chikungunya transmission in southern France in 2014
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. Projections of the global distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic> under climate change scenarios generally anticipate expansions in eastern North America, Central Africa, northern and eastern Australia, and East Asia
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. Regional European models of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> under climate change scenarios suggest that climatic suitability will generally increase and populations expand northwards in the upcoming decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
