<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While several epidemiological models exist for Chikungunya, global climate change models for the disease so far solely focus on vector distribution (with one exception
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>). One limiting factor is the knowledge gap about the effect of temperature on the extrinsic incubation period (EIP) of Chikungunya in both 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. aegypti</italic>. Present-day models for Chikungunya in Europe and the United States overcame this challenge through approximations based on field data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> or drawing parallels to similar diseases such as dengue
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. One alternative approach that obviates the need to model the complex interactions of extrinsic and intrinsic factors related to Chikungunya transmission is correlative niche modelling, which treats the disease as a species with a specific environmental niche. This includes environmental effects on the pathogen (such as ambient temperature affecting the virus’ replication rate in the ectothermic vector’s body) as well as vector distribution. Commonly applied for species distribution models of disease vectors
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> as well as in conservation biology, this approach has successfully been applied to dengue
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>, Chikungunya
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>, Zika
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup> and other diseases
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
