<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="pbio-1001517-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001517.g001</span>
 <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <div class="title">Schematic diagram depicting several hypothetical mechanisms by which ambient temperature influences seasonal timing in birds and mammals.</div>
  <p>(A) Afferent neural circuits carrying environmental temperature cues. (B) Possible mechanisms involved in the transduction of temperature cues into effector pathways that influence seasonal timing. The relevant environmental temperature cues converge towards the POA that contains both thermosensitive neurons (TSN) and neurons that integrate environmental temperature information, which we call temperature-integrating neurons (TIN). How this information is relayed to elicit physiological responses related to seasonal timing is currently a mystery. We identify four possible pathways (see numbers in red at arrowheads): 1. Via thyroid hormones: Temperature controls the expression of TRH that in turn modulates the production and release of thyroid hormones via modulation of TSH at the level of the anterior pituitary 
   <a rid="pbio.1001517-Guillemin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Guillemin1">[89]</a>,
   <a rid="pbio.1001517-Schally1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Schally1">[90]</a>. Thyroid hormones can act directly on seasonal mechanisms or indirectly via the energy balance. In mammals, the sympathetic nervous system can also directly control Dio2 expression (see arrowhead 1′). 2. Via prolactin: Temperature influences PRL release via TRH or VIP. 3. Via melatonin: In mammals, but so far not in birds, MEL is known to be a powerful intermediate in the transduction of other environmental cues, such as photoperiod. In mammals, MEL modulates TSH in the pars tuberalis of the pituitary, which in turn modulates the seasonal activity of the hypothalamus 
   <a rid="pbio.1001517-Ono1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Ono1">[57]</a>. 4. Within the POA: The POA integrates both internal and external temperature information, but also hosts neuropeptides that control aspects of seasonality (e.g., GnRH-I system). These two systems could be directly interconnected within the POA. These four schematic pathways would then influence mechanisms that are directly involved in the seasonal recurrence of life-cycle events such as reproduction (HPG axis), hibernation (fat stores), etc. Note that this diagram is a highly simplified representation of the mechanisms involved, which are described in more detail in the references cited in the text.
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="pbio.1001517.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
