<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The most commonly used temperature and precipitation data at present is the TRMM data and observed meteorological data. For the TRMM 3B43 data, there was an obvious deviation for the Tibetan Plateau [
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-15-02271" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], so a Kriging interpolation method has been sometimes chosen to improve the accuracy of TRMM data [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-02271" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. At the same time, the spatial resolution of TRMM data is relatively low, so we must downscale it to do our research and to avoid resampling errors and we use the interpolation data of observed meteorological data directly in this work to further explore the time-space distribution of precipitation and temperature. Daily precipitation and temperature were collected from 1956 to 2011 from 2470 meteorological stations located nationwide in China and provided by the China Meteorological Administration (
 <uri xlink:href="http://cdc.cma.gov.cn/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cdc.cma.gov.cn/</uri>). As the data series from 1961 to 2011 are relatively complete, the observed temperature and precipitation in this period were selected as the basic analytic data in this study. For missing data, limited meteorological station data in adjacent spatial domains in the basin to achieve scale extension of time dimension of temperature and precipitation was utilized [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-15-02271" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The central difference method (CDM) was used for the interpolation of single missing data values, while multiple consecutive missing data were interpolated by computing the perennial average value of those days [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-15-02271" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. After extending the missing data, the basic data was further reorganized to obtain the accumulated temperature and annual precipitation of each station. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-02271-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref> shows the distribution of meteorological stations nationwide in China. This study selected Naqu Prefecture as the study site, while the density of meteorological stations in southwestern China is relatively small. Therefore, we firstly obtained the nationwide raster data by interpolating the data of national meteorological stations, and then we got the annual precipitation and accumulated temperature raster data of Naqu Prefecture by resampling the nationwide data, so that we can do our later study of Naqu Prefecture.
</p>
