<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The predicted increases in temperature variability in the identified hotspots suggest the potential for substantial impacts on top of the impacts caused by changes in the mean climate. Poor countries are located in the identified hotspot regions of increasing temperature variability. A growing body of climate-economy literature shows that poor countries are particularly vulnerable to weather and climate shocks, whereas rich countries tend to show no significant vulnerability (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">48</italic>
 </xref>). Tropical temperature fluctuations are not only strongly correlated with a temporal loss of agricultural output, as might be expected from anomalous weather affecting crop productivity and yields (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">9</italic>
 </xref>). They also affect the economic growth rate of countries, leading to long-term economic disadvantages compared to the development of other nations (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>). Moreover, it has been argued that high temperatures favor political instability and conflict in tropical countries (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">49</italic>
 </xref>), although this claim remains controversial (
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">50</italic>
 </xref>). Like our own analysis, these studies are often based on monthly climate anomalies over many years and, thus, integrate many individual weather and climate events. The unequal projected regional changes in climate variability therefore constitute a matter of climate justice.
</p>
