<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We develop an empirical bio-economic model for the 
 <italic>Sardinella aurita</italic> fishery by artisanal purse seines in Senegal, which takes into account climate effects on reproduction of the fish stock, productivity of harvesting and feedbacks on local input and output markets. Climate has a dynamic effect on yearly stock growth through changes in upwelling intensity, but also an effect on catchability, and thus, fishing pressure through fish stock distribution. We simulate the development of biomass, harvest, and prices and we compare outcomes concerning the fishery’s contribution to food and income security. To explore mitigation options, we suggest an easily implementable and overall welfare-increasing intervention: reduction of fuel subsidies. The price for fossil fuels shapes the adaptation process in fisheries. Fuel subsidies constitute one of the most widely used policy instruments: Sumaila et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] estimate that an annual 7.7 billion US Dollars of fuel subsidies are paid to fisheries globally. It has been argued that fisheries that are relevant for food security may need fuel subsidies to help maintain high effort, high catches and low fish prices for consumers [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. By contrast, several authors have found a detrimental dynamic impact on fish stocks [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Fishing fleets benefit from a subsidy decrease if the stock effect is large enough [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Against this background, we evaluate how climate change outcomes for a fishery could be shaped if fuel subsidies were abolished. Our results are informative for policymakers, as the findings shed light on the effect of expected climate change impacts and mitigation options while considering endogenous adaptation of actors. In summary, the study aims and achieves to investigate how a fishery may be impacted by climate change when both economic adaptation and development is considered, and continues to explore counteracting policy measures.
</p>
