<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Interior changes of community assembly, including species composition, plant functional groups and traits, can consequently regulate ecosystem function and sensitivity in response to exterior driver for predicting potential responses to regional environmental changes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72" class="xref">72</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b73" class="xref">73</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" class="xref">74</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75" class="xref">75</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b76" class="xref">76</xref>. Surprisingly, we found that PSD had similar importance as FTD in explaining the variance of alpine grassland communities from the PCA results (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4a,c</xref>) and that PSD had a significant impact negative impact on FTD with the highest standardized coefficient (
 <italic class="italic">β</italic> = −0.69) in the final SEMs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5" class="xref">Fig. 5</xref>). This may be explained by the environmental filtering theory that community assembly is not a random process but based on the filtering of environmental factors on plant functional traits
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b77" class="xref">77</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b78" class="xref">78</xref>. The indirect impact of HMI through PSD was thereby found as strong as the indirect impact through CWM (having same standardized coefficients, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5" class="xref">Fig. 5a</xref>). FTD had no significant effect on ANPP or PUE due to covariations with PSD in the SEM analyses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5" class="xref">Fig. 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). These findings indicate that alpine plants and communities have been adapted to local abiotic conditions because of environmental filtering effects on plant trait evolution. It should be clarified that both CWM and FTD, in addition to plant trait values, are also determined by species relative dominance as shown in their definitions. The productivity sensitivity to climate changes at the community level can also be modified by changes in plant relative dominance. Therefore, we suggest that the flexibility of plant functional traits within and across species as well as their dominance changes in response to climate change and human disturbance should be seriously considered in long-term and large-scale studies on ecosystem functionality.
</p>
