<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plants deploy many strategies and adaptations for survival and complete the life cycle in different ways under water stress, viz. drought escape, avoidance, and tolerance (
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Farooq 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yadav and Sharma, 2016</xref>). Drought tolerance is a complex trait controlled by many individual plant traits with small contributions (
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Halford, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fleury 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hu and Xiong, 2014</xref>). A total of eight cultivar parameters related to drought escape, avoidance, and tolerance traits were selected for improvement to maximize yield potential of future wheat cultivars under targeted climatic conditions (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). By adjusting 
 <italic class="italic">Ph</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pp</italic>, the rate of crop development could be increased, which could shorten the duration of the vegetative growth phase and help to escape terminal drought by early flowering and maturity. Early flowering is an important trait for drought escape while maintaining potential yield (
 <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shavrukov 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Gf</italic> has been suggested as a possible trait for increasing grain yield in wheat (
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Evans and Fischer, 1999</xref>). However, increasing 
 <italic class="italic">Gf</italic> could be in conflict with yield improvement due to water stress under terminal drought. The rate of canopy expansion and the maximum LAI could be adjusted by altering the cultivar parameter 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. This in turn will change the pattern and quantity of light interception and transpiration, and therefore, will affect crop growth, water use efficiency, and finally grain yield. A decrease in 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic> could help to avoid drought stress by reducing transpiration and root water uptake. 
 <italic class="italic">Ru</italic> is an important root trait affecting temporal patterns and total amount of water uptake in water-limited environments (
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manschadi 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2006
 </xref>). A faster root water uptake reduces current water stress experienced by the plant, but could be risky for successful completion of the life cycle under terminal drought. On the other hand, slower water uptake with a likely drought at the end of the growing season is less risky for drought avoidance and may achieve on average higher yields. 
 <italic class="italic">SG</italic> is a drought tolerance trait that enables plants to retain more green leaves longer after anthesis and improve potential yield under drought stress (
 <xref rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Silva 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2001
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Triboi and Triboi-Blondel, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Luche 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Christopher 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Wsa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Wss</italic> are two additional drought tolerance traits that could help in increasing yield potential under drought stress (
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Halford, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>).
</p>
