<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extreme temperature events</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>] the average global temperature in the period 2003-2012 was 0.78 °C higher than in the second half of 1900 century. Extreme heat is one of the most important global causes of weather-related mortality: more frequent and intense heat waves are determined by climate change. Heat and heat waves are projected to increase in severity and frequency with increasing global mean temperatures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of heat waves on mortality is well documented [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. It has been observed a rapid rise in the number of hot days and severe meteorological events [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] associated with excess deaths across Europe: the 2003 and 2012 heat waves temperatures reached or went beyond 35 °C degrees [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. In Europe, over 70.000 excess deaths were observed in 12 European countries in the heat wave summer of 2003. Summer temperatures as high as those are expected to be the norm by the middle of the century in Europe [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. There is evidence of an increased number of deaths and acute morbidity especially among respiratory patients due to heat waves. For each degree Celsius rise in temperature, the risk of premature death among respiratory patients is up to six times higher than in the rest of the population [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. The increase in respiratory mortality (relative risk) is larger than the increasing total or cardiovascular mortality [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. Moreover, climate scenarios for the next century predict that the warming will be associated with more frequent and more intense heat waves in wide areas of our planet with increased risk of wildfires and desertification. Heat and drought conditions contribute to wildfire risks. Smoke emissions can travel hundreds of kilometers downwind of fire areas, exposing people to a complex mixture of fine particles, ozone precursors, and other health-harming compounds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. One recent worldwide estimate is that 339,000 deaths annually may be attributable to landscape fire smoke [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. Respiratory and cardiovascular hospital admissions and emergency room visits increase in response to wildfire smoke exposures, strongly associated with PM levels [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. Drought conditions create multiple health challenges: in dry conditions, more pollen, dust, particulates, and when present, wildfire smoke which can irritate respiratory epithelium, exacerbate chronic respiratory illnesses, asthma, and increase risks for acute respiratory infection [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>] (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Effects of climate change on respiratory diseases</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>An increased number of deaths and acute morbidity especially among respiratory patients due to heat waves</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>An increased frequency of cardio-respiratory attacks due to higher concentrations of ground-level ozone</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Changes in the frequency of respiratory disease due to transboundary long-range air pollution</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Altered distribution of allergens and some infectious disease vectors</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
