<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Camera records (mainly focus on mammals)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to previous research, Hebei Wulingshan Nature Reserve was divided into one km
  <span class="sup">2</span> blocks by ArcMap 10.2 (totally 142 blocks; cell size 1 × 1 km). Some blocks were excluded because of topography limitation for research. Only blocks in Core Zone and Buffer Zone were selected for research. Each block had one camera unit for at least 4 months. Finally, 56 sites were obtained (Fig. S1 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1" href="#supp-1">Appendix I</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Camera units (SG-990V, 30; Digicool SG-680V, 20; Digicool SG-009, 20; Digicool, Beijing, China) were attached to trees 80–120 cm above the ground, and three to five m from a trail or point where animal movement might be expected. Moreover, the distance between each camera was far more than 400 m (mean: 558 m, range from 354 to 766 m). For each site, GPS location, elevation, slope, aspect, and habitat (e.g., vegetation cover, forest type, and human influence) were recorded. Three photos (1,200 PX) and a 15 s film (1,080 P) were taken for every trigger. Camera units were also set with a 2 min delay between each photograph and set for 24 h monitoring. At the end of each monitoring session, the units were tested to confirm that they were still operational and had unexposed frames; otherwise, the date on the last photograph was taken as the last operational date.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A monitoring network of infrared cameras has been created for Hebei Wulingshan Nature Reserve from September 2015 to December 2015; and from March 2016 to June 2018. A sampling effort of 22,379 camera-days across 56 sample sites was achieved (Fig. S1 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1" href="#supp-1">Appendix I</a>). A total of 1,736 records for 15 species were obtained. We defined detection at a sample point as one individual photographed during a 30 min period. If more than one individual were identified on a single photograph, we considered this one detection. All detections were summed for each camera site (
  <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">Jia et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">Li et al., 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-26">Liu et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Zhang et al., 2012</a>). Then, species were identified using several books (
  <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Jiang et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">MacKinnon, Phillipps &amp; He, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">Smith &amp; Xie, 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">Zheng, 2011</a>) and databases (Animal Diversity Web, 
  <span xlink:href="http://animaldiversity.org/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://animaldiversity.org/</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, 548 effective records for 15 species (two birds; 13 mammals) were selected.</p>
</sec>
