<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea ice in the polar region plays a crucial role in modulating the stratospheric polar vortex
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, the Earth surface albedo
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, the thermal interaction between atmosphere and ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, and the local ecosystems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. Antarctic sea ice is found to be affected by atmospheric and oceanic internal modes on the seasonal to interannual and interdecadal time scales, such as the El Niño–Southern Oscillation (ENSO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, Southern Annular Mode
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, Antarctic Circumpolar Wave
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, and Atlantic Multidecadal Oscillation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. These variabilities induce high-latitude circulation anomalies, leading to warm or cold air advection, anomalous sea ice motion, and ocean current change, and ultimately changes in the sea ice. On the intraseasonal time scale, there may be atmospheric or oceanic processes responsible for the changes in Antarctic sea ice. In particular, remote forcing from the tropics to the polar region needs to be examined.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study demonstrates the impact of the Madden–Julian oscillation (MJO) on the intraseasonal variability of Antarctic sea ice. The MJO is the dominant physical mode on the intraseasonal time scale with planetary-scale circulation coupled with a large-scale convective complex in the tropics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The MJO is known as a source of the subseasonal-to-seasonal predictability of weather and climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Many previous studies have explored the effects of the MJO on global circulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, regional precipitation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>, and extratropical temperature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Recently, the MJO is proposed to influence the polar region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. For example, a study showed that enhanced diabatic heating over the far western Pacific induces warming over the Arctic through the zonal mean fluid dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, and therefore, it is anticipated that the sea ice over this region can be changed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. There were also earlier studies to examine the MJO effect on the change in Antarctic sea ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. However, these were on a short intraseasonal time scale (i.e., a period of 10–15 days), and its impact was not found. The latter arises because an MJO index that is not separated by season was used, thus, the genuine seasonal effect was not captured well. While the MJO moves eastward along the equator during boreal winter, northward or northwestward propagation occurs along with the typical eastward movement during austral winter
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Additionally, it is likely that the synoptic-scale internal variability in the extratropics is larger than the atmospheric response forced from the tropics on this rather short intraseasonal time scale
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. In this study, we particularly investigate the effects of the tropical lower frequency variation with time scale ranging from 20 to 90 days. The time scale has a significant impact on the extratropical circulation and teleconnection, and, in fact, it is commonly used in studies associated with the MJO-related teleconnection to higher latitudes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Atmospheric circulation modulates the sea ice concentration and cover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> immediately or with some time lag through the thermal forcing and the mechanical forcing. The former is related to temperature advection by wind and the latter is related to the effect of wind stress on the sea ice velocity and Ekman drift in the ocean. Between the two, thermal forcing contributes dominantly to the intraseasonal variability of Antarctic sea ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. On the intraseasonal time scale, atmospheric circulation variation correlates coherently with sea ice extent variation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Since the circulation plays an important role, it is essential to investigate the dynamical processes of the MJO-induced circulation response in the Southern Hemisphere.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study aims to explore the influence of the MJO on Antarctic sea ice extent during austral winter and to investigate the dynamical mechanism generating the large-scale circulation response to the MJO. Since teleconnection pattern due to tropical forcing is prominent in the winter hemisphere due to the existence of strong potential vorticity in the background dynamic field, it is expected that the MJO influences the climate over the Antarctic region. For this, a series of simulations using a linear baroclinic model is performed, and ray tracing for poleward propagating waves is applied based on Rossby wave theory.</p>
</sec>
