<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dynamical mechanism generating the circulation anomaly</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To demonstrate the dynamic mechanism by which the MJO generates the anomalous circulation in the Antarctic region, we performed a numerical experiment (see Experimental design). Because it takes about two weeks for the circulation response to tropical convection to reach the high latitudes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, diabatic forcing preceding two MJO phases is imposed. The simulated upper-tropospheric geopotential height anomaly is plotted by averaging the model simulations of 15–20 days. The results show similar wave train-like anomalies to the observations for all eight MJO phases, although the centers of the circulation anomalies are slightly biased westward (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). Hereafter, we focus on the response to the forcings of MJO phases 2 and 4, but the same formation mechanism operates in MJO phases 6 and 8 with a sign reversal.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The result of the model experiment shows that the MJO phase-2 forcing (e.g., enhanced convection over the Indian Ocean and suppressed convection over the western North Pacific) generates a teleconnection pattern, with the anticyclonic circulation anomaly over the MD and the cyclonic circulation anomaly over the RS and Amundsen-Bellingshausen Seas (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). This pattern resembles the circulation anomalies observed at phases 3 and 4 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d,e</a>), although observation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d,e</a>) does not indicate an anticyclonic circulation anomaly over the AP or Drake Passage simulated in the model. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b,c</a> exhibits the circulation anomaly in response to monopole forcing. Interestingly, the opposite forcing induces the same signed circulation anomalies over nearly the same location, especially at high latitudes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b,c</a>). However, the suppressed convection over the western North Pacific (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>) is more responsible for the generation of the total circulation anomaly (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) than the enhanced convection over the Indian Ocean (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). To identify the path of wave energy activity, the ray tracing technique is conducted based on nondivergent barotropic Rossby wave theory (see the Methods section for more details). The waves emitted from the convection over the western North Pacific propagate southward across the equator and reach the Antarctic region (red lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>). Some waves cross the equator near central Africa, while other waves penetrate via the Maritime Continent. The waves starting from the convection over the Indian Ocean propagate southwestward over central Africa and then travel southeastward (blue lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Simulated circulation anomalies in response to the MJO and Rossby wave ray path. Upper-troposphere (σ = 0.229) geopotential height anomaly (shading, zonal mean is subtracted; m) averaged over 15–20 days of model simulation in response to diabatic forcing of MJO (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) phase 2, (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) phase 4, and its monopole forcing: (
     <span class="bold">b</span>,
     <span class="bold">e</span>) diabatic heating and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>,
     <span class="bold">f</span>) diabatic cooling. Simulated circulations correspond to the observed circulation in (left panels) phase 4 and (right panels) phase 6. Black (white) squares in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">d</span>) represent centers of the high-latitude cyclonic (anticyclonic) circulation anomalies in the observation, as seen in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1e,g</a>. Thick red (blue) contours indicate imposed diabatic heating (cooling). In (
     <span class="bold">b</span>,
     <span class="bold">c</span>,
     <span class="bold">e</span>), thick lines represent ray path of the Rossby waves seeded from the (red) diabatic heating and (blue) diabatic cooling regions for initial zonal wavenumber 2.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47150_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e655" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, the MJO phase-4 forcing (e.g., enhanced convection over the Indian subcontinent/Maritime Continent and weak suppressed convection over the western North Pacific) produces anticyclonic circulation over the MD and cyclonic circulation over the Amundsen-Bellingshausen Seas and AP (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>), similar to the circulation anomalies contemporaneously found at phases 5 and 6 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1f,g</a>). Separate forcing experiments (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e,f</a>) show that enhanced convection (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e</a>) produces circulation anomalies similar to the total circulation response (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>). Wave rays (blue lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e</a>) seem to behave as those represented by the red lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>, as the two are located in similar areas. In fact, however, the waves emanating from the enhanced convection cross the equator near the Maritime continent (not the western Indian Ocean) to reach high latitudes. This suggests that the wave train shifts eastward as the MJO phase proceeds. The suppressed convection is too weak to generate circulation response, as seen in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3f</a>. Note that antisymmetric circulation and sea ice anomalies develop at MJO phases 6 and 8 with respect to phases 2 and 4.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of the linear model simulations show that the high-latitude circulation anomaly propagates eastward as does the diabatic forcing (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). Subsequently, the wave train influences Antarctic sea ice variation as seen in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> summarizes the formation mechanism and the resulting change in sea ice extent. As shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b,c,e</a>, two dominant wave passages, referred to as the northerly ducts, are identified at the equator: the western Indian Ocean–central Africa and the Maritime Continent (green arrows in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). These northerly ducts allow waves to propagate from the Northern Hemisphere into the Southern Hemisphere. This is possible since the dispersion relationship for the barotropic Rossby wave now includes the effect of the basic meridional flow and, thus, the waves can penetrate the tropical easterly region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. This is confirmed by calculating the stationary total wavenumber (
  <span class="italic">K</span>
  <sub>s</sub>), which implies the preferred region for wave propagation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. The inset plot in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a> shows the two wave passage routes.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Dynamical mechanisms of MJO impact on the circulation and sea ice anomalies. Schematic illustrating the Rossby wave propagation from the MJO and formation mechanism of high-latitude circulation anomalies for the initial state of MJO (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) phase 2 and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) phase 4. The black solid and dotted circles denote anticyclonic and cyclonic circulation anomalies, respectively. Green arrows near the equator depict the two northerly ducts. P4 in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and P6 in (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) denote the MJO phases at which the wave trains shown in the plots are established. The inset plot in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) is the stationary total wavenumber (
     <span class="italic">K</span>
     <sub>s</sub>), with the two black arrows representing local peaks in this wavenumber. Red (blue) thick arrows denote poleward (equatorward) wind anomalies and red (blue) hatching indicates sea ice melting (freezing) area.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47150_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e749" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
