<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">An initial bottleneck restricting gene flow of the flea populations into Australia could have been the cause of the low haplotype diversity currently present [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>]. Over time, the result of extensive transportation and the movement of cats and dogs has facilitated interaction between flea populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. Additionally, the abundance of feral cats and dogs could expedite greater genetic transfer between flea populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. Despite an increase in diversity suggested by this study, it still reveals relatively low mitochondrial variability and highly restricted haplogroup populations of 
 <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> in Australia. The finding of six mtDNA haplotypes is considered to be unusually low compared to other flea species, such as the ten haplotypes of 
 <italic class="italic">Pulex simulans</italic> and 24 haplotypes of 
 <italic class="italic">Oropsylla hirsuta</italic>, the prairie dog flea [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>]. It is expected that for at least every ten samples of mtDNA sequences greater than 500 bp (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">cox</italic>1), multiple haplotypes are expected for one species of animal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. Nevertheless, low mitochondrial variability has also been observed in other arthropod species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. High homology was similarly found at the 
 <italic class="italic">cox</italic>1 and 
 <italic class="italic">cox</italic>2 mtDNA regions in a study of 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles stephensi stephensi</italic>, an important malarial vector in India [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Oshaghi et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>] suggested the low genetic variation is a result of unrestricted gene flow due to the lack of geographical barriers. This, along with extensive movement of hosts, could be the potential contributing factor for the low genetic variation found within Australia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>].
</p>
