<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">At present, over half of the world population lives in cities. The urban population is expected to increase to 66% by 2050, where 6.3 billion people will reside in urban areas. Together with Africa, Asia will have the most rapid urbanisation and, as a result, 52% of the global urban population will be concentrated in Asia in 2050 (UNDESA 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2014</xref>). By 2030, the world will have an estimated 40% freshwater shortage (UN Water 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2018</xref>). Many Asian cities depend largely on groundwater. Unsustainable use of groundwater results in land subsidence as observed in Bangkok, Bandung, Jakarta, Ho Chi Minh City (HCMC) and Tokyo (Erkens et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2015</xref>; WWAP 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2015</xref>). Cities also generate vast amounts of solid waste. In developing Asian cities, the largest portion of Municipal Solid Waste (MSW) ends in landfills that often lack proper sealing to prevent leaching (Guerrero et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2013</xref>; Gupta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2015</xref>). Without appropriate treatment, solid waste releases hazardous substances that potentially pollute groundwater, surface water and oceans (Jambeck et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2015</xref>; Zarfl et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2011</xref>). Discharge of untreated sewage, combined sewer overflows and polluted stormwater runoff, increasingly pollutes Asia’s surface waters. Nutrient emissions in Asia and Africa are projected to double or triple within 40 years, causing serious eutrophication leading to biodiversity loss, and threatening drinking water quality, fisheries, aquaculture and tourism (e.g., Dai et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2017</xref>; Ligtvoet et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>; OECD Korea Development Institute 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2017</xref>). Particularly urban areas, including almost all megacities around the world, are vulnerable to both water-related threats and large sources of pollution as well (Ligtvoet et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). Water pollution affects urban citizen’s health and limits urban economic growth (OECD 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2015a</xref>; Ligtvoet et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2014</xref>). Finally, the recovery and reuse of freshwater, energy and materials from wastewater and solid waste are important for realising a circular economy that can address the increasing scarcity of sparse materials, nutrients, freshwater and energy resources (EC 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>; Henckens et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2014</xref>; Van Leeuwen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2018</xref>). Hence, the urban water cycle is crucial for sustainable urban development (Van Leeuwen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2018</xref>), which is clearly reflected in the UN Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) 6 and 11 (UN 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2018a</xref>).
</p>
