<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is among the key challenges that hinder sustainable livelihoods and economic development, particularly for developing countries like Tanzania. The main livelihood source of the people is rain-fed agriculture, with only 2 % of arable land having irrigation facilities (Eriksen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2005</xref>; Shemsanga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ahmed et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2011</xref>). According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2014</xref>) an additional of about 1–3 °C of global temperature is expected by 2100 accompanied with variations in rainfall by regions. The National Adaptation Programme of Tanzania (NAPA) predicted the mean daily temperature to rise by 3–5 °C throughout the country and the mean annual temperature by 2–4 °C (URT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2007</xref>). The report further predicts that rainfall in some parts of the country will increase while others experience decrease (URT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2007</xref>). According to URT (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2012</xref>), the change in temperature and precipitation patterns have led to increased risk of recurrent droughts and devastating floods, threats to biodiversity, an expansion of plant and animal diseases and a number of potential challenges on public health. People with low adaptive capacity are thought to be more vulnerable to the adverse effects of climate change, which contributes to the loss of their natural resources (Eriksen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2005</xref>; Paavola 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2008</xref>). Furthermore, Bakengesa et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2011</xref>) in Kilombero Ramsar Site revealed that change in rainfall patterns and inflow have affected habitats and dependent wildlife.
</p>
