<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to Van den Ban and Hawkins (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" class="xref">2000</xref>), perception has been defined as the process by which information or stimuli is received from our environment and transformed into psychological awareness. Perception is important in climate change because it is one of the elements that influence adaptation process. The forest adjacent households’ ability to perceive effects of climate change is a key precondition for their choice to adapt (Maddison 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2006</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2007</xref>; Gbetibouo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2009</xref>). Adaptation to climate change requires that forest adjacent households first realize that the climate has changed, and then identify useful adaptations and implement them (Maddison 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2006</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2007</xref>). A better understanding of forest adjacent households’ perceptions of climate change, on-going adaptation measures, and the decision-making process is important to inform policies aimed at promoting sustainable adaptation strategies for all sectors of the economy. For example, currently in most areas, forest adjacent households perceive that the climate has become hotter and the rains are less predictable and shorter in duration (URT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2012</xref>). The change in rainfall and temperature trends and pattern (URT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2007</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2012</xref>) is expected to pose adverse effects on livelihoods of the people in most parts of the country. According to IPCC (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2014</xref>) climate change adaptation is “a process of adjustment to actual or expected climate and its effects, in order to moderate harm or exploit beneficial opportunities”. According to Moser (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2010</xref>) adaptation strategies can range from short-term to long-term, aim to meet more than climate change goals alone, and may or may not succeed in moderating harm or exploiting beneficial opportunities. Coping can be distinguished from adaptation as it refers to the use of existing resources to achieve desired goals during and immediately after climate-induced hazards (Regmi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2010</xref>). In other words, coping is a short term strategy that is applied immediately after events in order to moderate harm. In a long run, some coping strategies may then be developed to become adaptation strategies. Reuveny (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">2007</xref>) urged that, individuals adapt to climate change in three main ways: stay in a place and do nothing, accepting the costs; stay in the place and mitigate changes; or leave affected areas. A significant majority of the forest adjacent households sustain their livelihoods by direct use of of forest resources including NTFPs. They also generate cash income from the trade of these products. These products are utilized by forest adjacent households to meet subsistence needs and currently act as economic base and safety nets during periods of climate induced stresses (Paavola 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2008</xref>; Nkem et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2010</xref>). Sustainable utilization of forest products especially NTFPs can significantly contribute to increasing the adaptive capacity of the forest adjacent households through improved food and health security, increased well-being and increased cash income.
</p>
