<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this regard, frequency and intensity of extreme weather events such as drought and floods have increased in some parts of Tanzania affecting climate sensitive sectors including agriculture (URT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">2008</xref>). A number of climate change perceptions and adaptation studies conducted in Tanzania (Naess 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2008</xref>; Lema and Majule 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2009</xref>; Nelson and Stathers 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2009</xref>; Lyimo and Kangalawe 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2010</xref>; Mongi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2010</xref>; Swai et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">2012</xref>; Kangalawe and Lyimo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2013</xref>; Kihupi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2015</xref>) focused on smallholder farmers in semi-arid areas with little attention to humid areas and specifically the forest adjacent households whom the majority have varied livelihood activities. This study assessed forest adjacent household’s voice on their perceptions and developed adaptation strategies against climate change effects in Kilombero District, Tanzania. The study addressed the following specific questions: (1) How do the forest adjacent households perceive climate change and its effects in line with existing empirical data? (2) How are the forest adjacent households cope and adapt to the effects of climate change? (3) What socio-economic factors influence their coping and adaptation strategies? The findings have generated empirical information on forest adjacent households’ perception on climate change that can inform different national existing strategies and policies for example the climate change strategy and NAPA. Furthermore, results are useful to policy and decision makers within the natural resource sectors in order to implement existing policies (National Agriculture and Forest policies) and strategies [reduced emission from deforestation and forest degradation (REDD+) and the National Climate Change] through developing and strengthening the existing coping and adaptation strategies.
</p>
