<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although the Earth is a “passive system” with no active regulation of temperature or heat content (based on current knowledge, that is), the effect of ocean heat uptake on the geographical distribution of warming and the heat storage patters on the surface of the planet closely mirror thermodynamic processes within the human body. Blood within the circulatory system is constantly redistributed, not only to meet the demands of metabolic and immune processes, but also to move heat from/to specific regions and maintain thermal homeostasis ( 
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flouris 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flouris &amp; Cheung, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenny &amp; Jay, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kiyatkin, 2010</xref>). These blood flow adaptations can reach dramatic proportions in the human body. For instance, during rest in thermoneutral conditions, 0.5 L/min of blood (5–10% of cardiac output) supplys the skin ( 
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lossius 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 1993
 </xref>). Nevertheless, during heat stress, up to 8 L/min of blood (50–70% of cardiac output) is directed to the cutaneous circulation, mainly by restricting visceral and renal blood flow ( 
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lossius 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 1993
 </xref>). These enormous changes in blood flow have a vast effect on the regional distribution of heat and the heat storage patterns, which ultimately affect the entire body’s thermal homeostasis. Therefore, measuring temperature in specific regions of the body, such as the rectum, esophagus, or the visceral organs, can only indicate regional changes in heat content ( 
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flouris &amp; Cheung, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flouris &amp; Cheung, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenny 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenny 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taylor 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Webb, 1986</xref>). Moreover, peripheral tissues can tolerate greater changes in heat with less threat to the health and survivability of the organism, whereas increases in specific organ structures such as the brain can threaten organism health ( 
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kiyatkin, 2010</xref>). Nevertheless, for more than 100 years, scientists have been using single region temperature measurements to make assumptions about the thermal strain across the entire body. Moreover, the currently recommended criterion when addressing heat-related health risks is a single temperature measurement in the rectum ( 
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">World Meteorological Organization and World Health Organization, 2015</xref>).
</p>
