<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing levels of plasticity among individuals, populations and species</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multicellular organisms are complex combinations of phenotypic properties that display more or less plasticity (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8" href="#bib8">Bradshaw, 1965</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91" href="#bib91">Sultan, 2000</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64" href="#bib64">Pigliucci, 2001</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79" href="#bib79">Schlichting, 2003</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103" href="#bib103">West-Eberhard, 2003</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69" href="#bib69">Pigliucci and Preston, 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3" href="#bib3">Araya-Ajoy and Dingemanse, 2014</a>). One should therefore not expect plasticity to be correlated across phenotypic dimensions or environments. A given genotype may show a plastic response (a non-flat reaction norm) of one or some particular dimension(s) of the phenotype in response to a certain environmental factor, whereas other phenotypic dimensions are not affected by the same environmental factor. Similarly, a given genotype or phenotypic dimension may display plasticity in response to changes along the gradient of one environmental factor, whereas changes along other environmental gradients do not affect the expression of the same genotype nor influence its associated phenotypic variability (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99" href="#bib99">Valladares 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>). Conclusions regarding the consequences of plasticity responses and gene by environment interactions therefore depend on the choice of trait(s) as well as on the choice of environmental covariate(s) (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99" href="#bib99">Valladares 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9" href="#bib9">Brommer, 2013</a>). Assessments of plasticity are typically focussed on traits with established or 
  <span class="italic">a priori</span> functional significance and how they respond to changes along some ecologically important environmental gradient. Consequently, there is a risk with a reductionist approach that we might arrive at a biased view of, and perhaps even overestimate, the importance of plasticity. To improve our understanding of the evolutionary dynamics of plasticity and its consequences, it is necessary to also identify those environmental factors that do not elicit plastic responses, as well as the ecological settings under which plasticity is less beneficial.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A plastic response in a given phenotypic dimension can be demonstrated experimentally. However, to reliably classify genotypes, populations or species as being non-plastic is complicated because it is impossible to determine with certainty that observable phenotypic variation among individuals is 
  <span class="italic">not</span> influenced at all by responses to 
  <span class="italic">any</span> environmental cues. This is because the population or species under investigation may potentially show plasticity in response to environmental cue(s) that have not yet been investigated, or have a restricted window of sensitivity not yet tested (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64" href="#bib64">Pigliucci, 2001</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103" href="#bib103">West-Eberhard, 2003</a>). Furthermore, the outcome of plasticity experiments conducted under laboratory conditions may not accurately reflect the role of plasticity under different and usually more complex and challenging circumstances in the wild (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57" href="#bib57">Nussey 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99" href="#bib99">Valladares 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29" href="#bib29">Fox and Reed, 2010</a>). It may not be possible to reliably compare and rank individuals, populations or species with regard to some overall level of or capacity for whole organism plasticity. However, comparisons can be done at the level of specific phenotypic dimensions and with regard to how they respond to changes along the gradient of one or a few specified environmental factors. In lieu of estimates of whole organism plasticity, multiple phenotypic dimensions can be examined, modelled and compared simultaneously by either using multivariate statistical analysis or using composite measures of plasticity based on averages across traits or dimension reducing techniques (such as principal component analysis) as a means to inform about differences in the nature and magnitude of plasticity among individuals, populations and species (see, for example, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11" href="#bib11">Carroll and Corneli, 1995</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67" href="#bib67">Pigliucci 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1999
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70" href="#bib70">Pollard 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2001
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57" href="#bib57">Nussey 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14" href="#bib14">Chun, 2011</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16" href="#bib16">Davidson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3" href="#bib3">Araya-Ajoy and Dingemanse, 2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
