<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions and future directions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Plasticity research has grown tremendously, from &lt;10 papers published per year before 1983 to nearly 1300 papers in 2013. There has been an increased interest in the questions of how interindividual variation and plasticity influences the performance and ecological success of individuals, populations and species.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Our understanding of causes and consequences of plasticity and its role in generating and maintaining phenotypic complexity and diversity is hampered by imprecise definitions, hypothesis and predictions, and a tendency to consider observational case studies as evidence in support of predictions and confirmation of theory. Authors should take great care to clarify how they interpret and use plasticity and related terms.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Within an individual, homeostasis, canalization or the absence of plasticity (a flat reaction norm) in a focal trait must be compensated for by higher plasticity or flexibility along some other phenotypic dimension(s); it can thus be argued that there is no such thing as a non-plastic individual.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Inferences and conclusions with regard to causes and consequences of plasticity should be restricted to the particular phenotypic dimension(s), aspects of plasticity and environmental cues(s) that have been investigated, and not extended to general statements regarding plasticity as such, unless a whole organism approach is used.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>The consequences of plasticity may differ depending on whether one is concerned with effects mediated by variation among individuals in the capacity to express plasticity and flexibility, or with effects driven by greater interindividual phenotypic variation resulting from induced responses (in which case there need be no genetic variation in plasticity).</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>To put predictions to empirical tests, we must be able to quantify and compare the nature and magnitude of plasticity among individuals, populations and species. In the wait of estimates of whole organism plasticity, multiple phenotypic dimensions can be examined, modelled and compared using multivariate statistical analysis or by using composite measures of plasticity based on averages across traits or dimension reducing techniques.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>To improve our understanding of the evolutionary dynamics of plasticity and its consequences, and to avoid overestimating its importance, it is necessary to identify also those phenotypic dimensions that are less likely to express plasticity or flexibility, those environmental factors that do not elicit plastic responses as well as the ecological settings under which plasticity is less beneficial.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Past and current research, based on theoretical modelling and observational data, indicates that plasticity may either promote or impair ecological success of populations, depending on environmental conditions. However, firm evidence to this effect is lacking.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>To demonstrate causal relationships and mechanisms linking plasticity variation to aspects of individual or population fitness requires methods allowing for experimental manipulation, replication and controlled comparisons. It is also important to distinguish between effects mediated by variation in the capacity to express plasticity and flexibility, as opposed to effects mediated by a higher (or lower) level of interindividual phenotypic variation resulting from plasticity (in which case there need be no genetic variation in plasticity).</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Whether and how standing phenotypic variation resulting from plasticity influences aspects of ecological success of populations can be experimentally investigated by first using a split-brood design to increase and decrease interindividual phenotypic variation and then comparing for instance establishment success, population dynamics and persistence of phenotypically highly variable versus less variable groups.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>To experimentally demonstrate that interindividual genetic and phenotypic variation affects ecological success of populations and species is tedious, but feasible (
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37" href="#bib37">Hughes 
      <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
     </a>; 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102" href="#bib102">Wennersten and Forsman, 2012</a>; 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24" href="#bib24">Forsman, 2014</a>). However, to disentangle any effects of whole organism plasticity from effects owing to genetic variation, and to rigorously investigate how variation in the capacity to express plasticity affects fitness of individuals and on the ecological success of populations and species, requires experimental approaches yet to be discovered. S/he who finds a solution to this problem will have a key to considerable future scientific advance. Let the quest for this Holy Grail begin!
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
