<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What is plasticity?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As pointed out by others, the concept of phenotypic plasticity is deceptively simple, and it has been defined in numerous ways by different authors (see, for instance, Box 1 in 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105" href="#bib105">Whitman and Agrawal, 2009)</a>. One apparent form of intraindividual plasticity, common to most if not all multicellular organisms, is the pronounced phenotypic differentiation among cells found in different organs and types of tissue (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94" href="#bib94">Sánchez Alvarado and Yamanaka, 2014</a>). Cells that comprise blood, bone, nerve and muscle within a single individual are phenotypically extremely different, despite that they share an identical (at least close to) set of genes and alleles. Such induced differentiation has previously been discussed from a plasticity perspective within the domains of ecology and evolutionary biology (see, for example, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76" href="#bib76">Sarà, 1996</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55" href="#bib55">Newman and Müller, 2000</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79" href="#bib79">Schlichting, 2003</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plasticity is oftentimes defined as the ability of a single genotype to exhibit a range of different phenotypes in response to variation in the environment. The term phenotypic plasticity is used in studies that concern and report on phenomena that are in fact rather different, and alternative terms are sometimes used for one and the same phenomenon (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61" href="#bib61">Piersma and Drent, 2003</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105" href="#bib105">Whitman and Agrawal, 2009</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87" href="#bib87">Stamps and Groothuis, 2010</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9" href="#bib9">Brommer, 2013</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86" href="#bib86">Snell-Rood, 2013</a>). The same or similar concepts are sometimes also used for different phenotypic dimensions, such as morphology, physiology, life history and behaviour, and for situations when the phenotype changes in response to variation in either the external or the internal environment. On one hand, the tendency to apply the same concept to different types of context-dependent phenotypic variation can be justified on the grounds that science may benefit from unifying, common theoretical frameworks. On the other hand, it is sometimes justified to use different concepts. Given the rich terminology (
  <a rid="tbl1" ref-type="table" href="#tbl1">Table 1</a>), however, authors should take great care to clarify how they interpret and use the plasticity concept and related terms to avoid misunderstandings, because people vary in what they think plasticity is and what it is not.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Active versus passive plasticity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One distinction worth mentioning in this context is that between active and passive plasticity (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77" href="#bib77">Scheiner, 2006</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43" href="#bib43">Kurashige and Callahan, 2007</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105" href="#bib105">Whitman and Agrawal, 2009</a>), because there might be differences in the way that these two aspects of plasticity affect the ecological success of individuals and populations. Active plasticity is used for predominantly anticipatory, and often highly integrated, phenotypic changes in response to some environmental cue or signal, and reflect modifications of developmental pathways and regulatory genes. In active plasticity, such as in the case of wing-length polymorphism in some species of insects (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74" href="#bib74">Roff and Fairbairn, 2007</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81" href="#bib81">Schwander and Leimar, 2011</a>), the magnitude of the induced phenotypic response(s) is not necessarily correlated with the strength of the environmental signal (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77" href="#bib77">Scheiner, 2006</a>). However, graded responses are also relatively common for active plasticity. For example, the magnitude of inducible defences in prey may increase as the number of predators, or the amount of cue produced by predators, increases. Passive plasticity, on the other hand, may stem from direct environmental influences on chemical, physiological and developmental processes, and is generally not considered anticipatory, but a mere consequence of the environment, such as stunted growth owing to low resource levels. In the case of passive plasticity, when the environment acts directly on the expression of the trait, phenotypic changes are often proportional to environmental differences (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77" href="#bib77">Scheiner, 2006</a>). Active phenotypic plasticities are often (unlike ‘truly' passive plasticities) considered adaptive, but the distinction between the two is not always clearcut (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77" href="#bib77">Scheiner, 2006</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105" href="#bib105">Whitman and Agrawal, 2009</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Developmental plasticity versus phenotypic flexibility</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The term ‘developmental plasticity' is used by many researchers who focus on irreversible phenotypic variation in traits of individuals (or genotypes) that result from environmentally induced modifications of development and growth. Some traits remain largely fixed after maturity, such as structural body size in some unitary organisms, the number of vertebrae in limbed vertebrates and various morphological defence structures induced by the presence of predators. Reaction norms (or norms of reaction) that describe the association linking the phenotypic expression of genotypes to an environmental gradient, and genotype by environment interactions that refer to the differential phenotypic responses of alternative genotypes, are key components in this field (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88" href="#bib88">Stearns, 1989</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73" href="#bib73">Roff, 1997</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50" href="#bib50">Lynch and Walsh, 1998</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64" href="#bib64">Pigliucci, 2001</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103" href="#bib103">West-Eberhard, 2003</a>). Developmental plasticity is not restricted to traits that display quantitative variation, and it can result in discrete phenotypic classes that represent developmental threshold responses regulated by complex mechanisms including polygenic effects and shifts induced by continuously distributed underlying cues (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88" href="#bib88">Stearns, 1989</a>). A candidate example is wing polymorphism, the co-occurrence of flight-capable individuals that possess fully developed functional wings and flightless individuals with only partially developed or no wings that in some insect species seems to be regulated by juvenile hormone titres (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib107" href="#bib107">Zera, 2003</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74" href="#bib74">Roff and Fairbairn, 2007</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81" href="#bib81">Schwander and Leimar, 2011</a>). Plasticity can also involve mechanisms that operate between or across generations. In quantitative genetics and evolutionary biology, when the environment responsible for the induced phenotypic response consist of the (female) parent, the developmental plasticity is usually referred to as maternal effects (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73" href="#bib73">Roff, 1997</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53" href="#bib53">Mousseau and Fox, 1998</a>) or cross generational plasticity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The term ‘phenotypic flexibility' seems to be used primarily by researchers who focus on intraindividual plasticity, that is, reversible changes within individuals of labile, context-dependent physiological, morphological and life-history traits (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61" href="#bib61">Piersma and Drent, 2003</a>). Examples include metabolic and endocrine switches, shifts in the sizes of body parts and organ systems in relation to reproductive condition and metabolic demand, changes in colour patterns in relation to seasonality, changes within individuals among years in the timing of reproductive activities in response to weather conditions and changes in number of eggs or offspring between sequential reproductive events. Phenotypic flexibility is also applied to changes in behavioural traits (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18" href="#bib18">Dingemanse 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
   </a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87" href="#bib87">Stamps and Groothuis, 2010</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98" href="#bib98">Tuomainen and Candolin, 2011</a>), for instance, as a result of learning and experience or adjustments depending on the presence or absence of predators, and encompasses both developmental behavioural plasticity and activational plasticity (for a thorough discussion see 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86" href="#bib86">Snell-Rood, 2013</a>). Despite the flexible nature of many behavioural traits, there is also a tendency of individuals to display consistency through time. In the behavioural plasticity literature, there is a growing interest in the causes and consequences of such consistency within individuals and repeatable variation among individuals, often referred to as animal personalities or ‘behavioural syndromes', for instance in the form of shyness versus boldness in different types of behaviour and across environmental contexts (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87" href="#bib87">Stamps and Groothuis, 2010</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9" href="#bib9">Brommer, 2013</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3" href="#bib3">Araya-Ajoy and Dingemanse, 2014</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Is plasticity distinct from genetic polymorphism?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are still articles published (including some of my own) that contain phrasings and arguments along the lines of genetics versus plasticity that might suggest that the authors do not consider plasticity a property of the genotype. There are probably examples of intraindividual reversible phenotypic flexibility and behavioural plasticity that are only loosely connected to genetics. Plasticity is not equivalent to genetic polymorphism, and their evolutionary dynamics can differ considerably (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17" href="#bib17">Day and Bonduriansky, 2011</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30" href="#bib30">Frank, 2011</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75" href="#bib75">Saito 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2013
   </a>). However, irreversible developmental plasticity is not 
   <span class="italic">fundamentally</span> different from genetic determinism, except for the environment dependence of the expression of the phenotypic state, and they are best interpreted and analysed within a common, quantitative genetics, framework (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1" href="#bib1">Agrawal, 2001</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64" href="#bib64">Pigliucci, 2001</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103" href="#bib103">West-Eberhard, 2003</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38" href="#bib38">Jablonka and Lamb, 2006</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45" href="#bib45">Leimar 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2006
   </a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17" href="#bib17">Day and Bonduriansky, 2011</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102" href="#bib102">Wennersten and Forsman, 2012</a>). Most phenotypic traits display a certain amount of plasticity, and plasticity includes genetic components (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88" href="#bib88">Stearns, 1989</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63" href="#bib63">Pigliucci, 1996</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64" href="#bib64">2001</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69" href="#bib69">Pigliucci and Preston, 2004</a>). Indeed, the existence of crossing norms of reaction, such that different genotypes display different phenotypic responses to environmental change, reflects an underlying genetic polymorphism (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88" href="#bib88">Stearns, 1989</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64" href="#bib64">Pigliucci, 2001</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103" href="#bib103">West-Eberhard, 2003</a>). This means that population-level consequences of plasticity predicted by theory are largely mediated by the same mechanisms as are those of genetic polymorphisms (for exceptions see 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102" href="#bib102">Wennersten and Forsman, 2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
