<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From single traits to a whole organism perspective</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It can be argued that ‘traits' do not really exist, except as mental constructions to aid communication (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33" href="#bib33">Fristrup, 2001</a>). Indeed, individuals are developmentally, functionally and phenotypically integrated complex units (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58" href="#bib58">Olson and Miller, 1958</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80" href="#bib80">Schlichting and Pigliucci, 1998</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69" href="#bib69">Pigliucci and Preston, 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99" href="#bib99">Valladares 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62" href="#bib62">Piersma and van Gils, 2011</a>). Within an individual, homeostasis, canalization or the absence of plasticity (or a flat reaction norm for a genotype) in a focal trait must reflect some sort of buffering mechanism and plasticity in some other trait(s) (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69" href="#bib69">Pigliucci and Preston, 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105" href="#bib105">Whitman and Agrawal, 2009</a>). Such buffering can be mediated by a flexibility of physiological processes, developmental pathways and by behavioural adjustments (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>). Although developmental plasticity and phenotypic flexibility can enable individuals to change their phenotype according to the environment, mobile organisms may also have the opportunity to change their environment according to phenotype by means of matching habitat choice (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19" href="#bib19">Edelaar 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39" href="#bib39">Karpestam 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
  </a>). This raises the questions of whether it is meaningful and possible from a whole organism perspective to classify individuals, populations or species as being either plastic or non-plastic
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If one takes into consideration the entire integrated suite of physiological, behavioural, morphological and life-history phenotypic dimensions, it can be argued that there is no such thing as a non-plastic individual, because lack of or low levels of plasticity in one trait is generally compensated for or made possible by higher plasticity or flexibility along some other phenotypic dimension(s). This realization is important when it comes to making comparisons, evaluating hypotheses and testing predictions pertaining to the fitness consequences of plasticity for individuals and populations. To avoid misunderstandings, any inferences and conclusions with regard to causes and consequences of plasticity should be restricted to the particular phenotypic dimension(s), aspects of plasticity and environmental cues(s) that have been investigated, and not extended to general statements regarding plasticity.</p>
</sec>
