<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How to manipulate plasticity in order to establish causation?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies based on observational approaches can offer important insights, generate hypothesis and testable predictions and uncover patterns and associations in accordance or disagreement with predictions. However, demonstrating causal relationships and mechanisms linking either variation in the capacity for plasticity itself or plasticity-induced phenotypic variation to aspects of individual or population fitness is complicated because it requires experimental manipulation, replication and controlled comparisons (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24" href="#bib24">Forsman, 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To experimentally manipulate the level of or capacity for plasticity seems very challenging, at least if one aims to test for effects of the capacity to express plasticity or flexibility (independent of genetic variation), and if one is concerned with whole organism rather than single trait plasticity. Artificial selection or genetic engineering might be used to increase or reduce levels of plasticity-induced phenotypic variation (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42" href="#bib42">Krebs and Feder, 1998</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20" href="#bib20">Feder, 1999</a>). However, interpretation of such manipulation studies is not straight forward, because of the potential for pleiotropy and epistasis (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50" href="#bib50">Lynch and Walsh, 1998</a>), and because changes in plasticity of the focal trait may be accompanied by increased or decreased plasticity in buffering traits. Phenotypic engineering based on hormonal treatments offers another possibility to experimentally manipulate the phenotypic expression of plastic and flexible traits (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85" href="#bib85">Sinervo and Huey, 1990</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41" href="#bib41">Ketterson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1996
  </a>), but again interpretation of results is complicated because hormones can have a multitude of cascading and interacting effects on organismal functioning. To test for effects and consequences of plasticity based on comparisons between experimental treatments that consist of unmanipulated individuals with naturally high versus low plasticity is equally problematic, because differences in plasticity between treatments would not be independent of genetic variation. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12" href="#bib12">Chevin 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2013)
  </a> provide a discussion and offer suggestions on the related issue of experimental evolution of plasticity.
 </p>
</sec>
