<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population-level consequences of plasticity revisited</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of what has been said above, is there any rigorous evidence in support of the predictions (
  <a rid="tbl1" ref-type="table" href="#tbl1">Table 1</a> in 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102" href="#bib102">Wennersten and Forsman, 2012</a> and references therein) that plasticity should promote the ecological and evolutionary success of populations and species? It is important in this context to distinguish between effects mediated by variation in the capacity to express plasticity and flexibility versus consequences associated with a higher (or lower) level of interindividual phenotypic variation resulting from plasticity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The buffering effect of plasticity-induced phenotypic variation against environmental change should apply primarily to labile or flexible traits, and to fine-grained environments where the changes are predictable (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102" href="#bib102">Wennersten and Forsman, 2012</a>). Recent reviews and discussions of behavioural flexibility are largely in accordance with this prediction (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98" href="#bib98">Tuomainen and Candolin, 2011</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86" href="#bib86">Snell-Rood, 2013</a>), but the evidence is based almost exclusively on observational data and theoretical modelling. For instance, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib100" href="#bib100">Vedder 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2013)
  </a> report on a quantitative assessment of the importance of plasticity in adaptation to climate change based on a long-term population study of wild great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) and conclude that the most important way that birds can cope with climate change is their evolved ability to adjust their behaviour and seasonal timing of reproductive activities depending on spring temperature and abundance of a critical food resource, with extinction risk being 500 times higher in the absence of plasticity. Modelling approaches suggest that developmental variability and learning can enhance nonheritable phenotypic variation and, by smoothening of multipeaked landscapes that relate genotypes to fitness, this can in principle affect both the course and the rate of evolution to a fitness peak, and it can do so in changing as well as in ‘fixed' environments (see, for example, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34" href="#bib34">Ghalambor 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30" href="#bib30">Frank, 2011</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75" href="#bib75">Saito 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2013
  </a>). However, although plasticity can accelerate evolutionary rate, there are indications that it may decrease the average fitness (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75" href="#bib75">Saito 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2013
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of developmental plasticity, it has been stated that it may enhance establishment success, promote invasiveness, decrease vulnerability to environmental change and reduce extinction risk because it allows for individuals (or their progeny) to develop phenotypes that are well suited to novel conditions without first undergoing local genetic adaptation through natural selection (see, for example, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91" href="#bib91">Sultan, 2000</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60" href="#bib60">Pfennig 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>). 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24" href="#bib24">Forsman (2014)</a> reported on the results of a meta-analysis of experimental manipulation studies of plants and animals, demonstrating that greater genetic and phenotypic variation among individuals included in founder groups contribute to increased establishment success, but that study did not aim to evaluate the effects of plasticity on establishment. The reason for this exclusion was that, to my knowledge, there are as yet no studies that have experimentally manipulated the capacity for plasticity to investigate whether and how this might affect establishment and population persistence. In contrast, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16" href="#bib16">Davidson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2011)
  </a> reported on the results of a meta-analysis that indicate that invasive plant species display higher phenotypic plasticity compared with co-occurring, closely related, noninvasive species. They used for their comparisons both separate traits and a composite measure of species plasticity based on means across different traits. On a larger scale, it has been suggested that plasticity promotes evolutionary diversification and speciation (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71" href="#bib71">Price 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2003
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103" href="#bib103">West-Eberhard, 2003</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59" href="#bib59">Pfennig and McGee, 2010</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60" href="#bib60">Pfennig 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66" href="#bib66">Pigliucci, 2010</a>), but again experimental evidence seems to be lacking.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of plasticity in some contexts should be contingent upon the spatial and temporal scales of environmental heterogeneity and change, relative to the dispersal capacity and generation time of the organisms (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46" href="#bib46">Levins, 1968</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31" href="#bib31">Frank and Slatkin, 1990</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75" href="#bib75">Saito 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2013
  </a>). It is conceivable that if there is a substantial time lag between exposure to the environmental cue and the expression of the induced response, selection may drive the population to extinction before the appropriate phenotype has been realized (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102" href="#bib102">Wennersten and Forsman, 2012</a>). Costs associated with such time lags are likely to be manifest most strongly for irreversible developmental plasticity when the induced change is not realized until the next generation. This hypothesis could potentially be evaluated experimentally by first using a split-brood design, exposing half of the siblings to a range of environmental conditions to increase the level of interindividual phenotypic variation, and the other half to homogeneous conditions, and then comparing the establishment success, population dynamics and persistence of phenotypically highly variable versus less variable founder groups. This would not answer the question of whether the capacity for plasticity buffers against environmental change, but would indicate whether standing phenotypic variation resulting from plasticity promotes ecological success of populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether or not plasticity is beneficial for fitness of individuals and viability of populations is also contingent on how reliably the cues predict future environmental conditions and selective regimes. For instance, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72" href="#bib72">Reed 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2010)
  </a> presented results of a stochastic individual-based model and found that demographic consequences of plasticity depend in a complex, nonadditive way on the reliability of environmental cues and the magnitude of environmental fluctuations. When environmental variation was highly unpredictable, strong plasticity increased rather than decreased extinction risk (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72" href="#bib72">Reed 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>). See also 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12" href="#bib12">Chevin 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2013)
  </a> for a discussion of this issue.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taken together, it seems that plasticity may either promote or impair ecological success of populations, depending on environmental conditions. However, firm evidence to this effect based on experimental manipulation approaches is lacking. Solving the problem of how to manipulate the capacity for developmental plasticity and flexibility is a daunting task, but it is crucial for continued scientific progress and to further our understanding of the many ways by which environmental heterogeneity and change may influence the evolution of genetic and phenotypic diversity at different levels of biological organization on one hand, and to investigate how plasticity affects the ecological success on the other hand.</p>
</sec>
