<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What is a trait?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not all types of traits can be straightforwardly assigned to either of the above categories of plasticity. For instance, the size and shape of antlers in mammals of the family Cervidae, such as deer, is an example of irreversible developmental plasticity, but new antlers are grown each year, and the antlers of an individual can change in both size and shape among years. Similarly, the size and colouration of feathers in birds remain largely fixed after feathers are fully grown, but can change within individuals between moults. This raises the question of whether the antlers of a deer, the plumage of a bird or aspects of behavioural and life-history characters as expressed on different occasions by the same individual should be considered as one or as different traits. One way to address such intraindividual plasticity is to quantify, compare and model individual reaction norms based on longitudinal data (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57" href="#bib57">Nussey 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3" href="#bib3">Araya-Ajoy and Dingemanse, 2014</a>). In modular organisms, phenotypic responses to environmental cues can be differentiated and restricted to certain body compartments, such as size and shape of leaves subjected to sun-exposed versus shaded environments (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67" href="#bib67">Pigliucci 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1999
  </a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68" href="#bib68">2003</a>), and aerial versus aquatic leaves in some plants (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10" href="#bib10">Bruni 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1996
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92" href="#bib92">Sultan, 2003</a>). Interestingly, this enables the individual to be a generalist, and may be of particular importance for sessile organisms that cannot choose or move to a more suitable environment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As another case in point, consider the plethora of factors that influence growth rate and body size in snakes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>). Snakes have indeterminate growth, meaning that they continue to grow more or less throughout life, although at a rate that decreases with increasing body size and age, and with males or females growing larger adult body sizes depending on species (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82" href="#bib82">Shine, 1991</a>). Their growth rates are flexible and influenced by the internal environment, including genetic makeup and number of vertebrae (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49" href="#bib49">Lindell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1993
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83" href="#bib83">Shine, 2000</a>), as well as by the external environment, for instance in the form of prey availability (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26" href="#bib26">Forsman and Lindell, 1996</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48" href="#bib48">Lindell and Forsman, 1996</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23" href="#bib23">Forsman, 1996b</a>). Unlike vertebrate taxa with limbs, snakes display considerable variation in the number of vertebrae, both among species and among individuals within populations (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5" href="#bib5">Arnold, 1988</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49" href="#bib49">Lindell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1993
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47" href="#bib47">Lindell, 1994</a>). Vertebral number reflects the combined effects of heritable (additive) genetic variation and developmental plasticity in response to temperature conditions during early embryonic development, and unlike growth rate and body size it does not change during the rest of the life of the individual (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5" href="#bib5">Arnold, 1988</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49" href="#bib49">Lindell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1993
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83" href="#bib83">Shine, 2000</a> and references therein). Because snakes are gape-limited predators that swallow their prey in one piece, their foraging success depends on body size (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27" href="#bib27">Forsman and Lindell, 1993</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22" href="#bib22">Forsman, 1996a</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through its effect on locomotor capacity and speed (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4" href="#bib4">Arnold and Bennett, 1988</a>), there is also potential for vertebral number to indirectly influence foraging success and growth rate. Snakes are ectothermic, and their growth rates depend strongly on body temperature, as do virtually all aspects of their physiology and behaviour, including foraging activities (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36" href="#bib36">Huey and Kingsolver, 1989</a>). Body temperature of snakes is in turn influenced by behavioural thermoregulation mediated via shifts in bodily postures and shuttling between microhabitats; examples of reversible phenotypic flexibility and behavioural plasticity (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90" href="#bib90">Stevenson, 1985b</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21" href="#bib21">Forsman, 1995</a>). Body temperature of snakes and other ectothermic organisms is also influenced by external weather conditions, and by body colouration and body size, all of which affect the rate at which solar radiation is converted into body heat as well as equilibrium body temperature (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89" href="#bib89">Stevenson, 1985a</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21" href="#bib21">Forsman, 1995</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28" href="#bib28">Forsman 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2002
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2" href="#bib2">Ahnesjö and Forsman, 2006</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39" href="#bib39">Karpestam 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
  </a>). This example illustrates that to apply the plasticity concept(s) to single ‘traits' (for example, body size) as a means to increase our understanding of organismal design and differentiation among individuals and populations can be a daunting endeavour (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
