<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P3" class="p">Three principal methodologies are typically used to surmise information on the physics and statistics of contemporary unforced GMST variability: 
 <bold class="bold">1)</bold> Unforced GMST variability is studied using the output of coupled atmosphere-ocean global climate models run under perpetual preindustrial boundary conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>–
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <bold class="bold">2)</bold> Unforced GMST variability is studied using observed or reconstructed datasets spanning the most recent century to approximately the past millennium
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>, and/or 
 <bold class="bold">3)</bold> Unforced GMST variability is studied in climate model experiments that incorporate historical estimates of time-varying external radiative forcings
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>–
  <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Such studies could be used to draw inferences about unforced GMST variability in the future if it is assumed that GMST variability is more-or-less independent of the climatological GMST. However, given that many features of the climate system are not independent of absolute temperature, it is plausible that the physics and statistics of GMST variability might not be conserved across a wide range of climatological GMST values. For example, a warmer climate will likely be characterized by changes in mean sea ice extent
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>, hydrology
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>, upper ocean stratification
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, and surface energy budget partitioning
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>, all of which could impact GMST variability.
</p>
