<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12282-sec-0015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions, limitations and perspectives on adaptive divergence</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have reviewed here evidence strongly suggesting that the striking phenotypic differentiation in ecologically relevant traits exhibited by natural populations of blue tits in their southern range‐edge putatively reflects adaptation to the heterogeneity of their habitat. This is not exclusive to a concomitant role of plasticity (as has been discussed for laying date and body mass), bearing in mind that plasticity itself can vary across populations (Porlier et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0104">2012a</a>), can be adaptive and can evolve. The conclusions presented here are the result of 40 years of individual monitoring in contrasted habitats and of collection of data on a diverse set of phenotypic traits, including estimations of fitness, on individual relatedness and on genetic and genomic variation. This long‐term effort has provided compelling evidence for a habitat‐driven phenotypic variation that is most likely driven by local adaptation: laying date is a heritable trait, which shows contrasted distributions and divergent selection across evergreen and deciduous habitats, and these differences are partly maintained in aviary conditions. However, we acknowledge here that these clear conclusions come with certain limitations which will inspire our future research. First, our study system is dependent on the natural heterogeneity of the habitat, and as such, it has some inherent limitations. In particular, there is a lack of replication of deciduous landscapes in Corsica because of its rarefaction in the Mediterranean region. Second, studying a variety of traits in natural bird populations is not easily combined with common garden and/or reciprocal transplant experiments, which makes it more difficult to provide evidence that observed phenotypic differences have a genetic basis. Third, divergent selection has not yet been illustrated (nor explored) for all the traits presented in Table 
  <a rid="eva12282-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#eva12282-tbl-0001">1</a>. Fourth, some of the phenotypic variation observed between our study sites (e.g. differences in yellow chroma across Corsican populations) is not clearly linked to habitat or geographic distance. In these rare cases where no ecological driver was yet identified, the most parsimonious explanation for this phenotypic variation remains that it is explained by nonadaptive processes such as drift (even if, in the specific case of the yellow chroma, the literature on the evolution of colours suggests that a finer exploration of factors such as parasites, food abundance or environmental stressors will probably reveal that some of these factors may explain the observed population differences). Two of the most relevant and promising perspectives to overcome these limitations are the multidimensional study of (natural, social and sexual) selection across habitats and the development of an ecological genomics approach.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a recently developed theoretical model, the strength of local adaptation is shown to be correlated to trait dimensionality (Macpherson et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0085">2015</a>): local adaptation (or the fitness advantage of residents over immigrant individuals) increases with the number of traits under spatially variable selection, in other words the number of traits influencing adaptation to environmental heterogeneity. Although we have presented here a phenotypic divergence measured on many different traits, some of these traits, in particular the timing of breeding, display stronger differences across populations than others. A comparative analysis across traits could offer a comprehensive view on which traits are more strongly habitat related. Also, as many of these traits are correlated, further work on the evolution of habitat‐specific trait combinations should integrate estimations of phenotypic and genetic covariances (Teplitsky et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0130">2014a</a>). Finally, the recent development of new approaches for the study of the dynamics of selection in space and time and its impact on adaptive evolution (Bell 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0003">2010</a>; Siepielski et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0122">2013</a>; Chevin and Haller 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0030">2014</a>) makes the estimation of spatial variation in selection for all traits in Table 
  <a rid="eva12282-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#eva12282-tbl-0001">1</a> a timely and exciting perspective which would greatly contribute to understanding differences in adaptive divergence rates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has long been acknowledged that loci involved in adaptation should show increased levels of genetic differentiation between populations (Lewontin and Krakauer 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0083">1973</a>; Nielsen 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0099">2005</a>). Benefiting from that idea, several methods have been proposed to detect loci under selection (e.g. Nielsen 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0099">2005</a>; Excoffier et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0047">2009</a>; Narum and Hess 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0098">2011</a>). Our next step in this project is to explore further the genomic differentiation across temporal, spatial or ecological boundaries and attempt to pinpoint genomic regions that have been involved in adaptation. While it will be impossible to identify all loci responsible for phenotypic variation (Manolio et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0086">2009</a>), new tools are being developed to most accurately capture loci with larger effects. Based on the strong phenotypic divergence described in this article, we are particularly excited at the perspective of examining whether outlier loci co‐localize with candidate genes that have been described for the timing of breeding (Johnsen et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0067">2007</a>; Caprioli et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0018">2012</a>; Liedvogel et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0084">2012</a>) and for personality (Savitz and Ramesar 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0117">2004</a>; Fidler et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0048">2007</a>; Mueller et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0095">2014</a>). Such data will also allow to answer the crucial question of whether these focal traits are affected by the same molecular mechanisms in different populations and different ecological contexts.
 </p>
</sec>
