<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12282-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolutionary biologists are primarily interested in understanding the processes that explain the origin and maintenance of biological diversity. Phenotypic differences within a given species can have at least three main origins: genetic drift, phenotypic plasticity or evolutionary divergence, also called adaptive divergence. For populations to adapt to their local environment, that is for local adaptation to occur, divergent selection between habitat patches should result in higher relative fitness of resident versus immigrant genotypes (Williams 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0136">1966</a>). This process of divergent adaptation, although primarily triggered by opposing forces of natural selection, also involves a complex interplay between selection, gene flow, genetic drift and the presence of genetic variation in fitness traits (Hedrick 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0061">2000</a>; Savolainen et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0118">2013</a>). Hence, demonstrating an adaptive process requires several steps that involve knowledge on the phenotypic variation, the populations' genetic properties and dynamics, the quantitative genetic (co)variation of adaptive traits and the characterization of the shape, direction and strength of natural (social and sexual) selection acting on these traits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnitude of adaptive divergence is theoretically expected to increase with the amount of genetic variation within populations (Fisher 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0049">1930</a>; Lande 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0079">1980</a>) and the level of environmental divergence between populations (Endler 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0046">1977</a>). Adaptive divergence is also expected to be greater when genetic drift (Lande 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0078">1976</a>; Hereford 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0064">2009</a>) and gene flow between populations (Slatkin 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0126">1985</a>; Lenormand 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0081">2002</a>) are lower. However, the interplay between ecological and evolutionary processes can substantially complicate this general picture. For instance, although gene flow is generally predicted to have a homogenizing effect counteracting phenotypic diversification (Slatkin 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0127">1987</a>; Garcia‐Ramos and Kirkpatrick 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0051">1997</a>; Lenormand 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0081">2002</a>), gene flow can reversely promote adaptive divergence by counteracting inbreeding depression or by increasing genetic variation, and thus adaptive potential (Garant et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0050">2007</a>). As a consequence of this complexity in the interactive processes, the study of local adaptation is ideally multifaceted and multidisciplinary (Kawecki and Ebert 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0068">2004</a>), a challenge which is more realistically faced in experimental systems than in free‐living populations. One of the best ways to investigate higher performance of resident versus immigrant organisms in a given habitat is to use reciprocal transplants or common garden experiments because these approaches allow maximizing the power to reveal genotype‐by‐environment interactions. Such experiments have provided so far the most extensive contributions to our understanding of processes involved in adaptive divergence (see Blanquart et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0006">2013</a> for a review). However, they are not easily applicable in many organisms and do not always allow an accurate evaluation of the relative importance of selection versus gene flow or genetic drift, in particular in highly mobile organisms occupying a heterogeneous environment (see e.g. Merilä and Hendry 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0091">2014</a> for a review in the context of a response to climate change).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study of the origins of biological diversity between species has provided several emblematic examples of adaptive divergence (Schluter 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0119">2000</a>). Two prominent examples are the adaptive radiation in beak size and shape in the Galapagos Darwin's finches (e.g. Grant 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0055">1986</a>) and the explosive diversification of cichlid fishes in the lakes of East Africa (e.g. Kocher 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0069">2004</a>). Overall, studies of species complexes have provided sufficient examples to conclude that adaptive radiation is widespread (Schluter 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0119">2000</a>; Gavrilets and Losos 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0052">2009</a>). However, when it comes to understanding phenotypic variation at smaller temporal and spatial scales, there is much less compelling examples, in part because the above‐mentioned complexity of processes makes it very difficult to demonstrate that phenotypic divergence is adaptive and that it has a genetic basis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although historically, geographic isolation of populations was seen as a prerequisite for their adaptive divergence (Mayr 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0088">1963</a>), it has now long been recognized that reproductive isolation can evolve even between populations connected by gene flow whenever divergent selection is strong relative to gene flow (Maynard Smith 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0087">1966</a>; Rice and Hostert 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0112">1993</a>). However, the realization that such divergence in spite of gene flow can occur at microgeographic scales, that is within the range of the organism's dispersal distance, is only just arising (Postma and Van Noordwijk 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0107">2005</a>; Milá et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0093">2010</a>; Richardson et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0113">2014</a>). This is surprising given that some classical examples of fine scale adaptation, such as the adaptive variation in colour morphs of the Peppered Moth 
  <span class="italic">Biston betularia,</span> date back several decades (Saccheri et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0115">2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We aim here at showing how the Mediterranean blue tit 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span> study system is an equally fascinating example of phenotypic divergence. We will outline the story of a long‐term project where we tested for phenotypic and genetic divergence as well as for possible local adaptation of bird populations using a diversity of complementary approaches – from the study of phenotypic differentiation to the recent development of ecological genomics. This project started with the erection of nest boxes by Jacques Blondel in 1975 in Mediterranean oak forests of Provence (Southern France) and on the island of Corsica, with the purpose of comparing breeding strategies between mainland and island populations (Blondel 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0007">1985</a>). The long‐term monitoring of blue tits in these forests led to the striking observation that populations as close as 24 km differed in their breeding phenology by up to 1 month, depending on the type of vegetation they use for reproduction (Blondel et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0012">1999</a>). Although the habitat‐specific phenotypic differences were soon found salient (Blondel et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0010">1993</a>; Lambrechts et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0073">1996</a>, 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0074">1997a</a>), understanding the processes that lead to this intraspecific biodiversity is still an ongoing objective. Indeed, if one is to avoid the Panglossian paradigm whereby adaptation is considered a fundamental assumption (Gould and Lewontin 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0054">1979</a>), one needs to consider alternative (and nonexclusive) adaptive (including plasticity) and nonadaptive (including drift) processes when testing for an adaptive divergence. Moreover, the integration of phenotypic, genetic and fitness data is required to confidently confirm evolutionary adaptation at the genetic level (Barrett and Hoekstra 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0002">2011</a>) and is at the core of current research in this study system. Within the abundant literature published from this study system, we will focus here on the main findings that provide tests for an adaptive origin to the strong phenotypic differentiation observed across heterogeneous Mediterranean landscapes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After briefly presenting the model system, we first summarize the main phenotypic divergence observed in blue tit populations living in forests dominated either by deciduous or evergreen trees. For each divergent trait, we review the evidence obtained from aviary/common garden experiments regarding a possible genetic origin to the observed phenotypic differentiation as well as evidence for heterogeneous selection. Second, we argue that most phenotypically differentiated traits display heritable variation, a fundamental requirement for evolution to occur. Third, we review evidence for nonrandom dispersal, selective barriers and assortative mating as processes that could reinforce local adaptation. Fourth and finally, we show how population genetics and ecological genomics support isolation – by – environment (IBE) across habitats. As this study is published in a Special Issue that aims at highlighting women's contribution to basic and applied evolutionary biology, we have added some personal comments on women's position in this long‐term project (Box 
  <a rid="eva12282-fea-0001" ref-type="boxed-text" href="#eva12282-fea-0001">1</a>).
 </p>
 <div position="float" content-type="Box" id="eva12282-fea-0001" orientation="portrait" class="boxed-text" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Box 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Personal reflections</div>
  </div>
  <sec id="eva12282-sec-0017" class="sec" xmlns="">
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Research presented here is based on the Mediterranean blue tit study system that was started forty years ago by J. Blondel. The project was originally developed by men only, in particular by J. Blondel, P. Perret and M. Lambrechts. In the past 10 years, the sex ratio of the team has largely become equal. We do not feel that this change in sex ratio led to any more changes in research questions than expected due to the inclusion of any new researcher in a team. However, more equal sex ratios may have resulted in more diverse ways of working with students and positively impacted group team working in the field and in consequent research work. We do not intend to draw general conclusions based on the progression of this single scientific group, yet we wish here to share some personal feelings as women working in the field of evolutionary biology.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Working in a country (France) where 80% of women claim to be victims of sexism at their workplace (2013 poll on 15 000 women by the Higher Council of Professional Equality (CSEP)), we feel privileged to state that the authors of this article have not experienced overt gender‐based discrimination in their PhD, postdoctoral or senior research years. However, this does not exclude the occurrence of more subtle or hidden preconceived biases about the professional capacity of males and females that are still common worldwide. These are often reflected in recruitment outcomes when applying for permanent/tenure track positions (Reuben et al. 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0111">2014</a>). In addition, the fact that tenured positions tend to be secured at an increasingly older age, often at a time when fertility curves in women are declining, only aggravates women's underrepresentation in science (Ceci and Williams 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0022">2011</a>). While in‐depth studies quantifying gender bias in science and identifying its causes and consequences are available elsewhere (Ceci and Williams 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0022">2011</a>; Williams and Ceci 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0137">2012</a>; Reuben et al. 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0111">2014</a>; Leslie et al. 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0082">2015</a>), here we highlight how, as women, we interacted with the requirements of scientific work involved in this long‐term research project, and how we believe to have created a positive working environment from which the research programme, women and men researchers, and their children, have all benefitted from.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conducting long‐term research in ecology implies being committed to fieldwork for several weeks (if not months) away from home annually. As several female researchers reported beforehand (e.g. Mcguire et al. 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0090">2012</a>), we reconciliate the two by occasionally bringing our children to the field and by relying on our partners and family for engaging in joint child rearing. This is true for both mothers and fathers working in our research group. At the same time, flexibility is an equally important aspect of running a large‐scale field project with a larger number of fieldworkers. Thus, parental leaves of team members were never an issue as field logistics were always prepared well ahead of time and contingency plans were available. Importantly, special efforts were made to accommodate researchers with small dependents (
    <span class="italic">i.e</span>. their children), thereby substantially improving the suitability of the work environment for mother and father ecologists (for an excellent analysis of the challenges faced by women ecologists, see the study of Mcguire et al. 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0090">2012</a>). These steps not only incredibly benefitted each individual researcher at such special point in their life (Williams and Ceci 
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0137">2012</a> and references therein), but it also strengthened the team of fieldworkers available each year, and allowed to foster a sense of continuity, inclusion and identity in promoting the long‐term dimension of the programme.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of fieldwork practicalities, the only noticeable change following this sex‐ratio transition was a lowering of the highest nest boxes to allow access to all, which made life on the Blue tit field easier for both men and women. With more PI women in the field, fieldwork became a more family friendly adventure (Fig. 
    <a rid="eva12282-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12282-fig-0004">B1</a>(A)), allowing mothers – and fathers – to find a new middle ground that focuses on fieldwork. From the child's perspective, coming to the field is an incredibly enriching experience (Fig. 
    <a rid="eva12282-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12282-fig-0004">B1</a>(B)), as they are exposed to wilderness we are increasingly separated from in our daily lives. Equally importantly, they can also witness their parents in their professional role, in a unique environment and in a setting void of gender roles. Including children into our fieldwork routines often increased our participation in science outreach projects in kindergartens and schools while back at home, but also within the field site communities. Although quantitative data are needed to support this claim, we believe that transgressing traditional divides of work and life by welcoming children in the field sensitizes us to further participate in educational science outreach projects and thus directly impacts our communities. We hope this testimony will provide encouragement to young women and men and convince them that embarking in a field project is rewarding both professionally and personally and that it can be made compatible with a fulfilling family life.
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="eva12282-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure B1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Bringing children to the field. (A) The daily nest box monitoring in the Fango valley and in good company. (B) Allowing children to participate in fieldwork increases their awareness of the natural environment, which is often a stepping stone to set up science outreach projects. Photo credit: (A) F. Laurière; (B) M.‐O. Beausoleil.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="EVA-9-135-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </div>
</sec>
