<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12282-sec-0014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Isolation by environment revealed by population genetics and genomics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Throughout the duration of the project, it was established that an impressive number of phenotypic traits diverged between the mainland and the island of Corsica, but also at small spatial scales within Corsica (Table 
  <a rid="eva12282-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#eva12282-tbl-0001">1</a>). Moreover, for a large number of these often uncorrelated traits, vegetation type was systematically identified as the driver for phenotypic differentiation. Given that significant additive genetic variance was reported for several of these traits, it is pertinent to ask whether there is a habitat‐driven genetic basis for the systematic differences observed at the phenotypic level. As discussed above, aviary and cross‐fostering experiments provided evidence for a genetic basis in the habitat‐specific differentiation of some of the traits (in particular laying date), but not others (e.g. morphology, clutch size), even though all traits were heritable. In this study system, testing whether blue tit genetic differences are driven by habitat type [defined as isolation by environment (IBE, Wang and Bradburd 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0134" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0134">2014</a>), isolation by ecology (Edelaar and Bolnick 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0044">2012</a>) or more broadly genotype–environment associations (GEA, Hedrick et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0062">1976</a>)] therefore becomes a necessary stepping stone before identifying the genetic basis of local adaptation (Barrett and Hoekstra 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0002">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gaining an in‐depth knowledge of population genetic structuring has recently witnessed immense progress thanks to next‐generation sequencing (NGS) methods (Davey et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0032">2011</a>). For our study system, we could thus transition from a panel of 6–10 highly polymorphic, neutral microsatellite markers (Porlier et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0105">2012b</a>) to up to 
  <span class="italic">c</span>. 12 000 bi‐allelic single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers (Szulkin 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>, 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-7777" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-7777">in press</a>). SNP markers were generated through a RAD seq (restriction site associated DNA sequencing) approach (Baird et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0001">2008</a>) and positioned in both coding and noncoding regions of the genome. Thus, 197 resident birds from D‐Rouviere and the three Corsican populations (D‐Muro, E‐Muro and E‐Pirio) were genotyped using single‐end RAD sequencing (Szulkin 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>, 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-7777" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-7777">In press</a>). The distribution of allelic frequencies revealed by the SNP marker data set differed between the mainland and Corsica and was characterized by a larger number of rare allelic variants in Corsica when compared to the mainland – a variability that will need to be addressed in future population genomic work. Using a series of complementary population genetics and landscape genetics analyses, both microsatellite and SNP‐based studies found multiple evidence of habitat‐linked genetic differentiation (Porlier et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0105">2012b</a>; Szulkin 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>, 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-7777" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-7777">in press</a>, see Table 
  <a rid="eva12282-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#eva12282-tbl-0002">2</a>), which we refer to as isolation – by – environment (IBE, Wang and Bradburd 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0134" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0134">2014</a>). Importantly, SNP‐based analyses also found a small yet highly significant genetic differentiation, measured with pairwise 
  <span class="italic">F</span>st tests, between D‐Muro and E‐Muro (Table 
  <a rid="eva12282-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#eva12282-tbl-0002">2</a>). This result was further corroborated by several complementary population genomic analyses. Given that the two study sites are only 5.6 km apart and that blue tit average dispersal distance is believed to range between 330 m and 4 km (depending on dispersal distance estimation method (Tufto et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0132">2005</a>; Ortego et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0100">2011</a>) while maximum dispersal values are known to range up to 470 km (Winkel and Frantzen 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0139" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0139">1991</a>), the genetic distinctiveness of the two populations is remarkable. Overall, an important question that thus needs to be further addressed is whether genetic IBE results from reduced dispersal through habitat choice, local selection against maladapted genotypes or a combination of both. Research in progress will focus on combining phenotypic and genetic data to improve our understanding of the ecological and evolutionary processes shaping observed patterns of genetic differentiation.
 </p>
 <div id="eva12282-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Above the diagonal: 
    <span class="italic">F</span>st values from Porlier et al. (
    <a rid="eva12282-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0105">2012b</a>, data averaged across several years), 
    <span class="italic">n </span>= 247 Individuals, 6–10 microsatellite markers. Below the diagonal: 
    <span class="italic">F</span>st values for SNPs retained after filtering with 5% MAF and a 95% call rate. 
    <span class="italic">n </span>= 197 individuals, 3159 SNPs (Szulkin 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>, in press). Empirical 
    <span class="italic">P</span>‐values in brackets were computed using 500 permutations (lowest 
    <span class="italic">P</span>‐values are therefore bounded by 0.002)
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <thead valign="top">
    <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D‐Rouvière</th>
     <th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D‐Muro</th>
     <th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E‐Muro</th>
     <th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E‐Pirio</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D‐Rouvière</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D‐Muro</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0541 (
      <span class="italic">P </span>≤ 0.002**)
     </td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E‐Muro</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0335 (
      <span class="italic">P </span>≤ 0.002**)
     </td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0156 (
      <span class="italic">P </span>= 0.004**)
     </td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E‐Pirio</td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0520 (
      <span class="italic">P </span>≤ 0.002**)
     </td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0099 (
      <span class="italic">P </span>= 0.347)
     </td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0102 (
      <span class="italic">P </span>= 0.403)
     </td>
     <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="permissions">
   <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The possibility of combining pedigree‐based quantitative genetics with genomic data is indisputably an exciting new analytical framework to study heritability (Stanton‐Geddes et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0129">2013</a>; Berenos et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0004">2014</a>) and variation of phenotypic traits in our blue tit study system. Assuming a sufficiently dense marker density, the complementary use of SNP‐based relatedness estimators and field‐collected pedigrees should allow to accurately perform not only quantitative genetic analyses, but also to identify regions of the genome that have undergone selection (Jensen et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0065">2014</a>). Several methods have been developed to meet these goals: for example, QTL‐focused approaches (recently identified as prone to type one error in the context of field‐based studies with limited sample size, Slate 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0125" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0125">2013</a>) are being replaced – or complemented by – new methods for phenotype‐associated genomic prediction (Goddard and Hayes 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0053">2009</a>), genomic partitioning (Robinson et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0114">2013</a>; Santure et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0116">2013</a>), as well as relatedness‐ and population structure‐corrected genomewide association studies (GWAS) and candidate gene‐based approaches (Savolainen et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0118">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the decreasing costs of sequencing and the development of sequencing platforms capable of generating even longer sequence reads at lower cost, SNP data sets are likely to be replaced with sequence (haplotype) data and even whole genome sequencing in the future. While genotype‐by‐sequencing approaches will allow us to substantially improve the availability of reference genomes, alignment and ascertainment bias‐free allelic frequency data, some challenges will also lie ahead: bioinformatics capacity in terms of processing power and know‐how needs to be regularly updated. In addition, analytical lines of research will always have to be balanced with time spent in the field – a cornerstone stage necessary for the collection of phenotypic, fitness and environmental data relevant to our study species of interest.</p>
</sec>
