<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12282-sec-0012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selective barriers against migrants</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Richardson et al. (
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0113">2014</a>) describe this mechanism as reduced fitness for migrants, acting before they reproduce through premating isolation. The habitat‐specific breeding phenology could well work as a reinforcing barrier against maladapted dispersal if laying date is culturally or genetically inherited. Indeed, if two populations are breeding at different spring periods, they will obviously not mate with each other, which in turn will strengthen the reproductive barrier that may have arisen for other independent reasons. Anecdotic cases of birds born in deciduous habitats but breeding in evergreen ones support this view, as these birds initiated reproduction too early compared to the caterpillar abundance (Charmantier, pers. comm.), and vice versa for the reverse situation. Apart from this phenological mismatch between habitat types, it has also been suggested that differences in social dominance of birds originating from deciduous or evergreen habitats could contribute to restricting dispersal and maintaining population phenotypic differentiation at a micro‐geographic scale (Braillet et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0017">2002</a>). Indeed, the larger size of male blue tits from D‐Muro (and possibly stronger colorations) provides them with a systematic dominance over the smaller males of E‐Pirio, thereby creating a potential barrier for the settlement of evergreen birds in deciduous areas. Finally, the dialects and differences in avian songs detailed previously could also contribute in driving population divergence, such as what has been shown in species where females prefer to mate with the males possessing the local versus a foreign dialect (e.g. Podos 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0103">2010</a>). Hence, the existence of dialects in Corsica could contribute to explain the reduced gene flow between valleys, previously highlighted as part of an insular syndrome (Blondel et al. 
  <a rid="eva12282-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12282-bib-0012">1999</a>). In the future, we aim at testing this crucial hypothesis using both mate choice experiments and playbacks.
 </p>
</sec>
