<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There has been a general trend toward earlier flight periods in Swedish butterflies the last 20 years, and 
  <span class="italic">Anthocharis cardamines</span> is among the species that has advanced its adult emergence most. Moreover, most Swedish butterfly species follow the typical pattern of later flight dates in more northern populations but this cline is steeper in 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span>. This type of correspondence appears to be a general trend as the rate of phenological change over time shows a significant correlation with the degree of change in flight date with latitude. This was true for both the full dataset with all Swedish butterflies as well as for the subgroup of univoltine, pupal diapausers, to which 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> belongs. The results also show the quite intuitive pattern that butterfly species that are bivoltine start reproduction earlier in the year compared to univoltine species. This is most likely because selection in bivoltine species favors individuals that can use a longer period of the favorable season to produce two rather than one generation. In this respect, the early spring flight period of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> is clearly atypical for an univoltine butterfly in Sweden, occurring on average more than a month earlier than the other species (May 31 as compared to July 5). The early emergence of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> is very probably a direct consequence of that newly hatch larvae feeds on flowers and developing fruits of early flowering Brassicaceae plants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the last decades, there have been substantial phenological changes in a large number of animal and plant species (Walther et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2002</a>; Menzel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2006</a>; Parmesan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2007</a>). As the typical direction of change has been an advancement of phenological events, it has been causally linked to recent climate change and in particular the global increase in temperatures (Sparks and Yates 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">1997</a>; Stefanescu et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2003</a>). The results presented here add to this literature. More interestingly, this study and that of Karlsson (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>) found that the rate of phenological change over time was correlated with the phenological changes across latitudes. This suggests that species of butterflies that show strong latitudinal variation in phenology, presumably due to spatial variation in climate, also tend to show strong effects of changes in climate over time. This correspondence is expected if the adaptations that control butterfly life cycles and phenology include response to aspects of climate that changes in a similar way over time and space, and that populations along the latitudinal gradient respond in similar ways to climatic cues. While temperature is one obvious and important aspect of climate, other cues, such as the photoperiod, will not show this type of parallel change in time and space, i.e., the photoperiod at a given time of year varies with latitude while it is not influenced by temporal changes in climate at any given location. For our particular study system, this pattern suggests that it is reasonable to use the “space for time” paradigm to get a rough idea of how climate is likely to affect the phenology of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> and how this might influence its host utilization (Hodgson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2011</a>). Indeed, it seems likely that both temporal and spatial changes in the phenology of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> are reflecting strong effects of thermal conditions on the hatching of adults in comparison with other butterfly species. In support of this idea, the flight date of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> shows a strong response to ambient spring temperature during pupal development where an increase of 1°C advances flight date with 6.4 days. Mean value for other univoltine butterflies overwintering in the pupal stage is an advancement of 3.3 days/°C (cf. Karlsson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The regulation of life cycles of temperate insects is typically due to plasticity in relation to seasonal cues such as photoperiod and temperature (Tauber et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">1986</a>; Nylin and Gotthard 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">1998</a>). Given the patterns shown here, it seems likely that the part of the life cycle determining adult emergence of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> in the spring is highly dependent on temperature. As this species spends the overwinter period in the pupal stage, it is the post-diapause pupal development in spring that will determine when the adults hatch. Hence, variation in adult emergence is likely to be strongly affected by the thermal reaction norms of pupal development. The advancement of spring phenology during the last decades as well as the latitudinal variation is likely to be largely a consequence of plasticity in response to variation in temperature (Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2008</a>; Merilä and Hendry 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2014</a>). However, thermal reaction norms have a genetic basis and may evolve in response to environmental changes. Indeed, recent experimental studies demonstrate that thermal reaction norms of post-diapause development in 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> varies among populations from different latitudes suggesting that a part of the spatial variation in phenology seen here is due to local adaptation in these thermal reaction norms (Posledovich et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2014</a>; Ståhandske et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2014</a>). This also indicates that natural selection due to consistent directional change in climatic conditions over time will alter adaptations that are central for the evolution of phenology. From a climate change perspective, such evidence of local adaptation in thermal reaction norms suggests that responses to similar changes in temperatures will differ between regions along latitudinal gradients.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the field survey examining host plant use of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> in three regions along a latitudinal gradient, we documented significant differences among regions in which of the host species that were used for oviposition. Given that the butterfly has strong preferences for plants in a given phenological stage (Arvanitis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2008</a>; this study), it is likely that effects of climate on the temporal overlap between the butterfly and each of the host plant species were important for these among-region differences. Such differences in temporal overlap between the butterfly and the different host plant species in response to latitudinal variation in temperature are to be expected if the thermal reaction norms differ between host plants and between the butterfly and its preferred host plants. It might seem reasonable to assume that phenological specialists, such as 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span>, are particularly sensitive to changes in climate. However, while the butterfly is expected to be under strong selection to match its phenology with the temporal distribution of Brassicaceae flowers in the spring, it is simultaneously strongly selected to be able to use multiple hosts given that the temporal overlap with one given species varies among years (Wiklund and Friberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2009</a>). As a result, the specialized feeding on the young fruits and seeds of its hosts is combined with the ability to utilize a quite wide host range of Brassicaceae species. Such a notion, that the species can be characterized as a phenological specialist but a host species generalist, is strongly supported not only by our data on latitudinal variation in host use but also by data on between-year variation in host use at a given site. During a 5-year study of the species at one locality in Sweden (the central location in this study), the species oviposited on 16 of the 18 available Brassicaceae species (Wiklund and Friberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2009</a>). A tentative conclusion is therefore that an assumed sensitivity of herbivores specializing in particular phenological stages of their host plants to climatic variation might sometimes be buffered by an ability to switch host plant species. If such host plant switching does not occur, we should expect very strong selection on consumer reaction norms to match the reaction norms of their resources.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results also show that within species, the phenological state and size of the hosts at the time of butterfly reproduction are important for oviposition. For most of the plant species, we found that later-flowering individuals attracted more eggs, although in one of the main hosts, 
  <span class="italic">C. paludosa</span>, early flowering plants were significantly more used for oviposition. These results are important in two respects. First, they provide further evidence that phenological stage is important for butterfly host plant selection and that not only among-species choice but also choices within species are influenced by the phenological stage of the host plant. Moreover, several within-species patterns varied among regions suggesting that the exact temporal overlap between butterfly oviposition and host plant flowering had a strong effect on the realized host use across the climatic gradient described by the latitudinal range and that this overlap differed among regions. This suggests that the effect of climatic variation on host plant phenology, both in space and over time, will be of major importance for the realized host use of 
  <span class="italic">A. cardamines.</span> Second, given that butterfly attack has strong negative effects on plant fitness (König 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2014</a>), the documented patterns of butterfly preferences translate to butterfly-mediated selection on plant flowering phenology. Given that butterfly attacks are relatively frequent in host plant populations, our documented patterns suggest that butterfly-mediated selection on plant flowering phenology may differ not only among different host plant species but also among regions within species.
 </p>
</sec>
