<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We would expect higher [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] to affect biochemical discrimination because of the known effects elevated [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] has on stomata (size, density, and conductance; 
 <xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">Woodward, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">Woodward &amp; Bazzaz, 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr">Tognetti et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Ainsworth &amp; Rogers, 2007</xref>). In a meta-analysis of trees in European temperate and boreal forests, leaves responded to an increase in [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] with a significant (21%) decrease in stomatal conductance (the rate of passage of atmospheric CO
 <sub>2</sub> into plant tissue; 
 <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Medlyn et al., 2001</xref>). Increased [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] also causes a decrease in stomatal density (the number of pores on a leaf surface) and stomatal index (the number of pores compared to the number of total epidermal cells); these indices have been liberally applied to the geologic record to reconstruct [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] (
 <xref rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr">Retallack, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Beerling &amp; Royer, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">Roth-Nebelsick et al., 2014</xref>). Because stomata directly control the flow of carbon dioxide into leaves and control carbon isotope fractionation by diffusion (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Farquhar, Ehleringer &amp; Hubick, 1989</xref>), changes in stomatal parameters could affect fractionation as well. Additional factors must be considered; the dependence of Δ
 <sub>leaf</sub> on [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] may in part be due to isotopic discrimination associated with photorespiration (
 <xref rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr">Schubert &amp; Jahren, 2018</xref>). Indeed, previous growth chamber studies in prescribed CO
 <sub>2</sub> environments showed increased carbon isotope fractionation with increased [CO
 <sub>2</sub>]; 
 <xref rid="ref-84" ref-type="bibr">Schubert &amp; Jahren (2012)</xref> found a strong hyperbolic correlation (
 <italic>r</italic> &gt; 0.94) between [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] and Δ
 <sub>leaf</sub> values in two species of herbaceous angiosperms. Based upon these growth chamber experiments (
 <xref rid="ref-84" ref-type="bibr">Schubert &amp; Jahren, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), the relationship between [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] and Δ
 <sub>leaf</sub> is expected to be most sensitive at geologically low [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] (including pre-Industrial to present values) as it was in the levels present during plant growth in this study.
</p>
