<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We identify regions across the globe (between 50 degrees latitude north and south) where significant changes in rainfall have occurred during the main growing season months within the last 33 years. We use rainfall data compiled by the University of California Santa Barbara Climate Hazards Group known as the Climate Hazards Group Infrared Precipitation with Stations version 2 (CHIRPSv2, [
 <xref rid="pone.0170615.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]). Using the CHRIPSv2 dataset, for each 0.05 degree pixel, a 1981–2013 time series of main growing season rainfall was produced. This primary growing season was defined at each pixel as the three-month period with the highest climatological mean rainfall. While this interval may not align with the primary growing season at every location, it does generally hold for rainfed agriculture, and in those locations where it does not align with the growing season it serves as a proxy for crop available water resources. Time series of these three month accumulations were then transformed into standardized precipitation index (SPI) time series using the gamma distribution to parameterize the historical values [
 <xref rid="pone.0170615.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. The SPI calculates rainfall anomalies from main wet season precipitation as normalized variables, which convey the probabilistic significance of the observed or estimated rainfall [
 <xref rid="pone.0170615.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. For each pixel, we calculated the trend (using a linear regression algorithm in IDL) in SPI over the time period. Finding the trend in SPI allows us to identify meaningful shifts in rainfall at each location in a way that looking at rainfall amounts may not capture. We screened out areas where the trend was not statistically significant at the 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.05 level to identify only those pixels with a statistically significant change in wetting or drying. These pixels were classified as wetting (positive slope) or drying (negative slope) and all other pixels were classified as neither.
</p>
