<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Drought is already having marked impacts on plant populations across the southwestern USA and northeastern México (
 <xref rid="ref76" ref-type="bibr">Miriti 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Bullock 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref133" ref-type="bibr">Winkler 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref135" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>; but see 
 <xref rid="ref89" ref-type="bibr">Peters 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>). Individual plants may be able to tolerate short-term drought by adjusting strategies, as we demonstrated here, but these adjustments may not be enough to compensate for the negative population effects brought by increased plant mortality within a population (e.g. 
 <xref rid="ref84" ref-type="bibr">Ogle and Reynolds, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Le Roux 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>). For example, alpine grass species in Switzerland were able to maintain agb production in response to experimental short-term warming when adequate soil moisture was maintained, but experienced biomass declines and mortality when short-term warming coincided with drought (
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">De Boeck 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). High levels of alpine plant mortality were also observed in response to natural drought in Australia, suggesting that the seasonal timing of drought events may be more important than their duration (
 <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Griffin and Hoffmann, 2012</xref>). Timing of seasonal precipitation plays a major role in Baja California systems (
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Douglas 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993
 </xref>) and has shaped the fire history of SSPM (
 <xref rid="ref114" ref-type="bibr">Skinner 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>). We demonstrate that drought during the seedling establishment phase can reduce survival rates of 
 <italic>H. brandegeei.</italic> Surely, the timing of drought in systems like the sky islands of SSPM will not only influence establishment, but also phenological traits and performance of already established individuals (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Crimmins 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>; present study). These patterns share similarities with how the sub-Antarctic cushion 
 <italic>Azorella selago</italic> responds to experimental drought (
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Le Roux 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>). Reduced rainfall treatments caused increased stem mortality and accelerated senescence. Our study also showed increased mortality, albeit on single-stemmed seedlings. The response of older, multi-stemmed 
 <italic>H. brandegeei</italic> would likely have produced results similar to 
 <italic>A. selago</italic>, whereby individual plants were unable to support biomass at current levels and, thus, lose individual stems to compensate for reduced water availability (
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Le Roux 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Barbeta 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>).
</p>
