<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The sensitivity of the scaling relationship between timespan and magnitude of temperature change to errors was tested using a Monte Carlo approach. 10,000 versions of our compilation were created with randomly applied normally distributed timespan errors of ±50% (2
 <italic class="italic">σ</italic>), and normally distributed magnitude errors of ±4 °C (2
 <italic class="italic">σ</italic>). Our compilation is dominated by O-isotope, TEX
 <sub class="sub">86</sub>, alkenone and Mg/Ca proxies (153 data points), which have typical errors of ≤4 °C (refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>). Our modelled errors likely exceed the magnitude uncertainties in the records we studied because we are interested only in relative changes in temperature within individual records rather than the absolute temperatures. In our approach, magnitude trends can change sign after addition of errors (that is, warming becomes cooling). Tests using a routine that ignored trend reversals caused by the addition of errors (‘rejection sampling') demonstrated that the combined oceanic and continental data have 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> values of &lt;0.01 in a fractionally lower proportion of simulations (99.92% versus 99.99%). Issues of stratigraphic incompleteness are unlikely to impact timespan estimates unless the timespan is defined through a cumulative dating method such as astronomical cycle calibration, where missing cycles lead to an underestimation of true timespan. Errors of the size we use here for Monte Carlo analysis are nevertheless unlikely to result from incompleteness. Indeed, tests using much larger timespan errors of ±70% (2
 <italic class="italic">σ</italic>) still yielded significant 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> values (
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> value&lt;0.01) in &gt;99% of simulations (simulations with timespans that become negative after error addition are rejected). The mean Spearman's 
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic> coefficient describing the correlation between timespan and magnitude in our 10,000 simulations for the combined ocean and continental data is 0.37±0.09 (2
 <italic class="italic">σ</italic>). Analysis of separate continental and ocean data demonstrates that the scaling in the continental data is unlikely to be robust in the presence of significant errors owing to the small size of this data set (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>=31), with 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> values of &lt;0.05 yielded in ∼76% of simulations, with a mean 
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic> of 0.43±0.22. In contrast, analysis of the oceanic data demonstrates 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> values &lt;0.05 in 99.99% of simulations, with mean 
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic>=0.35±0.10. The mean of the calculated slopes in our simulations was 0.09, with an uncertainty of±0.03 (2
 <italic class="italic">σ</italic>). Thus, the uncertainty in the slope from the Monte Carlo error analysis is the same as that derived from the regression and bootstrapping of the raw data (0.10±0.03), albeit with a fractionally lower slope value. We employed bootstrapping (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>=1,000) to quantify the 95% uncertainty interval for the calculated slope of each individual Monte Carlo simulation. Our results indicate that slopes were significantly &gt;0 in &gt;99% of the simulations.
</p>
