<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avenues of further methodological research</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The preceding Earth system sciences challenges (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) are rather generic for complex dynamical systems and apply to many other fields. The challenges point to a way forward to advance causal inference methods for such systems. In the short term, our example applications demonstrate that the existing methods already address some of the mentioned challenges. For example, PCMCI was developed to address high-dimensional time-lagged linear and nonlinear causal discovery and takes into account autocorrelation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> and CCM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> was specifically built to account for nonlinear state-dependent relationships. The largest potential for short-term methodological advancements lies in combining different conceptual approaches in order to address multiple challenges.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, to give some examples, such as those listed in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, causal network learning algorithms that deal well with high-dimensional data are limited by their inability to identify causal directionality among Markov equivalence classes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. This shortcoming can be alleviated by combining causal network learning algorithms with the SCM framework and making additional assumptions on (independence of) mechanisms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>
  </span> that permits to identify causal directions in these cases. Secondly, novel methods can incorporate ideas from theory on causal discovery in the presence of unobserved variables and selection bias
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>, time-sub-sampling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>
  </span>, time-aggregation and cyclic feedbacks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>
  </span>, and measurement error
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>
  </span>. Thirdly, filtering methods as preprocessing steps, e.g., based on wavelets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>
  </span>, can help to disentangle causal relations on different time scales, in the simplest example by filtering out a confounder like the seasonal cycle.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the mid-term, it is worth exploring methods that have not been applied to Earth system data, but whose theoretical properties may render them suitable for the challenges at hand. For example, further methods that are based on the principle of independent mechanisms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>
  </span> such as prediction invariance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span> or causal discovery from non-stationary data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span> can potentially make use of the ubiquitously present nonstationarity and external perturbations in Earth system data to infer causal structure. While the black-box character of most machine learning algorithms and deep learning in particular does not lend itself directly to causal discovery, such tools can nevertheless be useful in many aspects of causal discovery. For example, Chalupka et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>
  </span> use neural networks to reconstruct causal features from gridded time series datasets. Also conditional independence tests can be based on deep learning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>
  </span> and causal inference can be phrased as a classification problem
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
  </span>. And the other way around: causal knowledge, as argued by Pearl, should be incorporated into machine learning to yield more robust predictions and classifications, for example, in such unresolved problems as extrapolation and domain adaptation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
