<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combining observational causal inference and physical modeling</div>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the long term, we envision that the two main approaches to understand the Earth system (observational data analysis and Earth system modeling) should become more and more integrated. On the one hand, the generic problem of model evaluation has outlined ways on how causal inference methods can be used to identify weaknesses of physical models and guide model improvement. Furthermore, the currently often heuristic parametrization schemes in physical models can be guided by causal analyses of the respective variables, similar to the proposal to utilize machine learning to systematically replace parametrization schemes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>. Causal discovery can also help to design computationally expensive physical model experiments more efficiently: causal relationships estimated from climate model control runs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>
  </span> (long model runs with fixed pre-industrial conditions) can provide guidance on where numerical experiments are useful and where causal effects are not to be expected.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, physical constraints, either from theoretical knowledge or from experimental (modeling) results, can be used to regularize causal inference methods, for example, by defining variables, restricting functional classes, identifying expected noise distributions, time lags and time aggregation, or general data preprocessing. Even more integrated, novel causal inference methods can make combined use of observational as well as experimental data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span> which has already led to fruitful insights in genetics. In Earth system sciences, also information from real experiments on subsystems can be incorporated, not on a large climatic scale
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, but for example from ecosystem
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
  </span> and mesocosm experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>
  </span> in ecological labs.
 </p>
</sec>
