<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Computational and statistical challenges</div>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a computational and statistical point of view, scalability is a crucial issue, both regarding sample size (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, point 15) and high dimensionality (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, point 16). While larger sample sizes (long time series) are typically always beneficial for more reliable causal inferences, the computational time of methods may scale unfavorably with sample size (e.g., cubically for some kernel methods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>). The more variables are taken into account for explaining a potentially spurious relationship, the more credible a causal discovery becomes. However, many variables together with large time lags to account for physical time delays (e.g., to identify atmospheric teleconnections), lead to high dimensionality which may strongly affect statistical reliability. This compromises statistical power, that is, the probability to detect a true causal link, and potentially also the control of false positives at a desired significance level
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. Low-statistical power implies that, especially, weak causal effects with low signal-to-noise ratio, which are sometimes of interest, are not well detected. Last, uncertainty estimation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, point 17) that also takes into account potentially available data uncertainties (measurement value as well as dating uncertainties, see points 11 and 14), poses a major challenge for causal inference methods.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the challenges discussed in this section are the same for correlation or regression methods which are, in addition, ambiguous to interpret and often lead to incorrect conclusions as shown in the examples section. We therefore emphasize that there is no strong reason to avoid adoption and exploration of modern causal inference techniques. Each of the methods summarized in the method overview section addresses one or several of these challenges. In Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> we list key strengths and suggest future research directions further discussed in the next section.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>List of methods, key strengths, and further research directions addressing current limitations</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Method</th>
      <th>Key strengths</th>
      <th>Further research directions</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Granger causality and nonparametric extensions
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>Significance assessment; nonparametric versions</td>
      <td>Dealing with contemporaneous effects and feedback cycles; high-dimensionality; deterministic dependencies; synergistic effects; time scales; unobserved variables</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Nonlinear state-space methods
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>State-dependent nonlinear systems; contemporaneous effects</td>
      <td>Significance assessment; high-dimensionality; highly synchronous dynamics; high stochasticity; time scales; unobserved variables</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Conditional independence-based algorithms
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>High-dimensionality; unobserved variables; nonparametric tests</td>
      <td>Significance assessment; deterministic effects; synergistic effects; time scales; contemporaneous feedback cycles</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>PCMCI
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>High-dimensionality; time delays; strong autocorrelation; nonparametric tests</td>
      <td>Unobserved variables; deterministic effects; synergistic effects; time scales; contemporaneous feedback cycles</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Information-theoretic algorithms
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>High-dimensionality; nonparametric; time delays; information-theoretic interpretation</td>
      <td>Significance assessment; unobserved variables; deterministic effects; synergistic effects; time scales; contemporaneous feedback cycles; efficient entropy estimation</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Structural causal models
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>Contemporaneous effects; nonparametric versions</td>
      <td>High-dimensionality; synergistic effects; time scales; unobserved variables; time delays</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Invariance-based methods
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>Utilizes heterogeneity in space and time</td>
      <td>Causality in stationary regimes; same as for SCMs</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Bayesian score-based approaches
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>Bayesian uncertainty assessment; inclusion of expert knowledge</td>
      <td>High-dimensionality; nonlinearity; deterministic effects; synergistic effects; time scales; contemporaneous feedback cycles; unobserved variables; combine with cond. independence-based methods
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>
       </span>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>This table is intended to be a rough method guide. A detailed overview is beyond the scope of this Perspective and hardly possible because comparison studies are currently largely lacking. Spurring research to overcome this lack is a goal of this Perspective and the accompanying platform 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.causeme.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">causeme.net</span>. The terms used in this table are explained in the challenges section and illustrated in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, a crucial challenge when interpreting the output of causal inference methods is that causal conclusions are based on the assumptions underlying the different methods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. These assumptions should, but often cannot, be tested and it is important to make them transparent and discuss how different assumptions would alter conclusions for a particular application.
 </p>
</sec>
