<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Detecting and attributing climate change</div>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Detection and attribution approaches quantify the evidence for a causal link between external drivers of climate change and long-term changes in climatic variables
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. The goal is to first detect a change and then attribute this change to the contributions of multiple anthropogenic and natural forcings, and from internal variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Importantly, the focus lies on the effects of long-term forcings on long-term climatic trends or also changes in, e.g., the frequency of extreme weather events. Such research questions require counterfactual worlds, which can only be constructed with climate models, that are then statistically analyzed. For example, the optimal fingerprinting method
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> is based on attributing detected long-term responses to fingerprint patterns using multiple linear regression. Hannart et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>
  </span> discuss the inclusion of Pearl’s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> causal counterfactual theory for a more rigorous foundation of detection and attribution studies.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, observational causal inference methods can help to improve climate models as discussed above and can also directly be used to analyze climate feedbacks in paleo-climate data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, which is still challenging due to scarce available data and dating uncertainties (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Furthermore, the recent concept of emergent constraints attempts to identify an observable statistical relationship between a feature of interest and a future climate change signal. For example, climate sensitivity, i.e., the response of global mean temperature to greenhouse gas emissions, can be constrained this way
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>
  </span>. The underlying premise is, however, that today’s dependencies between the predictors and climate sensitivity represent actual physical processes that also hold under future climate change. Here causal discovery can give more robust insights by identifying causal predictors that are more likely to hold under future climate change scenarios.
 </p>
</sec>
