<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58185-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Owing to its expected better correspondence to equilibrium surface temperature change, effective radiative forcing (ERF) has taken precedence over the older definition of stratospherically adjusted radiative forcing (RF) for measuring perturbations to the Earth's radiative energy budget (Boucher et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0006">2013</a>; Forster et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0016">2016</a>; Myhre et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0031">2013</a>; Shine et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0041">2003</a>). ERF takes into account the radiative effects of tropospheric and land surface changes to the top of atmosphere (TOA) energy budget, in addition to the stratospheric temperature change, in response to a forcing. Together, these atmospheric and land surface changes are termed rapid adjustments. While there is no formal separation of timescales, rapid adjustments tend to manifest themselves on a period of weeks to months and are distinct from the (generally) slower climate feedbacks, such as the sea ice/albedo, lapse rate, water vapor, and cloud feedbacks, which are driven by the surface temperature response (Sherwood et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0040">2015</a>). Therefore, rapid adjustments are usually considered to be part of the forcing (Forster et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0014">2013</a>; Gregory et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0017">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has long been known (Manabe &amp; Wetherald, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0026">1975</a>) that an increase in CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations cools the stratosphere, which reduces longwave (LW) outgoing radiation, increasing the positive forcing compared to the instantaneous radiative forcing (IRF) of CO
  <sub>2</sub> (the convention in this paper is to report IRF at the TOA). Such knowledge is incorporated into the definition of RF. More recently, it has been acknowledged that CO
  <sub>2</sub> perturbations also change the thermal structure of the troposphere, which leads to changes in water vapor and cloud profiles (Gregory &amp; Webb, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0018">2008</a>). CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing also drives land‐surface changes due to its effects on plant stomatal conductance (Doutriaux‐Boucher et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0012">2009</a>; Richardson et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0035">2018</a>). These components all induce their own responses in the TOA energy balance, which are not included in the standard RF framework.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, for some forcing agents, stratospheric temperatures do not change in the same way as for CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing, and tropospheric changes can be more important (Hansen et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0021">2005</a>). Aerosols have significant impacts on tropospheric radiative heating rates and many aspects of clouds (Ramanathan et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0034">2001</a>), rendering RF as an unsatisfactory method of comparing forcing impacts across greenhouse gases and aerosols (Boucher et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0006">2013</a>; Myhre et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0031">2013</a>). To date, rapid adjustment analyses have largely been based on CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing (Andrews &amp; Forster, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0003">2008</a>; Block &amp; Mauritsen, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0004">2013</a>; Chung &amp; Soden, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0007">2015a</a>, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0008">2015b</a>; Gregory &amp; Webb, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0018">2008</a>; Vial et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0049">2013</a>; Zelinka et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0055">2013</a>) and an investigation across forcing mechanisms has not been made.
 </p>
</sec>
