<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We witnessed to one such event in Southern Italy (on 10 May 2014) between two toad species, the common toad 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> and the green toad 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). They belong to the 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes viridis</italic> species groups, whose divergence has been estimated to the Oligocene (around 20–30 million years ago; 
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Maxson, 1981</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Garcia-Porta et al., 2012</xref>), and which have largely overlapping distributions in Central, Eastern, and Southern Europe (
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sillero et al., 2014</xref>). Although syntopy is not uncommon, especially in lowland areas, they show distinct spatio-temporal patterns of habitat use (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lanza, Nistri &amp; Vanni, 2006</xref>), making hybridisation at least three-times unexpected. First, they show markedly different breeding phenologies: 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> is an early and explosive breeder, while 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> is a late and prolonged breeder (
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lanza, Nistri &amp; Vanni, 2006</xref>). In Italy, breeding activities of 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> begin earlier in the year (early winter to early spring, with variation among sites at different altitude and latitude) and usually last one to two weeks. 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> starts breeding later (middle to late spring), and this activity may last two to three months. Furthermore, breeding activities in syntopic areas have been systematically reported as asynchronous, regardless of intraspecific differences between sites (
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lanza, Nistri &amp; Vanni, 2006</xref>). Second, 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> display differences in their altitudinal distribution. 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> breeding sites commonly occur from 0-2,000 metres above sea level (MASL), while 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> shows marked preferences for sites in lowland areas, rarely being observed above 1,000 MASL (
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Romano, De Cicco &amp; Utzeri, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Spilinga et al., 2007</xref>). Third, in spite of the largely polytopic habits of these two species, differences exist in habitat and breeding site preferences. 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> favours open areas and bushlands and breeds in temporary shallow waters, and 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo bufo</italic> most commonly inhabits forested habitats while using slow-running or deeper, wider standing waters as breeding sites.
</p>
