<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change represents a major challenge for modern and future agriculture, in particular for grapevine cultivation and wine production due its wide geographical distribution, and economic relevance. A significant warming has already been observed in most grape-growing areas of the world affecting the varietal choice as well as grape quality (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mozell and Thach</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). The constant temperature increase trend has been triggering an advanced phenology, anticipating the ripening phase to warmer periods and affecting grape composition and development (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Teixeira et al., 2013</xref>). An increased intensity of visible and UV solar radiation is also severely impacting on leaf morphological and biochemical parameters such as area, pigment, and antioxidant composition (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Castagna et al., 2017</xref>), and berry characteristics, such as sugar-acid ratio and polyphenol abundance and composition (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bobeica et al., 2015</xref>). Finally, water deficit will be a major concern, not only in hotspots already facing seasonal drought, but also where rare heavy rains will alternate with drought during the same season. The scientific community is thus deploying great efforts to study the grapevine response to environmental changes (extensively reviewed in 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Geròs et al., 2015</xref>), with the aim to improve disease and yield prediction models and to identify key genetic traits to be used in grapevine breeding. Transcriptomic studies could be very useful to investigate plant adaptation as tuning of gene expression represents a major adaptive response of the plant. The increasing availability of grapevine transcriptomic data has prompted the creation of 
 <italic class="italic">Vitis</italic>-gene expression compendia, such as VTCdb which included only microarray data (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wong et al., 2013</xref>) and Vespucci which comprises both microarray and RNA-seq data (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moretto et al., 2016</xref>, see 
 <bold class="bold">Table 
  <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>
 </bold>). These databases contain a considerable amount of information that requires proper tools to be explored and interpreted. NES
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>RA algorithm (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Asnicar et al., 2016</xref>) has been developed to expand known LGNs in model organisms, such as 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. thaliana</italic>, from transcriptomic data. It showed better performance than other approaches such as ARACNE (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Margolin et al., 2006</xref>) and NESRA (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Asnicar et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
