<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this work we present the application of NES
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>RA to expand four grapevine LGNs related to the response to climate changes using the Vespucci compendium. To cope with the large computational requirement, NES
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>RA was run on the gene@home project developed on the Berkeley Open Infrastructure for Network Computing (BOINC) platform TN-Grid, which manages the distribution of the calculation among computers made available by the volunteers participating in the gene@home project (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Asnicar et al., 2015</xref>). Here, we show that this approach can provide reliable results also in a non-model species such as 
 <italic class="italic">V. vinifera</italic>, for which a much more limited amount of data is available. NES
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>RA final output consists in an expansion gene list and in an interaction file – defining the relationships among the genes – which are used to reconstruct the expansion network. This represents a helpful tool for biologists to expand LGNs based on 
 <italic class="italic">a priori</italic> knowledge and/or experimental evidence on a system biology level providing novel candidates for further characterization. We focused on four grapevine networks possibly involved in the climate change response. Two networks are related to the secondary metabolic pathways for anthocyanin and stilbenoid synthesis, involved in the response to solar radiation, the remaining two are signaling networks, related to the hormones abscisic acid (ABA) and ethylene, involved in the regulation of cell water balance and cuticle transpiration. The network named “Anthocyanins,” i.e., the red pigments of grapes, comprises 
 <italic class="italic">VvUFGT</italic>, which codes for the main enzyme responsible for anthocyanin biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ford et al., 1998</xref>), a cluster of four 
 <italic class="italic">VvMYBA</italic> genes (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kobayashi et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Walker et al., 2007</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">VvMYC1</italic>, coding for transcription factors known to physically interact and regulate 
 <italic class="italic">VvUFGT</italic> expression (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hichri et al., 2010</xref>). The network named “Stilbenoids,” i.e., grapevine secondary metabolites with plant defense properties (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mattivi et al., 2011</xref>), is composed by 13 genes: four 
 <italic class="italic">VvSTS</italic> genes encoding for different stilbene synthase isoforms, the enzymes catalyzing the synthesis of resveratrol, 
 <italic class="italic">VvMYB14</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">VvMYB15</italic>, coding for two characterized regulators of stilbene biosynthesis in grapevine (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Höll et al., 2013</xref>) and seven genes encoding for peroxidases, enzymes potentially involved in the oligomerization of stilbene monomers. These enzymes have been included even if they have not been proved yet to be part of the stilbenoids regulatory network. The network named “ERFs” is formed by three genes coding for ethylene responsive transcription factors: 
 <italic class="italic">VvERF045</italic> is up-regulated during berry ripening, while 
 <italic class="italic">VvERF042</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">VvERF044</italic> are down-regulated and belong to the 
 <italic class="italic">SHINE</italic> clade of AP2/ERF transcription factors that in 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> have been associated to cuticle structure, leaf and flower composition, and water loss (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aharoni et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shi et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Leida et al., 2016</xref>). Finally, the network named “ABA” consists of five genes related to ABA signaling: three encoding for transcription factors, the ABA responsive element binding factor 
 <italic class="italic">AREB2</italic>, the homeobox 
 <italic class="italic">HB7</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">VvNAC26</italic>; one for an ABA receptor homologous to the 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> ABA insensitive 
 <italic class="italic">ABI1</italic> gene, and one for a receptor kinase 
 <italic class="italic">LRK10</italic>. These genes are up-regulated by ABA treatment in grapevine cell cultures and pre-véraison berry skin samples (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nicolas et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pilati et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">VvNAC26</italic> expression affects berry size, likely by positively regulating ABA biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tello et al., 2015</xref>); 
 <italic class="italic">HB7</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">ABI1</italic> are strictly interdependent in the ABA response in 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soderman et al., 1996</xref>), whereas 
 <italic class="italic">LRK10</italic> is related to ABA signaling and drought resistance in 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lim et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
