<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent seabed warming in the northeastern Gulf of Maine has surpassed the lower physiological threshold for lobster settlement and rapidly expanded the suitable thermal habitat for lobster northeastward (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). By virtue of a well‐mixed water column, warming has made a larger range of depths more suitable for juvenile lobster in the northeastern compared to the southwestern Gulf of Maine. We suggest that the expanded thermal habitat may have played a significant role in the unprecedented surge in landings in the northeastern Gulf of Maine and could explain the decline in settlement density at shallow water monitoring stations as the area of the thermally suitable seabed expanded (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Thus, cooler than average years (e.g., 2004) and warmer than average years (e.g., 2012) show a waxing and waning of potential nursery habitat area, respectively (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Over the past decade as waters warmed, settlement densities in shallow areas have declined (Table 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>), but these declines may have been offset by expanded thermal habitats (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and increased depth of larval sounding behavior (Annis, 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). To the extent that trends in recruitment predict trends in landings, these results suggest an alternate future for the American lobster fishery, which has been predicted to be on the verge of an imminent decline due to the decline in the density of observed settlers (Le Bris et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Oppenheim, 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Our two methods of estimating newly settled lobster abundance suggest relative stasis (or a slight increase) in the southwestern Gulf of Maine and a somewhat more positive outlook for near‐term landings in the northeastern Gulf of Maine than would be suggested simply from shallow settlement densities.
</p>
