<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The thermally mediated dilution hypothesis is not the only potential explanation of declining recruitment density. Declining reproductive output (Koopman, Westgate, &amp; Siders, 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), recruit‐per‐egg ratios (Le Bris et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), and lipid‐rich prey of larvae (Carloni et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) have been proposed as mechanisms driving declines in recruitment density under warming conditions. Consequently, Le Bris et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) project that recruitment in a warming Gulf of Maine will show widespread declines across the American lobster's range with only slight increases projected for the northeastern Gulf of Maine. The assumption of reduced recruitment naturally leads to the conclusion that the Gulf of Maine lobster fishery is on the precipice of an imminent decline (Le Bris et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Oppenheim, 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). However, these alternative hypotheses may not fully capture patterns of lobster demography in the Gulf of Maine. Recruitment patterns predicted from SST alone may underestimate recruitment in stratified regions where there are significant surface‐to‐bottom thermal differences. Additionally, declining per capita egg production could be offset by increased spawning stock biomass (ASMFC, 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Le Bris et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Sherman et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) facilitated by an increased area of suitable habitat offshore (Tanaka &amp; Chen, 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Since the abundance of stage‐one larvae has been shown to be significantly correlated with the abundance of spawning stock biomass (Carloni et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) it would stand to reason that stage‐one larvae have increased alongside spawning stock biomass. However, annual fluctuations in spawning stock biomass, temperature, spawn timing, and coastal current characteristics may impact the total amount of competent stage‐four larvae transported across suitable recruitment habitats. Finally, the degree to which larval lobsters are food limited in the plankton is not well understood (Carloni et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14778-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Nonlinear effects of warming on multiple life stages make even short‐term projections of recruitment exceedingly difficult. However, each effort to do so highlights processes that merit observation; in this case, determining whether deep‐water settlement can offset nearshore declines in abundance, and how this may affect landings forecast models.
</p>
