<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The performance of the band-shifting scheme has been assessed using hyper-spectral data from radiative transfer simulations and field observations [
 <xref rid="B53-sensors-19-04285" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The errors in 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm43">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> at the target wavelength are within a few percent, usually well below 5%. Another assessment has been performed with satellite data [
 <xref rid="B53-sensors-19-04285" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-sensors-19-04285" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. From global products on a one-twelfth-degree resolution grid, all coincident SeaWiFS and MODIS-Aqua daily 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm44">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> values were accumulated for the year 2003 and compared (approximately 50 million spectra). After band shifting, the median ratio 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm45">
   <mrow>
    <mi>μ</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> between MODIS-Aqua and SeaWiFS data is closer to 1 in all cases. Thus, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm46">
   <mrow>
    <mi>μ</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> between MODIS-Aqua 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm47">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> at 488 nm and SeaWiFS 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm48">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> at 490 nm is 1.030 versus 1.007 after band shifting, i.e., when MODIS-Aqua 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm49">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is expressed at 490 nm. Similarly, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm50">
   <mrow>
    <mi>μ</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is 1.108 for comparisons between MODIS-Aqua data at 547 nm and SeaWiFS 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm51">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> at 555 nm, whereas it is 0.978 after band shifting. At 510 nm, the median ratio is also close to 1 (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm52">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>μ</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mn>0</mn>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mn>979</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) despite the spectral distance between 510 nm and the original MODIS-Aqua bands (approximately 20 nm). On the other hand, improvements are fairly limited in the red domain (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm53">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>μ</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mn>0</mn>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mn>92</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>). The values of 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm54">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>s</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> in this spectral interval are often very low, and relative uncertainties are likely to be high. The results obtained with satellite data appear satisfactory, taking into account that the errors associated with the band-shifting scheme cannot be separated from actual differences between sensor-specific products.
</p>
