<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For each wheat-growing grid cell and year, we first determined whether the cell and year were affected by SWS or EWS (
 <italic class="italic">D
  <sub class="sub">i</sub>
 </italic> = 1) or were not affected by SWS or EWS (
 <italic class="italic">D
  <sub class="sub">i</sub>
 </italic> = 0) during each wheat growing season, on the basis of the thresholds defined in table S2. For a 1-year window of water scarcity, we considered only the events during the year of harvest. For a 2-year SWS/EWS window, the grid was considered to be affected by water scarcity (
 <italic class="italic">D
  <sub class="sub">i</sub>
 </italic> = 1) if SWS/EWS thresholds were met either in the harvest year or during the previous harvest year. Similarly, a 3-year window of water scarcity categorized a grid as experiencing SWS/EWS if conditions were met during the SPs of the harvest year or the two preceding years. The use of the 1-, 2-, and 3-year windows allowed us to examine the impacts of a sequence of SWS (EWS) events on WhP (e.g., the 2010 droughts in Russia and India and the 2012 drought in the United States). The area affected by severe or extreme drought was then determined as follows
 <disp-formula id="E1" class="disp-formula">
  <math id="m1" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mtext class="mtext">Area affected by drought</mtext>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mn class="mn">100</mn>
     <mo class="mo">*</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mstyle displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
        <msubsup class="msubsup">
         <mo stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</mo>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mi class="mi">i</mi>
          <mo class="mo">=</mo>
          <mn class="mn">1</mn>
         </mrow>
         <mi class="mi">n</mi>
        </msubsup>
       </mstyle>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">D</mi>
        <mi class="mi">i</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo class="mo">∗</mo>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">w</mi>
        <mi class="mi">i</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mstyle displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
        <msubsup class="msubsup">
         <mo stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</mo>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mi class="mi">i</mi>
          <mo class="mo">=</mo>
          <mn class="mn">1</mn>
         </mrow>
         <mi class="mi">n</mi>
        </msubsup>
       </mstyle>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">w</mi>
        <mi class="mi">i</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
 </disp-formula>where weight 
 <italic class="italic">w
  <sub class="sub">i</sub>
 </italic> is the share of the global WhA (for WhA calculations) or global WhP. We also accounted for variations in grid size due to latitude.
</p>
