<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Arctic climate is subject to a drastic change. A key element in Arctic climate change is the rapid decline in sea ice coverage and thickness seen in observations in particular since 2000. Research is needed to improve understanding of sea ice development and weather forecasting abilities since an increased human use of the Arctic in all kinds of economic sectors is anticipated. Here we report on results with respect to the potential future of large-scale sea ice development in the Arctic as they are relevant for shipping. We also make suggestions on how to improve weather forecasts, which are essential for regional sea ice forecasting on shorter time scales. The results described here also provide relevant input on the environmental conditions to studies of the potential development in other economic sectors such as oil and gas exploration and fisheries (see, e.g., Petrick et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the EU-funded project ACCESS—Arctic Climate Change, Economy and Society, studies were performed to enhance the understanding of the interaction between this decline of sea ice and changes in the atmosphere and ocean. Long-term trends in response to anthropogenic forcing appear on the centennial time scale, but large natural variability of the atmosphere–ocean–cryosphere system is superimposed on time scales of years to a few decades, which hampers the detection of trends. Earth System Models are our only tools to predict the system, but they have their limits since they are sensitive to how well physical processes are represented and spatially resolved in the models and as a consequence of the natural variability.</p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we discuss our abilities to hindcast and predict sea ice conditions in the Arctic Ocean. In the first part, we present new findings regarding the pan-Arctic sea ice evolution from 1980 to 2040. Earth system model simulations, chosen according to the models’ performance in comparison to observed sea ice concentration in the twentieth century, will be used to evaluate the evolution of the Arctic sea ice volume based on a subset of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) program called Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 5 (CMIP5) (Taylor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2012</a>). From the past to present, we compare these simulations (Shu et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2015</a>; Song 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2016</a>) with a model that assimilates observations [PIOMAS—Pan-Arctic Ice-Ocean Modelling and Assimilation System; Zhang and Rothrock [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2003</a>)] and sea ice volume estimations based on observed freezing conditions expressed as Freezing Degree Days (FDD) deduced from ERA-Interim reanalysis (Dee et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2011</a>; Gao 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2013</a>) for the historical period. ERA stands for European reanalysis. ERA-Interim is a data set resulting from a global climate reanalysis covering the period from 1979 to the present. This combination allows a validation of the Earth system model results on the large spatial scale. We will then present results focusing on future sea ice conditions on a finer spatial scale, using the best performing CMIP5 model to drive a regional, finer scale model. In the second part, we zoom into the conditions in the shelf areas of the Arctic, as they are relevant for ship navigation, taking into account critical narrow passages along the Northeast Passage (NEP). In the third part, we will introduce recent findings regarding the options to improve high-latitude weather forecasts in the future, which is also pivotal for improving sea ice prediction in critical regions to allow safer operations in Arctic ocean regions.
 </p>
</sec>
