<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Throughout the Jurassic in the Sundance Seaway, benthic communities varied in composition along a water‐depth gradient that reflects onshore–offshore position, and this pattern is shown by the distribution of biofacies (Fig. 
 <xref rid="pala12278-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>). In the Middle Jurassic, biofacies M2 (
 <italic class="italic">Camptonectes</italic> sp.), M6 (
 <italic class="italic">Gryphaea planoconvexa</italic>), and M8 (
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nebrascensis</italic>) occur mostly in deeper water environments (carbonate deep subtidal and offshore), with the biofacies M2 also occurring in the open shallow subtidal of sequence J1a. Biofacies M3 (
 <italic class="italic">Camptonectes stygius</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Procerithium?</italic> sp.), M4 (
 <italic class="italic">Liostrea strigilecula</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Camptonectes platessiformis</italic>) and M7 (
 <italic class="italic">Astarte meeki</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pleuromya subcompressa</italic>) occur mostly in open shallow subtidal facies, but also in the adjoining ooid shoal and peritidal environments. Biofacies M3 and M4 also record the highest abundance and diversity of epifaunal grazing gastropods, possibly indicating a position well within the photic zone, where algal growth increased the complexity of the habitat (Fürsich 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1984</xref>). Restricted shallow subtidal facies, which formed under elevated salinity conditions in the most inner part of the carbonate ramp during sequence J1a (Clement &amp; Holland 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), lie at the shallow extreme of the gradient. Biofacies M1 is most common in samples from siliciclastic systems, but occur also in open shallow subtidal facies of sequences J2, highlighting the eurytopic character of its dominant species 
 <italic class="italic">M. curta</italic>.
</p>
