<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Further, we explored the attributes of our time‐series with tools in the package Systat 13.1 (Systat Software Inc., Chicago, Illinois, USA, 2009). First, we used autocorrelation function analysis and partial autocorrelation function analysis plots (Box &amp; Jenkins, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1976</xref>) to examine whether time‐series were autocorrelated or not. Second, because most of our time‐series were sinusoid shaped with a seasonal component, we used a Fourier transformation on raw data and modeled them with autoregressive integrated moving average models (ARIMA; Hamilton, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>). We built forecast models for eight new surveys (predicted for the next 2 years) with an ARIMA with seasonal periodicity of four surveys for the same datasets used in TRIM analyses. Because most time‐series were not autocorrelated, we then fitted stepwise multiple regressions to the log(x + 1) transformed abundances of the same datasets, using a variety of climatic independent variables, including sea surface temperatures that characterize El Niño and La Niña events. These variables are detailed in Table 
 <xref rid="ece33515-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref> and fall into three categories as follows: (1) variables related to the conditions of the day of the survey; (2) variables related to the month of the survey; and (3) variables with a time lag of 15 or 30 days preceding the survey (see details in Lucas et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Because insect development is temperature dependent, the accumulation of degree‐days is used routinely in entomology and is relevant in the context of predicting changes in herbivore populations (e.g., Ives, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1973</xref> for pests). Hence, we considered the accumulation of degree‐days as explanatory variables in the (3) category and calculated them as indicated in Table S1. Another important variable in category (3) was the El Niño/Southern Oscillation (ENSO) index, obtained from the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration (
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Although we removed variables with high multicollinearity from the final models (i.e., when tolerance values &gt;0.001), models should be viewed as explanatory analyses. Eventually, we performed a canonical correspondence analysis (CCA) to evaluate the influence of climatic variables (Table S1) on the composition of saturniid species within each survey (details in Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece33515-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>).
</p>
