<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Widespread declines in bird populations are evident across much of North America, with recent findings revealing that an alarming one-third (37%) of North American bird species are of high conservation concern [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Long-distance neotropical migrants have declined more steeply than residents and short-distance migrants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. Longer journeys mean that these birds encounter more potential impediments along their migratory routes, including collisions with man-made infrastructures, light pollution, increased predation risk, and inadequate food sources [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. In addition, anthropogenic and environmental threats on the breeding and wintering grounds add to the suite of stressors for neotropical migrants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. Unfavourable weather conditions are one of the most detrimental factors that can compromise their survival and reproductive phenology [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Having a more holistic understanding of the climatic processes and their impacts on migratory birds would allow conservation strategies to be effectively implemented for these species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Migratory birds have endured arduous and perilous journeys between and within North, Central and South Americas for millennia. However, with climate change projections predicting drastic alterations in climatic conditions, uncertainty exists about the future persistence of migratory bird populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. The predicted increase in the frequency, intensity, and duration of extreme weather events—including droughts, intense precipitation, and windstorms—are expected to have adverse effects on avian population dynamics [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Neotropical migrants may be particularly susceptible to extreme climate variability, as climate fluctuations and anomalies can result in direct mortality and/or impact food availability during all stages of their annual cycle: breeding, wintering, and migration [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. Understanding how climatic conditions at different stages of the annual cycle influence the survival of neotropical migrants is critical in evaluating how climate change will impact migratory birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The objective of this study was to examine how annual survival of a neotropical migrant, western yellow-breasted chat (
  <span class="italic">Icteria virens auricollis</span>; hereafter: chat), is influenced by climatic conditions during its breeding, wintering, and spring migratory periods. We developed capture-mark-recapture models constrained with climate variables to evaluate the effects of: (1) El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO) during the entire annual cycle; (2) temperature and precipitation conditions on the breeding grounds; (3) precipitation level on the wintering grounds; and finally (4) wind speed, precipitation level, and number of storm events on the spring migration route. Survival was estimated using 15 years (2001–2015) of capture-recapture data from a breeding population of chats in southern British Columbia, Canada. Our study presents the first comprehensive analysis on how adult survivorship of chats in this endangered population [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>] in Canada can be influenced by climate factors throughout three major phases of its annual cycle.
 </p>
</sec>
