<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change forecasts indicate an increase in the frequency and intensity of extreme weather, including storm events, droughts, and prolonged precipitation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>]. With stronger climate fluctuations and anomalities against a backdrop of anthropogenic changes to the landscape, these stressors present a challenge for long-distant neotropical migrants during all stages of their annual cycle [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Our study showed that storm events were more frequent during weaker ENSO events (i.e. higher SOI values), and that westerly wind speed within the western flyway was also positively correlated with SOI values [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. However, the direction and degree to which ENSO is affected by climate change are unclear [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>]. We found that the frequency of storm events was negatively associated with chat survival, whereas GDD had a positive association. Both of those climate indices are expected to increase with climate change; whether the effects of one factor would offset the effects of another is unknown. Therefore, given such uncertainties, we are currently unable to predict with confidence the mechanistic effects of climate change on the population dynamics of chats. The interplay between these climate factors within the context of climate change will need to be further explored to elucidate how neotropical migrant bird survival will respond to a changing climate. We also recommend conducting a similar study for multiple chat populations across its range, allowing for a more complete and broader picture of the population dynamics with respect to climate conditions. Furthermore, understanding the cumulative effects of climate change and other anthropogenic threats such as habitat loss and man-made migration hazards will be critical to prioritize appropriate strategies for chats and other neotropical migratory passerines.
 </p>
</sec>
