<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Authors’ contributions</div>
 <p>ACH, DJG, and CAB designed the study. ACH and CAB conducted the field work. ACH and AD managed and compiled the data. DJG conducted most of the data analysis. ACH wrote the manuscript with contributions from all co-authors. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acknowledgements</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We thank Michael Bezener, Richard Armstrong, Tiinesha Begaye, Tim Forrester, Natasha Barlow, Jenn Baici, Jon Ruddy, Hilary Lefort, Julien St-Amand and many others for their contributions in the field. We also thank the En’owkin Centre, the Osoyoos Indian Band, and many other private land owners for access to their lands.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Competing interests</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Availability of data and materials</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dataset used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consent for publication</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not applicable. This study does not contain individual person’s data in any form.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scientific permit to capture and band migratory birds and Species at Risk Act permits were granted to Christine Bishop. The project was reviewed by Animal Care Committees at Simon Fraser University and the British Columbia Ministry of the Environment.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Funding</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was funded by Environment and Climate Change Canada, the En’owkin Centre, and the Science Horizons Program (Government of Canada).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Publisher’s Note</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
