<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study species and area</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The yellow-breasted chat is a neotropical migratory songbird with a transcontinental distribution extending from southern Canada, the United States, Mexico, to Central America (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The western 
  <span class="italic">auricollis</span> subspecies has a fragmented breeding distribution in the west, which includes our study area in the south Okanagan valley of British Columbia, Canada, at the northern tip of the geographic range for this subspecies (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Genetic evidence indicates that the western subspecies overwinters on the westcoast of Mexico (southern Baja California, Sinaloa to Oxaca) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. Chats in the south Okanagan valley nest in low elevation (&gt;500 m) riparian thickets dominated by wild rose (
  <span class="italic">Rosa</span> spp.), snowberry, and other native shrub species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Their diet consists primarily of insects, but also includes fruits and rose petals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. We colour-banded, monitored, and resighted birds breeding in the Okanagan valley from Penticton (49º 27′ N, 119º 36′ W) to Osoyoos (49º 1′ N, 119º 26′ W) on the USA border, a distance of 66 km between 2001 and 2015. To ensure that resighted individuals were accurately determined, colour combos were confirmed upon multiple observations and by at least two observers (see McKibbin and Bishop [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>] for details). Birds were sexed and aged (second-year [SY] or after second-year [ASY]) based on plumage characteristics and molt limits [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Location points used to collect climate data from the approximated migration route (wind = 
     <span class="italic">circle</span>; precipitation = 
     <span class="italic">triangle</span>), wintering ground (
     <span class="italic">diamond</span>), and breeding ground/study site (
     <span class="italic">star</span>) of yellow-breasted chats (western subspecies). 
     <span class="italic">Shaded</span> in 
     <span class="italic">light and dark grey</span> are the breeding and overwintering ranges of yellow-breasted chats (both subspecies), respectively, adapted from IUCN (April 2016)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12898_2017_139_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
