<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In Asia, there is a growing consensus that individuals need to promote sustainable consumption and build a sustainable society. The current empirical study extended the literature by identifying perceived risk, personality traits, VBN theory and TPB model and proposed a moderating model for pro-environmental behavioral intention of undergraduate students with structural equation modeling. This model predicts relationships between factors of pro-environmental behavioral intention, environmental concern, sustainability value, social norms, pro-environmental attitude and perceived risk of climate change. It also provides improvements to the measurement of personality trait mitigation by considering roles of sustainability value, environmental concern, social norms, perceived risk and pro-environmental attitude. The findings also highlight the psychological significance of personality traits and antecedent constructs pro-environmental attitude to climate change. The effects of personality on the antecedents of pro-environment behavioral intention cannot be overstated; the current findings are strong encouragement for future research in this field. Overall, our study demonstrates that personal traits may pose some barriers to encourage pro-environmental attitude for undergraduate students and could be served as a useful framework for further investigations. Green education could improve pro-environmental attitude and build its connections to the planet, value and concern for undergraduate students and they may behave more eco-friendly manners. From a practical perspective, understanding of driving or deterring factors of the pro-environmental attitude and behavior intention can better inform green educators and sustainability policy managers in Taiwan. By expanding the scope of research beyond traditional pro-environment behavioral intentions, this conceptual model helps clarify how pro-environmental behaviors can help fight climate change and it is a call for further research. Further research is necessary to explain the detailed interactions of personal traits and pro-environmental behavior related to GCC issues—for example, actors of participants, situational activators and information sources of participants [
 <xref rid="B98-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>].
</p>
