<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">A comparison between the 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cw</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub> values at the observation sites suggests that the Yangtze subaqueous delta was widely erodible during most of the study period. The seabed at the observation sites with water depths from &lt;1 m to 21 m (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>) was not erodible only during slack waters under calm weather, which generally comprised less than 40% of the study period (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). It can be inferred that the erodibility in the subaqueous delta deeper than 21 m is comparable to the erodibility at the observation sites due to the similarity of tidal conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup> and comparable 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub> values (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4c</xref>). The lack of a significant vertical trend in the 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub> values of the core sediments suggests that the deposit layers are relatively homogenous for the upmost approximately 20 metres. This vertical stability does not reflect the seasonal changes in the erodibility of the real-time surficial sediment. According to the present Yangtze’s sediment discharge (ca. 120 Mt/yr), its seasonal variability, and the subaqueous delta area (&gt;10, 000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>), the deposition in the subaqueous delta during summer can be several centimetres in thickness. The erodibility of this fresh deposition must be even lower than that shown above (the upper 30 cm of the sediment sampled during the dry season). This low erodibility was also verified using known erosion dynamics produced by other researchers. For example, vertical degradation appeared in the mouth area of the North Branch (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref>) between 1997 and 2012 with a mean rate of −6.7 cm/yr and margin recession was also noted in the subaqueous delta front offshore of the South Branch
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. Du 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> also reported an erosion rate of approximately 2 cm/yr at the mouth area off the South Branch. The amount of sediment eroded from the subaqueous delta was more than 1 billion tons from 2002 to 2013 and mainly occurred between −6.4 m and −19 m isobaths
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. In contrast, high and dense vegetation in the salt marshes of the Yangtze Delta efficiently attenuates waves and currents
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>, and the 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cw</italic>
 </sub> is generally lower than the 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub> of the bed sediments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>, which suggest a much lower erodibility. However, marsh edge collapses can result in the loss of salt marshes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>. Tidal flat erosion is expected to create steep slope along the lower marsh edge, and marsh edge collapses subsequently shrinks salt marshes.
</p>
