<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">An erodible seabed does not necessarily lead to net erosion. Both erosion and deposition events occur during a tidal cycle. Net seabed erosion/accretion depends on the balance between the erosion flux and deposition flux
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. The erosion flux is determined by the sediment erodibility, whereas the deposition flux is determined by the suspended sediment concentration
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, net erosion of the Yangtze Delta can be expected under sediment starvation, given the erodible seabed. Longshore currents play an important role in residual sediment transport. The suspended sediment concentrations in the Yangtze Estuary and adjacent coastal waters has significantly reduced in response to the decrease in riverine sediment discharge
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>, which would decrease the deposition flux and may result in net erosion through or within the subaqueous delta. In fact, a few of the most recent studies support this finding
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. Of course, the morphological response to a decline in the riverine sediment discharge may spatially vary, and accretion may continue somewhere in the large subaqueous delta
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. Over the next several decades, the sediment discharge from the Yangtze River will further decrease as many new dams are constructed in the Yangtze basin
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>, and continued delta erosion can be expected, particularly in the subaqueous delta front, where longshore currents develop. The CHIRP subbottom seismic profiles and vertical distribution of grain size (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>) suggest that 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub> is low and the strata are most likely erodible for the uppermost 10-20 m of the subaqueous delta deposit. The erosion rate of the Yangtze subaqueous delta was 3–7 cm/yr over the past one to two decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. Assuming that the delta experiences a similar erosion rate under decreased river sediment supply, increased coastal hydrodynamics and a slight downward increase in 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub>, the erosion of the uppermost 10–20 m sediments will likely continue for the next decades of this century or even a few centuries.
</p>
