<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Presumably, the erodibility and morphological trends of the world’s deltas under river damming can differ greatly because the major influencing factors, namely the delta sediment properties, the local hydrodynamics for sediment resuspension, and the presence of longshore currents for the residual transport of sediment, can greatly change. The Yangtze Delta can likely be described as having a low 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cr</italic>
 </sub>, high 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cw</italic>
 </sub> and relatively strong longshore currents. Prior to river damming, the Yangtze Delta experienced rapid accretion due to the abundant fine-grained sediment supply
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>. In other words, the uppermost several metres of sediment layers were not very compacted. The Yangtze Delta is under the impact of meso-macro tides and is exposed to the sizeable East China Sea, which suggests a high 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cw</italic>
 </sub>. The monsoon-driven longshore currents off the Yangtze River mouth are relatively strong, with residual flow velocities that reach approximately 30 cm/s
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. In comparison, the Mississippi and Nile deltas are under the impact of micro tides
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>. However, perhaps many of the deltas would experience erosion under dam-generated sediment starvation, although deltas differ in terms of their erodibility. For example, the Mississippi subaqueous delta experienced severe erosion during storms
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. Long-term coastal recession that was associated with river damming and wave-induced longshore currents was found in the Nile delta
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
