<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">We tested the hypothesis that wild dogs nocturnal activity and ranging distance were greater following hot days by comparing activity and distances traveled with dry bulb daily maximum air temperature (the highest temperature (in  °C) within a 24-h period). In models of nocturnal activity and distance traveled, maximum daily temperature referred to the preceding period of daylight. As heat stress is also effected by capacity for evaporative cooling, we also included total daily rainfall (mm) as an independent variable. Temperature and rainfall were measured at Mpala Research Centre (37°2′E, 0°6′N), within the study area (Caylor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2016</xref>). We tested the hypothesis that wild dogs were more active and traveled further on moonlit nights by comparing activity and distances traveled with levels of moonlight, which were estimated (from data at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.usno.navy.mil/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.usno.navy.mil/</ext-link>) as the number of hours the moon was in the sky between sunset and sunrise (0–12 h), multiplied by the proportion of the full moon that was illuminated (0–1) to give a combined moonlight variable measured in full-moon hours (0–12; Online Resource 5). For example, a moonlight value of 12 would indicate a full moon for 12 h between sunset and sunrise. The moonlight variable did not account for cloud cover as these data were not available; however, we would expect cloud cover to be correlated with rainfall. We tested the hypothesis that wild dogs were more active and traveled further during the denning period by comparing activity and distances traveled with reproductive status, was represented as denning/not denning. As behavior during he denning period is impacted by days since occupying a particular den site and pup age (in days) (Woodroffe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2017</xref>), these were included as independent variables in models of the denning period (Online Resource 4).
</p>
