<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32273-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for conservation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Globally, bird response to edge was either species‐ or guild‐specific but our results provided evidence that forest edges in fragmented landscapes can be important habitats for generalist forest birds as well as for some specialist edge and interior forest species (Imbeau et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0038">2003</a>). However, further research is required to investigate whether higher bird densities (corresponding to individual birds singing) at edges are also paralleled by higher fitness parameters (breeding success, survival) inducing spatial variation in population dynamics. For example, higher nest predation rates at edges could result in lower breeding success for songbirds, as already shown in other studies (Flaspohler et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0028">2001</a>). Our results confirmed that forest edges are valuable for conserving and even enhancing biodiversity in managed, fragmented landscapes, by increasing local habitat heterogeneity and mitigating the effects of landscape homogenization linked to modern forestry practices (Dolman et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0022">2007</a>). Combined with negative factors in African wintering areas for migratory birds, changes in temperate forest structure and composition are thought to be responsible for the decline in common woodland birds in Europe (Gregory et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0032">2007</a>; Vickery et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0061">2014</a>). Moreover, forest edges are not only important habitats for breeding birds but they are also extensively used by migratory passerine birds during stopovers (Keller et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0042">2009</a>). Refuelling in high‐quality stopover stations is critical for migratory birds, as low body condition during this phase of the annual cycle can increase mortality (Rodewald and Brittingham 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0055">2004</a>). Higher avian predation rates on invertebrates have been actually recorded experimentally at forest edges in fragmented landscapes, suggesting that prey availability and accessibility may be much higher at edges compared to forest interiors (González‐Gómez et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0031">2006</a>; Barbaro et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0007">2012</a>; Bereczki et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0010">2015</a>). The loss of favorable stopover sites linked to current land‐use changes in European landscapes has been proposed as one of the factors related to the long‐term population decline in Afro‐Palearctic migrant birds (Sanderson et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0058">2006</a>; Gregory et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0032">2007</a>; Vickery et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0061">2014</a>), pointing out the conservation value of forest edge habitats for stopover insectivore migrants. A better integration between forestry practices and optimal management of forest edges is thus needed, including complex understorey structures at forest edges, a measure potentially highly beneficial to a large range of forest bird species but also to various insect taxa such as butterflies (van Halder et al. 
  <a rid="ece32273-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32273-bib-0033">2011</a>). Finally, our results also provide evidence that seminatural open habitats are important habitats for some specialist species with high conservation value in our study sites. Because some of these open habitat species exhibited negative responses to forest edges, landscape planning should aim at increasing the area of open patches in forested landscapes. This may provide both habitat for the persistence of these species and corridors enhancing dispersal toward extensive intact open habitats, particularly in continuous forest plantations.
 </p>
</sec>
