<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of climate changes on populations of birds has recently been under extensive study (Mitrus et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2005</a>; Potti 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2009</a>; Wesołowski and Cholewa 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2009</a>; Goodenough et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2011</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2015</a>; Chmielewski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>; Whitehouse et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2013</a>). It has been shown that many avian species in Europe breed earlier as a result of higher temperatures caused by global climate changes (Both and Visser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2005</a>; Wesołowski and Cholewa 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2009</a>; Bauer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2010</a>; Matthysen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2010</a>; Fletcher et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>; Bartošová et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2014</a>). It has also been suggested that climate change not only means higher temperatures but also more frequent extreme weather events (Tebaldi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2007</a>; Coumou and Rahmstorf 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2012</a>; McCarthy et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2012</a>; Zhang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2012</a>; Tang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2013</a>; Richter 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2015</a>; Feser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2015</a>). Extreme weather events are likely to disturb life history strategies of some species and make it more difficult for organisms to adapt to local environments (Visser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2008</a>; Chamberlain and Pearce-Higgins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2013</a>; Tobolka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2015</a>; Indykiewicz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2015</a>). On the other hand, it was suggested that the recent extreme weather events can be treated as a natural experiment that may elucidate the mechanisms by which birds adjust their phenology to fluctuating environments (Wesołowski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2016</a>). The question is whether current changes in the timing of breeding can be attributed to evolutionary changes in response to the documented selection pressures, or whether they result from individual plasticity—the capacity of an individual to fit its phenology to environmental conditions (Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2008</a>; Piersma and Gils 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2011</a>; Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2014</a>). If phenotypic plasticity plays a major role in adjusting to unpredictable weather conditions in spring, examining the limits of plasticity may be an important goal for future research (Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2008</a>; Piersma and Gils 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2011</a>; Stamps 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2015</a>; Wesołowski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maximizing the number of broods raised during a single breeding season could be a good reproductive strategy if it does not cause a decrease in the rates of survival of parents or produced young (Williams 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1966</a>; Stearns 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">1992</a>). The Great Tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) is an optionally double-brooded species—only some pairs produce a second clutch after successfully fledging young from the first brood (Gosler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1993</a>). High variation in the frequency of second broods between breeding seasons is commonly observed in this species (Lack 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1958</a>; Mägi and Mänd 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2004</a>). Verboven and Verhulst (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">1996</a>) showed that the timing of breeding is the most crucial factor influencing the decision to have or not to have a second brood in the current breeding season.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature has a major influence on the optimal laying date of insectivorous passerines. It affects the timing of peaks in spring caterpillar abundance (Perrins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">1991</a>; Thorley and Lord 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2015</a>). In 2013, low spring temperatures caused birds to lay unusually late (Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2014</a>), and it was followed by the earliest breeding season on record in 2014 (temperature characteristics of that period showed that those 2 years were the most extreme in 40 years; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Warmth sums (sum of the daily maximum temperatures in the period of 15 March–15 April) by year for the period of 1975–2014 (the most extreme 2013, 90.2 °C, and 2014, 425 °C, were marked as 
     <span class="italic">squares</span>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="484_2016_1152_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we report on responses of Great Tits and Blue Tits (
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>) to extreme spring temperature variation between 2013 and 2014. The data were gathered in two different habitats (an urban parkland and a deciduous forest), in Łódź (central Poland), within an ongoing long-term study into breeding biology of hole-nesting birds occupying nestboxes (Banbura et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2013</a>; Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2015</a>). We predict that laying dates should depend on ambient temperature in both tit species and that an early breeding season should induce Great Tits to have more second clutches (as early laying females tend to have more second clutches) and vice versa.
 </p>
</sec>
