<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was conducted in 2013 and 2014 as part of a long-term research project (started in 1999; Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2015</a>), concerning the breeding biology of secondary hole-nesting birds occupying nestboxes near Łódź, central Poland (51° 47′ N, 19° 28′ E). The study sites are located in two floristically and structurally contrasting habitats, an urban parkland (51° 45′ N, 19° 24′ E) and a deciduous forest (51° 50′ N, 19° 29′ E), 10 km apart. The urban parkland area (80 ha) consists of the zoological garden (16 ha) and the botanical garden (64 ha). This area is one of the biggest recreation and entertainment areas in Łódź (Glądalski et at. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2016a</a>). It has a highly fragmented tree cover, formed artificially with large areas of tree-free spaces. The vegetation mainly consists of hornbeam 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus betulus</span>, pedunculate oak 
  <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span>, Scots pine 
  <span class="italic">Pinus silvestris</span>, birches 
  <span class="italic">Betula</span> sp., poplars 
  <span class="italic">Populus</span> sp., willows 
  <span class="italic">Salix</span> sp., limes 
  <span class="italic">Tilia</span> sp., maples 
  <span class="italic">Acer</span> sp., and many exotic tree species. The forest study site (130 ha) is situated in the Łagiewniki forest—a rich deciduous forest, located north of Łódź. Large parts of the forest come directly from the ancient woodland typical for this region of central Europe. Oaks (
  <span class="italic">Q. robur</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Q. petraea</span>) are the dominant tree species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study sites were supplied with standard wooden nestboxes (Lambrechts et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2010</a>) with a removable front wall and with internal dimensions of 11.5 (depth) × 11 (width) × 30 (height) cm and a 3-cm-diameter entrance located 20 cm from the bottom of the nestbox (ca. 200 nestboxes were set in the parkland and ca. 300 nestboxes were set in the forest). Second clutches are clutches produced by females that had a successful first clutch (with at least one fledged young) in the same year. A total of 227 first clutches and 42-s clutches of the Great Tit were studied in 2013 and 2014. A total of 80 first clutches of the Blue Tit were studied in 2013 and 2014 (there were no second clutches in Blue Tits).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The local temperatures for Łódź were obtained from TuTiempo.net database (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.tutiempo.net/climate/ws-124650.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://en.tutiempo.net/climate/ws-124650.html</span>). As an indicator of thermal conditions for tits, we used a pre-laying-early-laying warmth sums of the daily maximum temperatures between 15 March and 15 April each year (Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2014</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2015</a>; Wawrzyniak et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2015</a>). The mean laying dates are described as days from 1 March.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used ANOVA to compare mean laying dates between years and study areas. Fisher’s exact test was used to test for differences in the proportion of second clutches between extreme years in the parkland and in the forest. Graphical and statistical analyses were performed using STATISTICA 10 (StatSoft Inc. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2011</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
