<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Tropical forests represent the world's most biodiverse ecosystems, as well as providing its largest stores of living carbon and contributing more to biomass productivity than any other biome on the planet. Changes here can therefore have global consequences, potentially nowhere more so than in Amazonia where between 6,000 and 16,000 tree species exist (Cardoso et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Ter Steege et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and as much as 100 Pg of carbon is stored in biomass (Feldpausch et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). While the physical, chemical, and biological environment have all been changing over recent decades, it is the changes in climate—both documented and projected—which are widely expected to cause some of the most profound changes in forest communities and ecosystem processes (Esquivel‐Muelbert, Baker, et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Thomas et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). For example, higher temperatures and intensifying drought may threaten larger trees due to hydraulic failure (McDowell &amp; Allen, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Rowland et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), which could eventually compromise forest biomass and productivity. In Amazonia, because forest diversity is concentrated in the wetter, least seasonal forests (Francis &amp; Currie, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Gentry, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1988</xref>), a persistent lengthening of the dry season might threaten a large portion of tropical biodiversity. Here we aim to better understand how Amazonian trees have responded to the last 30 years of environmental change, by analysing floristic records from long‐term tree monitoring in the Neotropics to assess the potential compositional changes to date.
</p>
