<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34812-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within‐year variations in body mass</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All three species showed similar seasonal trends in body mass. Newly fledged juveniles were lighter than adults and, although this difference decreased rapidly until August, it persisted throughout the year in all species: mean 0.21 g (1.92% of mean adult body mass) in blue tits, 0.03 g (0.33% of mean adult body mass) in coal tits, and 0.35 g (1.87% of mean adult body mass) in great tits. All of these values were significantly different from zero (
  <span class="italic">t</span> tests, blue tits: 
  <span class="italic">t </span>= −93.86, 
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 300,420; coal tits: 
  <span class="italic">t </span>= −8.77, 
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 60,796; great tits: 
  <span class="italic">t </span>= −76.48, 
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 209,730; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 2.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">−16</span> for all species). After August, both age classes showed similar seasonal trends in body mass, with mass oscillating predictably with three separate peaks in April/May, August, and December in all species (Figures 
  <a rid="ece34812-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34812-fig-0001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34812-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34812-fig-0002">2</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34812-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34812-fig-0003">3</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34812-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34812-fig-0004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34812-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34812-fig-0005">5</a>a–c).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34812-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Seasonal variations in mean population body masses for adult (orange lines) and juvenile (blue lines) tits (monthly means and standard error bars). (a) Blue tits; (b) coal tits; (c) great tits. More than 12 months are included for (a) and (c) because the juvenile age class begins with individuals recorded as age 3 and then comprises individuals recorded as age 5 after December. There were fewer records for coal tits than for the other investigated species, and there were thus insufficient data for juveniles in May and June to allow those months to be plotted. Standard error bars are shown but are extremely small due to the large sample sizes</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-1202-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34812-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Seasonal variation in mean (and standard error) population body masses of male (orange line) and female (blue line) adult great tits. Females exhibited a clear peak in body mass in April and May that was not found in males</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-9-1202-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34812-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Linear regression coefficients of body mass in relation to year for all months, species and age classes. Coefficients that are significantly different from zero are presented as circles; coefficients that are not significantly different from zero are presented as triangles. Parabolic curves are fitted to each species–age class combination. “Long‐term rate of change” refers to the rate of change between the same month in one year and the next and does not reflect within‐year rate of change, as might be observed from one month to the next</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-9-1202-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34812-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Linear regression of mean population body mass against year of capture for juvenile blue tits captured between 1967 and early 2017. The regression coefficient (−0.0146) was significantly different from 0 (
    <span class="italic">t </span>= −10.27, 
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-9-1202-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34812-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Linear regression coefficients of wing length in relation to year for all months, species, and age classes. Coefficients are significantly lower than zero for all species and both age classes in at least 7 months of the year and are not significantly higher than zero for any species or age class in any month. Coefficients significantly different from zero are presented as circles; coefficients not significantly different from zero are presented as triangles. “Long‐term rate of change” refers to the rate of change between the same month in one year and the next and does not reflect within‐year rate of change, as might be observed from one month to the next</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="ECE3-9-1202-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When great tits were separated by sex, the April/May peak only occurred in females, while the August and December peaks occurred in both sexes (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34812-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34812-fig-0002">2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
