<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The idea of the NEA cod moving into a more northern distribution area is not supported by the findings of this study. On the contrary, the centres of gravity of the cod biomass distribution are surprisingly stable throughout the simulation period. While the distribution area in north, south and west is largely constrained by the ocean bathymetry which is unaffected by climate change, a further easterly distribution is constrained by temperatures which still are below the levels preferred by cod (Eide 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2014</a>). It is reasonable to expect this to be the case also for other benthic species in the Barents Sea, while pelagic species are less constrained in their spatial distributions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="italic">SinMod</span> simulation based on the A1B climate scenario suggests a significant environmental shift in the mid 2030ies, causing a corresponding increase in the environmental carrying capacity for the NEA cod stock of about 10 %. The shift also leads to a significant increase in the cod stock biomass, most visible at medium exploitation rates and low smartness levels. In open access, the increased carrying capacity level is not fully utilised due to higher fishing effort and extended seasons. Also at low exploitation levels, the environmental effect is less visible since the cod stock already has reached a high stock level.
 </p>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous conclusions suggesting that fisheries management decisions to have a greater impact on the development of fisheries than climate change (Eide 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2007</a>) seem to hold also after including the spatial dimension. Technological and other changes captured with the smartness parameter also have great importance and both management regimes and smartness levels clearly affect profits and fleet diversities. Given sound combinations of management and smartness levels, the climate change impacts on the NEA cod fishery could, however, significantly enhance the economic utilisation of this natural resource.
 </p>
</sec>
