<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">DNA extraction and PCR setup were performed in a dedicated ancient DNA laboratory at Landcare Research, Lincoln, New Zealand. DNA was extracted from subsamples (3.45–6.03 g, mean = 5.19 g) of each midden using the MoBio PowerMax kit. DNA extractions were performed in four batches, each consisting of seven samples and one negative extraction control. A variable length region (40–120 bp within eukaryotes) of the 18S rRNA gene was amplified using the primers Nem18SF and Nem18SR
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup> with linker sequences at the 5′ end. A detailed assessment of the taxonomic biases of these primers has yet to be performed, but alignment of the primers with 18S sequences from plant pathogens (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>) and parasitic eukaryotes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup> show that any mismatches are concentrated at the 5′ ends. Moreover, sequencing results that we have obtained using these primers indicate that they are highly specific to eukaryotes and amplify DNA from a broad range of eukaryote taxa. The short amplicon length makes them ideal for ancient DNA, and they target a region that is variable enough to provide useful taxonomic resolution. PCR reactions (12.5 μL) contained 1 μg/mL BSA, 1x PCR buffer, 2 mM MgSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, 40 μM dNTPs, 0.4 μM each primer, 1U Platinum HiFi Taq and 1 μL DNA extract. Cycling conditions were an initial denaturation at 94 °C for 3 min, followed by 55 cycles of 94 °C for 30 sec, 55 °C for 30 sec, 68 °C for 45 sec and a final elongation at 68 °C for 10 min. Each PCR was repeated in triplicate and PCR batches included negative controls. Products were visialised on 3.5% agarose gels. None of the extraction or PCR negative controls produced visible bands of amplified product on agarose gels. Following this, 1 μL of each amplicon library was dual indexed using 0.75 μL of 2 μM indexed adapters (P5/P7) in 20 μL reactions using iTaq DNA polymerase and following the manufacturers reaction mix. Cycling conditions were 94 °C for 2 min, followed by 7 cycles of 94 °C for 20 sec, 55 °C for 10 sec, 72 °C for 30 sec and a final elongation at 72 °C for 10 min. Indexed libraries were quantified using a Qubit 2.0. Equal amounts were pooled and purified using a Pippen Prep with a size-selection window of 220–260 bp. After final quantification and pooling, sequencing was performed using 2 × 150 bp kit on an Illumina MiSeq (Macrogen, South Korea).
</p>
