<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On the surface, it may seem that global climate change has favorable effects on plants and animals. For plants, global climate change appears beneficial as it allows for the earlier onset of spring, prolonged growing season, as well as increased concentrations of atmospheric carbon dioxide, which is necessary for plant photosynthesis (Myneni, Keeling, Tucker, Asrar, &amp; Nemani, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Indeed, satellite data from a series of NOAA meteorological satellites have demonstrated, in Northern latitudes, increased plant growth during the summer and elevated plant respiration during the winter, which corresponded to rising temperatures and the lengthening of the active growing season (Myneni et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Tree ring analyses in the Northern hemisphere have demonstrated increased tree growth during the past century (Briffa et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>; Jacoby, D'Arrigo, &amp; Davaajamts, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). Additionally, rising temperatures have allowed for the increased distribution and survival of some plant species; numerous studies have demonstrated an upward tree line migration and increased population growth at higher elevations and latitudes (Kullman, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Lloyd, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Mazepa, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Meshinev, Apostolova, &amp; Koleva, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0078" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Smith, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>; Sturm, Racine, &amp; Tape, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0123" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Walther et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0134" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). For example, Smith (
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>) detailed the expansion of vascular plants, 
 <italic>Colobanthus quitensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Deschampsia antarctica</italic>, within Antarctica from 1960 until 1990. In Galindez Island, numbers of 
 <italic>D. antarctica</italic> increased from 500 plants in 1964 to over 12,000 plants in 1990; similar effects were observed for 
 <italic>C. quitensis</italic>. This expansion held true across multiple locations within Antarctica.
</p>
