<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The gas exchange between the atmosphere and plants is mainly regulated by stomata. But structure and physiology of stomata are also influenced by gasses (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">García-Mata and Lamattina, 2013</xref>). Elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> regulate stomatal density and conductance. Moreover, there is increasing evidence that this response is modified by interaction of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with other environmental factors (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yan et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al. (2015)</xref> reported that 800 μmol.mol
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> increases the NO concentration in 
 <italic class="italic">A. thaliana</italic> guard cells, inducing stomatal closure. Both NR and NO synthase (NOS)-like activities are necessary for CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-induced NO accumulation. Comprehensive pharmacological and genetic results obtained in Arabidopsis by 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chater et al. (2015)</xref>, show that when CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration is around 700–1000 ppm, stomatal density and closure are reduced. They also illustrate that those elements necessary for this process are: activation of both ABA biosynthesis genes and the PYR/RCAR ABA receptor, and ROS increase. However, 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shi et al. (2015)</xref> provide genetic and pharmacological evidence that high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration induces stomatal closure by an ABA-independent mechanism in tomato. They show that 800 μmol.mol
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> increase the expression of the protein kinase OPEN STOMATA 1 (OST1), NOX, and nitrate reductase (NR) genes. They also show that the sequential production of NOX-dependent H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and NR-produced NO are mainly dependent of OST1, and are involved in the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-induced stomatal closure.
</p>
