<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over the past two decades, the increasing concentration of pharmaceuticals and other personal care compounds (PPCP), together with their ubiquity in the aquatic environment and evidence of adverse biological effects linked to exposure, has led to their classification as emerging pollutants of priority concern [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Pharmaceutical compounds are designed to target specific metabolic and molecular pathways in both humans and animals (medical and veterinary use), which are generally evolutionary conserved [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], thus they may be highly potent pollutants by eliciting biological effects at very low-concentrations. Personal care products are used for improvement of the quality of life and include products such as cosmetics, UV blocker agents (sunscreens) or fragrances [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. PPCP residues are continuously released into the aquatic environment, leading to chronic exposure even for relatively degradable compounds, thus are generally regarded as persistent or pseudo-persistent pollutants [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Arnold et al. [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] coined the term “Medicating the Environment” referencing the continuous released of PPCP into surface waters with almost no legal restrictions for discharge. The major source of PPCP residues input into the aquatic environment is inadequately treated wastewater effluents. However, other dispersal pathways include manufacturing facilities, waste disposal, aquaculture, and animal husbandry and horticulture along rivers and in coastal areas [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. PPCP occurrence in the marine environment was first presumed to be negligible due to likely high dilution processes. However, recent works have indubitably demonstrated the pervasive nature of these compounds, with significant concentrations of PPCP residues in estuarine and marine areas (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]), as well as in marine macroalgae, bivalves, and fish [
 <xref rid="B59-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Geographically, available data on marine environments refers mostly to Europe, North America, and China, with incipient or absent information of Africa, Latin America or the Caribbean [
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. With global consumption and access to PPCP rising, it will inevitably lead to higher ambient concentrations and greater potential for bioaccumulation and hazardous effects in marine fauna.
</p>
