<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dominantly Ice Free Conditions in the Earliest Pliocene Nordic Seas</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our reconstructions reveal sea ice-free conditions and relatively high marine productivity in the Iceland Sea between 5.0 and 4.6 Ma, evidenced by the absence of IP
  <sub>25</sub> and relatively high concentrations of the open water biomarker brassicasterol (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2B</a>). Dinoflagellate cyst concentrations are high (~3,000 to ~12,000 cysts/g; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2A</a>), and the assemblage has clear Atlantic water characteristics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, suggesting a Nordic Seas circulation different from today
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. Ice-free conditions are supported by reconstructed summer SSTs ~5 °C higher than modern (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2D</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> and high phytoplankton productivity related to the presence of Atlantic water masses in the Iceland Sea.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Biomarker and sedimentological data from the Iceland Sea and Yermak Plateau. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Dinoflagellate cyst concentrations from ODP Site 907 from this study (white circles) and ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
     </span> (gray circles). (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) IP
     <sub>25</sub> concentrations (blue circles) and brassicasterol concentrations (green circles) from ODP Site 907. (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) IP
     <sub>25</sub> concentrations (blue circles) and brassicasterol concentrations (green circles) from ODP Hole 910C
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
     </span>. Blue squares indicate IP
     <sub>25</sub> concentrations and green squares indicate brassicasterol concentrations from ODP Hole 911A (this study). (
     <span class="bold">D</span>) High-resolution alkenone-based SST reconstruction from ODP sites 907
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
     </span>, 642
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span> and 982
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
     </span>. Modern summer SSTs for each location is from the World Ocean Atlas 2013 (ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
     </span>). (
     <span class="bold">E</span>) IRD record from ODP Site 907 from ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
     </span>, placed on the ATNTS2012 timescale. (
     <span class="bold">F</span>) IRD record from ODP Hole 911A ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
     </span>. Vertical dotted lines indicate time slices discussed in the text and used in the reconstructions in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_37047_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e571" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The low-resolution Yermak Plateau biomarker record suggests occasional sea ice edge conditions at 4.9 and 4.6 Ma (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1B</a>). High IP
  <sub>25</sub> and low brassicasterol concentrations indicate seasonal sea ice occurrence at ODP Hole 911A (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2D</a>), while the absence of IP
  <sub>25</sub> and high brassicasterol concentrations at the neighboring ODP Hole 910C indicate sea ice-free conditions and enhanced primary productivity at this time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Yet, a clear, uniform interpretation of the low-resolution biomarker data from these sites, located very close to each other, is difficult to make. The difference in biomarker signature at the two sites could be consistent with a highly variable sea ice margin, comparable to modern conditions in this region (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. High brassicasterol concentrations at ODP Hole 910C suggests substantial primary productivity, which is often elevated close to marginal ice zones
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. However, SSTs remain relatively high and indicate an Atlantic rather than polar water influence
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Alternatively, as seasonal sea ice was already present in the Arctic Ocean since the Late Miocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, sea ice could have also been exported from the Arctic Ocean towards the Yermak Plateau until it encountered the warmer Atlantic waters of the West Spitsbergen Current. With a sub-aerially exposed Barents Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>, the heat advection through the West Spitsbergen Current towards the Yermak Plateau is increased
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3A</a>), thereby inhibiting a long-term sea ice cover but allowing occasional local sea ice formation or sea ice export from the Arctic. It is, however, very likely that the different paleoceanographic interpretations for ODP holes 910C and 911A are best explained by the different ages of the investigated samples at both sites and that sea ice appeared in the region only sporadically.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic illustration of sea ice extent in the Arctic Ocean and Iceland Sea during the Pliocene. Warm water surface currents (red): NwAC = Norwegian Atlantic Current, WSC = West Spitsbergen Current. Cool water surface currents (blue): BG = Beaufort gyre, EGC = East Greenland Current, EIC = East Icelandic Current. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Sea ice (white shaded area) was most likely restricted to the central Arctic Ocean between 5.0 and ~4.6 Ma (e.g. ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
     </span>), while Atlantic waters extended into the Iceland Sea (Site 907). (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Seasonal sea ice or sea ice transported with the EGC first appear in the Iceland Sea around 4.5 Ma. The Yermak Plateau was sea ice free
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
     </span>, although occasional sea ice may have occurred. (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) Sea ice expanded across the Arctic Ocean
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
     </span> and established a seasonal/extended sea ice cover on the Yermak Plateau and an extended sea ice cover or possibly a sea ice edge (solid line at edge of white shaded area) in the Iceland Sea. This occurred contemporaneous with increased northward heat transport in the eastern North Atlantic and Norwegian Sea. The northward heat transport also brought moisture that was transported via the westerlies (yellow arrows) towards Eurasia where increased freshwater outflow through the Eurasian rivers (light blue arrows) led to freshening of the Arctic Ocean, which favors sea ice formation. Maps were generated with Ocean Data View
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_37047_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e665" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
