<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First Early Pliocene Sea Ice in the Iceland Sea</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea ice emerged in the Iceland Sea around 4.5 Ma as evidenced by the first occurrence of IP
  <sub>25</sub> at ODP Site 907. Together with elevated brassicasterol concentrations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2B</a>), the IP
  <sub>25</sub> data suggest sea ice edge conditions (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1A</a>), with generally high productivity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Dinoflagellate cyst concentrations are still relatively high for an open ocean site, although lower compared to the preceding interval (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2A</a>). Several dinoflagellate cyst species disappeared at this site around 4.5 Ma
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, which has been related to the emergence of a modern-like EGC
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> and the replacement of Atlantic water with cooler, fresher arctic-sourced water. When sea ice occurred at 4.5 Ma, reconstructed summer SSTs of ~10 °C remained well above modern values (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2D</a>), suggesting either a strong seasonal contrast between warm summers and winters with sea ice, or that transported sea ice melted in the Iceland Sea. While our data unequivocally demonstrates sea ice presence in the Iceland Sea at 4.5 Ma, we cannot conclude whether sea ice formed locally in the Iceland Sea, was exported from the Arctic to the Iceland Sea with the EGC or was a combination of both. In ODP Hole 910C, a significant drop in brassicasterol concentrations (to values below 2 ng/g sediment) and the absence of IP
  <sub>25</sub> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2C</a>) could be indicative for a permanent sea ice cover at 4.5 Ma (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1B</a>), but the Yermak Plateau most likely still remained sea ice free and dominated by Atlantic water
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between 4.4 and 4.1 Ma, samples for biomarker analyses were not available at ODP Site 907 due to a heavily sampled sediment core. However, earlier studies show a decrease in summer SSTs from 10 to 6 °C
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> around 4.4–4.3 Ma and a fragmentary dinoflagellate cyst record with low concentrations to even barren samples
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2A,D</a>). This suggests a strengthened influence of cool, Arctic waters via the EGC in the Iceland Sea about 100–200 ka later than the first sea ice occurrence at 4.5 Ma. Although this lag is not fully understood, it may be reflecting a gradually intensifying EGC that leads to long-term, cool conditions in the Iceland Sea. The Yermak Plateau generally remained sea ice free
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, but the occurrence of IP
  <sub>25</sub> in a single sample (~4.4 Ma) in ODP Hole 911A reflects that conditions were sporadically suitable for sea ice to be present (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2C</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, the sea ice reconstructions for the Iceland Sea and the Yermak Plateau around 4.5 Ma correspond favorably to the reorganization of Nordic Seas surface circulation. This paleoceanographic change most likely occurred as a consequence of changed flow direction through the Bering Strait
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> allowing cool and low salinity Pacific water to enter the Arctic Ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. While today, Arctic–Atlantic surface water exchange occurs through both the Fram Strait and the CAA
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, the latter was closed during the Early Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Such setting favors the role of the EGC as the only pathway for cool, fresher water and possibly also as sea ice exporter from the Arctic already in the Early Pliocene (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3B</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
