<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Influence of Sea Ice Expansion on Pliocene Arctic Climate</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the relatively high Early Pliocene atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations of 380–400 ppm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, the changes in North Atlantic and Arctic paleoceanography caused sea ice to occur as far south as the Iceland Sea at 4.5 Ma. This development was likely controlled by the emergence of a modern-like EGC, which was established as a consequence of a surface water flow reversal across the Bering Strait
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The changed paleoceanography was crucial to allow the import of fresher, cooler Arctic water and sea ice into the Iceland Sea. Whether sea ice was exported directly from the Arctic, or the fresher, cooler water favored local sea ice formation in the Iceland Sea yet remains ambiguous. Nevertheless, the effects of a changed EGC and appearance of sea ice along its pathway are also recognized from the dinoflagellate cyst turnover in the Iceland Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> and the onset of biosiliceous sedimentation in the Labrador Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> at 4.5 Ma. Around that time, small IRD amounts are recorded at ODP Site 907, indicating that Greenland did have ice caps or small ice sheets that could produce icebergs and ice rafted detritus (IRD)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>, albeit in volumes considerably lower than in the Late Pliocene and Quaternary. Tectonic uplift made elevated plateaus available in Greenland during the Early Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> where glaciers and ice caps could nucleate and eventually expand into a large, IRD producing ice sheet. Such large ice sheet started to deliver considerable IRD into the North Atlantic during the Late Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, when the zonal gradient in the Nordic Seas was already established. In fact, the cooler water and more substantial sea ice presence in the Iceland Sea after 4.0 Ma and in the Late Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, may have contributed to the gradual expansion of continental ice in Greenland. A more substantial and long-term sea ice presence along the East Greenland coast acts to thermally isolate Greenland from relatively warmer Atlantic waters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> and reduces heat advection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, as well as providing a sea ice-albedo feedback and inhibiting ocean–atmosphere heat exchange. These combined effects, together with the tectonic uplift of the circum-Arctic land masses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span> all provide positive feedbacks for expansion of the Greenland Ice Seet (GIS).
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the modern context of increasing atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations and rapidly declining Arctic sea ice, our study provides fundamental insights into consequences of a (seasonally) sea ice-free Arctic by demonstrating that limited sea ice presence in the Arctic Ocean and Iceland Sea together with a high Early Pliocene atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration (380–400 ppm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>) correspond to a strongly reduced GIS. The occasional presence of sea ice in the Early Pliocene Iceland Sea and Yermak Plateau was insufficient to provide an insolating buffer between the warm surface waters in the Nordic Seas and the GIS before ~4.0 Ma. Together with the high atmospheric Pliocene greenhouse gas concentrations, this setting likely inhibited major glaciation in Greenland. It is only when a more stable ice edge developed along the coast of East Greenland in the Late Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> and CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations gradually decreased
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> that the GIS could expand to reach the coast line
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. As such, sea ice along the east Greenland coast acts as a positive feedback for sustaining and expanding the GIS. Our data do not allow disentangling the relative effects of Arctic sea ice extent and greenhouse gas concentrations on the GIS, which should be addressed in future modeling studies.
 </p>
</sec>
