<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.6.1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic and hydrological variation</div>
 <p id="p0100" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is widely accepted that local climate and weather variation, climate change, eutrophication, and hydrological variations are key drivers of CyanoHABs (
  <a rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib72">Paul, 2008</a>). ITCZ and El Ńino Southern Oscillation (ENSO) cause greater than average rainfall in Tanzania in the short rainfall season (October to December) while the cold phase (LA Ńina) causes a dry condition than the average and these can work synergistically (
  <a rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib26">GLOWSFIU, 2014b</a> and 
  <a rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib37">Kijazi and Reason, 2009</a>). A study by 
  <a rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib66">Paavola (2008)</a> on drought in Morogoro region enumerated all the drought years which indicates that Morogoro is a drought-prone area. Mean climatic conditions, for example, temperatures (
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">New et al., 2006</a>) of Morogoro agrees with a threshold of more than 20–35 °C air temperature (
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">Elliott, 2012</a> and 
  <a rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib88">Sinha et al., 2012</a>) which is the optimal temperature for CyanoHAB formations. However, a study by 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Baig et al. (2017)</a> demonstrated a threshold of 24–28 °C (water temperature), where the highest peak of cyanobacteria was observed. Moreover, the same study noted a decline of cyanobacteria blooms and chlorophyll-a when temperatures were 30 °C. Another factor in Morogoro, drought (
  <a rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib66">Paavola, 2008</a>) can be depicted (negative values of standardized precipitation index (SPEI)) from 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a>, has the characteristics to prolong periods of surface temperatures, stabilizing water columns and increasing nutrient concentration indirectly (
  <a rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib76">Reichwaldt and Ghadouani, 2012</a>).
  <div id="fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Standardized Precipitation and Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) in Morogoro (Data point generated from “
     <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">eartH2Observe Water Cycle Integrator</a>,” available on 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wci.earth2observe.eu/" id="intref0130" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wci.earth2observe.eu/</span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0030" class="alt-text">Fig. 5</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
