<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Factors influencing the proliferation of harmful algal blooms</div>
 <p id="p0045" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is no single factor that can describe the formation of cyanobacteria bloom (
  <a rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib91">Te and Gin, 2011</a>) but rather a complex set of interactions (
  <a rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>) of several environmental factors (
  <a rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib96">Wells et al., 2015</a>) and optimal conditions should be met (
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">Berger and Gobler, 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Descy and Sarmento, 2008</a>). Factors such as light intensity and duration, temperature, nutrient availability, episodic hydrological events (droughts and floods events), bio-physiological and chemical characteristics and ecosystem structure are responsible for bloom formation (
  <a rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib55">Moore et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib72">Paul, 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib76">Reichwaldt and Ghadouani, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib49">Merel et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib32">Hazen and Sawyer, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Ndlela et al., 2016</a>). Few have studied the impact or the mechanism that co-exist between cyanobacteria and carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) (
  <a rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib94">Visser et al., 2016</a>). Most studies suggest the use of chlorophyll-a as a proxy measure of algal blooms (C. 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">Anderson et al., 2015</a>). Other studies (
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">Elliott, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib76">Reichwaldt and Ghadouani, 2012</a>; and 
  <a rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib55">Moore et al., 2008</a>) have demonstrated the influences of major weather shifts on freshwater HABs dynamics. For example, a positive/negative correlation that exists between rainfall intensity and length of dry periods which in turn determine the occurrence of cyanobacteria blooms (
  <a rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib68">Paerl et al., 2016</a>). These studies establish how individual weather phenomena directly or indirectly influence CyanoHAB proliferation. In the same line of argument, Anderson (2014) suggest case studies especially events that mimic future climate scenarios if studied can be more informative than doing single parameters.
  <div id="fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic diagram of interactive physical, chemical and biological controls on harmful algal bloom formation and proliferation along the freshwater-to-marine continuum. Adapted with permission from “Mitigating the Expansion of Harmful Algal Blooms Across the Freshwater-to-Marine Continuum”, by 
     <a rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib70">Paerl et al. (2018)</a>. 
     <span class="italic">Environmental Sciences &amp; Technology</span>, 
     <span class="italic">52</span>, 5519–5529. 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b05950" id="intref0120" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b05950</span>. Copyright (2018) American Chemical Society.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0010" class="alt-text">Fig. 1</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0050" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some studies have also looked into single or few factors and their influences on HABs. The factors are not standing alone because sometimes they may interact; therefore multifactor analysis should be done to critically highlight at what state (say mixing and pH) favours the growth or at what level (temperature, flushing, and nutrient inputs) CyanoHABs decrease. Others for example (
  <a rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib85">Shen et al., 2012</a>), concluded a link between environmental factors and how they influence HABs dynamics is neither well documented nor explained. Although there have been efforts in the understanding of HABs such as a recent scientific consensus (
  <a rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib33">Heisler et al., 2008</a>) highlight some doubts which need to be cleared.
 </p>
 <p id="p0055" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many studies have used methanol for the extraction of cyanotoxins (
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">Codd, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Fyumagwa et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib38">Kim et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">Mbukwa et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib49">Merel et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52">Metcalf and Codd, 2014</a>). The approach was challenged by a recent study (
  <a rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib94">Visser et al., 2016</a>) which question the validity of the previous findings. This is still debatable.
 </p>
</sec>
