<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General and predicted climate changes in Tanzania</div>
 <p id="p0085" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature is the most studied climate parameter when addressing CyanoHAB dynamics. In Tanzania, evidence and projection of an increase in temperature can be deduced from models (as in 
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>) and empirical studies (
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">New et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib100">World Wide Fund For Nature, 2006</a>). To further highlight this, in Tanzania there are climate change hotspots (
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Niang et al., 2014</a>) which are Lake Tanganyika (directly linked with cyanobacteria dynamics and decrease in fish productivity) and Mountain Kilimanjaro (a good indicator of global warming). Changes in climate (for example warming) has been attributed to the occurrence of blooms (
  <a rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib72">Paul, 2008</a>). While studies on climate variability and cyanobacteria dynamics are limited (
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Ndlela et al., 2016</a>), existing ones (for example in Lake Tanganyika) indicate chlorophyll-a concentrations are constant throughout a year with the alteration of dry and wet seasons (
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">De Senerpont Domis et al., 2013</a>). Chlorophyll-a is used as a proxy for cyanobacterial biomass estimation in marine and freshwaters (
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">Dörnhöfer and Oppelt, 2016</a>). A study by 
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Niang et al. (2014)</a>, which was based on more than 90 years of observation suggests that increased stratification, nutrient fluxes and decreased productivity was due to recent increases in surface temperatures. The effects have negatively affected the catches of sardines by 30–50% (
  <a rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib16">Drakenberg et al., 2016</a>). Predicted changes in climate (
  <a rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib100">World Wide Fund For Nature, 2006</a>) in the region require measures such as finding out the influence of both temperature and rainfall has to nutrients increases in the water bodies (
  <a rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib68">Paerl et al., 2016</a>; and 
  <a rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib70">Paerl et al., 2018</a>).
  <div id="fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Projected changes in air temperatures (°C) for different climate scenarios in Tanzania (Data generated from “
     <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">KNMI Climate Explorer</a>,”).
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0015" class="alt-text">Fig. 2</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
