<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.7" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrological variations</div>
 <p id="p0105" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Mindu Dam a Man-made Dam situated in the Ngerengere River Catchment, Morogoro Urban, there has been periodic maintenance of floodgates and other infrastructure to ensure that gates do not get jammed in the event of heavy rainfall and river flows (
  <a rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib26">GLOWSFIU, 2014b</a>). The water level peaks (which is an indicator of hydrological variations) in 
  <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">Fig. 6</a> depicts some dry and wet years in Morogoro, which indicate there could be severe drought and wet years which was also reported by 
  <a rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib66">Paavola (2008)</a>. The dry and wet peaks in the (SPEI) in 
  <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a> also indicates negative values for dry and positive values for wet years which corroborates with water levels peaks variations in Mindu Dam (
  <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">Fig. 6</a>). These variations are useful in describing the formation of algal blooms as highlighted in the framework of 
  <a rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib76">Reichwaldt and Ghadouani, 2012</a> and 
  <a rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib104">Zhang et al. (2016)</a>. Lack of monitoring both climate, hydrological and other environmental variables make it impossible to study and ultimately manage CyanoHAB variations in this study area.
  <div id="fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Variations of water levels (m) and volume (m
     <span class="sup">3</span>) in Mindu Dam for a period of 1997–2013 (data from 
     <a rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib95">WAMI/RUVU, 2013</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0035" class="alt-text">Fig. 6</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0110" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is widely accepted that evapotranspiration can assist forecasting the hydrology and climate systems hence ecological dynamics (
  <a rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib102">Yang et al., 2016</a>). Land use characteristics (residential, agriculture, industrial, forest and undeveloped area) can also be a factor in determining the severity of bloom formation (
  <a rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84">Shayo et al., 2017</a>). These hydrological variations in the Morogoro Urban suggest optimal conditions for the proliferation of CyanoHABs. A study of 
  <a rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib101">Yanda and Munishi (2007)</a> on hydrological and land use/cover change analysis for the Ruvu River (Uluguru) and Sigi River (East Usambara) watersheds both in Morogoro which looked at the historical flow data confirmed sedimentation in the catchment due to land use. The same study found a match between the flows and rainfall variations, but also predominance declining flows in both the dry and wet seasons. These seasonal variations in flow are a very important predictor for the formation of cyanobacteria in the catchment.
 </p>
</sec>
