<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="p0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cyanobacteria (blue-green algae) are oxygenic photosynthetic bacteria that occur naturally in fresh, brackish, and marine waters, and terrestrial environments (
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">Codd et al., 2005b</a>). Apart from their function as primary producers (
  <a rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib56">Moorehead et al., 2011</a>), cyanobacteria are now a worldwide problem (
  <a rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib74">Pham and Utsumi, 2018</a>) because they can form massive blooms that produce a wide range of toxins (
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">Codd, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib11">Codd et al., 2005a</a>,
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">b</a>; 
  <a rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib103">Zamyadi et al., 2012</a> and 
  <a rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib90">Suzane, 2016</a>). Over many years cyanobacteria were not regarded as water-borne pathogens (
  <a rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib11">Codd et al., 2005a</a>,
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">b</a>), but recently the US Environmental Protection Agency (
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">EPA, 2014</a>) listed cyanobacteria on the Contaminant Candidate List (CCL), meaning that is an issue of public health concern. According to the 
  <a rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib99">World Health Organization (2003)</a>, 60% (worldwide) of samples from freshwater systems investigated had a mass occurrences of toxin-producing cyanobacteria.
 </p>
 <p id="p0015" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The multiple environmental and health impacts of cyanobacteria have attracted researchers from different fields (
  <a rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib80">Sanseverino et al., 2016</a>). One example is the development of models (
  <a rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib28">Guven and Howard, 2006</a>) studying occurrence, extent, and timing, while others have demonstrated the dynamics of cyanobacteria toxins in aquatic systems (
  <a rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib77">Rodgers, 2008</a>). 
  <a rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib34">Ho and Michalak (2015)</a> for example, outlined several metrics for examining cyanobacterial proliferation. They include abundance, remotely-sensed/spectral metrics, species-specific, toxicity, and qualitative metrics.
 </p>
 <p id="p0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Harmful cyanobacteria, or CyanoHABs, are now a problem of global environmental concern and efforts are being taken to prevent, predict, minimizes, and suppress their occurrences (
  <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">Gatz, 2018</a>). Triggers for CyanoHABs have been studied (
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Kubiak et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib69">Paerl and Otten, 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib76">Reichwaldt and Ghadouani, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib81">Schmidt et al., 2014</a>). These studies have demonstrated a scientific understanding of the dynamics of cyanobacteria. Despite all these efforts, geographical variation in CyanoHABs is not well explored, including the links between triggers and CyanoHAB proliferation. In the tropics, Tanzania is an example of insufficient CyanoHAB. Of the few studies consulted, the particular reviews suggest the dominance of both 
  <span class="italic">Microcystis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Cylindrospermopsis</span> species in the tropics, and their occurrence is throughout the year, unlike temperate regions in which their occurrences are confined to the warm summer months. In nearby Lake Victoria, blooms of cyanobacteria have been observed since 1980 which are associated with massive fish kills (
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Ndlela et al., 2016</a>). Some reviews recommend preventive measures to be taken to combat cyanobacteria occurrences in major lakes (
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Ndlela et al., 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0025" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate and hydrological variations are considered as important factors promoting the occurrence and dominance of CyanoHABs in the aquatic environment (
  <a rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib65">Ogashawara et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib76">Reichwaldt and Ghadouani, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib31">Havens et al., 2016</a>). Other studies (e.g. 
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Ndlela et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib96">Wells et al., 2015</a>) suggests that little is known regarding climate variability and changes in cyanobacteria dynamics in Africa. In addition there can be a conflict between the observation and experimental data. On the other hand, of the few studies, genetic characterization of cyanobacteria isolated from Africa and Europe demonstrated the variation of cyanobacteria from different geographical regions (
  <a rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib29">Haande et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib30">Harke et al., 2016</a>). A study of 
  <a rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib89">Sinoven (2009)</a> suggested that generalization of CyanoHAB dynamics should be avoided because local climate and weather strongly impact contribution to an occurrence, as well as their extent. Sometimes cyanobacteria can withstand or adapt to changes or climatic fluctuations (
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">El-Shehawy et al., 2012</a>). Studies (e.g. 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Lugomela et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib63">Nonga et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib48">Mdegela et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Fyumagwa et al., 2013</a>; and 
  <a rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib36">Kihwele et al., 2014</a>) in the United Republic of Tanzania have demonstrated the occurrence of toxin producing-cyanobacteria in specific regions. However, these studies are not sufficient to conclusively judge CyanoHABs dynamics and their link with climatic and hydrological variation, because most of them are event-driven, for example, post-mortem of Flamingo mortality in Lake Manyara. In this particular study, our goal was to review and synthesize cases of CyanoHABs (occurrence, extent, and timing) and how they have been linked with climate, hydrological variations and or environmental (nutrients, land use etc.) changes in the United Republic of Tanzania. It will also to provides the status as it stands to water managers, researchers, and policymakers to elucidate and plan the best management practices in water resources.
 </p>
</sec>
