<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.5.1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Manyara, Arusha</div>
 <p id="p0090" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plankton dynamics are system- (weather and hydrological) specific, for example, temporal variability in precipitation can be an important driver of the seasonal development of plankton (
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">De Senerpont Domis et al., 2013</a>). Indirectly, increases in precipitation and warming are likely to impact water reservoirs stratification (
  <a rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib30">Harke et al., 2016</a>). The National Adaptation Programme (
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">The United Republic of Tanzania, 2007</a>) specifically for Lake Manyara emphasizes an increase in frequencies of floods, drought and land degradation which reduces the frequency of recreational and tourism activities. The report further argues that it is the hydrological conditions in Lake Manyara that influence birds' (Flamingo) breeding patterns. Among the studied climate parameters in relation to algal blooms is temperature (
  <a rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib96">Wells et al., 2015</a>). Generally, Manyara for example, temperature indicates an increasing trend (
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Fig. 3</a>a) which were also demonstrated by 
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">New et al. (2006)</a> and insignificant variations in precipitation (
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Fig. 3</a>b), which is a key driving factor of CyanoHABs.
  <div id="fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a). An increasing air temperature trend (observed) (from Climate Research Unit TS 4.00) and (b) Observed Precipitation (mm/day) from Global Precipitation and Climate Centre version 7 (GPPCC V7) for Manyara (Data generated from “
     <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">KNMI Climate Explorer</a>,”).
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0020" class="alt-text">Fig. 3</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0095" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standardized Precipitation and Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) (
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>) obtained from Water Cycle Integrator (WCI) portal (available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wci.earth2observe.eu/" id="intref0010" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wci.earth2observe.eu/</span>) generally indicate drought conditions (negative values of SPEI) for most of the years (for example 1994, 2000, 2004, 2008). Some post-mortem studies in the same years (
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Lugomela et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib63">Nonga et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib36">Kihwele et al., 2014</a>) may confirm whether Lesser Flamingos were exposed to cyanotoxins. The hypothesis needs to be tested whether weather and hydrological changes contributed significantly in the changing of the concentration of CyanoHABs in the Lake Manyara which could have resulted in the deaths of birds. Case study analysis is an appropriate approach to investigate these events.
  <div id="fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Standardized Precipitation and Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) for Manyara (Generated from “eartH2Observe Water Cycle Integrator,” available on 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wci.earth2observe.eu/" id="intref0125" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wci.earth2observe.eu/</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0025" class="alt-text">Fig. 4</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
