<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in body mass of birds should reflect a trade-off between costs and benefits of energy storage (reviewed in 
  <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">Witter &amp; Cuthill, 1993</a>). Costs of energy storage include a reduction in flight efficiency and thereby increased risk of predation (
  <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">Lima, 1986</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">Rogers, 1987</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-17">Gosler, Greenwood &amp; Perrins, 1995</a>); benefits include lower probabilities of starvation and thermal stress, as well as a higher likelihood to survive in case of diseases and their related periods of pathogen-induced anorexia (
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Speakman, 2018</a>). Much evidence suggests that birds actively regulate energy reserves relative to their needs (reviewed in 
  <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">Witter &amp; Cuthill, 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">Witter, Swaddle &amp; Cuthill, 1995</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Thomas, 2000</a>), increasing reserves as food resources become more unpredictable (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Bednekoff &amp; Krebs, 1995</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">Ekman &amp; Hake, 1990</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Hurly, 1992</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Ekman &amp; Lilliendahl, 1993</a>; but see 
  <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Acquarone et al., 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">Cucco et al., 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Boon, Visser &amp; Daan, 1999</a>) or predictably scarce, as when overnight temperatures decrease (e.g. 
  <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">Ekman &amp; Hake, 1990</a>). The ability of birds to regulate their body mass might be compromised during periods of elevated energy expenditure, as during the feeding of dependent young. The reproductive stress hypothesis invokes this idea to explain the mass loss during breeding (
  <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">Bryant, 1979</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Moreno, 1989</a>). Alternately, it has been suggested that birds might deliberately maintain a lower mass to save energy during frequent flight as when flying back and forth while feeding young (flight adaptation hypothesis; 
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Freed, 1981</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">Norberg, 1981</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In several studies body mass was positively correlated with fat reserves (see 
  <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">Witter &amp; Cuthill, 1993</a>), therefore fluctuations in body mass may provide insight into the trade-off between costs and benefits of fat storage on a daily basis. Most mass-regulation studies have looked at mass change within one day or change in body mass from before and after some experimental manipulation. We propose that the amplitude and pattern of day-to-day fluctuations in body mass over several days also can provide insight into management of energy reserves by birds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most mass-regulation studies have focused on temperate-zone birds that experience food shortages in winter (
  <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">Lehikoinen, 1987</a>; except 
  <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Acquarone et al., 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">Cucco et al., 2002</a>, which looked at temperate zone birds in spring). Little is known about variation in body mass of birds living in tropical areas. Limited evidence suggests that under relatively uniform tropical conditions, seasonal variation in body mass of residents is small (
  <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">Ward, 1969</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Clark Jr, 1979</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-35">Nwaogu et al., 2017</a>). In subtropical Florida scrub-jays, body mass varies little throughout the year (
  <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Woolfenden, 1978</a>). It may be important for birds living in a mild climate and experiencing relatively predictable foraging conditions to maintain a stable and low body mass that is optimal for flight efficiency, because conditions in which energy reserves are useful are infrequent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured the body mass of free-living Florida scrub-jays during the breeding season in south central Florida, USA. Florida scrub-jays breed cooperatively and maintain permanent, all-purpose territories (
  <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Woolfenden &amp; Fitzpatrick, 1996</a>). A strict dominance hierarchy exists within scrub-jay families in which males dominate females and, within each sex, breeders dominate helpers (
  <a rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-55">Woolfenden &amp; Fitzpatrick, 1977</a>). A recent study on long term mass variation for females and males breeders throughout the breeding season showed that both sexes lost mass during the period of nestling care, but not when feeding fledglings. Although post-fledging is a period of peak effort (
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Brand &amp; Bowman, 2012</a>) this is also the period during which contributions by helpers is at its highest, suggesting that their contributions might buffer mass losses by breeders. Despite this, few studies have examined mass loss in non-breeding helpers of cooperative species. We examined variation in day-to-day mass fluctuation relative to social class (female breeder, male breeder, or prebreeding helper), stage of the breeding cycle (building, incubation, dependent nestlings, dependent fledglings) and fortnight of the breeding season. We sought to examine whether mass fluctuations were greater in birds lower in the social dominance hierarchy (
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Krams, 2002</a>), and in the periods of higher energy demand, i.e., when nestling feeding occurrs (
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Moreno, 1989</a>). We tested for the ability of individuals to maintain a stable mass by looking at the effect of body mass fluctuation between two consecutive days on fluctuation between the following third and fourth day. Beside the energy demands of parental effort during reproduction, bird mass could be influenced by local factors, such as predator presence or food abundance (
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Krams, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Krams, 2002</a>), and by daily weather conditions (
  <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Wiley &amp; Ridley, 2016</a>). We do not quantify variation in predator abundance among different scrub-jay territories. Most of the study area is well managed using prescribed fire. We do know that predator abundance increases and jay survival and reproduction declines with time since fire, but virtually all of our birds occupy habitats that are earlier than this successional decline in demography. From this we assume that predation risk is relatively evenly spread among all the territories. To test for possible short-term effects of climatic stress on mass (
  <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">Lima, 1986</a>), we also investigated whether day-to-day fluctuation in mass were related to any of six weather variables collected in the study area.
 </p>
</sec>
