<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal patterns of mass variation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Florida scrub-jays exhibited a pattern of diurnal mass gain frequently observed in other diurnal birds (reviewed in 
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Clark Jr, 1979</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">Haftorn, 1989</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Ekman &amp; Lilliendahl, 1993</a>; but see 
  <a rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-29">Manu &amp; Cresswell, 2013</a>). Birds weighed the least in the morning, presumable because of nighttime fasting, and gained weight throughout the day. Birds in all social classes—female and male breeders and helpers—exhibited this pattern, although only one helper was measured multiple times within a single day. The 0.205 g gain in mass per hr is great enough to warrant caution whenever mass measurements taken at different times of day are compared. In this study we accordingly inserted the time of the day in all models comparing mass measurements. Time-adjusted measurements of the same birds taken on consecutive days, possible in this study because individuals were trained to land on an electronic balance and therefore were measured without capture are a useful alternative to repeated measurements of birds at the same time of day, for example dawn or dusk, employed in many laboratory studies (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Thomas, 2000</a>), but very difficult to obtain and very stressful for free-living birds (
  <a rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-6">Carpenter, Paton &amp; Hixon, 1983</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-26">MacLeod et al., 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">MacLeod &amp; Gosler, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Moiron, Mathot &amp; Dingemanse, 2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Breeding stage and calendar date (fortnights) affected the mass of female breeders. Females exhibited the common pattern in passerines of mass loss between the incubation and nestling stages (reviewed in 
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Moreno, 1989</a>). Mass during the fledgling stage also was lower than mass during the incubation stage. Male breeders did not show a tendency to decrease in mass during the breeding period. Their weigh fluctuated and showed some significant difference when comparing different stages or fortnights, but the differences were small (&lt;1 g). The patterns of mass variation for female and male breeders in this study are consistent with mass data for an adjacent study population of the Florida scrub-jay collected over three years during the building, incubation and nestling stages (
  <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">Schoech, 1998</a>) and to data collected in the same population in different years (
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Brand &amp; Bowman, 2012</a>). However, in these studies the patterns of mass variation in helpers were never examined in detail before. Helpers exhibited an increase of mass in the last part of the breeding period, which is somewhat surprising given their energetically demanding contributions to feeding of nestlings (
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Stallcup &amp; Woolfenden, 1978</a>) and fledglings (
  <a rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-30">McGowan &amp; Woolfenden, 1990</a>). This suggests helpers may be employing a bet hedging strategy by providing help to their parents thereby increasing their indirect fitness, yet at the same time attempting to maintain or even gain mass thereby not potentially reducing their longer-term survival prospects. Several studies documented costs associated with helping in cooperative breeders (
  <a rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-40">Reyer, 1984</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">Heinsohn &amp; Cockburn, 1994</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">MacLeod &amp; Clutton-Brock, 2015</a>). Florida scrub-jay helpers might be attempting to minimizing these costs to protect their long-term direct fitness potential by surviving to become breeders.
 </p>
</sec>
