<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The predicted climate change foresees a total increase in temperature combined with frequent dry spells. From this study, we can conclude that this scenario does not in general appear to be favorable for rice production. A moderate increase in temperature in “cool” regions, e.g., in highland valleys of Rwanda, combined with low or moderate drought stress, might result in a yield increase for rice. However, here, a temperature increase of only a few degrees, when combined with drought at the seedling and tillering stages, resulted in dramatic yield decreases for all cultivars. Some of the cultivars could not tolerate drought at all at the higher temperature. Rice is primarily cultivated in tropical and subtropical areas, being the staple food and major income crop for millions of poor people in densely populated areas. A severe decrease in production due to climate change will therefore heavily affect public health in these areas. This calls for a sincere screening to find rice capable of surviving an increased temperature with spells of drought. Here, cultivar differences in survival and production was clearly seen among the evaluated cultivars, although none of them a survived high temperature combined with drought at both the seedling and tillering stages. In this context, understanding the molecular background for some of the cultivars showing better ability to sustain the combined increase in temperature and dry spells is a necessity. Though drought and temperature combination did not affect the quality characteristics to a high extent, the combination of these stresses indirectly affect the nutritional quality and human health promoting compounds, since the quantity of produced grains becomes insufficient to meet the ideal daily intake and to fulfil the required nutritional content resulting in malnutrition. Thus, thorough screenings of cultivars that combine high quality and the capacity to withstand combined stresses at all stages of plants development and understanding involved mechanisms have to capture the attention of rice researchers.</p>
