<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">The largest discrepancies among climatologies result from the blocking index, which can take a range of forms, each highlighting different features of a block. The existing blocking indices can be classified into two broad types, based on absolute and departure fields (see [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">88</xref>] for a review). Traditionally, the former identified mid-latitude blocking highs on a 1-D basis by requesting several meridional gradient criteria around a constant latitude representative of the climatological jet stream (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">89</xref>]). Subsequent modifications have been applied to account for spatial [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" class="xref">90</xref>] or seasonal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>] variations of the jet stream, or to design more optimal filters [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" class="xref">91</xref>]. Others have extended the approach to 2-D by applying the blocking index within a latitude band, avoiding the need of a reference latitude (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">86</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" class="xref">92</xref>]). In doing so, the focus turns to Rossby wave breaking [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" class="xref">93</xref>], which recognises blocking as a high-low dipole (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>e), regardless of whether it is dominated by the poleward anticyclone (as in traditional methods) or the equatorward cyclone. This approach captures classical mid-latitude blocks associated with the weakening of the jet stream, but also high-latitude and low-latitude blocks, which rather involve southward and northward shifts of the jet stream respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">94</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>]. In contrast, anomaly methods search for field departures from the time mean (i.e. anomalies exceeding a given threshold), emphasising the 2-D anticyclonic area of the blocking high (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" class="xref">98</xref>]). Recent studies have combined both traditions into a hybrid index of height anomalies associated with meridional reversals in order to reduce discrepancies and minimise ‘misdetections’ arising from the single approaches (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">88</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" class="xref">99</xref>]). Other studies have also proposed local wave activity, a dynamical measure of the waviness of the jet stream, as a diagnostic of blocking (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" class="xref">100</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" class="xref">101</xref>]). This approach is able to capture blocking but also other events associated with meridional displacements of PV contours.
</p>
