<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn31056-sec-0023" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Suggestions on management of institutional food service</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ohly and Fritz (
  <a rid="fsn31056-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn31056-bib-0044">2010</a>) found that leadership style has a significant impact on organizational climate, while organizational climate has a comprehensive impact on the organization because it impacts organizational performance. Therefore, it is recommended that supervisors of institutional food service strengthen their education and training of managers in school lunchtime kitchens and make the employees aware that leadership style and corporate/school system are good for building relationships between managers and employees on the job site.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this study show that organizational climate has a significant impact on food safety and hygiene behaviors of employees of institutional food services. The study also finds that organizational climate is an intermediary factor in the leadership style of food safety and health behavior. Therefore, it is recommended that the supervisors of institutional food services should create a good organizational climate that is beneficial for employees to adhere to food safety and hygiene behaviors.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this study show that leadership style has a significant impact on food safety and health behaviors of the employees of institutional food services. However, the difference between transactional leadership style and transformational leadership style is not significant. In other words, both leadership styles are applicable to employees of institutional food services; thus, management can use them freely to achieve organizational goals. With regard to the development of transactional and transformational leadership styles, it is recommended that the supervisors of institutional food services receive leadership training courses for empowerment training and have interschool/company visits for observations, exchanges, and experience sharing.</p>
</sec>
