<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Abiotic factors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Abiotic factors altered by urbanization were mainly temperature and wind. Temperature may influence birds directly via the urban heat island phenomenon (
  <a rid="ref-182" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-182">Rizwan, Dennis &amp; Chunho, 2008</a>), by increasing temperatures during winter and favoring bird presence (
  <a rid="ref-122" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-122">Leston &amp; Rodewald, 2006</a>). The urban heat island may have an indirect effect on seasonal stabilization of resources used by birds by favoring an extended growing season of vegetation (see below Biotic factors).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of studies analyzed the seasonal variation of temperature along urbanization gradients. However, most of them were concentrated in China, especially in Beijing (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1" href="#supp-1">Table S2</a>). The majority of studies were concentrated between 2010 and 2018 (22 of 24 studies), and the most widely used remote sensors were the Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) and Landsat 5 and 7, although both have contrasting spatial resolutions (1,000 and 60–120 m, respectively). These remote sensors measured the land surface temperature (LST). In general, studies found that urban areas had a higher seasonal LST variation than rural or natural areas. Other studies that compared urban with desert or sand dune areas showed a smaller seasonal change of LST in urban areas. This heterogeneity in results suggest that seasonal fluctuations of LST associated with urbanization are context-dependent. Even within a given study area, results vary for different land uses compared to the urban area. For example, 
  <a rid="ref-149" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-149">Meng et al. (2009)</a> found that the seasonal change of LST was higher in the urban area than in the forest, but seasonal change of LST was bigger in the grassland than in the urban area.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal fluctuation of wind intensity may be altered by urbanization. A study in Phoenix (USA) showed that in urban areas, wind speed was significantly reduced, contributing to increased plant growth and accumulated biomass (
  <a rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-8">Bang, Sabo &amp; Faeth, 2010</a>). This increase in plant biomass can have positive impacts on higher trophic levels, such as birds. Similarly, a reduced wind speed may have direct positive effects on the reproductive success of birds by reducing the probabilities that eggs and nestlings fall from the nest (L Leveau, pers. obs., 2014).
 </p>
</sec>
