<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diurnal scale</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Abiotic factors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Undoubtedly, artificial lighting is the most notable factor altering the natural day-night cycle in urban areas, exerting negative effects on wildlife (
   <a rid="ref-160" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-160">Navara &amp; Nelson, 2007</a>). For example, Black-tailed godwits (
   <span class="italic">Limosa limosa</span>) avoided illuminated areas when selecting nest sites (
   <a rid="ref-134" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-134">Longcore &amp; Rich, 2004</a>). However, some bird species may take advantage by extending their feeding times (
   <a rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-55">Deviche &amp; Davies, 2014</a>; see examples below). Global maps indicate that the areas most impacted by artificial lighting are the most urbanized ones, such as east North America and Europe (
   <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Cinzano, Falchi &amp; Elvidge, 2001</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-134" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-134">Longcore &amp; Rich, 2004</a>). The greatest increase of light pollution from 1992 to 2012 occurred in Mediterranean-climate ecosystems and temperate ecorregions (
   <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Bennie et al., 2015</a>). Within cities, artificial lighting increases with rising urbanization level (
   <a rid="ref-113" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-113">Kyba et al., 2012</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-84" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-84">Hale et al., 2013</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-105" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-105">Katz &amp; Levin, 2016</a>), being more intense in commercial (
   <a rid="ref-131" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-131">Lim et al., 2018</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-141" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-141">Ma, 2018</a>) than in residential areas. In Berlin, most of zenith directed light comes from streets, including direct and scattered lights from lamps, automobile headlights, advertising lights located in the street area and, to some extent, light from building facades (
   <a rid="ref-111" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-111">Kuechly et al., 2012</a>). The next land use with high light emissions was the commercial/industrial/service and public service area. 
   <a rid="ref-225" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-225">Zheng et al. (2018)</a> found that main roads, commercial and institutional areas were brightly lit in Hangzhou (China), whereas residential, industrial and agricultural areas were dark at night. In Flagstaff (USA), 33% of uplight was found to arise from sports lighting; when sport lighting was off, commercial and industrial lighting accounted for 62% (
   <a rid="ref-137" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-137">Luginbuhl et al., 2009</a>). In Reykjavik (Island), almost 50% of artificial light at night came from street lights (
   <a rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-88">Hiscocks &amp; Gudmundsson, 2010</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The urban heat island phenomenon may impact the day-night variation of temperature. 
   <a rid="ref-117" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-117">Lazzarini et al. (2015)</a> found that day-night difference of land surface temperature (LST) was lower in urban than in natural areas of desert cities in North America, Africa and the Middle East.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biotic factors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Food availability at night is another factor promoting nocturnal activity of diurnal bird species (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). Artificial lighting attracts invertebrates, which are more abundant under street lights than in patches between lights (
   <a rid="ref-188" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-188">Scanlon &amp; Petit, 2008</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Davies, Bennie &amp; Gaston, 2012</a>) (but see 
   <a rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-66">Farnworth et al., 2018</a>). By attracting invertebrates, street lights provide potential food resources for insectivorous birds that extend their activity time after sunset (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). However, the attraction of invertebrates by lamps depends on the type of light (
   <a rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-62">Eisenbeis &amp; Hänel, 2009</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-133" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-133">Longcore et al., 2015</a>). 
   <a rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-62">Eisenbeis &amp; Hänel (2009)</a> found that mercury lamps attracted more insects than sodium lamps. In aquatic environments, artificial light at night has been shown to alter the activity of diurnal fish species, allowing a constant activity of the Baunco fish (
   <span class="italic">Girella laevifrons</span>) through the day and night (
   <a rid="ref-176" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-176">Pulgar et al., 2018</a>). Moreover, diurnal raptors may exploit alternative food resources available at night at sites with artificial light, such as bats (
   <a rid="ref-151" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-151">Mikula et al., 2016</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.6056/fig-1</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Schematic diagram of intervening factors and possible mechanisms influencing the temporal dynamics of bird composition in urban areas.</div>
    <p>Urbanization promotes the temporal stabilization of several environmental characteristics such as light, food, temperature and habitat structure (red boxes and circles). Human disturbance, such as the passing of pedestrians may provide food for birds, whereas the passing of cars may increase the urban heat island. Factors in circles may be strongly affected by the socioeconomic characteristics of citizens. The environmental stabilization is produced at different temporal scales (purple boxes), which in turn promote the temporal homogenization of bird communities. Dashed lines and boxes indicate factors and processes that require further research</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="peerj-06-6056-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
