<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Possible Mechanisms</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of stabilization of biotic and abiotic factors seems to vary at the different temporal scales. At the diurnal scale, stabilization of abiotic conditions such as light seems to be the most relevant, inducing nocturnal activity of birds. On the other hand, artificial light can increase food availability for nocturnal birds, especially insectivores. However, in the case of species that feed on human food waste or earthworms, such as 
  <span class="italic">Columba livia</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> sp., food resource does not seem to be a limiting factor at night. Moreover, without artificial light, it is difficult that diurnal species could find food. At the seasonal and interannual scales, the stabilization of biotic factors seems to be the dominant determinant of bird composition stabilization. However, this stabilization of biotic factors is usually mediated by the effect of abiotic factors, such as water or the urban heat island phenomenon during winter.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diurnal homogenization of bird composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies suggest that nocturnal activity is mainly regulated by artificial light, which alters melatonin secretion (
   <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Dominoni et al., 2013a</a>). Melatonin is a hormone related to the biological rhythm in animals (
   <a rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-104">Jones et al., 2015</a>). Daylength may be a significant factor, as birds presented the greatest night activity on shortest days (
   <a rid="ref-185" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-185">Russ, Rüger &amp; Klenke, 2015</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">Dominoni &amp; Partecke, 2015</a>). Meteorological factors such as temperature and cloud cover may influence the nocturnal activity of birds (
   <a rid="ref-185" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-185">Russ, Rüger &amp; Klenke, 2015</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">Dominoni et al., 2014</a>). Bird density was positively related to the degree of nocturnal activity, suggesting a role of intraspecific competition (
   <a rid="ref-185" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-185">Russ, Rüger &amp; Klenke, 2015</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-58">Dominoni et al., 2013b</a>). Alternatively, a greater bird density may promote a greater probability of appearance of nocturnal feeding (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). Finally, the importance of food availability at night was suggested, but it was very little explored (
   <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">Dominoni et al., 2014</a>). However, other authors postulated that birds may have lower energetic demands during winter and may delay the start of foraging activity as a response to the urban heat island phenomenon (
   <a rid="ref-164" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-164">Ockendon et al., 2009</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Clewley et al., 2016</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal homogenization of bird composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lower seasonal variation of bird communities in urban than in non-urban areas may be related to the extinction of migratory species and to the lower seasonal variation of resident species (
   <a rid="ref-172" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-172">Pennington, Hansel &amp; Blair, 2008</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-102">Jokimäki &amp; Kaisanlahti-Jokimäki, 2012b</a>). Migratory species arrive at a site to exploit surplus resources not used by year-round residents (
   <a rid="ref-142" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-142">MacArthur, 1959</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-94">Hurlbert &amp; Haskell, 2003</a>). If urban areas were characterized by a stabilization of resources, the surplus provided to migratory species would be diminished (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). Nevertheless, urban areas may be characterized by a low amount of food resources to migrants, especially those that feed on insects (
   <a rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-64">Faeth et al., 2005</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-205" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-205">Teglhøj, 2017</a>). Moreover, human disturbance such as pedestrian and car traffic, and nest parasitism may be especially negative to migratory birds (
   <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Burger &amp; Gochfeld, 1991</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-226" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-226">Zhou &amp; Chu, 2012</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-183" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-183">Rodewald &amp; Shustack, 2008</a>) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). In seasonally temperate areas, constant food availability to omnivorous and insectivorous species throughout the year may stabilize their temporal variation relative to populations in rural or natural areas. For instance, the African woolly-necked stork (
   <span class="italic">Ciconia microscelis</span>) were provided supplementary food by humans year-round in KwaZulu-Natal (South Africa), and humans were motivated by pleasure (
   <a rid="ref-206" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-206">Thabethe &amp; Downs, 2018</a>). Silvereyes (
   <span class="italic">Zosterops lateralis</span>) in Dunedin (New Zealand) complemented their seasonal foraging on insects by using exotic and native trees (
   <a rid="ref-213" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-213">Waite et al., 2013</a>); the exotic English oak (
   <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span>) had the highest abundance of arthropods. The advance of reproductive phenology in the Abert ’s Towhee (
   <span class="italic">Melozone aberti</span>) in Phoenix was related to predictability and limited change of food resources in urban areas (
   <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Davies et al., 2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increased stable presence of resident species may negatively affect migratory species by interspecific competition for food and nesting places (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). For example, House sparrows may use aerial hawking of insects, depleting resources for migratory species that exploit the same resources. House Sparrows and European Starlings nest in holes of buildings and trees, the same nest substrates as those used by several migratory swallow and swift species in the Neotropic, Neartic and Paleartic regions (
   <a rid="ref-168" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-168">Palomino &amp; Carrascal, 2006</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-124" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-124">Leveau, Isla &amp; Bellocq, 2015</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-30">Chantler &amp; Boesman, 2018</a>). Finally, supplementary feeding during winter may generate a surplus of resources, favouring the arrival of winter migrants (
   <a rid="ref-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-175">Plummer et al., 2015</a>), and therefore promoting an opposite process to seasonal homogenization of bird communities.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, quantity and quality of food, artificial light and the urban heat island phenomenon may affect the physiology of bird individuals, altering their phenology by lengthening the breeding season (
   <a rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-55">Deviche &amp; Davies, 2014</a>). A continental study across Europe showed that several species had a longer singing period (as a proxy of the breeding season) in urban than in rural areas (
   <a rid="ref-156" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-156">Møller et al., 2015</a>). Moreover, this effect of urbanization was higher in species that colonized cities long before other species and in the biggest cities, due to a target effect and a lower risk of extinction (mechanism of island biogeography 
   <a rid="ref-156" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-156">Møller et al., 2015</a>). It is noteworthy that this longer breeding season in urban areas was also observed in migratory species, despite the negative effects of urbanization on this group of species (see references above).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interannual homogenization of bird composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interannual composition stability in highly urbanized areas is probably driven by the high densities that some species reach there, favoured by several factors such as a constant food supply, habitat stability and a favourable microclimate during winter (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). A high dominance of a few species, typically the House Sparrow and the Rock Dove, may diminish their extinction probabilities at local scales, at least in the short and mid-term (between 2 and 10 years). However, at longer temporal scales (&gt;10 years), biotic instabilities may occur due to strong competitive interactions between species (
   <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">DeAngelis &amp; Waterhouse, 1987</a>). 
   <a rid="ref-193" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-193">Shochat et al. (2010)</a> showed that dominant bird species were highly efficient foragers that leave scarce resources to subordinate species, probably leading to their exclusion in the long term. On the other hand, bird community fluctuations are probably more governed by environmental stochasticities in rural or natural than in urban areas, due to natural disturbances or climatic fluctuations, which affect the persistence of rare species, leading to increased temporal variation of bird composition (
   <a rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-39">Collins, 2000</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-187" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-187">Sasaki &amp; Lauenroth, 2011</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
