<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Urbanization has many impacts on natural and semi-natural environments; urban expansion promotes fragmentation of ecosystems, perforation through the creation of different urban areas, alteration of biogeochemical cycles, the occurrence of the urban heat island phenomenon and pollution (
  <a rid="ref-154" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-154">Miller et al., 2001</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-82">Grimm et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-191" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-191">Shanahan et al., 2014</a>). These environmental changes have impacts on the spatial dynamics of species, producing significant declines in species diversity in highly urbanized areas and significant changes in bird composition (
  <a rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-63">Faeth, Bang &amp; Saari, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-203" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-203">Suarez-Rubio, Leimgruber &amp; Renner, 2011</a>). The uniform structure of urban areas across the world promotes the invasion of a reduced number of cosmopolitan species, leading to biotic homogenization (
  <a rid="ref-148" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-148">McKinney, 2006</a>). A scarcely explored consequence of urbanization is the temporal stabilization of biotic and abiotic factors, which may induce a decline of the temporal beta diversity of biological communities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds are one of the most widely studied taxa in urban environments because they are easily observable and respond to environmental changes (
  <a rid="ref-120" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-120">Lepczyk et al., 2017</a>). Birds can be used as indicator species of habitats that support other species and, therefore, contribute to the understanding of the impact of urbanization on biodiversity (
  <a rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-74">Gil &amp; Brumm, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-120" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-120">Lepczyk et al., 2017</a>). In addition, birds are associated with ecosystem services and disservices (
  <a rid="ref-190" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-190">Sekercioglu, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-140" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-140">Lyytimäki et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-218" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-218">Wenny et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-13">Belaire et al., 2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In natural areas, biotic factors such as predator presence or food availability, and abiotic factors, such as the variation of light throughout the day or seasonal changes in rain or temperature, induce temporal changes in species composition, favoring the coexistence of species through temporal segregation and an increase in beta diversity (
  <a rid="ref-189" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-189">Schoener, 1974</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-87">Herrera, 1978</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-110" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-110">Kronfeld-Schor &amp; Dayan, 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-211" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-211">Uchida &amp; Ushimaru, 2015</a>). For example, light variation during the day allows the coexistence of diurnal and nocturnal raptors in a given area, reducing their agonistic interactions (
  <a rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-98">Jaksić, 1982</a>). Seasonal fluctuations in the amount of resources favor the coexistence of resident and migrant species in temperate regions (
  <a rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-94">Hurlbert &amp; Haskell, 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Dalby et al., 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently, several authors noted that urban areas may promote a significant loss of temporal heterogeneity of biological diversity (
  <a rid="ref-204" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-204">Suhonen et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-128" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-128">Leveau &amp; Leveau, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-115" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-115">La Sorte, Tingley &amp; Hurlbert, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-124" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-124">Leveau, Isla &amp; Bellocq, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-210" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-210">Uchida, Fujimoto &amp; Ushimaru, 2018</a>), presumibly as a consequence of the stabilization of biotic and abiotic factors. Dampening of temporal variation in resources may influence bird community composition by favouring the temporal persistence of bird species capable of exploiting such resources, the so-called urban exploiters and adapters (see 
  <a rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-17">Blair, 1996</a>). Furthermore, stabilization of habitats and resources may promote the local extinction of those species adapted to temporal changes of resources and natural disturbances (
  <a rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-75">Gliwicz, Goszczyński &amp; Luniak, 1994</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-138" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-138">Luniak, 2004</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-195" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-195">Shochat et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-61">Duckworth, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-169" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-169">Parris, 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-173">Pickens et al., 2017</a>). For example, the Bachman’s sparrow (
  <span class="italic">Peucaea aestivalis</span>) is related to fire disturbance, and a decline in its numbers is predicted due to projected urban growth (
  <a rid="ref-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-173">Pickens et al., 2017</a>). The ultimate consequences of these changes would be the local dominance and regional expansion of species benefited by the stabilization of resources in urban environments (
  <a rid="ref-195" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-195">Shochat et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-61">Duckworth, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-169" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-169">Parris, 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stabilization of urban environments needs to be addressed at several temporal scales because urbanization may promote the dampening of environmental conditions between day and night, seasons and years. For example, the profound alteration produced by artificial light in urban environments at night is associated with nocturnal activity of birds (
  <a rid="ref-180" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-180">Rejt, 2004</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-114" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-114">La, 2012</a>). The reduced annual variation of food resources in urban areas has a negative effect on the presence of migratory species and favors the permanence of resident bird species (
  <a rid="ref-124" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-124">Leveau, Isla &amp; Bellocq, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-129" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-129">Leveau &amp; Leveau, 2016</a>). Moreover, the management of interannual natural disturbances, such as flood or fire, in urban areas may lead to the extinction of bird species associated with the changes in the landscape induced by such disturbances (
  <a rid="ref-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-173">Pickens et al., 2017</a>). Temporal stabilization of the environment in urban areas may induce a temporal homogenization of bird communities; under this scenario, humans perceive a similar bird composition at any time and can be disconnected from the natural rhythms of nature (
  <a rid="ref-124" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-124">Leveau, Isla &amp; Bellocq, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-129" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-129">Leveau &amp; Leveau, 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most reviews about urban bird ecology were conducted in developed countries (
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Chace &amp; Walsh, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-191" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-191">Shanahan et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-181" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-181">Reynolds et al., 2017</a>). Cities in developing regions, such as in Latin America, have socioeconomic and morphological contrasts with cities in developed countries. For example, Latin American countries have lower per capita income, higher socioeconomic inequality, and more compact and dense cities (
  <a rid="ref-92" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-92">Huang, Lu &amp; Sellers, 2007</a>) than developed countries. These socioeconomic and morphological factors could affect bird communities; therefore, there is a need to conduct research in developing countries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this review, factors that were stabilized by urbanization and that may influence the temporal dynamics of bird composition were categorized as biotic and abiotic (
  <a rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-90">Hooper et al., 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-171" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-171">Pau et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Beninde, Veith &amp; Hochkirch, 2015</a>), such as food and artificial light, respectively. This classification allows us to determine the relative role of biotic or abiotic factors at the analyzed temporal scales. Therefore, the specific aims of this synthesis were to: (1) review evidence of temporal stability in biotic and abiotic factors influencing birds in urban environments across different temporal scales; and (2) assess the impact of urbanization on temporal persistence of bird species composition at different temporal scales. Finally, possible lines of research are recommended.
 </p>
</sec>
