<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toward future research</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we developed adaptation pathways in the current major wheat-producing countries, based on sequential introduction of the minimum adaptation measures necessary to maintain current wheat yields through the 21st century. The adaptation pathways revealed that the timing and intensity of adaptations required differs markedly among countries. The adaptation pathways are sensitive to both climate model uncertainty and natural variability of the climate system, and the degree of sensitivity differs among countries. In addition, we showed that forecasts of necessary adaptations are important to achieve the benefit of the adaptation pathways. Here we discuss several issues that must be considered to improve the approach proposed and adopted in this study, as well as the robustness of the results.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, analyses synthesizing multiple climate projections will be required. Although we employed multiple climate models and ensemble runs to show the impacts of their uncertainties on the adaptation pathways, we need both more projections and more comprehensive analyses to identify robust adaptation pathways that can overcome the uncertainties.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the availability and accessibility of adaptation levels assumed in this study include uncertainties. For example, the pathways in this study indicate when new crop varieties are required in addition to the existing crop varieties; however, it is uncertain whether the assumed new varieties will become a reality. Regarding irrigation, in the adaptation levels we included a large expansion of irrigation that may not be adopted due to economic limitations. The assumptions underlying the selectable adaptation levels need to be refined based on further empirical evidence.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third, under the given adaptation sets we assumed that farmers are always able to attain the highest yield by optimizing planting dates and wheat varieties. However, the rate at which farmers will adapt is uncertain
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. Better representation of farmers’ decision-making will be needed for more in-depth analyses. With respect to the effect of climate change on crop yield, we did not consider the impacts of pests and diseases (we considered only their indirect impacts by assuming that the risk of pests and diseases varies with the length of the growing period). Because pests and diseases affect crop yield and need to be adapted to, more precise analyses will be needed regarding this point.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fourth, we also assumed that maintaining the current yield will be the target in the future as well, but the amount of yield required would vary with changes in socio-economic conditions (e.g., global food production necessary in 2050 is projected to be 60% higher than that of 2005/2007
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>). If an increase in the demand for food is expected due to population increase, for example, the adaptation pathways in this study may be insufficient. In addition, we accounted for neither adaptation costs nor technological progress in wheat production. Linkage with socio-economic projections will enable us to analyze adaptation pathways more comprehensively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although there is certainly room for improvement, this study is a useful first step in quantifying the temporal dimension of adaptation for global food production. Further research will enable us to develop more robust adaptation pathways, which would provide useful information for adaptation planning in each country.</p>
</sec>
