<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">It is well understood that climate change augments existing inequalities, rendering those most marginalized at greater peril to the health consequences of a changing climate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. In fact, the first key message from the Lancet’s Countdown on Climate Change and Health report emphasizes the disproportionate impact climate change has on the world’s most marginalized people and the consequential impacts this has on these populations if social and environment justice concerns are not addressed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>]. Watts et al. state: “By undermining the social and environmental determinants that underpin good health, climate change exacerbates social, economic, and demographic inequalities, with the impacts eventually felt by all populations” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>]. Those who are at greatest risk to the effects of climate change are those who are most marginalized based on socially and environmentally mediated factors, such as socioeconomic status, culture, gender, race, employment, and education [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. Marginalized groups who tend to be the most affected by the mental and physical health implications of climate change are: Indigenous peoples, children, seniors, women, people with low-socioeconomic status, outdoor labourers, racialized people, immigrants, and people with pre-existing health conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. Importantly, these marginalized groups are not homogenous. People may experience intersections of marginalization based on a variety of the above social indicators.
</p>
