<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The HAPPI protocol [
 <xref rid="RSTA20160450C9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] consists of coupled land–atmosphere initial condition ensemble simulations with prescribed sea surface temperatures (SSTs), sea-ice, greenhouse gas (GHG) and aerosol concentrations, and solar and volcanic activity, which coincide with three forced climate states. This includes a present-climate decade (2006–2015) that is simulated using observed external forcings (such as observed SSTs, sea ice, GHG and land use), and two future-climate decades (2091–2100) with the global mean temperature forced to 1.5°C or 2°C, using prescribed SST conditions. The 1.5°C future-climate experiment uses the atmospheric concentrations of the year 2095 taken directly from RCP2.6. RCP2.6 is used because coincidentally the multi-model mean of CMIP5 models stabilizes at 1.5°C at the end of the century. For the SSTs and sea ice, the CMIP5 multi-model mean SST/sea-ice anomaly between 2091–2100 and the present day is added to the observed values which were used in the present-climate experiment. Incidentally, this means that multi-model spread in SSTs at this warming level is not accounted for in the HAPPI set-up. The 2°C future-climate experiment employs a similar experimental design, but uses a weighted combination of RCP2.6 and RCP4.5 multi-model mean for the GHGs, SSTs and sea ice, as there is no single RCP scenario that directly stabilizes at 2°C. As aerosols are not well mixed, and should not be averaged between two RCP scenarios, these are kept the same for both the 1.5°C and 2°C future-climate experiments (see [
 <xref rid="RSTA20160450C9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] for details). Natural forcings (solar and volcanic activity) correspond to the present-climate decade in all climate states. Land use in future-climate decades is the same for both 1.5°C and 2°C and is taken from RCP2.6. Hence, HAPPI implicitly assumes that both climate targets require the same changes in land use.
</p>
