<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Outbreaks of vector-borne diseases have increasingly been linked to human activities. As people alter landscapes through such activities as forestry, ranching, and agriculture, they may influence disease epidemiology in a variety of ways[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B1" href="#B1">1</a>]. In addition to its direct effects on interactions between pathogens and their vectors and hosts, landscape change can alter disease dynamics indirectly via changes in vector ecology. In the case of avian malaria, for example, the influence of host-pathogen relationships on malaria prevalence is fairly well documented [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>]. However, the impacts of vector ecology and environmental changes on vector ecology are poorly understood. This uncertainty adds a measure of complexity to the prediction of malaria transmission rates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mosquitoes are the main vector group for avian malaria [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>]. Mosquito abundance is often influenced by environmental factors such as temperature, rainfall, water quality, and habitat [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>]. Vector groups for both human malaria (
  <span class="italic">Anopheles</span> mosquitoes) and avian malaria (
  <span class="italic">Culex</span> mosquitoes, 
  <span class="italic">Culex quinquefasciatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. univitattus</span>) demonstrate sensitivity to temperature changes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>]. Further complexity in the epidemiology of avian malaria is introduced by other unknowns, such as the blood meal frequency of infected mosquitoes, transmission rates, and the ratio of vectors to birds in a given habitat [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B10" href="#B10">10</a>]. Research indicates that anthropogenic activities often alter water quality and availability, and may influence the amount of rainfall that a locality or region receives [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B11" href="#B11">11</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>]. Such trends will alter the infection patterns of water-borne pathogens and those with water-dependent vectors. The impacts of environmental change on vector-borne diseases may be further enhanced if the vector plays an amplifying role in the pathogen’s life history, as in the case of avian malaria lifecycle, in which sexual reproduction of haemosporidia occurs in the mosquito [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental influences on pathogen success have been observed in other host-pathogen systems. For example, the role of water quality is evident in the case of avian influenza prevalence in waterfowl, which co-varies with water salinity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>]. In the lifecycle of 
  <span class="italic">Schistosoma</span>, snail vectors show faster growth rates when food availability (plant production) is increased in nutrient-enriched waters [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>]. Human malaria prevalence is also influenced by water quality, which affects the breeding success of mosquito vectors. Kengluecha 
  <span class="italic">et al. </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B15" href="#B15">15</a>] found that 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles</span> species abundance fluctuated in accordance with changes in water temperature, pH and dissolved oxygen. The dependence of the mosquito lifecycle on water is strong enough that it can influence patterns of infection at regional extents. For instance, Wood 
  <span class="italic">et al. </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B16" href="#B16">16</a>] showed an apparent pattern of higher infection prevalence in nesting sites of blue tits, 
  <span class="italic">Parus caeruleus,</span> closer to the River Thames, as a result of increased vector abundance near the water.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The generality of many of these results is unclear. As a test of our emerging understanding of avian malaria ecology, we used a case study in the Western Cape of South Africa to test the following predictions: (1) the infection prevalence of avian malaria would vary with vector abundance; (2) vector abundance and infection prevalence would vary with season and rainfall (with more rainfall encouraging higher prevalence of vectors and avian malaria); and (3) vector type and species would vary with water quality, which would reflect in prevalence patterns.</p>
</sec>
