<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in infection prevalence with rainfall and location</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> prevalence varied significantly across districts (see Figure  
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">6</a>; 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>3, 15</sub> = 8.21; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.002). Sites in the west coast district displayed infection prevalences of 23 – 70% (mean 44%; s. d. = 9.56). The west coast district was the driest region from which birds were sampled, with sites in that region receiving between 200–400 mm rainfall annually. Sites in the wetter districts of the City of Cape Town and Boland (which received between 600–800 mm rainfall) had lower mean infection prevalences of 7% and 12% respectively. 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> prevalence was also correlated with latitude (
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.04; see Table  
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F6" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Map showing infection prevalence by site (overall site prevalence = 0.27; n = 20).</span> Numeric labels indicate sites with the smallest and largest sample sizes. There was a significant pattern of variation in 
    <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> prevalence with location (
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001; see Table  
    <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>), with most heavily infected sites situated in the West Coast District.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1475-2875-12-370-6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the exception of Strandfontein (which falls within the City of Cape Town), the largest number of mosquitoes were caught in and around the Boland District, whereas the lowest number were caught in the West Coast District (Figure  
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">7</a>). This variation in mosquitoes caught across districts was notable, although not significant (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>3, 15</sub> = 3.03; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.06).
 </p>
 <div id="F7" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Map displaying prevalence of mosquitoes and potential vectors caught per site (total catch = 516; n = in 20 sites).</span> Numeric labels indicate sites with the smallest and largest sample sizes; notably, no mosquitoes were caught at 6 sites. The most mosquitoes were trapped in the Boland and Cape metropolitan districts.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1475-2875-12-370-7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in infection prevalence with rainfall followed a seasonal pattern, with wetter sites generally displaying lower infection prevalences (Figures  
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F8" href="#F8">8</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F9" href="#F9">9</a>). Infection prevalence showed significant correlation with rainfall (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span> = - 0.43; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.05) and days of rainfall (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span> = - 0.49; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.02) two months prior to sampling across seasons. Seasonally, infection prevalence was negatively related to rainfall during winter sampling months (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span> = - 0.43; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.05) and days of rainfall 2 months prior (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span> = - 0.51; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.02).
 </p>
 <div id="F8" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Rainfall (mm, left axis) and site prevalence (right axis) in summer sampling months (standard deviation bars = +/- 0.49).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1475-2875-12-370-8" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="F9" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Rainfall (mm, left axis) and site prevalence (right axis) in winter sampling months (standard deviation = +/- 1.65).</span> The pattern of higher infection prevalence with less rainfall is more apparent during winter.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1475-2875-12-370-9" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
