<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of our field and laboratory experiments suggest that the recent, rapid SST rise may play a key role in the collapse of 
  <span class="italic">P. lividus</span> populations along the Israeli Mediterranean coast. Even though this species is known to present strong fluctuations in population size
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>, we presume that this collapse is unprecedented because such a large scale, long-term (probably more than a decade) decline has not been recorded for this key species anywhere before. The urchins’ mortality in our study was not the result of a distinctive extreme weather event. During the summer of 2012, average daily seawater temperature was above 30 °C for 65 consecutive days including 12 days with temperature higher than 31 °C. The year of 2012 was not unique—the summer peak water temperatures during the last decade have often been higher than the observed lethal temperature of ~30.5 °C
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a>. Over-harvesting, the main cause for 
  <span class="italic">P. lividus</span> population decline elsewhere
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>, is not a factor along the Israeli coastline, since there is no commercial fishing of this species in the region, and poaching is rare. Other documented mortality factors such as predator hyper-abundance, toxic algae blooms, wave action and pollution
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a> have been ruled out as well, since no unusual episodes of these factors have been recorded. The possibility of exclusion by an invasive herbivorous fish, 
  <span class="italic">Siganus rivulatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Siganus luridus</span>, possible resource competitors of 
  <span class="italic">P. lividus</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>, was recently examined. Results from the field and laboratory experiments showed that reduced food availability can have sub-lethal impacts that may affect fitness in the long-term
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>. Therefore, temperature may be the proximal cause while competitive exclusion might play some role in the population collapse on the long-term; however, further work is required in order to determine its scope. Our results therefore provide strong evidence that the current SST temperature during the summer months is above the thermo-tolerance range of this species, and may have greatly contributed to the species near-extirpation in the region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Disease is often considered as the driving mechanism behind sea urchin mortality due to elevated temperature
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>. A positive correlation between temperature rise and urchin mortality due to disease has been observed in the field, and in laboratory and mariculture systems
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">38</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">40</a>. Mass mortality of 
  <span class="italic">P. lividus</span> due to bald sea urchin disease occurred in the Canary Islands during a particularly warm autumn in 2003
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a>, but infection was also associated with unusually low wave height, and as a result, the mortality was limited to the intertidal populations and to that specific extreme event. Although we did not observe any external morbidity symptoms, such as spots, lesions, failure to hold spines erect and spine loss in the present work, we cannot rule out the possibility that temperature-induced disease may be the mechanism behind the discussed 
  <span class="italic">P. lividus</span> population collapse. Deciphering this will require further study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One may argue that the origin of the sea urchins (lab reared specimens) may affect their survival in the experimental setup during abrupt temperature rises due to the long-term rearing in relatively stable temperature conditions (with highest temperature of 29 °C). However, it may be similarly argued that the temperature range of the reared urchins served as a reliable simulation of the historical conditions experienced by the natural populations of 
  <span class="italic">P. lividus</span> in the eastern Mediterranean in the past prior to the latest temperature increase during the last decades where it reached the lethal threshold of 30.5 °C in mid-summer.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We presume that the unexplained decline in population size in southern Lebanon during the previous decade
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>, which probably followed the decline observed along the Israeli coastline, is part of an expanding contraction of the urchins’ distribution from the hottest regions of the Mediterranean as a result of recent seawater temperature rise. We therefore predict that populations decline might soon occur farther northwest as the sea warms up in those areas as well.
 </p>
</sec>
