<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115" class="p">This study is sited in Kibirizi sector, southwest Rwanda, a mountainous region of the country, which has continually suffered from poverty and waning soil fertility, and which the National Adaptation Plan of Action for climate change identifies as high risk for both recurring heavy rain and drought (EICV, 2015, 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">GoR, 2006</xref>). The study period coincided with numerous climatic shocks. Torrential rain and flooding occurred in 2014 and 2015; extended dry spells in 2013, 2014, and 2016 decimated harvests throughout the country (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">FEWS NET, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">FEWS NET, 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">FEWS NET, 2016</xref>) and combined to produce what some have called “the longest drought in six decades” (
 <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Times, 2016</xref>). The study site comprises 4 
 <italic class="italic">umudugudu</italic> (smallest administrative unit, roughly translating as ‘rural settlement’) that were selected as 1) representative of rural settlements throughout Rwanda; and 2) eliciting variations in the degree and type of agricultural intensification (see 
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Agriculture (either own farm or working others’ land) is the principal livelihood for nearly all households, who cultivate rain-fed, mixed crop-livestock systems for both subsistence and commercial ends. Cultivation on hillsides is circumscribed by two growing seasons per year (one from September to December, the other from March to May) and restricted to marsh and valley areas during dry seasons. When possible, households diversify livelihoods to include non-farm employment such as small businesses, skilled labor in masonry or house framing, and other labor such as collecting sand or making charcoal. The CIP has been implemented in Kibirizi since 2010 and the program has been widely adopted, with over 90 percent of survey respondents participating in 2015.
</p>
