<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consistency and synergies with other scenario frameworks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different initiatives and frameworks exist that explicitly acknowledge the importance of biological invasions at various spatiotemporal scales and that call for measures to prevent the introduction and significantly reduce the impact of invasive alien species (box 
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box2" href="#box2">2</a>). The increasing attention biological invasions receive from different fields (i.e., science, policy, economy, civil society) stresses the necessity that emerging biological invasion scenarios are consistent with other qualitative and quantitative scenario frameworks. This can be achieved by linking the ASNs to already existing quantitative or semiquantitative frameworks (see box 
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box2" href="#box2">2</a>). Such a connection between already established frameworks is crucial to increase the applicability of the novel framework, to increase its acceptance by the relevant communities, and to ensure its ongoing adaptation and refinement.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To adequately capture the complexity of the ASNs, it is necessary to include information from a wide range of different fields (e.g., ecology, economy, sociology) and to integrate them into driver models of the ASN framework. Although some important drivers need to be quantified and modeled from scratch, others have already been investigated in other scenario frameworks (e.g., human population change, KC and Lutz 
  <a rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52">2014</a>; land-use change, Hurtt et al. 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">2011</a>; climate change, IPCC 
  <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">2014</a>). These scenarios follow the specific storylines of the respective scenario framework that might, however, be close to the new ASN storylines in terms of their internal logic and assumptions on how the world might change in the future. Identifying these synergies between the different scenario frameworks provides the opportunity to exchange information that can be integrated in either one.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ASNs can be coupled with other scenario frameworks through a one-to-one mapping process (Zurek and Henrichs 
  <a rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib123">2007</a>) in which the similarities and assumptions of future developments within different socioeconomic and biophysical sectors of either storyline and how these match across scenarios are compared (van Vuuren and Carter 
  <a rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib115">2014</a>, van Vuuren et al. 
  <a rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib117">2014</a>). We illustrate such an approach in ­figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">3</a> for a fictitious mapping of the ASNs onto the widely used representative concentration pathways and shared socioeconomic pathways storylines. The connection of the storylines provides the justification to exchange quantitative data between the scenarios. Data exchange can be done through loose or tight coupling (IPBES 
  <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>), such that output from the models of one framework can serve as input to the models of another one. Tight coupling includes feedback loops between the frameworks and therefore enables nonlinear dynamics of the system. Although making the model more realistic, it dramatically increases the complexity and the number of uncertain parameters and processes, which makes model behavior intractable and often reduces robustness (“integronsters,” Voinov 
  <a rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib113">2010</a>). Loose coupling is more robust and the implementation is more straightforward as different models can be run sequentially, but they are limited in their explanatory power of nonlinear dynamics.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The one-by-one mapping approach to establish the relationships among different sets of environmental scenarios. (a) The different axes represent three different sets of global environmental change scenarios (x-axis: shared socioeconomic pathways [SSP], O’Neill et al. 
    <a rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib79">2017</a>; y-axis: radiative forcing or representative concentration pathways [RCP], van Vuuren et al. 
    <a rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib116">2011</a>; z-axis: alien species scenario narratives [ASN]). The scenarios can be combined using reference assumptions described in the individual storylines. The mapping of different sets of scenarios provides information on their similarity and, therefore, how results from one framework can be linked to another. (b) A narrative comparison between the four hypothetical ASNs and the SSPs and (c) a comparison between the four hypothetical ASNs and the RCPs. The congruency between scenarios is bound between 0 (no relationship) and 1 (a perfect relationship), with darker colors indicating higher congruency between the narratives.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="biz070fig3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Independent of the coupling procedure chosen, all models need to be harmonized (IPBES 
  <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>). This means that all inputs have to be standardized and output metrics need to follow a consistent format. This is also necessary for model benchmarking to evaluate model performance and the validity of the derived predictions (McCarthy et al. 
  <a rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib74">2012</a>). For the development of the ASNs, this means that the biological invasion models need to be designed in a way that output variables from models of other frameworks can readily be integrated and vice versa.
 </p>
</sec>
