<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Narratives for the possible futures of biological invasions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental change scenarios are based on qualitative storylines that capture the trajectories of important drivers (i.e., components) of the focal system and how they might change in the future under different assumptions how the world develops (Rounsevell and Metzger 
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">2010</a>). Although several procedures have been developed that suit the varying needs of environmental scenarios, each with its individual benefits and drawbacks (see Alcamo 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">2001</a>, Jaeger et al. 
  <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">2007</a>, 2008, Henrichs et al. 
  <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>, Wodak and Neale 
  <a rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib122">2015</a>), new emerging storylines need to be tailored to the focal system and the scope of the scenario exercise (i.e., biological invasions).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this section, we propose a structure to develop such qualitative global storylines for biological invasions. We dissect this process into three components that deal with defining the scope of the scenario exercise, identifying the relevant drivers of biological invasions, and the storyline development process (figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2</a>). This structure rests on the schemes proposed by Jaeger and colleagues (2007) and Henrichs and colleagues (2010).
 </p>
 <div id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The proposed steps for the development of storylines for biological invasions in the twenty-first century. For each step, the relevant tasks are highlighted. In addition, we propose a set of participants that should contribute to each of the steps (the left hand side in italics). For step 3, we show multiple possibilities for the storyline development, as is explained in the text. The darker boxes show the development procedure we propose as the most suitable.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="biz070fig2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <sec id="sec3-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Defining the scope of the scenario exercise</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The scenario process starts by defining the scope of the exercise with respect to the overarching theme and the specific components of the system we want to explore. Setting a clear scope from the beginning helps structuring the process and defining main targets and outputs the project wants to achieve (Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>). In our case, the scope is to develop the first global storylines to derive robust future predictions on how numbers, abundances, distributions and impacts of alien species might change throughout the course of the twenty-first century (figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2</a>a). These storylines are intended to explore how these aspects of biological invasions might change under different assumptions on how the global socioecological system and its components likely develop. In addition, this exercise is intended to advance invasion science by identifying key aspects of the system and emerging challenges in the near and distant future.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying drivers and stakeholder involvement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological invasions depend on a range of different biotic, abiotic, socioeconomic, and sociocultural drivers (a nonexhaustive selection of likely relevant major drivers is shown in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplemental table S1</a>). Their importance, however, differs with respect to the spatial and temporal context, the environmental realm (marine, freshwater, terrestrial), and the taxonomic groups considered. Identifying these drivers and evaluating which might be most important for biological invasions in the future is a daunting task. Making use of available knowledge requires the inclusion of different experts (i.e., scientists, stakeholders, and decision-makers) with a broad range of expertise to ensure that all relevant facets of the system are addressed. Stakeholders can adopt different roles related to the degree of involvement and resulting responsibilities. These can range from mere consultation and decision support to codesigning or leading specific decisions in the storyline evolution (Volkery et al. 
   <a rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib114">2008</a>, Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>). In addition, the expert panel should not only encompass various scientific and nonscientific backgrounds but should also be well balanced in terms of gender and geographical and cultural backgrounds (Hannagan and Larimer 
   <a rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib35">2010</a>, Krueger et al. 
   <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">2012</a>, IPBES 
   <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We propose that the driver assessment for the biological invasion scenarios should follow a two-step procedure that involves different groups of participants at the different stages. In a first step, experts in invasion science and thematically closely related fields of environmental change identify a long list of drivers, mechanisms, and pathways of biological invasions. Such an assessment should be done in a systematic manner using established methods such as systematic literature reviews, meta-analysis, or participatory surveys (e.g., Lortie 
   <a rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib69">2014</a>, Kuebbing et al. 
   <a rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib63">2018</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequently, a scientist and stakeholder panel with expertise in the previously identified drivers should be invited to discuss individual features and trajectories of the drivers and how they interact (figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2</a>b). Within this context, the drivers can then be classified into different categories to provide a more nuanced assessment on their impacts and how they interact. We can distinguish between direct drivers with immediate effects and indirect drivers with cascading effects (Secretariat of the Convention on Biological Diversity 
   <a rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib94">2014</a>, IPBES 
   <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>) or between exogenous drivers, whose effects are beyond immediate human control (e.g., climate change, market or technology development), and endogenous drivers, whose effects can be mitigated by human control (e.g., species introduction or removal, land-use change). Understanding these different facets of the drivers and their interactions is crucial for identifying possible societal interventions, uncertainties, and thresholds (Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The process of driver discussion and prioritization can be structured by using a variety of different techniques that reduce the uncertainty in the assessment and increase reproducibility (e.g., Delphi technique, Okoli and Pawlowski 
   <a rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib81">2004</a>; fuzzy set theory, Kok et al. 
   <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">2015</a>; multiagent role games, Bousquet et al. 
   <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">2002</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Constructing qualitative storylines</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are different ways to construct storylines on the basis of the previously defined subset of driving forces (IPBES 
   <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>). Storylines can explore a range of possible futures (exploratory scenarios; Kok et al. 
   <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">2011</a>), develop pathways to a specific predefined target (target-seeking scenarios; Alcamo 
   <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">2001</a>), or explore the effects of different policies (policy-screening scenarios; IPBES 
   <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, storylines can be constructed inductively, incrementally, or deductively (Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>, Wodak and Neale 
   <a rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib122">2015</a>). Inductive storylines are based on the description of individual events and likely effects that result from specific decisions made in the present. They provide a large degree of freedom to explore possible futures but, at the same time, are less systematic in their construction (Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>). Incremental storylines describe deviations from a most plausible reference scenario (i.e., business as usual). Such a reference scenario generally assumes that historic trajectories continue without dramatic or sudden changes and allows the assessment of how changes in system drivers lead to deviations from this scenario (Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>). Finally, the deductive approach uses a more systematic assessment of the range of possibilities on how the identified drivers are likely going to change future trends and interact with other aspects of the global socioecological system. That way, consistent logic of the different storylines can be identified providing a holistic view on the topic (Jaeger et al. 
   <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">2007</a>, Henrichs et al. 
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">2010</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A final crucial step is to decide whether the storylines should be constructed depending on already existing scenario frameworks or independently (Zurek and Henrichs 
   <a rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib123">2007</a>). Developing dependent storylines with strong links to existing frameworks facilitates the establishment of links between them and at a later stage to adopt the new findings into integrated model frameworks. However, these storylines would be constrained on the assumptions of the existing framework that might not consider all relevant aspects. Constructing independent storylines provides the freedom to explore different facets of the focal system more rigorously and in a way specifically tailored to the respective topic. These independent storylines can then, a posteriori, be linked to other scenarios (see below).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because no attempt has so far been made to develop global biological invasion storylines, we suggest to start with exploratory scenarios using a deductive approach to develop independent storylines (figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2</a>c). The development of independent storylines enables the exploration of plausible futures for biological invasions without being constrained by already existing scenarios of other facets of global environmental change (e.g., climate change) that do not capture all aspects relevant for biological invasions. Descriptive storylines allow us to explore the future range of possible outcomes of alien species richness, abundance, and impacts. Only when we understand the interactions between the various drivers and how they influence the future trajectories of biological invasions can we then develop more focused scenarios that provide insights into how we can arrive at specific desired targets (e.g., target-seeking scenarios on how to achieve the goals of Aichi target 9 of the Convention on Biological Diversity). Finally, we suggest following a deductive scenario process to ensure the most systematic approach to obtain storylines through standardized methods and processes. This way, other working groups and initiatives can assess, reproduce, and extend the storylines in the future.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After establishing the conceptual foundation, the first ASN storylines can be constructed. We suggest using a two-axes approach (van der Heijden 
   <a rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib37">2005</a>), in which each axis represents one of the identified influential drivers resulting in a 2 ⋅ 2 storyline matrix for different driver combinations (e.g., social values versus trade, land use and land cover change versus climate change). The qualitative description of futures with a focus on the respective two drivers should also include an assessment of their impact on other drivers of the system and the implications on future biological invasions. Each of these two-axes approaches will therefore result in four comprehensive storylines of the future system with a specific focus on the two drivers on the main axes. Given the complexity of the topic (i.e., biological invasions) and the multitude of influential drivers, such an assessment will result in multiple qualitative storylines. However, because all of them consider the entire system (with a different special focus on individual drivers) the storylines will, in many cases, follow similar logic. Those storylines with similar logic and underlying assumptions can be aggregated into scenario families (i.e., archetypes) that have overlapping scope and describe similar potential futures (Hunt et al. 
   <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">2012</a>, Kriegler et al. 
   <a rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib61">2012</a>). This way, a high number of storylines can be condensed to a more practical number (e.g., 4–5, as was suggested by IPBES 
   <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">2016</a>), which is essential for the communication of the ASNs to stakeholders and politicians, as well as for a targeted future development of biological invasion scenarios.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We acknowledge that alternative valid approaches for constructing storylines of biological invasions exist. Scrutinizing the validity and comprehensiveness of the driver assessment and storyline logic, as well as their construction process is crucial. Furthermore, there is substantial potential for future refinements and improvements of the ASN concept. However, we believe that the approach presented in the present article provides a useful basis for developing comprehensive qualitative storylines of biological invasions.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
