<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We find national governments are taking a variety of roles in public health adaptation in practice, though the variation in approaches does not simply follow the federal, decentralized/unitary, centralized divide. Among the sampled federal countries for example, the Swiss and Belgian national governments have both primarily taken central coordinating roles in adaptation, employing legislative policy instruments to formalize vertical coordination with the cantons and regions, respectively [
 <xref rid="B83-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. The Swiss government has also prioritized capacity building for example through its health adaptation guidelines for Swiss municipalities [
 <xref rid="B83-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>], while the Belgian government has focused on planning or implementing national-level surveillance and programs (e.g., eradication of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes japonicus</italic> mosquito, infrastructure maintenance) [
 <xref rid="B94-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. Coordination is not prominently stressed, however, in the US’ or Canada’s health adaptation planning documents and webpages. The US has sought to put adaptation on the national policy agenda through recent executive orders requiring adaptation planning among national agencies [
 <xref rid="B95-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>], but has also emphasized resource provision and capacity building, most notably through the Building Resilience Against Climate Effects (BRACE) Framework and Climate-Ready States and Cities Initiative [
 <xref rid="B96-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>]. The Canadian national government’s approach has been to identify priority areas for action through extensive vulnerability assessments and research [
 <xref rid="B98-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>], and provide resources such as a series of extreme heat events guidelines [
 <xref rid="B100-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>], then allow sub-national governments and health officials to adopt adaptation initiatives as they see fit. Meanwhile, among the sampled unitary systems, the UK’s approach has prioritized cross-sectoral collaboration on adaptation, while also emphasizing capacity building and identifying priority areas for action [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. The French national government has identified priority areas for health adaptation action, and conducted centrally-driven surveillance and adaptation of hospital infrastructure [
 <xref rid="B104-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. These varied approaches to national-level health adaptation, along with the types of adaptation initiatives being planned or implemented (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot2-ijerph-13-00889" class="xref">Section 3.2</xref>) suggest that though federal governments are taking a larger coordinating role, the federal/unitary divide does not fully explain the variation in national-level approaches to public health adaptation.
</p>
