<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">Once we obtained the converged MCMC chains, we used the posterior estimates of the environmental covariates to project the point intensity of spillover per unit area in geographic and environmental space. For the final spillover risk model, we calculated the probability that the predicted intensity exceeds the lower 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> percentile of the median intensity estimated for the locations with spillover events. This threshold was chosen because the database contains location uncertainty in nearly 20% of the spillover locations. Before we simulated future scenarios of spillover, we compared the data used for model fitting with the data from climate change predictions with an extrapolation analysis [ExDet (Mesgaran et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2014</xref>)]. Briefly, extrapolation analyses consist of finding extended variable ranges (type 1 extrapolation) and different correlation structures (type 2 extrapolation) that might affect the behaviour of the statistical model. These analyses are performed with the raster data used for model transference and result in highlighting geographical areas where the model might misbehave. We used the extrapolation analysis results to remove all areas where models faced extrapolation due to novel climatic conditions. We used the 16 climate change scenarios under two different greenhouse gas representative concentration pathways [RCP 45 and 85 (Hijmans et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2005</xref>)]. This approach has been suggested to represent degrees of confidence in the potential outcomes of climate change given the variability between global circulation models, RCPs and downscaling methods (Beaumont et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2008</xref>). Concentration pathways are a series of alternative trajectories that greenhouse gas concentration might follow depending on a series of ecological, technological, socio-economic, political and demographic factors that could result in different degrees of climate change. The number that accompanies the acronym RCP indicates the severity of greenhouse gas concentration (van Vuuren et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
