<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Determining the number of generations (i.e., voltinism) obtained based on the climate data and developmental parameters, is useful to estimate the establishment potential for invasive species or introduced biological control agents [
 <xref rid="pone.0161319.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0161319.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. To estimate the voltinism of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic>, the Kearneysville Fruit Tree Research and Education Center (KFTREC) of West Virginia University located in Kearneysville, West Virginia (USA) (39° 23’ 45” N, 77° 53’ 44”; 160 m in elevation) was selected as a site for modeling and simulation of voltinism. The center had been utilized 
 <italic class="italic">Osmia</italic> bees for orchard pollination and experienced problems associated with 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> infestation during the past ten years. In addition, historical weather data (e.g., hourly temperature) directly collected at the center were available. The developmental parameters estimated herein were applied to calculate degree-days using daily minimum and maximum temperature data of ambient air from weather stations at KFTREC. Specifically, we used the lower development threshold (LDT) and upper developmental threshold (UDT) of 12.4°C and 37.8°C, respectively, for 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> development from eggs to adults found in this study. Degree-days were calculated by using single sine/vertical cutoff methods [
 <xref rid="pone.0161319.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] and cumulative degree-days (CDD) were obtained by summing calculated degree-days over a period of time. The voltinism of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> was calculated by dividing CDD per specific period (month or year) by the thermal constant requirement of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> development from eggs to adults.
</p>
