<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another reason for the differentiated result of climate change impacts could be that many previous broad‐scale studies have considered the direct effects of climate change only. While individual studies have already incorporated selected indirect climate change effects previously, such as modifications in seed dispersal and biotic interactions (e.g. Brooker 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>) or changes in forest structure (e.g. De Frenne 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), here we applied a novel combination of simulation modelling and empirical climate–diversity relationships to comprehensively assess both direct and indirect impacts of climate change. While all species groups indicated a strong direct response to climate, indirect effects also had a distinctive effect on the trajectories of a number of species groups studied (e.g. Araneae, saproxylic beetles, see Fig. S4). In line with our initial hypothesis, these indirect effects of climate change were considerably delayed; that is, forest structure and composition reacted slowly to changes in climatic conditions, resulting in a delayed response of other species groups. Also direct climate change impacts could be delayed, an effect that was not accounted for here. As the species groups investigated here have relatively short life cycles compared to the pace of climate change, a swift direct response to a changing environment can be assumed (see e.g. Danks 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>), and the lag of direct climate effects might be negligible in our study. Furthermore, our study does not consider biotic interactions within the investigated species groups or any associations with other species groups except trees (see e.g. Thuiller 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
