<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">To assess the impact of climate change by incorporating the uncertainties related to general circulation models (GCMs), we applied 24 GCMs from the World Climate Research Programme (WCRP) Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 3 (CMIP3) multi-model dataset [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>] as future climates (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" class="xref">3</xref>: Table S1). The climate change scenarios were generated based on scenario A1B of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Special Report on Emission Scenarios, which assumed rapid economic growth, the rapid spread of new and efficient technologies, and a balanced emphasis on all energy sources [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. The A1B scenario is most commonly cited as a high emission scenario in the Fourth Assessment Report of IPCC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>]. We selected the A1B scenario as a possible future because we considered that we should assess the worst case first for the purpose of conservation. The A1B scenario is similar to between Representative Concentration Pathways 6.0 and 8.5 in the later climate scenarios CMIP5 in the Fifth Assessment Report of IPCC, which is second and highest emission scenarios [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. We only used the data for the period 2081–2100 because the fractional uncertainty for natural factors of internal variability (such as the El Niño Southern Oscillation, which occurs every few years or decades) is larger in shorter-term climate scenarios. Such internal variability is a noise for global warming prediction, which would emphasize or cancel the effects of greenhouse gases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. The climate of the twentieth century experiment (20c3m) was used as baseline for current climate. We calculated differences in the means and minimum daily temperatures, and ratios of precipitation between 1961 and 1980 of 20c3m and 2081 and 2100 of the A1B scenario. These differences and ratios were spatially interpolated from original spatial scales (approximately 125 km to 444 km in latitude) to 1-km grid cells using a simple linear interpolation method, and then applied to the current climatic data (i.e. climatic data for grid cells) and used as future climatic data. The four climatic variables in each grid cell were calculated using the future climate scenarios in the same manner as the calculations for current climate. When comparing the current climate to the future climate scenarios within the study area, warmth index and minimum temperature increased in all scenarios, summer precipitation increased in all but four scenarios, and maximum snowwater decreased in all scenarios (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" class="xref">3</xref>: Table S1).
</p>
