<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The processes of solar incident energy conversion to plant biomass through C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> photosynthesis and associated energy losses are illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>. Since about 51.3% of the total solar energy striking leaf surface is outside of the 400–700 nm range of PAR, photosynthetic pigments intercept only remaining 48.7% of the total solar incident energy. However, photosynthetic organisms reflect or transmit about 4.9% of total solar incident energy as they weakly absorb in the green region of visible spectrum. This leaves only 43.8% of the total solar energy available for absorption by chlorophylls in the leaf. Leaf chlorophylls absorb maximally in the blue and red regions of PAR with 400 and 700 nm wavelengths, respectively. The reaction centers in the Photosystem I (PSI) and PSII drive photochemistry with the energy level of red photons only. Consequently, the energy absorbed at blue photon needs to be converted to the lower energy level of red photons resulting in heat dissipation of 6.6% of the intercepted solar energy, leaving only about 37.2% of the initial solar energy (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). The assimilation of one CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> molecule into carbohydrate by Calvin cycle requires 2NADPH and 3ATP molecules (
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhu et al., 2008</xref>). The absorption of four moles of photons by chlorophyll molecules will generate one molecule of NADPH through linear electron transport chain, which is coupled to translocation of six protons into the thylakoid lumen. The synthesis of 1ATP molecule require 4 protons. Thus, absorption of 8 moles of photons are required to generate 2NADPH and 3ATP molecules to assimilate one CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> molecule into carbohydrate. The eight moles of red photons contain 1388 kJ energy whereas one-sixth of a glucose molecule (1C carbohydrate unit), contains only 477 kJ energy (
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhu et al., 2008</xref>). Thus, the minimum energy loss between photons absorbed by reaction centers and photosynthetic linear electron transport chain to carbohydrate assimilation is, 1 – (477/1388), which represents a loss of 24.6% of the total incident solar energy, leaving about 12.6% of the total energy (
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhu et al., 2008</xref>). In C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants, photorespiration and respiration result in the loss of fixed carbon causing 6.1 and 1.9% expense of total energy. Thus, it is estimated that out of the total incident solar energy striking the leaf surface only about 4.6% is conserved to plant biomass, suggesting a maximum theoretical energy conversion efficiency of 0.046 in C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). This estimate, however, does not include energy consumed in N and S reduction which needs to be taken in to account as they also consume photosynthetically generated electrons (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foyer and Noctor, 2002</xref>).
</p>
