<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">The growing discursive space around Indigenous peoples and climate change is uneven by region and population, however reflecting different national political circumstances, the nature of the risks posed by climate change, and the extent and nature of engagement by Indigenous Peoples Organizations and communities in climate advocacy (Ford et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2016b</xref>; Maldonado et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2016</xref>). Mainstream media also likely influences national and international discourse on Indigenous issues in this context, establishing the salience of climate change as an issue, influencing how the public and policy makers understand and engage with it, and making visible Indigenous experiences of climate change (Boykoff 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2012</xref>; Carvalho 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2010</xref>; Schmidt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2013</xref>). The role of the media herein is particularly important for Indigenous peoples—who in many cases are geographically isolated and often have less access to institutional power—serving as an important forum from which to broadcast alternative narratives and generate public pressure (Koch-Baumgarten and Voltmer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2010</xref>; McCallum et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2012</xref>). Media coverage of climate change has also been demonstrated to materially impact Indigenous communities, including access to funding streams (Callison 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2014</xref>; Marino and Lazrus 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, studies reveal pervasive under-representation of Indigenous issues within mainstream media coverage in high-income nations, and the widespread use of frames which perpetuate racist tropes and delegitimize Indigenous actors while masking socioeconomic legacies of colonization (Anderson and Robertson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2011</xref>; Rankine et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
