<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microbes are part of a complex soil food web, which consists of numerous species or taxa across different trophic levels, including primary producers (plant roots and algae), primary consumers (bacteria, archaea, fungi, viruses, and root-feeding fauna), and secondary and higher-level consumers (bacterivores, fungivores, and predators) (
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>10</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>50</italic>
 </xref>). These organisms are all important components of the plant-soil system that are able to alter the outcome of PSFs (
 <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>51</italic>
 </xref>). Although widely acknowledged as important drivers of soil biogeochemical processes modulated by climate (
 <xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>52</italic>
 </xref>), soil food webs show high interactivity and complexity (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>). Climate change effects on soil food webs will be affected by the fact that combined responses of the individual components of PSFs—decomposers, mutualistic symbionts, and herbivores/pathogens—are all influenced (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>7</italic>
 </xref>). However, the net effects will be difficult to predict when we consider all the individual components of the soil biota in isolation. The elegance of the PSF concept is that the overall functional consequences of climate change on the soil biota can be assessed through its combined impact on plant performance and, ultimately, the net PSF effect. This may also have implications for extremely long-term patterns in PSFs. For example, body size of soil invertebrates decreased during the dry and warm conditions in the Paleocene-Eocene Thermal Maximum, affecting ecosystem functions such as organic matter decomposition and nutrient cycling, which, in turn, affected plant diversity (
 <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>53</italic>
 </xref>). The consequences of these long-term effects on the soil food web for PSFs have not yet been assessed. The influence of climate change may also affect plant community composition through mechanisms such as shrub encroachment, as discussed in the section on succession.
</p>
