<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual degree-day models results under current climatic conditions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g003" href="#pone.0221057.g003">Fig 3B and 3C</a> show that, on average, MEAM1 and MED should have enough accumulated day-degrees in the present climate (1986–2015) to complete one generation over England, Wales and much of Scotland. Two generations are predicted in much of southern and central England. Only in parts of the Scottish Highlands and associated Islands are there areas which are unsuitable for even one generation to be completed. Whereas the alternative parameters for MEAM1 [
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref013">13</a>], shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g003" href="#pone.0221057.g003">Fig 3A</a>, indicate that one generation could occur everywhere, with at least 3 generations being possible in southern and central England. The thresholds used for MED were the higher of the values reported (refer to 
  <a rid="pone.0221057.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0221057.t001">Table 1</a>). Mapping these means the UK was depicted as less favourable than the other set of thresholds would imply. Given these less favourable data still show that much of the UK is theoretically suitable for 1–2 generations per year, this increased our confidence that at least some parts of the UK would be suitable for outdoor establishment. Choosing the lower threshold from [
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref017">17</a>] would make the UK appear more favourable still.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, it should be noted that many summers over the 30-year period represented by these data will have been much hotter (or cooler) than the mean, potentially allowing more (or fewer) generations to have developed from any whiteflies escaping from glasshouses. Moreover, there will be numerous locations within each 25 km grid cell where temperatures accumulate faster (or slower) than the value representing each cell that is based on the estimated mean agricultural altitude [
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref029">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In France, the number of potential mean annual generations increases up to a maximum of 7 along the Mediterranean coast. Except for areas of high ground (The Massif Central in central southern France, the Alps in the east and the Pyrenees to the south), there is a general southward increase in generation number.</p>
</sec>
