<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate indices under current climatic conditions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the climate indices were found to be significantly different in all months, the results show the summer months (June, July, and August) to be the most significantly different. These are also the key months for potential 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> development outdoors. The indices showing the most significant differences between East Anglia and Mediterranean France are TG10p and TN10p: the number of cold days and cold nights that are colder than the 10
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile of days and nights in Mediterranean France (refer to Table A in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a> for the full index definitions).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The JRC-MARS and E-Obs datasets do show significant differences for some of the climate indices used in this study, however, the indices showing most significant differences between East Anglia and Mediterranean France are consistent between the two datasets (Table B in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a>). This provides evidence that the spatial and temporal differences observed in these indices represent genuine climate differences, rather than variations caused by the specific dataset used.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4A and 4B</a> clearly show that there is a strong gradient across France in the number of days as cold as the coldest 10% of days and nights in Mediterranean France, but quite a flat profile across the UK. The indices incorporating user-defined thresholds, although not the most significantly different between regions, are informative. Mid- to southern France spends more than 80% of the summer months in conditions optimal for 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> development (temperature during egg to adult &gt; 15°C), but there is a sharp decline in the time spent in optimal conditions for development across northern France and into the UK from south to north (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4C</a>). Similarly, mid- and southern France experience the greatest amount of time in conditions optimal for survival (temperature &gt; = 20°C and &lt; = 30°C), but the amount of time diminishes in northern France and into the UK (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4D</a>). The UK experiences only a very small amount of time in conditions optimal for 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> survival (&lt;15% of time during the summer months). However, the results also show that, even in Mediterranean France, conditions are only optimal for 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> survival for 40–60% of the time during these warmest months. This may contribute to the low number of outdoor observations as compared to Crete where outdoor populations of whitefly are a very serious problem [
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref039">39</a>]. The corresponding values for Crete—amount of time in conditions optimal for survival (temperature &gt; = 20°C and &lt; = 30°C)—using the same methodology as for the UK and France, is 70% of the time during June-August for the whole island.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0221057.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0221057.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Latitudinal transects from the EObs dataset.</div>
   <p>A: Percentage of summer months as cold as the 10
    <span class="sup">th</span> percentile cold days in Mediterranean France, B: Percentage of month as cold as the 10
    <span class="sup">th</span> percentile cold nights in Mediterranean France, C: Percentage of month available for optimal development conditions from egg to adult (&gt;15°C), D: Percentage of month available for optimal survival conditions (&gt; = 20°C AND &lt; = 30°C). The left-hand panels show the transects through France and the right-hand panels show the transects through the United Kingdom. The vertical shaded bars correspond to the regions for Mediterranean France and East Anglia as shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g002" href="#pone.0221057.g002">Fig 2</a>. Latitudinal averages are constructed by excluding the Central Massif, the Alps, the Pyrenees, Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland from the datasets as high elevations are likely to hinder whitefly colonisation. The indices for the number of days in the month meeting each condition were converted to percentage of the month by dividing by the number of days in each month and multiplying by 100.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0221057.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
