<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="sec013" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual degree-day models results under current climatic conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g003" href="#pone.0221057.g003">Fig 3B and 3C</a> show that, on average, MEAM1 and MED should have enough accumulated day-degrees in the present climate (1986–2015) to complete one generation over England, Wales and much of Scotland. Two generations are predicted in much of southern and central England. Only in parts of the Scottish Highlands and associated Islands are there areas which are unsuitable for even one generation to be completed. Whereas the alternative parameters for MEAM1 [
   <a rid="pone.0221057.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref013">13</a>], shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g003" href="#pone.0221057.g003">Fig 3A</a>, indicate that one generation could occur everywhere, with at least 3 generations being possible in southern and central England. The thresholds used for MED were the higher of the values reported (refer to 
   <a rid="pone.0221057.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0221057.t001">Table 1</a>). Mapping these means the UK was depicted as less favourable than the other set of thresholds would imply. Given these less favourable data still show that much of the UK is theoretically suitable for 1–2 generations per year, this increased our confidence that at least some parts of the UK would be suitable for outdoor establishment. Choosing the lower threshold from [
   <a rid="pone.0221057.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref017">17</a>] would make the UK appear more favourable still.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, it should be noted that many summers over the 30-year period represented by these data will have been much hotter (or cooler) than the mean, potentially allowing more (or fewer) generations to have developed from any whiteflies escaping from glasshouses. Moreover, there will be numerous locations within each 25 km grid cell where temperatures accumulate faster (or slower) than the value representing each cell that is based on the estimated mean agricultural altitude [
   <a rid="pone.0221057.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref029">29</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In France, the number of potential mean annual generations increases up to a maximum of 7 along the Mediterranean coast. Except for areas of high ground (The Massif Central in central southern France, the Alps in the east and the Pyrenees to the south), there is a general southward increase in generation number.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec014" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate indices under current climatic conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the climate indices were found to be significantly different in all months, the results show the summer months (June, July, and August) to be the most significantly different. These are also the key months for potential 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> development outdoors. The indices showing the most significant differences between East Anglia and Mediterranean France are TG10p and TN10p: the number of cold days and cold nights that are colder than the 10
   <span class="sup">th</span> percentile of days and nights in Mediterranean France (refer to Table A in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a> for the full index definitions).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The JRC-MARS and E-Obs datasets do show significant differences for some of the climate indices used in this study, however, the indices showing most significant differences between East Anglia and Mediterranean France are consistent between the two datasets (Table B in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a>). This provides evidence that the spatial and temporal differences observed in these indices represent genuine climate differences, rather than variations caused by the specific dataset used.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4A and 4B</a> clearly show that there is a strong gradient across France in the number of days as cold as the coldest 10% of days and nights in Mediterranean France, but quite a flat profile across the UK. The indices incorporating user-defined thresholds, although not the most significantly different between regions, are informative. Mid- to southern France spends more than 80% of the summer months in conditions optimal for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> development (temperature during egg to adult &gt; 15°C), but there is a sharp decline in the time spent in optimal conditions for development across northern France and into the UK from south to north (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4C</a>). Similarly, mid- and southern France experience the greatest amount of time in conditions optimal for survival (temperature &gt; = 20°C and &lt; = 30°C), but the amount of time diminishes in northern France and into the UK (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4D</a>). The UK experiences only a very small amount of time in conditions optimal for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> survival (&lt;15% of time during the summer months). However, the results also show that, even in Mediterranean France, conditions are only optimal for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> survival for 40–60% of the time during these warmest months. This may contribute to the low number of outdoor observations as compared to Crete where outdoor populations of whitefly are a very serious problem [
   <a rid="pone.0221057.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref039">39</a>]. The corresponding values for Crete—amount of time in conditions optimal for survival (temperature &gt; = 20°C and &lt; = 30°C)—using the same methodology as for the UK and France, is 70% of the time during June-August for the whole island.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0221057.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0221057.g004</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Latitudinal transects from the EObs dataset.</div>
    <p>A: Percentage of summer months as cold as the 10
     <span class="sup">th</span> percentile cold days in Mediterranean France, B: Percentage of month as cold as the 10
     <span class="sup">th</span> percentile cold nights in Mediterranean France, C: Percentage of month available for optimal development conditions from egg to adult (&gt;15°C), D: Percentage of month available for optimal survival conditions (&gt; = 20°C AND &lt; = 30°C). The left-hand panels show the transects through France and the right-hand panels show the transects through the United Kingdom. The vertical shaded bars correspond to the regions for Mediterranean France and East Anglia as shown in 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g002" href="#pone.0221057.g002">Fig 2</a>. Latitudinal averages are constructed by excluding the Central Massif, the Alps, the Pyrenees, Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland from the datasets as high elevations are likely to hinder whitefly colonisation. The indices for the number of days in the month meeting each condition were converted to percentage of the month by dividing by the number of days in each month and multiplying by 100.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0221057.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec015" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change projections</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the climate warms by GWL2 in July, and by GWL1.5 in August, the amount of time with optimal development conditions for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> in East Anglia becomes statistically indistinguishable to that of Mediterranean France in the current climate (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g005" href="#pone.0221057.g005">Fig 5</a> compared to 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g004" href="#pone.0221057.g004">Fig 4C</a>; see also Table C and Fig A in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a>). Similarly, the amount of time with optimal survival conditions for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> in East Anglia becomes statistically indistinguishable in July and August between GWL1.5 and GWL2 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g006" href="#pone.0221057.g006">Fig 6</a>; see also Fig B in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a>). However, by GWL4 the difference for July and August reverses and Mediterranean France rises above the optimal survival temperature for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g006" href="#pone.0221057.g006">Fig 6</a>). The climate indices results indicate that there would be a gradual northward shift across France in the locations most suitable for 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> development and survival around GWL2 and then a shift across into the UK by GWL4.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0221057.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0221057.g005</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Latitudinal transects showing the percentage of month (A: June, B: July, C: August) available for optimal development conditions from egg to adult (&gt;15°C) under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions.</span> The left-hand panels show the transects through France and the right-hand panels show the transects through the United Kingdom. The vertical shaded bars correspond to the regions for Mediterranean France and East Anglia as shown in 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g002" href="#pone.0221057.g002">Fig 2</a>. Latitudinal averages are constructed by excluding the Central Massif, the Alps, the Pyrenees, Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland from the datasets as high elevations are likely to hinder whitefly colonisation. The indices for the number of days in the month meeting each condition were converted to percentage of the month by dividing by the number of days in each month and multiplying by 100.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0221057.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="pone.0221057.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0221057.g006</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Latitudinal transect showing the percentage of month (A: June, B: July, C: August) available for optimal survival conditions (&gt; = 20°C AND &lt; = 30°C) under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions.</span> The left-hand panels show the transects through France and the right-hand panels show the transects through the United Kingdom. The vertical shaded bars correspond to the regions for Mediterranean France and East Anglia as shown in 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g002" href="#pone.0221057.g002">Fig 2</a>. Latitudinal averages are constructed by excluding the Central Massif, the Alps, the Pyrenees, Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland from the datasets as high elevations are likely to hinder whitefly colonisation. The indices for the number of days in the month meeting each condition were converted to percentage of the month by dividing by the number of days in each month and multiplying by 100.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0221057.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The number of cold days and nights as cold as the 10
   <span class="sup">th</span> percentile of days and nights in Mediterranean France under current climate conditions for the Mediterranean France region remains significantly different to East Anglia under the climate projections (Table B in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a>). However, the comparison shows that some parts of southern UK will be comparable to parts of south-western France where 
   <span class="italic">B</span>. 
   <span class="italic">tabaci</span> has been found outdoors at GWL4 (Figs C-F in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0221057.s001" href="#pone.0221057.s001">S1 Appendix</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
