<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec018" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts of climate change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> is unlikely to become established outdoors in the UK under current climate conditions, with continued future climate change, the risk of establishment outdoors in the UK is expected to increase. The movement of pests northward in France with climate change has already been demonstrated for the pine processionary moth (
  <span class="italic">Thaumetopoea pityocampa</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref045">45</a>], highlighting the increasing pest threat to the UK.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taken together, the results of the future climate indices analyses indicate that a 2°C global temperature rise above pre-industrial levels will reduce the prevalence of 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> outdoors in Mediterranean France in July and August as conditions become sub-optimal for survival. The rise in temperature could potentially lead to a greater threat to the UK in the months of June and September and/or a shift northwards in distribution (up to and including southern UK) as conditions in the UK become more favourable. These results differ from previous studies that suggest a northward spread for 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> across France as a result of future climate change and an increase in its range throughout southern Europe but not northern Europe [
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref015">15</a>]. However, the Gilioli study ([
  <a rid="pone.0221057.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221057.ref015">15</a>]) used a physiologically based population dynamics model to map the potential distribution of 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> in Europe. The population of immatures and adults were constrained with a temperature dependent mortality rate function linked to a development rate function. Although the model outputs correspond closely to the known limits of 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> distribution outdoors in Europe, by linking mortality to the suitability for development they did not take account of any other factors, such as the influence of cold weather. Furthermore, the climate data used was limited to monthly mean minimum and maximum temperatures with an interpolation routine based on geographical location and the time of sunrise used to derive hourly temperature data. Unlike the current study, which used a suite of climate model projections, the climate change scenario tested was flat (1 and 2°C were added to each hourly temperature).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study suggests that 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> could establish outdoors in East Anglia and across southern England in the future, which would make eradication of outbreaks in future more challenging than the current situation, where outbreaks are confined to glasshouses. Given the crucial need for an early warning system against 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. tabaci, we have identified that key indices for 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> survival and development in summer change gradually with increasing latitude (northwards from areas of France with a Mediterranean climate). This means that monitoring any possible northwards spread of 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tabaci</span> populations outdoors in France should also provide an important indicator of any change in the risks of outdoor populations of this species developing in the UK.
 </p>
</sec>
