<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Gymnocarpos przewalskii</italic> (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) is a small shrublet distributed throughout the semi‐arid regions of northwestern China, from the westernmost end of the Tarim Basin, through the Hami Basin and the Hexi Corridor, to the Wulate Prairie at the easternmost. The plant has succulent‐mucronate leaves and a well‐developed root system, and shows an outstanding adaptation to arid regions. It has low dispersal capabilities, because both seeding and germination rates are low, and although it can propagate clonally, the dispersal of cloned offspring is very limited in scope and concentrated around the mother plant (Wang &amp; Ma, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Therefore, 
 <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic> can serve as a good model for spatial and temporal scale phylogeographic analysis in the region. Moreover, it is a protected plant of first conservation priority (Fu, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1992</xref>). Thus, the phylogeographic study of the species has important values, for both the origin and evolution of flora of the Chinese northwestern deserts, and plant protection. Previous phylogeographic studies of 
 <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic> (Ma, Zhang, &amp; Sanderson, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) based on chloroplast genetic data alone showed the species to have high levels of genetic variation, especially in the western Tarim Basin, the Hami Basin, the Liuyuan region in western Gansu, and at the easternmost end of the distribution of the species. To explain the above genetic structure, a scenario that the four regions were glacial refugia for 
 <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii </italic>was hypothesized (Ma et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35113-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). However, that study used only chloroplast DNA fragments, and therefore, the ability to investigate population dynamics and genetic structure of the species was limited.
</p>
