<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used the Linear Scaling (LS) bias correction method (
 <xref rid="c94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">White and Toumi 2013</xref>) in order to adjust RCM time series with correction values based on the differences between mean observed (gridded ANUSPLIN) values and RCM simulation. The LS method aims to perfectly match the monthly mean of corrected values with that of observed ones (
 <xref rid="c56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lenderink et al. 2007</xref>). It operates with monthly correction values based on the differences between observed and raw data (raw RCM simulated data in this case). The LS method was applied to the CRCM5 simulation over the historical period as well as on the RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 future simulations. Comparison between the bias-corrected climate data from the CRCM5 model driven by CanESM2 under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 and climate data from other RCMs driven by CanESM2 or the Irish Centre for High-End Computing EC Earth climate model (ICHEC-EC-EARTH) under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 over two time periods (2011–2040 and 2041–2070) across Canada showed that the bias-corrected climate data from CRCM5-CanESM2-RCP4.5 and CRCM5-CanESM2-RCP8.5 used in this study were not far outliers compared to other models and did not deviate significantly from the ensemble mean (see Figure S1). The bias-corrected minimum and maximum temperature for each month and each CRCM5 grid were used to obtain 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M129" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">0</mn>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> values for each grid cell for the hottest month of the year, and to calculate the number of months each cell was suitable (if at all) for CHIKV transmission. A risk category corresponding to the mean temperature of the warmest month of the year was assigned to each 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M130" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">50</mn>
    <msup class="msup">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">km</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mn class="mn">2</mn>
    </msup>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> grid cell representing the transmission potential for CHIKV under short-term and long-term projected climatic conditions simulated using the two different emission scenarios.
</p>
