<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">10</xref> shows the time series of the global-mean and Arctic-mean changes in the TOA and surface net energy fluxes from the two simulations. Over the Arctic (67°–90°N), the TOA fluxes are very similar for the two runs, while the net surface flux into the Arctic Ocean is substantially smaller in the 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> run than in the FixedIce run (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">10b</xref>). This is expected because the use of the fixed sea-ice concentration (SIC) in the FixedIce run reduces the upward longwave (LW) radiation and sensible and latent heat fluxes (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7,</xref>
 <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" class="xref">8</xref> and Supplementary Figures 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">19</xref>) and therefore should lead to a larger downward net flux in the FixedIce run. Thus, the Arctic surface flux difference shown in Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">10b</xref> is what we should expect physically from the change we imposed, whose impact on the Arctic TOA flux is negligible. Because of this, the small difference in the global-mean TOA flux between the two runs after year ~100 (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">10a</xref>) is likely due to other changes outside the Arctic region, rather than the direct effect of the imposed SIC change in the Arctic. Noticeable differences exist only after about year 100 in the global-mean fluxes between the two runs, and the TOA-minus-surface flux difference is similar between the two runs throughout the whole simulations (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">10a</xref>). Thus, the global-mean and Arctic-mean TOA and surface net fluxes from the two runs are reasonable.
</p>
