<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change as a fact of life is particularly formidable to low income rural communities whose livelihoods heavily depend on rain-fed subsistence agriculture like those in the focus of this study, the Mazungunye communal lands (IPCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). According to Hellmuth et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>), climate change presents risks to lives and livelihoods at the individual level and to the economy and the infrastructure at regional and national levels. Rural people are believed to be particularly vulnerable to climate change. Their vulnerability is not attributed to climate change only but is also a combination of social, economic and environmental factors that interact with it (Turpie &amp; Visser 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). A study conducted by Chazovachii et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref> concluded that communal farmers in Masvingo Province have not been passive victims of the vagaries of climate change and variability. They have rationally responded to it through various adaptation and mitigation strategies, both individually and collectively. However, as observed by Ofoegbu et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), rural communities have remained vulnerable to climatic-induced shocks although they are employing a plethora of mechanisms to mitigate the effects of climate change. This is because their high exposure to climate change risks does not match their adaptive capacity. The researchers identified such factors (challenges) as barriers to adaptation, which became the focal point of the study. According to Gukurume (
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>), in Zimbabwe many studies have tried to understand the effects of climate change on agriculture, health and the economy, as well as strategies to mitigate climate change, just to mention a few, but there is little evidence that any studies have been dedicated to unearthing the challenges faced by rural people in their efforts to mitigate the effects of climate change specifically in the Mazungunye communal lands. Several studies on climate change have focused on industrialised countries or urban areas, thereby ignoring rural communities in the developing world that are engulfed in more complex realities of the climate change phenomenon (Mahiya &amp; Gukurume 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). It was the fundamental intention of this study to close the knowledge gap by unravelling the challenges faced by rural people in mitigating the effects of climate change in the Mazungunye communal lands.
</p>
