<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p content-type="flushleft" class="p">In summary, there is a strong correspondence between streamflow trends from gauges with natural streamflow and those with human-modified streamflow, indicating that large-scale trends in climate are clearly evident in human-modified watersheds. These results suggest that hydrologic alterations due to climate change and subsequent impacts on freshwater ecosystems will likely be realized in similar ways in natural and human-modified systems. We do not, however, find as strong a relationship between natural and human-modified systems for streamflow variability (IQR trends) or extreme low flows (1st percentile trends), indicating that water management operations that leave water in streams for water delivery or aquatic habitat purposes provide more uniform flows throughout the year. This confirms the increasingly important role that reservoirs may play in managing baseflow and hydrologic variability (
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>). Additionally, in the western United States, streamflow used for environmental purposes typically has more junior rights than other entities such as agriculture or urban water use, so watersheds that are becoming drier may have environmental flows eliminated first (
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>). Streamflow trends are largely driven by large-scale precipitation and evapotranspiration trends (and thereby by temperature trends), with changing precipitation patterns being particularly important [and more uncertain (
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>)] for water management in the future. Given the importance of streamflow for agriculture, urban water deliveries, and aquatic ecosystems, our results indicate that large-scale climate trends are already affecting water availability, regardless of whether rivers are natural or managed.
</p>
