<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying biodiversity hotspots on a local scale, using multiple data sources, and ecological niche modeling, has the potential to contribute to more effective nature reserve management.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we used infrared-triggered camera trapping, field surveys, and interviews to create a dataset on the distribution of species (mammals and birds) in Hebei Wulingshan Nature Reserve (Hebei Province, China).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identified 101 species (14 orders, 38 families), 64 of which (2,142 effective records) were selected for environmental niche modeling. All results were reclassified into three groups: “priority areas” (areas including the potential distributions of over 80% of species), “important areas” (those with 50% of species), and “normal areas” (all other areas). Our results show that priority areas (1.31–1.82 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) and important areas (7.73–21.44 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) for conservation were mainly covered by the core and experimental zones of the reserve; additionally, a kilometer-wide margin around the outside of the nature reserve seems to be important to maintaining biodiversity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We close by suggesting some actions for enhancing conservation of biodiversity in the reserve, including monitoring, strengthen law enforcements, introducing popular science, and co-operating with local people.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
