<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study identified a set of priority areas and questions which can assist in guiding research and action aimed at mitigating the joint impacts of NCDs and climate change. Of the total 19 priorities identified, the three high priority questions common to both 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t002" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t002">Table 2</a> (&gt;90% agreed to include) and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t003" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t003">Table 3</a> (&gt;60% agreed as a “high priority”) plus the highest ranked priority (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t003" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t003">Table 3</a>), can be used reasonably confidently as a basis for future research. The process of identifying high priorities (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t002" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t002">Table 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t003" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t003">Table 3</a>) had the advantage of concomitantly highlighting low priorities (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figures S5 and S6</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identified priorities are consistent with existing frameworks and position statements on climate change and health but are considerably more detailed. In particular they reflect many aspects of the WHO research priorities consensus [
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-12-12941">27</a>] which presents five empirical and scenario-based categories 
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, (i) assessing the risk; (ii) identifying effective interventions; (iii) guiding health-promoting mitigation and adaption decisions in other sectors; (iv) improving decision support; and (v) estimating the costs of protecting health from climate change. Moreover, the priority question, “
  <span class="italic">how can the harms that lead to NCDs be described and conceptualised in a way that more easily supports policy formation?</span>”, fits well with the proposition that, there is a premium on “
  <span class="italic">understanding (among other issues) how best to frame advice for policy-makers…</span>” [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-12-12941">31</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The need for research on climate change and food security and systems, and urban design, transport and housing, dominated the identified priorities. Behaviour, communication and information systems were also prominent. Further, all the priority areas and questions met the criteria of: having the capacity to impact positively one or more negative aspects of the interface between climate change and NCDs; being amenable to mitigation through legal and ethical frameworks and governance systems; and the potential to address critical deficits in our knowledge and understanding of how to mitigate and/or manage impacts of the NCD and climate change crises.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Delphi process was a suitable method for surveying experts on this topic. It was similarly used previously to achieve expert agreement on “grand challenges” for NCD prevention [
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-12-12941">35</a>], many of which are consistent with the priorities identified in our study. The response rate was acceptable [
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-12-12941">45</a>], and ranking is one of the most common measures used to identify consensus in the Delphi process [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-12941">46</a>]. The Round 1 questionnaire was informed by a summary of the results of face-to-face debate and careful consideration of the issues by a panel of 25 multi-disciplinary, international experts and stakeholders. It was structured yet flexible which is reportedly an advantage [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-12-12941">47</a>,
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-12-12941">48</a>]. Moreover, there were inbuilt validations of the results. For example: three external experts reviewed the analysis of Round 1; another expert panel reviewed the final results; the 10 priorities identified in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t002" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t002">Table 2</a> had a high rate of respondent agreement (&gt;90%) and three of these were confirmed as high priority by the rankings shown in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t003" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t003">Table 3</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, inevitably there are limitations to the Delphi method such as issues with questionnaire design, the selection of experts, subject and researcher bias, and lack of representation, as well as challenges in managing larger groups [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-12-12941">47</a>,
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-12-12941">49</a>]. Other methods of gaining consensus do exist including structured expert judgement [
  <a rid="B50-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-12-12941">50</a>], consensus development conference, nominal group technique [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-12-12941">47</a>] and brainstorming [
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-12-12941">49</a>]. There are also different forms of Delphi methods including the “policy Delphi” and the “real time Delphi” [
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-12-12941">49</a>]. The Delphi survey in this current study was chosen as the method of gaining consensus as its use is recommended when examining less explored topics and identifying/prioritizing issues [
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-12-12941">45</a>,
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-12-12941">47</a>]. In addition, exposure to subject bias may be also seen as an advantage as its presence may change other subject’s views, hence generating consensus [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-12-12941">47</a>,
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-12-12941">49</a>]. Additionally, Round 2 respondents were exposed to the yield of research questions and areas from Round 1, which would likely reduce promote congruence and reduce confusion.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants in both the face-to-face workshop and the subsequent Delphi process came from a diverse range of disciplines and geographical regions. A number of steps were taken to reduce possible confusion and misunderstanding of the task. These included the use of the Sydney Resolution (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S1</a>) as the initial framing for workshop participants, and the Communiqué from the workshop (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S2</a>) being provided to Delphi respondents along with explicit instructions for the inclusion and ranking of priorities. The selection of respondents was from among experts with recognized knowledge, experience and interest in the general topic. However, the characteristics of the Delphi respondents changed between Round 1 and Round 2 in that the ratio of males to females almost halved as did the proportion of respondents from Europe versus other regions, and the proportion of academics versus other sectors (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-12941-t001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-t001">Table 1</a>). It is not possible from our research to know what if any bias this may have introduced.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another potential source of bias may be that representation from the developing world was limited in both the initial workshop and Delphi process, primarily because NCDs and climate change is a new field of enquiry and resources, and infrastructure and academic expertise is limited in developing countries. There was a lack of representation at the workshop from disciplines such as architecture; urban planning; transport; and economics. However, this was remedied in the selection of Delphi survey participants and it has been argued that, where few experts are available, a small sample may be used with confidence [
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-12-12941">51</a>]. Several Round 2 respondents did not rank the research questions. Consequently, the results tend to emphasize the priority inclusion of research topics rather than their specific order of priority. Some of the proposed priorities included more than one research question and are, therefore, not readily researchable without further breakdown. The survey was completed in 2012 and it is possible that respondents’ opinions may have changed since then. Notwithstanding this, the identified priorities are not inconsistent with the 2015 recommendations of the newly formed Lancet Commission on Health and Climate Change [
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-12-12941">17</a>]. Nor did our literature review indicate that the identified questions and areas have been satisfactorily addressed in the interim.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extensive variety of research modalities and disciplines required to generate credible evidence to support policy solutions in this area is hindered by practical impediments including the absence of a common language and purpose for communicating and debating the confluence of NCDs and climate change. As noted by McMichael [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-12-12941">31</a>], population health researchers and epidemiologists primarily focus on methods and problems within their ‘comfort zone’ such as exposure to risk from infections or toxins versus their effect, and controllable versus confounding variables. He further pointed out that environmental health theory and practice is based on and directed by efforts to understand exposure and effect but, despite the sophistication of new technologies for quantifying such exposures, pales into insignificance when compared with attempting to understand and research the complexities and uncertainties implicit in climate change and health. Additionally, as shown in an audit of Canadian research on health and climate change, despite recent increases, funding is inadequate and is not commensurate with the risks posed [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-12941">52</a>]. Other barriers include the siloed way in which research funds have traditionally been acquired by funding bodies and dispersed to researchers, and the lack of clarity around framing and prioritizing explicit areas and questions to guide research efforts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Notwithstanding its limitations, the process we undertook identified solution-oriented priority areas for research into NCDs and climate change whereas previous frameworks have largely outlined principles and broad areas. Prior work on NCDs and climate change has nominated 
  <span class="italic">strategies</span> to prevent climate change which also have NCD co-benefits [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-12-12941">53</a>] while the results of our study frame potentially researchable 
  <span class="italic">questions</span> and areas to guide evidence generation. The emphasis towards interventions that employ legal solutions was important for a number of reasons. Legislation, regulation and taxation are standard items in the public health toolbox and, as exemplified by the WHO’s Framework Convention on Tobacco Control [
  <a rid="B54-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-12-12941">54</a>], have been shown to promote robust global and national health governance mechanisms capable of effecting positive individual, population and sovereign health behavior and policy change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As pointed out by others, making research into the health impacts of climate change manageable and meaningful requires firmly locating it in the broader agenda of global health equity [
  <a rid="B55-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijerph-12-12941">55</a>,
  <a rid="B56-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-12-12941">56</a>], supported by multi-disciplinary collaboration using a variety of research methods [
  <a rid="B57-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-12-12941">57</a>], and empirical data on past and present events and outcomes, and scenario-based health risk projections [
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-12-12941">27</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
