<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Experimental Section</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following approval from the University of Sydney Human Ethics Research Committee (reference number 13885) a three step process (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-12941-f001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-f001">Figure 1</a>) was undertaken.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Step 1: Initial Identification of Priority Research Areas</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We convened a three day workshop at The University of Sydney under the auspices of the Global Health Justice Network of the Worldwide Universities Network (WUN). The aim was to explore, debate and identify broad areas of knowledge deficit and priorities at the interface between NCDs and climate change to which the law might be applied to mitigate current and/or future harms and achieve co-benefits. The workshop followed a structured process of presentations by WUN members on various aspects of NCDs and climate change, panels, facilitated plenary debate, and small group discussions. The 2008 Sydney Resolution [
   <a rid="B44-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-12-12941">44</a>], a call to action on NCDs acknowledging the link with climate change and advocating for healthy places, healthy food, healthy business, healthy public policy and healthy societies, was used as the framework and starting point for the discussions. The plenary debate and small group discussion sessions were documented during the workshop.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Broad areas for research were identified as priorities if they: 
   <div list-type="simple" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <span class="label">(a)</span>
     <p>had the capacity to impact positively one or more negative aspects of the interface between climate change and NCDs</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <span class="label">(b)</span>
     <p>were amenable to mitigation through legal and ethical frameworks and governance systems</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <span class="label">(c)</span>
     <p>had the potential to address critical deficits in our knowledge and understanding of how to mitigate and/or manage effects of the current NCD and climate change crises.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results were documented in a workshop consensus Communiqué (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S2</a>)
  </p>
  <div id="ijerph-12-12941-f001" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>A summary of the study method and major actions.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-12941-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Step 2: An International Delphi Process</div>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot1-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1. Identification of Priority Research Questions</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Delphi process [
    <a rid="B45-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-12-12941">45</a>] was used to test and expand on the priority areas identified through the workshop.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot2-ijerph-12-12941" sec-type="subjects" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. Delphi Participants</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants were suggested by the workshop delegates, from among authors of relevant journal articles, and professional contacts of one of the authors (RC) from among experts involved in the development of the Sydney Resolution [
    <a rid="B44-ijerph-12-12941" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-12-12941">44</a>]. We sought participants from a wide geographical spread, both genders, a range of ages and career stages, and a variety of disciplines and sectors.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot3-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3. Data Collection</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Delphi process consisted of two rounds and was completed in 2012. In 
    <span class="bold">Round 1</span>: the Communiqué comprising the workshop delegates’ priorities, a participant information sheet and a semi-structured questionnaire were emailed to an international sample of experts who had not attended the workshop. The questionnaire asked participants to: (i) state what, if any, broad research priority areas they believed were missing from the Communiqué; and (ii) suggest at least one but no more than three priority research questions that would address one or more knowledge deficits in the overlap between climate change and NCD prevention and which would be feasible to conduct (see questionnaire at 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S3</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
    <span class="bold">Round 2</span> questionnaire consisted of the responses to Round 1 after removal of duplicates and arranged in categories. It was emailed with an explanatory letter and instructions to respondents from Round 1 who were asked to either: (i) exclude or include the priority research areas identified in Round 1; and (ii) to rank each included question as either high, medium or low priority (see questionnaire at 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S4</a>). Specifically, participants were requested to identify those areas and questions that: 
    <div list-type="simple" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>were of central importance to the global response to NCD prevention and climate change;</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>addressed a knowledge or evidence deficit that is preventing progress in an area of high importance to the overlap between mitigating or adapting to climate change and preventing or significantly reducing the impact of NCDs and/or which focused on social and health justice issues;</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>addressed problems at the interface between NCDs and climate change which may be amenable to modification through legal interventions;</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>had a degree of urgency or immediacy.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot4-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.4. Analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two of the authors (SB and RC) reviewed the responses to Round 1, removed duplicates and collated the remaining responses under 13 categories: food production; food security; policy; corporate social responsibility; urban design, transport and housing; regulatory interventions; social justice; economics; trade; behaviour and communication; information; systems; and water. The responses were then assessed for quality and consistency by three academic experts in health policy and law, sociology and politics from Bristol University (UK) who had attended the workshop. The categories were further condensed and each of the 100 questions gleaned from Round 1 was allocated to one only of six categories: food systems and security; urban design, transport and housing; economics trade and business; social justice; behaviour, communication and information systems; and regulation, governance and policy, which formed the structure of the Round 2 questionnaire.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses from Round 2 were entered onto an Excel spreadsheet and analyzed by the: 
    <div list-type="simple" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>majority agreement to include as a 
       <span class="italic">high</span> priority;
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>ranking of order of importance as a 
       <span class="italic">high</span> priority;
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <span class="label">-</span>
      <p>majority agreement to identify as a 
       <span class="italic">low</span> priority.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Step 3: Verification and Deconstruction of the Final Priority Questions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following analysis of the responses to Round 2, an expert panel of three internationally recognized academics reviewed the researchers’ interpretation and rankings of the final results and advised on further analysis of the priority areas/questions.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
