<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0204188.s001" class="supplementary-material">
 <label class="label">S1 File</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Supporting information including statistics results and other measures.</title>
  <p class="p">Distances of INMET weather stations from nesting grounds in each region considered in this study, from north to south (Table A). Nest and climate data availability for each region between 2005–2016 included in our analyses. The typical nesting season in RN occurs between November–May, while the typical nesting season in BA occurs between October–April (Table B). Results of Tamhane’s T2 test for statistical differences in hatching success and emergence success between nesting beaches within Rio Grande do Norte (RN) and Bahia (BA), Brazil, from north to south. Statistically significant p–values are indicated in bold (Table C). Results of Generalized Linear Mixed-Effects Models for local climate influences on hatching success (HS) and emergence success (ES) across Brazil as well as within Rio Grande do Norte (RN) and Bahia (BA). For these models, the binomial family was specified, and the year nests were laid was the random effect. Model parameters included: average air temperature (temp), accumulated precipitation (acc.rain), average precipitation (avg.rain), average humidity (humid), average solar radiation (rad) and average wind speed (wind). The temporal scales used were: the month nests were laid (0.climate variable), the month nests were laid and one-month prior (0.1.climate variable), the month nests were laid and two months prior (0.2.climate variable), two months prior to nesting (2.climate variable), and during the incubation period (inc.climate variable). The models with the lowest AICc values and high significance are highlighted in gray. P–values for combined models are presented for each parameter in the order the model is written (Table D).</p>
  <p class="p">(PDF)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="pone.0204188.s001.pdf" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption class="caption">
   <p class="p">Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
