<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
 <p class="p">Supplementary material for this article is available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/9/eaau2406/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/9/eaau2406/DC1</ext-link>
 </p>
 <p class="p">Table S1. Definitions of SWS and EWS for the present study.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S2. Return period of SWS and EWS (as defined in table S1), calculated as the average ± SD across all grids included in the global wheat-growing area (fig. S1) for the year of harvest and as the cumulative value for the harvest year and the preceding year.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S3. A list of the CMIP5 GCMs used in this study (with brief descriptions).</p>
 <p class="p">Table S4. Symbols for weighting schemes used in the paper.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S1. Weights of grids as used in the study.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S2. Relationship between the proportion of the global arable land affected by severe water scarcity (SWS) and the cereal price index.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S3. Relationship between the proportion of the global wheat growing area affected by severe water scarcity (SWS) and the cereal price index.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S4. Relationship between the proportion of the wheat growing area of the top ten wheat exporters affected by severe water scarcity (SWS) and the cereal price index.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S5. Change in the wheat production area (WhA) affected by severe/extreme water scarcity for the major world areas and the five main producers.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S6. Extent of wheat production affected by severe water scarcity for the harvest year (a) and the harvest and preceding year(s) (b) for the period from 1861 to 2100.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S7. Area affected by severe water scarcity for two different definitions of wheat sensitive period.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S8. Changes in median/maximum wheat area affected by severe and extreme water scarcity expressed as absolute change and change per 1°C global temperature increase for period 2041–2070.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S9. Changes in median/maximum wheat area affected by severe and extreme water scarcity occurring expressed as absolute change and change per 1°C global temperature increase for period 2071–2099.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S10. Comparison of area affected by severe and extreme water scarcity when future harvest is shifted by ±1 month.</p>
 <p class="p">Movie S1. The annual extent of SWS events for the period 1901–2016 based on the CRU data and then projections for six GCM models under the RCP 2.6 scenario.</p>
 <p class="p">Movie S2. The annual extent of SWS events for the period 1901–2016 based on the CRU data and then projections for six GCM models under the RCP 4.5 scenario.</p>
 <p class="p">Movie S3. The annual extent of SWS events for the period 1901–2016 based on the CRU data and then projections for six GCM models under the RCP 8.5 scenario.</p>
</supplementary-material>
