<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2f4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Path analysis: pre-migratory period</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We predicted that nestling mass would be positively correlated with total body water and fat mass because individuals in poor condition may not be able to compensate for their poor start owing to impaired cognition, increased susceptibility to disease both in and out of the nest, or size related dominance hierarchies at high quality foraging locations 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Meril1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Meril1">[25]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Nowicki1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Nowicki1">[57]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Marra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Marra1">[58]</a>, and that timing of nesting would negatively influence total body water and fat mass, because early fledging birds likely have a head start for accumulating lean tissue and fat mass relative to late fledging individuals. We also predicted that the progression of moult would negatively influence total body water given increased protein demands by tissues that support feather growth 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Baggott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Baggott1">[59]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Bauchinger1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Bauchinger1">[62]</a>, and that moult would negatively influence fat mass given increased thermoregulatory costs and a higher basal metabolic rate during moult (
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Baggott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Baggott1">[59]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Myrcha1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Myrcha1">[63]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Bonier1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Bonier1">[67]</a>). We included time captured in our path model because body mass may vary with time of day 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Baggott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Baggott1">[59]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-JenniEiermann1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-JenniEiermann1">[68]</a>. We included date captured because migratory birds generally improve condition through time in preparation for migration 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Lindstrm2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Lindstrm2">[26]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Bairlein1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Bairlein1">[69]</a>. A term for year was also included. We examined two-way interactions between nestling mass, timing of nesting, and moult progression with date captured and year, and two-way interactions between nestling mass with timing of nesting and year with date captured (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028838.s015" href="#pone.0028838.s015">Table S11</a>). Owing to ontogeny, we also examined whether timing of nesting and date of capture influenced moult progression 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Neto1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Neto1">[66]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0028838-Bojarinova1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0028838-Bojarinova1">[70]</a>. Last, we tested for differences in moult progression across years and examined the effect of two-way interactions between timing of nesting, date captured, and year on moult (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0028838.s015" href="#pone.0028838.s015">Table S11</a>). All structural equations for the pre-migratory period included a random effect for individual nested within natal nest to control for covariances within individuals and among nest mates, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
