<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Under the future climate change scenarios, the spatial distribution of the pelican is predicted to slightly change. The pelican’s breeding distribution might be facilitated by the moderate scenario, increasing near 9%. However, under the severe scenario, the prediction decreased to near −20%. This trend is similar to other studies described for seabirds, whose breeding distribution will be reduced by climate change (
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Jenouvrier et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Krüger et al., 2018</xref>). This increase in habitable area is explained by the climatic conditions in southern Chile, and those climatic conditions will likely be similar to the current conditions of the central coast of Chile (
 <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Falvey &amp; Garreaud, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Garreaud, 2011</xref>). Over the last decade, an increase in pelican abundance has been reported along the coast of southern Chile, with observations of large flocks following schools of pelagic fishes in the inner sea (
 <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Imberti, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Häussermann, Forsterra &amp; Plotnek, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Cursach, Rau &amp; Vilugrón, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cursach et al., 2018</xref>). In this area, there has even been one report of an unsuccessful attempt to nest (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Cursach, Rau &amp; Vilugrón, 2016</xref>). The occurrence of competitive interactions with other seabirds has also been observed with endemic species from Patagonia (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Cursach, Rau &amp; Vilugrón, 2016</xref>). In southern Chile, a group of pelicans was observed displacing nesting pairs of Imperial shag (
 <italic>Phalacrocorax atriceps</italic>), causing the abandonment of the nest (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Cursach, Rau &amp; Vilugrón, 2016</xref>).
</p>
