<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The climatic issue also poses a challenge to the conservation of the tropical rainforest of the Amazon. Recent estimates suggest that the combination of deforestation and global climate change could cause an increase in the occurrence of forest fires in the Amazon of up to 50% by 2050, creating a cycle of degradation and biodiversity loss [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. Studies report thresholds that should not be exceeded in order to ensure the maintenance of the Amazon rainforest–up to 40% deforestation and a temperature rise of 3°C to 4°C [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref093" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>]. In the Amazon, there exists a nonlinear interaction between several drivers that has culminated in the environmental changes that have been observed–the region has warmed 1°C in the last 60 years and lost about 20% of its original vegetation cover [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref096" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. Among these drivers are climate change and land use due to global warming and deforestation, which in turn induce a greater frequency of extreme climatic events and forest fires, increasing the vulnerability of the systems of the Amazon [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref096" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. These studies show how vegetation suppression and environmental change interact synergistically in tropical areas, which places the northeast and southern regions of the Amazonas on highest alert. The northeast portion because: 1) it was the one region that possessed many microregions–Manaus, Itacoatiara and Rio Preto da Eva–with the highest values for the indicator of vegetation cover and deforestation; and 2) it could experience the greatest climate change according to the CSI. The southern portion, comprising the microregions of Madeira and Purus, deserves special mention because: 1) according to reports of the Instituto do Homem e Meio Ambiente da Amazônia (IMAZON), it contains a concentration of municipalities in which deforestation increased the most in 2016, in addition to suffering intense pressure from the agricultural frontier, which is expanding from neighboring states; and 2) it is one of the places where climate change may be more prominent, according to the CSI.
</p>
