<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regarding climate, the CSI showed the northern and northeastern regions and the southwest portion of the state to be more vulnerable. In general, the projections of climate change for the region are inconsistent due to complex thermodynamic ocean-atmosphere interactions and the different results presented by different climate models [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref087" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. Some models have projected rainier climates whereas others have projected drier climates for the Amazon Basin, though, the consensus is of an increase in mean temperature and reduction of rainfall for most of the Amazon territory–the same was found in the present survey by CSI [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref082" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref088" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. The impacts may be severe since climate change might turn extreme events, like the droughts of 2005 and 2010, into the rule more than an exception. The close relationship and dependence of the populations of Amazonas to the hydrological regime has raised concerns about food security, mobility, and water potability, among others. It is noteworthy that the regions of the state where climate change has been most prominent are also those associated with higher disaster rates (southwest and northeastern regions), the poorest social indicators (northern and southwestern) and the highest population density in the state (metropolitan area) [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref091" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>]. The long-term consequences of maintaining this socio-environmental pattern might be the loss of economic, human, and natural assets.
</p>
