<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue journalpublishing3.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bull World Health Organ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bull. World Health Organ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BLT</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0042-9686</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1564-0604</issn><publisher><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4669736</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BLT.15.166199</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.15.166199</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorials</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Climate change and health in Pacific island states</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Rokho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell-Lendrum</surname><given-names>Diarmid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Pacific Technical Support, World Health Organization Regional Office for the Western Pacific, Level 4, Provident Plaza One, Downtown Boulevard, 33 Ellery Street, Suva, <country>Fiji</country>.</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Maternal, Newborn, Child and Adolescent Health, World Health Organization, Geneva.</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Public Health, Environment and Social Determinants of Health, World Health Organization, Geneva.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to Rokho Kim (email: <email xlink:href="kimr@who.int">kimr@who.int</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>93</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>(c) 2015 The authors; licensee World Health Organization.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution IGO License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/igo/legalcode">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/igo/legalcode</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. In any reproduction of this article there should not be any suggestion that WHO or this article endorse any specific organization or products. The use of the WHO logo is not permitted. This notice should be preserved along with the article's original URL.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>The health and well-being of human populations &#x02013; and the very existence of low-lying island states &#x02013; depend on an ambitious outcome at the 21st Conference of the Parties to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change, (Paris, 30 November to 11 December 2015). Unless the world dramatically reduces emissions of greenhouse gases, especially carbon dioxide from burning of fossil fuels, it is estimated that global average temperature will increase by 2.6&#x02013;4.8 &#x000b0;C and sea level will rise by up to a metre around the end of this century.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> These changes would have major health impacts.</p><p>By the 2030s &#x02013; now less than 15 years away &#x02013; approximately 250&#x02009;000 additional deaths are projected to occur every year from malnutrition, malaria, diarrhoea and heat stress attributable to climate change.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Climate change will disproportionally affect small island states, because of their relatively small land area, high population density and dependence on local ecosystems for subsistence. Rising sea levels threaten to make low-lying island nations such as Kiribati, the Marshall Islands and Tuvalu uninhabitable. Understandably, Pacific island leaders have called for increases in global average temperatures to be limited to less than 1.5 &#x000b0;C.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref></p><p>Pacific island countries are confronted with a triple burden of noncommunicable diseases, infectious diseases and climate change impacts. In some Pacific island states, mortality rates from noncommunicable diseases are already among the highest in the world. Since 2012, there have been over 40 large infectious disease outbreaks in the region: most were caused by climate-sensitive diseases such as dengue, chikungunya and Zika virus infections.<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> There have also been several record-breaking extreme climate events in the Pacific recently. Extreme events often damage or destroy health facilities, disrupting essential health services when they are needed most urgently. For example, in Vanuatu, cyclone Pam seriously damaged many health facilities: two hospitals, 19 health centres and 50 dispensaries in 22 affected islands. In the most affected province, 21 of 24 health facilities were damaged. The economic impact was estimated to be more than 60% loss of gross domestic product.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p><p>The World Health Organization (WHO) has been working with ministries of health and other stakeholders of Pacific island countries to build climate resilient health systems. Although a disease-specific approach is useful initially, in the long run a comprehensive intersectoral programme is required. As recommended by WHO,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> this programme should address (i) health governance and policies tackling climate risks; (ii) health information, integrated surveillance and climate early warning systems; and (iii) preventive and curative services (water and sanitation, pest and vector control, food safety, disaster risk management for health, safe and environmentally sustainable health facilities, vaccination and child health services).<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref></p><p>In the past five years, WHO has assisted thirteen Pacific island countries to develop national climate change and health vulnerability and impact assessments to guide health system adaptation plans. These assessments highlighted common climate risks such as direct impacts of extreme weather events (e.g. drowning and injuries), waterborne and vector-borne diseases.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> In Fiji, where a recent outbreak of dengue fever affected over 20 000 people, dengue, leptospirosis, typhoid fever and diarrhoea were targeted as priority climate-sensitive diseases.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Fiji has produced a strategic action plan for climate change and health for 2016&#x02013;2020, including the development of early warning and response in vulnerable communities. However, as for other small island developing states, implementation will be a huge challenge. The health sector has received less than 1.5% of the multilateral funds for climate change adaptation distributed to date.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref></p><p>The international response to climate change is a major opportunity to improve global health. For the first time, international commitments for reductions in carbon dioxide emissions, if fully implemented, would have a meaningful impact on global temperature rise.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> The Paris climate pact, if sufficiently ambitious and effective, would be considered not only a major turning point in climate change policy, but also a far-reaching public health treaty to protect and promote the health and well-being of vulnerable populations, particularly those of small island states.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref></p></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Pachauri RK and Meyer LA, editors. Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. Geneva: Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change; 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Quantitative risk assessment of the effects of climate change on selected causes of death, 2030s and 2050s. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2014. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/globalchange/publications/quantitative-risk-assessment/en/">http://www.who.int/globalchange/publications/quantitative-risk-assessment/en/</ext-link> [cited 2015 Oct 30].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Suva Declaration on climate change. Suva: Pacific Island Development Forum Secretariat, 2015. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pacificidf.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/PACIFIC-ISLAND-DEVELOPMENT-FORUM-SUVA-DECLARATION-ON-CLIMATE-CHANGE.v2.pdf">http://pacificidf.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/PACIFIC-ISLAND-DEVELOPMENT-FORUM-SUVA-DECLARATION-ON-CLIMATE-CHANGE.v2.pdf</ext-link> [cited 2015 Oct 8].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cao-Lormeau</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Musso</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emerging arboviruses in the Pacific.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>. <year>2014</year>
<month>11</month>
<day>1</day>;<volume>384</volume>(<issue>9954</issue>):<fpage>1571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61977-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25443481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Vanuatu post-disaster needs assessment cyclone Pam. Port Vila: Government of Vanuatu; March 2015. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pacificdisaster.net/pdnadmin/data/documents/16599.html">http://www.pacificdisaster.net/pdnadmin/data/documents/16599.html</ext-link> [cited 2015 Oct 30].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Conference report, strengthening health resilience to climate change. In: Conference on health and climate change, Geneva, 27-29 August 2014. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2014 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/globalchange/mediacentre/events/climate-health-conference/whoconferenceonhealthandclimatechangefinalreport.pdf?ua=1">http://www.who.int/globalchange/mediacentre/events/climate-health-conference/whoconferenceonhealthandclimatechangefinalreport.pdf?ua=1</ext-link> [cited 2015 Nov 3]. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Operational framework for building climate resilient health systems. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2015. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/189951/1/9789241565073_eng.pdf">http://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/10665/189951/1/9789241565073_eng.pdf</ext-link> [cited 2015 Oct 29].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Human health and climate change in Pacific island countries. Manila: World Health Organization; 2015. In press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">Fiji climate change and health adaptation: proceedings of the symposium, 9 February 2015, Suva, Fiji. Suva: Fiji Ministry of Health and Medical Services; 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Based on data from Climate Funds Update website. Heinrich B&#x000f4;ll Stiftung and the Overseas Development Institute. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.climatefundsupdate.org/Home">http://www.climatefundsupdate.org/Home</ext-link> [cited 2015 Sept 5].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Synthesis report on the aggregate effect of the intended nationally determined contributions. Bonn: United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change; 2015. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/2015/cop21/eng/07.pdf">http://unfccc.int/resource/docs/2015/cop21/eng/07.pdf</ext-link> [cited 2015 Oct 30].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Niera M. Our climate, our health: It&#x02019;s time for all health professionals to take action [Internet]. Geneva: Media Centre, World Health Organization; 2015. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/commentaries/climate-change-conference/en/">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/commentaries/climate-change-conference/en/</ext-link> [cited 2015 Nov 3].</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>