<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The analysis was conducted in two phases. First, a one-way ANOVA with 1-sided Dunnett post-hoc tests comparing the treatment conditions to control was conducted to investigate how differences in message content affected the three respective mediators of perceived internal, external, and response efficacy. Then the mediation model was analyzed with SPSS version 21 and the SPSS PROCESS macro version 2.15 [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. The PROCESS macro can be downloaded for free from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://processmacro.org/download.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://processmacro.org/download.html</ext-link>. The mediation analysis tested whether the message treatment conditions, as compared to the control group, influenced the three mediators of internal, external, and response efficacy, and how these types of efficacy, in turn, influenced political behavior. The PROCESS macro utilizes a regression based path analytic framework to test hypothesized direct and indirect effects. In addition to OLS regression coefficients, the PROCESS macro offers bootstrapped confidence intervals for the indirect effects of the experimental conditions on political behavior through perceptions of internal, external, and response efficacy, while accounting for all control variables. The use of bootstrapped confidence intervals is generally considered superior to alternatives such as the Sobel test or causal steps approach [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Bootstrapped intervals were calculated using 10,000 sampling iterations and bias-corrected estimates. The 95% confidence intervals may be interpreted such that if the lower and upper confidence intervals are either both above 0 or both below 0 there is a statistically significant effect, whereas if they straddle 0 there is not a significant effect.
</p>
