<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Assessment of seedling morphological traits made it possible to identify three groups of seed orchards based on three traits selected a priori, namely final height, root mass, and nitrogen content (
 <bold class="bold">Figure 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </bold>). These groups also showed different trends of height growth during the growing season (
 <bold class="bold">Figure 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </bold>). The height growth curves modeled for each of the orchard groups (
 <bold class="bold">Figure 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2C</xref>
 </bold>) showed that southern seed sources (SO1 and SO3) and those from the second-generation orchards (SO2 and SO7) had higher height growth relative to sources from the west (SO4 and SO5) and the north-east (SO6 and SO8) (
 <bold class="bold">Figure 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">5A</xref>
 </bold>). Our results agree with those obtained by 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lesser and Parker (2004)</xref> in a study of young white spruce seedlings grown from 127 seed sources from Ontario and Quebec which showed that, in general, the southerly seed sources had a greater capacity for height growth at the end of the second growing season. A north-south cline was also observed in 63 young white spruce populations from Ontario and Quebec grown under nursery conditions (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li et al., 1997</xref>) and in a two-year nursery study of ten first-generation Quebec seed orchards (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carles et al., 2011</xref>), indicating local adaptation to temperature. In a study involving 8- and 13-year-old white spruce trees from 26 seed sources, representing six ecological regions of the temperate and boreal forest in Quebec, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jaramillo-Correa et al. (2001)</xref> also showed that populations from southern ecological regions grew taller than those from northern regions. Such a cline following temperature variation was also observed for black spruce (
 <italic class="italic">Picea mariana</italic>) in the area of sympatry with white spruce in Quebec (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beaulieu et al., 2004</xref>), and it had been observed for other conifers in other parts of the world, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus patula</italic> (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saenz-Romero et al., 2011</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus pseudostrobus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saenz-Romero et al., 2012</xref>) in Mexico, where quantitative trait variation following altitude and temperature variation was observed in controlled environment tests for both species. It was also recently shown, at least for the northeastern part of the natural range of white spruce in North America, that most of adaptive genetic variation in genes significantly associated to climate was also related to temperature, with many significant linear relationships noted between allelic variation and temperature, which is mainly following a north-south latitudinal trend in this region (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hornoy et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
