<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group class="fn-group">
 <fn id="Fn1" class="fn">
  <label class="label">1</label>
  <p class="p">The circles in Fig. 
   <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref> are plotted at the midpoints of the latitude bands. There are relatively few grid boxes for some latitude bands, and higher-latitude bands with little data are excluded. Uncertainty is estimated by bootstrapping the years used at each grid box (1000 bootstrap samples are generated) and then calculating a 90 % confidence interval for the median sensitivity in each latitude band (or averaged over several latitude bands).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn2" class="fn">
  <label class="label">2</label>
  <p class="p">The model names and the exact time periods used are given in [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>]. The daily precipitation rates are first conservatively interpolated [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>] to an equal-area grid with constant spacing in longitude of 3°. Following [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>], the precipitation extremes in a given climate are calculated by aggregating daily precipitation rates (over both land and ocean and including dry days) at a given latitude and then calculating the 99.9th percentile. Calculating the change in precipitation extremes at each grid box and then taking the zonal average has been found to give similar results [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>]. The sensitivities are averaged over 10° latitude bands for presentation in Fig. 
   <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn3" class="fn">
  <label class="label">3</label>
  <p class="p">The observationally constrained estimate is obtained by regressing the sensitivity for climate change against the sensitivity for variability across the models, and then using this regression relationship together with the observed sensitivity for variability to estimate the sensitivity for climate change. The sensitivity for variability (% K
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) is calculated in both models and observations based on the 99.9th percentile of daily precipitation rates aggregated over the tropical oceans (30S to 30N) and the mean surface temperature over the tropical oceans, as described in detail in [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>]. The sensitivities for climate change are calculated in 10° latitude bands relative to the change in global-mean surface temperature, as for the other sensitivities shown in Fig. 
   <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>. Differences in convective parameterizations are less important in the extratropics, and the correlation coefficient across models between the sensitivities for climate change and variability becomes smaller for climate change at higher latitudes, reaching a value of 0.5 at 50S and 40N as compared to a maximum of 0.86 at 20N. SSM/I data from Remote Sensing Systems [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>] are used for the observed precipitation rates and NOAA MLOST data [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>] for the observed temperatures.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn4" class="fn">
  <label class="label">4</label>
  <p class="p">Percentiles are calculated including zero precipitation amounts, and the simulations have 500-m horizontal grid spacing and use the cloud microphysics scheme referred to as “Lin-hail” in [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>].
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn class="fn">
  <p class="p">This article is part of the Topical Collection on 
   <italic class="italic">Extreme Events</italic>
  </p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
