<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on national crop yields and questionnaire surveys, large differences in vulnerabilities to current climate changes were detected across Europe. In Northern Europe, the short duration for crop development and cool temperature are the major concerns, while the temperature extremes and low rainfall limits the crop productivity in Southern Europe, although the most negative effects will be found for the continental climate in the Pannonian zone, which includes Hungary, Serbia, Bulgaria, and Romania [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. It was predicted that the enhancement of greenhouse gas emissions and abrupt climatic changes will occur that may increase the crop yield in North-Western Europe and decrease the crop yield in the Mediterranean area [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Wheat production is heavily affected by the temperature extremes due to climate change in many countries, and may reduce the crop yield by 6% for each °C rise in temperature [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Drought and high temperatures are key stress factors with high impact on cereal yields [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], and 
 <italic class="italic">Rubisco</italic>, the central enzyme of photosynthesis, is disrupted if the temperature increases from 35 °C, and stops the photosynthetic process [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Gong et al. (1997) reported the negative influence of heat stress on antioxidant enzymes in 
 <italic class="italic">Zea mays</italic> [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. The combined impact of heat and drought stresses on crop yield have been examined in sorghum, maize, and barley. It was revealed that the combined effect of heat and drought stress had more damaging outcomes as compared to individual stress [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Xu and Zhou (2006) subjected the 
 <italic class="italic">Leymus Chinensis</italic> under the combined stresses of drought and heat and found that the function of Photosystem II (PSII) decreased [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. 
</p>
