<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Community and Species Distribution Modelling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic suitability was modelled for the two grassland communities that make up the LNGT, the Lowland Themeda Grassland community (GTL) and the Lowland Poa Grassland community (GPL), as well as related grassy communities, the 
  <span class="italic">Bursaria-Acacia</span> woodland and scrub community (NBA) and the Lowland Grassland Complex (GCL). An understanding of the distribution of each community, in addition to its structurally dominant species, is necessary for the practical management and conservation of a listed community under changing conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GTL and GPL were modelled separately because they are expected to respond differently to changing climate variables due to the different photosynthetic pathways employed by their structurally dominant species. 
  <span class="italic">Poa labillardierei</span> is a C3 grass, while 
  <span class="italic">Themeda triandra</span> is a C4 grass. In general, it is expected that global warming will increase the dominance of C4 grasses, which have higher water efficiency, greater drought tolerance, and greater persistence in warmer climates than C3 species [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref018">18</a>]. However, the effect of elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> and competitive interactions between C4 and C3 plants under different nutrient conditions and seasonality are not well understood [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref019">19</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref020">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Presence locations for each of the grassland communities were generated by randomly sampling 1000 points from within the existing distribution of each of the community types from the state-wide digital vegetation map, TASVEG3.0 [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref021">21</a>]. Although grasslands covered a larger extent prior to European settlement in the early 19
  <span class="sup">th</span> century, and preferential clearing may have occurred in the past on more fertile soils or areas with fewer trees, the remaining grasslands are distributed within the likely extent of the original, so sampling the current distribution is a reasonable approximation to the range of suitable climatic conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climatic suitability for the two structurally dominant grasses, 
  <span class="italic">Poa labillardierei</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Themeda triandra</span>, were modelled under current and future climate conditions to assess the extent to which the composition of the grassland communities might change under future climate conditions. Locality data for the Australian geographic extent of these species were downloaded from the online database Atlas of Living Australia (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://collections.ala.org.au/public" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://collections.ala.org.au/public</span>). After excluding spatially suspect records, there were 19,313 unique observations from the years 1770 to 2014 for 
  <span class="italic">Themeda triandra</span>, and 5,755 observations for 
  <span class="italic">Poa labillardierei</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">labillardierei</span> from the period 1853 to 2013.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Maxent model [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref022">22</a>] was used to project the distribution of climate suitable for the grassland communities and species under current and future climate conditions. Maxent is a Species Distribution Model (SDM), or climate envelope model, which uses presence only data. SDMs are based on the statistical relationship between environmental or climatic variables and the current, observed distribution of a species or community. Assuming that this relationship remains unchanged, the future distribution of the species is then projected according to future climatic conditions. Other modelling approaches are available, including Boosted Regression Trees, Generalized Linear Models and Generalized Additive Models, and ensembles of these are sometimes used to represent the range in SDM outputs [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref023">23</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref025">25</a>]. We chose Maxent because it is has been shown to perform well in comparison to several other models when there are few presence records available [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref026">26</a>]. For each model run, ten replicate Maxent runs were calculated by cross-validation and using default values for all other parameters (e.g. regularisation). Relative occurrence probabilities above 0.5 were considered suitable, following Phillips &amp; Dudík [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref027">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Choice of explanatory variables has an important influence on the outcome of species distribution models [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref028">28</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref031">31</a>]. We use models based on climate variables to project changes to the communities and species’ potential climate domain. Our results therefore indicate relative climatic suitability rather than habitat suitability. In the absence of knowledge about the specific variables which determine grassland distributions in Tasmania, we used saturated models based on the full set of thirty five commonly used bioclimatic variables and allowed Maxent to perform variable selection. Maxent has been shown to be robust to correlated variables [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref032">32</a>], and avoids over-fitting by applying a regularization penalty for each term included in the model [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref022">22</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref034">34</a>]. We used the default regularization settings, based on values determined as optimal in empirical tuning [
  <a rid="pone.0124014.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124014.ref027">27</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
