<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the MOD09A1 remote sensing data, vegetation type data, topographic data and four climatic data sets, this paper analyzes the spatial and temporal distribution patterns and trends of NDVI in the growing season of TP from 2001 to 2017. The GRA method is used to study the lag time of NDVI response to climatic factors in TP for 17 years. With the method of multiple nested time series, NDVI trends and dynamic change of NDVI response to climatic factors in seven periods are analyzed, and the main conclusions are as follows:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p>The mean NDVI in the growing season of TP in 2001–2017 is 0.49, and the spatial difference is significant. The NDVI value of vegetation generally shows a spatial distribution of increase from west to east and from south to north. The change rate from west to east is 0.13/10° E, while the change rate from south to north is 0.30/10° N.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p>During the period from 2001 to 2017, the NDVI in the growing season of TP shows a slight trend of increase, with a growth rate of +0.01/10a.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p>The results of the seven periods indicate that the area where overall NDVI value of TP shows an increasing trend is enlarging with the extension of the study period. The area where NDVI value of meadows and grasslands shows a decreasing trend is declining, and the areas with significant increase and extremely significant increase of the NDVI value in forest lands (coniferous forests and broad-leaved forests) are increasing significantly.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p>The results of lag time show that the response of the NDVI in TP to the four climate factors (air temperature, precipitation, relative humidity, and sunshine duration) varies from 2001 to 2017, and the lag of air temperature is not obvious, and the response lags behind cumulative precipitation by zero to one month, relative humidity by two months, and sunshine duration by three months. The results of the seven periods show that the NDVI of the growing season and the lag time response of air temperature, precipitation, relative humidity and sunshine duration remain basically unchanged at the existing research scale, and the vegetation response time to climatic factors has certain stability.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(5)</label>
   <p>The correlation between NDVI and climatic factors in different altitudes shows significant differences. The correlation between NDVI and air temperature in the study area is the highest (0.632) in the low-altitude area and the lowest (0.608) in the high-altitude area. The highest correlation (0.625) with precipitation is located in extremely high-altitude area and the lowest correlation (0.588) in the low-altitude area). The highest correlation (0.623) with relative humidity occurs in the low-altitude area, while the area with the lowest correlation (0.612) is located in the extremely high-altitude area. The highest correlation (0.703) with sunshine duration occurs in the low-altitude area, while the area with the lowest correlation (0.626) is located in the extremely high-altitude area. The GRD between NDVI and sunshine duration decreases with the increase of altitudes. The GRD between NDVI and precipitation increases as the altitudes rise. The change of GRD between NDVI and relative humidity is relatively stable in different altitudes. The GRD between NDVI and air temperature fluctuates with the rise of altitudes.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
