<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mathematical model we proposed, called ET30, is based on the construction of a nonlinear mathematical function (Lagrange polynomial) which allows us to estimate the average temperature values in the next years, avoiding the weather forecast with fixed point, which is very difficult to do for a short period of time (days) and practically impossible to realise for a longer period of time, such as decades [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Using this type of mathematical algorithm allows us to find a function 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>, through the interpolation of the experimental measurements, which would estimate the average temperature of each month for the year 2030, according to the climate tendency recorded in the last five decades. From a mathematical point of view, the experimental measurements are the solutions to an unknown function 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>, defined as a table function, represented by the values of air temperature, at the height of 2 m above the ground (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">January1961</sub>, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">February1962</sub>,…, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">December2013</sub>), recorded between January 1961 and December 2014, called interpolation points or interpolation nodes. The interpolation function 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic> must have the value of the unknown function 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>, in the interpolation points 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>, must be a continuous function along the period of time during which the measurements were taken (January 1961–December 2014), and must also be a Lagrange polynomial nonlinear function. Having in mind the purpose of increasing the estimation accuracy of temperatures at ground level, in the next decades, we have used the mathematical model for three sets of temperature values recorded between 1st of January 1961 and December 2014: the first set of values is represented by the average values of the air temperature, during the day, calculated with the arithmetic mean of the values recorded in a day, the second set of values is represented by the average of monthly temperatures, calculated with the arithmetic mean of the values recorded in a month, during the daytime, and the last set of values is represented by the average of temperatures recorded during five consecutive years, for the same month. We have proposed this estimation method with the purpose of reducing the daily fluctuations. In order to see the reliability of the model, it was tested for the years 1991 and 1992, by having built a model, in the same way as was previously presented, for the values recorded between 1st of January 1961 and 31st December 1990 and another model for estimating the values for the years 2011, 2012, and 2013, using the values recorded between 1st of January 1961 and 31st December 2010. The program sequences of model ET30 were calculated using the programming language FORTRAN, the data processing being done using the OringiPro.
</p>
