<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We hypothesized that short-term local manipulative experiments and large-scale observational studies identify different responses of soil nutrients to changes in climatic conditions. These differences may be due to the manner in which the entire ecosystem responds to rapid (i.e. days to months, e.g. drought) 
 <italic class="italic">vs</italic>. slow (i.e. centuries to thousands of years, e.g. changes in aridity) climatic changes. The properties of ecosystems thus often respond in a simultaneous and predictive manner to slow changes in climate (e.g. plant cover, diversity, soil properties and nutrient pools), but rapid climatic changes will likely disrupt the simultaneous responses of these slowly changing processes to climate change. For example, a change in water supply in manipulative precipitation experiments in local environments (e.g. similar plant species, plant cover, or soil type) could directly influence the balance between nutrient uptake/leaching 
 <italic class="italic">vs</italic>. mineralization/decomposition, particularly in arid ecosystems (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ansley et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Davidson et al., 2004</xref>). In contrast, and in addition to precipitation, abiotic factors (such as temperature and soil age and taxonomy) and vegetation co-vary simultaneously along a precipitation gradient. For example, increases in aridity across a gradient often lead to reductions in the diversity and cover of vascular plants, rates of litter decomposition, and availability of C and N (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Delgado-Baquerizo et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jiao et al., 2016</xref>), all of which co-evolve over millennia (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ehrenfeld et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lambers et al., 2009</xref>). All these co-varying factors likely affect the processes involved in the cycling and storage of soil C, N, and P. We thus posit that short-term local manipulative experiments could provide useful information for predicting shifts in soil processes in response to rapid changes in climate (from years to decades, e.g. drought), such as those we are facing today. In contrast, observational studies might provide unique information for understanding the response of soil processes to long-term changes in climate (from centuries to thousands of years, e.g. increases in aridity [
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Huang et al., 2015</xref>]).
</p>
