<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several papers in the issue highlight the development of genetic resources that will unleash significant untapped potential for genetic improvement. The development of effective phenotyping and breeding approaches is a challenge for the less-well studied grain legumes in particular. Modern breeding efforts to improve yield, disease resistance and quality are constrained by a low level of genetic diversity in breeding programmes. Large genetic diversity exists in seeds of grain legumes held in gene banks, but these are not fully used in active breeding programmes. 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowling 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2017)
 </xref> explore the concept of evolving gene banks, applying optimal contribution selection to manage long‐term genetic gain and genetic diversity in pre-breeding populations. They simulated pre-breeding using a founder population based on crosses between elite crop varieties and exotic lines of field pea, subjecting the population to 30 cycles of recurrent selection for an index comprising four economically important traits. They conclude that optimal contribution selection provides the control necessary to actively improve evolving gene banks for economic traits, while maintaining high levels of genetic diversity. This revolutionary plant breeding system will allow breeders to access valuable genes that have been lost through modern breeding programmes. The plant breeding method described by Cowling 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> captures valuable genes from wild relatives and moves them into the breeding programme by crossing the genetically diverse exotic lines with elite lines, creating evolving gene banks. The new rapid-cycle plant breeding method will have long-term benefits for all plant breeders, and could help to adapt and develop climate-ready crops, but the immediate challenge is to validate the results in commercial pulse crops.
</p>
