<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Flowering time sensitivity to June temperatures varied dramatically among the 23 Nunavut Arctic plant species and intraspecifically across different parts of Nunavut. Intraspecifically, flowering time sensitivity was greater in the Arctic Archipelago than on the Nunavut mainland and similarly Baffin Island plants were more sensitive than their conspecifics on Ellesmere Island. The intraspecific variation in temperature sensitivity could be indicative of adaptation to different climatic conditions across Nunavut and smaller temperature changes in colder location having a relatively larger temperature sensitivity due to lower growing degree days required to flower at colder locations (Panchen &amp; Gorelick, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Parmesan, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Prevéy et al., In Press). The diverse intraspecific flowering time sensitivity to temperature in different parts of Nunavut and the variation in warming trends in different parts of Nunavut (Tables 
 <xref rid="ece32702-tbl-0004" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">4</xref>, S2 and Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32702-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>) suggests that there could be greater changes in some parts of Nunavut than in others. From the warming trend and temperature sensitivity analysis conducted here, the greatest and most immediate changes are likely to be seen in the south and west, i.e., Nunavut mainland and Victoria Island, with Victoria Island likely to see the greatest changes because of the greater temperature sensitivity on the Nunavut archipelago than the Nunavut mainland. The least changes could be seen on Baffin Island; however, this could be counterbalanced by the apparent greater flowering time temperature sensitivity of Baffin Island plants. As the Arctic climate warms, the variation in flowering and fruiting time sensitivity to temperature among species and intraspecifically has implications for Arctic ecological communities, including altered community composition, competition, and pollinator interactions (Callaghan, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; CaraDonna, Iler, &amp; Inouye, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ellebjerg et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Euskirchen, Carman, &amp; McGuire, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Hegland, Nielsen, Lázaro, Bjerknes, &amp; Totland, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Høye, Post, Schmidt, Trøjelsgaard, &amp; Forchhammer, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; McKinney et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Molau, Nordenhäll, &amp; Eriksen, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Parmesan, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Rathcke &amp; Lacey, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1985</xref>).
</p>
