<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Different species are known to have different flowering time temperature sensitivity, and, thus, variation among species is to be expected (Calinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Hart et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Kimball, Davis, Weihrauch, Murray, &amp; Rancourt, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ledneva, Miller‐Rushing, Primack, &amp; Imbres, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Mazer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Miller‐Rushing &amp; Primack, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Panchen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Parmesan, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). However, the magnitude of the variation is surprisingly high in contrast to other studies (Oberbauer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Wolkovich et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) but not unprecedented (Olsson &amp; Ågren, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Wagner &amp; Simons, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Future research could expand on this study to include a larger number of species in order to compare flowering time sensitivity to temperature across life history strategies (Calinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Molau et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Post et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Seed dispersal time of the 20 Arctic species also appears to be sensitive to temperature, in contrast to experimental warming studies (Bjorkman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Jones et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>) but in alignment with faster fruit maturation at Zackenberg, Greenland experimental warming sites (Ellebjerg et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Only two species, 
 <italic class="italic">Androsace septentrionalis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Chamerion latifolium</italic>, showed no flowering time sensitivity to June temperatures in any part of Nunavut. 
 <italic class="italic">A. septentrionalis</italic> is an annual, or more often biennial in Nunavut, that must complete its life cycle within the year and whose time of flowering is influenced primarily by snow melt date (Inouye et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">A. septentrionalis</italic> also showed no significant trend to earlier flowering in an alpine community (CaraDonna et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The late‐summer flowering 
 <italic class="italic">C. latifolium</italic> also showed no sensitivity to July or August mean temperatures (data not shown), suggesting that its flowering time may be triggered by day‐length. The two species with the greatest variation in time of flowering, 
 <italic class="italic">Saxifraga oppositifolia</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ranunculus nivalis</italic>, are either early‐flowering and/or snow bed species, groups of species that have been identified by a long‐term phenology study in Sweden to be most labile in terms of flowering time (Molau et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Arctic species’ sequence of flowering is consistent from year to year in Nunavut from 1896 to 2015 and is comparable to the current day (Molau et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Panchen &amp; Gorelick, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32702-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>a). Hence, herbarium specimens can be used to determine species’ sequence of flowering.
</p>
