<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pixel basis, least-squares linear regression of annual information from SST, CHL, and the eastern and northern components of water speed was used for deriving the significance of temporal trends (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) and its magnitudes (slopes; that is, annual changes in target features) over the past three decades (fig. S1). CHL data were sourced online as annual composites, whereas data on SST and marine currents were obtained on a monthly basis and averaged yearly to generate a linear relationship to extract slopes. This calculation was repeated for every pixel of the globe. These magnitudes were combined to obtain our spatially explicit Cumulative Impact Index. Different layers were first resampled following a bilinear interpolation procedure to match the spatial resolution of the coarsest SST product (that is, 1° grid). Absolute values for the slopes of obtained trends (a proxy to the magnitude of environmental changes) were then standardized to the maximum value to make all variables comparable. These relative values [ranging from 0 (no change) to 1 (maximum recorded change)] were subsequently added on a pixel basis and standardized again to the maximum value. In this way, we obtained a dimensionless index ranging from 0 (no change) to 1 (maximum change), thereby providing information about spatial heterogeneity in the magnitude of environmental changes and highlighting those marine areas that have undergone the largest changes in their environmental conditions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used information on the global distribution of 2183 species of vertebrates composed of 1729 fish, 124 marine mammals, and 330 seabirds to derive spatially explicit information on species richness (number of species) and to identify hot spots of marine biodiversity. The worldwide distribution of species was sourced online from the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.iucnredlist.org/</span>) and BirdLife International (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.birdlife.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.birdlife.org</span>) as ESRI (Environmental Systems Research Institute) supported geodatabases, including spatial information on species-specific occurrences (presence/absence). Occurrence shapefiles were transformed to 0.5° dichotomous grid features, with “1” denoting presence and “0” indicating absences. Obtained grid features for different fish, marine mammal, and seabird species were added to obtain three maps indicating the number of species per group occurring in each pixel. Each map was standardized by the total number of species per group to obtain a relative measure of the spatial distribution of fish, marine mammal, and seabird species richness. These relative values were subsequently added on a pixel basis and standardized again to the maximum value to obtain a dimensionless index ranging from 0 (absence of species) to 1 (maximum species richness), providing information about the spatial heterogeneity in species richness and highlighting hot spots of marine biodiversity without biases toward those groups (for example, fish) with a larger number of species (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). We considered hot spots of marine biodiversity to be those marine areas enclosing pixels with values of species richness over the upper 95th percentile, which was a threshold that identified relatively small and compact marine areas of special concern within the main ocean basins (that is, Pacific Ocean, Indian Ocean, and Atlantic Ocean; fig. S3).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we evaluated changes in landings of fish over the last 60 years to look for temporal trends in the exploitation of marine resources. Further, we identified those countries that have contributed the most to fishing captures in general and at the derived hot spots of marine diversity during the last decade in particular. Long-term information (1950–2013) on marine fishing captures (in metric tons) was sourced from FAO using the FishStatJ software. Captures were restricted to marine fish (1149 species) and grouped per year, country, and MFA (according to FAO categories). Least-squares linear regressions of annual information on fish landing were used for deriving the temporal trend per country and MFA (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
