<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Climate change will affect mean weather, such as rainfall amounts and temperature. In addition to changing average conditions, it may also increase variability and extremes (eg, more intense rainfall events). The latter is probably of most consequence for human health. Although globally, interannual temperature has not increased in variability,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> there is evidence of regional changes in extremes,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> as both the mean climate and climate variability shift in response to anthropogenic forcings (Figure 
 <xref rid="epi412359-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). These shifts in weather will be moderated by local environmental conditions and human adaptation, leading to changes in three broad categories of exposure that have the potential to influence health. The first are direct effects such as the influence of a heatwave upon mortality.
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref> The second are indirect exposures such as changing weather altering the growing season and distribution of plants, affecting pollen production, which in turn impacts on allergic disease
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>; other examples include changing weather patterns affecting mosquito breeding and life cycles, leading to changes in malaria and dengue fever (see below).
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref> Changes in temperature and humidity alter the geography of vector‐borne diseases, by shifting vector breeding sites
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> and altering the transmission windows of vector‐borne diseases.
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> In many cases, more data are needed to characterize the relationships between vector, pathogen, and climate.
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref> Third, climate change may act through economic and social disruption, for example, leading to mental health effects from extreme events such as flooding
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref> or influencing global crop yields leading to increased hunger.
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref> Flooding, whether coastal, fluvial, or pluvial, carries direct risks of drowning
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref> as well as a range of health risks in the aftermath of the event, including the spread of water‐borne diseases,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref> and the spread of microbial contaminants in buildings.
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref> The risk of exacerbating existing medical conditions, through disrupted access to medicines and medical facilities, is also a concern.
</p>
