<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The lack of agreement regarding the status of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peltata</italic> throughout the region is problematic in terms of control strategies (PIER, 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Dodd and Hayes 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Manual control is difficult given its predominantly vegetative mode of reproduction since root fragments re‐sprout and stem fragments readily take root (Paynter et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Chemical control using glyphosate has proved to be effective against 
 <italic class="italic">M. peltata</italic> in forestry plantations in some countries like the Solomon Islands (Miller 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1982</xref>). Biological control has been proposed although the controversial issue of its native/invasive status in the Pacific region has complicated matters (Dovey et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Dodd and Hayes 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Native weed species have an important ecological role and reduction of these species could have a destabilizing impact on ecosystems. Thus, in the case of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peltata</italic> it would be prudent to undertake further research to ascertain its status to assess the suitability of biological control. It is also important that any control strategies for 
 <italic class="italic">M. peltata</italic> are underpinned by information describing its potential distribution. Climate change will add to the complications of managing such a species because changes in climate may lead to shifts in the climatic limits that usually constrain its range (Taylor et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31915-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012a</xref>). An estimate of how the potential range of 
 <italic class="italic">M. peltata</italic> is likely to shift under climate change would contribute to an understanding of the potential impact of the species in the Pacific region.
</p>
