<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Datasets</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were collected from the local Rivelin population of long-tailed tits during 1995–2011, including first egg dates for 824 nests (559 first nesting attempts and 265 renests) and failure dates for 590 nests (410 first attempts and 180 renests). Data from 2001 were omitted from all analyses because access to the field site was limited by an outbreak of foot and mouth disease, and data from 2003 were excluded in analyses regarding the timing of renesting and termination of breeding due to limited search effort for renests at the very end of the field season in that year. Weather data were obtained for the period 1968–2011 from the Weston Park Meteorological Station, located 5 km from the center of the Rivelin study site. Monthly mean temperature and monthly total precipitation were calculated. These data were very strongly correlated with UK Climate Projections (UKCP) interpolated data (available until 2006, Jenkins et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">2008</a>) for the 5 km × 5 km grid cell containing the study site (Pearson's correlations with 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 11; May precipitation: 
  <span class="italic">rp</span> = 0.84; all other comparisons: 
  <span class="italic">rp</span> &gt; 0.96). Food abundance data were also collected at four locations, from a total of 16 trees, within the Rivelin study site by collecting caterpillar frass samples throughout the spring for the period 2009–2012, as caterpillars are the primary food source of long-tailed tits provisioning nestlings. We hence calculated the annual date of peak caterpillar abundance, and assessed the association between peak date and spring weather variables to test the hypothesis that food abundance declines earlier in years with warmer spring temperatures (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Appendix S1</a> for full methods).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">National data were obtained for the period 1968–2010 from the British Trust for Ornithology's (BTO) Nest Record Scheme (NRS; Crick et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2003</a>). These nest records include an unknown proportion of first nesting attempts and renests, from various locations throughout the U.K. (mainly England) excluding the Rivelin Valley area. The mean annual lay date was calculated across all records within each year (mean annual sample size = 50; range = 18–123). For weather data, we used Central England Temperature from the HadCET database (Parker et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">1992</a>), as used in previous analyses of climatic influences on lay dates using nest record card data (Crick et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">1997</a>; Crick and Sparks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">1999</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
