<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mechanisms of phenological change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climatic model of local long-tailed tit phenology explains the majority (65%) of the temporal variation in the population's mean lay date, with March temperature being the most important driver. Earlier breeding in years with warm March temperatures is likely to be driven largely by the alleviation of energetic and resource constraints; this topic has received copious attention in the literature and we therefore do not discuss it further here (e.g., Crick and Sparks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">1999</a>; Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">2002</a>; Schaper et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">2011</a>; Vatka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">2011</a>). We have also presented rare evidence that the termination of breeding is highly sensitive to temperature, with breeding ending earlier in years with warm April temperatures (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>C). One plausible mechanism for this is an influence of April temperature on food availability. Caterpillars are the dominant component of long-tailed tit chick diets (Cramp and Perrins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">1993</a>; P. Gullett, pers. obs.) and the optimum nestling food source in terms of nutrition and energetic value (Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">2006</a>; García-Navas and Sanz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">2011</a>). Given that temporally matching breeding with the peak in caterpillar abundance benefits productivity and survival in ecologically similar species (van Noordwijk et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">1995</a>; Thomas et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">2001</a>), we hypothesized that the timing of the seasonal decline in caterpillar availability may be an important determinant of the timing of breeding termination. Our limited data suggest that caterpillar abundance at the study site peaked earlier in years with warmer April temperature, but showed no relationship with March temperature. April temperature thus seems to have a similar influence on the timing of peak caterpillar abundance at our study site to that reported in other UK woodlands, in which peak frass biomass advances by 8.5 days per 1°C increase in spring temperature (Smith et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">2011</a>). Applying this relationship with our study site, in which April temperatures have increased by 1.9°C over the course of this study, indicates that if long-tailed tits track caterpillar phenology there should be a 17-day advance in breeding termination. This predicted advance in termination date is remarkably close to the observed advance of 16 days. It thus seems likely that earlier peaks in caterpillar abundance in years with warm Aprils contribute to the earlier termination of long-tailed tit breeding in these years. Earlier seasonal decline in caterpillar availability in warm years is thought to contribute to a decline in double brooding of great tits (Husby et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">2009</a>), and earlier gonadal regression in warmer years caused earlier cessation of breeding in an aviary study of starlings 
  <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span> (Dawson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">2005</a>). There is thus mounting evidence that climate change is driving an advance in the timing of breeding termination in numerous species, and further study into the mechanisms behind this should be a priority for research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate explained half the variation in breeding season length in our study population, primarily due to increased duration in years with warm February and March temperatures and shortening in years with warm Aprils. The effect of February temperature was unexpected given that February temperature was not closely associated with the timing of first breeding attempts. This pattern could partly arise because February and March temperatures are positively correlated, but the tolerance levels were sufficiently low to justify including both variables in the analysis. We consider it likely that warmer conditions in the prebreeding period may enhance parental body condition through reducing energetic expenditure for thermoregulation and food acquisition (e.g., Crick and Sparks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">1999</a>; Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">2002</a>; Schaper et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">2011</a>; Vatka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">2011</a>), enabling prolonged investment in energetically demanding reproductive behavior.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we found no evidence for a trend in the timing or intensity of nest predation in this species, and the breeding phenology was not associated with either predation parameter. In this study predation patterns are not a primary driver of breeding phenology, but species in different ecosystems or locations could be more susceptible to changing predation patterns (Adamik and Král 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">2008</a>) and predation effects should therefore be taken into account in phenological monitoring schemes.
 </p>
</sec>
