<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mechanisms of phenological change: climate, predation, food, adaptation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the study site, long-tailed tit pairs typically start nest-building in February/March and egg laying in March/April; renesting attempts occur between March and May and pairs finish breeding by early June (MacColl and Hatchwell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">2002</a>). Therefore, to investigate the effects of climate on reproductive phenology we modeled: (a) initiation date in response to temperature and precipitation during February, March, and April; (b) renesting date in response to temperature and precipitation during March, April, and May, and the timing and intensity of predation; (c) termination index in response to temperature and precipitation during March, April, and May, and the timing and intensity of predation; and (d) breeding season length in response to temperature and precipitation during February, March, April, and May, and the timing and intensity of predation. We constructed multiple linear regression models with normal error structure (Shapiro–Wilk normality tests: 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.3 for all response variables). We used an information-theoretic approach to model selection in which all possible models were constructed given the set of predictors; model fit was assessed using Akaike's Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AICc) and model averaging was conducted over the 95% confidence set of models (Burnham and Anderson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">2002</a>). Collinearity between climatic predictors was within the tolerance levels to which Information Theoretic methods are robust (Variance Inflation Factor &lt;3.9 for all variables; Freckleton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">2010</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Table S2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to test the hypothesis that the timing of breeding termination is influenced by the seasonal decline in caterpillar availability, we estimated the timing of peak caterpillar abundance in the Rivelin study site for the period 2009–2012, and determined the correlation between annual peak date and mean temperature during March and April. Full methods are described in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Appendix S1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we tested the hypothesis that local genetic adaptation may contribute to the observed changes in breeding phenology in the study population, because selection may act on the focal phenological traits (initiation and termination). Following the results of the climatic analysis, we modeled initiation date in response to March temperature and termination index in response to April temperature, comparing models in which year was included as an additive or interactive effect, in order to assess whether the observed temperature-phenology reaction norms have changed significantly over time. Such a temporal change in reaction norms would be compatible with the hypothesis that selection is driving evolutionary change in the form of phenological responses.</p>
</sec>
