<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation indices</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The timing and intensity of nest predation may influence the timing of renesting and termination, and consequently breeding season length (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>D). We therefore calculated two measures of predation timing to test for trends in predation patterns: (i) the annual time of predation, as the median date of all nest predation events; (ii) the annual time of predation of first nesting attempts, as the median date of predation events of first nesting attempts; these two indices of predation timing were highly correlated (
  <span class="italic">rp</span>
  <sub>14</sub> = 0.96, 
  <span class="italic">P &lt;</span> 0.0001) and we used the former index in subsequent analyses as it offered a more complete picture of predation timing. We also calculated two indices of predation intensity: (i) annual proportion of nests predated, which was the annual proportion of nests predated among nests known to have been predated or fledged; (ii) annual Mayfield predation estimate, which was the annual Mayfield estimate of predation risk throughout the nesting cycle; these two indices of predation intensity were highly correlated (
  <span class="italic">rp</span>
  <sub>14</sub> = 0.98, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.0001) and we used the latter in subsequent analyses because it offers a more comprehensive measure of predation rates (Mayfield 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">1975</a>). Annual Mayfield estimates were calculated via a three-part process: (i) we calculated daily nest survival rates at the egg laying, incubation, and chick-rearing stages using the Mayfield method (Mayfield 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">1975</a>); (ii) we used these daily survival rates to calculate the probability of a nest surviving the entire duration of each stage by raising the daily rates to the power of the stage duration in days, assuming stage durations of 9 days for egg laying, 15 days for incubation, and 16 days for chick rearing (the typical durations of these stages in the focal population; Hatchwell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">2004</a>); (iii) we calculated annual nest predation risk as the product of the three annual stage-specific survival probabilities, subtracted from one.
 </p>
</sec>
