<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predicting phenology at larger spatial and temporal scales</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The form of bivariate relationships between long-tailed tit phenology and March temperature during 1995–2010 at the local scale (β = −2.94; 95% confidence intervals −4.29 to −1.58) was similar to that at the national scale (β = −3.62; 95% CIs −4.94 to −2.31). Moreover, predictions of national mean lay date from 1968 to 2010, derived from the climatic (March temperature) model of the local Rivelin population's phenological response during 1995–2011, were strongly correlated with the observed values of the national population's mean lay date (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001; 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>40</sub> = 0.678), and the slope of the relationship between predicted and observed values was very close to unity (β = 1.17; 95% CIs 0.76–1.57; Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig05" href="#fig05">5</a>). Predictive capacity was still high when using the local phenology model to predict national phenology in years entirely outside the range of years during which local data were collected, that is, from 1968 to 1994 (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001; 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>25</sub> = 0.629), and the slope between predicted and observed values in this period was lower, but again not significantly different from unity (β = 0.76; 95% CIs 0.37–1.14; Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig05" href="#fig05">5</a>). Predictive capacity does not deteriorate over time (linear model of the squared difference between predicted and observed values, regressed against year: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,40</sub> = 1.48, 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.04, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.23; quadratic model: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>2,39</sub> = 0.88, 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.04, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.42), although, the extent of advance in mean lay dates tends to be under predicted from the March temperature model in recent years (1995–2011; Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig05" href="#fig05">5</a>). The range of March temperatures used when constructing the local model (1995–2011: 3.80–8.6°C) was similar to the range of March temperatures experienced by the national population over both time periods (1968–2010: 3.3–8.4 °C; 1968–1994: 3.3–8.3°C). The residuals of the relationship between observed and predicted national annual mean lay dates were not associated with temperature (1968–2010: 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.05, 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>40</sub> &lt; 0.0001; 1968–1994: 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.05, 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>25</sub> &lt; 0.0001).
 </p>
 <div id="fig05" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Predictions of national average lay date derived from the local climatic model (average lay date in response to March temperature), compared with observed national average lay dates, 1968–2010 (filled circles: 1968–1994; open circles: 1995–2010). Observed and predicted dates are strongly correlated (solid line: 
    <span class="italic">r</span>
    <sub>40</sub> = 0.68; 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001), and the slope of this relationship is close to unity (1.17 ± 0.20); dashed lines represent 95% confidence intervals. Predictive capacity is similar when restricting prediction to those years that were not represented in the local model (i.e., 1968–1994; filled circles; 
    <span class="italic">r</span>
    <sub>25</sub> = 0.63; 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001). Day one represents 1 March.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ece30003-1864-f5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
