<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scaling up from local to national, short-term to long-term</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The local and national models of lay date as a function of March temperature are statistically indistinguishable, and the locally derived phenology model performs reasonably well in predicting previous mean lay dates at the national scale. We thereby show that intensive local studies that capture a broad range of phenological responses can provide useful inference at much larger spatial scales. Such spatial extrapolation is likely to be crucial for developing broad-scale predictive capacity in the face of climate change, because the inherent patchiness of phenological data at national and regional scales mean that such broad-scale data offer limited ability to detect patterns such as the divergent trends in breeding initiation and termination. It is important to note that there are inevitably limits to such spatial extrapolations, particularly in species with broad geographic ranges, such as the long-tailed tit. Applying local models to areas experiencing markedly different annual weather regimes would clearly be inappropriate, and multiple local studies in areas of contrasting climates are thus required in order to develop predictions across the species' large geographic range. However, this study shows that local studies can be used to develop accurate phenological predictions at much broader spatial scales within regions experiencing similar climatic regimes. Given the key role of phenology in determining species' responses to climate change (Miller-Rushing et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">2010</a>), this is an essential first step towards the goal of developing mechanistic models of species' responses to future climate change (Diez et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, the local model's predictive capacity was upheld when applied to a much longer and non-overlapping time period than that used to construct the model, and predictive capacity did not decrease further back in time or at higher temperatures. This indicates that temporal extrapolation from relatively short-term studies (17 years in this case) is possible. Much caution is needed when make predictions outside the range of climatic conditions experienced during the reference study. This is not a major issue in our study, however, as the range of climatic conditions used in the local model encompasses most of the predicted range of future climatic conditions across the U.K. over the next 60 years under a high carbon emissions scenario (March: used in model 3.8–8.6°C, predicted 6–9°C; April: used in model 7.7–12.3°C, predicted 7–12°C; Jenkins et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">2008</a>). Although the increasing discrepancy between historic and future climatic variables further into the future will make longer-term predictions tricky, our analysis strongly suggests that data from intensive local studies can be used to predict future phenological shifts over time scales of several decades.
 </p>
</sec>
