<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study system</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We studied a population of 25–72 pairs (mean 46 pairs) of long-tailed tits in the Rivelin Valley, Sheffield, U.K. (53°23′N, 1°34′W). Long-tailed tits are single brooded, but nest predation rates are high and pairs that fail frequently initiate a second or third renest attempt if there is sufficient time to raise a brood. Renests thus account for around 32% of nests per year (range = 0.26–0.40), and the proportion of renesting showed no temporal trend over the course of the study (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1,13</sub> = 0.05, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.43). The long-tailed tit is a facultative cooperative breeder and some failed breeders help other pairs rather than renesting themselves, particularly if they fail later in the season (MacColl and Hatchwell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">2002</a>; Hatchwell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">2004</a>). At least 95% of adult birds in the study site are uniquely marked with color-rings each breeding season and all pairs within the study site are monitored and their nests located by observation. A very small proportion (estimated to be &lt;5%) of nesting attempts are not found each year, but through monitoring parental activity it is known that the vast majority of these are short-lived attempts that rapidly fail (Sharp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">2008</a>). Nests are monitored approximately every 2 days. In the case of nest failure, the study site is searched intensively for renesting attempts. The date on which the first egg of each clutch is laid (hereafter referred to as first egg date) is recorded so that day 1 corresponds to 1 March, and is accurate to within 1 day for all accessible nests. Inaccessible nests comprise approximately 10% of the data, and their first egg date is estimated by observing the time at which parents stop lining nests, which typically occurs when laying starts, and/or by recording the date when females commence incubation (the last day of egg laying) and assuming a clutch of 10 eggs (the modal clutch size in the study population; Hatchwell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">2004</a>). Observations of nestling provisioning and fledging dates suggest that these lay dates for inaccessible nests are generally accurate to ± 2 days.
 </p>
</sec>
