<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here we deviate somewhat from orthodox Bayesian practice. A typical Bayesian approach would assume a distributional form for the discrepancy vector 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>
 <bold class="bold">
  <italic class="italic">ε</italic>
 </bold>
 <sub class="sub">
  <bold class="bold">
   <italic class="italic">D</italic>
  </bold>
 </sub>. However, because this error is likely long-term dependent, and the probability distributions for its components are not necessarily normal, finding and justifying a proper parametric model for it is non-trivial. To deal with this conundrum, we adopt an approach inspired by prior work [
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. We postulate that model error can be derived from inter-model trend differences. The reasoning for this implementation is as follows. Imagine a particular trend submodel 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">T</italic>,
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> represents the “true” system. Associated with this system is trend 
 <bold class="bold">
  <italic class="italic">x</italic>
 </bold>
 <sub class="sub">
  <bold class="bold">
   <italic class="italic">i</italic>
  </bold>
 </sub> and pseudo-observations 
 <bold class="bold">
  <inline-formula id="pone.0214535.e011" class="inline-formula">
   <alternatives class="alternatives">
    <graphic xlink:href="pone.0214535.e011.jpg" id="pone.0214535.e011g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <math id="M11" class="math">
     <msubsup class="msubsup">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">x</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">i</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">'</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msubsup>
    </math>
   </alternatives>
  </inline-formula>
 </bold>. If only the rest of the models are available to the researcher, then the best-fit model 
 <italic class="italic">j</italic> to these pseudo-observations is associated with trend 
 <bold class="bold">
  <italic class="italic">x</italic>
 </bold>
 <sub class="sub">
  <bold class="bold">
   <italic class="italic">j</italic>
  </bold>
 </sub>. The difference between the best model and the pseudo-observed trends is then the unscaled error of the 
 <italic class="italic">j</italic>th model. Thus, we obtain samples for unscaled discrepancy 
 <bold class="bold">
  <italic class="italic">ε</italic>
 </bold>
 <sub class="sub">
  <bold class="bold">
   <italic class="italic">D</italic>
  </bold>
 </sub> directly from the differences between each model’s trend and the next-closest model trend (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] for details). We acknowledge that this parameterization is simplified; model error is an emergent research topic [
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. We thus hope this work can galvanize more research on parametrizing model error.
</p>
