<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Ecological niche models (ENMs) were estimated based on the maximum entropy algorithm implemented in Maxent 3.3.3k [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. We first used the jackknifing function in Maxent to identify the most important set of environmental variables. We used SDMTools in ArcGIS 10.3 to remove variables with high inter-variable correlations. In the end, we used 6 variables for analysis: (1) annual mean temperature, (2) mean diurnal temperature range, (3) isothermality, (4) annual temperature range, (5) annual precipitation, and (6) precipitation seasonality. Associations between presence points and environmental variables [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] were used to reconstruct the ecological niche of 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic>. We hypothesized an accessible area (
 <bold class="bold">M</bold> in the BAM diagram framework) [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] that included all of Europe, North Africa, and parts of the Middle East but excluded western Asia for lack of data documenting 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic> occurrence in this region. We used Maxent’s bootstrap function to create 10 replicate analyses. We used a partial receiver operating characteristic (pROC) [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] to test model robustness via Niche Toolbox (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://shiny.conabio.gob.mx:3838/nichetoolb2/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://shiny.conabio.gob.mx:3838/nichetoolb2/</ext-link>); the 5 testing subsets of the occurrence data were used to test model predictions. For further evaluation of our predictions regarding the occurrence of 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic>, we used a set of 3186 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic> records discarded during the early phases of data filtering of the original dataset. We excluded those records used in model calibration; we used a one-tailed cumulative binomial probability test to assess the probability of obtaining the observed level of correct predictions by chance alone given the background expectation of correct predictions determined by the proportional coverage of the study area by regions of predicted suitability.
</p>
