<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To summarize the model results for present-day conditions, we calculated the median of the medians from the predictions based on the 5 subsets of occurrences as an estimate of the current geographic distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic>. For future conditions, we calculated medians across all single-GCM median model outputs (5 subsets of occurrences x 17 GCMs = 85 combinations), as an estimate of the potential distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic> under each corresponding RCP. For present-day conditions, an uncertainty index was derived from the range (maximum—minimum) of predictions from 5 Maxent runs (i.e. 5 combinations based on the 5 subsets of occurrence records), which summarizes uncertainty deriving from the particular availability of occurrence data. For the future conditions, an uncertainty index of future model predictions was calculated as the range across all combinations of GCMs and occurrence subsets (within each RCP; 5 subsets of occurrences x 17 GCMs = 85 combinations) [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], thereby including uncertainty deriving both from the availability of occurrence data and variation among GCMs in future climates anticipated. To avoid known problems with model overfitting [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], we thresholded models using a fixed allowable omission error rate of 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic> = 5% [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>], assuming that 5% of the occurrence data may have included errors that misrepresented environmental values. This thresholding approach omitted the 5% of records with the lowest suitability to account for the reality that such large datasets often include some errors (either in the occurrence data or the environmental data), so this 5% trimming allows those errors to be ignored and not affect the results.
</p>
