<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An Added Blanket of Aerosol Over South Asia during El Niño</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations from the CALIPSO satellite of scattering ratio at 532 nm, a proxy for mixing ratio in the atmosphere, reveal the presence of the elevated layer of aerosol over South Asia during July-August of 2015 and 2016 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a,b</a>). During the El Niño period of July–August 2015, this aerosol layer appears thicker and centered over the entire North Indian monsoon region (15–45°N, 60–120°E), in contrast to the non El Niño period of July–August 2016, when the layer is extended mostly over the Arabian Peninsula (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a,b</a>) and less thicker over the monsoon region. The ECHAM6–HAMMOZ simulations reproduce the general observed ATAL features (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c,d</a>), although they overestimate the scattering ratio at 550 nm by 0.06–0.11 (details in section 5.4). Importantly, the model simulates the thicker ATAL during the monsoon season of 2015 associated with El Niño conditions over the Pacific. Time series
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> of CALIPSO scattering ratio at 532 nm (SR@532 nm) averaged over the Asian region (15–45°N, 5–105°E) at 15, 16 and 17 km also peak during the summer of 2009, another El Niño year. However, the 2009 northern hemisphere summer UTLS was also influenced by volcanic aerosols from the Sarychev eruption (Kuril Islands, Russia) in June 2009
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. While it is difficult to separate volcanic aerosols from ATAL using satellite observations, the use of models allows us to understand the distinct role of ATAL during El Niño years by removing the influence of volcanoes (i.e. the contribution of this eruption on UTLS aerosols is not included in the model). Overall, our model simulations capture the general behavior of the ATAL and the influence of El Niño on its loading and geographic distribution, but have the tendency to overestimate its thickness.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Mean Scattering Ratio (SR) averaged for 15–18 km and for the month of July–August. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) CALIOP observations for 2015 (El Nino year) and, (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) CALIOP observations for 2016 (normal year). (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) ECHAM5-HAMMOZ simulation (aeronAMIP) for 2015. (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) ECHAM5-HAMMOZ simulation (aeronAMIP) for 2016. (Figure created using the MATLAB software).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46704_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e446" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Asian monsoon region exhibits strong convergence from the nearby deserts, the East Asian land mass and adjacent oceans. This makes the monsoon region a preferred destination for many different aerosol species including desert dust, industrial emissions (e.g. sulfate) and local carbonaceous components
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Micro pulse lidar at Visakhapatnam and boundary layer lidar observations at Gadanki and Tirupati in India also show elevated aerosol in the lower troposphere (2–5 km) during the monsoon season due to transport from West Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. The monsoon convection can lift these Asian boundary layer aerosols and trace gases to the UTLS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Due to the reduced rain and associated scavenging, the aerosol loading over the Indo-Gangetic Plain and North India is anomalously high during El Niño
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Irrespective of the weak upward motion over South Asia, the aerosol loading becomes deeper due to the anomalous inflow of the East Asian aerosols towards the monsoon region which are transported to the upper troposphere over Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Distribution of seasonal mean (July–September) TOMS aerosols index, aerosol optical depth from MISR and ECHAM5-HAMMOZ model simulation. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) TOMS aerosols index for the non El Niño years during 1978–2005. 
     <span class="bold">(b</span>) TOMS aerosols index averaged during strong El Niño years considered in this study (1982, 1991, 1994, 1997, 2002, 2004, 2009 and 2015). Aerosol optical depth from MISR for 
     <span class="bold">(c</span>) non El Niño years during 2000–2013, 
     <span class="bold">(d</span>) strong El Niño years (2002, 2004, 2009). Distribution of simulated aerosol optical depth (excluding sea salt) at 550 nm as obtained from (
     <span class="bold">e</span>) aeronCL, (
     <span class="bold">f</span>) aeronEL experiments. In Fig. (
     <span class="bold">a–e</span>) the region of elevated aerosol is indicated by the black ellipsoid. (Figure created using the COLA/GrADS software).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46704_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e515" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We utilize the ECHAM5-HAMMOZ state-of-the-art aerosol-chemistry-climate model (see Methods and experiment details in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) in order to understand the formation and possible impact of this elevated aerosol over the Indian monsoon region. Our model simulations show the aerosol layer (ATAL) during the monsoon season over South Asia (23–40°E) and its anomalous enhancement during recent El Niño events (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a–c</a>). The higher aerosol loading in the ATAL (greater aerosol extinction by 3E-4 km
  <span class="sup">−1</span> to 5E-4 km
  <span class="sup">−1</span> near 100 hPa) strengthens the layer over the entire North-Indian belt, which is mainly governed by the vertical transport of aerosols from East Asia (~110–120°E). Model simulations for the El Niño years 2009 and 2015 also show higher aerosol loading (3E-4 km
  <span class="sup">−1</span> to 5E-4 km
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) in the ATAL (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1a,b</a>). This enhancement during the monsoons season of El Niño years 2009 and 2015 is also evident in the scattering ratio over North India and Tibetan Plateau (70–100°E, 25–35°N) from CALIOP and model simulation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Despite the influence of the Sarychev volcanic plume entrained on the periphery of the monsoon anticyclone, the air inside the anticyclone over North India remained relatively isolated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, with the peak observed on CALIOP measurements during the summer 2009 mainly reflecting the influence of El Niño. It has to be mentioned here that the excess aerosol loading in ATAL is visible in the years with a persistent El Niño condition throughout the summer monsoon season (JJAS). The year 2014 was likewise an El Niño year with considerable precipitation deficiency in June and July associated with the warm Pacific SST anomaly, which eventually turns out to be less-deficit/moderate-excess in the following months (August/September) accompanied with the decrease warming in Pacific SST
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Due to the changes in the circulation pattern, especially in the second half of the season, the aerosol uplifting from the east Asian region becomes relatively weak (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>), resulting in smaller aerosol extinction values in 2014 compared to 2015 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Details of experiments conducted in the present study.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Sr No.</th>
      <th>Name of the Experiment</th>
      <th>Sea surface temperature (sst)</th>
      <th>Period of simulations</th>
      <th>Aerosol switched on/off</th>
      <th>Experiment description</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>aeroffCL</td>
      <td>Climatological SST</td>
      <td>Ensemble since 21May 31May 2003</td>
      <td>off</td>
      <td>Passively transported aerosol (aero-off)- with Climatological SST</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>aeronCL</td>
      <td>Climatological SST</td>
      <td>Ensemble since 21May 31May 2003</td>
      <td>On</td>
      <td>Interactive aerosols (aero-on) with Climatological SST</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>aeroffEL</td>
      <td>Canonical El Niño type SST (Fadnavis 
       <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2017)
      </td>
      <td>Ensemble since 21May 31May 2003</td>
      <td>off</td>
      <td>Passively transported aerosol (aero-off) with El Niño SST</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>aeronEL</td>
      <td>Canonical El Niño type SST (Fadnavis 
       <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2017)
      </td>
      <td>Ensemble since 21May 31May 2003</td>
      <td>on</td>
      <td>Interactive aerosols (aero-on) with El Niño SST</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>aeronAMIP</td>
      <td>Monthly varying AMIP SST</td>
      <td>January 2005-December 2016</td>
      <td>on</td>
      <td>Interactive aerosols with monthly varying AMIP SST and forced with meteorology</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>aeroffAMIP</td>
      <td>Monthly varying AMIP SST</td>
      <td>January 2005-December 2016</td>
      <td>off</td>
      <td>Passively transported aerosol (aero-off) with monthly varying AMIP SST and forced with meteorology</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Distribution of seasonal mean (July–September) aerosol extinction (1E-4 km
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) zonal cross section (23–40°N) from ECHAM5-HAMMOZ model simulations (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) aeronCL, (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) aeronEL, (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) difference between aeronEL and aeronCL, (
     <span class="bold">d</span>–
     <span class="bold">f</span>) same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">c</span>) but for black carbon aerosols (ng•m
     <span class="sup">−3</span>), (
     <span class="bold">g–</span>i) same as (
     <span class="bold">a–c</span>) but for sulfate aerosols (ng•m
     <span class="sup">−3</span>). Wind vectors in (
     <span class="bold">d–f,i</span>) are obtained from model simulations. The vertical velocity field has been scaled by 300 m•s
     <span class="sup">−1</span> (Figure created using the COLA/GrADS software).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46704_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e768" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Time series of Scattering Ratio (SR) averaged for 15–18 km over the Indo-Gangetic plain and Tibetan Plateau region (25–35°N, 70–100°E) from the ECHAM5-HAMMOZ aeronAMIP simulation (black) and CALIOP (red). (Figure created using the Origin (OriginLab, Northampton, MA)).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46704_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e777" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During El Niño, a robust vertical ascent is visible over East Asia, which can lift boundary layer pollutants from East Asia into the UTLS region (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). These pollutants are further transported to South Asia from East Asia. At the same time, the ascent over 90–100°E further promotes the vertical transport from South Asia along with the strong ascent over East Asia (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">b</a>). Increased aerosols in the El Niño simulations (aeronEL) clearly show the strong ascent over East Asia (~110–120°E in the troposphere; and 90–100°E in the upper troposphere 500–150 hPa) (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">d</a>). The strong ascent along with the rising branch of circulation from East Asia further enriches the aerosols in the UTLS over South Asia and therefore promoting the enhanced subsidence over Indian region (70–90°E).
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aircraft, balloon sonde measurements and model simulations suggest that the aerosols in the ATAL is composed of organic carbon, black carbon, nitrate and sulfate aerosols
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Lofting of black carbon aerosols (mostly absorbing) from North India and East China accumulates during El Niño, while sulfate aerosols (mostly scattering) are transported from East-Asia (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d–i</a>). Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> illustrates how the aerosol enters the ATAL mainly from East Asia during El Niño. The black carbon and sulfate aerosol loadings are large during El Niño over the southern slopes of the Himalayas and Tibetan Plateau (TP) (85°E–100°E) (1000–300 hPa), and in the ATAL (130–70 hPa).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a> shows the percentage increase of each type of aerosol in the troposphere (1000–300 hPa) and in the UTLS (300–70 hPa) during El Niño. The enhancement of sulfate, dust, and organic carbon aerosols in the UTLS thickens and widens the ATAL over the South Asian region. Additionally, the higher amounts of sulfate aerosols in the UTLS can significantly cool the surface by scattering incoming solar radiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a> illustrates the aerosol-induced reduction in solar radiation at the surface during El Niño (aeronEL - aeronCL), with simulated values of −5 to −20 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> over northern India (70–90°E; 25–35°N). While this effect is caused by the aerosol enhancement during El Niño in the free troposphere and UTLS, there is also a considerable contribution from UTLS aerosol changes alone. Using dedicated model experiments, we quantify the effect on solar radiation at the surface due to aerosol changes during El Niño (aeronEL-aeronCL) in both these regions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c,d</a>). The presence of higher aerosol in the UTLS during El Niño leads to a reduction in solar radiation at the surface over Asia, with a minimum of −0.25 mWm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> over the Bay of Bengal. The tropospheric aerosol changes during El Niño, lead to surface solar radiation increases (0.25 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) over the Arabian Sea, north India, and the northern part of East Asia and decreases (−0.25 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) over the Indian peninsula, Bay of Bengal and the southern part of East Asia. The inhibition of surface solar radiation by the aerosol layer during El Niño has a cooling effect at the surface. The model simulations show an associated surface cooling of 1.5 K to 2 K at most locations except the desert regions of west-Asia and Mongolia (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5e</a>), therefore increasing the stability of the troposphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5f</a>). It should be mentioned that, in addition to the role of the enhanced aerosol layer quantified here, other El Niño induced changes in the UTLS region (i.e. changes in, distribution of greenhouse gases like water vapour, ozone or methane)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> will also have important associated radiative effects. By contrasting two sensitivity simulations (aeroffEL-aeroffCL), we find that the change in UTLS gases (for 52 gas phase species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>) also reduces surface solar radiation (−5 to −15 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) over North India, comparable to the effect of aerosols (−10 to −20 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b,g</a>). Using offline radiative calculations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, we estimate that the increase in UTLS ozone, methane and water vapour during El Niño (aeronEL-aeronCL) leads to mean regional (20–40°N, 75–85°E) surface solar radiation changes of −0.6 to −1.1 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>. This suggests that the changes in gases in the UTLS will contribute alongside the aerosol-induced radiative effects at the surface (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5h</a>). Also, the combined heating rates changes from aerosols and gases produce significant cooling in the mid-upper troposphere over North India and Tibetan Plateau region (20–35°N) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5i</a>), which promote subsidence over this region.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Percentage increase in UTLS (300–70 hPa) and troposphere (1000–300 hPa) aerosols during El Niño at a location in the ATAL (30°N, 90°E). (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) aerosol induced simulated changes in solar surface solar radiation (W•m
     <span class="sup">−2</span>) (aeronEL-aeronCL). Simulated changes in surface solar radiation (mW.m
     <span class="sup">−2</span>) due to aerosols in (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) the UTLS (300–70 hPa) (aeronEL-aeronCL), and (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) for the troposphere (1000–300 hPa) (aeronEL-aeronCL). (
     <span class="bold">e</span>) aerosol-induced anomalies in surface temperature (K) (aeronEL-aeronCL), (
     <span class="bold">f</span>) aerosol induced anomalies of Brunt Väisäla frequency (1E-5 sec
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) during El Niño (aeronEL-aeroffEL) (ave:20–35°N). Simulated changes in surface radiation (W•m
     <span class="sup">−2</span>) due to (
     <span class="bold">g</span>) all 52 gas phase species in ECHAM (aeroffEL-aeroffCL), (
     <span class="bold">h</span>) UTLS methane, water vapour and ozone in the offline model. (
     <span class="bold">i</span>) Net heating rates (ave: 20–35°N) from aerosols and gases (52 gas phase species) in ECHAM model simulations (K•day
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) (aeroffEL-aeroffCL). (Figure created using the COLA/GrADS software).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46704_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e935" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aerosol layer and intensifying monsoon droughts</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The El Niño itself leads to a decrease in rainfall over India (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6a</a>), with a suppressed rainfall during the summer season estimated at 2 to 6 mm•day
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The inclusion of aerosols (aeronEL-aeronCL) amplifies decrease in rainfall by 17% over the central India (10–25°N, 70–85°E). We estimate (aeronAMIP-aeroffAMIP experiments) that the aerosol loading in 2009 and 2015 has induced a rainfall deficit of 1–7 mm•day
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (i.e. ~14%) over the central India (Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4a,b</a>). The combined effect of El Niño and the increased aerosol loading leads to a rainfall deficit of approximately 4 to 12 mm•day
   <span class="sup">−1</span> over India (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6b</a>). A schematic depicting aerosol distribution in the ATAL during normal and co-occurring El Niño simulation is shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6c,d</a>.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Seasonal mean (July - September) precipitation anomalies (mm•day
      <span class="sup">−1</span>) obtained from (
      <span class="bold">a</span>) aeroffEL-aeroffCL simulation, indicating reduced rainfall during El Niño than climatology when no aerosols were introduced, (
      <span class="bold">b</span>) aeronEL-aeronCL simulation, indicating reduced rainfall during El Niño relative to climatology when aerosols were introduced. Comparison of 
      <span class="bold">a,b</span> indicates that aerosols have increased the scarcity of drought in El Niño simulation. A schematic depicts aerosol distribution in the ATAL during (
      <span class="bold">c</span>) normal and (
      <span class="bold">d</span>) co-occurring El Niño simulation. Vertical transport of sulfate aerosols from East Asian during El Niño is shown in (
      <span class="bold">d</span>). (
      <span class="bold">a,b</span> created using the COLA/GrADS software and 
      <span class="bold">c,d</span>) plotted using NCL and 3D effect and schematic designs created using Adobe illustrator).
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46704_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e999" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This combined effect produces an aggravated subsidence over the Indian region compared to the individual effect of El Niño. The effect of aerosols weakens the zonal winds and enhances the anomalous subsidence over the monsoon region from the meridional overturning circulation over 15–30°N (Figs 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>, 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5a,b</a>). The upper tropospheric temperature has a significant role in driving the monsoon circulation from the ocean to the sub-continent
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span>. The strong cooling during El Niño (Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5c</a>) is further intensified by the presence of the aerosols (Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5d</a>). This weakens the zonal inflow from the ocean, reducing the strength of a feeble monsoon Hadley circulation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span>, which in turn leads to an anomalous large-scale subsidence and suppresses the convection, therefore enhancing the severity of droughts
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span>. The anomalous cooling over North India and TP is a consequence of the enhanced aerosol loading over the South Asian upper troposphere. While the general overestimation of UTLS aerosols in our model suggests that the impact on the severity of droughts is likely smaller than estimated here, this might be balanced by the additional contribution from nitrate aerosols
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span> (not simulated here).
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We attribute the increase of drought severity to the following mechanism:
   <div list-type="order" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par15">The El Niño induced atmospheric circulation lifts the boundary layer aerosol from East Asia to the UTLS and then to West Asia into the ATAL region.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par16">The added blanket of aerosol reduces the solar insolation, cooling the upper troposphere over the Tibetan Plateau and surface over North India.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par17">The resulting enhanced stability leads to a weakening of the monsoon Hadley circulation.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par18">The anomalous large-scale subsidence results in amplifying the severity of monsoon droughts.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par19">There are additional radiative impacts from changes in UTLS gases also contributing to the increase in monsoon droughts severity.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
