<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The century-long systematic monitoring of Indian monsoon records reveals that frequent floods and droughts were not unfamiliar to this nation of 1.3 billion people. Statistical analysis shows that in the second half of the twentieth century the frequency of droughts has increased relative to the first half
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. A number of studies attribute droughts to El Niño effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, which modify the Walker and Hadley large-scale circulations through atmospheric tele-connections. The existing literature shows that most of the Indian droughts are accompanied by El-Niños
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. In addition to the increasing frequency of droughts, South Asia underwent a widespread declining trend in its total seasonal monsoon precipitation (~7% from 1951 to the present). This is largely blamed on the anthropogenic aerosols as they generally reduce temperatures over land, resulting in weaker land-sea thermal contrast
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. The land-sea thermal contrast is the essential force required to pull the monsoon circulation from ocean to land. Aerosols interact in many ways with the monsoon - the enhancement or suppression of the Indian summer monsoon rainfall depends on its duration and scale (including remote influences), along with its distinct direct and indirect radiative effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to this conventional understanding, the presence of the recently discovered aerosol layer in the upper troposphere and lower stratosphere (UTLS) known as “the Asian Tropopause Aerosol Layer (ATAL)” covering South Asia (defined here as the region spanning 0–100°E, 20–45°N) during the monsoon season
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> may have a role in controlling the monsoon precipitation. The development of the ATAL is associated with convective transport of aerosols from the lower atmosphere to the UTLS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Observations from satellites (CALIPSO, SAGE-II), balloon-borne experiments (BATAL)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, (StratoClim)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, and CARIBIC aircraft (Civil Aircraft for the Regular Investigation of the atmosphere Based on an Instrument Container – Lufthansa, Airbus 340–600) reveal that the ATAL extends over the 12–18 km range and is possibly composed by sulfate aerosols along with black-carbon, organic aerosols, nitrates and dust particles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. The unprecedented growth in Asian aerosol emissions during the past few decades, mainly from China and India, is therefore expected to exacerbate this phenomenon
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Indian emissions have an important contribution to the ATAL due to the vicinity of the centre of Asian monsoon convective updraft
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. This region shows a higher growth in sulfate aerosol compared to China
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> leading to a pronounced contribution to the ATAL composition. These sulfate aerosols significantly alter the radiative balance of the atmosphere by reflecting incoming solar radiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> back to space. CALIPSO and SAGE-II observations show a positive trend (+0.004 over the period 1996–2014) in UTLS aerosol optical depth during summer which causes a regional radiative forcing of around −0.1 W•m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> over that 18 year period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. A previous study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> has indicated the presence of large amounts of fine dust particles and carbonaceous aerosols in the upper troposphere in early monsoon season.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fire-generated aerosol is also commonly observed over Asia during summer months
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, often associated with El Niño events, which promote forest fires over many parts of the globe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. For example, widespread forest and peatland fires over maritime southeast Asia in September 2015 released large amounts of aerosols and carbon emissions (carbon monooxide, carbon dioxide, methane)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. The smoke lifted by the monsoon circulation and trapped in the anti-cyclone
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> also alters the regional chemical budget and the associated radiative forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. This usually large contribution from natural sources can mask some of the contribution from anthropogenic aerosol.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, using satellite observations and model simulations, we explore for the first time the contribution of anomalously high aerosol loadings over the UTLS region during El Niño in worsening drought conditions over the Indian subcontinent.</p>
</sec>
