<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations and reanalysis data</div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aerosol distribution during the monsoon season is studied from three different satellites (1) Aerosol Index from Total Ozone Mapping Spectrometer (TOMS) for July-September during the period 1979–2005 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://disc.gsfc.nasa.gov/datasets/TOMSEPL3_V008/summary" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://disc.gsfc.nasa.gov/datasets/TOMSEPL3_V008/summary</span>), (2) Aerosol Optical Depth (AOD) from Multi-Angle Imaging Spectroradiometer (MISR)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span> for July-September during the period 2000–2013 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://misr.jpl.nasa.gov/getData/accessData/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://misr.jpl.nasa.gov/getData/accessData/</span>), (3) CALIOP Scattering Ratio (SR) for July - August during June 2006–December 2015 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://eosweb.larc.nasa.gov/project/calipso/calipso_table" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://eosweb.larc.nasa.gov/project/calipso/calipso_table</span>). The TOMS detects aerosols over bright targets (e.g. deserts), while MISR provides aerosol information over the oceans and land
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. TOMS aerosol index data during 1979–2005 comprises measurements from two different instruments Nimbus-7 (Nov 1978–May 1993) and Earth Probe (July 1996–2005). The TOMS AI data after 2001 is not recommended for trend analysis due to calibration issues associated with sensor degradation (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://daac.gsfc.nasa.gov/guides/GSFC/guide/tomsl3" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://daac.gsfc.nasa.gov/guides/GSFC/guide/tomsl3</span> dataset.gd.shtml)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. However, this data is considered in the current study since the focus is to study the seasonal variation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CALIOP lidar makes range-resolved measurements of elastic backscatter at 532 and 1064 nm and of linear depolarization ratios at 532 nm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>. In this study, we analyse CALIOP lidar measurements of total backscatter at 532 nm and depolarization ratios at 532 nm. Due to the low signal-to-noise ratio of the CALIOP signal in the UTLS, a specific treatment of the level 1 data was developed to infer backscatter profiles from the upper troposphere to 40 km
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. This technique uses a depolarization ratio threshold of 5% to remove clouds, horizontal averaging of ~100 km to increase SNR and is similar to what has been previously published
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. It reveals the presence of the ATAL during every summer Asian monsoon period, even in the absence of a volcanic eruption, confirming earlier results
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. This is also verified by the stratospheric aerosol product developed by the CALIPSO team
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. The ATAL has also been detected by the Stratospheric Aerosol and Gas Experiment (SAGE) II data between the late 90’s to 2005
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. The stratospheric aerosol product dataset is now publically
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span> available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://eosweb.larc.nasa.gov/project/calipso/stratospheric_table" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://eosweb.larc.nasa.gov/project/calipso/stratospheric_table</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used zonal and meridional wind data from National Center for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) reanalysis, available for the period 1948–2009
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span> the rainfall data from GPCP (Global Precipitation Climatology Project) for the period 1979–2015 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/data.gpcp.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/data.gpcp.html</span>) and TRMM_3B42 (version 7) rainfall estimate for the period 1997–2016 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pmm.nasa.gov/data-access/downloads/trmm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pmm.nasa.gov/data-access/downloads/trmm</span>). In this study, we have considered only strong El Niño years 1957, 1965, 1967, 1972, 1977, 1982, 1991, 1994, 1997, 2002, 2004, 2009 and 2015 when the amplitude of the SST anomalies in either eastern or central tropical Pacific exceed one standard deviation. Also, the Niño-3 index must be more than the threshold value (&gt;0.5) from June to September. In our analysis, we considered monsoon season of the co-occurring El Niño year since lead-lag correlations between all Indian summer monsoon rainfall and Niño-3 index exhibits a maximum negative correlation for zero lag year (details are documented previously)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>
 </p>
</sec>
