<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">We address this gap by performing a large-scale meta-analysis strictly based on randomised controlled field trials, measuring factual changes in behaviour. The behaviours targeted are essential to mitigate climate change and include household and individual behaviours directly relevant to the production of greenhouse gases emissions. The six included behaviours are as follows. First, energy consumption in the home: within this category we examined interventions that targeted electricity or gas demand, purchase of energy-efficient appliances or consumption of renewable energy. Second, transportation: this category includes the analysis of air travel, private car use, or alternative options such as walking, cycling, or use of public transportation. Changes in both energy and transportation behaviours are deemed critical to achieve reductions in CO
 <sub>2</sub> emissions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Third, consumption of animal products: interventions targeting reduced consumption or avoidance of meat and dairy products. Recent estimates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> highlight that, particularly in developed countries, eating fewer animal products has a high potential for carbon emissions reduction. Fourth, food waste: interventions aiming to reduce the frequency or amount of food wasted. Food waste is a vastly overlooked driver of climate change. The Food and Agriculture Organisation (FAO) quantified the food wastage in terms of carbon footprint and concluded that the contribution of food wastage emissions to global warming is almost equivalent (87%) to global road transport emissions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Fifth, water consumption: interventions targeting the quantity of water consumed including, for instance, time in shower or laundry frequency. Household actions that consume the largest amounts of water (showers and dishes/clothes washing) are also actions that consume large amounts of energy, and thus saving water saves energy (US Department of Energy)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Sixth, recycling
 <italic>:</italic> includes both the reuse of natural resources, recycling of plastic, paper or cans. Recycling contributes to reducing emissions from resource extraction, landfill methane and waste incineration (US Environmental Protection Agency [EPA])
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
