<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We hypothesize that there are regions where present‐day mean water availability, as simulated by global climate models, is among the factors influencing future changes in P – ET. To discuss reasons that support this hypothesis, let us start by considering a drying region, that is, where simulations from different models generally project a decrease in P – ET. Under this condition, our expectation is that those simulations with lower P – ET in the present period (hereafter referred to as drier reference state) are more likely to project a smaller decrease in P – ET (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl58462-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>a). The underlying argument is that simulations with a drier reference state have less drying potential because ET over land can normally not exceed P on multidecadal timescales (Greve et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Kumar et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Padrón et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), and because ET rates are reduced when soil moisture conditions are low (Koster &amp; Suarez, 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Seneviratne et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Let us now consider wetting regions, that is, where simulations project an increase in P – ET for the future. It is possible that the differences causing some simulations to have higher P – ET than others in the present will remain in the future. This can lead to a stronger increase in P – ET for simulations with a wetter reference state, for example, due to processes related to the intensification of the hydrological cycle under global warming (e.g., Held &amp; Soden, 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Finally, we note that there are several examples of other bounded variables with an influence of the present‐day state on future projections, such as Arctic ice extent (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Massonnet et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), runoff (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), and carbon storage (Mystakidis et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58462-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
