<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Minimal heat abatement involves a covered structure such as an open barn or shed, which shields animals from incoming radiation while providing natural ventilation, plus ample access to clean, cool water. In Florida, shaded cows experienced 6% to 10% higher milk production, and lower rectal temperatures and respiration rates than their non-shaded counterparts [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. The Minimal heat abatement can be easily implemented and is economical in many locations [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Moderate abatement incorporates forced ventilation (fan systems or tunnel-ventilation) into housing structures to increase convective heat loss through improved air movement and exchange [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Tunnel ventilation is implemented by running large exhaust fans at high flow rates at one endwall of a barn, thereby creating longitudinal air movement along the barn. Moderate abatement was shown in New York and Ohio to lower indoor ambient temperature by 0.4°C relative to natural ventilation [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Holstein dairy cows experienced 50% slower rectal temperature rise and 14 breaths/min slower respiratory rate in northern Israel under moderate abatement relative to natural ventilation [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. High heat abatement introduces water sprinkling to increase the cooling effect of forced ventilation. Studies conducted at different locations and under variable environmental conditions generally showed that High heat abatement yielded more comfortable environmental conditions for cows and increased milk production as compared to unmitigated, outside conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. In Florida, Bucklin et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] observed a ~6-unit lower THI under High heat abatement as compared to outdoor THI. In Missouri, Igono et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] found that milk production under High heat abatement was 2 kg/cow greater than in shade conditions. Milk production during summer 1988 was 15.9% greater in Kentucky under high heat abatement relative to shading alone [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Intense heat abatement involves air conditioning or high pressure evaporative cooling and adoption is generally inhibited by high capital expense [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. A study conducted by Hahn and Osburn [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>] indicated that U.S. southern regions (West, Southwest, South, Ohio Valley, and Southeast) would be the most economically suitable areas for intense heat abatement. Previous studies demonstrated the efficiency of Intense heat abatement. In Thailand, Khongdee et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] found that evaporative cooling decreased THI levels by 3 units relative to no evaporative cooling, and that the physiological impacts of heat stress on Thai Friesian crossbred cows raised under evaporative cooling were generally dampened, leading to 1 kg/cow/day greater milk production. In northern Mississippi, Smith et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] found that mean peak daytime barn THI under Intensive cooling was ~3 units lower relative to Moderate or High heat abatement. Smith et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] found that Holstein dairy cows had 3 to 5 kg/cow/day greater milk yield under Intense cooling than under High heat cooling. Holstein cows raised in a hot and dry climate condition (Saudi Arabia) under Intense heat abatement had improved pregnancy rates compared to those raised under High heat abatement (35% vs. 23%), and greater milk production (0.98 kg /cow/day) [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Collier et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214665.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] found that Intense heat abatement improved barn environmental conditions and cow physiological functions (respiration rate, rectal temperature) in arid environments, but its effects depend on system design (fans quantity, position, and speed; rate of misting water injection).
</p>
