<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">The species occurrence data was collected from Global Biodiversity Information Facility database
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup> (GBIF, available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.gbif.org</ext-link>, accessed 25 February 2018), Centre for Agriculture and Bioscience International
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup> (CABI, available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cabi.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.cabi.org/</ext-link>, accessed 25 February 2018) supplemented with several recent field and herbarium records collected by the authors. All the records were thoroughly checked for accuracy before use. A total of 133,096 occurrence points were initially recorded. As the occurrence records are often biased towards geographically convenient or environmental-friendly areas such as near cities or areas with high population density
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup>, this results in the sampling bias in geographic space. Thus, spatial thinning was undertaken to remove the spatial autocorrelation and sampling bias, where in grid cells of 10 × 10 km were created and a single occurrence point was selected randomly from each cell with more than one occurrence points. After filtering, a total of 9,046 points retained, which comprised of the native European and Asia Temperate (Armenia) range (7,659 points) and the introduced regions in Asia (49 points), Africa (15 points), Australia (33 points), Oceania (83 points), Northern America (1190) and Southern America (17 points). The native and introduced regions were delineated according to biogeographical distribution scheme followed by the USDA-Germplasm Resource Information Network
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>
 </sup> (GRIN, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://npgsweb.ars-grin.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://npgsweb.ars-grin.gov</ext-link>, accessed 27 February 2018).
</p>
