<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We also explore to what extent future climate change impacts may be lessened by whales shifting their distribution to better align with changing prey distributions. A separate set of equations were used in Model 2 to account for the relative favourability of environmental conditions encountered for whales based on the sea‐ice outputs of the coupled climate–NPZD model. Rather than explicitly modelling individual whale movement, we used a probability distribution function for whale species and each time step (although it was held constant over the historical period to 2012) to describe the relationship between whale distribution and sea‐ice extent and thickness. In the first instance, parameters of this relationship were estimated using 
 <math id="nlm-math-60">
  <msubsup>
   <mi>ν</mi>
   <mrow>
    <mi>L</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>j</mi>
    <mo>,</mo>
    <mi>A</mi>
   </mrow>
  </msubsup>
 </math>. A gamma distribution was derived for each historical whale species distribution from this information, and shape and rate parameters were estimated with respect to latitude. We assumed changes in sea ice affected relative favourability of environmental conditions encountered by whales, with modifications to the alpha shape parameter shifting each whale distribution north or south according to corresponding increases or decreases in sea ice (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). We used relative changes in sea‐ice thickness 
 <math id="nlm-math-61">
  <msub>
   <mi>i</mi>
   <mi>y</mi>
  </msub>
 </math>as the multiplier so that each whale distribution at each Latitude 
 <italic>L</italic> changes relative to those corresponding to starting or base ice conditions (
 <math id="nlm-math-62">
  <msub>
   <mi>i</mi>
   <mn>2012</mn>
  </msub>
 </math>). We held whale distributions prior to 2012 constant. Although the direction of change can be predicted with some certainty (see Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), its extent remains uncertain and hence our approach provides an illustrative approximation only, but could be validated with fine‐scale data on the distribution of whales with respect to sea ice.
</p>
