<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33629-sec-0014" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the following datasets were rescaled to a 5‐km resolution using ArcGIS 10.3.1 (ESRI, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0017">2015</a>). A presence–absence dataset of the worldwide distribution of the Little Owl was provided by the IUCN (2 × 2 km original resolution; BirdLife International &amp; NatureServe, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0007">2014</a>; Figure 
  <a rid="ece33629-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33629-fig-0001">1</a>). A dataset containing long‐term average climatic data for a number of climatic factors was included (original resolution 0.93 × 0.93 km at the Equator, average values for the years 1950–2000; Hijmans, Cameron, Parra, Jones, &amp; Jarvis, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0028">2005</a>). The climatic parameters included were annual mean temperature (BIO1, ͦ C*10), temperature seasonality (BIO4, defined as the standard deviation*100), minimum temperature of the coldest quarter (BIO11, C*10), annual precipitation (BIO12, mm, log transformed), and precipitation of the wettest month (BIO13, mm, log transformed). Altitude was also included (ALT, m above sea level). Different habitat types were included as follows: forest (FOR), arable land (ARA), urban and industrial areas (URB), permanent crops and pastures (including orchards; PCR), mixed agricultural areas (MAG), water bodies (WAT), sparse vegetation (SVE), and grassland (GRA; CORINE data, 250 × 250 m original resolution; European Environment Agency, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0018">2013</a>; Table 
  <a rid="ece33629-sup-0007" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece33629-sup-0007">S3</a> and Fig. 
  <a rid="ece33629-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece33629-sup-0001">S1</a>). The Human Footprint, featuring information on human population pressure, human land use and infrastructure, and human access (including roads), was also taken into account (original resolution 1 × 1 km; Sanderson et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0058">2002</a>; Wildlife Conservation Society—WCS and Center for International Earth Science Information Network—CIESIN—Columbia University, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0070">2002</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33629-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>European distribution map of the Little Owl 
    <span class="italic">Athene noctua</span> used on the RAMAS simulations. Gray is present, white is absent. Within Europe, the Little Owl is native to all but Great Britain, where it has been introduced
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-7-10987-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
