<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33629-sec-0028" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic viability</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PVA in VORTEX suggested that not all populations in Europe are likely to remain extant and retain 99% of the initial genetic variability over the next 100 years. The Balkan population was genetically viable, as were the Spanish and the Italian populations. The Portuguese and Danish populations were not viable in the long run.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The northern European population is estimated to count a maximum of 118,000 individuals. The population is therefore vulnerable to losing a significant amount of genetic diversity. A part of the northern population has already been investigated for loss of genetic diversity, namely the Danish population. A low historic genetic variability was found, and an even lower genetic variability was found in the population at present (Pertoldi et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0050">2012</a>). Further, PVA on the Danish population predicts it to perish within the near future (Andersen et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0004">2015</a>). An increased mortality level decreased the stochastic growth rate by approximately a factor 10. It would thus be very useful to determine the actual mortality rate of the Portuguese population, in order to determine the actual state of the population. The Portuguese population is at present considered to be stable but fluctuating in size (BirdLife International, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0006">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the Balkan population counts 24,000–65,000 individuals, the population can be considered genetically viable. The Balkan population consists of the Cypriote population of 4,000–10,000 individuals, the Greek population of 5,000–15,000 individuals, and the Romanian population of 15,000–40,000 individuals (BirdLife International, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0006">2015</a>). Even if considering the low population estimates, both the Romanian and the Greek populations are likely to maintain their genetic diversity if managed as demographically independent populations. The Cypriote population, however, might not in itself be considered a genetically viable management unit if counting only 4,000 individuals. Being an island population located approximately 75 km from mainland Europe, the Cypriote population is effectively isolated from the mainland population. Nevertheless, as the population has survived on the island for centuries, long‐term genetic drift is not likely to pose a great threat to the population. The Italian populations can be considered genetically viable independently of each other and be managed as separate demographic units without risking the loss of a significant amount of genetic diversity. The Spanish population can be considered both genetically viable and demographically independent concerning population management. The MVP(K)s presented here are in line with the MVP(K) found for 28 species of birds, averaging 6,667 individuals (Reed, O'Grady, Brook, Ballou, &amp; Frankham, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0054">2003</a>). Reed et al. (
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0054">2003</a>), however, did not consider genetic viability but only extinction risk and defined MVP as the minimum K that would decrease the risk of extinction below 1%. A study on Harbor Seals 
  <span class="italic">Phoca vitulina</span> found the MVP(K) required to maintain 95% genetic diversity to be 75 individuals, while 200 individuals are required to maintain 99% genetic diversity (Olsen et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0044">2014</a>). They found that 1,000 individuals are required to ensure a 1% or less risk of extinction.
 </p>
</sec>
