<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33629-sec-0029" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat suitability</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both climatic factors and landscape structure affected the large‐scale distribution of the Little Owl. This result conforms well to population studies that have found that the reproductive output of Little Owls is limited by excessive rainfall, which may relate to decreased availability of large insects in the breeding season (Bultot et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0011">2001</a>; Nieuwenhuyse et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0043">2008</a>; Tome et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0067">2008</a>). Buildup urban areas have also previously been found to correlate positively with the presence of Little Owl, although only when the buildup areas were at a low intensity (Nieuwenhuyse &amp; Bekaert, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0042">2002</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Little Owl is associated with the agricultural landscape. Surprisingly, either arable land, mixed agriculture, or permanent crops had a significant influence on the spatial distribution of the Little Owl on a European scale. Previous studies found that both orchards and meadows had a positive influence on the presence of Little Owl (Nieuwenhuyse &amp; Bekaert, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0042">2002</a>; Nieuwenhuyse et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0043">2008</a>; Zabala et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0071">2006</a>). Increasing tree cover did on the other hand affect the Little Owl negatively, which also conforms well with several investigations showing that Little Owls avoid forested areas (Gottschalk et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0026">2011</a>; Nieuwenhuyse et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0043">2008</a>; Sunde, Thorup, Jacobsen, &amp; Rahbek, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0063">2014</a>), possibly because of increased predation risk from other raptorial birds such as Tawny Owls (
  <span class="italic">Strix aluco</span>; Michel, Jiménez‐Franco, Naef‐Daenzer, &amp; Grüebler, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0038">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The predictive power of the GLM was relatively low, which resulted in a habitat suitability model that did not register the nuance in the highly suitable areas. This might be related to the large scale and large range at which the regression model was built. It could also be due to the scale at which the Little Owl is registered is larger than Little Owl home range. A study on Eurasian Eagle Owls, 
  <span class="italic">Bubo bubo,</span> examined the distribution of the owl on three spatial scales (Martínez, Serrano, &amp; Zuberogoitia, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0036">2003</a>). A GLM was built for each scale, and Martínez et al. (
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0036">2003</a>) found that their models were best at predicting the presence/absence of the Eurasian Eagle Owl at home range scale and below. The model build at landscape scale only accounted for 25.97% of the deviance in the distribution. The Eurasian Eagle Owl depended more on small‐scale features such as nesting and feeding grounds than on landscape ecology (Martínez et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0036">2003</a>). This could be the case for the Little Owl as well. As an obligate cavity breeder, the Little Owl can only settle in areas where nesting cavities are present. At a large scale, it was not possible to include the presence of nesting cavities in the analysis. A study of habitat preference of the Little Owl and the Long‐eared Owl 
  <span class="italic">Asio otus</span> in Spain also looked at different scales (Martínez &amp; Zuberogoitia, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0037">2004</a>). Again, the presence of both species was best described at the nest‐site or home range scale, whereas the landscape scale model had the least predictive power. The presence of Little Owl was especially correlated with arid plantations, which is where the Little Owl primarily finds nesting cavities in this area (Martínez &amp; Zuberogoitia, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0037">2004</a>), further confirming that Little Owl distribution might be closely linked to features on a home range scale rather than landscape scale. Throughout its range, the Little Owl is found within different habitat types (Nieuwenhuyse et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0043">2008</a>). The incidence that the Little Owl prefers different habitat types with different areas of the study range might also explain the low explanatory power of the model, and it would be interesting to see if the analysis performed better on a smaller part of the range.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only little over 20% of the variation in Little Owl distribution could be explained by the GLM on a macroscale using landscape and climatic factors. This might be because habitat preference of owl species is best described at a home range scale within a smaller geographical range (Martínez &amp; Zuberogoitia, 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0037">2004</a>; Martínez et al., 
  <a rid="ece33629-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33629-bib-0036">2003</a>). Thus, when wanting to describe habitat preference and to further manage and conserve owls, it is important to look at a smaller scale and range. The macroscale approach did not catch important parts of the landscape features important to the Little Owl; therefore, it is advisable to work at a microscopic landscape scale.
 </p>
</sec>
