<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We also note that some limited‐area studies show highly nonlinear yield changes with, for example, very steep declines at high daily temperatures for U.S. maize, soy, and cotton (Schlenker &amp; Roberts, 
 <xref rid="eft2497-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Data are unavailable for other crops or regions, so this cannot be incorporated here but indicates that the linearity of the meta‐analysis (Challinor et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2497-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) may be oversimplified. It is possible, however, that a linear response to annual average temperatures may capture probabilistic increase in short‐term extremes, as these may follow longer‐term averages. Similarly, studies have suggested that responses to minimum and maximum daily temperatures are opposite for rice, and though the use of mean temperature in the meta‐analysis presumably captures the average of these changes if daily extremes were to be substantially different from prior studies (e.g., under a future climate scenario), the relationship with mean temperature may no longer hold. Another factor that may be oversimplified is our use of a globally uniform (though crop‐specific) CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization effect derived by the meta‐analysis (Challinor et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2497-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Some research has suggested regional differences but indicates that more research is necessary to adequately account for these in models (McGrath &amp; Lobell, 
 <xref rid="eft2497-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Additionally, as discussed in section 
 <xref rid="eft2497-sec-0001" ref-type="sec" class="xref">1</xref>, aerosols are likely to play an additional role through their effects on both direct and diffuse radiation and nutrient fertilization, so should be accounted for as these effects become better understood. Hence, there is ample room for improving our understanding of the crop response to individual pollutants. These results also highlight the prominent role of methane, suggesting that it would be useful to perform simulations with detailed, computationally expensive plant level and climate modeling driven by methane alone to compare with our statistical modeling approach.
</p>
