<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35000-sec-0020" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSIONS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results add to our understanding of the relationship between year‐to‐year climate variability, phenology, and demography, as illustrated by changes in survival in hibernating ground squirrels. Although the phenology of UGS does not appear to have changed over time, UGS survival is affected by climate, with each age class responding differently. Warmer winter temperatures may increase juvenile survival, but decrease adult survival, making it difficult to predict how this population may respond to prolonged and increasing warming. We suspect warmer temperatures in our study area have facilitated the invasion of cheatgrass, and that this relatively new food source is benefiting UGS, especially juveniles whose emergence coincides with leaf and seed production, which may explain the observed increase in UGS density over time. Our results suggest that the potential negative impact of warming on yearling/adult UGS survival seems outweighed by the observed increase in juvenile survival fueled by warmer winter temperatures and cheatgrass invasion. Additional work will help assess whether these population‐level benefits will continue, or will remain short‐lived in light of continued warming (Rezouki et al., 
  <a rid="ece35000-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0049">2016</a>; Tafani et al., 
  <a rid="ece35000-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0055">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is, however, impossible to infer from our results how seasonal changes in climate could affect population structure and dynamics without a thorough understanding of the impact climate variability has on fertility components such as age at maturity, reproductive success, and age at last reproduction. Indeed, after an experimental reduction in UGS population density back in the 1960s, age at maturity and fertility contributed most to changes in the population growth rate in lawn and edge habitats (Oli et al., 
  <a rid="ece35000-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0041">2001</a>). However, both survival and fertility rates contributed equally to proportional changes in population growth rate within non‐lawn habitats. Future studies could help establish a solid connection between climate variability and UGS population dynamics by focusing on seasonal climate impacts on fertility and density estimates across habitats types, but this would involve manpower and resources that were not available at the time of our study.
 </p>
</sec>
