<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35000-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of season‐specific climate on UGS viability fitness</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data were obtained from a weather station approximately 26 km (16 miles) from the field site. Although a weather station is located &lt;1 km from the field site, data were only available from 2009 to present. Climate variables of interest were compared between these two weather stations for available co‐occurring years and were found to be highly correlated (see Appendix 
  <a rid="ece35000-app-0001" ref-type="app" href="#ece35000-app-0001">A</a>).
 </p>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fall</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snow acts as an insulator and can prevent the ground from freezing (Happold, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0023">1998</a>; Inouye et al., 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0028">2000</a>). In Alpine marmots, when snow depth is &gt;110 cm, the burrow temperatures are thought to be buffered against air temperatures (Tafani et al., 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0055">2013</a>, Appendix D). To assess the potential influence of below‐freezing temperatures on UGS survival before an insulating layer of snow was present, the number of days below freezing that occurred after estivation began and before permanent snow cover occurred (August–November or December) were tallied up each year 
   <span class="italic">t</span> (e.g., August to December 2015), and the impact of that variable on survival was assessed between year 
   <span class="italic">t</span> and 
   <span class="italic">t</span> + 1.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Winter</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because winter conditions could affect over‐winter survival as well as fitness postemergence, we considered the average snow depth and temperature from December of the previous year (
   <span class="italic">t </span>− 1) until emergence the next spring (
   <span class="italic">t</span>) in examining the influence of winter conditions on survival from 
   <span class="italic">t</span> − 1 to 
   <span class="italic">t</span> (direct effect) and from 
   <span class="italic">t</span> to 
   <span class="italic">t</span> + 1 (cross‐seasonal effect).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spring</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snowmelt determines when food resources become available (Inouye et al., 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0028">2000</a>; Rezouki et al., 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0049">2016</a>; Vuren &amp; Armitage, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0061">1991</a>; Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). In years when squirrels emerged long before snowmelt (snow melted late relative to other years), their body mass typically declined before increasing again as food became accessible (Knopf &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0033">1977</a>), indicating the importance of spring temperatures as they relate to forage availability and body mass at spring emergence. Since temperatures in year 
   <span class="italic">t</span> could influence survival from 
   <span class="italic">t</span> − 1 to 
   <span class="italic">t</span> or from 
   <span class="italic">t</span> to 
   <span class="italic">t</span> + 1, we considered the maximum temperatures between March 15th and March 31st (per Knopf &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0033">1977</a>) in our model selection framework.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summer</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summer precipitation and temperatures influence food availability, with hot and dry summers causing earlier plant senescence (Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). Precipitation may be positively correlated with survival through improved forage quality (Armitage, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0004">1994</a>). Previous studies have shown that timing of UGS estivation roughly coincides with the drying out of vegetation (Knopf, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0032">1973</a>), suggesting declines in precipitation have the potential to shorten the active season via changes in plant availability. To examine the influence of summer food conditions in relation to UGS phenology, growing degree days (at 0°C; Frank, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0020">1996</a>) were calculated from emergence until the estimated date of juvenile emergence, when forage quality and quantity is essential to this age class. We also considered an aridity index that incorporates average temperature and precipitation from June to August (BGI, Bagnouls‐Gaussen Index: daily rainfall (mm) minus twice the average temperature (°C) (Canale, Ozgul, Allainé, &amp; Cohas, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0010">2016</a>; Aridity Index, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0002">2014</a>), as well as average temperature and average precipitation alone as variables that could influence survival to the following year.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
