<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35000-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">METHODS</div>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uinta ground squirrel ecology</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uinta ground squirrels typically emerge from hibernation between March and April and enter estivation by August, depending on elevation, age, and sex (Eshelman &amp; Sonnemann, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0019">2000</a>). UGS mate within a week of emergence, and adult and yearling females can produce a single litter each year of four to six juveniles (Eshelman &amp; Sonnemann, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0019">2000</a>). Maximum life expectancy is 7 years in the wild, but average life expectancy for juveniles is approximately 1.46 years (Oli et al., 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0041">2001</a>). Yearling males rarely emerged from hibernation in breeding condition, while the number and sequence of emergence of females in the early spring affected breeding and social organization by limiting the number of females which retained residences in the study area (Paul, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0045">1977</a>; Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). Spring climatic conditions influence emergence date and emergence order of each sex and age class: adult males and females emerge before yearlings in warmer springs, but colder springs cause a more synchronous delayed emergence of sex and age classes (Knopf, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0032">1973</a>), making it more likely for yearling females to breed (Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). The diet of UGS is composed of graminoids and forbs, and historically they primarily consumed Kentucky bluegrass (
   <span class="italic">Poa pratensis</span>; Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). Contemporary surveys show that the site is now dominated by cheatgrass (
   <span class="italic">Bromus tectorum</span>), but 
   <span class="italic">Poa </span>spp. including 
   <span class="italic">Poa pratensis</span> are still present (C. Falvo, unpublished data). Extensive data were collected from 1964 to 1971 on UGS behavior and demography (Knopf &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0033">1977</a>; Slade &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0053">1974</a>; Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>), but in 1968 the population was reduced by approximately half to study density‐dependent dynamics (Slade &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0053">1974</a>); thus, we excluded those later years from our analysis. Contemporary data collection began in 2014 up to 2017 in the same location, in order to make comparisons to historical survival probabilities.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field site and data collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contemporary data were collected from 2014 to 2017 at the Utah State University Forestry Field Station in Logan Canyon, UT, in accordance with IACUC protocol #2220. Sites were checked approximately every 3–6 days starting in March for signs of emergence, and there were 9 capture dates in 2014, 12 in 2015, 19 in 2016, and 23 in 2017. There were 95 unique captures in 2014, 55 in 2015, 86 in 2016, and 44 in 2017. Historical data from 1964 to 1968 were collected in the same location by previous researchers detailing the behavior, social, and population dynamics of UGS. Historical data collection was considered a census since technicians were present at the site the entire summer, from emergence until estivation (i.e., prolonged torpor during a hot period; UGS transition to estivation from hibernation without emerging from their burrows; for more detailed description of site and capture methods, see Knopf &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0033">1977</a>; Slade &amp; Balph, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0053">1974</a>; Walker, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UGS were caught using Tomahawk live‐traps (Tomahawk, Wisconsin, USA) that were baited with rolled oats and peanut butter. Traps were set early in the morning before squirrels were active, checked within an hour, and squirrels were processed within 2–3 hr of capture. At initial capture, the age of the animal was determined and individuals were classified as juveniles (young of the year), yearling (1‐year‐old), or adult (≥2‐year‐old) based primarily on body mass, reproductive status, and comparison with individuals of known age from previous years of trapping. Each individual's mass was determined by placing the animal in a cloth bag and using a Pesola scale (±2 g.; Pesola Company, Baar, Switzerland). For contemporary data, additional morphometric variables (body, hind foot, and tail length) were measured using a measuring tape or calipers. The reproductive status of males and females was recorded (males as scrotal or non‐scrotal; females as pregnant, lactating, or non‐reproductive). Small, numbered, noncorrosive metal ear tags (Monel 1005‐1, National Band and Tag Company, Newport, Kentucky) were placed on each squirrel at first capture for identification upon recapture. Passive Integrative Transponders (PIT tags, Biomark) were also injected under the skin to keep track of individuals in case of ear tag loss.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of season‐specific climate on UGS viability fitness</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data were obtained from a weather station approximately 26 km (16 miles) from the field site. Although a weather station is located &lt;1 km from the field site, data were only available from 2009 to present. Climate variables of interest were compared between these two weather stations for available co‐occurring years and were found to be highly correlated (see Appendix 
   <a rid="ece35000-app-0001" ref-type="app" href="#ece35000-app-0001">A</a>).
  </p>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0006" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fall</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snow acts as an insulator and can prevent the ground from freezing (Happold, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0023">1998</a>; Inouye et al., 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0028">2000</a>). In Alpine marmots, when snow depth is &gt;110 cm, the burrow temperatures are thought to be buffered against air temperatures (Tafani et al., 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0055">2013</a>, Appendix D). To assess the potential influence of below‐freezing temperatures on UGS survival before an insulating layer of snow was present, the number of days below freezing that occurred after estivation began and before permanent snow cover occurred (August–November or December) were tallied up each year 
    <span class="italic">t</span> (e.g., August to December 2015), and the impact of that variable on survival was assessed between year 
    <span class="italic">t</span> and 
    <span class="italic">t</span> + 1.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0007" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Winter</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because winter conditions could affect over‐winter survival as well as fitness postemergence, we considered the average snow depth and temperature from December of the previous year (
    <span class="italic">t </span>− 1) until emergence the next spring (
    <span class="italic">t</span>) in examining the influence of winter conditions on survival from 
    <span class="italic">t</span> − 1 to 
    <span class="italic">t</span> (direct effect) and from 
    <span class="italic">t</span> to 
    <span class="italic">t</span> + 1 (cross‐seasonal effect).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0008" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spring</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snowmelt determines when food resources become available (Inouye et al., 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0028">2000</a>; Rezouki et al., 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0049">2016</a>; Vuren &amp; Armitage, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0061">1991</a>; Walker, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). In years when squirrels emerged long before snowmelt (snow melted late relative to other years), their body mass typically declined before increasing again as food became accessible (Knopf &amp; Balph, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0033">1977</a>), indicating the importance of spring temperatures as they relate to forage availability and body mass at spring emergence. Since temperatures in year 
    <span class="italic">t</span> could influence survival from 
    <span class="italic">t</span> − 1 to 
    <span class="italic">t</span> or from 
    <span class="italic">t</span> to 
    <span class="italic">t</span> + 1, we considered the maximum temperatures between March 15th and March 31st (per Knopf &amp; Balph, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0033">1977</a>) in our model selection framework.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0009" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.4</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summer</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summer precipitation and temperatures influence food availability, with hot and dry summers causing earlier plant senescence (Walker, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0062">1968</a>). Precipitation may be positively correlated with survival through improved forage quality (Armitage, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0004">1994</a>). Previous studies have shown that timing of UGS estivation roughly coincides with the drying out of vegetation (Knopf, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0032">1973</a>), suggesting declines in precipitation have the potential to shorten the active season via changes in plant availability. To examine the influence of summer food conditions in relation to UGS phenology, growing degree days (at 0°C; Frank, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0020">1996</a>) were calculated from emergence until the estimated date of juvenile emergence, when forage quality and quantity is essential to this age class. We also considered an aridity index that incorporates average temperature and precipitation from June to August (BGI, Bagnouls‐Gaussen Index: daily rainfall (mm) minus twice the average temperature (°C) (Canale, Ozgul, Allainé, &amp; Cohas, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0010">2016</a>; Aridity Index, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0002">2014</a>), as well as average temperature and average precipitation alone as variables that could influence survival to the following year.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35000-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Capture–mark–recapture analyses and model selection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine whether UGS survival has changed over time, we used Cormack–Jolly–Seber (CJS, Lebreton, Burnham, Clobert, &amp; Anderson, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0038">1992</a>) capture–mark–recapture (CMR) models developed in R (R Core Team, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0047">2013</a>, version 3.2.3) using the RMark package (Laake, 
   <a rid="ece35000-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0036">2013</a>) to estimate annual apparent survival (
   <span class="italic">ϕ</span>) and recapture probability (
   <span class="italic">p</span>) from both historical and contemporary data.
  </p>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0011" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.1</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Goodness‐of‐Fit</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used goodness‐of‐fit (GOF) tests computed in the RELEASE software implemented in program MARK (Cooch &amp; White, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0014">2006</a>), which tests assumptions of the CJS model that every marked animal present at time 
    <span class="italic">t</span> has the same probability of recapture, and that every marked animal immediately after 
    <span class="italic">t</span> has the same probability of surviving to 
    <span class="italic">t</span> + 1 (White &amp; Cooch, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0064">2012</a>) (see Appendix 
    <a rid="ece35000-app-0002" ref-type="app" href="#ece35000-app-0002">B</a> for details). We considered a global model where survival was allowed to vary by age, sex, and time period (historical vs. contemporary). Although a global model may pass GOF tests, this does not imply that assumptions of the CMR modeling framework are met perfectly. We therefore estimated 
    <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <span class="mi">c</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
    </div> to adjust model likelihoods for over‐dispersion in the data by dividing the overall 
    <span class="italic">χ</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span> values by the total degrees of freedom, which is not biased as high as the median 
    <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <span class="mi">c</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
    </div> approach for CJS models (White, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0063">2002</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0012" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.2</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Detection probability (
    <span class="italic">p</span>)
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of a 46‐year gap in the CMR data, appropriate recapture and survival parameters were fixed to 0 between the historical and contemporary study periods. Additionally, data on adult males were not available during the first 2 years of the historical study, and thus, these parameters were also fixed to 0. For historical years, we fixed 
    <span class="italic">p</span> to 1 because trapping was considered a census in those years (Slade &amp; Balph, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0053">1974</a>). Since estimates for 
    <span class="italic">p</span> consistently converged to 1 for females, and for both sexes in 2016, we also fixed 
    <span class="italic">p</span> = 1 for those sex‐year combinations. All other recapture probabilities were estimated by comparing models that allowed variability by age, sex, and year using QAICc (AIC adjusted for sample size and over‐dispersion; Burnham &amp; Anderson, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0009">2002</a>). The top performing model for 
    <span class="italic">p</span> was then used alongside alternative parameterizations for 
    <span class="italic">ϕ</span>.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0013" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.3</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apparent survival probability (
    <span class="italic">ϕ</span>)
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To keep our model selection process down to a reasonable number of models (Burnham &amp; Anderson, 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0009">2002</a>), we first examined the influence of demographic categories and time (age, sex, and year) on apparent survival. We carried forward the highest‐ranked term(s) into a final set of models where we considered univariate effects of phenological variables and seasonal climate variables (emergence dates, season length; winter, spring, summer, or fall climate) interacting with age. By avoiding model dredging, we acknowledge we may have overlooked certain variable combinations supported by the data, and of importance in affecting actual UGS survival. 
    <div list-type="order" id="ece35000-list-0001" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>
       <span class="italic">Demographic categories</span>. Within each subset of models, we only considered models that tested for ecological hypotheses of interest. For instance, we expected survival to be different between males and females because females bear the cost of reproduction, and after gestation and provisioning for their offspring, they have less time to gain mass before estivation begins (Knopf, 
       <a rid="ece35000-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0032">1973</a>). We also anticipated differences in survival between juveniles and older age classes because juveniles have the shortest amount of time to gain mass prior to estivation. Models with three age classes (juvenile, yearling, and adult) vs. two age classes (juvenile, yearling, and adult combined) were compared, as we did not anticipate large differences in survival between yearlings and adults (Oli et al., 
       <a rid="ece35000-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0041">2001</a>).
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>
       <span class="italic">Phenological variables</span>. We compared models that accounted for the effect of emergence date, season length, and a cross‐seasonal effect of either on survival (
       <span class="italic">t </span>− 1 to 
       <span class="italic">t</span> and 
       <span class="italic">t</span> to 
       <span class="italic">t </span>+ 1). Emergence date was the calendar date the first squirrel was seen in a given year, and season length was based on the amount of time squirrels were known to be active, from emergence to estivation in a given year. An early emergence date may be beneficial (if forage availability and snowmelt are also initiated early), or detrimental (if snow cover persists beyond emergence). Similarly, a longer season may be beneficial if food resources have not yet senesced, and nutritional quality is not compromised.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>
       <span class="italic">Seasonal climate variables</span>. We considered the number of below‐freezing days after estivation and before permanent snowpack, winter temperature, winter snowfall, maximum March temperature, growing degree days (GDD), Bagnouls‐Gaussen summer drought index (BGI), summer temperature, and summer precipitation.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece35000-sec-0014" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.4</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model selection</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used QAICc to score model(s) in each tier of our model selection process (see above), while ensuring that each model reflected ecological hypotheses of interest, as per Lebreton et al. (
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0038">1992</a>). Because time‐varying climate variables are redundant with annual changes in survival, generic (fixed effect) time variation in survival (if selected in our demographic set of models) was never considered along with time‐varying covariates in the final model set. Overall, this tiered approach was preferred because it allowed us to consider models that reflected relevant ecological hypotheses while restricting the number of models considered to a reasonable level.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate how well our best‐performing models fit the data, we calculated 
    <span class="italic">R</span>, the ratio of deviance reduction for a model relative to a fully saturated model and a null model (Iles et al., 
    <a rid="ece35000-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35000-bib-0026">2013</a>). This involved calculating the deviance reduction measure (
    <span class="italic">D</span>
    <sub>MOI</sub> = 1 − dev
    <sub>MOI</sub>/dev
    <sub>NULL</sub>) where MOI is the model of interest and NULL is the least parameterized model that was considered (~age class). This value was used to calculate the ratio of deviance reduction (
    <span class="italic">R</span> = 
    <span class="italic">D</span>
    <sub>MOI</sub>/
    <span class="italic">D</span>
    <sub>FULL</sub>) where FULL refers to a fully saturated temporal model (~ age class * time), providing a relative measure of deviance reduction.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
