<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15" class="p">In principle, NEP from BEPS should not equal the RLS, because NEP excludes the net emission from anthropogenic and natural disturbances (land cover and land-use change, harvest, plantation, fires, and insects) (
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">Supplementary Discussion</xref>). Those disturbances can induce both immediate LAI reduction and subsequent gradual LAI increase due to regrowth. In BEPS, a LAI reduction induces additional transfer of the same portions of biomass pools to soil organic matter, which is subsequently respired as a source of carbon to the atmosphere. This disturbance-enhanced carbon loss by respiration is mostly compensated by regrowth, which is driven by observed LAI series in the same period, whereas NEP equals RLS for undisturbed areas. If the carbon gain through regrowth equaled the carbon loss due to enhanced respiration, the simulated NEP would equal RLS for disturbed areas. This would be true only if the disturbance and recovery were historically maintained at constant rates. However, there are considerable differences between NEP modeled by BEPS and RLS for areas with large changes in short vegetation (SV), tree cover (TC), and bare land. To assess these differences, we also show in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> the simulated accumulated NEP curves after excluding pixels (8 km resolution) with changes in SV or TC coverage over 20% and 30%, respectively, in the accumulation, based on SV and TC high-resolution (30 m) map produced from Landsat data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. Excluding these areas with large SV or TC changes results in small decreases in accumulated NEP by 8.0% and 2.5% for these two cases, respectively, suggesting that cumulative NEP approximately equals cumulative RLS at the global scale since 1981. These effects of disturbance on simulated NEP are small, because pixels with 20% and 30% disturbance in SV or TC are only 6.7% and 2.0% of the land area, respectively (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">12</xref>), and the LAI observations used to drive BEPS can capture a large portion of the impacts of disturbance on photosynthesis and ecosystem respiration. These exclusions always cause smaller NEP values, because the contributions from undisturbed portions within the excluded pixels are discounted. Changes from SV to TC or from bare land to SV or TC within the excluded pixels are also discounted, although they may incur small sinks (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">13</xref>), which are associated with LAI changes (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">14</xref>). For simplicity, we do not exclude disturbed pixels in the results shown in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>.
</p>
