<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f3" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 3</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Mass balance in the critical zone of Mullins Glacier as a function of single parameter changes in climate forcing.</title>
  <p class="p">Results are displayed for baseline environmental conditions at two sites (L01, 1,642 m elevation; L02 1,542 m elevation) (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>) Mass balance sensitivity to changes in average annual air temperature, over the magnitude of temperature change recorded at Taylor Dome. The results show a non-linear response to warming air temperatures. (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>) Sensitivity to changes in annual snowfall (with snow plotted as cm water equivalent). The slightly non-linear response is due to increased periods of relatively high albedo for elevated snow conditions. Bottom-left panels show changes in solar forcing functions over the last 250 ka and the associated mass balance response: (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) Orbital parameters; (
   <bold class="bold">d</bold>) December 21 top-of-atmosphere solar intensity (upper curve), and integrated summer energy (lower curve)
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref> computed for a threshold of 350 W m
   <sup class="sup">−2</sup> resulting from the orbital configurations of 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>. The summer energy is defined as the sum of insolation intensity exceeding a given threshold
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>; (
   <bold class="bold">e</bold>) Modelled point mass balance over the 250 ka time period at L01 (grey line) and L02 (blue line) for the orbital configurations shown in 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>. Light tan, vertical bars in 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">d</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">e</bold> mark peaks in summer energy and show that this quantity essentially changes in pace with obliquity variations
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>. Bottom-right panels show point mass balance plotted as a function of summer energy (
   <bold class="bold">f</bold>) and mid-summer solar intensity (
   <bold class="bold">g</bold>). Small red dots correspond to values for arbitrary time periods plotted as red vertical lines across 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">d</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">e</bold>. Summer energy, which incorporates changes in summer duration as well as intensity, displays the strongest correlation with mass balance.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ncomms14194-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
