<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We thank K. Kaschner and C. Garilao for providing the AquaMaps distribution and depth preference data for the species used in the projections. We also thank M. Pinsky for providing helpful feedback on the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> The authors acknowledge funding for this work from The Leona M. and Harry B. Helmsley Charitable Trust; the Waitt Family Foundation; the “Tenure-Track System Promotion Program” of the Japanese Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports Science and Technology (MEXT); and the David and Lucile Packard Foundation. 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> S.D.G. and C.C. designed the study. J.G.M. refined the climate velocity model and ran climate velocity simulations. H.D. conducted research and performed analyses on the relationship between range and carrying capacity. B.O. and T.M. developed the bioeconomic model and methods with the supervision of S.D.G. and C.C. and prepared all data for use in the bioeconomic model. B.O., T.M., J.B., J.G.M., S.D.G., and H.D. performed the analyses in the manuscript and the Supplementary Materials. B.O., T.M., J.B., J.G.M., and S.D.G. prepared the graphics. S.D.G., B.O., T.M., and J.B. co-wrote the paper with advice and guidance from C.C., D.O., B.S.H., C.V.K., M.B., and K.M.K. All authors contributed to this work, read the manuscript and the Supplementary Materials, and provided edits to these documents. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> C.C. is a trustee for Environmental Defense Fund and Global Fishing Watch, is senior fellow at the Property and Environment Research Center, and is a research associate with the National Bureau of Economic Research. S.D.G. is a trustee of the National Marine Sanctuary Foundation, Rare, the Resources Legacy Fund, and COMPASS. All other authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Species distribution maps can be accessed through the AquaMaps portal (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aquamaps.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.aquamaps.org/</ext-link>). Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors.
 </p>
</ack>
