<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From an evolutionary perspective, a study based on the effects of climate change on endemic species in Sahara-Sahel showed that some groups with a high capacity to adapt to global change (for example, those with a high dispersal capacities) may be able to colonize distinct areas, while groups with low adaptive capacity may be more vulnerable to extinction (
 <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Vale &amp; Brito, 2015</xref>). This result is consistent with the finding from study on arid-adapted plants, where desert plants may be resilient to climate change since they presented with positive population growth rates (
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Salguero-Gómez et al., 2012</xref>). Also, at an intraspecific level, semiarid plants could present a better response to climate change in more arid populations because of the greater phenotypic plasticity of these populations in comparison with more mesic populations (
 <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Lázaro-Nogal et al., 2015</xref>). Persistence against climate change may be favored by species with seed dormancy, since seeds may resist long periods of drought (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Clauss &amp; Venable, 2000</xref>), while rapid life cycles and fast reproductive processes allow species to take advantage of short windows of ecological opportunities when resources are abundant, such as episodic rainfalls (
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Aronson et al., 1993</xref>), which allow water to be retained in water-scarce conditions. However, there is evidence of an evolutionary lag time for 
 <italic>Chaetanthera</italic>, 
 <italic>Malesherbia</italic> and 
 <italic>Nolana</italic> to adapt to new, more severe arid conditions, and thus rapid adaptation to ongoing climate change may be unlikely (
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Guerrero et al., 2013</xref>). This tells us that the study of arid lineages and their future in the face of climate change is still in process. Therefore, describing these evolutionary advantages is also important when evaluating the future distributions of various species. For example, in our study, some species of the genus 
 <italic>Leucocoryne</italic> (geophite) showed a large niche breadth and low similarity; at the same time, it is known that these plants have bulbous structures that enable it to store water in prolonged droughts (
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Jara-Arancio et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
