<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Forcing.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1819989116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S4
  </span> presents model results of the direct and total aerosol radiative forcing at the top of the atmosphere (TOA). The direct aerosol forcing is −0.46 ± 0.009 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>, which closely agrees with the best estimate of −0.45 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> of the IPCC (
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>). Our total direct plus indirect radiative forcing is −0.9 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>, which also agrees with IPCC (
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>). However, by also accounting for the chemical aging of aeolian dust by air pollution we obtain a −0.3-W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> larger effect, about −1.2 ± 0.06 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (
  <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>, 
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>). The dust aging has multiple consequences, such as increased solar radiation scattering from hygroscopic particle growth and decreased lifetime from more efficient rainout, while the climate effect is dominated by the enhanced CCN activity. Since dust particles are globally abundant and relatively large in size, their increased hygroscopicity effectively enhances cloud droplet formation (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>). To account for these effects, it is needed to simulate the particle chemistry and thermodynamics of crustal ions, dependent on the composition of aeolian dust from different deserts, which was not included in the IPCC climate models. 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1819989116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S3 and S4
  </span> show the global, multiannual mean geographic distribution of the aerosol direct and total radiative forcing, both at the TOA and the bottom of the atmosphere (BOA), making the distinction between fossil fuel generated and all anthropogenic aerosols. The differences between the TOA and BOA forcings represent heating of the atmosphere through the absorption of sunlight, mostly by black carbon. We find that the negative (cooling) BOA forcings from aerosols are generally largest over South and East Asia, partly in excess of −20 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (annual average), which can regionally dwarf the positive (warming) radiative forcing from greenhouse gases. The strong surface cooling downwind over the ocean can significantly reduce evaporation and precipitation on a regional scale (
  <a rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" href="#r16">16</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
