<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Response.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We performed equilibrium climate response computations, following the example of Shindell et al. (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>), with the difference that they computed atmospheric composition changes offline with different models, whereas we calculate the processes online with a coupled atmosphere–ocean model. The equilibrium assumption is justified for short-lived climate forcers since most of the climate response that follows phaseout of fossil fuels and other pollution sources happens within a few decades. Although the equilibrium assumption does not apply to CO
  <sub>2</sub>, this is not relevant here because the phaseout of CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions does not translate in a near-term temperature decrease (
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>, 
  <a rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" href="#r19">19</a>
  <a href="#r20">*</a>
  <a href="#r21">*</a>–
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>). In the period during which CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations still increase, the warming is tempered by heat transport into the deep oceans. When CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions are phased out, the atmospheric concentrations can decrease, but with a delay due to the slow uptake of anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> by the oceans (
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>). These physical climate and carbon cycle effects are of opposite sign and of similar magnitude. Consequently, even if fossil CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions stop abruptly, global temperatures remain constant for several centuries, which means that past CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions commit the planet to persistent warming on the human timescale (for a discussion, see ref. 
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>). While the timing of air pollution and greenhouse gas emission phaseout is the subject of scenario studies, here we focus on the climate response magnitude. For example, global warming from increasing CO
  <sub>2</sub> scales approximately linearly with cumulative emissions (
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>). It implies that the phaseout may occur over 5 or 50 y, but the integral climate response over these periods is the same. In fact, the key factor is “societal inertia” from the slow phaseout of polluting infrastructure, often constructed to last for many decades (
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>, 
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The warming and precipitation pattern changes that result from removing aerosols in our climate simulations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1819989116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S7
  </span>) are comparable to those presented by Samset et al. (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>), who analyzed the ensemble results from four climate models. They reported that the removal of anthropogenic aerosols causes a global mean surface warming of 0.5–1.1° and a precipitation increase of 2.0–4.6%, where we find 0.73 ± 0.03 °C and 3.2 ± 0.2%, respectively. Consistent with our results, they showed how the aerosol-related climate response patterns differ markedly from those of greenhouse gases. However, they studied anthropogenic emissions of SO
  <sub>2</sub> and fossil fuel black and organic carbon, without the distinction between fossil fuel use and other anthropogenic sources, and did not consider pollution impacts on dust. Further, they did not account for the greenhouse gases O
  <sub>3</sub> and CH
  <sub>4</sub>, and calculated CO
  <sub>2</sub> and aerosol reductions separately to contrast the cooling and warming patterns. While greenhouse gases act globally, the radiative forcing and consequent net warming from aerosol removal is regional and most pronounced over the continental northern hemisphere (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). In agreement with the results of Samset et al., we find that the removal of aerosols creates south–north shifts of precipitation over the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans and relatively strong rainfall increases over Africa, South and Northeast Asia (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1819989116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S7
  </span>). Westervelt et al. (
  <a rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" href="#r33">33</a>) studied precipitation changes from the removal of SO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions in the United States. The computed reductions of aerosol sulfate and cloud droplet number concentrations were found to cause increasing precipitation over the United States, and downwind over the Atlantic Ocean, qualitatively consistent with our results. 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1819989116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S3 and S4
  </span> illustrate that the direct radiative effect of aerosols at the BOA typically exceeds that at the TOA by a factor of 2–3, e.g., due to solar radiation absorption within the atmosphere by black carbon, and that the radiative forcing can regionally exceed the global average by a factor of 5–10. This results in strong, although localized influence on surface temperature, evaporation and associated precipitation.
 </p>
</sec>
