<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Health Risks.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Possible future impacts of air pollution on mortality have been estimated previously by using the output from chemistry–climate and chemical transport models that applied Representative Concentration Pathway scenarios (RCPs) (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>). Apart from the fact that the new GEMM was not available at the time, it differed from our approach by estimating increased and avoided mortality from different RCPs, assuming that economic development drives air pollution control. Here we estimate the attributable effects of both fossil fuel and all anthropogenic air pollution plus greenhouse gases by removing emissions in the model, rather than applying time-dependent scenarios that rely on assumptions about socioeconomic futures. While this may seem a daring assumption, these source categories will need to be phased out to reach the 2 °C target of the Paris Agreement (
  <a rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" href="#r7">7</a>). We realize, however, that especially agricultural emissions cannot be fully avoided in a world with growing food demand, although a large fraction (e.g., of ammonia and methane sources) could be effectively controlled. A limitation of our approach is that it refers to emission and demographic data for 2015, while population growth is expected up to about 9 billion by the middle of the century, especially in developing countries where air pollution levels can be very high. Therefore, we performed sensitivity simulations that account for the projected population in 2050, indicating that the total excess mortality may be about 10% higher globally. Most of the increase is due to population growth in South and West Asia, and especially in Africa, while in East Asia the population is expected to decline. In Europe and the Americas (notably South America) projected population changes are comparatively small. Interestingly, the avoidable excess mortality in 2015 and 2050 are practically the same (within 1–2%). Furthermore, we did not take into account that the introduction of clean household energy in low-income countries could substantially reduce excess deaths from household air pollution, estimated at about 2.9–4.3 million per year (
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>). The phaseout of anthropogenic emissions is expected to be paralleled by a reduction of household air pollution from the introduction of clean “zero carbon” domestic energy sources.
 </p>
</sec>
