<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Classifying population migratory behavior</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Populations of juncos were classified according to a scale of migratory distance based on published reports in the literature 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-33">33</a>– 
    <a rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-35">35</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-40">40</a>– 
    <a rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-42">42</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-44">44</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">45</a>
   </span>, personal observation. Each population was ranked on a scale from 1 (sedentary) to 6 (long-distance migrant) based on the average distance migrated by individuals in that population ( 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). Distance migrated also varies within populations. For example, in the Eastern United States, females 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">46</a>
   </span> and adults 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">47</a>
   </span> generally migrate farther from their breeding ranges than males and yearlings, respectively. Some junco populations also exhibit partial migration, in which a subset of individuals remains on the breeding grounds while others depart 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-35">35</a>
   </span>. The classification system employed here broadly categorizes the general migratory phenotype of each population and was organized to resemble previous reports for other species (e.g. blackcaps 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
   </span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessing the migratory behavior of individuals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals from two populations of 
   <span class="italic">J. h. thurberi</span> residing in southern California were captured as recently independent offspring and held in captivity under identical conditions in a ‘common garden’. Individuals were held individually (0.61 m × 0.61 m × 0.61 m cages) in a climate controlled indoor aviary with 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> access to food and water. Individuals were neither visually nor acoustically isolated, and light regimes were changed bi-weekly to match photoperiod at their home latitude. All methods were reviewed and approved by the IACUC at Indiana University (protocol #09-037). To reduce the probability of capturing siblings and pseudoreplication, individuals were captured from multiple locations, and one individual from each identified sibship (one in each population) was randomly included in all analyses, as in previous studies 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
   </span>. Additional studies of these captive common garden populations are reported elsewhere ( 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">48</a>
   </span>; Atwell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> in review).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Briefly, spring nocturnal restlessness behavior was scored from 3 March to 1 August 2010 by recording intervals of night-time perch-hopping activity of birds housed indoors in individual cages equipped with microswitched perches. This method is considered effective to capture 95% of migratory behavior observed in infrared video and ultrasound methods 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">49</a>
   </span>, and even non-traditional songbird migrations tend to occur at night 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">50</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">51</a>
   </span>. Juncos typically migrate at night 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>
   </span>, and this sampling period overlapped with the typical spring migration as well as breeding seasons of dark-eyed juncos 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">41</a>
   </span>. As was found in prior studies of migratory restlessness in the junco (e.g., Ketterson and Nolan 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">52</a>
   </span>) and other species, migratory restlessness extended into the typical breeding period, perhaps due to caged birds’ inability to perform reproductive activities 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">53</a>
   </span>. Nocturnal hops were recorded starting 30 minutes after dusk until 30 minutes before dawn under a daylight regime that simulated the photoperiod at their native latitude. GraphPad Prism 3.0 (GraphPad, USA) was used to quantify the seasonal intensity of individual spring migratory restlessness by calculating the area under each fitted seasonal profile curve, which provided a total migratory propensity score for each bird (n = 36 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">14</a>
   </span>; Atwell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> in review).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sampling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of population differences in genotype was conducted using DNA collected between 1996–2010 from adult juncos that were captured from breeding or wintering populations as a part of other studies. Less than 100 μL of whole blood was collected via capilary tube from a small puncture in the alar vein for future extraction. Both males and females were included, and in all populations in which sexes were known, the sexes did not differ in allele length for either locus (t-test, all p &gt; 0.1). Birds sampled in their winter range were captured from December through February, after juncos are thought to have arrived at their wintering grounds and before they have departed in the spring 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">54</a>
   </span>. All individuals from breeding locations were captured as adults during the breeding season of that population. No known siblings were included in these analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genotyping</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We extracted DNA from whole blood from 15 populations spanning the range of migratory phenotypes in the genus 
   <span class="italic">Junco</span> ( 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). We developed primers surrounding a microsatellite repeat of interest based on previously published reports for 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
   </span> in birds, and we modified the primers to more closely match the junco sequence based on the junco transcriptome ( 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-55">55</a>
   </span>; See 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">Table 2</a> for primer details). The primers were used to amplify the respective polymorphisms in a single multiplex reaction using an amplification kit and following the manufacturer’s directions (Qiagen Inc, Valencia, California, USA). An initial 15´ heat activation cycle (95°C) was followed by 35 cycles of 94°C denaturation for 30”, 60°C annealing for 90”, and 72°C extension for 60”, and a final elongation of 10´. PCR products were then diluted 1:200 in ddH 
   <sub>2</sub>0 with LIZladder (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, California, USA), denatured at 95°C for 5´, and placed on ice. Samples were analyzed on an ABI 3730 using Peak Scanner v1.0 (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, California, USA).
  </p>
  <div id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="anchor" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 2. </span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Primers used in this study.</div>
    <p>Both primers are based on Steinmeyer 
     <span class="italic">et al.</span>
     <span class="sup">
      <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
     </span>, and 
     <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> was modified to match junco sequences 
     <span class="sup">
      <a rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-55">55</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="article-table">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene name</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward primer 5´ → 3´</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse primer 5´→ 3´</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">CLOCK</span>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTTCTCAAGGTCAGCAACTTGT</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGTAGGAACTGCTGGGGKTGCTG</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GATGTGAGTAACCAGCCACT</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATAACACAGGAGCGGTGA</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to assess the relationship between allele length and migratory behavior among populations for both loci, we performed Spearman's correlations between population mean allele length and population migratory status. Qualitatively similar results are obtained with major allele count methods that have been applied in previous studies 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
   </span> and when only dark-eyed subspecies were considered (data not shown). Within the sub-species groups for which we sampled multiple populations (Oregon juncos and slate-colored juncos, see 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>), we additionally performed a nested ANOVA on allele lengths with population as a grouping factor within each subspecies to determine whether mean allele length differed significantly between populations or these subspecies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To relate individual variation in allele length of 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> to migratory restlessness, we fit linear models with migratory restlessness as the dependent variable and all combinations of population, mean allele length of the individual, sex, and each pairwise interaction as predictors. The resulting models were compared against each other using Akaike's Information Criterion. When the best fit model yielded a significant interaction term, we followed with a separate linear model for each population 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">56</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were performed in R version 2.15.2 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">57</a>
   </span>. Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and heterozygosity were calculated with the package 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/genetics/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">genetics</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-58">58</a>
   </span>. All reported p-values are two-tailed, and hence conservative with respect to 
   <span class="italic">a priori</span> directional hypotheses.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
