<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The wealth of literature dealing with disease’ sensitivities to the climate mainly involve correlation or regression analysis. For example, Pearson’s correlation coefficients can be used to describe the crude relationship between average weather variables and logarithm of diarrhea morbidity [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. A further study measured the link between climate change and diarrhea-associated morbidity and predicted the dynamics of diarrhea-associated morbidity in subtropical Taiwan by applying a climate variation-guided Poisson regression model [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. However, such correlation analysis can only identify the static relationship between climate variables and infectious disease related parameters (
 <italic class="italic">i.e.,</italic> morbidity). In addition, other time series methods, such as cross-correlation analysis, provide opportunities for recognizing time lags and the temporal correlation between incidence data and climate data. They also assume that diseases respond linearly to climate variables, while research has revealed that climate change can have nonlinear influences on biological systems [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. This indicates that the impacts on infectious diseases might be different under different climate regimes. Therefore, those methods that assume linear relationships would fail to detect nonlinear relationships. On the other hand, Woolf’s relative risk statistic (RR) [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], which has been applied to estimate the increased risk of contracting a disease before and after a certain condition (or trait) is present [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], has become a standard measure in biomedical research [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Later, many more statistical factors have been proposed, including haplotype relative risk (HRR) [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], which is used to calculate the risk of disease in the presence of particular antigens or phenotypes. Potential impact fraction (PIF) was also developed by the WHO, to estimate the disease burden caused by the change of a given risk factor based on relative risk measurement [
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. With RR as reference, if the relationship between infectious disease-related parameters and climate variables varies at two different climate statuses (
 <italic class="italic">i.e.</italic>, historical climate and present climate), it is possible to reasonably state that an infectious disease as sensitive to climate change through a metric that is similar to the RR, and employed to compare the risk variation corresponding to a specified change in a risk factor’s level.
</p>
