<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <p>Photoperiodic responses are major factors entraining circannual life-cycles, functioning to adaptively synchronize annual routines to seasonal fluctuations in ecological conditions. Photoperiodism in physiology and behaviour is enforced by genes, including the vertebrate 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> orthologues, which are associated, for example, with phenology of migration in fish and breeding in birds. However, the role of 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> in photoperiodic plumage molt processes is unknown. We analyzed variation in molt schedules in relation to 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotype, using the long-distance migratory barn swallow (
  <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) as a model and by identifying males and females using molecular sexing techniques. Consistently with previous studies, we found one very common (
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>7</sub>) and two rare (
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>6</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>8</sub>) variants of a functionally significant 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> polyglutamine repeat. Molt schedules of primary wing feathers of swallows during their wintering period in Nigeria differed among 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotypes: rare (1.1%) 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>7</sub>/
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>8</sub> heterozygotes had significantly delayed molt compared to the other genotypes. Molt schedules did not differ between males and females, and no differential association between molt and 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> in relation to sex emerged. The same rare 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotype that exhibited delayed breeding in Europe was here found to delay molt in Africa. Though based on a limited number of 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>7</sub>/
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>8</sub> individuals from an otherwise very large sample, these novel results suggest that 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> is involved in the photoperiodic control of both molt and breeding, potentially also via reciprocal carry-over effects. If confirmed in species with higher 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> polymorphism, present results may have far-reaching consequences for the study of photoperiodic control of molt and expression of annual routines.
 </p>
</div>
