<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">The increase in the area of land under cultivation, and the increase in the area of land being irrigated, in conjunction with changes in planting practices (both the ratio of the area of grain crops to the area of cash crops and the area of grain crop cultivation increased), all led to an increase in ET. Other factors which contributed to the increase in ET include: the wide adoption of drip irrigation and other water-saving measures; the increased use of chemical fertilizers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>; and the increased use of plastic film mulch. The use of drip irrigation and other water-saving measures decreased the amount of water used for irrigation and to some degree increased the effectiveness of fertilizer use. These measures promoted crop growth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>, and thus may have caused ET to increase accordingly, so ET was negatively correlated with the quantity of water used for irrigation between 1984 and 2014. There was a positive correlation between ET and the use of plastic film mulch. Plastic film mulch has been widely used in northern China for many years to modify the soil surface. It leads to an increase in topsoil temperature which promotes early growth, it maintains soil water content, and it promotes increased yield
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>. Although plastic film mulch reduces soil evaporation at the early stage of plant growth, ET increased during the overall growth period in northwest China
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>. Higher relative humidity can reduce the water vapour gradient between a plant leaf and the atmosphere, which lowers the water vapour diffusion rate, and thus reduces evaporation so that there is a decrease in ET. As shown in Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, ET had an increasing trend, while relative humidity was decreasing. Thus ET has a negative correlation with relative humidity. Precipitation increases the soil moisture content, which increases the likelihood of evaporation. In addition, precipitation satisfies some of the crop water demand and so promotes crop growth. Crop growth leads to increased ET. Thus precipitation has some effect in increasing ET. As wind speed increases, the water vapour diffusion resistance decreases, which leads to increased ET. In a study of the sensitivity of ET to global climate change in the arid zone of Rajasthan, India
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>, when wind speed increased by 20%, ET increased by 7%; as humidity increased by 20%, ET decreased by 4.3%. Our study data show that the average temperature and solar radiation in the 31-year period were relatively stable in the study region, and thus had little effect on ET.
</p>
