<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Over the period from 1880 to 2012, average global temperatures have increased by 0.85°C. The period from 1983 to 2012 was very likely the warmest 30-year period in the last 800 years [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. A great many shifts in the distribution and abundances of species occurred in this period [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Approximately 20% of all of the world’s plant species are on the brink of extinction [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Thomas et al. stated that 15–37% of species in their sample of regions and taxa will be extinct based on mid-range climate-warming scenarios by 2050 [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Survival of many species is threatened by many issues caused by global warming, such as rising sea levels, increased rainfall, increased drought, extreme weather, and climate events [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Particularly, those species with high economic values face over-harvesting and environmental disruption. Although evolution of species has proven that they can adapt to the changing environment [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], enormous challenges for wild species and their ecosystems have emerged with this rapid rate of global warming. Currently, species shift, contract, expand, or fragment their range in response to the changing climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. These range shifts that track suitable climatic conditions have been observed in more than 1000 species, and habitat shifts appear to be one of the most important and effective methods by which species have adapted to changes in the environment [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Thus, understanding the impacts of climate change on range shift of different species is important for biodiversity conservation and biological resource protection [
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163718.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The increasing work on species distribution models (SDMs) has provided a new approach for predicting those changes.
</p>
