<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34" class="p">CAM5 simulations are carried out using finite volume (FV) dynamical core and CAM4 physics. Shallow and deep convections are parameterized using the methods described by Park and Bretherton (2009)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup> and Zhang and McFarlane (1995)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>, respectively. The model simulations are performed at three different resolutions 1.9° × 2.5°, 0.9° × 1.25° and 0.45° × 0.63° using FV dynamical core referred as 2°, 1° and 0.5° in the text. The six members of each of the ensembles are initialized with initial conditions at 6-hour intervals starting from 1800 UTC 31 March 2000. The initial conditions at 6-hour intervals are produced from a separate model run initialized at 0000 UTC 01 January 2000. The SSTs are prescribed using 20-year climatological (1982 to 2001) mean with monthly variations, downloaded from the NCAR website. Model is integrated for a period of 6 months. The first 2 months are discarded as spin-up. Model performance is evaluated against observations from Tropical Rain Measuring Mission (TRMM)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>, product 3B43 and Modern-Era Retrospective analysis for Research and Applications (MERRA)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> reanalysis data set. The CAM5 experiments were also conducted using different parameter combinations for manually tuned Zhang and McFarlane scheme for the same 6-month period. The manually tuned simulations with changes in the deep convective scheme were performed for 2
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> and 1
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> model resolutions. Due to limited computing resources the automated model tuning method (Downhill simplex method) was performed only at 1
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> model resolution and with India Meteorological Department (IMD)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup> land only data for precipitation.
</p>
