<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Interestingly, when focusing on sensitivity metrics related to species loss or temporal turnover, the uncertainty related to variation in SDMs is not necessarily larger than in GCMs and is lower than in RCPs, which is as expected. When researchers do not have the computational capability to implement a full treatment of uncertainty, focusing on those metrics might be an avenue. In terms of conservation planning, it also means that optimization algorithms that rather focus on securing diversity (both α- and β-diversities in a complementarity way) should be less affected by uncertainty from GCMs and SDMs. They should thus mostly concentrate their efforts on assessing the effects of emission scenarios. Alternatively, there are also alternative modelling techniques that explicitly focus on community-level metrics (i.e. pixel-based). Since those approaches do not rely on stacking individual SDM, they are less prone to bias coming from aggregating models with different quality
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. However, modelling α- and β-diversity explicitly is not as straightforward than modelling individual species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Similar analyses than the one proposed here but with community-level modelling approaches will be interesting to understand whether they are less influential on projection outputs than SDMs. In this study, we have also proposed novel ways of communicating both the uncertainties and their sources either per region, sub-region or pixel. This shall help pave the way to better communicate and map both the metric and the variance in this metric from the different sources of uncertainty. Yet, it shall also illustrate how the importance of these different sources varies in space and time and that conservation actions or biodiversity management should account for those variations. We have seen that sources of uncertainty can strongly vary in space depending on the quality of biodiversity models for some particular groups or the variability of projections among GCM (Supplementary Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">5</xref>–
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">8</xref>).
</p>
