<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">Biodiversity scenarios are not meant to predict the future precisely, but rather to project the range of possible futures allowing to better understand uncertainties and alternative visions of this future. These visions allow for considering how different political options, represented here by the RCPs, might influence the persistence of biodiversity under a wide range of possible futures. However, to be useful, one has to acknowledge also other sources of variations that may influence the overall modelling exercise
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. There are different types of biodiversity models, and here while considering only a single type (i.e. statistical SDM), we show that different algorithms could lead to substantial variability in the sensitivity metrics used. This variation may blur the utility of using several RCPs to discuss their impact on biodiversity persistence. This issue was long recognized in climate sciences such that it is no longer conceivable to show projected climatic trends from a single GCM only. Rather, ensembles of climate trajectories are usually shown (or least statistics thereof) and offered to users through data portals (e.g. CMIP5). The biodiversity modelling community needs to more consistently follow this path and report and communicate the variability resulting from the different options in biodiversity models (e.g. SDMs, dispersal scenarios) and input data (e.g. GCM, RCP). However, the range of biodiversity model types, algorithms, input data or parameterizations is so large that it seems currently impossible to report the variability even across biodiversity model types. However, we urge that variabilities originating from modelling algorithms, input data and external forces be assessed and reported comprehensively for better informing science, users and decision-makers in exploring options for the future.
</p>
