<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35" class="p">In order to identify the dominant influential factors on 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>, and considering that the soil temperature data sets do not report collocated measurements of soil properties at the Russian meteorological stations in the RHST dataset or the boreholes in the IPY dataset, we seek to extract soil information for these sites from the spatially explicit global/regional soil databases. To our knowledge, there are four such soil databases that are recent and/or widely used: HWSD
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>
 </sup>; WISE30sec
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup> (hereafter WISE); SoilGrids250m
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>
 </sup> (hereafter SoilGrids); and NCSCD
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Among them, WISE is developed based on HWSD, but includes updates on the mapping unit composition, adopts a consistent taxotransfer procedure, and provides information down to 2 m
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. We therefore used WISE instead of HWSD in this study. The SoilGrids product, unlike the other three databases that rely on soil classification maps to derive spatially explicit information, predicts soil properties using statistical methods from a list of covariates (climate, vegetation, topography, lithological units, etc), and thus can generate high-resolution maps (250 m) dependent on the resolution of input covariates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>
 </sup>. However, in a pre-processing, we found that SoilGrids gives a much higher SOC stock (in kg C m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>) than other databases in most grid cells in the northern hemisphere, and gives a global total SOC storage of 2757 Pg C for 0–1 m and 4570 Pg C for 0–2 m (calculated using their 250 m resolution map). This total SOC storage is almost twice the estimate by the majority of previous studies (see a short review in ref
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>.). Therefore, we did not use SoilGrids in this study.
</p>
