<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many important characteristics of precipitation are expected to change in response to climate forcing, including the mean, frequency, intensity, and spatial pattern. Current global climate models (GCMs) are able to capture expected global mean changes with some confidence (Allen &amp; Ingram, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Pendergrass &amp; Hartmann, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014a</xref>), and there is evidence that the multimodel mean follows the expected Clausius‐Clapeyron scaling (∼7% °C
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) of extremes on global scales (O'Gorman, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Pendergrass &amp; Hartmann, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014c</xref>). However, regional intensity changes are much less certain, especially over the tropics where the 99.9th percentile changes range from almost 0 to over 30% °C
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> across CMIP5 models, while observational constraints suggest the value should be close to 11% °C
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (O'Gorman, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Recent work has shown that not only are extreme rates uncertain in the tropics, but frequent moderate rates that produce the majority of accumulated surface rainfall also have major biases. In conventionally parameterized versions of the Community Atmosphere Model (CAM), moderate rates represented by the mode (i.e., the rain rate range associated with the most accumulated rainfall) and median (i.e., the rain rate where half the accumulated rainfall comes from more/less intense rates) of the rainfall amount distribution are significantly weaker than observed, particularly in regions of organized convection associated with the Madden Julian Oscillation (MJO), tropical waves, and monsoons (Kooperman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016a</xref>). Likewise, conventional versions of CAM simulate a much weaker response of moderate rates to climate forcing relative to superparameterized versions that represent convection with embedded cloud resolving models (Kooperman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016b</xref>).
</p>
