<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study included the collection of daily data using an ESM for five consecutive days. The study examined the positive relationship between day-level supervisor developmental feedback and employee voice. This is consistent with and further advances previous research concerning leadership and employee voice. Leadership has always been regarded as a critical antecedent to employee voice (
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">Detert and Burris, 2007</a>). Within the social exchange framework, the use of employee voice depends on the treatment received from supervisors. Supervisors offer qualitative information facilitating employee development, by providing developmental feedback. To reciprocate for supervisors’ positive treatment, employees provide change-oriented suggestions. Our research provided empirical evidence for this social exchange relationship on a daily basis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, we examined the underlying affect and relationship paths for the relationship between feedback and voice. The result showed that positive affect and perceived rapport mediated the positive influences of supervisor developmental feedback on employee voice at the episode level. Relationship and positive affect have always been regarded as motivation factors, increasing employee enthusiasm and triggering intrinsic motivations to improve the organizational 
  <span class="italic">status quo</span> (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung, 2012</a>). 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung (2012)</a> provided empirical evidence for the mediating roles of relationship and affect within the social exchange framework. Moreover, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Colquitt et al. (2013)</a> provided meta-analytic evidence for these two paths. Based on research of 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung (2012)</a> and 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Colquitt et al. (2013)</a>, we further tested the dual-path model, adopting a within-person approach.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">Lawler and Yoon (1996)</a> found that positive social exchange induced positive effect, which in turn increased relational cohesion and commitment behaviors. However, our research did not test the sequential mediation effects of positive affect and perceived rapport in the relationship between supervisor developmental feedback and employee voice. A potential reason for this is that important moderators may have been omitted in this study. The relationship between positive affect and perceived rapport was stronger when employee regarded supervisors’ support as stable and controllable (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lawler, 2001</a>). Therefore, it is critical to investigate the sequential relationship between positive affect and perceived rapport with a different research design involving potential moderators (e.g., supervisor authenticity).
 </p>
 <sec id="S5.SS1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical Implications</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our research contributes to the voice and SET literature in two ways. First, this study revealed the positive influences of supervisor developmental feedback on employee voice at the episode level, extending our understanding of the antecedents of voice. Given the importance of voice for both organizations and individuals, previous research focused on the relationship between supervisor behavior and voice (
   <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Mowbray et al., 2015</a>). However, those studies have not considered the influences of supervisors’ daily interaction with employees. In a daily organization context, supervisors’ managerial strategies are implemented and transferred through interaction with their employees (
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">Schaubroeck et al., 2016</a>). It is important to gain insights into this dynamic process to enhance managerial effectiveness.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study adopted supervisor developmental feedback, one of the basic supervisor interaction strategies, as an influencer of employee voice. Day-level supervisor developmental feedback enhances employees’ potential opportunities to develop and grow, by providing them with general rules about how to behave in organizations (
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>). In addition, supervisor developmental feedback can help create a positive team climate, free from pressure and fear of making mistakes. This can minimize the psychological costs of voice (
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Li et al., 2011</a>). Thus, driven by the reciprocal norm (
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Cropanzano and Mitchell, 2005</a>), employees are more likely to engage in voice to improve organizational effectiveness, returning the benefits offered by supervisors. Our research provides a new perspective on how voice is integrated in the daily interaction of supervisor–employee interaction, enlarging the scope of the voice literature.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, this study explored both the affect and relationship paths through which day-level supervisor developmental feedback influences day-level employee voice, contributing to SET. Within the SET framework, previous research provided evidence of the mediating role of relationship and affect at the between-person level (
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung, 2012</a>). However, few studies have explored these two mechanisms at the within-person level. Perceived rapport with supervisors or affect fluctuates on a daily basis. We advanced 
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Colquitt et al. (2013)</a> dual path social exchange model, by introducing the notion of daily within-person variations in employee positive affect and perceived rapport with supervisors. This study investigated whether the relationship and affect mechanisms that explain the employee voice associated with resource exchanges at the episode level are similar to those at the between-personal level. This adds to our knowledge of the dynamic social exchange process.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study found that supervisor developmental feedback provides employees valuable information and a positive climate, facilitating their growth in organizations (
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>). Day-level supervisor developmental feedback enhances employees’ positive affect and perceived rapport with supervisors. Consequently, positive affect and perceived rapport advance employee motivation and strengthen the ability to express voice. This study found no significant difference between affect and relationship path. Positive affect and perceived rapport have the same influences in facilitating the transformation from supervisor developmental feedback to employee voice. Our research advances SET by examining SET at the episode level.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S5.SS2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Practical Implications</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study has practical implications for managerial practices. First, daily developmental feedback by supervisors can support employees in finding their voices. In daily supervisor–employee interactions, the supervisor should provide developmental feedback, rather than simply performance feedback. However, managers should also focus on the characteristics of supervisor developmental feedback. Developmental feedback is informational in nature (
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>). Thus, when giving developmental feedback to employees, managers should provide clear information, to enhance the positive influences associated with supervisor developmental feedback (
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Li et al., 2011</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, by considering positive affect and perceived rapport as mediators, this study revealed that managers should be alert to employees’ positive affect and perceived rapport induced by supervisor developmental feedback. Once employees’ positive and perceived rapport increases, their motivation and ability are both strengthened, encouraging them to express their voice. Thus, managers should be responsible for maintaining and enhancing their employees’ positive affect and perceived rapport.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S5.SS3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations and Future Research</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Like all studies, this research had some limitations. First, common method variance (CMV) remains a concern (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">Fuller et al., 2016</a>). While the study adopted a two-wave ESM, all the data were collected from a self-report questionnaire, increasing the risk of a CMV problem. Future studies should assess voice from the perspective of supervisors or colleagues, to rule out CMV and to test the robustness of these results.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, we cannot infer causal relationships between our focal variables. We attempted to establish a firm causal effect between supervisor developmental feedback on employee voice using multi-wave diary analysis. However, a reverse causal effect remains a possibility. A different experimental design may support the development of firm causal results.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third, 
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Lawler and Thye (1999)</a> proposed that an individual’s emotional state is the starting point of a relationship. 
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">Sears and Hackett (2011)</a> provided empirical evidence for the positive relationship between positive affect and LMX. To consider the implicit influence of positive affect on perceived rapport, we collected data at different time points in a day. However, the current study did not provide significant support for this relationship (γ = 0.133, n.s.). This outcome aligns with findings by 
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung (2012)</a> and 
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Colquitt et al. (2013)</a>, which also found that the relationship and affect paths are independent. Thus, future studies should examine potential boundary conditions to assess the relationship between these two paths.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fourth, this research adopted a two-wave ESM design to collect data at 10:00 A.M. and 17:00 P.M. to explore the relationship between supervisor development feedback and employee voice and its underlying mechanism based on previous research. However, the daily self-report experiences (e.g., positive affect and perceived rapport with supervisors) fluctuate within a workday. Our research did not capture the influence of the variations in our focal variables. Future research could combine an ecological momentary assessment and an ESM to offer a more comprehensive insight into the dynamic social exchange process.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
