<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hypothesis Development</div>
 <sec id="S2.SS1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor Developmental Feedback and Employee Voice</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The definition of supervisor developmental feedback provided by 
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou (2003)</a> suggests that it includes three specific characteristics. First, feedback is informational in nature. Supervisor developmental feedback is useful and provides valuable information for employees, facilitating improvements on the job. Second, supervisor developmental feedback is future-oriented, focusing on the employees’ growth in the organization, rather than on the discrepancies between anticipated goals and achieved outcomes. Third, developmental feedback is well suited to creating a positive team climate, free from fear of making mistakes (
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>; 
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Li et al., 2011</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Employee voice is risky and costly, because it challenges the 
   <span class="italic">status quo</span> and places stress on existing workplace relationship (
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">Ng and Feldman, 2012</a>). Previous research has indicated that whether employees render voice or not depends on supervisors’ supportive behavior (
   <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">Zhang et al., 2015</a>). Supervisor developmental feedback reveals supervisors’ genuine care and attention, which nurtures employees’ sense of gratitude and indebtedness. This ensures a reciprocal interpersonal relationship and further motivating them to voice to provide change-oriented suggestions to the organizations as a way of reciprocating for the positive treatment they have received from their supervisors (
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">Carnevale et al., 2017</a>). Furthermore, the agreeable team climate created by supervisor developmental feedback strengthens employee psychological safety, which has been examined as a critical motivator of employee voice. Research has provided firm empirical evidence for the relationship between supervisor support and employee voice within social exchange framework (
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Liang et al., 2012</a>; 
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Liu et al., 2017</a>). For example, 
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">Carnevale et al. (2017)</a> argue that a supervisor facilitates employees’ proactive attempts to express their voice by offering valuable resources. Thus, we hypothesized the following:
  </p>
  <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I1" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Hypothesis 1. Supervisor developmental feedback (morning) relates to day-level employee voice.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S2.SS2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mediating Role of Perceived Rapport With Supervisors</div>
  <sec id="S2.SS2.SSS1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor Developmental Feedback and Perceived Rapport With Supervisors</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived rapport is the immediate subjective outcome of interaction with the supervisor (
    <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">Curhan et al., 2006</a>). Rapport is composed of two factors: feelings about the process and feelings about the relationship. Feelings about the process include perceptions that the employees have been justly treated and heard, and that the interaction process with supervisors is efficient. Feelings about the relationship include the positive impressions of and trust toward the supervisors. This creates a solid foundation for working and interacting with the supervisors in the future (
    <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Curhan et al., 2010</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social exchange theory is relational in nature (
    <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Cropanzano and Mitchell, 2005</a>). Previous research has adopted leader–member exchange (LMX) to indicate the relationship between supervisor and employee in the social exchange process (
    <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">Reb et al., 2018</a>). LMX is a two-way interaction, in which a supervisor and an employee deliberately exchange tangible or intangible resources relevant to work tasks and social intentions (
    <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">Sheer, 2015</a>). Given the daily supervisor–subordinate interaction context, subordinates form perceptions of relationship quality with supervisors based on the subjective experiences. This is the dynamic foundation for LMX (
    <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Selvarajan et al., 2018</a>). This study’s goal was to examine the underlying mechanism through which supervisor developmental feedback influences employee voice at the episode level. As such, the study adopted perceived rapport, instead of LMX, as the proxy mediator between supervisor developmental feedback and employee voice.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the arguments above, we proposed that supervisor developmental feedback influences perceived rapport by enhancing feelings about the process and feelings about the relationship. Feelings about the process involve employees’ perceptions of procedural and interpersonal justice with respect to communication with supervisors (
    <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">Curhan et al., 2006</a>). SET suggests that employees tend to recognize the quality of treatment received through exchanges with supervisors as an indicator of perceived justice (
    <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">Lee and Jensen, 2014</a>). The provision of feedback to employees is an important process, as it allows supervisors to influence employees’ perceptions of justice (
    <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Karkoulian et al., 2016</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor developmental feedback is future-oriented, focusing on employee improvement on the job (
    <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>). Developmental feedback reveals a supervisor’s care for an employee’s career growth. It involves devoting valuable resources to reward appropriate behavior (
    <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>). As such, employees will feel respect and that they are treated with sensitivity when receiving supervisor developmental feedback. This strengthens their perceptions of justice toward the communication process.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feelings about the relationship include positive impressions of and trust toward supervisors. Employees develop trust toward their supervisors when they attribute the supervisors’ behavior to sincere motives and selflessness (
    <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Chen et al., 2014</a>). Further, they develop positive impressions toward their supervisors, based on the supervisors’ demonstration of character. Developmental feedback reveals supervisors’ expressions of sincere and holistic concern about their employees’ personal welfare. Thus, supervisor developmental feedback is likely to trigger employees’ gratitude and indebtedness, ensuring reciprocal supervisor–employee relations and firm affective bonds of trust. Thus, we hypothesized the following:
   </p>
   <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I2" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Hypothesis 2. Day-level supervisor developmental feedback (morning) positively relates to day-level perceived rapport.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec id="S2.SS2.SSS2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived Rapport With Supervisors and Employee Voice</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trust toward supervisors and perceptions of justice are two core factors associated with perceived rapport (
    <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Curhan et al., 2010</a>). Previous research has shown a positive relationship between perceived rapport and sequential active behavior (
    <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">Curhan et al., 2009</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Voice means challenging the 
    <span class="italic">status quo</span>, placing stress on existing team relationships (
    <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Morrison, 2014</a>). Trust in supervisors is a psychological state and includes positive expectations about the supervisor’s intentions or behaviors when they engage in taking risks (
    <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Gao et al., 2011</a>). Trust in supervisors signals a strong sense of sharing within the relationship, where employees tend to exhibit new ideas and concerns without fear of being ridiculed (
    <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Chen et al., 2014</a>). 
    <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Gao et al. (2011)</a> argued that when employees have a high level of trust in their supervisors, employees will engage in voice, even when it means taking extra risks.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived rapport also involves perceptions of justice toward interaction with supervisors. When employees perceive that supervisors treat them with dignity and respect in daily encounters, they are more likely to engage in voice (
    <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">Takeuchi et al., 2012</a>). A high level of perceived rapport communicates that supervisors consider employee needs and that supervisors are willing to develop and maintain an ongoing relationship with them (
    <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">Tyler and Lind, 1992</a>). In such a context, employees are likely to be broadly and deeply invested in this relationship, and work beyond their formal job descriptions in return. For example, this may involve initiating changes in organizations (
    <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">George and Brief, 1992</a>; 
    <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">Zhang et al., 2015</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, we hypothesized the following:</p>
   <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I3" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Hypothesis 3. Day-level perceived rapport relates to day-level employee voice.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor developmental feedback provides valuable information to employees, fostering their development in organizations and job-related improvements. This feedback helps create a positive team climate, free from pressure and fear of making mistakes (
    <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>; 
    <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Li et al., 2011</a>). Thus, in daily encounters, supervisor developmental feedback nurtures employee perceptions of justice and trust in supervisors, enhancing perceived rapport. In turn, when employees develop perceived rapport based on a supervisor’s demonstration of developmental feedback, the relationship becomes more of a social exchange. Once they regard their relationships with their supervisors as beyond the traditional economic exchange relationship, they are more likely to reciprocate the supervisor developmental feedback. This is done by expressing constructive suggestions and concerns, oriented toward facilitating organizational effectiveness. 
    <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">Zhang et al. (2015)</a> found that supervisor expression of genuine and holistic concerns toward employees develop high-quality relationships that encourage discretionary expressions of employee voice. Following the logic of SET, we developed the following hypothesis:
   </p>
   <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I4" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Hypothesis 4. Day-level perceived rapport mediates the relationship between day-level supervisor developmental feedback (morning) and day-level employee voice.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S2.SS3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mediating Role of Positive Affect</div>
  <sec id="S2.SS3.SSS1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor Developmental Feedback and Positive Affect</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive affect is a relatively short-lived positive evaluative state, with neurological and cognitive elements (
    <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Lawler and Thye, 1999</a>). Positive affect is immediate, internal, and involuntary. It is produced by the results of a social exchange process (
    <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">Weiner, 1985</a>). Beneficially initiating social exchange actions can engender positive affect (
    <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">Cropanzano et al., 2017</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When receiving developmental feedback, employees are likely to be immersed in their current jobs, pay attention to skill mastery (
    <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>), and capture potential opportunities to achieve career growth in organizations. Increasing expectations of career success in organizations enhances employees’ positive affect in the workplace (
    <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Kidd, 2004</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, supervisor developmental feedback is meant to enhance employees’ learning and development in the future (
    <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Li et al., 2011</a>). This also signals employees that their supervisors support and care about the benefits they provide the organization. From a social exchange perspective, supervisors’ expressions of sincere concerns about followers’ personal welfare will induce employees’ positive affect in the relationship (
    <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung, 2012</a>). 
    <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Fredrickson (2003)</a> suggested that positive affect occurs in safe and comfortable circumstances. 
    <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Heled et al. (2016)</a> discovered a positive relationship between beneficial team climate and employees’ positive emotional state. Integrating arguments above, we hypothesized the following:
   </p>
   <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I5" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Hypothesis 5. Day-level supervisor developmental feedback (morning) positively relates to day-level positive affect (morning).</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec id="S2.SS3.SSS2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive Affect and Employee Voice</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Morrison (2014)</a> suggested that voice often stems from automatic processes. Voice is consistently preceded by an intense emotional episode. Individual affect plays a vital role in shaping employee voice.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a “broaden and build” perspective, positive affect expands individual thinking, attention, and behavioral repertories. This helps employees build social and psychological resources (
    <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Fredrickson, 2003</a>). Positive affect provides employees with more flexible cognition and the ability to integrate diverse materials (
    <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Isen, 1998</a>). When experiencing positive affect, employees are more likely to connect and integrate divergent stimulating content and produce more creative solutions to organization problems (
    <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">George and Brief, 1992</a>). Positive affect strengthens employees’ abilities to express their voice.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From an affect infusion perspective, positive affect drives the individual to regard the workplace as safe and to believe that everything is going well (
    <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Liu et al., 2017</a>). Voice is risky and costly, and it can only be practiced strategically (
    <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">Ng and Feldman, 2012</a>). An employee can only engage in voice if they feel psychologically safe (
    <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Liang et al., 2012</a>). Research has shown that employees experiencing positive affect believe favorable outcomes are more likely, and perceive others more positively (
    <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Liu et al., 2017</a>). In such context, employees do not fear punishment when the expression of voice does not play out as desired.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social exchange theory proposes that positive affect is an internal self-reinforcing stimulus, leading employees to reciprocate the socioemotional benefits their supervisors offer in the social exchange relationship (
    <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lawler, 2001</a>). This motivates employees to go beyond their job roles, engaging in extra-role behavior that enhances organization effectiveness (
    <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Chen et al., 2014</a>). In addition, positive affect provides a greater ability to express voice. Based on this logic, we hypothesized the following:
   </p>
   <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I6" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Hypothesis 6. Day-level positive affect (morning) positively relates to day-level employee voice.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung (2012)</a> found that when working with a supervisor who is more willing to share information and express their thoughts, employees are more likely to experience positive moods. This contributes to strengthening employee voice. Supervisor developmental feedback offers guidance to employees about how to achieve career growth in organizations, nurturing their positive affect. In turn, positive affect acts as a subtle signal to employees about their active response in this social exchange interaction. Given an increased ability and motivation to exercise voice, employees are motivated to render a constructive voice, benefitting broader organization goals. Therefore, we propose the following hypothesis:
   </p>
   <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I7" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>Hypothesis 7. Day-level positive affect (morning) mediates the relationship between day-level supervisor-provided developmental feedback (morning) and day-level employee voice.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
