<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S2.SS3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mediating Role of Positive Affect</div>
 <sec id="S2.SS3.SSS1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor Developmental Feedback and Positive Affect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive affect is a relatively short-lived positive evaluative state, with neurological and cognitive elements (
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Lawler and Thye, 1999</a>). Positive affect is immediate, internal, and involuntary. It is produced by the results of a social exchange process (
   <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">Weiner, 1985</a>). Beneficially initiating social exchange actions can engender positive affect (
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">Cropanzano et al., 2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When receiving developmental feedback, employees are likely to be immersed in their current jobs, pay attention to skill mastery (
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou, 2003</a>), and capture potential opportunities to achieve career growth in organizations. Increasing expectations of career success in organizations enhances employees’ positive affect in the workplace (
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Kidd, 2004</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, supervisor developmental feedback is meant to enhance employees’ learning and development in the future (
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Li et al., 2011</a>). This also signals employees that their supervisors support and care about the benefits they provide the organization. From a social exchange perspective, supervisors’ expressions of sincere concerns about followers’ personal welfare will induce employees’ positive affect in the relationship (
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung, 2012</a>). 
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Fredrickson (2003)</a> suggested that positive affect occurs in safe and comfortable circumstances. 
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Heled et al. (2016)</a> discovered a positive relationship between beneficial team climate and employees’ positive emotional state. Integrating arguments above, we hypothesized the following:
  </p>
  <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I5" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Hypothesis 5. Day-level supervisor developmental feedback (morning) positively relates to day-level positive affect (morning).</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S2.SS3.SSS2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive Affect and Employee Voice</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Morrison (2014)</a> suggested that voice often stems from automatic processes. Voice is consistently preceded by an intense emotional episode. Individual affect plays a vital role in shaping employee voice.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a “broaden and build” perspective, positive affect expands individual thinking, attention, and behavioral repertories. This helps employees build social and psychological resources (
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Fredrickson, 2003</a>). Positive affect provides employees with more flexible cognition and the ability to integrate diverse materials (
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Isen, 1998</a>). When experiencing positive affect, employees are more likely to connect and integrate divergent stimulating content and produce more creative solutions to organization problems (
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">George and Brief, 1992</a>). Positive affect strengthens employees’ abilities to express their voice.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From an affect infusion perspective, positive affect drives the individual to regard the workplace as safe and to believe that everything is going well (
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Liu et al., 2017</a>). Voice is risky and costly, and it can only be practiced strategically (
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">Ng and Feldman, 2012</a>). An employee can only engage in voice if they feel psychologically safe (
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Liang et al., 2012</a>). Research has shown that employees experiencing positive affect believe favorable outcomes are more likely, and perceive others more positively (
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Liu et al., 2017</a>). In such context, employees do not fear punishment when the expression of voice does not play out as desired.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social exchange theory proposes that positive affect is an internal self-reinforcing stimulus, leading employees to reciprocate the socioemotional benefits their supervisors offer in the social exchange relationship (
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lawler, 2001</a>). This motivates employees to go beyond their job roles, engaging in extra-role behavior that enhances organization effectiveness (
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Chen et al., 2014</a>). In addition, positive affect provides a greater ability to express voice. Based on this logic, we hypothesized the following:
  </p>
  <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I6" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Hypothesis 6. Day-level positive affect (morning) positively relates to day-level employee voice.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung (2012)</a> found that when working with a supervisor who is more willing to share information and express their thoughts, employees are more likely to experience positive moods. This contributes to strengthening employee voice. Supervisor developmental feedback offers guidance to employees about how to achieve career growth in organizations, nurturing their positive affect. In turn, positive affect acts as a subtle signal to employees about their active response in this social exchange interaction. Given an increased ability and motivation to exercise voice, employees are motivated to render a constructive voice, benefitting broader organization goals. Therefore, we propose the following hypothesis:
  </p>
  <div list-type="simple" id="S2.I7" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Hypothesis 7. Day-level positive affect (morning) mediates the relationship between day-level supervisor-provided developmental feedback (morning) and day-level employee voice.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
