<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="S3.SS1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples and Procedure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the research purpose, this study adopted the experience sampling method (ESM) to collect data for analysis. We recruited our participants through alumni networks of our college. We first selected 187 of the alumni who volunteered, who updated their contact information and work background within the past 2 years. We then randomly chose 151 participants who worked full hours per week in China. We coded them from 1 to 151 and applied a random number generator in Microsoft Excel to choose 100 initial participants to invite for the survey process. We contacted participants through email, social apps, and telephone to request study participation. Of the initial 100 participants, 69 alumni confirmed their participation in our research. We explained the research purpose and procedure, and then formed a research group on WeChat, a social app.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the first Sunday of the sampling period, we sent study participants a website link to our initial questionnaire (including code, gender, education, and tenure). To better infer the causal relationship between our focal variables, we collected data from two time points (e.g., 10:00 A.M. and 17:00 P.M.) according to the research of 
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">Qin et al. (2018)</a>. From the following Monday to Friday, participants received a questionnaire at 10:00 A.M. (supervisor developmental feedback and positive affect) and a questionnaire at 17:00 P.M. (perceived rapport with supervisors and employee voice). Based on the potential influences of positive affect on perceived rapport with the supervisor (
   <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lawler, 2001</a>), we provided the survey related to positive affect in the morning, and the survey of perceived rapport in the afternoon. Using this process, we collected 310 matched data nested across 62 people for 5 consecutive days. Five participants failed to finish the initial survey.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study participants worked in a variety of industries in mainland China, including financial services, Internet companies, and manufacturing. This ensured sample representativeness. Male participants represented 48.4% of all subjects; 11.3% held degrees of college and below; 41.9% held bachelor degrees; and 46.8% held master’s degrees and above. The mean tenure in the current organizations was 8.218 (
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = ±7.602).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S3.SS2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A self-reported five-point Likert scale was used in the study: 1 indicated “strongly disagree” and 5 indicated “totally agree,” if there was not a special explanation. All items were translated into Chinese using a back translation procedure (
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">Brislin, 1970</a>), ensuring translation accuracy.
  </p>
  <sec id="S3.SS2.SSS1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervisor Developmental Feedback</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the three-item scale developed by 
    <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Zhou (2003)</a> to measure supervisor developmental feedback. A sample item was “Today my supervisor focused on helping me to learn and improve while giving me feedback.” The Cronbach’s α for this scale was 0.941.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="S3.SS2.SSS2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Voice</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The four-item voice scale, developed by 
    <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">Van Dyne and LePine (1998)</a> based on the research of 
    <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">Lebel (2016)</a>, was used to measure employee voice. A sample item was: “Today I spoke up with concerns about work not being done effectively.” The scale yielded a Cronbach’s α of 0.871. The study adopted self-reported questionnaires, rather than supervisor-reported questionnaires, to measure voice. This is because in ESM, it is difficult for supervisors to differentiate employee voice on a daily basis (
    <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">Carpenter et al., 2014</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="S3.SS2.SSS3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive Affect</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 20-item Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS) scale was adopted to measure daily positive affect. The current adopted five items with highest loadings in the positive affect scale (e.g., Enthusiastic, Interested, Determined, Excited, and Inspired). The Cronbach’s α for this scale was 0.909.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="S3.SS2.SSS4" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived Rapport</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We adapted four items from the rapport dimension of the Subjective Value Inventory (SVI), developed by 
    <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">Curhan et al. (2006)</a>. The four items were “Did your supervisor consider your wishes, opinions, or needs today?”; “Do you feel your supervisor listened to your concerns today?”; “How satisfied are you with your relationship with your supervisor as a result of the communication today?”; and “Does the communication today make you trust your supervisor?” Items were rated on a five-point scale, ranging from “1 = not at all” to “5 = a great deal.” The Cronbach’s α of this scale was 0.927.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="S3.SS2.SSS5" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control Variables</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We incorporated gender (coded as 0 for male and 1 for female), education (coded as 1 for college and below, 2 for bachelor, and 3 for master and above), and tenure in the current organization (years), based on their potential influence on our results (
    <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hsiung, 2012</a>; 
    <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">Duan et al., 2017</a>; 
    <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">Qian et al., 2018</a>). Following the suggestion of 
    <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">Aguinis and Vandenberg (2014)</a>, we conducted separate analyses with and without the control variables. The results were virtually the same, and removing the control variables from the equation models did not alter the interpretation of the findings. Thus, we reported the results without control variables in this study.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S3.SS3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytical Approach</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We collected data at the between-person level (gender, education, and tenure) and at the within-person level (supervisor developmental feedback, positive affect, perceived rapport, and employee voice) from our samples. Considering the nested nature of our data, we adopted multilevel data modeling (
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">Raudenbush and Bryk, 2002</a>) for the analysis. We applied Mplus 7.4 (
   <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">Muthén and Muthén, 1998/2012</a>) software, using a restricted maximum likelihood estimation method for the analysis. Based on previous research, the multilevel path analysis was effective to test our conceptual model (
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">Koopman et al., 2016</a>), because it permitted a simultaneous examination of the underlying affect (i.e., positive affect) and relationship (i.e., perceived rapport) paths through which daily supervisor developmental feedback impacted employee voice.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first stage of hypothesis testing was to investigate the systematic within- and between-person variance for the daily variables. The proportion of within-person variance for voice was 23%; for supervisor developmental feedback, it was 26%; for positive affect, it was 34%; and for perceived rapport, it was 29%. These results justified the use of multilevel analysis. We ran the multilevel path analysis with multiple mediators with random slope and used robust estimators indicated the within-person effect. Before the regression analysis, all the daily variables were group centered.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
