<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Daily precipitation projections (mm/day) for Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5 for January 5, 2020 to December 26, 2099 were obtained online from the Pacific Climate Impacts Consortium (PCIC) data portal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Twelve sets of projections were obtained. PCIC derives these projections by statistical downscaling of 12 global climate models (GCMs) (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) from the Coupled Model Inter-comparison Project Phase 5 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The downscaled projections were generated using monthly bias-correction and spatial disaggregation (BCSD), a methodology commonly used in hydrologic modeling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. RCPs represent a range of greenhouse gas (GHG) concentration scenarios up to 2100, based on assumptions about economic activity, energy sources, population growth and other socio-economic factors. RCP 8.5 is a ‘status quo’ scenario characterized by increasing GHG emissions over time leading to high GHG concentration levels up to the year 2100 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The precipitation projections for RCP 8.5 entered Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) as projected mean weekly precipitation (
 <italic>w</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub>) at the grid corresponding to the geographic coordinates of N49.44, W-122.97 decimal degrees (i.e. the corresponding grid point near the Seymour Dam used in our historical precipitation data). The expected cases derived from model (1) were aggregated to annual counts and compared to historical annual counts as the percent change (from historical) in annual incidence of disease during the 2020s (2020–2039), 2040s (2040–2059), 2060s (2060–2079), and 2080s (2080–2099). The results are presented using the ensemble mean of all 12 projections along with the minimum and maximum to represent natural climate variability and uncertainty across climate models. 
</p>
