<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35215-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marsh phenology modeling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use the longest continuous satellite record of the Earth's ecosystems, the Landsat CDRs from 1984 to 2014, to create the phenological records of the marshes (Table 
  <a rid="ece35215-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#ece35215-tbl-0002">A1</a>). The data are collected by three Landsat series satellites: (a) the Landsat 5 equipped with the Thematic Mapper (TM) that launched in 1984 and decommissioned in 2011; (b) the Landsat 7 equipped with the Enhanced Thematic Mapper Plus (ETM+) that launched in 1999; and (c) the Landsat 8 equipped with the Operational Land Imager (OLI) that launched in 2013. All three sensors have a 30‐m spatial resolution and a 16‐day temporal revisit cycle. The study area locates within the Landsat scenes of Path 22 Row 40 and Path 22 Row 39. There are 359 relatively cloudless images (mosaics of the two Landsat scenes) used for the phenology modeling.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) values are calculated as a proxy for the marshes' aboveground biomass (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.7; Mo, Kearney, Riter, Zhao, &amp; Tilley, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0031">2018</a>), and the NDVI‐based phenological records of the marshes are modeled using an advanced modeling technique, the nonlinear mixed model (Mo, Momen, &amp; Kearney, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0032">2015</a>). This method is developed by Mo et al. (
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0032">2015</a>) to provide a rigorous statistical analysis for phenological curves of different vegetation that are represented by nonlinear functions with repeated‐measure variables. Phenological measurements (i.e., the NDVI) made on the same observational units (i.e., marsh systems) over time are treated as repeated measurements. The phenological records of the different marsh systems are fitted into three nonlinear models, the Gaussian, the stepwise Gaussian, and the stepwise logistic functions. The goodness‐of‐fit of the models is assessed via the Efron's pseudo 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> and the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC), the Akaike Information Criterion Correction (AICC), and the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). The pseudo 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>, a statistic similar to 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> in the linear regression, indicates the percent variance explained by the nonlinear models (Hardin, Hilbe, &amp; Hilbe, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0019">2007</a>). The pseudo 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> ranges from −∞ to 1. A pseudo 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> closer to 1 indicates more variability in the data is explained. The AIC, AICC, and BIC indices evaluate models based on the principle of parsimony, that is, a model explains more variation in the data with fewer variables is considered a better fit (Boyce, Vernier, Nielsen, &amp; Schmiegelow, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0003">2002</a>; Richards, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0045">2005</a>). Key phenological parameters, that is, peak NDVI, peak NDVI day, and growing season length (bracketing days that had NDVI &gt;90% of peak NDVI) for each marsh system in each year are estimated from the best‐fit model. The phenology modeling only considered existing marshes, that is, it is corrected for the marsh area changes over the 30 years.
 </p>
</sec>
