<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35215-sec-0013" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The marshes' phenological changes in the last 30 years</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlations between the growing season length and the atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration may be the result of the stimulation of elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration on photosynthesis in marsh plants (Cherry, McKee, &amp; Grace, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0007">2009</a>; Rasse, Peresta, &amp; Drake, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0043">2005</a>). This is the first study we know of that reports a positive correlation between atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration and coastal marshes' growing season length, which reflects a broad pattern of ecosystem change due to a changing climate (Walther et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0056">2002</a>). The various responses among marsh systems are likely to reflect the different physiological characteristics of the marsh plants. The intermediate and brackish marshes have a high percentage of C3 plants, whereas saline marshes are mostly C4 plants. Elevated atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> promotes the plant growth of C3 marsh species, for example, 
  <span class="italic">Schoenoplectus americanus</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Scirpus maritimus</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Scirpus olneyi</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Puccinellia maritima</span>, but does not enhance, or even impairs, the plant growth of C4 species, for example, 
  <span class="italic">Distichlis spicata</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Spartina alterniflora</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Spartina patens</span> (Arp, Drake, Pockman, Curtis, &amp; Whigham, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0001">1993</a>; Cherry et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0007">2009</a>; Drake, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0012">2014</a>; Erickson et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0015">2007</a>; Rasse et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0043">2005</a>). This is because the increased atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> stimulates photosynthesis of C3 plants, but not the photosynthesis of C4 plants that is nearly saturated under ambient conditions as C4 plants concentrate CO
  <sub>2</sub> at the site with their primary CO
  <sub>2</sub>‐fixing enzyme. Moreover, the elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> may even inhibit the plant growth of C4 species by reducing their stomatal conductance, transpiration, and ion uptake (Ghannoum, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0016">2009</a>; Rozema et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0046">1991</a>). Yet, the freshwater marshes, which have the highest percentage of C3 plants among the different marsh systems, demonstrate no response to higher CO
  <sub>2</sub> levels in our study. One possible explanation is that the high nutrient loading in freshwater marshes—freshwater marshes are closest to the surface runoff—favors species that are unresponsive to elevated atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> (Langley &amp; Megonigal, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0026">2010</a>; Langley et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0027">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global warming has a general effect of promoting plant growth that is manifested in increasing the growing season NDVI and lengthening the active growth season, especially in the middle and high latitudes (Myneni, Keeling, Tucker, Asrar, &amp; Nemani, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0035">1997</a>; Zhou et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0061">2001</a>). Although it was reported that warming increased the annual peak biomass of the marshes in Massachusetts, USA (Charles &amp; Dukes, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0006">2009</a>), this study did not find a similar effect of temperature on the peak NDVI nor on the growing season length of the marshes in Louisiana. This result might be expected because the ambient temperatures in Louisiana (at latitudes around 30ºN) are already close to the optimum conditions for the marsh growth.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indeed, the linear models used in this study are highly simplified. These models do not consider other environmental factors, such as water temperature and nutrient availability, which can vary substantially with in situ conditions, or the nonlinear effects and the interactions among the different factors. For instance, the enhancement of CO
  <sub>2</sub> uptake by C3 plants may be eventually slowed down by photosynthetic downregulation, nutrient limitations, or increased disturbance from sea‐level rise, thus the CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization on the marshes will not continue over long time frames as decades (Erickson et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0015">2007</a>; Langley et al., 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0027">2013</a>). In addition, the marshes may suffer from other stresses such as pests, herbivores, and pathogens that can also be intensified by a warmer climate (Van der Putten, Macel, &amp; Visser, 
  <a rid="ece35215-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35215-bib-0055">2010</a>). Nevertheless, this study provides a “baseline” scenario for future marsh phenology with unconstrained sole impacts from temperature or CO
  <sub>2</sub>, as well as observational inputs for more advanced modeling studies.
 </p>
</sec>
