<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For evaluating changes in health costs we apply the cost-of-illness approach, which distinguishes between direct and indirect cost components [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] and intangible costs. Direct costs refer to costs for medical procedures and services for treatment and care of a disease. They can further be divided into direct medical and direct non-medical costs (cf. Le et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]). The former include medical treatment (in hospital or outside) and medicine while the latter include costs of transportation of patients and family members, costs of accommodation during visits etc. The latter costs are mainly borne by households privately and could not be appraised due to lack of data. Indirect costs refer to productivity losses due to morbidity and mortality. Intangible costs are controversial as they refer to costs from e.g., pain, anxiety or the hypothetical costs for the value of life lost. While former studies value premature death by means of the value of statistical life (VSL) there is growing recognition that it is more meaningful to value changes in life expectancy and to apply the value of life year (VOLY), especially for air pollution, which shortens everyone’s life to some extent [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Desaigues et al. [
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] conducted a large contingent valuation study for European countries and recommend a value of 40,000 € per life year lost due to premature death (Years of Life Lost, YLL) and disease (Years Lived with Disability, YLD) expressing the willingness to pay for extending one’s life expectancy. We multiply a VOLY of 43,000 € which is adjusted by the Austrian CPI (consumer price index) value of 7.9% [
 <xref rid="B59-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>] for the base year 2010 by changes in YLL and YLD due to increased physical activity and improved air quality. This value is a conservative one as other European studies use higher values e.g., 50,000 € from ExternE [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] or 60,000 € from the HEIMTSA study [
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. In a sensitivity analysis we calculate the economic effects for a higher VOLY and compare them to the VSL results (applying a value of 1,650,000 € [
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>] for changes in death cases).
</p>
