<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is having a great impact on the Arctic environment
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>. Increasing air temperatures cause longer periods of ground thawing and changes in precipitation affect the hydrology and the amounts of oxygen that diffuse into the ground with impact on the microbial decomposition of organic carbon
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>. The until now well-preserved archaeological deposits may thereby be exposed to accelerated degradation that destroys the integrity of stratified layers and leads to the loss of key elements such as archaeological wood, bone and ancient DNA. While the physical destruction due to e.g. coastal erosion has been studied to some extent
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>, very little is known about how climate change affects the microbial degradation of organic archaeological deposits and therefore the extent of this threat to our common heritage remains largely unknown. To our knowledge, the coupling between climate change and the degradation of organic archaeological deposits has only been studied at one site in the Arctic, i.e. the Qajaa kitchen midden in the Disco Bay area in Greenland. Results from Qajaa have shown that even a small increase in soil temperature may lead to substantial degradation of the buried remains
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>. Furthermore, the organic-rich archaeological deposits at Qajaa produce enough heat during decomposition to further increase soil temperatures and consequently accelerate the rate at which the organic matter is degraded
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>. So far it is unknown whether these results are site-specific or whether the many well-preserved organic archaeological deposits located in other Arctic areas are equally vulnerable.
</p>
