<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Finally, as in any other model, our results are linked to how climate change and drought were parameterised. The fact that gradual climate change drove the long-term dynamics of community structure is linked to climate change effects being kept until the end of the simulation, while drought events ended before the stabilisation phase. This enabled testing whether drought effects (on top of climate change) would be long lasting, even after ceasing drought events. Even if our results cannot be verified on the long term, we defend that designing best- and worst-case scenarios, as we did here, aids our understanding of how drought may impact ecosystem stability in the future [
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Furthermore, the results obtained using our model and parameterisation agreed with those obtained by others in field studies. Hence, although lack of data prevented us from using a trait-based approach to drought simulation, we trust that our statistical approach reflects the general drought tolerance of these PFGs. Especially considering that PFG responses to drought were parametrised and validated in collaboration with botanists working within the study area. Finally, other drivers, such as carbon, nutrient and water cycles and pest outbreaks are known to interact with drought in affecting vegetation dynamics [
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. We could expect stronger drought effects if these factors were to be included in our model; yet, unfortunately, we do not currently have the data that would enable us to simulate these processes at large spatial scales and across multiple plant groups. Existing dynamic vegetation models, like LANDIS-II, have been coupled to carbon, nutrient and water cycle models (see e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]), but also insect outbreak dynamics [
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. These models focus on forest stand dynamics and future work is needed to expand them to other ecosystems, as responses can vary across vegetation types [
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Doing so requires systematic quantification how different plant groups respond to and affect these bio-geochemical cycles and pest dynamics, which is still lacking [
 <xref rid="pone.0206138.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>].
</p>
