<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Temperature and precipitation play a vital role for all living systems, and in particular, plants are sensitive to climatic variations during the growing season. It has long been known that during summer, temperature and precipitation are generally anticorrelated at interannual scales (
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">23</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>). A global analysis reveals that precipitation and temperature averaged over the warmest 3 months (denoted by “warm season” in the remainder of the article) are strongly negatively correlated in many land regions of the world (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). This negative correlation, prevalent in most models (fig. S1), is to a large extent driven by land surface feedbacks (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">26</italic>
 </xref>), associated with impacts of soil moisture limitation on surface temperature (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">27</italic>
 </xref>). These feedbacks tend to be dominant in transitional climate regimes between dry and wet climates (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">28</italic>
 </xref>) and also include interactions with boundary layer processes (
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">29</italic>
 </xref>). In addition, synoptic-scale correspondence between cloud cover/precipitation and incoming shortwave radiation can play a role (
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">26</italic>
 </xref>). Regions with a particularly high negative correlation include the southeastern United States, the Amazon region, southern Africa, western Russia, large parts of India, and northern Australia. Over ocean regions, this correlation is often positive, in particular, for regions affected by El Niño, indicating that ocean conditions drive the atmosphere (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>). The negative correlation between temperature and precipitation during the warm season over land should lead to an occurrence rate of hot and dry summers that is higher than if both variables were uncorrelated. Here, we focus on land only and aim at quantifying this effect. Furthermore, because of their wide-ranging impacts, detecting and quantifying changes in the co-occurrence of extremes in temperature and precipitation (
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">30</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">31</italic>
 </xref>) under a warming climate are important for making reliable risk projections. Hao 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">30</italic>
 </xref>) quantified changes in concurrent monthly extremes in temperature and precipitation over the observational period and detected substantial increases in the occurrence of joint warm and dry months. Similarly, Mazdiyasni and AghaKouchak (
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">31</italic>
 </xref>) demonstrated an increase in concurrent meteorological droughts and heat waves in the United States. However, these studies do not separate the overall warming trend from changes in the dependence between temperature and precipitation. Here, we quantify how the dependence structure between warm season temperature and precipitation changes under a strong greenhouse-gas forcing scenario and how this influences the likelihood of extremely hot and dry warm seasons.
</p>
