<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">LD cases have been voluntarily reported to the CDC since 1991 by state and territorial health departments as part of the National Notifiable Disease Surveillance System (NNDSS). The annual county-level number of cases for the period 2000–2016 is publicly available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/lyme/stats/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://.cdc.gov/lyme/stats/</ext-link> and is the main input for our analysis. A total of 482,297 cases were reported during that period (see the evolution of the number of cases in annual maps elaborated by the CDC, also available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/lyme/stats/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://.cdc.gov/lyme/stats/</ext-link>). Until 2007, a case of LD was defined as either (1) a physician-diagnosed erythema migrans rash of more than 5 cm in diameter or (2) at least one objective late manifestation (i.e., musculoskeletal, cardiovascular, or neurologic) with laboratory evidence of infection with 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> (CDC 1997). The national surveillance case definition was revised in 2008 to include probable cases. State or local health departments are responsible for ensuring that cases reported to the CDC meet the case definition, and state health officials have used various methods to ascertain cases including provider-initiated passive surveillance, laboratory-based surveillance, and enhanced or active surveillance [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Over 95 percent of LD cases in the United States occurred in 15 states during our study period, primarily in the Northeast and Upper Midwest (Connecticut, Delaware, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, Vermont, Virginia, West Virginia, and Wisconsin). These are the “high-incidence states,” where the average incidence was at least 10 confirmed cases per 100,000 persons in the previous three reporting years (see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/lyme/stats/tables.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://.cdc.gov/lyme/stats/tables.html</ext-link>). We focus our analysis on counties from those states and present results for the incidence of LD—cases per 100,000 population—including all cases reported during our period of analysis. Because the case definition changed in 2008, we also provide estimates based on the LD incidence reported before and after 2008. Annual population data used to calculate the LD incidence is publicly available from the U.S. Bureau of Economic Analysis (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bea.gov/iTable/index_regional.cfm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://.bea.gov/itable/index_regional.cfm</ext-link>).
</p>
