<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From a conservation point of view, it is concerning if the management of fens does not results in the restoration that was targetted. A decline in bryophyte diversity and cover as a consequence of fen abandonment has been well-documented [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], and a positive influence of mowing on the coverage of endangered bryophyte species has also been reported [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. A reversal in the decline of bryophyte cover will depend on disturbance (e.g. mowing and trampling), their ability to compete for space, and their capability for generative reproduction, which varies considerably between species [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The continental site has a higher water pH value and is more productive than the oceanic site, probably because of a stronger influence of oxygen-rich spring water. A more productive fen will have less space and be drier and shadier at ground level, limiting fen-adapted species. The increase in field layer productivity may have been exacerbated by climate warming, further increasing the competition for light and space. Factors that counteract this process through breaking up the field layer and creating space for less competetive bryophytes are trampling by large herbivores and rodent winter activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. There were fewer significant changes in the vegetation at the oceanic site compared to the continental. It may be that this is a result of the buffering effect of the high precipitation and humidity that characterise an oceanic climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. However, the sample size at the continental site is higher (
 <italic>n</italic> = 17) than at the oceanic site (
 <italic>n</italic> = 13), which may have influenced the occurrence of significant results in the statistical tests.
</p>
