<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ross Sea.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Ross Sea ice extent has a prominent, consistent monthly minimum in February but large variability in its month of maximum, which is July in 3 y, August in 8 y, September in 16 y, October in 12 y, and November in 1 y (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig06" href="#fig06">Fig. 6
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>). The record high monthly value came in September 2007, although the highest yearly value was much earlier, in 1999 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig06" href="#fig06">Fig. 6 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>). The overall but nonuniform reduction of sea ice coverage since the 2007 high led to an almost total disappearance of the sea ice cover and record low in February 2017, with some rebounding the following year (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig06" href="#fig06">Fig. 6
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>). The month that deviated the most from the average annual cycle was December 1979, in a year when the ice cover had been below average since September (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig06" href="#fig06">Fig. 6
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). Further interannual variability can be illustrated by the contrast between the September 2007 record high ice extent being followed the next summer by a February also with an unusually high ice extent, versus the high September 1996 ice extent being followed by a low February ice extent (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig06" href="#fig06">Fig. 6
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>). This phenomenon of high September ice extents being followed sometimes by high and sometimes by low February ice extents is mentioned also in the Weddell Sea section and could be illustrated with many more examples on the sector plots. What happens during the decay season varies greatly depending on the surrounding atmospheric and oceanic conditions.
 </p>
</sec>
