<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par98" class="p">To relate these expressions to the relationships between variations in our known parameters across the AMIP5/CMIP5 ensemble we must make several additional assumptions. We assume that Δ
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">O</sub> and Δ
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> are uncorrelated so the unknown Δ
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">O</sub> values simply contribute to the regression residual, limiting the correlation. We expect this assumption to be approximately valid since Δ
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">O</sub> and Δ
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> are errors in completely different stand-alone ocean and atmospheric model components, which are largely developed separately. We also assume that the response sensitivity constants, 
 <italic class="italic">λ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">F</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">λ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">C</sub>, are approximately consistent across the models. We expect some deviations between individual model sensitivity constants, 
 <italic class="italic">λ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">F</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">λ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">C</sub>, from their multi-model mean values which will contribute to our residual 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">F</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">C</sub> terms, together with other non-linear and non-local contributions to Δ
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">R</sub> and Δ
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">R</sub>. If any of these regression residual terms were dominant we would not expect strong correlations for R1 to R4. Any regression result can be influenced by potentially misleading cross-correlations of important external parameters with both of the variables used in the regression. We expect and assume these local and non-local cross-correlations to be weak. We discuss the potential implications of these assumptions on our inferences for drivers of coupled SST biases in the R2 subsection below.
</p>
