<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Population expansion was indicated by the total population size. The population information (total population size and its sex and age structures) in Guangzhou in the 2030s, 2060s and 2090s was projected using the framework employed by the United Nations Population Estimates and Projections [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Based on this framework, we integrated historical sex- and age-specific mortality rates, total fertility rate (
 <italic class="italic">TFR</italic>), population counts (population size and migration), life expectancy at birth and sex ratio from 5-year periods during 1950–2015 in Guangzhou. The historical (1950–2015) and projected 
 <italic class="italic">TFRs</italic> (2020–2100), and historical period sex- and age-specific mortality rates (1950–2015) were obtained from the United Nations provided at the Chinese national level data, as the Guangzhou city specific data were not available. However, available mortality data for several years (i.e., 2010) indicated that the mortality rates for the total population, males, and females in Guangzhou were similar to the national levels [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. The historical population size and sex ratio data were collected from the Guangzhou Statistical Yearbook [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Historical life expectancy at birth were obtained from several previous studies [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Based on these historical data, we first generated the probabilistic projections of sex-specific life expectancies at birth for 2020–2100 using a Bayes hierarchical model [
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. A sample of 10,000 trajectories of future life expectancy were estimated to show their probability distribution. Then the period probabilistic population projections for 2020–2100 were estimated using the standard cohort-component model [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. This method provides a sample of 10,000 values of any future population quality to approximate its predictive distribution. To consider the uncertainty of projection, we employed the median and 90% interval of projection trajectories to respectively represent the medium, low and high scenarios of population index increases in the future: total population size, sex-and age-specific population size, and proportion of the elderly population (≥65 years) (Please refer to 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-16-00376" class="xref">Figure S3 and Table S2</xref> for details).
</p>
