<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Adaptation was defined by the IPCC as “the process of adjustment to actual or expected climate and its effects” [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. The main types of climate change adaptation include physiological adaptation (or acclimatization), behavioral (e.g., air conditioning), infrastructure (e.g., healthcare systems), and technological adaptation (e.g., heat warning systems) [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. In this study, we employed three adaptation scenarios in this study to capture their effects on the heat-related health effects. In the first scenario (S1), we assumed that people’s adaptation would increase by 8.92% per decade [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], which was estimated by Yang’s study conducted in Shanghai that has the similar socioeconomic characteristics with Guangzhou. In Yang’s study, they assessed the long-term variation in the association between ambient temperature and daily cardiovascular mortality in Shanghai from 1981 to 2012. Their findings showed that the extremely hot effects (99th percentile of mean temperature) decreased by 8.92% per decade. This is a unique study that has assessed the long-term variation of heat effects in China. However, the 30-year study duration might not totally capture the long-term variation of people’s adaptation. In addition, Yang et al. assessed only heat effects on cardiovascular mortality. Therefore, we used another adaptation scenario (S2) that was from Petkova et al.’s study conducted in New York City. This study quantitatively assessed the effects of people’s adaptation on daily temperature impacts over a period spanning more than a century [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. They observed that a decrease in heat effects of 4.6% per decade could be attributed to people’s adaptation. In addition, people’s adaptation to high temperature could also be measured by the change of minimum mortality temperature (
 <italic class="italic">MMT</italic>) that is the temperature with the lowest mortality risk. The increase of 
 <italic class="italic">MMT</italic> over time suggests improved adaptation to heat effects [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. In a recent study, Todd and Valleron assessed the temperature–mortality relationship in France from 1968 to 2009, and observed that the 
 <italic class="italic">MMT</italic> increased by about 0.2 °C/decade [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-00376" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. In this study, we also employed the change of 
 <italic class="italic">MMT</italic> to assess people’s adaptation (S3), and assumed (consistent with Todd and Valleron, 2015) that the 
 <italic class="italic">MMT</italic> would also increase by 0.2 °C per decade in Guangzhou.
</p>
