<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results suggested that long-term malaria mitigation should focus on maintaining malaria-sensitive Iiwi under the RCP8.5 climatic projection. This may be a worst case climate scenario and success in maintaining Iiwi population is also likely to maintain other populations of threatened and endangered Hawaiian honeycreepers, as well as less sensitive species such as Amakihi and Apapane. Second, our results indicated that mitigation strategies should especially focus on high-elevation forests as this is currently the only remaining habitat where abundant highly susceptible Iiwi and other critical populations of honeycreepers are found [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Fortunately, delays in climate warming suggest that malaria intensity at high-elevations will not substantially increase for a few decades [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. As a result, we found that single mitigation strategies including evolution of malaria tolerance, mosquito reduction, or malaria transmission control by refractory mosquitoes were effective at high elevation. Third, different mitigation strategies may be needed for mid-elevation forests due to the differences in malaria infection risk, both currently and in the future. Implementation of single mitigation strategies at mid elevation including feral pig control or release of sterile/incompatible male mosquitoes provided a benefit to native bird populations for several decades, after which other conservation solutions or integrated mitigation strategies will be required. Fourth, mosquito intervention strategies produced different long-term outcomes in terms of mosquito abundance. While both strategies may be effective in reducing malaria infection in Hawaiian birds, using refractory mosquitoes results in much higher mosquito abundance than using sterile/incompatible males. Further consideration regarding the long-term risk for transmission of other vector-borne diseases is needed for these different outcomes. Fifth, the best long-term solution for native honeycreepers, without human intervention, is to evolve malaria-tolerance. Unfortunately, without better understanding of the genetic mechanism(s) that facilitate evolution of malaria tolerance it is currently impossible to determine whether this adaptation is feasible, which species might be able to develop tolerance, and how rapidly tolerance might evolve. Our results for Iiwi indicated that malaria mortality would need to decline dramatically, perhaps unrealistically so, for successful evolution by species with high malaria sensitivity. We also caution that adaptation for most of the threatened and endangered Hawaiian species may be unlikely given the small size of their remaining populations and the likelihood that evolved tolerance in more common species will accelerate the demise of species that are not able to adapt because the common species would serve as a disease reservoir. To date the historical evidence suggests that extinction from malaria is considerably more common in Hawai’i than adaptation. Thus, remaining native forest birds may benefit most if research, development, and assessment of alternative mitigation strategies is accelerated rather than delayed.
</p>
