<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Through the acquisition of knowledge and skills, education represents a key asset to combat climate change.
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref> According to the UNESCO, successful mitigation and adaptation may be achieved through scientific teaching and learning.
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref> The Lancet advocates that tackling climate change could be the biggest global health opportunity of the 21st century;
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref> through the application of the Lancet Health and Climate Change Commission’s multidisciplinary recommendations pertaining to education, research, collaborative actions and political commitment, seizing a global engagement opportunity through public resonance will be feasible.
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref> Education will play a pivotal role in the achievement of the Paris Agreement and the Sustainable Development Goal (SDG) 13 which strives to ‘take urgent action to tackle climate change and its impacts’.
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref> Following the use of educational platforms and other means to achieve SDG 13, it is predicted that the accomplishment of other climate-related SDGs such as SDG 2 and SDG 6 which strive to ‘End hunger, achieve food security and improved nutrition and promote sustainable agriculture’
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref> and ‘Ensure access to water and sanitation for all’,
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref> respectively will be facilitated. For example, epigenetics has demonstrated that environmental conditions can lead to modifications in the DNA of individuals adapting to changing climates;
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref> instruction and training can be an enabler to assist in such transitions to anticipated climates. Education creates a platform for learners to make informed decisions and build communities of practice centred on these issues, thereby strengthening, in the long run, resilience to climate change. Such democratisation of science and enhancement of societal relations may be achieved through engagement of the public in debate on issues and governmental decision-making.
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>
</p>
