<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Current Preparedness, Barriers to Engagement, and Perceived Value of Resources</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While half of respondents indicated their primary hospital is well prepared to respond to climate-related events—with 35% agreeing and 15% strongly agreeing with the statement 
  <span class="italic">“The primary hospital that I admit to is well prepared for climate-related events (e.g., disasters/emergencies, extreme weather events, increases in certain diseases, etc.)”</span>—the other half had no opinion or disagreed (30% were neutral and 20% disagreed).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fewer respondents indicated that “My primary place of work is doing an effective job minimizing its use of fossil-fuels (e.g., conserving energy/water, recycling equipment, 
  <span class="italic">etc.</span>)”; only 6% strongly agreed and 23% agreed with this statement, while 7% strongly disagreed, 34% disagreed, and 30% were neutral.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significant barriers to engaging with patients on the issue were identified. Respondents’ lack of knowledge about how to approach the issue with their patients (71%), and their lack of time (69%) were found to be the most common barriers. Less common barriers included non-billability of time spent speaking with patients about it (39%), patient disinterest (27%), and lack of perceived impact (22%).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A large majority of respondents agreed that each of three specific resources would be helpful to them: 
  <span class="italic">“continuing medical education (CME) on climate change and health”</span> (41% strongly agree, 48% agree); 
  <span class="italic">“patient education materials”</span> (41% strongly agree, 45% agree); and 
  <span class="italic">“policy statements provided by my professional associations”</span> (34% strongly agree, 48% agree).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many respondents provided open-ended suggestions of other resources that would be helpful to them; the majority of these suggestions focused on advocacy and alternate forms of education. For advocacy, responders suggested a greater presence of local professional associations involved in the issues and working to influence policy, community advocacy, public service announcements, and use of social media. For useful alternate forms of education, responders suggested webinars, videos, and podcasts, as well as presentations in the community at public forums and churches, and patient education materials made available at churches to inform the public about the health effects of climate change.</p>
</sec>
