<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a near consensus among African American physicians in the National Medical Association that climate change is occurring, and that its impacts are relevant to direct patient care. A majority of these medical practitioners have concluded that they are already encountering health impacts of climate change in their practice—most notably injuries due to extreme weather, health effects of hotter temperatures, detrimental impacts on chronic diseases due to air pollution, and more allergy problems—and they anticipate that some of these problems will increase in the next 10 to 20 years. They believe that physicians should inform their own patients and the general public about the health risks created by climate change, and that medical societies should have a significant advocacy role. They strongly support education at all levels of medical education, including undergraduate and continuing medical education (CME), and favor public education and patient education materials. Moreover, these African American physicians support government efforts to protect and prepare people and to address the problem.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These findings suggest avenues for continued work and study. Clinicians who believe it is their responsibility to educate their patients and the public should be enabled to do so through the development of appropriate educational resources. Other relevant medical/clinical societies should assess the experiences and preferences of their members to determine the extent to which they are similar to, or different than, those found among NMA members. If the current pattern of findings are found more broadly through the medical community, the medical education community should determine if changes are needed in undergraduate education and CME, and medical associations should consider what roles they wish to play in educating the public and policy makers, and in advocating for preventive and protective measures.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Few members of the public and policy makers have personal contact with a climate scientist, but most people have contact with—and trust—physicians and other health professionals. Given this, and the profound health consequences associated with climate change, the medical and health communities may have a special role to play in helping individuals, communities, and nations come to terms with climate change, and make informed decisions about how to respond. Of course, funding would be needed to support such activities; funders should consider how they can support the climate and health efforts of the clinical and public health community.</p>
</sec>
