<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">Both incremental and transformational climate change adaptation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>
 </sup> strategies are needed for common bean cropping systems of smallholder farmers in south-eastern Africa, whereby such farmers can have greater access to improved varieties and agronomic practices that allows their cropping systems to be more resilient to increased heat and drought conditions, while maintaining or improving nutritional composition of bean grains. Recent plant breeding progress to develop drought- and heat-adapted bean varieties indicates that genetics-based adaptation should be possible
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>
 </sup>, which can be a component of an overall portfolio of climate smart agriculture technologies and practices to ensure resilient of common bean cultivation to climate change impacts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">74</xref>
 </sup>. Where farmers have access to (and widely adopt) such improved bean varieties
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>, it may be possible to maintain yields in areas where cultivation suitability will be negatively impacted by climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>
 </sup>. As the breeding, testing and dissemination of new bean varieties can take a decade or more, our results highlight the need for accelerated development and seed-system dissemination of heat- and drought-tolerant common bean varieties that can maintain yields while also improving nutritional quality (e.g. via biofortification breeding) under future climate change scenarios.
</p>
