<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change occurs and becomes effective at global, regional, and local levels (IPCC 
  <a rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24">2014</a>). Presently, temperature changes are evident, yet not similar, on all continents and in the oceans, causing shifts in species phenologies, physiological and behavioral traits, geographic ranges, productivity, and the disruption of diverse species interactions. Thereby, climate change causes pervasive effects on ecosystems (Parmesan 
  <a rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25">2006</a>). Understanding the physiology of differential climate change effects on organisms is one of the many urgent challenges faced by contemporary science (Pörtner and Farrell 
  <a rid="b31" ref-type="bibr" href="#b31">2008</a>). For instance, responses of endotherms likely differ from those of ectotherms, those of mobile species differ from those of sedentary ones. Here, we explore further how physiological ecology can contribute to a holistic view of climate change impacts on organisms and ecosystems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In several special volumes, ecological and evolutionary physiologists pointed out the increasing importance of studying the physiological basis of organism responses to climate change including their tolerance limits to environmental change (e.g., in, “Climate and Evolutionary Physiology,” Chown et al. 
  <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">2010</a>; “Effects of ocean acidification on marine ecosystems,” Browman et al. 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2008</a>; “Biological responses in an anthropogenically modified ocean,” Boyd and Hutchins 
  <a rid="b4" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4">2012</a>; “Survival in a Changing World,” Barnes et al. 
  <a rid="b3" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3">2010</a>). Physiological study requires identifying the differences in sublethal and lethal effects of climate change within and among species, as a precondition for the successful prediction of ecological effects which result from the success or failure of organisms, populations, and species to cope (e.g., Denny and Helmuth 
  <a rid="b13" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13">2009</a>; Somero 
  <a rid="b41" ref-type="bibr" href="#b41">2011</a>; Araujo et al. 
  <a rid="b2" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2">2013</a>). Indeed, individuals exposed to adverse climate change may reach a state that is beyond their capacity to maintain homeostasis and display performances such as growth, reproduction, and behaviors or to defend themselves against biotic and physicochemical stresses. Theoretical and experimental efforts not only need to improve our understanding of thermal limits to organisms, but also to consider effects of multiple drivers both on land (e.g., reduced water availability in warming terrestrial environments) and in the oceans (e.g., combined effect of ocean warming, acidification, and hypoxia). As a consequence of disturbances to organism functioning, fitness may be reduced, populations may lose genetic variation and collapse, and extinction becomes likely (Deutsch et al. 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2008</a>; Folguera et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2009</a>). Understanding and explaining these phenomena must involve determining the combined and interactive effects of factors limiting the tolerances and distributions of species, by shaping the relevant physiological characteristics (Pörtner 
  <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">2010</a>; Bozinovic et al. 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2011a</a>). They must also involve knowledge of the scope of individual plasticity to shift such limits over time as well as the rate and limits of evolutionary adaptation to do so over generations (e.g., Reusch 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
