<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p content-type="flushleft" class="p">Long-term planning for water resources, agriculture, and irrigation and for associated infrastructure is currently based on the ability to adequately characterize variations in the two key observables: streamflow and precipitation (
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>) (
 <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>). The starting point is to gather the longest reliable instrumental time series to characterize the hydrologic statistics of streamflow and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> (
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>). That traditional practice is intrinsic throughout hydrology. To use that historical knowledge requires a further assumption relating to the stationarity of the relevant time series. The assumption has been recently challenged (
 <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>), because future streamflow may not be stationary. The objection is well-supported by evidence of anthropogenic impacts on streamflow, such as increasing water extraction for irrigation or land use/cover changes (
 <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>
 <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>). One consequence is that the future envelope of variability in streamflow is not necessarily well-represented by the past envelope, which potentially presents a major challenge to the community of hydrologists and water resource engineers (
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>). A question remains about the stationarity of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. Several studies have noted changes in the intensity of short-term precipitation (e.g., subdaily) related to increasing temperatures (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). The implication is that the short-term 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> is not stationary. The long-term 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> of relevance for water resources, agriculture, and irrigation depends on both storm intensity and storm frequency, and whether that is stationary has yet to be addressed. Here, we focus on interannual variations and restrict the analysis to annual 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>.
</p>
