<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Exposure is a measure of the projected magnitude of change in the physical environment due to climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Exposure factors are those climate variables included in the assessment that could impact a species (e.g., temperature, salinity). The exposure score includes information about the magnitude of the expected climate change, but not in relation to each species’ tolerances, which are often unknown. Exposure factors were chosen based on two criteria. First, factors were chosen on the basis that studies have found an effect on fish and invertebrate species in the Northeast U.S. Shelf. Second, factors were chosen that are likely to be well represented in the current class of global climate models (models are described below) [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Seven factors were selected: ocean surface temperature (upper 10 m), ocean surface salinity (upper 10 m), surface air temperature, precipitation, surface pH (upper 10 m), currents, and sea-level rise. Bottom estimates were not used owing to the low spatial resolution of current climate models and the fact that most of the models used do not resolve the bathymetry of the Northeast U.S. Shelf. Similarly, primary productivity was not used because of the importance of regional-scale oceanography and estuaries, neither of which are resolved in the current ensemble of current global climate models. All factors were equally weighted owing to the limited knowledge regarding the magnitude of effects and species responses to climate. Changes in the mean and variance of ocean temperature, ocean salinity, air temperature, precipitation, and pH were included, whereas only changes in mean sea level and ocean currents were considered resulting in a total of 12 climate exposure factors (
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Ocean temperature is an important climate factor, which numerous studies have linked to changes in distribution and productivity [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Fewer studies have linked changes in ocean salinity to biological responses, but changes in salinity may increase metabolic costs [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>], reducing resilience to other changes. Salinity also affects stratification, mixing, and thus the timing and magnitude of primary production [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Most climate models are at a scale where water temperatures in estuaries and freshwater areas are not resolved, so air temperature is used as a proxy [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>], as it is directly linked to the temperature in shallow water owing to air-water heat exchange [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Air temperature and surface ocean temperature are likely correlated because of the large-scale of climate induced warming, but the two factors are important and distinct in terms of their impact on the biology of some species (e.g., Atlantic Salmon are exposed to climate impacts both in freshwater and marine habitats). Streamflow is linked to productivity of a number of diadromous species [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Most climate models do not simulate streamflow, rather they have river routing systems that move water among model grid cells. Precipitation is therefore used here as a proxy of the amount of water in streams and rivers. Numerous studies have found an effect of increased dissolved CO
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</sub> (ocean acidification) on marine organisms from larval survival in molluscs to olfaction in fish [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Estimates of pH were derived from Earth Systems Models, which simulate the carbon system to varying degrees of complexity. Ocean currents were also used as a factor since most marine organisms have planktonic early life stages that rely on advection for transport to habitats necessary for the continuation of the life cycle [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Small-scale changes in currents cannot be assessed from the current global climate models, but changes in large scale changes can be considered. Sea-level rise threatens a variety of coastal habitats including marshes, seagrass beds, and beaches [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. This threat is exacerbated by the large degree of coastal development in the Northeast U.S. Shelf [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>] and the large reliance of fish and invertebrate species on coastal habitats during portions of their life history [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>].
</p>
