<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We computed EDDI using the non-parametric approach described in Hobbins et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], repeated here for the reader’s convenience. First, we computed empirical probabilities of E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> using the Tukey plotting position formula [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. For each day between 1950–2100, daily E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> estimates were aggregated over the preceding 12 weeks, thus maintaining a daily temporal resolution in our timeseries. Next we ranked each 12-week E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> total against the 12-week totals for the same date in the years of the reference period (1966–2005). To give an example, the 12-week E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> for August 31 is the summation of daily E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> from June 9 to August 31, and we ranked the 12-week E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> for August 31 in 2036 against all the August 31 12-week E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub>s from the reference period. The empirical probabilities were then mapped to an inverse normal approximation [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>] of these ranks to obtain standardized EDDI values. EDDI is distributed in a ~N(0,1) fashion (i.e., a standard normal distribution), with a range that is a function of the number of years in the reference period: in our case (n = 40) EDDI has a range of ±2.14. Because the distribution is normal, it can also be represented by percentiles. A zero EDDI value indicates that E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> accumulated over the aggregation period in a given year is equal to the median value from the reference period (the 50th percentile); negative values (lower E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub>, lower percentiles) indicate wet anomalies and positive values (higher E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub>, higher percentiles) indicate dry anomalies.
</p>
