<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Relying on thousands of SNPs, we explicitly tested whether genetic diversity and gene flow in 
 <italic class="italic">M. subnitida</italic> are affected by the amount of reminiscent natural habitats, and identified genomic signatures of adaptations to local environmental conditions. Considering the life history characteristics of our study species and the high statistical power granted by the large number of genetic markers employed, we formulated the following predictions: (a) Since natural habitats harbor floral resources and nesting sites (Vit et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), we expected to find a positive association between genetic diversity and the amount of reminiscent natural habitats surrounding sampling sites (DiLeo &amp; Wagner, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Fahrig, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), as found in bumblebees (Jackson et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>); (b) as restricted dispersal implies reduced gene flow across deforested areas, we expected to find significant isolation by landscape resistance (McRae, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>) and predicted that gene flow would be influenced by habitat amount as well as environmental correlates of genetic connectivity in other bee species, including elevation, terrain roughness, temperature, and precipitation (El‐Niweiri &amp; Moritz, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Jackson et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Jaffé, Pope, et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Jha, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>); and (c) based on the documented tolerance of our study species to extreme heat and water scarcity (Maia‐Silva et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), and previous candidate genes found associated with precipitation and latitude in honeybees (Chávez‐Galarza et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Henriques et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>) and urban land cover in bumblebees (Theodorou et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>), we expected to find genomic signatures of adaptation related to temperature, precipitation, and forest cover. Ours constitutes the first genomic study assessing both isolation by landscape resistance and local adaptation across the full distribution range of a bee pollinator.
</p>
