<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_DIB3685 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Data Brief</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Data Brief</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Data in Brief</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2352-3409</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6355956</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2352-3409(19)30034-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dib.2019.01.033</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Agricultural and Biological Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Data set on current and future crop suitability under the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5 emission scenario for the major crops in the Levant, Tigris-Euphrates, and Nile Basins</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>Chafik</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jaafar</surname><given-names>Hadi</given-names></name><email>hj01@aub.edu.lb</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005">American University of Beirut, Lebanon</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>hj01@aub.edu.lb</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0010"><p>This article describes crop suitability maps (raster data) for thirty five crops in the Jordan, Litani, Orontes, Nile, and Tigris-Euphrates river basins. Spatial data on crop suitability are provided for two periods: current conditions as the average of the years 1970&#x02013;2000, and projected future conditions for the year 2050 as an average for the years 2041&#x02013;2060. The data were generated by simulating mean monthly climatic data from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5). These climatic data are downscaled to the 1-km scale from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change 5th Assessment Report. Mean monthly climatic datasets from the WorldClim database were used to generate the suitability datasets using the FAO EcoCrop model under the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5 emission scenario for three General Circulation Models: CCSM4, GFDL-CM3, and HadGEM2-ES with a spatial resolution of 30 arc-seconds. The findings reveal that many crops in the Levant will witness a decrease in their suitability, whereas suitability of crops in the upper Nile Basin will increase by 2050.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0005"><bold>Specifications table</bold><table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><alt-text id="at0030">Table</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Subject area</td><td><italic>Agriculture and Climate Change</italic></td></tr><tr><td>More specific subject area</td><td><italic>Crop Suitability Modeling</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Type of data</td><td><italic>Raster</italic></td></tr><tr><td>How data was acquired</td><td><italic>FAO EcoCrop Model, Crop suitability modeling using current and projected climatic data</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Data format</td><td><italic>Geo-tiff rasters</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Experimental factors</td><td><italic>Geographic Coordinate System WGS1984</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Experimental features</td><td><italic>Minimum of Temperature and Precipitation Suitability</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Data source location</td><td><italic>Levant (Jordan, Litani, and Orontes), Nile and Tigris-Euphrates River Basins</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Data accessibility</td><td><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.17632/5n39tsf4p7.1" id="ir0005">https://doi.org/10.17632/5n39tsf4p7.1</ext-link>.</td></tr><tr><td>Related research article</td><td><italic>How projected climate change will affect crop suitability, yield, ET, and productivity in the Nile, Levant, and Tigris-Euphrates Basins &#x0201c;in press.&#x0201d;</italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0010"><bold>Value of the data</bold><list list-type="simple" id="li0005"><list-item id="u0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">Current and projected future crop suitability maps for nineteen major crops in the Levant, Tigris-Euphrates and the Nile basins.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">The data can be used to assess impact of climate change on crops in the MENA region.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0025">The data can be used as input to machine learning algorithms.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0030">The data can be compared or correlated with land use changes or results from other emission scenarios.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0035">The data can be valuable for stakeholders, researchers, and governments for agriculture and water management and policy directives.</p></list-item></list></p><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Data</title><p id="p0040">The data consist of crop suitability scores (scaled between 0 and 1, 0 being not suitable, and 1 is highly suitable), geo-located by coordinates (longitude and latitude) and provided in geo-tiff raster datasets for nineteen crops. It can be accessed via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.17632/5n39tsf4p7.1" id="ir0010">https://doi.org/10.17632/5n39tsf4p7.1</ext-link>. Mean monthly meteorological data (temperature in &#x000b0;C and precipitation in mm) from the WorldClim database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://worldclim.com/" id="ir0015">http://worldclim.com/</ext-link>) <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> were used for current climatic conditions (1970&#x02013;2000) and future projections (2050 as an average for 2041&#x02013;2060) as the input data for the FAO EcoCrop model <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> to simulate crop suitability for the major crops in the Near East and the Nile Basin. The crops are: alfalfa, apple, apricot, barley, beans, cabbage, carrot, cherry, chickpeas, clover, coffee, cotton, cucumber, dates, eggplant, grape, lettuce, maize, olive, onion, orange, peas, pepper, potato, rice, sorghum, soybean, sugarbeet, sugarcane, sunflower, tobacco, tomato, vetch, watermelon, and wheat. The result are two sets of crop suitability raster datasets at the 1-km resolution for each of the above crops, under current and future climatic conditions. The following river basins of the Near East have been selected as a study area for this work: Litani, Jordan, Orontes, Nile, and Tigris-Euphrates river basins (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The Near East is an arid to semi-arid region, which is predicted to have an increasing susceptibility to climate change due to the increase in greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Two sets of rasters were provided for each crop: one for current climatic conditions for the baseline period, and another for the future climatic conditions assuming an RCP 8.5 emission scenario.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Study area showing the Nile, Tigris-Euphrates, Jordan, Litani, and Orontes River Basins.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Experimental design, materials, and methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Climatic data acquisition</title><p id="p0045">The global meteorological data provided by WorldClim were downloaded and used as inputs for the crop suitability analysis for the current (baseline, representative of 1970&#x02013;2000) and future (2050, representative of 2041&#x02013;2060) climatic conditions. For the future climate (average of 2041&#x02013;2060) data sets, we used the average climate data from three general circulation models (GCMs): CCSM4, GFDL-CM3, and HadGEM2-ES, where they are based on the Representative Concentration Pathway RCP8.5, the highest emission scenario, from the CMIP5 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. These global climatic datasets are of 30 arc-seconds (~1&#x02009;km at the equator) spatial resolution. They include mean monthly precipitation (mm) and temperature (&#x000b0;C) data.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Processing the climatic data</title><p id="p0050">The global meteorological data are in geo-tiff format. We imported these data into the Terrset software, which houses the EcoCrop model for simulating crop suitability. Because EcoCrop recognizes raster files in RST format, we converted the TIF files into ASCII format (American Standard Code for Information Interchange). The ASCII files were imported to the Terrset software. The model used for automating the process of converting TIF to ASCII format in ArcMap is represented in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>.<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>A sample of the TIF/ASCII converter model in ArcGIS used to convert the monthly mean temperature data into SCII format (the same model for mean monthly data).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Simulating the crop suitability</title><p id="p0055">The suitability rasters for the major crops were globally modelled on a per pixel basis using the EcoCrop model for the current baseline and future climatic scenarios (separately for the three GCMs under RCP8.5 emission scenario) based on the combination of temperature and precipitation parameters choosing minimum of scores as the aggregation procedure. The EcoCrop model as programmed in Terrset software is used to model the suitability of the selected crops. EcoCrop uses the set environmental ranges specific for each crop as an input. These factors are the minimum and maximum temperatures, optimum minimum and maximum temperatures, kill temperatures, minimum precipitation, optimum minimum and maximum precipitation, and crop growing season length (days). In addition, the model uses monthly precipitation and monthly minimum and mean temperatures for the period of interest as inputs to determine the central niche of the studied crop. The model then generates a suitability index for each crop as an output. A detailed description of EcoCrop is found in <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. The EcoCrop is a mechanistic model. When the precipitation and temperature values exceeds their absolute threshold, the model will give a suitability score of zero. On the contrary, if these values are within the optimum and absolute thresholds, the model will give a suitability score ranging from 0 to 1. Using FAO crop ecological database, two sets of crop suitability maps for the basins were generated, one for current conditions and another set for the future conditions. Each set of maps is composed of nineteen maps (one map for each crop). To automate the process of clipping to the study area, a GIS model was formulated to automate the clipping process of all the suitability rasters to the boundary of the study area (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the legend for interpreting the suitability results. <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> shows a sample wheat suitability map for current and future conditions for four basins of the study area. Data shows that in the croplands of the Levant, suitability of crops such as wheat, grapes, apples, apricots, and many vegetable crops will decrease by 10&#x02013;50%, with variability among basins and countries. While only subtle changes in the suitability of crops in the Nile Basin were noticed (on a spatial average), suitability will change spatially. Crop suitability will increase in the middle of the Nile and decreasing in the upper parts of the basin. Wheat, barley and vegetables are the most crops susceptible to changes in crop suitability in the Nile.<fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Model used to clip the suitability rasters to the boundary of the study area.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Interpretation of the suitability results.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>Suitability range</bold></th><th><bold>Suitability category</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>0&#x02013;0.2</td><td>Very marginal</td></tr><tr><td>0.2&#x02013;0.4</td><td>Marginal</td></tr><tr><td>0.4&#x02013;0.6</td><td>Medium suitable</td></tr><tr><td>0.6&#x02013;0.8</td><td>Very suitable</td></tr><tr><td>0.8&#x02013;1</td><td>Highly suitable</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Crop suitability map for wheat under current and future climatic conditions in four basins of the Middle East.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibliog0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Very high resolution interpolated climate surfaces for global land areas</article-title><source>Int. J. Climatol.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1965</fpage><lpage>1978</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eastman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>TerrSet: Geospatial Monitoring and Modeling Software</chapter-title><year>2015</year><publisher-name>Clark Labs, Clark University, Massachusetts, USA</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>21st century climate change in the Middle East</article-title><source>Clim. Change</source><volume>92</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>432</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis: Working Group I Contribution to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</chapter-title><year>2014</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez-Villegas</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>Andy</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e4;derach</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Empirical approaches for assessing impacts of climate change on agriculture: the EcoCrop model and a case study with grain sorghum</article-title><source>Agric. For. Meteorol.</source><volume>170</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0035" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Transparency document</label><title>Supplementary material</title><p id="p0070"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0005"><caption><p>Transparency document</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge the <funding-source id="gs1">American University of Beirut</funding-source> Research Board (URB) for providing funds for this work.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="s0030" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Transparency document</label><p id="p0065">Transparency document associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2019.01.033" id="ir0020">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2019.01.033</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>