<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29" class="p">The bulk of analysis employs heatwave projections from the CMIP5 model archive
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. Participating models required daily data between 1861–2005 for the historical experiment, and from 2006–2100 for RCP8.5, resulting in 27 models (see Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S.1</xref> in the supplemental material). This experiment was chosen based on the number of models available, and evidence suggesting that it is our current emissions trajectory
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. To avoid biasing results towards one or a handful of models, only the first realization of each model was used. Identical analyses were performed using the same models for the RCP4.5 experiment, however results were very similar to those reported in this study and were omitted for the sake of brevity. Since RCP4.5 is considered a “middle of the road” scenario
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>, global warming does not exceed 3.5 °C, and therefore regional changes in heatwaves are significantly less. This is in agreement with recent work
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>, where little difference is found between the relationship of extremes and global warming between different emissions scenarios, relative to a large overall difference by the end of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century. Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S.1</xref> in the supplemental material demonstrates the temporal range of each 0.5 °C threshold under both experiments, which are generally reached later in time under RCP4.5. Thus, while relationships between global average temperature and heatwaves are very similar across the experiments, the impacts on heatwaves will also be felt later if RCP4.5 became our future trajectory.
</p>
