<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we have demonstrated how a management body might gather reliable descriptions of fishermen’s preferences with a relatively small investment of time and money: analyzing semistructured interviews with a relatively small sample of fishermen in a three-stage AHP process. We collected preference data from halibut fishermen across four communities in a region, distilled that information using inductive content text analysis, and then applied a quantitative decision analytic method—AHP—to identify the strength of preferences across alternatives and the features of the alternatives that underpin fishermen’s preferences. The findings demonstrated remarkably consistent, relatively homogenous preferences fishermen had about data collection methods on their vessels. This entire process can be completed in a relatively short time period (e.g., 12–18 months), which aligns with the timeframe of management decision-making in this fishery.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fisheries scientists and managers have increasingly adopted stock assessment and management strategies that are robust to the presence of biological uncertainty and environmental variation [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref055">55</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref058">58</a>]. However, it remains uncommon for fisheries managers to analyze fishermen’s preferences for incorporation in the decision-making process in structured or systematic ways. When the restructured observer program was implemented in the halibut fleet during 2013, it was anticipated that there would be challenges associated with the shift [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref059">59</a>]. Application of the methods presented in this paper during the regulatory review process (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212537.g003" href="#pone.0212537.g003">Fig 3</a>) could have provided managers with greater understanding of fishermen’s preferences and the tools necessary to anticipate and mitigate some major alterations to program design (e.g., resulting from vessel exemptions) that emerged during the first few years of the observer program in the halibut fleet [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref032">32</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref034">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Systematic 
  <span class="italic">ex-ante</span> analysis of halibut fishermen’s preferences might have provided reliable insights into characteristics of potential data collection alternatives that were desirable, objectionable, or important to them. This knowledge could have facilitated consideration of additional data collection alternatives for halibut vessels. Systematic consideration of those preferences could provide managers with the tools necessary to understand areas where fishermen’s preferences and management objectives converge or diverge. Through assessing type and strength of fishermen’s preferences related to management actions, it becomes possible for fisheries managers to choose confidently from the best (or least worst) decisions from multiple stakeholder perspectives at once. Managers can also use AHP to prioritize management plans [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref060">60</a>] or to assess multispecies management and resource allocation among user groups [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref044">44</a>]. This could lead to regulatory decisions with high likelihoods of meeting program objectives or data needs with minimal disruption or cost to fishing operations and lifestyles, as well as high levels of acceptance and compliance from the fishing fleet. In the case study of Pacific halibut, AHP could also be a useful tool to highlight ongoing perceptions fishermen have about data collection alternatives and to determine what drives those perceptions. This could inform future modifications of alternatives for data collection in the halibut fleet (e.g., reducing costs).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding the relative importance of multiple objectives in fisheries management decisions supports development of the most appropriate strategies [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref046">46</a>]. An AHP decision-making process similar to that presented in this paper could be used regularly and across multiple fisheries to provide insights into characteristics of decision alternatives that are desirable, objectionable, or important for fishermen. Managers could potentially increase acceptance of alternatives by stressing how well they perform in relation to each criterion and how important each criterion is to meeting data/management needs. Managers could also look at where proposed alternatives fare poorly on certain criteria and work to assure that proposed alternatives better reflect fishermen’s preferences and judgments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AHP can function as a useful decision-support tool without replacing existing decision-making methods [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref049">49</a>]. Using a three-stage AHP to document preferences of fishermen is compatible with broader trends in the management and sustainable use of fishery-ecological systems, including Management Strategy Evaluations (MSE) [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref057">57</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref061">61</a>]. The MSE framework outlines strategies for effectively managing uncertainty in decision-making. Within the MSE framework, there is increased space for systematically considering fishermen’s preferences, and for allowing social outcomes and preferences to play a direct role in decision-making. Characterizing fishermen’s preferences may facilitate decreased uncertainty during the decision-making process while increasing compliance on fishing grounds. AHP modeling is one way to characterize those preferences.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper did not aim to be statistically random in its sampling strategy (although the methods we illustrate could be used in conjunction with a statistically random sample frame). Instead, we sought to gain information from willing and interested fishermen. We have measured preferences in terms of consistency and strength across a set of criteria defined by the fishermen who participated in this study. In this instance, these opinions are so strongly invariable that it is likely they represent a large portion of the halibut fishermen in the region. That said, marginalized populations (including those based in ethnicity and gender) in the halibut fishery were not assessed in terms of their preferences, which may differ from the prevailing preferences reported in this paper.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interview sampling for this project was not stratified or targeted to reach specific ethnic or gender distributions, and there were not enough responses from underrepresented groups to be able to explore subgroup differences in any meaningful way through subsampling the interviews conducted for this paper. However, future studies could contribute to a growing body of literature focusing on marginalized and underrepresented groups [
  <a rid="pone.0212537.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212537.ref062">62</a>] to allow for demographic comparisons using the same methods presented here. AHP can provide an avenue for affected fishermen to play a role in designing policies that shape and reshape relationships between society and the life supporting marine ecosystems upon which human well-being depends. The three stage AHP methods described in this paper could be used to improve practices in the management of fisheries and other natural resources around the world.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Note: The term “fishermen” is used to refer to fishermen and women in Alaska throughout this paper. While there is some debate as to how people who commercial fish for a living prefer to be labeled, it is the understanding of the authors that the women who participated in this study refer to themselves as “fishermen.” Media coverage regarding women who fish in Alaska suggests the term “fishermen” or “fisherwomen” could be appropriate titles for women who fish commercially throughout the state (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alaskafishradio.com/fishermen-of-both-sexes-dislike-gender-neutral-title/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.alaskafishradio.com/fishermen-of-both-sexes-dislike-gender-neutral-title/</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
