<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to many ancient myths, humans did not invent fire-making de novo but rather learned it from personalities like Prometheus and subsequently spread the practice amongst themselves. These stories reveal how ancient myth-makers already grasped the fundamental importance of social learning—the process whereby individuals learn new behaviours, values and opinions from others [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Social learning is no less relevant in the era of human-environment challenges [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The importance of social learning and social processes more generally in climate change mitigation and adaptation is well recognised [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Increasingly sophisticated geophysical climate models are helping us understand the impacts of anthropogenic greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and the importance of these models is hard to understate. However, climate projections depend strongly on the assumed trajectory of GHG emissions [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This trajectory is determined by human behaviour and yet climate models generally do not incorporate dynamic social processes relevant to GHG emissions. Rather, GHG emissions are assumed to follow some specified trajectory. These trajectories are constructed with socio-economic factors in mind, (see Representative Concentration Pathways [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and Shared Socioeconomic Pathways [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007000.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] for instance), but are not coupled to climate dynamics and do not capture human responses to climate change in a mechanistic way.
</p>
