<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Logistic regression analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We performed a logistic regression analysis to directly assess the role of climate drivers in explaining megadroughts in the Southwest (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2, D and E</a>). For this analysis, the predictand is the binary variable of being in a megadrought or not being in a megadrought and the predictors are the ensemble mean NINO3.4, AMO, and total forcing time series as in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a> (local temperature is not included in the regression model because PDSI is explicitly dependent on temperature). Because of the strong autocorrelation in the annual megadrought time series, we binned all the relevant annual time series according to the boundaries of the start and end years of the megadroughts. Each megadrought period is thus a megadrought bin (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 14), and the surrounding periods are nonmegadrought bins that are divided according to the following rule: If a given nondrought period is larger than the average megadrought bin size of 22 years, then that period is divided into the largest possible equal (or equal ±1)–sized bins such that no bin is larger than 22 years; the continuous nondrought periods at the beginning and end of the time series also follow this rule. The predictor variables of NINO3.4, AMO, and total forcing are averaged over each bin segment. The logistic regression for the probability of megadrought during a given bin, π = Pr (
  <span class="italic">Y</span> = 1 ∣ 
  <span class="italic">X</span> = 
  <span class="italic">x</span>), thus takes the form logit(π) = log [π/(1 − π)] = β
  <sub>0</sub> + β
  <sub>1</sub>
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>1</sub> + … + β
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>k</sub>x
   <sub>k</sub>
  </span> for 
  <span class="italic">k</span> predictors. Because the bins are of varying sizes, the regression is weighted by the size of the bin. In addition, each variable is standardized so that the relative influence of each variable can be gauged by comparing the β
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span> values. To address the issue of small sample size (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 54 total bins) and to be commensurate with 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> (A to C), we performed the regression using a bootstrap sampling with replacement 999 times for each predictor/predictand(s) option. From this, we showed the β
  <sub>1</sub> distributions (the β
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span> distributions for multivariate logistic regression were very similar), and on the basis of the bootstrap sampling, we showed two different information criteria for determining the best regression model: the Akaike information criterion (AIC) corrected for the sample size and the Bayesian information criterion (BIC); both information criteria include a penalty term for the number of model parameters. For each bootstrap regression, the same randomly drawn data points were used for all the predictor/predictand(s) options, and the regression model with the minimum AIC and BIC was recorded; the bars in 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a> show the percentage of the bootstrap iterations where a given model had the lowest AIC and BIC and was thus the “best” model for those randomly drawn data points.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A further complication is that a few very large volcanic eruptions in the forcing time series introduce outliers that can influence the regression. Thus, in 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> (D and E), we showed two logistic regression analyses with one using the full time series and another where four outlying bins were removed for all regression variables (these corresponded to two megadrought bins and two nondrought bins); the outliers in the total forcing time series were considered as those values that were more than three scaled median absolute deviations away from the median (the default outlier detection method of MATLAB).
 </p>
</sec>
