<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">More than half the participants from Henan and Yunnan CDCs indicated malaria had re-emerged in recent years. This may be due to the increased number of imported malaria cases from overseas (foreign nationality or Chinese workforce infected overseas) and the risk of transmission of infected individuals present to the local population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>]. Furthermore, more participants in Henan and Yunnan thought malaria was occurring in new geographic areas, which are consistent with other studies showing that malaria was emerging and re-emerging in these regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. Greater prevention and control efforts should aim to inhibit malaria transmission in these areas. Although other studies also found malaria had re-emerged in Anhui Province since 2000 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>], participants from Anhui CDCs in this survey were less likely to claim that malaria re-emergence and geographic expansion had occurred. This could be due to the great reduction of malaria cases in Anhui Province from 34984 in 2006 to only 144 in 2014 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. Hence, CDC staff in Anhui may be less likely to have observed that malaria had re-emerged compared with the other two Provinces. In addition, the current National Malaria Programme and other related prevention and control measures were thought to be effective in reducing malaria incidence by most of the participants in this survey, which could affirm the overall effectiveness of current control plans. However, in other regions such as Yunnan there may be a need for plans to be further improved to meet the aim of malaria elimination. Furthermore, it will be interesting to know the reasons for the different perceptions of the CDC staff between Henan and Anhui Provinces in terms of malaria emergence and re-emergence, and expansion of epidemic foci, because the two Provinces, especially the malaria epidemic foci are next to each other. In addition, frontline CDC staff were more likely to indicate that malaria re-emerged which could be due to the fieldwork experience they had, compared with other workers. More relevant research among frontline staff in the prefecture and county lower-level CDCs should be conducted to assess the re-emergence of malaria in the context of climate change in China.
</p>
