<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Planning framework and scenarios</div>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We demonstrate this planning framework, illustrated in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, with an application for Mombasa, Kenya. Mombasa is the second largest city in Kenya with an estimated population of 1.1 million
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>. Urban water demand is currently estimated at 150,000 m
   <span class="sup">3</span>day
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and expected to grow to 300,000 m
   <span class="sup">3</span>day
   <span class="sup">−1</span> by 2035
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Mombasa has a warm, humid climate with average annual precipitation of 900 mm year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and a mean annual temperature of 26 °C
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>. Mean annual runoff (MAR) in the nearby Mwache river, the site of a proposed dam, is 113 MCM year
   <span class="sup">−1</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>. While GCMs all project warming in the region, there is disagreement on the direction of precipitation change. This creates substantial uncertainty in future runoff and therefore the reservoir capacity needed to meet yield targets over its lifetime. We apply our framework to develop and assess a flexible infrastructure design. The flexible design enables extra storage capacity to be added if the initial dam becomes insufficient due to warmer, drier climates.
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Schematic of integrated modeling framework. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Full planning framework. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Detail on characterizing transition probabilities using Bayesian statistical model applied to each virtual climate observation
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9677_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e451" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assess three planning scenarios, described in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, intended to evaluate the sensitivity of our results to social and technological planning assumptions. In the low-demand scenarios (A and B), we assume a target yield of 150,000 m
   <span class="sup">3</span> day
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (54.8 MCM year
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) with 90% reliability from the Mwache dam. We evaluate the two dam sizes proposed by the previous World Bank study
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span>, 80 MCM and 120 MCM, as well as a flexible alternative in which the height of the smaller dam can be raised, increasing the reservoir capacity to 120 MCM. In planning scenario C we assume a target yield of 300,000 m
   <span class="sup">3</span> day
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (109.6 MCM year
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) with 90% reliability over the entire planning horizon, reflecting the potential for rapid demand growth on relatively short timescales based on 2035 projections from
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>.
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Planning scenario definitions</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th colspan="2">Planning scenario</th>
       <th>Technology</th>
       <th>DR</th>
       <th colspan="4">Capacity [MCM]</th>
       <th colspan="2">Capex [M$]</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th/>
       <th>Demand</th>
       <th/>
       <th/>
       <th>Small</th>
       <th>Large</th>
       <th>Small</th>
       <th>Large</th>
       <th>Exp</th>
       <th>Flex + Exp</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <span class="bold">A</span>
       </td>
       <td>Low</td>
       <td>Earthen dam</td>
       <td>3%</td>
       <td>80</td>
       <td>120</td>
       <td>76.5</td>
       <td>99.2</td>
       <td>49.6</td>
       <td>148.8</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <span class="bold">B</span>
       </td>
       <td>Low</td>
       <td>Earthen dam</td>
       <td>0%</td>
       <td>80</td>
       <td>120</td>
       <td>76.5</td>
       <td>99.2</td>
       <td>49.6</td>
       <td>148.8</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <span class="bold">C</span>
       </td>
       <td>High</td>
       <td>RO desalination</td>
       <td>0%</td>
       <td>60</td>
       <td>80</td>
       <td>183.1</td>
       <td>232.2</td>
       <td>72.4</td>
       <td>255.5</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">DR</span> discount rate, 
      <span class="italic">RO</span> reverse osmosis, 
      <span class="italic">Capex</span> capital expenditure
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this scenario, the target yield is greater than observed MAR in the Mwache river, and therefore the dam cannot meet the target yield in today’s climate regardless of its size. Therefore, we model the combination of a 120 MCM dam and a desalination plant that is used to supply demand when reservoir storage is low. Three desalination alternatives are chosen, analogous to the dam design alternatives. A low capacity alternative designed to meet reliability targets in the current and expected future climate with 60 MCM capacity; the large alternative that meets the reliability targets across all projected future climates with 80 MCM capacity; a flexible alternative starts with 60 MCM and can be expanded to 80 MCM. Evaluating this second scenario allows us to compare the value of flexibility across two technology options, earthen dams and desalination, which have unique water supply profiles and cost structures.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bayesian learning about climate change uncertainty</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a, b</a> show historical observed regional annual 
   <span class="italic">T</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P</span> from the Climate Research Unit (CRU)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>, as well as individual GCMs’ projected changes in 
   <span class="italic">T</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P</span> relative to 1990. 90% confidence intervals (CIs) of GCM projections are developed using the Bayesian uncertainty approach, assuming the historical period is prior to 1990, and compared to CIs developed using a traditional democratic weighting. The Bayesian approach weights models based on how well they match historical observed changes in 
   <span class="italic">T</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P</span> (see Methods). The democratic approach assumes all models perform equally well
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. Between these two methods, the Bayesian approach produces smaller CIs because it assigns more weight to a subset of models that best match historical change in this region.
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Bayesian and democratic confidence intervals from GCM projections. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> and 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Modeled and observed temperature (precipitation) relative to 1990 values with uncertainty estimates. Thin gray lines are 20-year moving averages of GCM simulations over Mombasa. Thick black lines show the corresponding historical observed values. Orange (blue) shaded regions show the 90% CIs using the IPCC democratic weighting method (i.e. ±1.64*
      <span class="italic">σ</span>). Yellow (green) shaded regions show the 90% CI developed using the Bayesian uncertainty method applied to historical regional observations before 1990
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9677_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e713" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> presents Bayesian CIs based on historical observations, the SDP transition probabilities require Bayesian uncertainty estimates that reflect what will have been learned for many possible virtual future observations. We assume that precipitation change will range between −30% and +30% by end of century; we discretize this range at 2% for a total of 31 unique virtual precipitation change observations. We apply the Bayesian uncertainty analysis to each of these 31 virtual precipitation change observations in each time period. For example, two sample time series of virtual 
   <span class="italic">T</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P</span> observations and their corresponding updated uncertainty estimates are shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. An example of strongly increasing 
   <span class="italic">P</span> is shown at top; an example of modestly decreasing 
   <span class="italic">P</span> is at bottom. For each virtual observation, we simulate 10,000 virtual climate time series from the current observation to the end of the planning period and construct a 90% CI, shown by the shaded regions. This process is repeated for each time step, with darker colors in the plot corresponding to the CIs developed from virtual observations sampled later in the planning period. The darker CIs therefore reflect uncertainty estimates updated with information farther into the future. The sample of virtual observations showing strong increases in 
   <span class="italic">P</span> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a–d</a>), leads to high certainty by the end of the century that negligible water shortages will be incurred, assuming the small 80 MCM of dam capacity. Strong asymmetric uncertainty reflects the low-probability, high-severity risk of droughts; shortages occur only when runoff is substantially below MAR for several months. The alternate sample of virtual observations showing modest decreases in 
   <span class="italic">P</span> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e–h</a>) demonstrates a reduction in uncertainty in both 
   <span class="italic">P</span> and MAR. Expected water shortages increase substantially as more observations are collected, and the uncertainty increases as well due to non-linear relationships between MAR and shortages.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Learning over time using virtual observations. 
      <span class="bold">a</span>–
      <span class="bold">d</span> One sample realization of Bayesian learning over time in which precipitation increases strongly. Black dots represent a time series of virtual climate observations. Shaded regions indicate the projected 90% CI, updated with each time period’s virtual observation. Virtual observations of 
      <span class="italic">T</span> (
      <span class="bold">a</span>) and 
      <span class="italic">P</span> (
      <span class="bold">b</span>) are used to simulate MAR (
      <span class="bold">c</span>), and water shortages assuming 80 MCM dam capacity (
      <span class="bold">d</span>). 
      <span class="bold">e</span>, 
      <span class="bold">h</span> As in 
      <span class="bold">a</span>–
      <span class="bold">d</span> but for an alternative realization of virtual observations, showing modest decrease in 
      <span class="italic">P</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9677_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e799" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While two sample time series of observations are illustrated in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, the SDP optimal strategy accounts for a wide range of possible future observations and what would be learned if they were to be observed. This is achieved through the multistage stochastic optimization formulation, which allows for uncertain, rather than deterministic, transitions to new climate states in each period. In the first time period, shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, the SDP develops a threshold as a function of 
   <span class="italic">T</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P</span> during the 2001–2020 time period when the initial infrastructure decision is made. Above the threshold, in hotter and drier climates, the large dam is optimal and below it the flexible dam is. Due to the small cost difference between the flexible and large dam, investing in the large dam option upfront is preferred if the risk of shortages at the outset is high enough. This reduces expected costs by leveraging economies of scale. Panel b shows expansion thresholds for time periods 2–5 for the flexible dam. Expanding infrastructure capacity is optimal in drier and warmer states. In the 2041–2060 time period, the policy threshold shifts right, reflecting the narrowing of uncertainty due to additional information in later time periods. In later time periods, however, it shifts left, reflecting the influence of the end of the planning horizon which disincentivizes investment.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Optimal policies from SDP. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Threshold for initial decision between large static and flexible design as a function of 
      <span class="italic">T</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P</span> during the first time period (2000–2020). 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Thresholds for exercising the option to increase height of flexible dam as a function of 
      <span class="italic">T</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P</span> during the latter time periods as indicated on the legend. Results shown for planning scenario A
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9677_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e841" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> shows infrastructure decisions under the optimal policy across 1000 simulated climate time series. In planning scenario A, the flexible alternative is chosen in 90% of simulations, shown in panel a. When the flexible alternative is chosen, the option to expand is never chosen in about 90% of simulations. This highlights the low probability of reaching a climate dry enough to generate shortages beyond 10% of demand. The time period at which expansion is exercised varies; more rapid warming and drying leads to earlier expansion. Panel b shows cumulative distribution functions (CDFs) of the total cost (including shortage damages) of each alternative across the 1000 simulations under planning scenario A. The large static alternative has the same cost across simulations; as designed, no shortage damages are incurred in any feasible climate. The small dam performs better than the large dam in about 70% of simulations, but has substantially higher costs in 30% of simulations due to large damages from water shortages. The flexible dam mirrors the small dam in 70% of simulations, but the reliability risk is substantially mitigated because of the potential to expand. The high-end costs are higher than the large dam because, first, the cost of building the 80 MCM dam and expanding to 120 MCM is higher than building the 120 MCM dam upfront and, second, sometimes the dam is not expanded even when modest water shortages are incurred. The ability of the flexible alternative to mitigate both the risk of overbuilding and the risk of severe shortages demonstrates the high value of flexibility in this case.
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Simulated infrastructure decisions and costs. 
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Planning scenario A (low-demand, discounting). 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> planning scenario B (low-demand, no discounting); 
      <span class="bold">e</span>, 
      <span class="bold">f</span> planning scenario C (high-demand, no discounting
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9677_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e874" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The value of flexibility changes under planning scenarios B (no discounting; panels c and d) and C (high demand with desalination plant; panels e and f). Without discounting, the large dam is more favorable; it performs best in 60% of simulations, has no cost variability risk, and is chosen in 80% of simulations. Large economies of scale in the dam mean that a 120 MCM dam is only 30% more expensive than an 80 MCM dam for 50% additional capacity. This suggests it is often better to build the large dam upfront even if there is a relatively low probability that it will be needed. Scenario C evaluates a 120 MCM dam combined with a desalination plant. We find a high value of flexibility even without discounting. The flexible alternative is chosen upfront in over 80% of forward simulations. The CDF demonstrates that it outperforms the static alternatives by substantially mitigating the over build risk in comparison to the robust alternative. The flexible alternative also modestly reduces the shortage damage risk in comparison to the small alternative. While the flexible alternative only reduces cost at the 90th percentile and above, this substantially reduces the expected value as the maximum cost of the small plant reaches almost M$400.</p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Looking across scenarios, the flexible alternative is chosen most often in scenario A because discounting incentivizes delayed capital investments. This is not the case in scenario B because large economies of scale incentivize a single, large investment. In scenario C more modest economies of scale lead to high value of flexibility in the absence of discounting, highlighting differences in the value of flexibility across technologies. Across all scenarios, the flexible dam is expanded in no more than 10% of simulations, highlighting the low probability of reaching a climate that is hot and dry enough to incur substantial shortages.</p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, while the previous analysis has relied on a top-down analysis that uses GCM projections to develop probabilistic forecast, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> presents an illustrative bottom-up analysis that demonstrates the average cost and regret of each of the three dam alternatives in planning scenario A under different end-of-century climates without relying on probabilistic forecasts. Regret is defined as the difference between the cost of the chosen infrastructure alternative and the best possible infrastructure alternative in a given climate state. Three illustrative climates are chosen to demonstrate the tradeoffs across alternatives: a dry climate of 68 mm month
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, an moderate climate of 78 mm month
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, and a wet climate of 88 mm month
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. Differences in 
   <span class="italic">T</span> are not considered because its impact on water shortages is limited. The small dam without expansion has the highest maximum regret of any alternative of M$77, incurred in the dry climate. The large dam incurs positive regret in both the moderate and wet climates, with the latter incurring M$19 of regret. The flexible dam has the lowest maximum regret, with a modest M$4 of regret in the dry climate. This bottom up approach also highlights the ability of the flexible dam design and expansion strategy to mitigate risk in a range of different potential future climates.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Illustrative bottom-up regret analysis. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Total cost including shortage penalties; 
      <span class="bold">b</span> regret by infrastructure alternative in planning scenario A. Cost and regret are assessed in three representative end-of-century 
      <span class="italic">P</span>-values: a dry climate of 68 mm month
      <span class="sup">−1</span>, a moderate climate of 78 mm month
      <span class="sup">−1</span>, and a wet climate of 88 mm month
      <span class="sup">−1</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9677_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e923" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
