<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Improving nearshore fisheries monitoring and evaluation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On many coral reefs across the Pacific, including Hawai‘i, there is limited capacity for fisheries monitoring (
  <a rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-79">Pauly &amp; Zeller, 2014</a>), thus making fishing effort and total annual catch poorly understood and difficult to quantify (
  <a rid="ref-112" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-112">Zeller et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-71">McCoy, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-38">Gillett, 2016</a>). These realities behoove us to identify cost-effective and accurate monitoring tools and survey instruments to appropriately track ecological and social aspects of small-scale tropical fisheries, the results of which can successfully inform adaptive state and community-level fisheries management. To address this, Hawai‘i is currently exploring a range of options, including requiring recreational fishing licenses and/or reporting of recreational/non-commercial fisheries, which would provide critical information on non-commercial catch and effort (
  <a rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-76">Noncommercial Fisheries Licensing Steering Committee, 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In many of the locations, fishing effort was typically higher on the weekends and holidays than on weekdays (
  <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">Hayes et al., 1982</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">Friedlander &amp; Parrish, 1997</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Koike et al., 2015</a>). Along north facing shores, fishing effort was constrained in winter due to large surf (
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Everson &amp; Friedlander, 2004</a>; H. Koike, J. Carpio, A.M. Friedlander, 2014, unpublished data). Many locations in Hawai‘i, particularly sandy shores and embayments, experience higher fishing effort during summer (June–August) when juvenile goatfishes aggregate in mass very close to shore (
  <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">Kamikawa, 2016</a>). Summer months also experienced higher fishing pressure because school is not in session and weather conditions are typically more favorable, allowing more people to spend more time fishing with their families.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We recommend that creel surveys be conducted in a more standardized fashion, more regularly, and at additional sites, to provide more standardized data that has better spatial and temporal coverage, which will allow for more robust analyses. This is critical to address a variety of management issues. First, fishing effort and catch can change, not only across space, but also over time. For example, estimates were quite different at Puakō between surveys of the area in 1980–1981 and 2008–2009. Yet the exact location and size of the study site varied between surveys, which makes comparison more challenging. Nevertheless, current estimates of catch and effort could also be quite different for Hanalei Bay and Kāne‘ohe Bay, which were surveyed in 1992–1993 and 1991–1992, respectively. Therefore, repeat sampling of the same areas through time is needed. The surveys of 18 sites were conducted over decades, which does not allow for spatial and temporal aspects to be disentangled, which would have great importance for conservation and management actions. Furthermore, the information reported from these surveys hampered full analysis of the data. For example, some creel surveys only reported some of the species and/or family-level catch data. Another example is that some studies reported effort in semi-quantitative measures (e.g., frequency of occurrence) or number of fishers rather than the more preferred form of gear-hours, which better allows for estimates of effort and comparison among sites. These issues of standardization hindered the ability to conduct some analyses and forced us to look at coarse measures such as overall catch and effort. The execution of future creel surveys in a more standardized fashion will be of greater benefit to research and management. We recommend that when these data are available, analyses are conducted to the species-level, comparisons of catch and effort on a finer scale (e.g., within a survey area, better differentiation of gear types [e.g., cast net, laynet, surround nets]). Additionally, we recommend examining how fishing effort and catch vary across space and time, which was not possible in our study due to limited and non-standardized reporting of the creel surveys that were previously conducted.</p>
</sec>
