<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local monitoring as a tool for reducing illegal fishing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Illegal, unregulated, and undocumented (IUU) fishing activities are a major cause of negative fishing impacts in coral reefs and other marine environments (
  <a rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-98">Sumaila, Alder &amp; Keith, 2006</a>), with a lack of awareness on local regulations, as well as weak law enforcement, acting as key contributing factors for lack of compliance (
  <a rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-8">Bergseth, Russ &amp; Cinner, 2015</a>). In Hawai‘i, survey results show that fishers identify weak enforcement of fisheries laws as a top threat to fishery resources (
  <a rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-77">OmniTrak, 2011</a>), and lack of compliance and weak enforcement is one of the priority threats to Hawaiian coral reefs and a key capacity gap.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results highlight numerous illegal fishing activities occurring across the MHI (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table-5" href="#table-5">Table 5</a>). Illegal fishing activities were reported at at least half of the locations surveyed, with frequent violations at some locations. Violations at sites ranged from harvested undersized fish, take of prohibited species, use of illegal gears, and fishing in off-limit areas. Instances of illegal fishing and the spatial and temporal patterns of fishing catch and effort have important management implications, and such trends help guide strategies to optimally monitor fisheries given logistical limitations (e.g., limited time, equipment, and personnel to monitor vast amount of area). For this reason, managers and scientists cannot monitor the entire geographic areas of most coral reef fisheries as intensely as needed. In these situations, local monitoring efforts are critical to inform place-based management (
  <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">McClanahan &amp; Mangi, 2004</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-70">McClanahan et al., 2006</a>). However, these local monitoring efforts also need to be aggregated into broader analyses of temporal and spatial scales for managers to gain insights about fishery trends and appropriate management approaches.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Community monitoring via creel surveys can help detect and quantify the extent of illegal activities (e.g., Kahekili (
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Friedlander et al., 2012</a>)), but also potentially reduce them (Kīholo (
  <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">Kittinger et al., 2015</a>)). More enforcement capacity will be required in order to better support existing input and output regulations as well as new rules being advanced through community-led initiatives and state-wide initiatives (such as scoping the feasibility of a licensing system). Creel surveys could be better integrated with these educational and enforcement programs to inform these efforts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To best monitor legal and IUU fishing, we need to determine the most effective survey approach for a given set of personnel, geographies, and available resources. For example, many coastal areas in Hawai‘i are expansive and relatively undeveloped. Access points to these areas are generally indistinct and parking haphazardly on the side of a road is common. Local fishers often prefer to utilize these areas where resources are generally not as depleted. In addition to many line fishers, spear and net fishers tend to favor remote areas where capture success is likely greater due to higher resource availability. Based upon the general characteristics of the coastal areas and the diversity of shore-based fisheries in Hawai‘i, the roving survey is often considered the more suitable survey method to collect shoreline fishing information. Also, given that fishing effort is generally higher on weekends and holidays during non-winter months, optimally allocating limited effort for monitoring to those times and locations with higher fishing pressure, could possibly lead to better coverage of fishing activities as well as better enforcement of current regulations. Community monitoring can detect illegal activities, but also potentially reduce them (
  <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">Kittinger et al., 2015</a>). Also, more enforcement capacity will be required to better support existing input and output regulations. Some promising initiatives include the community fisheries enforcement unit, Makai Watch, and other existing initiatives in Hawai‘i. Creel surveys could be better integrated with these educational and enforcement programs.
 </p>
</sec>
