<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Technical measures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine protected areas (MPAs), have been proven to be highly successful in conserving biodiversity globally (
  <a rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-61">Lubchenco et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Lester et al., 2009</a>), and particularly in Hawai‘i (
  <a rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-26">Friedlander et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Friedlander, Brown &amp; Monaco, 2007</a>). MPAs can also benefit adjacent fisheries through two primary mechanisms: increased production and export of pelagic eggs and larvae (larval spillover), and net emigration of adults and juveniles (adult spillover) (
  <a rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-68">McClanahan &amp; Mangi, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-36">Gaines et al., 2010</a>). Within the MHI, there are numerous state-managed areas that limit fishing activities in nearshore marine waters. Existing MPAs in Hawai‘i that are fully protected from fishing have higher fish biomass, larger overall fish size, and higher biodiversity than adjacent areas of similar habitat quality (
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Friedlander, Brown &amp; Monaco, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-29">Friedlander et al., 2014b</a>). These protected areas can also benefit local fisheries, as in the case of the Pūpūkea-Waimea MPA on the north shore of O’ahu, which has resulted in significant benefit for fishers through adult spillover (
  <a rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-95">Stamoulis &amp; Friedlander, 2013</a>). There is much resistance to the establishment of MPAs from the fishing sector for a variety of reasons including: loss of fishing areas, displacement or marginalization of subsistence fishers, perceived loss of income and cultural access, and the long lag time before benefits are realized (
  <a rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-67">McClanahan, Maina &amp; Davies, 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-13">Cinner et al., 2009a</a>). Although not a panacea for coral reef fisheries management, MPAs in conjunction with other input and output controls are critical to sustaining fisheries and maintaining ecosystem health.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pacific islanders traditionally used a variety of closures that were often imposed to ensure large catches for special events, or as a cache for when resources on the usual fishing grounds ran low (
  <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Johannes, 1978</a>). Traditional periodic closures can be effective for short-lived taxa that reproduce quickly, but evidence across the Pacific, including Hawai‘i, shows that taxa that are long-lived and reproduce later in life do not benefit from rotational closures (
  <a rid="ref-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-107">Williams et al., 2006</a>). Rotational closures have been less successful in contemporary Hawai‘i where there are few to no controls on effort once the area is open to fishing.
 </p>
</sec>
