<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040" class="p">The data consist of crop suitability scores (scaled between 0 and 1, 0 being not suitable, and 1 is highly suitable), geo-located by coordinates (longitude and latitude) and provided in geo-tiff raster datasets for nineteen crops. It can be accessed via 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.17632/5n39tsf4p7.1" id="ir0010" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.17632/5n39tsf4p7.1</ext-link>. Mean monthly meteorological data (temperature in °C and precipitation in mm) from the WorldClim database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://worldclim.com/" id="ir0015" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://worldclim.com/</ext-link>) 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[1]</xref> were used for current climatic conditions (1970–2000) and future projections (2050 as an average for 2041–2060) as the input data for the FAO EcoCrop model 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[2]</xref> to simulate crop suitability for the major crops in the Near East and the Nile Basin. The crops are: alfalfa, apple, apricot, barley, beans, cabbage, carrot, cherry, chickpeas, clover, coffee, cotton, cucumber, dates, eggplant, grape, lettuce, maize, olive, onion, orange, peas, pepper, potato, rice, sorghum, soybean, sugarbeet, sugarcane, sunflower, tobacco, tomato, vetch, watermelon, and wheat. The result are two sets of crop suitability raster datasets at the 1-km resolution for each of the above crops, under current and future climatic conditions. The following river basins of the Near East have been selected as a study area for this work: Litani, Jordan, Orontes, Nile, and Tigris-Euphrates river basins (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). The Near East is an arid to semi-arid region, which is predicted to have an increasing susceptibility to climate change due to the increase in greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[3]</xref>. Two sets of rasters were provided for each crop: one for current climatic conditions for the baseline period, and another for the future climatic conditions assuming an RCP 8.5 emission scenario.
</p>
