<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The functional traits that showed the most plasticity, including leaf area and leaf thickness, are both related to leaf lifespan, where thicker and smaller leaves have higher leaf mass per area and are thus more likely to have longer leaf lifespans and more conservative strategies (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wright et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reich, 2014</xref>). The observed plasticity in these traits could be driven by the imposition of additional stress when transplanted to colder climates, or the release of that stress when transplanted to warmer climates, as there is some tendency toward more acquisitive leaf strategies at lower elevations (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cornwell and Ackerly, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Read et al., 2014</xref>). However, we found that the extent and importance of plasticity in traits varies by species. This is similar to 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cui et al. (2018)</xref>, who found that 
 <italic class="italic">Viola biflora</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">rockiana</italic> had low plasticity in leaf area in response to transplantation in the same study system. Plasticity in leaf P is likely to be more related to P availability in the soil along the elevation gradient. Leaf P may be less genetically controlled compared to environmentally controlled by access to that nutrient so movement to new places results in different P availability. δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N also had high plasticity, potentially for similar reasons to %P. Variation in foliar δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N has been linked to variation in soil N supply and nitrogen sources are primarily determined by local differences in N fixation, uptake, and outside sources (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Craine et al., 2015</xref>) which could vary substantially between sites. Carbon-related traits (%C and δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C) showed the lowest degree of plasticity in response to transplantation. This indicates that these traits might be more genetically controlled with little response to the environmental conditions in this experiment. Little variation in δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C suggests that moisture conditions do not vary substantially between transplant sites, resulting in little change in isotope ratios (or water use efficiency) between sites.
</p>
