<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0025" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Africa’s Green Revolution in Rwanda</div>
 <p id="p0090" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over the past decade, development policies across Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) have come to re-center on smallholder agriculture as an engine of economic growth. In hopes of catalyzing an African Green Revolution (
  <a rid="b0515" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0515">World Bank, 2007</a>), major development actors (e.g. the World Bank, the United States Agency for International Development, and the United Nations) and national governments have made substantial investments in agricultural intensification, (
  <a rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0245">Jayne et al., 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0335">Moseley et al., 2015</a>). As in earlier Green Revolutions in Mexico and Asia, contemporary agricultural intensification programs throughout SSA center on smallholders, aiming to encourage households to adopt high-yielding varieties of maize, rice, and wheat and to increase application of agrochemicals, which these varieties often require to achieve optimal productivity. Africa’s Green Revolution has thus far taken shape as a top-down enterprise, with governments and development agencies incentivizing and sometimes enforcing the increased adoption of technologies (
  <a rid="b9035" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9035">Gengenbach et al., 2018</a>, 
  <a rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0335">Moseley et al., 2015</a>, 
  <a rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0090">Clay, 2017</a>). Not only do intensification policies aim to sustainably end hunger and malnourishment—which have abated very little in SSA compared to other regions—they illustrate a renewed development emphasis on agriculture as an engine of overall economic growth (
  <a rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0400">Rashid et al., 2013</a>, 
  <a rid="b0515" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0515">World Bank, 2007</a>). As with earlier Green Revolutions, land and technology are identified as the limiting factors (
  <a rid="b9010" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9010">Jarosz, 2014</a>). Increased inputs (such as hybrid seed, chemical fertilizers, and pesticides) and agroengineering (terracing, draining wetlands, and irrigating fields) are thus positioned as essential to shore up ‘yield gaps’ and thereby curtail further expansion of agricultural land into biodiverse areas (
  <a rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0195">Foley et al., 2011</a>, 
  <a rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0295">Lobell et al., 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="b0475" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0475">Tilman et al., 2002</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0095" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, political economic and agroecological contexts in contemporary SSA poorly resemble those of 1960s and 1970s Asia. In contrast to consistent national markets and robust state-led subsidy programs that facilitated Green Revolutions in India, for example, decades of neoliberal reforms in SSA have meant weakened state involvement in agriculture and dependence on erratic global markets (
  <a rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0045">Bezner Kerr, 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0125">Dorward and Kydd, 2004</a>). There is growing evidence that input-based agricultural intensification has done little to meet pro-poor development goals in SSA. Although aggregate crop yields may have increased in some places, national-level food production figures say little about local-level food access (
  <a rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0050">Bezner Kerr, 2013</a>). Technology-driven intensification policies appear to have done little to address longstanding unevenness in land and resource access among smallholders, resulting in exacerbated malnutrition and inequality among some rural communities while large-holders, urban populations, and agribusiness benefit (
  <a rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0045">Bezner Kerr, 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0330">Moseley et al., 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0335">Moseley et al., 2015</a>). Moreover, increased yields in rural areas do not guarantee the emergence of nonfarm employment opportunities (
  <a rid="b9020" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9020">Haggblade, Hazell, &amp; Reardon, 2010</a>) and increased commercial activity is not universally beneficial across the socially diverse range of smallholder farmers (
  <a rid="b9030" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9030">Clay, 2018b</a>, 
  <a rid="b9035" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9035">Gengenbach et al., 2018</a>). To speak to the viability of intensification policies for pro-poor rural development in SSA, local-level research is needed to scrutinize links between intensification, yield increases and poverty reduction (
  <a rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0005">Abro, Bamlaku, &amp; Hanjra, 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0100" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With its Crop Intensification Program (CIP), Rwanda is an archetype of the New Green Revolution in SSA. In 2007, the country was the first to sign a compact with the Comprehensive Africa Agriculture Development Program (CAADP), a pan-African framework of agriculture-led growth. Since 2004, Rwanda’s Strategic Plans for the Transformation of Agriculture (PSTAs) have systematically transformed rural landscapes and livelihoods through land reform and technology adoption (
  <a rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0090">Clay, 2017</a>, 
  <a rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0210">GOR, 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="b9040" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9040">MINAGRI, 2012</a>). Striving to become a middle-income country by 2020, the GoR aims to convert largely subsistence-based smallholders to professional farmers. With its Land Policy (since 2006) and CIP (implemented since 2007 in pilot phases and countrywide since 2010), the Government of Rwanda (GoR) and development partners have formalized land tenure, drained marshlands, and constructed terraces throughout the country (
  <a rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0250">Kathiresan, 2012</a>). The CIP aims to increase the productivity of export-oriented crops by increasing access to hybrid seed and fertilizer, by augmenting agricultural extension services, and by compelling smallholders to consolidate landholdings with neighbors and cultivate crops selected by government authorities (
  <a rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0320">MINAGRI, 2011</a>). Crops under this ‘crop regionalization’ mandate (wheat, maize, rice, bean, cassava) were selected via a national-level exercise that considered agroecological zones and the crops’ export potential (
  <a rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0230">Huggins, 2014</a>). Contracts (
  <span class="italic">imihigo</span>) with higher administrative levels outline hectare targets on which to consolidate land and plant selected crops, assuring that national-level targets are enacted at local levels (
  <a rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0235">Ingelaere, 2014</a>). Routine audits at various levels further solidify the top down nature of this program. To ensure that they meet government quotas for land in the CIP: local administrators threaten noncompliant farmers with fines, uprooting crops, or appropriating land (
  <a rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0085">Cioffo et al., 2016</a>, 
  <a rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0090">Clay, 2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0105" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a CIP report states, the program “encourages crop specialization to realize economies of scale and to orient the agricultural sector more towards the commercial market” (
  <a rid="b9040" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9040">MINAGRI, 2012, p30</a>). While increases in agricultural production and commercialization are seen to have played a role in driving Rwanda’s impressive economic growth (8 percent yearly from 2000 to 2012) and poverty reduction (EICV, 2015; 
  <a rid="b0520" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0520">World Bank, 2014</a>), research also shows that these policies may exacerbate uneven land access (
  <a rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0115">Dawson, Martin, &amp; Sikor, 2016</a>) and food insecurity (
  <a rid="b9030" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9030">Clay, 2018b</a>). Studies on the initial phases of the CIP found that smallholder autonomy has been constrained, especially for socioeconomically disadvantaged households (Ansoms, Walker, &amp; Murison, 2014; 
  <a rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0230">Huggins, 2014</a>, 
  <a rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0395">Pritchard, 2013</a>). Studies also demonstrate that smallholders’ ability to succeed with CIP-prescribed land use practices is highly uneven—varying according to agroecolgical conditions and pre-existing resource access inequalities (
  <a rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0085">Cioffo et al., 2016</a>, 
  <a rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0090">Clay, 2017</a>). The present research builds on this work by investigating how Rwanda’s Green Revolution-inspired agricultural policies shape smallholders’ capacities to adaptively respond to perceived social-environmental changes. This research is timely as the GoR and development partners are currently scaling up these policies (
  <a rid="b9040" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9040">MINAGRI, 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="b0520" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0520">World Bank, 2014</a>) and given that similar policies are being widely implemented across sub-Saharan Africa (
  <a rid="b9015" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9015">Schurman, 2018</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
