<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0030" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods and study sites</div>
 <p id="p0110" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empirical materials informing this study were collected via quantitative and qualitative methods carried out in Rwanda from September 2014 to December 2016. An in-depth case study was used to consider the interplay among smallholder livelihoods, land use practices, and development transitions in the context of climatic variability, uncertainty, and change. Surveys and interviews focused on smallholder resource access and decision-making within changing institutional contexts and broader social-environmental changes. Iterative phases of data collection enabled the research team to build and test hypotheses and to periodically solicit feedback from study participants. As demonstrated by other studies, empirical attention to lived experiences with climatic shocks and adaptation to perceived climate change can yield valuable insight on response pathways in the face of current and future global climate change (
  <a rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0160">Engle and Lemos, 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="b0485" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0485">Turner, 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <sec id="s0035" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study site</div>
  <p id="p0115" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study is sited in Kibirizi sector, southwest Rwanda, a mountainous region of the country, which has continually suffered from poverty and waning soil fertility, and which the National Adaptation Plan of Action for climate change identifies as high risk for both recurring heavy rain and drought (EICV, 2015, 
   <a rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0215">GoR, 2006</a>). The study period coincided with numerous climatic shocks. Torrential rain and flooding occurred in 2014 and 2015; extended dry spells in 2013, 2014, and 2016 decimated harvests throughout the country (
   <a rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0180">FEWS NET, 2013</a>, 
   <a rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0185">FEWS NET, 2014</a>, 
   <a rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0190">FEWS NET, 2016</a>) and combined to produce what some have called “the longest drought in six decades” (
   <a rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0350">Times, 2016</a>). The study site comprises 4 
   <span class="italic">umudugudu</span> (smallest administrative unit, roughly translating as ‘rural settlement’) that were selected as 1) representative of rural settlements throughout Rwanda; and 2) eliciting variations in the degree and type of agricultural intensification (see 
   <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). Agriculture (either own farm or working others’ land) is the principal livelihood for nearly all households, who cultivate rain-fed, mixed crop-livestock systems for both subsistence and commercial ends. Cultivation on hillsides is circumscribed by two growing seasons per year (one from September to December, the other from March to May) and restricted to marsh and valley areas during dry seasons. When possible, households diversify livelihoods to include non-farm employment such as small businesses, skilled labor in masonry or house framing, and other labor such as collecting sand or making charcoal. The CIP has been implemented in Kibirizi since 2010 and the program has been widely adopted, with over 90 percent of survey respondents participating in 2015.
   <div id="t0005" position="float" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Four study 
      <span class="italic">umudugudu</span> characterized in terms of type and degree of Crop Intensification Program (CIP) attributes.
     </p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>
        <span class="italic">Umudugudu</span>
       </th>
       <th>Type of Intensification</th>
       <th>Degree of Intensification</th>
       <th>Number of surveys</th>
       <th>Number of interviews</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>A</td>
       <td>Terraced: high Marshland: none; Other CIP: some</td>
       <td>Highest</td>
       <td>109</td>
       <td>27</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>B</td>
       <td>Terraced: none Marshland: some Other CIP: high</td>
       <td>Medium-high</td>
       <td>119</td>
       <td>11</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>C</td>
       <td>Terraced: some Marshland: some Other CIP: low</td>
       <td>Medium-low</td>
       <td>67</td>
       <td>9</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>D</td>
       <td>Terraced: none Marshland: low Other CIP: low</td>
       <td>Lowest</td>
       <td>117</td>
       <td>24</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="p0120" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As elsewhere in Rwanda, three variations of CIP-prescribed agriculture have been implemented in Kibirizi: terraced-hillside agriculture, unterraced hillside-agriculture, and marshland agriculture. The rules are most strict in terraced areas. A regional agronomist selects crops each season according to government targets. Although households retain land titles, farmers are strongly compelled to cultivate selected crops by threat of fine, jailing, or land expropriation if a crop is not cultivated during a growing season. On unterraced land, restrictions are somewhat eased. However, households are still incentivized to grow selected crops and discouraged from growing four crops known for their subsistence importance: sweet potato, cassava, sorghum, and a regionally important grain known locally as 
   <span class="italic">ciraza</span>. Prior to each growing season, households submit contracts to local leaders indicating that they will grow selected crops. If they do not meet these contracts, individuals can be publicly disgraced during weekly meetings of village-level farmer associations. Cooperatives coordinate intensification activities in marshlands, with a regional agronomist making cropping decisions. While access to marshlands prior to 2005 was subject to 
   <span class="italic">de facto</span> land rights and planted in mixed crops and grazing, access now requires paying cooperative membership (5000 RWF, or 8 USD) and seasonal use fees (2000 RWF, 3 USD) per 100 m square parcel. Seed and fertilizer for government-selected crops are distributed through cooperatives, state extension agents, and (for maize and bean) by an American company called the One Acre Fund (known locally as 
   <span class="italic">Tubura</span>) which has partnered with the GoR. In addition, eucalyptus tree seedlings (
   <span class="italic">E. globulus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">E. maidenii</span> species) are sold at subsidized rates throughout the study area in line with government aims of increasing tree cover across Rwanda.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0040" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection and analysis</div>
  <p id="p0125" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Focus groups (n = 4, one in each umudugudu; 12–20 people each; participants recruited by local leaders) and key informant interviews served to introduce the research team and develop understanding of central issues. Interviews were conducted in Kinyarwanda or French with the help of a research assistant, employing open-ended questions to query changes in livelihoods, policies, and rainfall patterns over the past twenty years. Two primary concerns emerged surrounding agricultural livelihoods: climatic shocks have increased in magnitude and frequency and the CIP has altered land use decision-making by reducing household autonomy over crop selection and access to inputs. These issues informed subsequent research phases.</p>
  <p id="p0130" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the first author conducted a structured household survey from November 2014 to March 2015 with an adult male or female representative of all available households (households deemed unavailable if not present on three visits on separate days
   <a rid="fn1" ref-type="fn" href="#fn1">1</a>) in the four 
   <span class="italic">umudugudu</span> (428 households out of approximately 500 total) by a team of four Rwandan research assistants. In addition to documenting household demographics, assets, livelihoods, and food security, questions focused on land use, the influence of Rwanda’s CIP and broader agricultural policies on decision-making and crop yields, and changes in resource access, institutions, and climate. For questions addressing political economic and agricultural changes, a 10-year timeframe was used; this is supported in literature on agrarian change in SSA (
   <a rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0220">Guyer, 1997</a>). All surveys were conducted within respondents’ home compounds and administered in Kinyarwanda (1 h 56 min average per respondent). Third, a structured parcel-level survey (administered July 2015 to October 2015) was completed with all households that had operational land holdings (402 households and their 3017 parcels), meaning that 26 landless households were excluded. Questionnaire development and administration followed the same protocol as above with the addition of four local research assistants (secondary school graduates) who were trained in calculating field area and use of GPS units. All parcels less than 30 min’ walk from the homestead were visited, otherwise location was indicated on a map. The questionnaire included 30 questions at the household level (number and location of parcels, general challenges to agriculture, seed and labor availability, etc.) and 70 questions for each parcel operated, including general parcel characteristics (fertility, soil type, tenure status, years operated, etc.) and crop choice, yields, and challenges affecting yield for the previous three seasons.
  </p>
  <p id="p0135" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fourth, in-depth semi-structured interviews were conducted with 36 male and 36 female respondents (April 2015 to August 2015) from randomly-selected households. Each of these 72 interviews involved three members of the research team: one asked questions in English, another translated between English and Kinyarwanda, and a third took detailed notes. Meetings immediately following each interview ensured that details and overall meaning were accurately recorded. Interviews averaged 1 h 20 min and concentrated on changes in climate, land use, livelihoods, household agricultural labor, agricultural challenges, and perceptions and impacts of government policies. Fifth, unstructured interviews were conducted (October 2014 to December 2016) with 32 individuals representing key institutions involved in agro-ecosystem management, including leaders in six umudugudu, five mayors at ‘cell’ and ‘sector’ levels, agronomists, state employees overseeing land tenure issues, cooperative presidents, input distribution companies, health workers, local development officers, and security officials, among others. Questions pertained to contemporary and historical political, economic, environmental, and agricultural aspects of the study area and broader region, including the implementation of Rwanda's CIP and perceptions of climate change.</p>
  <p id="p0140" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In-depth interviews complement quantitative data with rich detail on power relations and the effects of institutional change. As a case study, this work does not consider regional differences. However, it provides a comprehensive picture on how development transitions intersect with broader social-ecological change, enabling visualization of the complex pathways by which smallholders weave together livelihood and land use strategies within social and biophysical contexts that vary markedly within the study site. Data from household and parcel surveys were analyzed using SPSS. Tests included descriptive statistics, bi-variate comparison of means, bivariate correlation, Chi-Square, multivariate analysis of variance (ANOVA), and other multivariate regressions. Interviews were coded and analyzed qualitatively using ATLAS.ti software. An initial round of coding was done and refined into a codebook that was employed in a second round of coding, enabling sub-themes to emerge. The coding strategy reflected attempts to account for relationships deemed statistically robust as well as to further explain relationships that remained unclear following statistical analyses.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
