<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0045" class="p">Although there are some studies on the quantitative design of ideotypes for high yield potential of winter cereals under current or future climatic conditions, either they involve local or manual optimization of only a few traits (e.g., wheat ideotypes by 
 <xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sylvester-Bradley et al., 2012</xref>), or they do not explore the full parameter space for optimization (e.g., barley ideotypes by 
 <xref rid="bib0445" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tao et al., 2017</xref>). Ideotypes for a target environment need to be optimized in a global multidimensional cultivar parameter space exploring in full the parameter ranges and their possible interactions. Although a few studies have assessed the quantitative yield potentials of wheat ideotypes under future climatic conditions in Europe, the ideotype design was not focused on shifting the upper threshold of genetic yield potential, particularly in high wheat productive countries at high latitude (
 <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Shewry, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Stratonovitch, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Senapati et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stratonovitch and Semenov, 2015</xref>). The objective of this study was to design wheat ideotypes to increase the genetic yield potential in the 2050-climate as projected by the 
 <italic class="italic">HadGEM2</italic> global climate model (GCM) for the 
 <italic class="italic">RCP8.5</italic> emission scenario in two high-wheat-productive countries, 
 <italic class="italic">viz</italic>. the UK and NZ. The design methodology was based on the knowledge of crop physiology, the Sirius wheat simulation model and evolutionary optimization in the multidimensional cultivar parameter space.
</p>
