<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Scientific collaboration can be seen as a self-organizing system where co-authorships represent links in a communication network between scientists (Newman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">2004</xref>; Wagner and Leydesdorff 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2005</xref>). Network analysis methods can then be used to discover the operating dynamics of this system (Wagner and Leydesdorff 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2005</xref>). It is very difficult to define the boundaries of research collaboration (Katz and Martin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">1997</xref>), hence choosing a metric to measure the outcomes of such activities is also challenging. The term ‘collaboration’ itself can refer to a wide range of activities, from general discussion and advice to active participation in data collection or analysis and from substantial to negligible levels of engagement, all of which can be encompassed by eventual co-authorship (Katz and Martin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">1997</xref>). Although data on co-authorships is easily accessible and verifiable, making it a relatively inexpensive and practical method to use for measuring collaborative interactions (Katz and Martin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">1997</xref>; Milojevic 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2010</xref>) the approach is by no means perfect. There can be many reasons why a collaborative effort does not lead to a joint publication, or why co-authorship does not reflect actual collaborative research (Katz and Martin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">1997</xref>; Melin and Persson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">1996</xref>). However, co-authorship should at least be positively correlated with collaboration (Glänzel and Schubert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2004</xref>). Co-authorship on published papers has been used to investigate aspects of scientific collaboration in many different fields, from mathematics (Brunson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2013</xref>; Grossman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2002</xref>) to social science (Moody 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2004</xref>) and engineering (Abbasi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2011</xref>). Co-authorship networks are therefore widely recognised as reasonable indicators of scientific collaboration, and provide an objective measure of the effectiveness of structures such as knowledge hubs to increase collaborative research.
</p>
