<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-12-11254" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. The Effect of Climate Change on Deposition in the Arctic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average Arctic air concentrations of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span>, Reactive Gaseous Mercury (RGM = HgO + HgCl
  <sub>2</sub>) and Total Particular Mercury (TPM = primary + oxidized particulate Hg) are shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-11254-f002" href="#ijerph-12-11254-f002">Figure 2</a> for the 1990s and the 2090s. The average concentration of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> is 4% higher in the 2090s compared to the 1990s, while the concentrations of both RGM and TPM are lower with 41% and 62%, respectively.
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-11254-f002" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The average Artic air concentrations of Hg
    <span class="sup">0</span> (
    <span class="bold">a</span>), Reactive Gaseous Mercury (RGM = HgO + HgCl
    <sub>2</sub>) (
    <span class="bold">b</span>) and Total Particular Mercury (TPM = primary + oxidized particulate Hg) (
    <span class="bold">c</span>) for the 1990s and 2090s divided into the contribution from North America (NA), Europe (EU), Asia (AS), and background concentration (BG).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-11254-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main reason for the differences between the two decades in the model is that the parameterization of the fast oxidation of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> to HgO during the AMDEs depends on the sea-ice fraction. The lower sea-ice fraction in the 2090s compared to the 1990s will result in a lower oxidation of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> to HgO and therefore a higher concentration of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> and lower concentrations of RGM and TPM.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-11254-f003" href="#ijerph-12-11254-f003">Figure 3</a>, the total annual deposition of Hg north of the Arctic Circle (66.5
  <span class="sup">o</span> N) is shown. The total deposition is 18% lower in the 2090s than in the 1990s, and the difference is statistically significant. RGM is the major component of the deposition due to a high dry deposition velocity to the surface, and the lower RGM air concentrations in the 2090s result in lower depositions.
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-11254-f003" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The total deposition of Hg in tons/year with the contribution from the different source areas including indirect contribution (
    <span class="bold">a</span>) and the relative contribution from the different source areas to the total deposition of Hg for the Arctic (
    <span class="bold">b</span>) for the two studied decades.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-11254-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial distribution of the average total annual deposition in the 1990s is shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-11254-f004" href="#ijerph-12-11254-f004">Figure 4</a> together with the difference in percent between the average total annual deposition in the 1990s and the 2090s. The deposition to the continents is significantly higher in the 2090s than in the 1990s due to significantly higher ozone concentrations in the troposphere, which is one of the main oxidant paths of mercury in the DEHM model. The deposition to the Arctic Ocean is significantly lower in the 2090s than in the 1990s due the reduction in sea ice coverage.
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-11254-f004" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Average of the total annual mercury deposition for the 1990s (
    <span class="bold">a</span>) and change in deposition in percent from the 1990s to the 2090s (
    <span class="bold">b</span>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-11254-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are several processes not accounted for in the DEHM model that potentially can affect the estimate of the importance of climate change for the Hg deposition within the Arctic. One process is re-volatilization from the surface. This is partly accounted for by the background concentration as described in section 2.1. It has been speculated that a reduction in sea-ice cover will lead to an enhanced re-volatilization from the Arctic Ocean, while another effect is that TPM deposited on the ice free water is less likely to re-volatilize immediately than when deposited on sea ice and snow and the combination of these two effects may be nearly neutral [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>]. On the other hand, the volatilization is dependent on the gradient between the concentrations in air and water, and a higher concentration of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> in air in the 2090s combined with a larger ice-free part of the Arctic Ocean will lead to a lower re-volatilization of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> from the surface. If re-volatilization was accounted for in the DEHM model this would have reduced the Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> concentrations in air (corresponding to a lower background concentration in the model), which would lead to lower estimated depositions to the surface. However, we estimate that this effect on the reduced oxidation to RGM and subsequent lower deposition is negligible compared to the effect of changes in sea-ice coverage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical studies [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-11254">22</a>] and combined experiments and model studies [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-11254">5</a>] indicate that reactions of Hg with atomic bromine can account for the conversion of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> to RGM during AMDEs, although the understanding of these processes is not yet complete [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>]. It has been suggested that higher temperatures will slow down the gas-phase oxidations and thus reduce the depositions if the present Br levels are unchanged [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>]. There are uncertainties regarding the origin of atmospheric Br that are associated with snow, refreezing leads and formation of first-year sea-ice [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>,
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-12-11254">37</a>]. Following the increasing atmospheric temperature the formation of first year sea ice is expected to increase, which could lead to an increase in release of Br to the atmosphere, which again will result in an increase of the rate of Hg deposition during AMDEs [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
