<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-ijerph-12-11254" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Concluding Remarks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have performed a series of model simulations to test how the Danish Eulerian Hemispheric Model (DEHM) reacts to climate change forcing. We have investigated how the atmospheric concentrations and depositions of Hg in the Arctic changes under a moderate climate change scenario. We have furthermore studied the contribution from the major source areas (Asia, Europe and North America) and finally we have investigated how changes in emissions affect the deposition in the Arctic compared to changes in climate.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the applied SRES A1B climate change scenario, the DEHM model predicts that Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> air concentrations is 4% higher, while RGM and TPM are 41% and 62% lower by the end of the 21st century compared to the end of the 20th century. This results in 18% lower Hg deposition to the Arctic. The reason for these differences is the smaller sea-ice coverage predicted in the 2090s than in the 1990s. This results in a lower oxidation of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> to HgO and therefore a higher concentration of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> and lower concentrations of RGM and TPM and thus lower deposition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We can see from the investigation of the major anthropogenic source areas that Asia contributes with 25% of the deposition to the Arctic, followed by Europe (6%) and North America (5%), with the rest arising from the background concentration. The fraction of contribution does not change significantly under the applied climate change scenario.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DEHM predicts between a 6% increase (Status Quo scenario) and a 37% decrease (zero anthropogenic emissions scenario) in Hg deposition to the Arctic under present day climate depending on which of the four emissions scenarios that are applied. The relative change in Hg deposition to the Arctic between the 1990s and the 2090s is the same for all applied emissions scenarios.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model system predicts total Arctic Hg deposition that are up to 47% lower for the end of 21st century compared to end of 20th century when combining the emission change scenarios with changed climate input. The combined effect of changing both emissions and climate input is different than the sum of the simulation with changed emission and the simulation with changed climate.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study indicates that the deposition of Hg to the Arctic decreases in a future warmer climate, although the changes are moderate. Furthermore, future climate mitigation measures are expected to reduce the atmospheric emissions of Hg further [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-12-11254">2</a>], which will also reduce the deposition. Lower atmospheric depositions in the future would lead to a lower uptake of Hg in the food webs and hence a lower exposure of the Arctic population to Hg if there were no other changes. However, climate change may alter other factors that influence the exposure, such as the air-surface exchange flux and release of Hg from reservoirs stored in glaciers and thawing permafrost, the inflow of riverine Hg to the Arctic Ocean, the methylation/demethylation in the Arctic Ocean and the fresh water systems, as well as the structure and dynamics of fresh water and marine food webs [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-12-11254">1</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>]. The results generated in this study indicate that climate change will reduce Hg depositions to the Arctic, although emission reductions appear to have a larger effect. This knowledge is valuable for decision makers when developing future emission reduction policies to protect the vulnerable ecosystems in the Arctic. However, the results are not very strong to form policies on alone due to the uncertainties. They could be applied in a broader understanding of the effects of Hg exposure to the Arctic population combining them with knowledge on bioaccumulation, human effects, and societal changes (e.g., diet) in a cross disciplinary study to form an integrated model system describing the cycling of Hg from source trough atmospheric transport, bioaccumulation in the food webs, exposure to top predators and humans and the caused effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only one climate change scenario has been applied in this study, and the predicted changes in the deposition of Hg due to changes in climate input is a sensitivity study of the DEHM model system and this does not necessarily reflect a correct climate response in the real atmosphere. There are uncertainties in the applied parameterizations both in this and in other models due to the knowledge gaps in the biogeochemical cycle of Hg [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>]. A slowly increasing trend in modelled atmospheric depositions in the Canadian Arctic in the period 1990–2005 is associated with changes in climate parameters [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-12-11254">9</a>], and this indicates an opposite effect of climate change on deposition to the predictions from this study. Further studies using measurements, other models and other climate change and emission change scenarios are thus needed to resolve this matter. There is also a need for the scientific community to further study the physical and chemical processes that are the most uncertain and that could become more important in a future warmer climate, notably the influence of bromine chemistry on the Hg deposition as discussed in this study. Combining measurements and models can improve our understanding of these processes.
 </p>
</sec>
