<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pervasive shrub encroachment into herb‐dominated ecosystems of high altitudes and latitudes can be attributed to climate change (Formica, Farrer, Ashton, &amp; Suding, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Huss et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Warmer temperatures promote woody encroachment in alpine tundra ecosystems through infilling of openings and advancement of tree‐line (Myers‐Smith et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Shrubs create living snow fences and a thick layer of leaf litter, impacting resident flora and fauna by altering microclimate and nutrient cycling (Becklin, Pallo, &amp; Galen, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Dona &amp; Galen, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Myers‐Smith et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Paleo‐ecological evidence suggests that shrub species are preadapted to invade the open conditions of tundra biomes and have extended their ranges into high altitude and latitude ecosystems under past periods of favorable climate (Naito &amp; Cairns, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Opportunistic growth, clonal spread, and high allocation to reproduction increase biomass and cover (“shrubification”) for these woody gap species, allowing them to rapidly spread into meadow openings (Myers‐Smith et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Fig. 
 <xref rid="ece33272-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). These same life history traits have the potential to alter consumer behavior and reconfigure negative (herbivory) and positive (pollination) plant–animal interactions (e.g., Lara‐Romero, Garcia, Morente‐Lopez, Iriondo, &amp; Brody, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Muñoz, Celedon‐Neghme, Cavieres, &amp; Arroyo, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). Here we ask whether encroachment of shrubby subalpine willows (
 <italic class="italic">Salix glauca and brachycarpa</italic>; hereafter 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic>) into alpine ecosystems interferes with pollination and thus reduces fitness in a native alpine wildflower, the skypilot, 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium viscosum</italic> (hereafter, 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic>).
</p>
