<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change effects on the structural and functional properties of riparian ecosystems remain to be more fully elucidated. Increasing awareness of the importance of wetlands for a number of ecosystem services such as flood protection, water purification, water availability via groundwater recharge, and biodiversity has spurred new studies into the functioning of wetlands in a changing climate (see Catford et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Kominoski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Garssen, Verhoeven, &amp; Soons, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Garssen, Baattrup‐Pedersen, Voesenek, Verhoeven, &amp; Soons, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref> for an overview). Most of the studies conducted so far investigate the effects of climate changes on riparian community composition with focus on the response of a single species or restricted species assemblages (Catford et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Garssen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). A recent extensive review of plant community responses showed that prolonged flooding and increased inundation depth of riparian areas trigger significant shifts in species composition that may lead to either increased or decreased riparian species richness, depending on the environmental characteristics of the areas (Garssen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>).In Garssen et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), species richness was observed to generally decline at flooded sites in nutrient‐rich catchments and at sites previously exhibiting relatively stable hydrographs (for instance rain‐fed lowland streams; see e.g., Beltman, Willems, &amp; Güsewell, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Baattrup‐Pedersen, Jensen, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), whereas an increase in species richness was detected at flooded sites in dry areas (e.g., in deserts and semi‐arid climate regions where many streams are intermittent; see e.g., Stromberg, Hazelton, &amp; White, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Horner, Cunningham, Thomson, Baker, &amp; Mac Nally, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In contrast, almost all studies of the effects of increased drought episodes on riparian plant community responses have shown a decline in species richness, particularly for herbaceous species (e.g., Stromberg, Bagstad, Leenhouts, Lite, &amp; Makings, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Westwood, Teeuw, Wade, Holmes, &amp; Guyard, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; reviewed in Garssen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). A &gt; 30‐day drought period threatens the survival of many species and usually entails a strong reduction in riparian plant biomass, and a high drought intensity (i.e., a 3–4 cm water table decline per day) may impair riparian seedling survival, thereby producing relatively rapid changes in riparian species composition (Garssen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
