<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This suggests that the large reduction in future LPS genesis simulated by HiRAM is caused by a weakening of the large-scale monsoon circulation and a corresponding drop in the ambient vorticity from which LPS form. Although the genesis mechanism of LPS is still the subject of active research (
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>), the presence of large low-level vorticity has been long held to be essential for genesis (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>). Recently, monsoon LPS have also been shown to have structural similarities to weak TCs (
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>) and to have a statistical association with the climatological mean state similar to that of TCs (
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>), which suggests that LPS genesis may also be favored by environments rich in cyclonic vorticity. This reasoning contrasts with a previous argument relating the possible recent decline in LPS activity to a midtropospheric drying (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>); HiRAM simulates such a drying, but it produces a comparatively minor effect on the MDGI (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1709031115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S7
 </ext-link>). The projected weakening of 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="i16" class="math">
   <mi class="mi">η</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> in HiRAM is in broad agreement with that in the CMIP5 ensemble mean, although the HiRAM weakening is stronger (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1709031115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S7
 </ext-link>). Weakening of the large-scale monsoon circulation over the last half-century has also been observed, although its underlying cause is debated (
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>). A slowing of tropical circulations in general may be expected from the increase in static stability that occurs in a warming troposphere (
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>), but the degree to which changes in diabatic heating might compensate in monsoon circulations is unclear.
</p>
