<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In order to assess anthropogenic habitat change as a possible explanation for the hybridisation event we registered, we performed a land-use change analysis considering an area of 119 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, inside the Partenio Regional Park (Regione Campania, Italy). The clearing where the hybridisation event was registered is located in the middle of the study area, approximately 15.6 km from the northern boundary and 2 km from the south-eastern boundary (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). We obtained a map of the area from Google Earth Pro 7.1.5.1557 (Google Inc., Mountain View, CA, USA). By using the ‘historical imagery’ tool, and keeping the extent and resolution of the map constant, we selected two images: one from 10 October 2014, five months after the hybridisation event, and one from 31 October 2006, a few months before the last assessment that confirmed the absence of 
 <italic class="italic">Bufotes balearicus</italic> from the site (
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carpino &amp; Capasso, 2008</xref>). The two images were imported into ArcGIS 10.3.1 (ESRI©), with a resolution of 4.5 m per pixel, and were georeferenced using administrative boundaries as reference points (RMS error = 6.23 m for the 2014 image; RMS error = 4.48 m for the 2006 image). The images were interpreted using direct recognition (
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Campbell, 1978</xref>), considering five discrete land-use classes that hold a clear ecological importance for both toad species: agriculture, forests, natural clearings, natural vegetation (other than forests), and artificial areas. For both images, a vector layer (format shapefile, ESRI©) was produced at a 1:25,000 scale. To perform the land-cover change analysis, following 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Falcucci, Maiorano &amp; Boitani (2007)</xref>, each vector layer was transformed into a raster layer using four different pixel resolutions: 25, 50, 75, and 100 m. The change detection analysis was performed for each pixel resolution, resulting in an average percentage change for every land-cover class.
</p>
