<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We evaluated the uncertainty in projections of climate‐driven distributional changes arising from different methodological decisions, and evaluated whether cross‐validation led to selection of the choices that maximized performance during pronounced historical drought periods, a proxy for future climate change. We focused on wetland‐dependent birds breeding in the Prairie Potholes of North America, a climatically dynamic landscape where climate change may reduce the abundance and productivity of wetlands that provide critical habitat for wetland‐dependent species (Johnson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Sorenson, Goldberg, Root, &amp; Anderson, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Steen, Skagen, &amp; Noon, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The distribution of migratory birds is reflective of the current year's wetland conditions (Fletcher &amp; Koford, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Johnson &amp; Grier, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1988</xref>; Niemuth &amp; Solberg, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Smith, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1970</xref>), allowing for inference into climatic effects on avian occurrence patterns. We used SDMs trained on normal and wet climatic conditions and predicted occurrence under drought to evaluate model performance when projecting to a climatically nonstationary period; future climate projections point to increasing summer drought in this system (Ballard et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). We address the following questions: 
 <list list-type="order" id="ece33403-list-0001" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">What is the amount of uncertainty in projections of range change attributable to a) GCM; b) climate covariate class; c) degree of collinearity; and d) thresholding procedure?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">How is the amount of projected range change affected by choices of a) GCM; b) climate covariate class; c) degree of collinearity; and d) thresholding procedure?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Which choices provide the best ability to extrapolate to a drought period? Are the same choices recommended based on cross‐validation?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
