<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study shows that the domestication of the European goldfinch has had severe consequences on the dynamics of wild populations in western Maghreb and may threaten many other local and Afro-Palearctic migratory songbirds. We first found that the distribution range of the species has undergone rapid retraction during the past 26 years in western Maghreb. We estimated the total number of domesticated goldfinches of 6.3 million in Algeria, and about 15.6 million in the entire western Maghreb. We showed evidence that the currently existing populations of goldfinch are under huge poaching pressure by an established international trading system, which threatens the persistence of the species in the area. Finally, poaching of goldfinches is currently conducted within one of the most important flyways in the world using mainly mist nets which might affect several migratory bird populations flying through this region.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We estimated a loss of range distribution for the European goldfinch of nearly 57% across western Maghreb during the past 26 years. The species is probably extinct or very scarce in the wild in the eastern part of the study area, that is, in Tunisia and Algeria (except for the western part). In our knowledge, such rapid range fragmentation is rare in Palearctic passerines
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. According to BirdLife International
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, the population trends of the species since 1980 have been stable based on provisional data for 21 European countries. Knowing that goldfinch poaching is either absent or low in these countries compared to western Maghreb, our results reveal that intensive poaching could affect severely population dynamics and may ultimately lead to rapid extinction of an abundant species. Although poaching has probably played a major role in the extinction of many wild populations, other factors like climate change leading to severe drought and forest fires shrinking the potential habitats for the species might have exacerbated the rapid range retraction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are a few mutually non-exclusive hypotheses that may explain why Moroccan populations did not decline as much as Algerian and Tunisian populations. First, there might be differences in poaching pressure between the three countries of western Maghreb so that Moroccan natural populations of goldfinch were less exploited than Algerian and Tunisian populations during the 1990s and early 2000s. Second, the higher availability of forests (an important habitat for the species) in Morocco
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> could have conferred a larger carrying capacity for the species and more resilience to population extinction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Third, the connection with the European populations of goldfinch may also have contributed to the persistence of Moroccan populations. In fact, in terms of distance, Moroccan populations are closer to European populations with a minimum distance between the Spanish and Moroccan coast of 14 km at the Strait of Gibraltar. Thus, it is possible that regular colonization of Moroccan habitats by Spanish populations compensates, to some extent, the effects of intensive poaching
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results showed that the price of the European goldfinch in the market, even corrected for the monthly per capita income, increased exponentially during the past 26 years. As it is the case in many species with economic value
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, the price increased continually as the species became rarer. The expensiveness of the species was probably one of the factors that increased the poaching motivation and caused extinction of wild populations. In addition, it also places the remaining populations under high harvest risk since one goldfinch is currently worth nearly the third of the average monthly income. Hence, because of the low effectiveness of the conservation plans, many non-poachers probably became increasingly interested in capturing or trading the goldfinch given the current economic crisis and high unemployment rate that countries of the western Maghreb encounter. Further conservation policies should include an economic perspective in the elaboration of new laws by understanding the relationship between the demand (customer) and the supply (poacher)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. We suspect a combination of the snob effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> ‒ people pay more money for rarer species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> and the bandwagon effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> ‒ people’s valuation of the species increased its popularity among society. In other words, the increased economic value of the goldfinch following the decline of the wild populations intensified the poaching pressure, which in turn heightened the popularity and social value of the species, leading to the increase in the demand. Therefore, conservationists and policy makers should elaborate effective supply-side and demand-side antipoaching policies and carefully think about the potential interplay between them
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We estimated an average of 6.3 million goldfinches domesticated for Algeria and 15.6 million for western Maghreb. This most likely represents the highest density of domesticated European goldfinches in the world. According to our estimates, nearly every family in the region possesses one caged individual, which reflects the cultural importance of the species to local people. Although our estimates were based on extrapolations from 15 provinces to the entire Algerian territory (48 provinces), we, nevertheless, carefully chose provinces that are well-distributed across the northern part of the country (east, center and west) where most Algerian population lives. Our extrapolation to western Maghreb (Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco) which was motivated by the similarity of the cultural importance and popularity of the goldfinch between the three countries needs further confirmation to overcome potential under- or overestimation biases. Surprisingly, a very low proportion of domesticated goldfinches are bred in captivity, which means that the primary supply for the pet owners are individuals that come from the flea markets, that is, those poached from wild populations. This lack of captive breeding combined with the large distribution of domestication for a species that has shown a severe range retraction is deeply alarming and requires enforcement of existing laws and raising awareness of the ecological consequences of poaching in general and the unsustainable practice of the cultural domestication of the bird in particular. Nonetheless, the cultural component of the domestication of the goldfinch has to be taken into account to solve the problem by applying actions that both satisfy people's needs and protect natural populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our survey revealed the international illegal trading network of European goldfinch that occurs in western Maghreb. Due to the extinction of most Tunisian and Algerian natural populations of the species, representing the primary supply for the local cultural domestication, the demand for the species increased. Thus, poachers started to illegally export the species from Morocco, where populations are still flourishing, to Algeria and Tunisia. This places the last populations of the Maghreb under high extinction risks because the Moroccan populations of European goldfinch are harvested to meet the demands of three countries which triples the poaching pressure. Moreover, cases of exportation of the goldfinch from western Maghreb to Europe (France and Belgium) were recently reported, which enlarges the international trading system of the species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. This international network of European goldfinch trafficking has to be regulated rapidly by reinforcing surveillance at borders, before the species goes extinct in its extreme southern margin of the Palearctic.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The introduction of mist nets as a capture tool is the most alarming poaching aspect that we recorded in our study. In fact, as the species became rare, the effectiveness of ground nets and lime sticks reduced because individuals have to land to be trapped, which is not the case for mist nets. The efficiency, larger capture capacity, and invasive aspect of mist nets could induce substantial collateral damage to local and migratory species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. North Africa is an important avian region where several species of European birds fly through or stop over twice a year during the migration from breeding areas in Europe to wintering grounds in Africa. We recorded 16 passerine species captured as by-catch during the goldfinch poaching from only 12 poachers who used mist net trapping in Northeast Algeria. Therefore, the number of species that have been intercepted in the entire western Maghreb must be substantially higher, especially in Morocco where millions of birds cross Gibraltar to reach African wintering areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Although our data are only qualitative, they should sound the alarm for immediate actions. The fate of birds captured as by-catch remains unclear, but we have evidence that the number of traded songbirds in the market, including migratory species, increased during the last five years, which coincides with the introduction of mist nets in the wild. Therefore, it is likely that the rarity and expensiveness of the European goldfinch led local people to seek for alternative pet birds which in turn became the target of poaching. This may be the start of another round of extensive poaching not for one species, but for a large spectrum of wild songbirds, which puts the Palearctic migratory birds under unprecedented poaching threat in the region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the species was listed in the nationally protected birds in the three countries of western Maghreb, the local conservation actions and politics of the species are still inefficient. The concentration of the conservation authorities is directed towards natural populations, international borders and national checkpoints. These measures are crucial, but do not treat the problem from its roots since the main trade center of European goldfinch is the weekly flea markets that are widespread in the region, representing the primary link between poachers, traders and customers. There, freshly captured wild birds are illegally sold all year long without any surveillance. Thus, future conservation strategies must firstly consider banning illegal trading of wild individuals in flea markets. In addition, other key urgent actions should include restoration planning, artificial breeding of the species, monitoring of wild populations, and sensitization of local people. First, the restoration of wild populations of European goldfinch in western Maghreb should be successful given the advantageous demographic proprieties of the species. In fact, the high reproductive rate of the species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> and the fast maturity of juveniles offer the species biological attributes that increase the recruitment probability, contribute highly to population growth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>, and potentially result in recolonization of habitats and range expansion. Second, promoting artificial breeding of the species in captivity is a top priority because it offers a sustainable harvest solution that should produce enough individuals to meet the cultural and socio-economic needs for local people. Third, regular individual marking and monitoring of wild populations are crucial to assess the success of restoration plans, estimate demographic parameters (survival and fertility), assess dispersal of individuals, and determine population trends. Finally, a social sensitization scheme should be initiated to raise the awareness of people about the consequences of poaching on ecosystem functioning and human well-being.
 </p>
</sec>
