<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">International trading</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between June 2008 and July 2016, a total of 18569 European goldfinches were intercepted on 30 occasions by the Algerian authorities (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). All these birds originated from Morocco and illegally crossed the Algerian border. These goldfinches were intercepted in seven Algerian provinces located in northwestern Algeria near the Moroccan border (4 provinces), in the north (1 province), and northeastern Algeria near the Tunisian border (2 provinces). Of the total number of European goldfinches, 98.1% were intended to be traded in Algeria and 1.9% were heading to Tunisia (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6a,b</a>). The mean batch size of transported European goldfinches was 618.9 ± 521.3 goldfinches (n = 30; range = 65–2020 birds).
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Apprehension of a thousand European goldfinches (
     <span class="italic">Carduelis carduelis</span>) by conservation authorities for illegal trading in Northwest Algeria near the Moroccan border (Oran, 2016).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2017_1103_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e910" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Number of individuals (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and occasions (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) of interceptions of the European goldfinch (
     <span class="italic">Carduelis carduelis</span>) by authorities in Algeria. The yellow arrow indicates the direction of European goldfinch exportation for international trading. Algeria is divided into administrative provinces. The map was made with MapInfo Professional software (version 15.0, 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pitneybowes.com/us/location-intelligence/geographic-information-systems/mapinfo-pro.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.pitneybowes.com/us/location-intelligence/geographic-information-systems/mapinfo-pro.html</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2017_1103_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e934" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
