<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cities are growing and many rural or peri-urban areas are becoming urban. By 2050, 60% more people will live in urban areas than today.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="TRU194C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C1">1</a>
  </span> In tropical climates within Asia and Africa, the proportion of the urban population is increasing by 1.5 and 1.1% per annum, respectively.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="TRU194C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C1">1</a>
  </span> Over the same time period, depending on the season and exact location within the tropics, the mean surface temperature is expected to rise by between 1 and 3°C.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="TRU194C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C2">2</a>
  </span> Urbanization and climate change could each alter the composition, intensity and seasonality of pathogen transmission and disease incidence across the tropics, but since both changes will occur at once, the drivers of these disease systems will interact in complex ways to determine what diseases are present and the corresponding seasonality of infection, disease and death.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tropics include much of the world's rural population as well as many of the fastest growing urban centers.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="TRU194C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C1">1</a>
  </span> In addition to chronic diseases that afflict more industrialized areas, these areas are disproportionately burdened by infectious diseases.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="TRU194C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C3">3</a>
  </span> While climate change and urbanization could act synergistically to increase the burden of current endemic diseases within densely populated urban cores, they could also result in complex (and possibly antagonistic) outcomes. These effects are most unpredictable in rural and peri-urban locations undergoing the transition into more developed, prosperous cities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The timing and magnitude of seasonal patterns in all-cause mortality is, of course, driven at any given location by the particular local mix of causes of death, and their individual seasonal characteristics. This further complicates predictions of the impact of changing climate and urbanization. Even if the likely effects on major causes of death could be predicted, their co-distributions, interactions and overall impact on mortality, and seasonality of mortality, would vary geographically. This is made yet more complex by the fact that both urbanization and climate change may alter ranges or occurrence rates of both infectious and chronic diseases.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="TRU194C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C3">3</a>,
   <a rid="TRU194C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#TRU194C4">4</a>
  </span>
 </p>
</sec>
