<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term (15–150 years) annual wild boar hunting bag data were acquired for 69 regions from 12 European countries. The relative change in the hunting bag from one year to another (λ = bag
   <sub>t</sub>/bag
   <sub>t-1</sub>) was calculated after excluding hunting bags smaller than 0.01 animals shot/km² (799 data points), as such small values cause large uncertainty in estimating λ. This procedure yielded a data set in which most data points prior to 1950 were excluded, allowing us to focus mainly on the period showing exponential wild boar population growth (see 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0132178.g001">Fig 1b</a> for some examples). Further, 87 data points were excluded that could have been affected by the political situation at that time (World War 2, Balkan War, split of Czechoslovakia). The final data set included 64 regions out of 12 European countries (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0132178.g001">Fig 1a</a>; details in 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s004">S1 Table</a>). In sum we analysed a total of 2075 annual hunting bags (mean: 32.5 years per region).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monthly precipitation sums and mean temperatures were acquired for the respective regions and periods (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s005">S2 Table</a>). Seasonal (3 months) precipitation sums and temperature means (weighted by the number of days per month) were calculated from the monthly data for spring (March–May), summer (June–August), autumn (September–November), and winter (December–February). Spatial autocorrelation analysis of the climatic data revealed that in none of the climatic variables the difference between climate stations increased below a distance of 300 to 400 km (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s001">S1 Fig</a>). However, climate stations used were not separated by more than 268 km to the next climate station in the data set. Thus, climate data can be considered representative even for the largest regions in our data set.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of food availability on population dynamics were investigated using the Austrian subsample (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 135 years, 6 regions (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s004">S1 Table</a>), mean: 22.5 years per region). Rank data on beech mast intensity (0 = &lt; 30% pollination, mast failure; 1 = 30–50% pollination; 2 = 50–70% pollination; 3 = 70–85% pollination; 4 = 85–100% pollination, full mast) were obtained from the Austrian Federal Office and Research Centre for Forests (BFW, bfw.ac.at/rz/pollen.main) for 1976–2013. In years where multiple measurements were available per region the rank data were averaged in order to obtain a more accurate measurement for the whole region. Data on areas under cultivation of corn (
   <span class="italic">Zea mays</span> L.) and potatoes (
   <span class="italic">Solanum tuberosum</span> L.) were acquired from Statistics Austria (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.statistik.at" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.statistik.at</span>) and were available from 1960 to 2011 and from 1966 to 2011, respectively.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male and/or female adult (&gt; 2 years) wild boar body mass data were obtained for one Italian region (Arezzo, Tuscany; M. Apollonio, pers. com.), three French regions [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref026">26</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref027">27</a>], three German regions [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref028">28</a>], one Spanish region [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref029">29</a>], one region from the Netherlands [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref030">30</a>], three regions of the former Soviet Union, reviewed in [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref025">25</a>], and one Austrian region (own data). It has been shown recently that in many species body size decreases as a response to climate change [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref031">31</a>]. Consequently, in order to include only data for comparable periods, data published before 1970 were excluded from the analysis of body mass. If only dressed body mass was available, live body mass was estimated by multiplying dressed mass by 1.25 (for Central European data) and 1.15 (for Eastern European data), respectively, to account for different ways of dressing in these areas [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref025">25</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">National data on the number of traffic accidents involving wild boar and the number of cars and trucks registered were acquired for Austria (1974–2011; Source: Statistics Austria, 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.statistik.at" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.statistik.at</span>), Germany (2007–2011; Sources: German Hunting Association, and German Federal Office of Statistics, 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.destatis.de" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.destatis.de</span>), and Switzerland (1992–2011; Source: Swiss Federal Office of Statistics, 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bfs.admin.ch" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.bfs.admin.ch</span>). In these three countries every accident involving a game animal has to be reported to the police and is therefore well documented.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test the reliability of wild boar hunting bags as a proxy for wild boar population size, we computed Pearson’s correlation coefficients for the relationship between the number of traffic accidents involving wild boar (corrected for the number of cars and trucks registered) and the hunting bag (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s002">S2a–S2c Fig</a>) as well as those between the relative year-to-year changes in the number of traffic accidents and λ (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s002">S2d–S2f Fig</a>). This was done for Austria, Germany and Switzerland (i.e., countries where reliable traffic accident data were available), with the latter in parts employing a different hunting system (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s002">S2 Fig</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test climatic effects on λ, temperature means and precipitation sums were considered during six seasons, spring (March-May), summer (June-August) and autumn (September-November) of the previous year, winter (December-February), and spring and summer of the census year. This large number of climatic variables and their interactions rendered statistical models computationally unfeasible. We therefore used the random forest method (a combination of binary decision trees created of bootstrapped samples of the data set and choosing randomly a subset of explanatory variables at each split [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref032">32</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref033">33</a>]) to pre-select important variables among all possible climatic variables. The number of variables randomly sampled as candidates at each split was set to 4 (number of predictor variables divided by 3) and the number of trees in the forest was set to 2000. The result of this analysis was very robust to changes of these parameters and showed that seasonal precipitation data contributed little to explaining the observed variance in λ (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s003">S3 Fig</a>). Therefore, only seasonal temperature data were included in subsequent analysis. Additionally, regional long-term mean winter and summer temperatures as well as their interactions with current mean winter and summer temperatures were included in the model in order to test for the effect of long-term thermal conditions. We chose the 30-year period from 1973 to 2002 to calculate average long-term temperatures because data were available for all regions without missing values for that period. We further included the long-term average of summer and yearly precipitation sums in the model, which were calculated over the same period as the long-term temperatures. Further, to test whether population density affected λ, 5-year averages of hunting bags (animals shot per km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) preceding the census year were included in the model, as a proxy of density, along with its interaction with mean winter temperature. The use of hunting bag data as a proxy of density is justified by the strong correlation of hunting bag data and number of traffic accidents involving wild boar (see 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s002">S2a–S2c Fig</a>). The average of the previous 5-years was chosen instead of a single measure from the respective previous year to avoid “regression to the mean” effects [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref034">34</a>], because the chance of a high λ occurring at random is much higher after a year with a low population density. To ease comparisons all variables were standardized to a mean of 0 and a SD of 0.5 [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref035">35</a>]. Finally, country and region were included in all models as nested random effects in order to correct for potentially consistent regional influences on hunting bags (e.g. differences in overall hunting pressure). Inspection of the distribution of residuals of this full linear mixed effects (lme) model by means of histograms and quantile-quantile plots gave no evidence for serious deviations from normality. This also applies to all models described below. We used linear mixed effects models because the pre-analyses showed that those were superior in describing the data, according to the Akaike Information Criterium corrected for small sample size (AICc), compared to additive mixed effects models.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The full lme model was further analysed using a multi-model averaging approach [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref036">36</a>]. Hereby, the multi-model average was calculated by including all possible nested models. However, the averaged estimates did not differ essentially when only certain subsets of models (i.e., with a delta AICc of below 4 and 10, respectively) were used for calculating the model-averaged parameter estimates (data not shown). Model-averaged parameter estimates were calculated with the natural average method, in order to avoid shrinkage towards zero, especially of weak effects [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref035">35</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref037">37</a>]. As we further aimed to determine which variable had the strongest impact on λ we also calculated model averaged estimates using the zero-method [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref035">35</a>]. However, the order of effect sizes of significant variables was identical for both model-averaging methods (compare 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0132178.t001">Table 1</a> vs. 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s006">S3 Table</a>). To obtain correct parameter estimates for main effects of variables involved in interactions, we selected models used for averaging as follows: If an interaction was significant in the model-average we selected only models where this interaction also was significant to calculate the weighted averages of the parameter estimates (i.e., annual and long-term winter temperature; 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0132178.t001">Table 1a</a>). In contrast, if an interaction was not significant in the model-average, we selected only models not containing this interaction, and models in which this interaction was not significant, to calculate weighted averages (i.e., annual and long-term summer temperature, and density; 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0132178.t001">Table 1</a>). This procedure of averaging also was applied in all further multi-model averages described below. Model-averaged residuals were subsequently checked for spatio-temporal autocorrelation by means of semivariograms which showed that residuals were neither temporally nor spatially autocorrelated (Figures A and B in 
   <a rid="pone.0132178.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0132178.s007">S1 File</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0132178.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0132178.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Impact of climate and food availability on wild boar population growth rate (λ)</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0132178.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0132178.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">(a) European data set (
        <span class="italic">n</span> = 2075)
       </th>
       <th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">(b) Austrian data set (
        <span class="italic">n</span> = 135)
       </th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">term</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">estimate</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">P</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RVI</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">term</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">estimate</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">P</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RVI</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">winter temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.180</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.025</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">&lt; 0.001</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">1.00</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">winter temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.237</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.064</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">&lt; 0.001</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">1.00</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">long-term winter temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">-0.252</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.033</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">&lt; 0.001</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">1.00</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">mast</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.284</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.112</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.012</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">1.00</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">prior autumn temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.179</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.027</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">&lt; 0.001</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">1.00</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">mast: winter temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">-0.926</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.247</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">&lt; 0.001</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.98</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">population density</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">-0.065</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.016</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">&lt; 0.001</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">1.00</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">prior autumn temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.173</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.062</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.005</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.94</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">summer temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">-0.050</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.023</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.031</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.82</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">long-term winter temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">-0.172</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.084</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.044</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.82</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">winter temperature: long-term winter temperature</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">-0.059</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.027</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.030</span>
       </td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">0.80</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">population density</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.133</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">area under cultivation of potatoes</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.096</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prior spring temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">area under cultivation of corn</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.092</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prior summer temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.027</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">summer temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.063</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">long-term summer temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.012</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">prior spring temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.022</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">long-term summer precipitation</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
       <td rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">winter temperature: long-term winter temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.045</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">winter temperature: population density</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">long-term yearly precipitation</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mast: long-term winter temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.098</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.664</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">spring temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.011</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mast: population density</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.097</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.291</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">summer temperature: long-term summer temperature</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.022</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td>
       <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="t001fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Parameters estimate, standard error (
      <span class="italic">SE</span>), p-value (
      <span class="italic">P</span>), and relative variable importance (
      <span class="italic">RVI</span>) for each term included in the multi-model averages of the European data set (a) and the Austrian subset (b). Interaction terms are indicated by colons, significant predictor variables are highlighted bold. See 
      <a rid="sec002" ref-type="sec" href="#sec002">methods</a> for the definition of seasons.
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to smaller sample size only those variables were included in the full lme model of the Austrian multi-model average that were found to be important in the European wide analysis (
   <a rid="pone.0132178.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0132178.t001">Table 1a</a>). To assess effects of food availability, beech mast of the previous year (binary coded; 1: moderate or full beech mast (categories 3 or 4; pollination ≥ 70%), 0: less than moderate beech mast (categories 0–2; pollination &lt; 70%), as well as areas under cultivation (% of total area of a region) of corn and potatoes during the previous year were included. Furthermore, the interaction between beech mast and winter temperature was included, because the vast amount of energy provided by tree seeds might have compensated for unfavourable climatic conditions. In addition to region, beech mast in the respective census year was added as a random factor to the Austrian subset models, to account for possible effects of mast intensity on hunting success.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further, we tested whether the frequencies of mast failure (mast category ≤ 1), moderate (1 &lt; mast category ≤ 3) and full beech mast (mast category &gt; 3; each coded 1/0) have changed in Austria since 1976 by computing three binomial linear mixed effects models, respectively, each with year as fixed and region as random effect (
   <span class="italic">n</span> for all three models = 165 years, 6 regions, mean: 27.5 years per region).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to test for an association of body mass with regional climate we computed the multi-model average of a linear model with adult (&gt; 2 years) wild boar body mass as a function of the long-term mean winter-temperature (see below), sex and their interaction (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 22 European regions).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were performed in R.3.0.2 [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref038">38</a>]. Linear mixed-effects models were computed using the package lme4 [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref039">39</a>], for multi-model averaging we used the package MuMIn [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref040">40</a>] and own functions. The random forest analysis was performed using the package randomForest (V 4.6–10) [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref041">41</a>]. Spatio-temporal autocorrelation of the residuals was checked using the package gstat [
   <a rid="pone.0132178.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132178.ref042">42</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
