<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Firstly, it is important to bear in mind that religious beliefs are often very prescriptive and specific, and elements like doctrine and subjective projection may underlie certain beliefs. They can also be either individually or communally held (Loubser 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>:72). It is for this reason that the formulation of certain Q-sort statements that may be regarded as being of a religious nature at face value (e.g. statement 8) may not coincide with a participant’s specific formulation of their religious beliefs, causing them to disagree with the statement altogether. This binary thinking stands in opposition to the evidential non-binary thinking exhibited throughout the research process, indicating a possible exception for religious beliefs. Beliefs entail more of what can be seen as disbelief – ‘on the one hand a system of beliefs which one accepts, and on the other, a series of systems of beliefs which one rejects’ (Rokeach 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1956</xref>:228) – and this will result in participants rather discarding statements they do not agree with. This rigid belief–disbelief dualism seems to be especially prominent in thinking that involves deeper religious commitments. This does not, therefore, automatically exclude religiosity when formulating conceptions of climate and climate change – allowance should be made for the participant rather holding different religious beliefs. This was illustrated especially clearly in the case of Participant #4 in Phase Four of the research process. Participant #4 loaded significantly for Factor 3 but instead opted for Factor 5. This variance may be attributed to the fact that they explained their religious views extensively during the actual interview in Phase Four, citing reasons for their climate beliefs but seemed to disagree with the individual statements that comprise the Factor 3 narrative.
</p>
