<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical and future net anthropogenic nitrogen inputs</div>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nitrogen input to the watersheds was captured in the form of net anthropogenic nitrogen input (NANI), which is defined as the sum of five components: fertilizer nitrogen input, agricultural nitrogen fixation, net food and feed import, atmospheric deposition, and nonfood crop export. Net food and feed import accounts for crop and animal nitrogen production (removal of nitrogen from the watershed) and human and animal nitrogen consumption (addition of nitrogen to the watershed) and includes bioenergy production and consumption. The nonfood crop export represents the nitrogen in cotton and tobacco harvested for sale and exported elsewhere for nonfood use. On average during the historical period, fertilizer was +72% of NANI; fixation was +45% of NANI; deposition was+ 14% of NANI; food and feed import was −30% of NANI (negative sign designates net export over the continental United States); and nonfood crop export was+ 0.78% of NANI. The nonfood crop export represents nitrogen leaving the watershed and its value is subtracted from NANI while all other components are added to estimate NANI. NANI was estimated using two different methods. First, for the empirical model development and for assessing historical TN loading, available data on the various NANI components was used to estimate historical NANI. Second, for estimating future TN loading, NANI estimates were developed based on output available in the LUH2 dataset. In addition, historical NANI was also estimated directly based on LUH2 data in the analysis focusing on isolating the impact of future changes to cropland area, developed land, or fertilizer application rates, in the absence of concurrent changes to the other factors. The first approach is described here, while the second is presented in Section “Future changes in TN flux due to change in land use and land management”.</p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observation-based NANI estimates were obtained as described in an earlier study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> for 1987–2005. NANI for 1976–1986 was estimated by modifying this methodology to accommodate a more limited data record during this decade. Briefly, fertilizer rates for 1987–2005, 1985–1986, and 1976–1984 were obtained from three earlier studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>, respectively. Atmospheric deposition rates for 1979–2005 were based on data from the National Atmospheric Deposition Program
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>. The NADP monitoring network was established in 1978, but had very few monitoring stations in that initial year. Atmospheric deposition rates for 1976, 1977, and 1978 were therefore assumed remain constant at 1979 levels. Agricultural nitrogen fixation, net food and feed import, and nonfood crop export were estimated for the agricultural census years of 1987, 1992, 1997, 2002, and 2007 using the NANI toolbox
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
  </span> and for the intervening years (1988–1991; 1993–1996; 1998–2001; 2003–2006) using linear interpolation. For the years preceding 1987, agricultural nitrogen fixation and net food and feed import were estimated for each HUC8 watershed by extrapolating a linear trend estimated based on the values for 1987, 1992, 2997, 2002, 2007, and 2012. Nonfood crop export, which are an extremely small component of NANI (on average 0.78% of NANI), were assumed to remain at 1987 levels for 1976–1986.
 </p>
</sec>
