<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of concomitant changes in precipitation</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The discussion up to this point has focused on the impacts of changes in land use and land management in response to broader societal shifts, as represented by the LUH2 scenarios and additional scenarios from the GCAM IAM. We now shift to accounting for the compound impacts of changes in land use and land management as well as changes in precipitation patterns resulting from climate change.</p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concomitant climate-induced changes in precipitation can either amplify TN flux increases or negate TN flux reductions due to land management, and the impacts of land use and land management and those of climate are not necessarily simply additive (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). For example, the reductions in TN fluxes for the continental United States resulting from anticipated changes in land use and land management for the SSP2-4.5 and the SSP5-8.5 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) scenarios would be fully offset by the impacts of projected changes in precipitation patterns. For the four other scenarios, the increases in TN fluxes would be further amplified by projected changes in precipitation patterns. As expected, the additional impact of climate would be greatest for scenarios associated with more extensive changes to climate (SSP3-7.0 and SSP5-8.5). Taken together, whereas the range of anticipated changes in the absence of concomitant changes to climate is −7 to 54% for the continental US, this range becomes 1–68% when both sets of drivers are taken into account. In addition, as previously noted
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>, the impacts of climate-change-induced precipitation changes are themselves regionally heterogeneous. The Northeast exhibits the strongest impacts both when considering land management alone (with loading increases ranging from 17 to 374%) and when considering the additional impacts of climate change (with total loading increases from both drivers ranging from 45 to 492%). In addition, in some cases the impacts of land management and climate changes are not additive (e.g., SSP3-7.0 scenario in the Northeast; Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1f</a>), illustrating the importance of considering these two sets of drivers concurrently. It is noteworthy that for some scenarios such as SSP2-4.5, decreases in nutrient loading due to changes in land management can help to offset increases in loading that would result from changes in precipitation patterns associated with the corresponding climate outcome. Such examples point to the possibility of not only limiting impacts of land management change on nutrient loading (as discussed earlier), but indeed of using land management to address eutrophication resulting from changes to the physical climate system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beyond the United States, Asian regions that have previously been identified as being particularly susceptible to increases in eutrophication as a result of future changes in precipitation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> also exhibit large projected future increases in cropland area and total fertilizer usage across the majority of prototypical pathways examined here (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>), suggesting that the overall scale of direct and indirect anthropogenic impacts is likely to be substantially larger than when considering climate alone. Globally, among regions with nonzero fertilizer use during the historical period (colored land regions in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>), the direction of change in fertilizer usage is consistent for at least five of the six examined scenarios for 67% of land area (colored regions in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>). Regions in South, East, and Southeast Asia stand out relative to other regions in having both high-historical fertilizer usage and a robust and large projected increase in fertilizer use, placing them at a high risk for a substantial future increase in eutrophication. These regions also coincide with those identified in an earlier study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> as being at high risk for future increases in eutrophication based on their high-historical precipitation and robust projected future increase in precipitation. When taken together, these two sets of analyses indicate that climate and societal changes are likely to conspire in this region to substantially impact inland and coastal water quality. Such intensified eutrophication could substantially impact water supplies, fisheries, and ecosystems. It is important to note, however, that the prototypical pathways examined here do not cover all possible outcomes, which will depend in no small part on policy and legislative action by individual countries. For example, future nitrogen use efficiency may improve in China and India as both countries are now increasing efforts to reduce nitrogen pollution by encouraging farmers to adopt best management practices
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span> and by promoting organic farming (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://darpg.gov.in/sites/default/files/Paramparagat%20Krishi%20Vikas%20Yojana.pdf" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://darpg.gov.in/sites/default/files/Paramparagat%20Krishi%20Vikas%20Yojana.pdf</span>).
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Highly populated regions in South, East, and Southeast Asia are at high risk of increased eutrophication due to large and robust projected increase in fertilizer application rates. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Fertilizer usage per unit area for the historical period (1976–2005) averaged across the 30 years. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Projected change in fertilizer usage per unit area by the end-of-the-century period (2071–2100) relative to the historical period, averaged across the 30 years and six scenarios and shown only for regions where at least five of the six scenarios agree on the direction of change from the historical to the end-of-the-century period. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Regions shown in white have no fertilizer usage; 
     <span class="bold">b</span> regions shown in white either have no fertilizer usage or do not have at least five scenarios with a consistent direction of change
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8884_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e804" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, we find that societal choices about land use and land management will have dramatic impacts on future nitrogen loading within the continental United States. In some cases, climate mitigation efforts could result in unintended increases in eutrophication, but opportunities to concurrently limit climate change and eutrophication do exist. Climate-induced changes in precipitation will exacerbate any loading increases due intensification of land use, or reduce the benefits of improved land management. Globally, South, East, and Southeast Asia will likely experience increased eutrophication by the end-of-the-century given projected trends in land use, land management, and precipitation across the majority of scenarios examined here. These results imply that strategies aimed at reducing eutrophication and associated water quality impacts must be based on an assessment of the combined impacts of changes in socioeconomic development and climate. Whereas some societal pathways can achieve climate mitigation while increasing food production, other mitigation pathways may have significant detrimental impact on environmental sustainability.</p>
</sec>
