<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Excessive nitrogen runoff is the primary cause of eutrophication in estuaries and coastal waters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. This eutrophication has led to increases in the occurrence, frequency, and intensity of water quality impairments such as harmful algal blooms (HABs)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> and hypoxia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, which impact human and ecosystem health
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span> and are also linked to increased ocean acidification
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anthropogenic activities that directly impact nitrogen export to water bodies include nitrogen inputs to watersheds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> and conversion of land to cropland and developed land
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. These activities are themselves linked to societal trends in population, wastewater management, fossil fuel use, agricultural management and productivity, dietary choices, and import and export of food products. As societies change, their choices will therefore also impact nitrogen runoff
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, but the possible impact of these changes have only been examined on limited scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> and out to at most 2030
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> or 2050
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anthropogenic activity also indirectly impacts nitrogen export through climate change and associated changes in precipitation patterns, because precipitation amount, intensity, and frequency affect the amount of nitrogen transported to downstream water bodies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Future changes in precipitation patterns will depend on broader climate outcomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, thus impacting future nitrogen loads, but existing studies have primarily been conducted at watershed-scale, and have only considered precipitation projections averaged across an ensemble of global climate models (GCMs)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> or projections from one to three individual GCMs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. One recent study, however, used precipitation projections from 21 GCMs to examine changes in total nitrogen (TN) export for the entire continental United States, finding that changes in precipitation patterns alone could increase riverine TN export for the continental United States by 19% by the end-of-the-century for a business-as-usual scenario
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only a handful of studies has examined the combined effects of land management and climate change on nitrogen loading, and these have focused on individual watersheds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An assessment of future nitrogen loading under various land use and land management scenarios, on their own and in combination with concomitant changes in climate, is necessary to understand the impacts of long-term societal changes on nitrogen loading. Here, we assess these impacts for the continental United States and through to the end of the 21st century across a set of alternative socioeconomic development pathways.</p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Projected future changes due to land conversion to cropland or developed land and changes in fertilizer application rates as considered here are based on integrated land use and emission scenarios obtained by combining shared socioeconomic pathways (SSPs, a.k.a. socioeconomic development pathways) and representative concentration pathways (RCPs, a.k.a. climate outcomes)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Five socioeconomic development pathways were developed in preparation for the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 6 (CMIP6) set of climate simulations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, and include SSP1 Sustainability, SSP2 Middle of the road, SSP3 Regional rivalry, SSP4 Inequality, and SSP5 Fossil-fueled development
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. These five SSPs represent state-of-the-art prototypical pathways for global environmental change during the 21st century, including projections under assumptions ranging from sustainable growth to increased consumption over the period 2015–2100. These SSPs, however, are not intended to represent a comprehensive set of possible futures, and other pathways have also been proposed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. Integrated assessment models (IAMs) were used to produce scenarios by combining these pathways with a range of climate outcomes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. The resulting land use projections were harmonized so as to provide a common starting point in 2015, and are available through the land use harmonization 2 (LUH2) dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of six combinations of socioeconomic development pathways and climate outcomes are considered here. These include the four Tier 1 scenarios
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, namely SSP1-2.6, SSP2-4.5, SSP3-7.0, and SSP5-8.5, each of which was contributed by a different IAM (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), as well as two of the Tier 2 scenarios, namely SSP4-3.4 and SSP4-6.0, both of which were contributed by the GCAM IAM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span> (see Methods for additional details). Following earlier work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, the second number in each scenario represents the corresponding climate outcome; for example, SSP1-2.6 is the SSP1 Sustainability pathway combined with the RCP2.6 climate outcome (i.e., achieving a radiative forcing of 2.6 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> in 2100). The SSP4 pathway was combined with two climate outcomes, yielding the SSP4-3.4 and SSP4-6.0 scenarios, achieving a radiative forcing of 3.4 and 6.0 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> in 2100, respectively.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, examining the combined impacts of socioeconomic development pathways and changes in precipitation patterns associated with a particular climate outcome can provide insight into whether direct and indirect impacts of anthropogenic activity will compound or offset one another in terms of their effects on nitrogen loading. We therefore also examine the joint influence of direct (via land use and land management) and indirect (via climate change-induced changes in precipitation patterns) societal impacts on future TN loading. Future changes in precipitation patterns are based on projections from CMIP5 models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span> for four climate outcomes (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5) (see Methods for additional details). Based on previous work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>, future changes in precipitation that are considered include changes in total annual precipitation and changes to extreme springtime precipitation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of changes in land use, land management, and precipitation patterns on TN flux is examined at eight-digit hydrologic unit (HUC8) subbasin scale within the continental United States using an updated version of an empirical model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> that estimates TN fluxes based on annual precipitation, extreme springtime precipitation, net anthropogenic nitrogen inputs, and land use (see Methods for further details).
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We find that societal choices will substantially impact riverine total nitrogen loading for the continental United States by the end of the century, and that regional impacts will be even larger. Future changes in precipitation will exacerbate loading increases. Although increased loading is possible for both high- and low-emission pathways, we find that limiting climate change and eutrophication can also be achieved concurrently. Increases in cropland area and agricultural intensification will likely impact other parts of the world as well, including vast portions of Asia.</p>
</sec>
