<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Interestingly, P concentrations responded less than N concentrations to changes in precipitation and temperature. Many reasons may account for this disconnection between climate and soil P across environmental gradients. For example, soil P is strongly linked to soil type and bedrock availability. Two sites with a similar climate may thus have a naturally different amount of soil total P. Soil P is also highly influenced by soil age. P is thus highly limited in ancient soils, primarily caused by P depletion due to prolonged weathering over millennia, even though soil P is often bound in complexes with Al, Ca, Fe, or allophane clay in young soils that contain an abundance of total P but where P is poorly available (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vitousek et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Walker and Syers, 1976</xref>). We did not control for soil age in our study, which may also account for the noisy relationship between soil P and climatic gradients. In addition, vegetation type may strongly influence the availability of P in soils. For example, in P-limited ecosystems, whether ancient, P-impoverished soils or young, potentially fertile soils (rich in total P, but with low P availability), plant species (e.g. Proteaceae family in Australan soils) with cluster roots, cluster-like roots, or dauciform roots that exude large amounts of P-mobilizing carboxylates (organic anions) may promote P mobilization and thus act as engineers and/or facilitators in ecosystems by converting poorly available P to more readily available forms and by enhancing P uptake of neighboring plants (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lambers et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Plaxton and Lambers, 2015</xref>). The lack of explicit control of the identity of plant species in our analyses may explain part of the noise in the soil P–climate relationship. The finding that the concentration of soil P was less affected by climate than those of C and N that are strongly controlled by the activity of organisms, and hence by climate, was not surprising, for the reasons presented above.
</p>
