<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The difference between observational and experimental studies may diminish if manipulative experiments are allowed to run for a sufficiently long time, because long-term interactions within communities may likely adjust soil nutrients towards those seen in natural communities. The time, however, should be of a magnitude that allows species substitutions in treatment plots to reach results similar to those along a comparable gradient, which would be impossible on human timescales. For example, if we apply a drought experiment to a beech forest in northern Germany and compare it with a level of drought equivalent to that of a semi-Mediterranean 
 <italic class="italic">Quercus ilex</italic> forest in southern France, we must give sufficient time to the experimental drought plots to reach results similar to those of an observational gradient study to allow a 
 <italic class="italic">Q. ilex</italic> community to replace the beech forest, which would not occur within a reasonable time for experimental studies. Most manipulative experiments are typically short-term, generally no more than a few growing seasons, so we do not know whether experimental studies of much longer duration would lead to response patterns that are more similar to those from observational studies. 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Harte et al. (2015)</xref> found that soil organic C in a 23 year warming experiment in montane grassland of Colorado Rockies declined by 25% during the first six years and increased thereafter until it reached approximately its preheating level in the 23th year of warming. Furthermore, observational studies may often not have been designed as climate change studies, allowing potential confounding effects to influence the results. Perhaps the most striking result would be the change of the vegetation composition along gradients (e.g. colonization by legumes could affect soil N irrespective of precipitation, drought or temperature). The effect on soil nutrients observed in manipulative experiments may thus represent the ‘true’ effect of rapid climate change, so experimental studies clearly produce more consistent results than observational studies. Notably, the responses of soil nutrients in short-term manipulative experiments within a single field may not necessarily apply to long-term manipulative experiments possibly due to an adjustment of the plant species to the altered environmental conditions that decrease the effect size in the long-term. Our findings thus highlight the importance of comparing short- and long-term effects side by side when forecasting the responses of an ecosystem to climate change.
</p>
