<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In summary, our analyses suggest that experimental and observational approaches identify contrasting responses of soil nutrients to climate change. Manipulative experiments, likely indicating short-term responses (months to years) prior to coincidental shifts in plant and microbial compositions that could counteract short-term responses, may be better predictors of the near-term impacts of climate change on soil nutrients. Observations along spatial gradients may thus be more indicative of changes over longer timescales (centuries to millions of years) when multiple aspects of the ecosystem have had a chance to adjust. The responses of soil nutrients found in experimental studies may reflect a ‘true’ short-term and rapid effect of climate change, whereas spatial variation in environmental factors in large-scale gradient observations is likely to heterogeneously influence climate-nutrient relationships, thus supporting the hypothesis of environmental heterogeneity (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dufour et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hector et al., 2007</xref>) in explaining the discrepancy in climate–nutrient patterns between experimental and observational studies. These differences clearly alert us to the risk of misinterpreting short-term experimental results and long-term observations due to the different timescales involved in each of them, especially at broad geographical scales that are structured by multiple internal and external drivers. Manipulative experiments and environmental gradient observations are both valuable, but we still need to recognize the inferential limitations of these two commonly used approaches and interpret their results cautiously. Experimental studies reproduce the conditions expected in the coming decades, thus simulating very fast rates of change that do not permit a shift in the distribution of vegetation, so experimental studies clearly produce more consistent results than observational studies. Experimental studies give us information about the extent to which the vegetation can support a sudden change whereas gradient observational studies give us information about the evolutionary responses of ecosystems to different conditions. Our study fills a critical knowledge gap and further suggests that both experimental and observational data are necessary to properly assess the responses of nutrient cycling to climate change.
</p>
