<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Epigenetic components of evolutionary potential</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmentally induced, transmissible phenotypic variation has been empirically demonstrated to arise from a diversity of non-Mendelian inheritance mechanisms known as ‘nongenetic inheritance’ (reviewed in Bonduriansky et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2012</a>). This phenomenon comprises all parent–offspring inheritance other than DNA sequence variants and can be classed broadly under ‘epigenetics’ to include any nongenetic mechanisms (somatic, behavioural and cultural inheritance), or DNA proximate molecular-level mechanisms 
  <span class="italic">sensu stricto</span> (Bonduriansky et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2012</a>; Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>). Here, we focus on molecular-level epigenetic factors that regulate gene expression via biochemical alterations to chromatin structure (e.g. DNA methylation and post-translational histone modifications), or through the actions of small noncoding RNAs (Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>; Schrey et al. 
  <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once thought to manifest only in transient, exquisite, developmental gene expression programmes that were reset in the germ line, the discovery of transgenerational stability of novel epigenetic states showed that natural variation can exist outside the DNA sequence and cause heritable variation in phenotypes even in the absence of genetic variation (Richards et al. 
  <a rid="b123" ref-type="bibr" href="#b123">2010</a>; Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>). Viewed as an extension of conventional within-generation phenotypic plasticity, nongenetic inheritance may serve to buffer a population against rapid environmental change (Bonduriansky et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2012</a>; Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>). Some types of epigenetic change may also promote the eventual transition of adaptive mechanisms from nongenetic alterations to changes in DNA sequence (Flores et al. 
  <a rid="b43" ref-type="bibr" href="#b43">2013</a>). For example, DNA methylation is known to increase the likelihood of cytosine-to-thymine transitions and thus may increase the likelihood of sequence mutations in regions that are methylated repeatedly across generations (Flores et al. 
  <a rid="b43" ref-type="bibr" href="#b43">2013</a>). Although lack of empirical data fuels debate regarding long-term evolutionary trajectories, transgenerational epigenetic effects have added another layer of complexity to our understanding of at least short-term adaptive responses to environmental change (Bonduriansky et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2012</a>; Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA methylation has been the most commonly studied epigenetic mechanism (Schrey et al. 
  <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>). The technique of methylation-sensitive amplified fragment length polymorphism (MS-AFLP) is currently the most tractable option for identifying and characterizing environmentally dependent epigenetic variation in natural populations (Schrey et al. 
  <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>; Table
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>). Despite some conceptual and technical limitations (reviewed in Schrey et al. 
  <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>), there is potential for MS-AFLP, or alternative methods (e.g. bisulphite sequencing: Cokus et al. 
  <a rid="b27" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27">2008</a>; or array-based methods: Marinković et al. 
  <a rid="b101" ref-type="bibr" href="#b101">2012</a>), to be used to characterize epigenetic variation in natural populations and thus identify populations or individuals that have the greatest capacity to rapidly adjust to environment change, at least in the short-term (Liebl et al. 
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">2013</a>; Schrey et al. 
  <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="tbl1" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Examples and descriptions of genetic and genomic approaches commonly used in population genetics.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Approach</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
      <span class="italic">Mapping genes associated with traits</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quantitative trait nucleotides/loci programs</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use experimental crosses to look for physical location of regions of genome underlying complex phenotypic traits.</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Barton and Keightley 
      <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">2002</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
      <span class="italic">Identifying loci putatively under selection</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genome-wide selection scans (GWSS)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Look for regions of the genome where genetic variation between populations differs relative to the genome-wide average (e.g. 
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>ST</sub>-outliers)
     </td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Oleksyk et al. 
      <a rid="b110" ref-type="bibr" href="#b110">2010</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
      <span class="italic">Associating genetic variation with selective pressures</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genome-wide association studies (GWAS)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Look for associations between genetic variants and particular phenotypic traits</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Stranger et al. 
      <a rid="b142" ref-type="bibr" href="#b142">2011</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic–environment associations (GEA)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Look for associations between candidate loci (e.g. outliers identified using GWSS) and environmental variables</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Bierne et al. 
      <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2011</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental correlation methods</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Look for correlations between allele frequencies and environmental variables. Some methods control for population structure.</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Joost et al. 
      <a rid="b74" ref-type="bibr" href="#b74">2007</a>; Coop et al. 
      <a rid="b29" ref-type="bibr" href="#b29">2010</a>; Eckert et al. 
      <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2010</a>; Hancock et al. 
      <a rid="b57" ref-type="bibr" href="#b57">2010b</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
      <span class="italic">Directly identifying the genes involved in adaptation</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expression profiling</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Looks for differential expression of genes under different conditions</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Harrison et al. 
      <a rid="b60" ref-type="bibr" href="#b60">2012</a>; Smith et al. 
      <a rid="b138" ref-type="bibr" href="#b138">2013</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
      <span class="italic">Estimating additive genetic variance and genetic correlations and predicting phenotypes without knowledge of underlying genotypes</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal model</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed in animal/plant breeding. Uses sparse or dense genome-wide markers to estimate additive genetic variance and genetic correlations and to predict breeding value for phenotypes without knowing particular loci underlying traits.</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Wilson et al. 
      <a rid="b161" ref-type="bibr" href="#b161">2010</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genome-selection</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employed in animal/plant breeding. Uses dense genome-wide markers to estimate additive genetic variance and genetic correlations and to predict breeding value for phenotypes without knowing particular loci underlying traits. Requires a reference population.</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Meuwissen et al. 
      <a rid="b105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b105">2013</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
      <span class="italic">Characterizing genome-wide methylation patterns</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methylation-sensitive amplified fragment length polymorphism (MS-AFLP)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detects variation in methylation at restriction sites (loci) using methylation-sensitive enzymes.</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Schrey et al. 
      <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The burgeoning field of ecological epigenetics aims to characterize evolutionary and ecologically important phenotypic variation from nongenetic sources, particularly under rapid environmental change (Bonduriansky et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2012</a>; Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>; Schrey et al. 
  <a rid="b133" ref-type="bibr" href="#b133">2013</a>). Several studies have examined epigenetic effects in response to environment and as a mechanism for coping with low levels of genetic variation (e.g. Herrera et al. 
  <a rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" href="#b64">2012</a>; Richards et al. 
  <a rid="b124" ref-type="bibr" href="#b124">2012</a>). For example, in a study examining patterns of DNA methylation across an expanding population of the introduced house sparrow 
  <span class="italic">Passer domesticus</span> in Kenya, Liebl et al. (
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">2013</a>) showed that epigenetic mechanisms may increase the flexibility of populations to adapt to changing environmental conditions. Epigenetic diversity was negatively correlated with genetic diversity and positively correlated with inbreeding, suggesting DNA methylation could act as a compensatory mechanism for low standing genetic variation between individuals in recently invaded populations. Limited empirical data concerning the implications of nongenetic inheritance for evolutionary potential currently constrain the general application of epigenetics to conservation. However, there is clearly scope for gathering epigenetic information alongside genetic data to understand better the relative contributions of epigenetic and genetic mechanisms to evolutionary potential in wild populations (Bonduriansky et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2012</a>; Ledón-Rettig 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exploring epigenetic mechanisms can also lead to insights into other important facets of conservation. For example, devil facial tumour disease (DFTD) is a contagious cancer that has devastated Tasmanian devil 
  <span class="italic">Sarcophilus harrisii</span> populations over the last two decades (Lane et al. 
  <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2012</a>). An important part of the vertebrate immune response to infection involves signals from the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) that are expressed on the surface of cells and allow the host to identify ‘nonself’ cells that should be destroyed (Bernatchez and Landry 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2003</a>). DFTD evades the devil's immune system by down-regulating MHC expression on the surface of the tumour cells, a mechanism that appears to be controlled by epigenetic, rather than structural modifications (Siddle et al. 
  <a rid="b135" ref-type="bibr" href="#b135">2013</a>). Understanding the epigenetic mechanism underlying DFTD has promising implications, for example DFTD cells could be epigenetically modified to up-regulate expression of MHC in the tumour cells and subsequently used as a vaccine that would prevent the disease from evading the devil's immune response (Siddle et al. 
  <a rid="b135" ref-type="bibr" href="#b135">2013</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
