<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations of traditional quantitative genetic approaches prompt supplementary and/or alternative methods for characterizing evolutionary potential in wild populations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For single traits, short-term evolutionary potential is contingent on the additive genetic variance associated with a trait in a population. Estimating additive genetic variance requires partitioning observed phenotypic variation into its genetic (additive and nonadditive) and environmental components. To allow comparison across traits and populations, measures of additive genetic variance must be standardized (Houle 
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">1992</a>; Hansen et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">2011</a>). In quantitative genetics, narrow-sense heritability measures the proportion of phenotypic variance that is additive and hence is a variance-standardized measure of additive genetic variation that indicates the extent to which a trait is genetically determined (Houle 
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">1992</a>; Hansen et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">2011</a>). Despite its common use as a trait-based proxy for evolutionary potential (Visscher et al. 
  <a rid="b156" ref-type="bibr" href="#b156">2008</a>), in many situations narrow-sense heritability may have little correlation with either actual capacity for rapid evolution in natural populations or with genetic variability, most likely because of inherent positive correlations between additive genetic variance and other components of phenotypic variance (Houle 
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">1992</a>; Hansen et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">2011</a>). As a consequence, traits with low heritability can still have high evolutionary potential. Houle (
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">1992</a>) proposed ‘evolvability’ (termed the additive genetic coefficient of variation) as a more appropriate measure of evolutionary potential, where additive genetic variance is standardized using the population trait mean and hence made independent of other variance components (i.e. nonadditive and environmental variance components) (Houle 
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">1992</a>; Hansen et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even with recent genomic advances (most notably the ability to estimate relatedness among sampled individuals using dense genetic markers), a quantitative genetics approach to measuring evolutionary potential in natural populations has some limitations (Hansen et al. 
  <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">2011</a>; Hendry et al. 
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2011</a>). By definition, measures based on additive genetic variation ignore the contributions of nonadditive effects, which manifest as dominance effects (interactions between alleles at a locus) and epistatic effects (interactions among loci) and are known to influence evolutionary trajectories (Hendry 
  <a rid="b62" ref-type="bibr" href="#b62">2013</a>). More practically, estimates of additive genetic variance require, in addition to relatedness information, an understanding of the relationship between traits and fitness (Visscher et al. 
  <a rid="b156" ref-type="bibr" href="#b156">2008</a>; Hill 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2012</a>). As genetic correlations between traits can strongly constrain evolution in response to selection, failure to account for genetic correlations will likely overestimate a population's evolutionary potential (Etterson and Shaw 
  <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2001</a>; Hendry 
  <a rid="b62" ref-type="bibr" href="#b62">2013</a>; Munday et al. 
  <a rid="b107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b107">2013</a>). Reliably predicting a population's response to selection will thus require relatedness information for a large number of individuals, corresponding phenotypic data for traits that are correlated with fitness, an understanding of how traits relate to fitness, as well as good estimates of additive genetic variances and genetic correlations (Hill and Kirkpatrick 
  <a rid="b66" ref-type="bibr" href="#b66">2010</a>). Whilst genomic advances have enabled direct estimates of key quantitative genetic parameters (e.g. additive genetic (co)variance, genetic correlations) to be obtained for wild populations using dense genetic markers without the need for laboratory crosses or detailed non-marker-based pedigrees (Gay et al. 
  <a rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" href="#b50">2013</a>; Robinson et al. 
  <a rid="b125" ref-type="bibr" href="#b125">2013</a>), information about how traits link to fitness and ability to obtain sufficient phenotypic data will still be limited in many conservation scenarios. Estimates of evolutionary potential obtained through quantitative genetic studies will also ultimately be trait-, population- and environment-specific, restricting general application (McGuigan and Sgrò 
  <a rid="b104" ref-type="bibr" href="#b104">2009</a>; Hendry et al. 
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2011</a>). Given these limitations, there is value in seeking alternative proxies for evolutionary potential in natural populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to supplementing the application of traditional quantitative genetic approaches in some conservation scenarios (see 
  <span class="italic">Using genomic advances to supplement application of traditional quantitative genetics approaches to conservation</span> below) (Hill 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2012</a>), genomics, in as much as it can link genetic variation to adaptively important trait variation, also provides scope for alternative measures of evolutionary potential to be developed. A robust genomic estimator of evolutionary potential would comprise weighted estimates of all adaptive or potentially adaptive genetic (including coding, regulatory and cryptic, see below), and epigenetic, variation. However, determining the genetic changes and epigenetic mechanisms underlying evolution of novel phenotypes and developmental pathways is by far the biggest challenge facing evolutionary biologists (Mackay et al. 
  <a rid="b98" ref-type="bibr" href="#b98">2009</a>; Radwan and Babik 
  <a rid="b116" ref-type="bibr" href="#b116">2012</a>). There are two major components of evolutionary potential: genetic (DNA-sequence-based) and epigenetic (non-DNA-sequenced-based; Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Schematic of the molecular basis of evolutionary potential. (A) The components of evolutionary potential are divided into its epigenetic (i.e. nongenetic inheritance not attributable to DNA sequence) and genetic (i.e. sequence-based) components. (B) Evolutionary potential is further divided into different types of underlying variation based on function. (C) Examples of the different types of variation are listed. (D) Different types of variation differ in their typical individual effect size on phenotype. (E) The typical ability to detect signals of selection differs between methods, as indicated by the shaded bars. Additional information about the methods in (E) can be found in Table
    <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>. Signatures of selection on epigenetic variants that are in linkage disequilibrium with sequence-based variations can be indirectly captured by all of these methods.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0007-1008-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
