<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Utilizing genome-wide variation to inform estimates of evolutionary potential</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In most conservation situations, genomic knowledge about traits (loci involved, additive genetic (co)variances, genetic correlations and genetic architecture) will be limited, and/or the predictability of environmental change and the required adaptive response(s) will be low. Under this scenario, screening genome-wide variation should be a sensible approach that may provide a generalized measure of evolutionary potential that accounts for the contributions of small-effect loci and cryptic variation and is robust to uncertainty about future change and required adaptive response(s). We use the term ‘genome-wide variation’ in a broad sense to reflect variation sampled representatively across the genome, which could encompass a range of metrics, including allelic diversity, heterozygosity and weighted measures that place greater importance on specific loci of interest within the context of genome-wide variation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A possible drawback of using genome-wide estimates of evolutionary potential is the inclusion of genetic variation that might be currently nonfunctional, and hence not necessarily informative about evolutionary potential. However, two main lines of evidence support genome-wide measures of variation as appropriate proxies for evolutionary potential. First, limited data from simulation (Caballero and García-Dorado 
  <a rid="b22" ref-type="bibr" href="#b22">2013</a>) and empirical (Coop et al. 
  <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">2009</a>) studies suggest that patterns at a large number of random or neutral loci are likely to be correlated with variation at a smaller number of QTL or 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub>-outlier loci. Second, and more significantly, for highly polygenic traits, genome-wide variation currently provides the best predictions of phenotypes (Meuwissen et al. 
  <a rid="b105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b105">2013</a>; Yang et al. 
  <a rid="b164" ref-type="bibr" href="#b164">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Screening genetic variation at a large number of genome-wide markers is a method already extensively used in animal and plant breeding to predict phenotypes without specific knowledge of the contributing loci (Meuwissen et al. 
  <a rid="b105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b105">2013</a>). This method (called genomic selection) uses information from all genotyped loci (typically ≫ 10 000 SNPs) to predict breeding values for desired phenotypic traits that may not be evident before an animal/plant reaches minimum breeding age (Meuwissen et al. 
  <a rid="b105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b105">2013</a>; Table
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>). Trait value predictions are achieved through comparison with a training population that has been measured for the trait of interest and genotyped using the same set of markers. By using all loci to predict phenotypes, genomic selection can also account for the contributions of small-effect alleles (Meuwissen et al. 
  <a rid="b105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b105">2013</a>; Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
