<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing effort</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We estimated and reported vessel activity and fishing effort for 2016 in units of days, hours, kilowatt-days, and kilowatt-hours. Days were calculated by summing the number of days a vessel was actively transmitting AIS or VMS signals. We excluded time at port by filtering out positions where a vessel is closer than 1000 m from shore and traveling at a speed under 0.1 knots. For each vessel, energy in kilowatt-days was estimated by multiplying active days by the vessel’s engine power. We estimated the hours at each AIS/VMS position as half the time elapsed between the previous and next position and calculated energy in kilowatt-hours by multiplying hours by the vessel’s engine power. Each position was classified as fishing or not fishing using GFW’s neural net model, and we used this classification to distinguish active fishing effort from transiting and other activities. We removed noise in AIS/VMS data by filtering out positions that had invalid coordinates (for example, &gt;90°N) and kept only track segments that had over five positions.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fraction of vessels detected by GFW relative to the total number of vessels varied by country and gear type (see the Supplementary Materials). For example, for China, we likely saw 100% of purse seiners and 95% of longliners in the Western and Central Pacific in 2016, but only 70% of all squid jiggers. We report scaled estimates of high-seas fishing costs and profits for the entire high-seas fishing fleet plus reefers and bunkers (tables S5 and S6).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate fishing costs in 2014, we adjusted total fishing effort using a published estimate of the short-run price elasticity of fuel demand of the global large-scale industrial fleet (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>). This resulted in an estimated 5.8% reduction of the total high-seas effort in 2016.
 </p>
</sec>
