<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing in the marine waters beyond national jurisdiction (the “high seas” covering 64% of the ocean’s surface) is dominated by a small number of fishing countries, which reap most of the benefits of fishing this internationally shared area (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). The rationality of widespread high-seas fishing has been questioned because of its environmental impacts and uncertain economic profitability (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Deep-sea bottom trawling can damage fragile habitats containing unique biodiversity including millenary deep-sea corals (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>). Highly migratory species such as tuna and sharks that move between the high seas and countries’ jurisdictional waters [exclusive economic zones (EEZs)] tend to be intensely fished and overexploited (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). Although the International Seafood Sustainability Foundation indicates that 57% of managed tuna stocks are considered to be at a healthy level of abundance, 13% are overfished (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>), and even those that are not overfished show slight declines in biomass over time (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>) and may benefit from increases in biomass. Oceanic sharks, of which 44% are threatened (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>), spend a great deal of time in the high seas, where shark fishing is largely unregulated and unmonitored (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the environmental impacts of fishing on the high seas are well studied, the lack of transparency and data has precluded reliable estimates of the economic costs and benefits of high-seas fishing. Fisheries data suggest that fish catch in this vast area amounted to around 6% of global catch and 8% of the global fishing revenue in 2014 (see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.seaaroundus.org/data/#/global" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.seaaroundus.org/data/#/global</span>). However, the high level of secrecy around distant-water fishing has impeded the calculation of fishing effort and associated costs. Nevertheless, recent technological developments in machine learning and satellite data now allow us to obtain a far more accurate picture of fishing effort across the globe at the level of individual vessels (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>). This capability provides a more transparent and novel method to examine high-seas fisheries and answer key questions such as whether fishing in the high seas is profitable and whether government subsidies enable current levels of fishing.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we characterize the global high-seas fleet in detail and estimate the net economic benefit of high-seas fishing using (i) reconstructed estimates of the global fishing catch and its landed value, (ii) the costs of fishing based on satellite-inferred fishing effort and vessel characteristics, and (iii) estimates of government subsidies per country. We report high-seas fishing profits by fishing gear type, flag state, and Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) region, with the goal of understanding whether fishing the high seas is economically rational.</p>
</sec>
