<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reefers and bunkers</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the same methodology as above, with slight modifications, to estimate the costs of the reefers (transshipment vessels and fish carriers) and bunkers (fuel replenishment vessels) that support the high-seas fishing fleet. To estimate fuel costs, we used the same formula as for fishing vessels, excluding the rules that increase engine LFs during fishing behavior (that is, 0.75 LF for trawlers, 9% increase in LF during fishing behavior for other gears, and 0.5 LF for auxiliary engines). This approach likely results in an underestimate of the fuel costs of these vessels because it does not account for the potential increase in power needed during rendezvous events. For labor costs, we used the same average upper and lower bounds of labor costs per day by vessel size class used to fill in gaps as described in the Labor costs section above (see also the Supplementary Materials). Similarly, we used the same fractions of total cost by vessel size class to estimate total costs. The main difference in methodology is apportioning high-seas costs from total cost. To do this, we calculated the fraction of total encounters that involved vessels from the high-seas fleet and used this estimate as the fraction of total costs associated with the high seas (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m10" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">C</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mtext">hs</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>)
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div id="m11" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">C</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mtext">hs</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mtext">TC</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">×</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">R</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <span class="mtext">hs</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mtext">TR</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>where TC
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> is the total costs of vessel 
  <span class="italic">i</span>, TR
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> is the total number of rendezvous of vessel 
  <span class="italic">i</span>, and 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m12" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">R</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mtext">hs</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> is the number of rendevouz of vessel 
  <span class="italic">i</span> with fishing vessels of the high-seas fleet.
 </p>
</sec>
