<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">First, the temporal window for spawning in the North is limited to late winter-spring due to the extreme seasonality of light and associated primary production (food for planktonic larvae) at high latitudes (&gt;60°N) (
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>). Significant changes in spawning phenology are therefore unlikely to occur in this region. Instead, northward expansions of spawning during historic and ongoing warming periods are well documented, especially for Atlantic cod, which extended its spawning activity to West Svalbard in the 1930s (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>). However, core spawning areas (e.g., the Lofoten archipelago for the Barents Sea population) have always been occupied during past centuries, possibly due to favorable combinations of biotic and abiotic factors that maximize recruitment success (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>). After spawning, dispersal of eggs and larvae toward suitable nursery areas—sometimes over hundreds of kilometers—plays an important role in terms of life-cycle connectivity and population replenishment (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>). Spawning at alternative locales (as required under RCP8.5 for both species and under RCP4.5 for Polar cod) could disturb connectivity and therefore increase the risk of advective losses and recruitment failure (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>). Accordingly, successful establishment of new spawning habitats will largely depend on a number of factors in addition to egg survival (i.e., prey availability, predation pressure, and connectivity), all of which are currently difficult to predict (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
