<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social awareness of abnormal weather is growing, particularly regarding the adverse effects of heat waves and droughts. Despite substantial efforts intended to mitigate climate change, the potential for the occurrence of extreme hot events is projected to increase in the future
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Over northern Eurasia, the difference in summer surface air temperature (SAT) between the 2000s and the 1980s shows a distinct spatial contrast, forming a continental-wide tripole pattern (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). Two regions with prominent SAT increases are around the Eastern European Plain and Central Siberia–Mongolia, in contrast to weak SAT changes around the West Siberian Plain. This tripole pattern has been recognised in many studies both in terms of summer mean SAT
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> and hot extremes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> such as the Russian heat wave in 2010
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> and multi-year heat waves in the 2000s around Mongolia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. In western Russia and Central Siberia–Mongolia, extreme hot events occurred with higher frequency than in the surrounding areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. However, questions remain regarding the drivers of both the recent change in summer SAT and the occurrence of extreme hot events on a regional scale. Here, we examine the leading factors that alter summer SAT over northern Eurasia. We analyse a dataset derived from a 100-member ensemble experiment called the “database for Policy Decision making for Future climate change”
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> (d4PDF, Methods), which comprises a 60-year integration (1951–2011) using MRI-AGCM3.2 (Meteorological Research Institute Atmospheric General Circulation Model version 3.2) driven by observed sea surface temperature (SST), sea ice, and natural and anthropogenic forcing.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summer SAT changes between the 2000s and the 1980s. JJA-averaged SAT change in the (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) JRA-55 and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) d4PDF datasets (100 member average). (
     <span class="bold">b</span>,
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Reconstructed SAT differences between the 2000s and the 1980s by a linear combination of the first through third PCs derived from (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) JRA-55 and (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) d4PDF (see Methods). The 1980s and 2000s refer to 1981–1990 and 2001–2010, respectively.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47291_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e274" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
