<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The soil physical and chemical properties parameters at soil depths of 0 to 30-cm input for the simulation were derived from the HWSD (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/land-water/databases-and-software/hwsd/en/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.fao.org/land-water/databases-and-software/hwsd/en/</uri>), including: soil type, bulk density, clay content, organic matter content, porosity, and pH value. Paddy cultivation in different regions of the study area were derived from the “
 <italic class="italic">Compilation of Paddy Field Irrigation Experiment Data in Heilongjiang Province</italic>”, which included the date of paddy field preparation and paddy puddling, transplanting, mid-season drainage, fertilization regime, and harvest date of 30 experiment stations in 542 experimental years from 1952 to 2002. In order to reduce the uncertainty of the simulation results, the following assumptions were made in this study. (1) Transplanting was used for rice planting. The cultivation techniques of rice seedlings nurseries in upland bed in Heilongjiang Province began in the 1950s, and were well promoted with the development of plastic film technology in the 1960s and 1970s. This technology is in line with the cold rice cultivation environment and rice growth physiology. (2) There was no change in rice transplanting and harvesting time. Due to seedlings nursery and upland bed cultivation technology, the rice transplanting date was more flexible and less affected by temperature. Farmers in different regions depended on experience to determine fixed transplanting and harvesting dates. (3) The stubble remained 10% after harvest. In the historical period, the straw harvested in the study area was used for living fuel and animal feed. Currently, crop straw burning is prohibited in Heilongjiang Province. In the future, straw will be developed into new energy, decorative materials and other uses. (4) Setting up mid-season drainage. This technology has been widely used by farmers in the study area because it reduces the ineffective tillering of rice, improves the fertilizer utilization rate, improves soil aeration, and effectively reduces CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. (5) There was no change in rice varieties during the study period.
</p>
