<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Whilst modelling the species habitat distribution in response to climate change is an active field of research, SDMs are subject to uncertainties and limitations. For instance, accuracy of the species location data is known to influence model projection outcomes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" class="xref">43</xref>. In this study, the species location data precision level was high. However, obtaining additional presence locations from the full extent of each population area could have improved the model validity, although using natural occurrence data in SDMs might under-predict potential distribution range, as plant species do not necessarily fully encompass their fundamental niche
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref>. Variable selection and accuracy of datasets are also a potential source of uncertainty in SDMs
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref>. In this study, only climatic variables were explored in SDM1 and SDM2 to model the broad climatic domain. However, exclusion of other environmental variables may have resulted in models predicted to increase the likelihood of climate impacts. In SDM3, geological and geomorphological variables were coupled with climatic variables, and the model predicted much slower climate impacts. This demonstrates that local conditions could potentially buffer (decouple) regional climate
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" class="xref">46</xref>, although coupling fine-resolution substrates (25 × 25 m grid) and low-resolution climate (1 × 1 km grid) might result in models weighted toward substrate variables. Moreover, soil and vegetation dataset in future years that are consistent with IPCC scenarios were not available at the time of the study. The predictive power of the models could be further improved by inclusion of better representations of substrates in future studies. The climate projections are subject to uncertainty as different combinations of downscaling methods, GCMs and emission scenarios may yield different outcomes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" class="xref">47</xref>. In this study, an ensemble of five GCMs was used, and therefore these uncertainties were averaged at the time of the climate projection modelling. It has been highlighted that the majority of SDM studies seldom take into account species demographic factors
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" class="xref">48</xref>. The SDMs developed in this study did not take into account adaptive potential of 
 <italic class="italic">T. robusta</italic>, as given the study time frame (1990–2070) and the species generation time (44 years)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>, there would not be sufficient time for genetic adaptation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" class="xref">49</xref>. Despite these limitations, the results of this study demonstrated that SDMs were useful to evaluate general trends in the mainly climatic habitat distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">T. robusta</italic> at both continental and regional scales under climate change.
</p>
