<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For assisted colonization to be a feasible conservation option for a species, we need an understanding of the fundamental niche (where species can occur) and realized niche (where species do occur), and the likely location of those niches in the future. Bioclimatic envelope, or niche-based, models are static models that correlate current species distributions with climate variables and project future distributions according to each species’ “climatic envelope”
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">35</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">37</sup>
 </xref>. Some models were developed sufficiently long ago for their predictions to be tested against actual observations, and they have proved their value. For example, in a meta-analysis of range shifts, latitudinal shifts matched the expected range shifts if a species were to track its bioclimatic envelope.
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">27</sup>
 </xref> While of proven utility, the assumptions on which these models are based can be questioned regarding their ability to predict the potential impact of climate change.
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">38</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">41</sup>
 </xref> Bioclimatic envelope models typically do not address stochastic events like local droughts and heat waves, which may impose the dominant climate stress on species in the future.
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">42</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">43</sup>
 </xref> They also do not address spatial variability. It is the microclimate experienced by an animal that has direct influence on an animal’s thermal status.
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">44</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">47</sup>
 </xref> All thermal aspects of those microclimates need to be quantified before they can be incorporated into climate change models.
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">7</sup>
 </xref> Although they do not incorporate measures of evaporation, miniature black globe thermometers can be attached to large mammals to provide a quantitative measurement of heat loads of their microclimates.
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">48</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
