<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numerous recent scientific assessments—including the IPCC 1.5°C report [
  <a rid="pmed.1002804.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pmed.1002804.ref001">1</a>] and the 
  <span class="italic">Lancet</span> Countdown [
  <a rid="pmed.1002804.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pmed.1002804.ref003">3</a>]—have made clear that health harms of climate change are no longer just a future threat: they are our current reality. These harms include illness, injuries, and deaths from increasingly dangerous weather (including extreme heat, precipitation, and flooding), worsening air pollution, the spread of infectious diseases, increases in food- and water-borne illnesses, reduced nutrition, and profound mental health harms caused or made worse by traumatic climate events.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Emissions of heat-trapping carbon pollution reached an all-time high in 2018 [
  <a rid="pmed.1002804.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pmed.1002804.ref004">4</a>]. Global warming and related climate changes are occurring at an accelerating pace [
  <a rid="pmed.1002804.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pmed.1002804.ref005">5</a>], as are the health harms they cause [
  <a rid="pmed.1002804.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pmed.1002804.ref003">3</a>]. Of greatest concern—if one or more possible tipping points in the world’s climate systems are triggered—these accelerating harms may occur in a nonlinear manner, with high potential for catastrophic consequences to health and prosperity [
  <a rid="pmed.1002804.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pmed.1002804.ref006">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This prospect should be of grave concern to—and should serve as a clarion call for—all health professionals. As health professionals, we pledge to do no harm. We often aspire further, to serve humanity by preventing needless harm and suffering and to foster conditions that give every person a fair chance at the blessings of good health—especially those who are most vulnerable. Climate change directly imperils these aims.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our collective contributions to human health and well-being over the past century have been remarkable. We have ushered in major improvements in health and longevity. Now, an entirely new challenge demands our full attention—the challenge of stopping and protecting people against the harms of climate change. Over the next decade, the nations of the world must embrace and accomplish three difficult but achievable objectives so that human civilization and the ecosystems on which we depend can continue to flourish: creating a clean energy economy, drawing down excess atmospheric carbon, and preparing for and adapting to health impacts.</p>
</sec>
