<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2dot1-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. Integrate Climate Change into Current Public Health Practice</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both public health participant groups expressed doubt that there would be significant new funding for public health agencies to work on climate change, suggesting a strategy to integrate climate change into existing programs where feasible. To promote greater engagement respondents advised: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“…first help people see that they already are influencing issues around climate change with what they do every day. Just tweaking and finessing it rather than completely changing their workload.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examples provided included integration of climate projections into accreditation-required community health assessments and public health emergency preparedness, home visitation program referrals for energy efficiency improvements, articulation of climate co-benefits in chronic disease prevention programs (e.g., active transportation), and inclusion of climate-related health outcomes in existing disease surveillance programs. Respondents cited the need for greater funding flexibility and workforce capacity building to implement these suggestions.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“PH non-engaged” and “Non-PH” respondents asked for more information on the range of health and equity impacts of climate change and climate solutions—including downscaled local health impacts—and how these connect to current work. A “PH non-engaged” respondent observed: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“We are involved with work on air quality, safe neighborhoods, reduction of traffic, water quality, biking paths, walkable communities, and obesity prevention (through community gardens, famers markets, and city planning). I do not make the links explicit currently, but would be interesting in doing so with guidance on ‘how to’”.</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some “PH engaged” respondents noted that adequate evidence for action already exists, and that the real need is for greater dissemination of existing knowledge: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“The public health sector needs to get their research out there. Good work has been done, but it has not effectively been shared with the public…both at community and institution level. This would provide opportunities for advocacy and help put pressure on legislators to introduce stronger legislation with more information on public health.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
