<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot5-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5. Coordinate and Shift Funding</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resource limitations have forced public health agencies into a reactive mode, responsive to one immediate health crisis after the next. Disinvestment in the public health infrastructure has thus weakened the ability of public health agencies to respond proactively to a slow-moving public health emergency such as climate change or address the determinants of climate change and health. Significant reinvestments in the public health infrastructure will be necessary in order to absorb the increasing impacts on health of climate change, and to enable conceptualization, organization, and practice that proactively optimize health and equity benefits from climate change work.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As mentioned in the results, respondents identified a number of strategic and creative ways to use existing funding. The fact that interviewees working on climate change outside of public health saw important and immediate roles for the public health sector supports the idea that inter-sectoral collaborations—for example the Health in All Policies approach—might incorporate more explicit linkages with climate change mitigation and resilience. Health and equity considerations could be integrated more explicitly into climate change program planning and policy development. Governmental and private funders could more explicitly permit or encourage integration of climate change, wherever relevant, in currently funded programs. Finally, foundations are setting the agenda for powerful movements around health, and these respondents are hungry for such a movement in public health for climate change.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the challenges, our respondents identified an array of promising initiatives that provide hope that, as the magnitude of the climate change threat to health becomes ever more apparent, the public health sector will find ways to engage on the issue.</p>
</sec>
