<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B3. Current Work Related to Climate Change and Health</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have you read or heard anything about climate change and health that you think may be related to the work you do every day and/or the mission of your program or organization?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have you heard of the concept of co-benefits? Co-benefits are strategies to prevent further climatic changes that also have a beneficial effect on health and quality of life.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you say you are you currently involved in work related to climate change, health, or co-benefits, even in a very broad sense? 
  <span class="italic">(Now follow one of two arrows below:)</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">If yes:</span> Please describe them. Do you make those connections explicit? If not, can you imagine making those connections more explicit? Would you be interested in further exploring some of these potential links between the work you are already doing and climate change? 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>If not, why not?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>If yes, what links are you thinking about exploring more in your work?</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">If no, prompt with:</span> Some of the ways we think climate change could be related to the work of your program include xxxxx… Is that something you would be interested in learning more about and exploring more in your work? 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>If not, why not?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>If yes, explore how the connections could be made in their work.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>If no, explore why not.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
