<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C4. Partnering with Public Health</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you currently work with PH organizations – either government agencies like a local health department, or other organizations that work on issues like asthma or obesity? 
  <span class="italic">(Now follow one of two arrows below.)</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">If yes:</span> Who have you worked with? 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Has that work with PH helped forward your agenda?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>What was successful about that partnership and what was challenging?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>How did working with that agency get started?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Has that partnership changed anything in your or their work?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>What do you think you and others got out of having public health at the table?</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">If no:</span> Would you like to be working with local public health groups more? 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>What could support building that relationship?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>What are some of the barriers to you creating those partnerships?</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there other (additional) things you’d like to see people in the PH community do that would help you in your work on climate change? 
  <span class="italic">Probe</span>: 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>What would you like to see your local PH groups or departments do?</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any thoughts about what might help or support greater partnerships or collaboration on climate change between you and public health organizations?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there things that would make it challenging for you to bring health into your work more? Or that would be helpful for you in making the connections between the climate change work you do and health more explicit?</p>
</sec>
