<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="app-group" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Appendix</div>
 <div class="app">
  <div class="title">A. “Public Health Engaged” Interview Tool</div>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A1. Introduction</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thank you for agreeing to meet with me/us. We are working with the Public Health Institute Center for Public Health and Climate Change on a project funded by the Kresge Foundation. We see climate change as one of the greatest health and equity challenges of the 21st century, and we also see that many climate action strategies could have very positive impacts on health. The goal of this project is to find out how to make it easier for the public health community to work on climate change and strengthen partnerships between public health workers and others who are working on climate change. We also want to know how public health could help others working on climate change to bring a stronger health frame to their work. We are starting by speaking to people in public health, climate change, equity, planning, environmental justice, and other fields, to learn more about their work and get their ideas on what would be helpful.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Everything you tell me will be kept strictly confidential, unless we specifically ask for your permission to quote you. I‘ll be taking notes, but only my co-investigator and I will have access to them. You should feel free at any time to ask me questions concerning the interview or the project, or to decline to answer a question. Do you have any questions? OK, let’s get started.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It will help to define what we mean by public health and climate change up front.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’re defining “public health” broadly to include the “upstream” or social, environmental and physical determinants of health, such as asthma from air pollution, housing conditions, education, income, access to healthy foods and transportation, 
    <span class="italic">etc</span>. When we talk about “public health workers” or “public health organizations”, we are talking about people both inside and outside of government that are working on any aspect of trying to improve population and community health.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When we talk about the impacts of climate change on health, we’re talking about both direct impacts like extreme heat, indirect impacts like rising food prices from drought, and the health effects of various strategies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions such as decreased air pollution from higher fuel efficiency. Also, this project is focused more on the US than on international issues, even though we understand that the global impacts are very significant.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(Note: * indicates questions you can skip if pressed for time.)</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A2. Public Health Involvement and Role</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, can you tell me a little about the work you do, especially work which you think relates directly or indirectly to climate change or co-benefits?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* You’ve talked about climate change and its links to (public health topic areas they mentioned). Are there other areas where you see key connections between climate change and public health, for example like emergency preparedness, vector-borne diseases, chronic diseases, and how do you see those links? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What about areas like maternal and child health, infectious diseases, or reproductive health?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What are your thoughts about the role of public health and public health workers in climate change—what should the public health community—inside and outside of government public health agencies—be doing about climate change? If you had lots of resources, in an ideal world, what would public health be doing around climate change?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you think that we should be striving to get everyone in public health engaged in climate change, or do you think we should focus on building expertise in a smaller more focused group of public health workers, or both? Do you have any thoughts about reaching out to workers engaged in direct service – like public health nurses, or restaurant inspectors or WIC workers about climate change, and whether they could or should have a role in climate change work?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A3. Framing</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you think there is a way we could use a health frame or health focus to help the public become more aware of and engaged with climate change?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Probes</span>: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What about areas like maternal and child health, infectious diseases, or reproductive health?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Are there any health messages frames that been particularly effective in your experience, or ideas you have as to what you think could be most compelling for your co-workers?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What about for the clients and population that you work with?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some people—with some support from polling data—think that it’s important to talk about the health co-benefits of climate action—for example, the air pollution benefits of (AB32), but to refrain from saying the words “climate change” or “global warming”; others think it’s very important to actually say the words “climate change”. What are your thoughts about that?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A4. Barriers</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* What are the barriers to public health participation and input into work that’s happening locally and regionally around climate change? I’d like you to think about both “upstream” or structural barriers, and more immediate barriers. Probe: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Are there specific issues, organizational, time, resources, leadership, 
       <span class="italic">etc.</span>, that make it hard for you to engage in climate-related work?
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have thoughts about why public health workers overall are not more engaged in climate change? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Are there specific issues, organizational, time, resources, leadership, 
       <span class="italic">etc.</span>, that make it hard for you to engage in climate-related work?
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What do you think it would take to get public health workers more engaged?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What would be effective ways to motivate and activate public health workers on the issue of climate change?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A5. Opportunities</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* What are some of the things that might help and support others in the public health sector become more interested or engaged with work related to climate change and health? Prompts: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>More information and understanding,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>time,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>resources,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>funding,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>leadership,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>peer support</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* Who should we be targeting with that support?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you see any key opportunities for public health in terms of local, state, or national climate or health policy engagement?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What about key opportunities for community education and engagement?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What about opportunities for partnerships with other sectors, other organizations, or other initiatives related to climate change that public health hasn’t yet been involved in?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A6. Multi-Sector Planning and Decision-Making for Climate Change and Health</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have you been involved in any climate change mitigation or adaptation planning, or other climate action work locally, regionally, or at the state or national level? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What do you see as any unique contribution or possible contribution of public health in that work?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Did others see PH as having a unique contribution, and what was that?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Who are the other stakeholders or organizations that you think public health should be working with on climate-related issues?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A7. Narratives about Public Health and Climate Change</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What made you first get engaged in climate change work? Can you tell me what, when, or who made you start caring about it or thinking it was an important public health issue?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What do you find most rewarding about it?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Can you tell me a story about an accomplishment or something you feel really good about in the work you are doing? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Did others see PH as having a unique contribution, and what was that?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Why does that story stick in your mind?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>How does that story make you feel?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What is the most disheartening aspect of your work on climate change and public health? How do you deal with that?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there other areas where you would like to expand your work related to climate change, climate-related impacts, or co-benefits?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec8-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A8. Networking</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you mind sharing the names of others who you think would be useful to interview on this subject? We are looking for other public health workers with some awareness or interest, and who may be able to increase their agency’s engagement. 
    <span class="italic">(Get contact information)</span>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you be interested in receiving information from the PHI Center for Climate Change and Health by email?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any questions for me/us? Is there anything else you’d like to share?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">You’ve been so helpful; I really appreciate the time you’ve taken to talk with me today. I just want to confirm that we can list you in the acknowledgements section of our final whitepaper. Do you mind if we contact you in the future with any follow-up questions that may emerge? Thank you very much.</p>
  </sec>
 </div>
 <div class="app">
  <div class="title">B. “Public Health Non-Engaged” Interview Tool</div>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B1. Introduction</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thank you for agreeing to meet with me/us. We are working with the Public Health Institute Center for Public Health and Climate Change on a project funded by the Kresge Foundation. We believe that climate change will pose a challenge to health and equity in the 21st century, and we also see that many climate action strategies could have very positive impacts on health. The goal of this project is to find out how to make it easier for the public health community to work on climate change, and strengthen partnerships between public health workers and others who are working on climate change. We also want to know how public health could help others working on climate change to bring a stronger health frame to their work. We are starting by speaking to people in public health, climate change, equity, planning, environmental justice, and other fields, to learn more about their work and get their ideas on what would be helpful.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We are going to ask you questions about climate change, but we know that it is not an issue that many people in public health know all that much about. So please don’t worry about whether or not your answers are “right”—for many of the questions there are no “right” answers. We are asking them so that we have a better understanding about where we should start when, later in our project, we develop some materials about climate change specifically for public health workers.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Everything you tell me will be kept confidential, unless we specifically ask for your permission to quote you. I’ll be taking notes, but only my co-investigator and I will have access to them. We will not quote you without asking specific permission.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">You should feel free at any time to ask me questions concerning the interview or the project or to decline to answer a question. Do you have any questions? OK, let’s get started.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It will help to define what we mean by public health and climate change up front.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’re defining “public health” broadly to include the “upstream” or social, environmental and physical determinants of health, such as asthma from air pollution, housing conditions, education, income, access to healthy foods and transportation, 
    <span class="italic">etc</span>. When we talk about “public health workers” or “public health organizations”, we are talking about people both inside and outside of government that are working on any aspect of trying to improve population and community health.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When we talk about the impacts of climate change on health, we’re talking about both direct impacts like extreme heat, indirect impacts like rising food prices from drought, and the health effects of various strategies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions such as decreased air pollution from higher fuel efficiency. Also, this project is focused more on the U.S. than on international issues, even though we understand that the global impacts are very significant.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(Note: * indicates questions you can skip if pressed for time.)</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B2. General Level of Awareness/Concern about Climate Change and Health</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, can you tell me a little about your organization, and the type of work that you do with your organization.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let’s start talking a bit about climate change. When you hear that term, what comes to mind? Probes: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>How does that story make you feel?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Are there any stories or things you’ve read or heard that particularly resonate for you?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What does this story or information make you feel?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Why do you think it resonates for you? What is important about this?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have your read or heard anything about the relationship between climate change and health or how climate change affects health? What have you heard?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* Are there particular things you’ve heard about climate change and health that are especially important to you? Probe: Are you concerned about a particular health endpoint, or something that impacts people’s health indirectly?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* How big of an issue do you think climate change is 
    <span class="underline">as a public health issue</span>? Do you think it will be a bigger issue for public health in the future? Why/why not?
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you ever talk about climate change with your co-workers, your staff, or your managers? Do you think they are aware of or concerned about climate change as a public health issue? Can you share any stories or examples that show their level of awareness or concern?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* We’re wondering what your clients or external stakeholders might think about the impacts of climate change on health. Can you give me some examples or stories that show their level of awareness or concern?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B3. Current Work Related to Climate Change and Health</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have you read or heard anything about climate change and health that you think may be related to the work you do every day and/or the mission of your program or organization?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have you heard of the concept of co-benefits? Co-benefits are strategies to prevent further climatic changes that also have a beneficial effect on health and quality of life.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you say you are you currently involved in work related to climate change, health, or co-benefits, even in a very broad sense? 
    <span class="italic">(Now follow one of two arrows below:)</span>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">If yes:</span> Please describe them. Do you make those connections explicit? If not, can you imagine making those connections more explicit? Would you be interested in further exploring some of these potential links between the work you are already doing and climate change? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If not, why not?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If yes, what links are you thinking about exploring more in your work?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">If no, prompt with:</span> Some of the ways we think climate change could be related to the work of your program include xxxxx… Is that something you would be interested in learning more about and exploring more in your work? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If not, why not?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If yes, explore how the connections could be made in their work.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If no, explore why not.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B4. Opportunities and Barriers</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* How comfortable would you be making the link to climate change when talking to your co-workers, community, or clients, and what would you need to support that? Explore comfort level and reasons.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What are some of the things that might help and support you and/or your organization become more interested or engaged with work related to climate change and health? Prompts: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If no, explore why not.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>more information and understanding,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>time,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>resources,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>funding,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>leadership,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>peer support</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>other supports?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you see other public health workers and public health organizations as having a role or responsibility in addressing climate change? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>funding,</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If so, what is that role?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What are some of the things you think public health workers might do to address climate change?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there things that would make it challenging for you to become more involved in work related to climate change and health? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Are there any larger “upstream” barriers that would prevent your organization or agency from becoming more involved in work related to climate change and health?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B5. Narratives about Public Health and Climate Change</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How did you first get interested in public health? Probes: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What do you find most rewarding about it?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Can you tell me a story about an accomplishment or something you feel really good about in the work you are doing?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Why does that story stick in your mind?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>How does that story make you feel?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What is the most disheartening aspect of your work? How do you deal with that?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let’s start talking a bit about climate change. When you hear that term, what comes to mind? Probes: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>How does that story make you feel?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Are there any stories or things you’ve read or heard that particularly resonate for you?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What does this story or information make you feel?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Why do you think it resonates for you? What is important about this?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B6. Networking and Closing</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there people, publications, or organizations that you especially trust to give you good information that is relevant to your work?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you think you or your colleagues might be interested in attending trainings or discussions about climate change and health? If yes—webinar? Teleconference? In-person?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you be interested in receiving information from the PHI Center for Climate Change and Health by email?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you mind sharing the names of others who you think would be useful to interview on this subject? We are especially looking for other public health workers with some awareness or interest, and who may be able to increase their agency’s engagement. 
    <span class="italic">(Get contact information)</span>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any questions for me/us? Is there anything else you’d like to share?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">You’ve been so helpful; I really appreciate the time you’ve taken to talk with me today. I just want to confirm that we can list you in the acknowledgements section of our final whitepaper. Do you mind if we contact you in the future with any follow-up questions that may emerge? Thank you very much.</p>
  </sec>
 </div>
 <div class="app">
  <div class="title">C. “Non-Public Health” Interview Tool</div>
  <p>Audience: Those who are not PH-identified, but who are doing climate change work (as self-defined), and who can facilitate bridging public health involvement.</p>
  <p>Goals: 
   <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>To discover how PH can more successfully engage with the non-PH sector working on CC to increase effectiveness of action.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>To explore the extent to which people working on CC already see the health connections.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C1. Introduction</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thank you for agreeing to meet with me/us. We are working with the Public Health Institute Center for Public Health and Climate Change on a project funded by the Kresge Foundation. We see climate change as one of the greatest health and equity challenges of the 21st century, and we also see that many climate action strategies could have very positive impacts on health. The goal of this project is to find out how to make it easier for the public health community to work on climate change and strengthen partnerships between public health workers and others who are working on climate change. We also want to know how public health could help others working on climate change to bring a stronger health frame to their work. We are starting by speaking to people in public health, climate change, equity, planning, environmental justice, and other fields, to learn more about their work and get their ideas on what would be helpful.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Everything you tell me will be kept confidential, unless we specifically ask for your permission to quote you. I‘ll be taking notes, but only my co-investigator and I will have access to them. You should feel free at any time to ask me questions concerning the interview or the project, or to decline to answer a question. Do you have any questions? OK, let’s get started.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It will help to define what we mean by public health and climate change up front.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’re defining “public health” broadly to include the “upstream” or social, environmental and physical determinants of health, such as asthma from air pollution, housing conditions, education, income, access to healthy foods and transportation, 
    <span class="italic">etc</span>. When we talk about “public health workers” or “public health organizations”, we are talking about people both inside and outside of government that are working on any aspect of trying to improve population and community health.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When we talk about the impacts of climate change on health, we’re talking about both direct impacts like extreme heat, indirect impacts like rising food prices from drought, and the health effects of various strategies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions such as decreased air pollution from higher fuel efficiency. Also, this project is focused more on the US than on international issues, even though we understand that the global impacts are very significant.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C2. Relationship between Their Work and Public Health</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, can you tell me a little about the work you do and your organization does, especially that relates to climate change? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What issues does your organization work on?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Where does climate change fit in terms of your organization’s priorities?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Can you talk about how you see the links between climate and health and equity, either in terms of the impacts of climate change itself, or how climate mitigation and adaptation strategies might affect health or equity? Are you familiar with the concept of co-benefits? Co-benefits are strategies to prevent further climatic changes that also have a beneficial effect on health and quality of life.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">If necessary, prompt with:</span> Some of the ways we think health could be related to the work of your program include xxxxx… Is that something you would be interested in learning more about and exploring more in your work? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What issues does your organization work on?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If yes, explore how the connections could be made in their work.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>If no, explore why not.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C3. Framing</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any thoughts about how the community or other stakeholders that you work with think about climate change? Do you have any stories or examples that show their awareness or concern?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How about how they view health? Do you have any stories or examples that show their awareness or concern?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any stories or examples of whether they are aware or concerned about the impacts of climate change on health?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In your experience, what are some of the challenges in talking to people in your community about climate change? Do you talk explicitly about climate change, or do you start from some different framing? If so, what/how? Do you ever/often talk about the links between climate change and health? Explore.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why do you think the general public is not more concerned about climate change?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you see opportunities for getting people more engaged in climate change action and strategies through the use of a health frame? Are there any ways that using a health frame might either help or hinder your own efforts around climate change, or things we should be careful about as we try to engage more people in climate change using a health frame?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C4. Partnering with Public Health</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you currently work with PH organizations – either government agencies like a local health department, or other organizations that work on issues like asthma or obesity? 
    <span class="italic">(Now follow one of two arrows below.)</span>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">If yes:</span> Who have you worked with? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Has that work with PH helped forward your agenda?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What was successful about that partnership and what was challenging?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>How did working with that agency get started?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Has that partnership changed anything in your or their work?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What do you think you and others got out of having public health at the table?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">If no:</span> Would you like to be working with local public health groups more? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What could support building that relationship?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What are some of the barriers to you creating those partnerships?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there other (additional) things you’d like to see people in the PH community do that would help you in your work on climate change? 
    <span class="italic">Probe</span>: 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>What would you like to see your local PH groups or departments do?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any thoughts about what might help or support greater partnerships or collaboration on climate change between you and public health organizations?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there things that would make it challenging for you to bring health into your work more? Or that would be helpful for you in making the connections between the climate change work you do and health more explicit?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C5. Narratives about Public Health and Climate Change</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What made you first get engaged in climate change work? Can you tell me what, when, or who made you start caring about it or thinking it was an important issue?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What do you find most rewarding about it?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Can you tell me a story about an accomplishment or something you feel really good about in the work you are doing? 
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Why does that story stick in your mind?</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>How does that story make you feel?</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What is the most disheartening aspect of your work on climate change? How do you deal with that?</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C6. Networking</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you mind sharing the names of others who you think would be useful to interview on this subject? We are looking for people with some awareness or interest, and who may be able to increase the consideration of health in their climate change work. 
    <span class="italic">(Get contact information)</span>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are there people or publications that you especially trust to give you good information that is relevant to your work?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Would you be interested in receiving information from the PHI Center for Climate Change and Health by email?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you have any questions for me/us? Is there anything else you’d like to share?</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">You’ve been so helpful; I really appreciate the time you’ve taken to talk with me today. Do you mind if we contact you in the future with any follow-up questions that may emerge? I just want to confirm that we can list you in the acknowledgements section of our final whitepaper. Thank you very much.</p>
  </sec>
 </div>
</div>
