<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Barriers to Engagement</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1dot1-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1. Public Health Perspectives on Individual-Level Constraints</div>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Belief that Climate Change is not Urgent, Immediate, or a Priority</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “PH engaged” respondents were, not surprisingly, highly aware of the health risks of climate change and the urgency of response. A number of these respondents from public health organizations recognized as leaders in climate change work did not feel it was a priority of their organization. The primary motivation for many “PH engaged” respondents’ engagement in climate change work is that those activities serve as a platform to address larger community health needs.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While there was interest and concern about climate change among “PH non-engaged” professionals, this group expressed less interest, urgency, or recognition of the breadth and currency of climate impacts on health, or that interventions are required now to prevent more severe future impacts. One respondent noted that the health impacts of climate change “
    <span class="italic">seem like a reach.”</span> Many of these respondents see the impacts as too distant in time and place to be of concern, “
    <span class="italic">a pervasive perception that climate change will happen in the future”,</span> although several acknowledged the need for public health response to extreme weather events. Almost all respondents—including those engaged with climate change—believe there is a lack of tangibility or immediacy to the issue; that makes it too abstract for people to engage with. For those “PH non-engaged” respondents that did perceive climate change as an immediate and urgent threat, it was not a priority for their organization or agency.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“PH non-engaged” interviewees expressed skepticism that climate change was a pressing issue for the communities they serve, relative to gun violence, unemployment, or housing issues. One respondent pointed out: 
    <span class="italic">“We can’t expect people to think about the future if they don’t have their immediate needs met.”</span> The exception to this was “PH non-engaged” respondents working in environmental justice organizations, who highlighted the importance of environmental protection—including climate change—for the communities they represent: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“In our community, there is a deep tie to the environment that is so dismissed: Latinos care about the environment because of the environment, not just for self-interest…People feel a strong tie with the land…We came from agrarian societies, and voters would support policies that protect water, trees, and land, even with costs associated. They understand the psychological benefits of preserving the earth, as well as the health benefits…That view is not well understood in the larger equity movement.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Insufficient Understanding of Impacts, Connections, and Solutions</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of self-efficacy emerged as a theme in several dimensions. The “PH non-engaged” respondents felt they lacked adequate information or expertise on health impacts of climate change, the health impacts of climate change planning and policies, and the connections between current public health work and climate change: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“There is a lack of knowledge that climate change has impact across sectors…In public health, people work on one narrow issue and folks might have a hard time making the links between their public health work and climate change.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“PH non-engaged” participants demonstrated low awareness of connections between climate change and their current work, as exemplified by these statements by three participants: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">“We do air quality projects… I’m very familiar with the concept of co-benefits but have never thought about it with regard to climate change.”</span> And, 
      <span class="italic">“It’s uncanny how connected our work is to climate change. It’s almost coincidental. But I wouldn’t necessarily link Safe Routes to School or physical activity to climate change.”</span> Finally, 
      <span class="italic">“WIC would be active in obesity, nutrition, social and environmental determinants of nutrition, but I don’t think of it as a climate change issue. The climate change issue is what happens when the food supply gets disrupted. That is emergency preparedness.”</span>
     </p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other “PH non-engaged” respondents were aware of the connections between their work and climate change, but expressed distinct unease at making these links explicit with their peers, community stakeholders, or decision-makers because they are uncertain about the local impacts of climate change and how it will affect the communities they work with, One “PH non-engaged” respondent said, 
    <span class="italic">“I know it’s a big issue, but I lack data to talk to community and decision-makers at the appropriate scale.”</span> In fact, both groups of public health respondents cited a need for better down-scaling of local climate change impacts, research on community impacts, and methods to forecast local health impacts based on down-scaled climate data. Significantly, many “PH engaged” respondents also did not feel they were experts, understood only one area such as emergency preparedness, and did not think systemically or about multiple impacts.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents from both public health groups expressed frustration at the difficulty of identifying specific meaningful solutions that match the scale and complexity of problem. Even respondents who understand that their own work may help to address climate change expressed skepticism about the effectiveness of their role: 
    <span class="italic">“The work of climate change gives me an overwhelmed feeling. I have a cynical feeling, like how much could it help, promoting Safe Routes to Schools?”</span>
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot1dot2-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.2. Public Health Perspectives on Institutional and Structural-Level Constraints</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Public health respondents from both groups identified myriad institutional and structural constraints that make efforts to engage in climate work challenging. Structures refer to the inter-institutional arrangements and interactions (such as laws, policies, and standard operating procedures) whose joint operation produce health and equity outcomes [
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-12-15010" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-12-15010">37</a>]. The institutional constraints operate within public health agencies and the public health sector, which together operate as the public health institution, while structural barriers operate across multiple interconnected systems and sectors outside of public health.
  </p>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Lack of Capacity in Public Health Infrastructure, Funding, and Workforce</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents from both public health groups said that adding climate change to existing public health priorities seems overwhelming without infrastructure, resources, and workforce capacity, especially given significant recent budget cuts. Two “PH engaged” respondents explained: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Public health has taken a huge hit in staffing with most public health departments at 40%–60% of their staffing levels prior to ten years ago, but have more on their plates. The field of public health keeps growing, and we need to prioritize what public health agencies should be doing. Protecting from climate change is one of those things…”</p>
     <p>“The public health workforce is being eroded rapidly…We will be down staggering numbers. They will need to be paid a living wage and have the tools to work on public health and climate change and be well equipped. It takes more than a guidebook, it takes training, monitoring systems, doing outreach and trainings, and that all takes dollars.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extent to which public health funding is largely through categorical programs with limited and tightly defined scopes of work exacerbates this view. One “PH engaged” said: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“You’re trying to do climate change work on top of everything else you’re doing. There is no funding stream, no time set aside. I try to carve time out to focus on it. But you have all these other things that you’re getting paid to do.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another agreed: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“We’re compartmentalized, and have mandates, missions, and activities that we do every day… feeling stressed in getting them accomplished. If we tell people they need to add climate change, there is a lot of resistance.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change cuts across many programmatic areas, yet respondents in both public health groups bemoaned the perception of program administrators that unless climate change is specifically mentioned in a program’s scope of work, funding cannot be used to address it, even if the grant or contract language might allow it.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many “PH engaged” expressed frustration with the difficulty of raising funds for work on climate change and public health, and how this limited interdisciplinary collaboration: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“The (X) Foundation, which gives incredible amounts of money to public health, specifically doesn’t fund environmental problems. That decision holds implications on the ability to be involved in issues like climate change. That really reinforces silos between public health and other disciplines, and within public health.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Formal and Informal Authority</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numerous respondents in both public health groups spoke about the importance of legal mandates to support public health engagement in climate change. Jurisdiction for implementation of climate change mitigation and adaptation policies varies amongst states that have policies in place, but are generally under the purview of environmental organizations such as the EPA, air boards, fire, water, and conservation agencies. Public health agencies are usually mandated to respond to emergent public health threats such as those caused by climate-related natural disasters and disease outbreaks, as well as limited occupational regulation (e.g., for heat risk). Few public health agencies have any explicit climate change-related mandates. A “PH engaged” gave this example: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“The overall direction and mandate in public health is missing the climate change component. How do you make heat-related illness a reportable disease to elevate it to other public health priorities like sexually transmitted infections?”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another “PH engaged” said: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Public health is struggling to see how it fits in. From an agency perspective, people think it’s relevant, but are constrained by the fact that they don’t have jurisdictional authority to do something about it. Addressing climate change would be mitigating greenhouse gases, but there is no jurisdictional authority related to that at all. They may feel that their hands are tied.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While public health respondents said that they lack formal authority over climate change’s health impacts or drivers, respondents from all groups believed that the public health sector has a lot of informal authority amongst communities and decision-makers. They believe that public health professionals could use this informal authority to provide greater leadership and possibly even move towards formal mandates for public health to address climate change.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Lack of Leadership: Risk Aversion and Politicization of Climate Change</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, across all groups there was a high level of consensus and frustration that public health leadership on climate change is sorely lacking. Strengthening leadership amongst the executive leaders 
    <span class="italic">of mitigating climate change, just raising their voices more in the public.”</span> who define priorities and allocate resources was identified as a crucial step. “PH engaged” participants voiced frustration with the absence of public health agency leadership and action on climate change: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Public health should be speaking out more on the importance of addressing climate change”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When asked why this was not happening, participants linked this to politicization, lack of higher-level institutional support, overt pressure to not act, and fear of repercussions in a risk-averse culture.One governmental “PH engaged” said working on climate change depends on “
    <span class="italic">if they have the leadership, vision, or leeway to get into things elected officials are going to slap them down for.”</span>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Those “PH non-engaged” who saw connections in their work to climate change expressed reluctance to make the links explicit based on perceived political constraints. In jurisdictions where leaders dispute that climate change is real or human-caused, there is fear about even mentioning the words “climate change”, as expressed by a “PH non-engaged”: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“In a public health department like this, the legislation controls your budget, and if there are legislators who feel in any way threatened by interventions, you could find yourself not getting funding for different things.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, participants from all groups believe the lack of public health leadership on climate change is exacerbated by a risk-averse culture in public health. One “PH engaged” governmental employee noted: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Some other parts of the government are less risk averse, but ours is more so… Their whole thing is that ‘we don’t want any surprises and everything goes through us’. Anything that causes anyone to be upset, they shy away from it.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another “PH engaged” respondent said: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“They need to know the Board of Supervisors (BOS) won’t fire them if they speak out on climate change…. Not until people are at the end of their careers will they say what needs to be said.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significantly, public health respondents from both groups indicated that the politicization of climate change and the risk aversion limiting public health involvement impacts their ability to fulfill basic roles, such as stating the likely health effects of policies being considered or the health conditions in their community that may be related to climate change.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Narrow Framework Limits Work on Root Causes of Climate and Health</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because many of the actions to address climate change include efforts to address systems change (e.g., transportation), respondents in both public health groups voiced a need for stronger public health practice on upstream prevention and the social determinants of health, such as food systems, active transportation, healthy housing, and the built environment, as well as more training and resources for that work. A “PH non-engaged” respondent explained: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Most of what we do as a public health department is service delivery. Prevention—which is what climate change work is—is a very tiny part of what we do.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A “PH engaged” participant agreed: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“So many public health departments are still entrenched in how funding is coming, silos, disease conditions, and individual behavior change. Those local health departments that are at least looking at neighborhood conditions will be better off. Climate change is still pretty far out.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recognition that climate change is complex and requires a sustained commitment led respondents to express frustration at a 
    <span class="italic">“reactive”</span> public health practice dominated by the 
    <span class="italic">“tyranny of the urgent”</span>. “PH engaged” respondents stressed that in order to work on climate change, public health will have to shift its resources and attention from service provision to systems changes: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Other things will have to go and be shifted to someone else’s responsibility so that public health can do its work at the broad population level…and focus on the macro-level changes that are needed.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A “PH engaged” respondent stressed that the root causes of climate change should be the focus, even beyond mid-stream environmental exposures: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“The focus on the air pollution benefits is myopic. That’s another challenge for public health: Even within the EPA, everything is organized according to a disease outcome or a health issue. Climate is a large problem that requires systems thinking. If we limit the conversation only to (air pollution), that’s short sighted without thinking about underlying issues.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Compartmentalization within and across Sectors</span> 
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to work on systems changes, public health will need to work effectively across public health programs, and across other sectors. Compartmentalization and lack of coordination across funding streams prevents work on cross-cutting issues like climate change and health. Respondents from all groups note that the silos become more challenging when working across sectors, given organizational barriers and differences in language, approach, and priorities: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“We don’t understand each other at all. We’re in different disciplines; don’t have knowledge of their expertise, different language, and different emphasis on what’s important. It takes twice as much work; you have to get a rudimentary understanding of what they’re doing. Some ways to get over that is willingness to spend a little more time making sure people understand each other.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One “PH engaged” government worker described territorial conflicts over climate change: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“There’s still a sense that public health shouldn’t be in the room because things are not a health initiative. But all public agencies should be responsible to the public and part of that is keeping them safe and healthy. There are turf issues, especially with infrastructure agencies, transit authority, or pollution-planning.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another “PH engaged” participant described: 
    <div class="disp-quote">
     <p>“Air pollution control district and planning are strong partners, but we still tend to get siloed, and they still think climate change is theirs. They all talk ‘health’, but don’t invite health to the table. (X University) organized a state-wide conference, and health was a major topic on the agenda, but they never invited (local health department) to the conference.”</p>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot1dot3-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.3. Non-Public Health Perspectives on Barriers to Public Health Engagement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, the “Non-PH” respondents identified very few barriers, and could identify numerous immediate roles for public health (described below in “3.2. Opportunities for Engagement”). However, “Non-PH” participants voiced frustration with the absence of public health agency leadership, action, and participation in contentious climate change policy-making: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>“I don’t know why public health feels that they are not allowed to do that. (A few public health leaders) are willing to stick their necks out, take political risks, and state what will happen to health with various policies.”</p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This group of respondents believed that the compartmentalization and lack of coordination across funding streams prevents work on cross-cutting issues like climate change and health, and warned against dedicated categorical funding for climate change. One said: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>“One of the most disheartening times in the movement was when people started to just fund climate, thinking it was its own thing, but it’s connected to every issue we work on. If you’re working on clean air, on food, you’re working on climate.”</p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Related to this, “Non-PH” participants described this as an important barrier, because: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>“
     <span class="italic">The siloed mentality also means we don’t get the big picture… this is all inter-related.”</span>
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another “Non-PH” participant agreed: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>“Part of the issue is a lack of integration and a lack of systems thinking. We look one piece at a time, but this affects us in a multitude of ways and we need to bring people together to solve these problems. We always solve one thing and create another problem, like with biofuels. There are water issues, rising food prices, even immigration problems that arise from making decisions in isolation.”</p>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
