<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Insufficient Understanding of Impacts, Connections, and Solutions</span> 
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of self-efficacy emerged as a theme in several dimensions. The “PH non-engaged” respondents felt they lacked adequate information or expertise on health impacts of climate change, the health impacts of climate change planning and policies, and the connections between current public health work and climate change: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“There is a lack of knowledge that climate change has impact across sectors…In public health, people work on one narrow issue and folks might have a hard time making the links between their public health work and climate change.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“PH non-engaged” participants demonstrated low awareness of connections between climate change and their current work, as exemplified by these statements by three participants: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">“We do air quality projects… I’m very familiar with the concept of co-benefits but have never thought about it with regard to climate change.”</span> And, 
    <span class="italic">“It’s uncanny how connected our work is to climate change. It’s almost coincidental. But I wouldn’t necessarily link Safe Routes to School or physical activity to climate change.”</span> Finally, 
    <span class="italic">“WIC would be active in obesity, nutrition, social and environmental determinants of nutrition, but I don’t think of it as a climate change issue. The climate change issue is what happens when the food supply gets disrupted. That is emergency preparedness.”</span>
   </p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other “PH non-engaged” respondents were aware of the connections between their work and climate change, but expressed distinct unease at making these links explicit with their peers, community stakeholders, or decision-makers because they are uncertain about the local impacts of climate change and how it will affect the communities they work with, One “PH non-engaged” respondent said, 
  <span class="italic">“I know it’s a big issue, but I lack data to talk to community and decision-makers at the appropriate scale.”</span> In fact, both groups of public health respondents cited a need for better down-scaling of local climate change impacts, research on community impacts, and methods to forecast local health impacts based on down-scaled climate data. Significantly, many “PH engaged” respondents also did not feel they were experts, understood only one area such as emergency preparedness, and did not think systemically or about multiple impacts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents from both public health groups expressed frustration at the difficulty of identifying specific meaningful solutions that match the scale and complexity of problem. Even respondents who understand that their own work may help to address climate change expressed skepticism about the effectiveness of their role: 
  <span class="italic">“The work of climate change gives me an overwhelmed feeling. I have a cynical feeling, like how much could it help, promoting Safe Routes to Schools?”</span>
 </p>
</sec>
