<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Lack of Capacity in Public Health Infrastructure, Funding, and Workforce</span> 
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents from both public health groups said that adding climate change to existing public health priorities seems overwhelming without infrastructure, resources, and workforce capacity, especially given significant recent budget cuts. Two “PH engaged” respondents explained: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“Public health has taken a huge hit in staffing with most public health departments at 40%–60% of their staffing levels prior to ten years ago, but have more on their plates. The field of public health keeps growing, and we need to prioritize what public health agencies should be doing. Protecting from climate change is one of those things…”</p>
   <p>“The public health workforce is being eroded rapidly…We will be down staggering numbers. They will need to be paid a living wage and have the tools to work on public health and climate change and be well equipped. It takes more than a guidebook, it takes training, monitoring systems, doing outreach and trainings, and that all takes dollars.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extent to which public health funding is largely through categorical programs with limited and tightly defined scopes of work exacerbates this view. One “PH engaged” said: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“You’re trying to do climate change work on top of everything else you’re doing. There is no funding stream, no time set aside. I try to carve time out to focus on it. But you have all these other things that you’re getting paid to do.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another agreed: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“We’re compartmentalized, and have mandates, missions, and activities that we do every day… feeling stressed in getting them accomplished. If we tell people they need to add climate change, there is a lot of resistance.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change cuts across many programmatic areas, yet respondents in both public health groups bemoaned the perception of program administrators that unless climate change is specifically mentioned in a program’s scope of work, funding cannot be used to address it, even if the grant or contract language might allow it.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many “PH engaged” expressed frustration with the difficulty of raising funds for work on climate change and public health, and how this limited interdisciplinary collaboration: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“The (X) Foundation, which gives incredible amounts of money to public health, specifically doesn’t fund environmental problems. That decision holds implications on the ability to be involved in issues like climate change. That really reinforces silos between public health and other disciplines, and within public health.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
