<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fish species invasions mediated by climate change in subarctic lakes have a strong effect on displacing native species, likely by predation. Invasion of northern pike across lakes in Sweden and Alaska has been consistently linked with observed or predicted extirpations of native, cold‐climate adapted subarctic species (Öhlund, Hedström, Norman, Hein, &amp; Englund, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0149" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Sepulveda et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0170" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). For example, the establishment of pike as a top predator over 6 years significantly reduced the abundance of native stickleback and eliminated Arctic charr via predation processes in a subarctic lake in Sweden (Byström et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Northern pike consumed native salmonids in Alaskan streams, causing significant declines in abundance (Sepulveda et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0170" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Projected invasions of pike due to climate change are predicted to cause the elimination of brown trout and Arctic charr from 50% and 73%, respectively, of lakes in Sweden by 2100 (Hein, Öhlund, &amp; Englund, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). These changes in species distribution due to community interactions with climate change are dependent on the feeding traits of both native species and the invader. For example, negative associations between invading Centrachid species (e.g., smallmouth bass) and subarctic fish in Ontario, Canada, have been concluded to be more likely driven by consumption rather than competition interactions (Alofs &amp; Jackson, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015b</xref>). However, the generality of this mechanism across subarctic freshwaters is highly dependent on the trophic position of both native and invading species.
</p>
