<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31" class="p">Finally, Maxent and CLIMEX offer two very different approaches to modelling habitat suitability. As a correlative model, Maxent generates predictions based on statistical relationships between occurrence patterns and environmental data. In contrast, CLIMEX, a semi-mechanistic model, can be calibrated by setting parameter values that describe the species’ response to temperature and moisture either based on physiological data or inferred from the species’ known distribution
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. A number of previous studies have compared the output of Maxent and CLIMEX for both invasive and non-invasive species. Most of these studies found the models to generate similar geographic extents of suitable habitat
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. For example, Kumar 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup> used both models to project the global distribution of the codling moth, 
 <italic class="italic">Cydia pomonella</italic>, a major pest of pome and stone fruits. Both models’ projections reflected the current known distribution of the moth, although Maxent projected marginally suitable habitat to cover a greater geographic extent than CLIMEX projected. In contrast, Kumar 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup> found that Maxent provided a more realistic model of the western cherry fruit fly, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhagoletis indifferens</italic>, compared to CLIMEX, and suggested that differences in the suitability maps may have occurred due to different spatial resolutions (5 km, Maxent; 18 km, CLIMEX) and predictor variables (WorldClim, Maxent; CliMond, CLIMEX). We suggest that it would be very worthwhile to undertake a thorough comparison of projections for Qfly derived from both Maxent and CLIMEX.
</p>
