<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">LMWL and local temperature-δ
  <sub>precip</sub> calibration
 </div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The δ
  <sub>precip</sub> isoscape of northern Canada is spatially complex due to regional differences in mean weather system trajectories, continentality, local orographic effects and varying degrees of continental moisture recycling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. Because each study area has its own potentially unique set of boundary conditions, δ
  <sub>precip</sub> signals preserved in ground ice are best interpreted in the context of local δ
  <sub>precip</sub> systematics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. We demonstrate the meteoric origins and seasonality of DHP174 pore ice by comparison with monthly δD and δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span> from the nearest GNIP station at Mayo, Yukon, ~210 km south of DHP174 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). Mayo and DHP174 are situated at similar elevations (600 and 720 m, respectively) in central Yukon in the western foothills of the Ogilvie Mountains. The Mayo data were used to constrain the LMWL (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>), and the temperature-δ
  <sub>precip</sub> regression lines (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>; Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Three Mayo records that plotted far below the LMWL (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) were excluded from the regressions because of suspected evaporative enrichment. Extreme leverage points (&gt;3
  <span class="italic">σ</span> Cook’s distance) were given a weight of zero in the calibration to avoid undue bias on the regression lines. By comparison with monthly GNIP data from Whitehorse (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>), a site that is ~325 km south of Mayo and has a similar LMWL
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>, the Mayo temperature-δ
  <sub>precip</sub> regressions are found to be skilful in predicting δ
  <sub>precip</sub> at other continental sites in Yukon (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which supports their application to more proximal sites such as DHP174.
 </p>
</sec>
