<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Paleoenvironment and stratigraphy</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DHP174 peat-sediment composite record (5.32 m composite depth) is the product of two core profiles that overlap stratigraphically and includes three lithostratigraphic units (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>) that were deposited over the last ~15.6 ka (see Methods). Unit 1 (5.32–4.78 m) is silty loess and was deposited between 15.6 and 14.3 ka cal BP. Unit 2 (4.78–4.38 m) is a graminoid-rich silty unit that aggraded relatively slowly (~0.1 cm decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span> average) from 14.3 to 11.2 ka cal BP. Unit 2 overlaps with the Younger Dryas interval (~12.9–11.7 ka cal BP), when the climate of northern Alaska was much colder than today
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Finally, Unit 3 (4.38 m to the surface, 10.5 ka cal BP to present) is primarily 
  <span class="italic">Sphagnum</span> moss, reflecting an aggrading peatland phase. The peat sequence accumulated at a relatively stable rate of ~0.4 cm decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, with the exception of higher rates at the time of peatland inception (4.38–4.13 m, ~2 cm decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and a brief slowdown near the core top (0.21–0.15 m, ~0.1 cm decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) during the period ~1000–200 cal yr BP.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Peat fibres were exceptionally well preserved throughout the profile (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2a–c</a>), which suggests a relatively uninterrupted aggradation of permafrost since inception, and a syngenetic origin of relict pore ice in this sequence. Downcore ice content is primarily structureless pore ice (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>) representing pore waters that froze in situ
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. Rare ice lenses (typically &lt;0.5 cm thick; Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2b</a>) were encountered in Unit 1 (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 7) and Unit 3 (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 2) but were not sampled. Ice lenses represent active layer waters drawn to the freezing front by cryosuction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, a process that is common in fine-grained sediments and may explain their higher number in Unit 1. Pore ice and lens ice derive from potentially different active layer water and cannot be directly compared. In this study, we focus exclusively on the dominant form of ice—relict pore ice.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the ~15.6-ka-long peat-sediment chronology described above, the relict pore ice hosted in the same peat-sediment sequence spans the last ~13.6 ka cal BP. The shorter relict pore ice chronology relates to the maximum depth at which active layer pore ice forms and becomes ‘relict’, which equals the maximum active layer thickness (ALT
  <sub>max</sub>). ALT
  <sub>max</sub> is defined as the thickest active layer likely to occur in a given climatic period and is ~58 cm for the study site today (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Because relict pore ice forms below the surface it will always be younger than the host sediments. For example, ca. modern relict ice (–68 cal yr BP; 58 cm below ground) is hosted in fossil peats that grew at the surface ~2065 cal yr BP (i.e. the depositional age of the peats). Relict pore ice in the basal sediments is likewise ~2 ka younger than the depositional age of the hosting sediments (see Methods for full details on the relict pore ice chronology).
 </p>
</sec>
