<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Peat-sediment age-depth model</div>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A composite Bayesian age-depth model for the peat-sediment sequence was produced using radiocarbon (
  <span class="sup">14</span>C) dates and cryptotephra isochrons (see Davies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span> for full details of the composite chronology). Depths are reported as core composite depths (ccd). The Bayesian age-depth model (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>) was constructed using the OxCal Poisson process model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seventeen macrofossil samples were picked for 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C dating from the upper monolith and core profiles (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This includes three dates from a previously collected core that was not used for pore ice analysis (DHP174-12, cored within 1.5 m of DHP174-13), but is included in the age model as it has precise modern cryptotephra and post-bomb 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C dates for its surface peat. Dates from all three cores were included in a composite profile where cryptotephra tie-points were used to correlate between the individual core profiles.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where possible, 
  <span class="italic">Sphagnum</span> remains were preferred as they can provide reliable 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C dates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>. In the mineragenic, non-peat core sections at the base of the DHP174-13L profile, terrestrial plant macrofossils (twigs and leaves) were used for 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C dating. Samples were pre-treated at the University of Alberta following standard procedures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>, and analysed for 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C content at the W. M. Keck Carbon Cycle AMS Laboratory (University of California, Irvine, CA, USA). Two secondary standards were pre-treated concurrently (a last interglacial non-finite-age wood, AVR-PAL-07; and a middle Holocene wood, FIRI-F) and the 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C results were within expected ranges. The unknown 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C dates were calibrated as appropriate using Bomb13NH1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span> and IntCal13
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> calibration curves with Oxcal v4.3.2
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Glass shard concentration profiles for cryptotephra were produced at 1 cm resolution using standard methods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. Three samples geochemically correlated with known eruptions using major element EPMA glass analyses (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>; see Davies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>) were included in the composite age-depth model to improve model accuracy. Katmai-Novarupta (10 ccd) is a historic eruption with an observed occurrence date of 1912 CE. The Aniakchak CFE II (116 ccd) and Hayes set H unit F2 (133 ccd) eruptions are widely reported in Alaska and beyond, and have well-constrained Bayesian age estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
