<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Permafrost stability and climate feedbacks</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rate and magnitude of recent climate warming has implications for the stability of ice-rich permafrost in E. Beringia, which is both widespread and sensitive to climate warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Cryostratigraphic evidence for regional failure of ice-rich permafrost in E. Beringia is linked to past hypsithermals, including thermokarst deposits in Alaska and Yukon dating to Marine Isotope Stage 5e
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, and thaw unconformities and thaw lake initiation dating to the early Holocene in parts of Yukon and the Mackenzie Delta region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. However, the warming threshold for such a widespread permafrost response is not well known. Our finding that today’s summer climate (last ~30 years) exceeds the early–middle Holocene thermal maximum by +1.7 ± 0.7 °C implies that the threshold for ice-rich permafrost stability in this region has already been crossed. This finding is consistent with recent evidence of climate-driven acceleration of thaw slump activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> and ice wedge network degradation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> in the Mackenzie Delta region and Western Arctic more broadly, which have been linked to climate warming. Continued warming and permafrost degradation in this region threatens to expose vast pools of frozen organic matter in near-surface permafrost to microbial activity and, if released to the global atmosphere as CO
  <sub>2</sub> or CH
  <sub>4</sub>, has the potential to amplify future warming trends
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
