<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Potential changes to suitable areas for kiwifruit cultivation under a changing climate were simulated based on the optimal climatic conditions for kiwifruit growth. This suitability simulation based on climatic conditions was critical in mapping the areas in which it is highly likely that kiwifruit orchards will be located in the future, in an effort to make subsequent KBB risk prediction more rational. For the predicted suitable areas for kiwifruit cultivation, we linked the Pss-KBB Risk Model with the Chill-day Model to assess the interactions of kiwifruit vine and blossom blight occurrence, resulting in potential, but more realistic, KBB risk prediction for a changing climate. Reflecting the warming temperature under climate change, the simulation of flowering dates by the Chill-day Model showed a decreasing (advancing) trend over future periods, similar to phenological changes reported in previous studies (
 <xref rid="b30-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Lenoir et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b48-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Yun, 2006</xref>). Considering that the RCP 8.5 climate change scenario from the HadGEM2-AO model projects a 4.1°C increase in temperature in the Korean Peninsula by 2100 (
 <xref rid="b2-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Baek et al., 2013</xref>), our results showed a reasonable shift in the kiwifruit flowering date corresponding to this projected temperature change, which actually provides one of the most compelling evidences of ongoing climate change. 
 <xref rid="b28-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Kwon et al. (2012)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="b21-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al. (2015b)</xref> showed that the modified Chill-day Model could predict flowering dates of Hayward with high accuracy (2.5 days and 2.0 days of MAEs with different ground-truth datasets, respectively) by comparing with ground-truth data representing more than 10 years. Therefore, it can be assumed that the flowering dates predicted by the Chill-day Model for the future periods may represent the actual phenophase of kiwifruit in the future, which in turn indicates that the climatic conditions determined by the predicted flowering dates may also represent the actual conditions that the KBB pathogen will encounter during future seasons. The assumption of a phenophase date for a plant is more likely to be true for perennial fruit trees (or vines) like kiwifruit, which last for more than 30 years once planted, than for annual crops such as rice, wheat, and maize. This is because perennial species do not require human-dependent planting activity, which makes prediction of the future phenophase difficult for annual species.
</p>
