<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results, using multiple models in an integrated way, clearly suggested one of the possible options for a local impact assessment and adaptation study, though there are still several factors further to be improved. Firstly, we used a single climate change scenario from the HadGEM2-AO model, which could not provide the uncertainty information that different GCMs carry. Although we showed the direct comparison results between the KMA scenario and the 11 GCM scenarios downscaled to 7 ASOS stations, it doesn’t mean the same results in other locations in the province. Once more high-resolution scenarios from multiple GCMs become available and are utilized in our integrated modeling approach in the near future, better decision-making for adaptation to climate change will possibly be realized by accounting for fundamental uncertainty inherent from the GCMs (
 <xref rid="b33-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Mathukumalli et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b35-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Ouma et al., 2016</xref>). Secondly, the uncertainty from individual biophysical models should be addressed, which results in low reliability of the models. The main causes of the model uncertainty include lack of integration of non-climatic confounding factors in modeling and insufficient calibration and validation due to limited ground-truth data. As more location-specific ground-truth data are secured through experiments and regular surveys, more reliable models can be used for the local impact studies. Lastly, our results should be taken with caution due to the limited factors considered for the integrated modeling. There are considerable uncertainties accounting for all of the factors affecting the host-disease dynamics, some of which may be impossible to project with currently available knowledge and technologies. For example, a range of environmental factors not directly considered by the models, such as elevated CO
 <sup>2</sup> concentrations, soil fertility, and other weather variables, might affect the biophysical interactions in the future. Therefore, a comprehensive mechanistic modeling approach that includes the biophysical responses of the host plant, the microbial pathogen, and their interaction with environmental factors can be an option for future research. In addition, more input information should be gathered in order to increase the overall reliability of the final results, including the creation of high-resolution maps for soil types, land use, plant cultivar, and additional meteorological variables, after which the results can be used to generate practical agricultural advice and policies by local government units (
 <xref rid="b11-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Geerts et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b44-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Tuck et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
