<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Thanks to the sophisticated satellite observing systems in operation since the turn of the millennium, the radiative fluxes in and out of the climate system at the TOA are now well determined (Loeb et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2012</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2018</xref>). This allows also an accurate estimation of the impact of clouds on the TOA radiation budget through the comparison of satellite measurements representing all-sky and clear-sky conditions, and an adequate assessment of their representation in climate models (e.g., Potter and Cess 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2004</xref>; Wang and Su 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2013</xref>). The magnitudes of radiative fluxes at the Earth’s surface, however, both under all-sky and clear-sky conditions, are not known with the same accuracy, since they cannot be directly measured from satellites (Kiehl and Trenberth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">1997</xref>; Hatzianastassiou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2005</xref>; Wild et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">2006</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2013</xref>; Trenberth et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2009</xref>; Trenberth and Fasullo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2012</xref>; Stephens et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2012</xref>; L’Ecuyer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2015</xref>; Pfeifroth et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2018</xref>). Similarly, the radiation budgets simulated by the latest generation of global climate models (GCMs) participating in the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) show large discrepancies already on a global mean basis particularly at the Earth’s surface, and this not only under all-sky, but also under clear-sky conditions, as will be shown in the present study.
</p>
