<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4309972</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep08118</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep08118</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impacts of reactive nitrogen on climate change in China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Yalan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Shenghui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Xiaotang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Zucong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Yong-Guan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Urban Environment, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, 1799 Jimei Road, Xiamen 361021, PR China</aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>College of Resources and Environmental Sciences, China Agricultural University</institution>, Beijing 100193, PR China</aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>College of Geography Science, Nanjing Normal University</institution>, Nanjing 210023, PR China</aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Research Center for Eco-Environmental Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, 18 Shuangqing Road, Beijing 10085, PR China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>shcui@iue.ac.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c2"><label>b</label><email>ygzhu@iue.ac.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>8118</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>03</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>01</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015, Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder in order to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>China is mobilizing the largest anthropogenic reactive nitrogen (Nr) in the world due to agricultural, industrial and urban development. However, the climate effects related to Nr in China remain largely unclear. Here we comprehensively estimate that the net climate effects of Nr are &#x02212;100 &#x000b1; 414 and 322 &#x000b1; 163&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively. Agriculture contributes to warming at 187 &#x000b1; 108 and 186 &#x000b1; 56&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a 20-y and 100-y basis, respectively, dominated by long-lived nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O) from fertilized soils. On a 20-y basis, industry contributes to cooling at &#x02212;287 &#x000b1; 306&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e, largely owing to emissions of nitrogen oxides (NO<sub>x</sub>) altering tropospheric ozone, methane and aerosol concentrations. However, these effects are short-lived. The effect of industry converts to warming at 136 &#x000b1; 107&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a 100-y basis, mainly as a result of the reduced carbon (C) sink from the NO<sub>x</sub>-induced ozone effect on plant damage. On balance, the warming effects of gaseous Nr are partly offset by the cooling effects of N-induced carbon sequestration in terrestrial ecosystems. The large mitigation potentials through reductions in agricultural N<sub>2</sub>O and industrial NO<sub>x</sub> will accompany by a certain mitigation pressure from limited N-induced C sequestration in the future.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Anthropogenic interventions of the global biogeochemical nitrogen (N) cycle have substantially raised the levels of reactive N [Nr, in general, including organic N, ammonium (NH<sub>4</sub>-N in water and NH<sub>3</sub> in air), nitrogen oxides (NO<sub>x</sub>), nitrous oxide (N<sub>2</sub>O), and nitrite &#x00026; nitrate] in circulation, and caused severe damage to the environment at local, regional and global scales<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. Such dramatic increases can aggravate the impacts on the balance of climate forces in many ways, either through changes to the atmospheric constituents, or through feedbacks within the terrestrial ecosystem<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. The atmospheric N<sub>2</sub>O emission directly contributes to global warming and ozone depletion; NO<sub>x</sub> compounds indirectly produce the short-lived climate-forcing agents (e.g. ozone, aerosol particles) and remove the long-lived climate-forcing agents (e.g. methane (CH<sub>4</sub>)); NH<sub>3</sub> also increases the formation of aerosols. In addition, the deposited and applied N into the terrestrial ecosystem alters the carbon (C) exchange and greenhouse gas (GHG) fluxes between land and air<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. There are many cooling and warming interactions between N and the climate; the dominant effect of N on climate change is likely to vary across regions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. For an equivalent increase in the human population, the emission mass of CO<sub>2</sub>-C into the environment is about 40 times that of Nr<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Although the absolute climate impact of Nr is dwarfed by the impact of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, the variety of Nr species and sources, and the complexity of climate forcers, indicates a need to better assess the integrated effects of Nr and to identify the key forcers at different scales, so as to take targeted measures for N management. A few studies have attempted to assess the combined impacts of Nr at global and regional scales<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>. The lack of systemic study of Nr on climate at the national level has also been noted by Pinder <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>, taking the United States as a case study. China is becoming the largest producer of Nr from both agricultural and industrial activities<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. The climate effects of Nr emissions in China are global rather than regional. The magnitude and acceleration of Nr creation in China warrants an integrated assessment of the significance of anthropogenic Nr on climate change.</p><p>N<sub>2</sub>O, as one of the GHGs, has gained worldwide attention, and has also been thoroughly assessed in China<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. It is well known that reducing N<sub>2</sub>O emissions offers the combined benefits of mitigating climate change and protecting the ozone layer<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. The increasing demands for food and energy in China have led to ever-increasing emissions of NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. These short-lived Nr emissions have multiple and profound effects on climate, the environment and human health<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>. However, their relevance to climate in China is still unclear in previous studies. In addition, ecosystem N availability strongly affects the terrestrial net C balance<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>, as well as many other ecosystem services associated with environmental quality<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. The terrestrial ecosystem C balance in China was investigated to under the influence of multiple global change factors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. The effects of N deposition and N fertilizer use have been identified in a few studies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>.</p><p>In this context, a comprehensive assessment of Nr emissions and use on climate impacts in China is needed to fully understand the consequences of Chinese agricultural, industrial and urban development. To address this need, we seek to answer three questions: (i) What are the climate change impacts of Nr emissions in China, (ii) what are the relative contributions from agriculture and industry sources, and (iii) what are the future climate impacts of Chinese Nr based on different development scenarios? A key challenge is to establish a calculation database for the different climate forcers related to anthropogenic Nr in China. We review and reconcile the relative data and parameters from a variety of literatures related to the Nr emissions in China and their radiative forcing intensities and atmospheric lifetimes. Global temperature potential (GTP) is the common metric to quantify and intercomparing the relative effects of climate forcers over varying timescales. GTP evaluates not only the long-term climate effect caused by emissions of long-lived species like N<sub>2</sub>O, but also the near-term climate fluctuations caused by emissions of the short-lived species NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. Accordingly, we use GTP to convert the climate change impacts of each of the processes to common units of equivalent Tg CO<sub>2</sub> (CO<sub>2</sub>e).</p><p>In this analysis, we combine the set of Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) scenarios, based on consistent radiative forcing levels<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>, and the set of Special Report on Emission Scenarios (SRES) scenarios, based on the best estimates of the current emissions and further mitigation potential<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. The comparison between RCPs and SRES is useful to determine the mitigation potentials or pressures of China's development and make the reasonable N management measures.</p><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Gaseous Nr effects on climate forcers in the atmosphere</title><p>The different gaseous Nr species show the different increase rates during 2000&#x02013;2005 in China, with 11.4%, 44.0% and 8.3% for N<sub>2</sub>O, NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). The emission sectors of Nr also show large variations. N<sub>2</sub>O is the only form of Nr that has unambiguous global implications through the strong warming effect on climate (E1). Total anthropogenic N<sub>2</sub>O emissions in China for 2005 were estimated at 1.04&#x02013;1.22&#x02005;Tg N. The primary source of N<sub>2</sub>O is agriculture. N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from agricultural soils (including emissions from applied fertilizer, manure and crop residues) amounted to a total of 0.59&#x02013;0.87&#x02005;Tg N, it can be further categorized as either direct (0.40&#x02013;0.59&#x02005;Tg) or indirect (0.19&#x02013;0.28&#x02005;Tg) emissions. Direct emissions are caused by N applied to the soils, while indirect emissions are related to subsequent processes after Nr emissions and re-deposition, or after leaching and runoff. Animal manure, including emissions from manure management and grazing animals, contributed 0.17&#x02013;0.18&#x02005;Tg N to the atmosphere. The emission factors for direct and indirect N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from agriculture in China were 1.87% and 0.66%, a little higher than the global mean values of 1.48% and 0.42%, respectively<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>. In addition, N<sub>2</sub>O from fuel combustion, industrial production, waste disposal and biomass burning delivered only 0.14&#x02013;0.30&#x02005;Tg N to the atmosphere. As a result, N<sub>2</sub>O exerts a strong warming effect at 345 &#x000b1; 19&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis, then transforms to 311 &#x000b1; 17&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S7</xref>). The close climate impacts on both timescales imply lasting effects on the climate system resulting from N<sub>2</sub>O due to its long atmospheric lifetime of around 120 years.</p><p>NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> contribute to climate change indirectly through altering the atmospheric constituents and corresponding climate forcers. NO<sub>x</sub> is a major byproduct of combustion. Fuel combustion in China resulted in a total of 4.04&#x02013;6.08&#x02005;Tg N of NO<sub>x</sub> emissions in 2005, mainly from the combustion sectors of power plants (1.15&#x02013;2.08&#x02005;Tg N), transportation (1.26&#x02013;1.66&#x02005;Tg N), industry (1.35&#x02013;1.79&#x02005;Tg N) and household use (0.27&#x02013;0.54&#x02005;Tg N). Agricultural soils contribute a minor part with only 0.17&#x02005;Tg NO<sub>x</sub>-N, mainly through microbial activity from agricultural soils. In sum, 4.34&#x02013;6.24&#x02005;Tg N is released to the atmosphere in the form of NO<sub>x</sub>. In comparison, the total emissions of NH<sub>3</sub> were 7.69&#x02013;12.3&#x02005;Tg N in 2005, becoming the largest source of atmospheric Nr in China. Agricultural soils (including volatilization and applied fertilizer and manure) and animal and human manure management are the main contributors, at 2.30&#x02013;5.20 and 4.37&#x02013;6.02&#x02005;Tg N, respectively; other sources are negligible for the country as a whole. As a result, the combined climate impact of NO<sub>x</sub> on ozone and CH<sub>4</sub> (i.e. ozone-CH<sub>4</sub> effect, E2) in China is &#x02212;350 &#x000b1; 166 and &#x02212;13.2 &#x000b1; 7.2&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a 20-y and 100-y basis, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S7</xref>). Our results show that the net cooling effect of NO<sub>x</sub> on ozone and CH<sub>4</sub> is notable only at a shorter time horizon, and gradually wears off with increasing time horizon. In addition, exposure to tropospheric ozone is known to inhibit photosynthesis, damage plants, and reduce plant primary productivity and land C sequestration capacity (E6)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. The reduction in C sequestration due to the ozone effect for China has been simulated by the terrestrial ecosystem model and estimated at 111 &#x000b1; 100&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e under controlled simulations for different scenarios<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. Therefore, the negative effects on the climate system and crop yields due to the indirect radiative forcing of ozone in China cannot be ignored. Both NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> can enhance the formation of light-scattering aerosols (E3). Compared with the NO<sub>x</sub> effect on the ozone-CH<sub>4</sub> effect (&#x02212;350 &#x000b1; 166 and &#x02212;13.2 &#x000b1; 7.2&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively), the direct aerosol effect of NO<sub>x</sub> is much less, with only &#x02212;97 &#x000b1; 39 and &#x02212;0.006 &#x000b1; 0.004&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively; while the corresponding NH<sub>3</sub> effects on aerosol are &#x02212;59 &#x000b1; 23 and &#x02212;0.11 &#x000b1; 0.13&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e, respectively. As the time horizon is extended, the direct aerosol effects of NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> both become smaller, and can be effectively ignored on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S7</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Nr enrichment effects on net C exchange in the terrestrial ecosystem</title><p>The inputs of Nr into the terrestrial ecosystem are in the forms of N deposition and N fertilization. N addition into ecosystems can alter the physiology of soil microbes and vegetation, and concomitantly alter the balance of biogenic fluxes of GHGs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. Our literature analysis results provide an explicit spatial map of N deposition over China (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). N deposition sums to 15.1&#x02005;Tg N/yr across China, with 3.56, 5.28, 5.68 and 0.57&#x02005;Tg N deposited into cropland, forest, grassland and wetland, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b&#x02013;e</xref>). The estimated N deposition is closed to the published inventories of NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> emissions used in our study. Without considering the response of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions mentioned above, N addition can stimulate terrestrial CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation in both natural vegetation and agricultural land; meanwhile, CH<sub>4</sub> emissions caused by N simulation to some extent offset the benefit of N-induced CO<sub>2</sub> uptake in terms of climate change<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. These opposed impacts of Nr enrichment differ markedly depending on the land cover type<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. The assessed N-induced CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> emission/uptake factors for different ecosystem types of China are summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S6</xref>. Our results show that in China forest land has the largest potential for CO<sub>2</sub> uptake (&#x02212;27 to &#x02212;5&#x02005;kg CO<sub>2</sub>-C/kg N), while cropland has the largest potential for CH<sub>4</sub> emissions (0.01 to 0.03&#x02005;kg CH<sub>4</sub>-C/kg N). Applying the flux factors of CO<sub>2</sub> uptake and CH<sub>4</sub> emission by ecosystem types in China from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S6</xref> to estimate the net C exchange (NCE) due to N deposition, the overall result indicates that the uptake of CO<sub>2</sub>-C (27 to 176&#x02005;Tg C) overwhelmingly surpasses the CH<sub>4</sub>-C emissions (0.11 to 0.21&#x02005;Tg C), resulting in an NCE of 27 to 176&#x02005;Tg in terrestrial ecosystems during 2000&#x02013;2005 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S6</xref>). Most regions in China's terrestrial system function as a net C sink; only a minor area in western China is an N-induced C source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3f</xref>). Our results further show that, during 2000&#x02013;2005, forest land has the largest C sequestration potential, with 31.9 to 136&#x02005;Tg C as a result of N deposition, followed by grassland (4.5 to 45&#x02005;Tg N) and cropland (1.8 to 5.6&#x02005;Tg N). For fertilized cropland, in addition to N deposition, applied N, including chemical and organic fertilizers, was evaluated at 35.7&#x02005;Tg in 2005<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>, resulting in a net CO<sub>2</sub> uptake of 14 to 58&#x02005;Tg C and CH<sub>4</sub> emissions of 0.40 to 1.06&#x02005;Tg C. The NCE of croplands due to N fertilization amounts to 13.6 to 57.0&#x02005;Tg C.</p><p>On the whole, N addition has a positive effect on terrestrial C sequestration over the past several years. The C sequestration simulated by both N deposition and fertilization exerts a cooling effect, &#x02212;50 &#x000b1; 86 and &#x02212;86 &#x000b1; 51&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S7</xref>). The climate cooling effects of N-induced C sequestration, however, offset only 18% and 35% of the warming effects of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions from agriculture in terms of GTP<sub>20</sub> and GTP<sub>100</sub>, respectively. Basically, taking the effects of these three GHG fluxes between air and land into account, Nr enrichment of the terrestrial ecosystem can be recognized as a strong warming agency.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Integrated climate change impact of Nr in China</title><p>On the national scale, anthropogenic Nr in China's ecosystem has a cooling effect on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis in theory (&#x02212;100 &#x000b1; 414&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) and a warming effect (322 &#x000b1; 163&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S7</xref>). However, the uncertainty of GTP<sub>20</sub> is so large that it is hard to conclude whether Nr causes cooling or warming in practice. The uncertainty is largely caused by the climate effects of atmospheric Nr. The collective climate-change impact of gaseous Nr emissions is cooling (in theory) at &#x02212;50&#x000b1;328 Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis but warming at 408&#x000b1;112 Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively, while the climate-change impact of Nr addition into the terrestrial ecosystem is cooling at &#x02212;50 &#x000b1; 86 and &#x02212;86 &#x000b1; 51&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e, respectively. The climate forcers of these two components offset each other through the Nr flows and exchanges between the atmosphere and the land.</p><p>The relative contributions of agriculture and industry sectors are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>. The overall impact of industrial Nr is cooling (&#x02212;287 &#x000b1; 306&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis but converts to warming (136 &#x000b1; 107&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis. The reason is that the cooling effects are largely from the short-lived agency, i.e., NO<sub>x</sub> emissions from fuel combustion. The effect of agriculture Nr is dominated by the long-lived effect of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. As a result, agriculture shows a net warming effect and a minor difference at two timescales, at 187 &#x000b1; 108&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis and 186 &#x000b1; 56&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively. The climate effects of Nr from agricultural and industrial sources cancel each other out on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis, but together contribute to warming effect on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Projection of Nr impact on climate</title><p>Under the SRES I-Business as Usual (BAU) scenario, we assume that Nr emissions and Nr addition will keep the current annual rates of increase. In 2020 and 2050, Nr in China will produce a cooling effect at &#x02212;314 and &#x02212;725&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis and a warming effect at 528 and 939&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S8</xref>). The results indicate that the increase of Nr compounds without any measures will mitigate the climate change on a 20-y basis however aggravate the warming effect on a 100-y basis. On a 100-y basis, the cooling effect of N-induced C sequestration declines significantly, from 86.0&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e in 2005 to 57.3&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e in 2020, then approaches zero in 2050. By contrast, the impact of Nr emissions on climate change becomes more important, increasing from 408&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e in 2005 to 585&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e in 2020 and 939&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e in 2050. The SRES II-improvement scenario is built on the assumption that the N use efficiency of cropland will increase by 20% in 2020 and another 20% in 2050. Compared to the BAU scenario, on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis, the improvement scenario enhances the net cooling effect with 41% and 38% for the years of 2020 and 2050, largely due to the agricultural N<sub>2</sub>O emissions reduction. The SRES III-abatement scenario is built on the assumption of total quantity control for NO<sub>x</sub> in 2020 and an improved NO<sub>x</sub> removal rate in 2050, respectively. On a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis, the abatement scenario reduces the net cooling effect by 95% and 139% compared to the BAU scenario, ultimately appearing as a net warming effect in 2050. The reduction in NO<sub>x</sub> emissions has a strong negative feedback on climate change in the short term, whereas the increase in N use efficiency represents a positive effect on the mitigation of climate warming. Improving agricultural N use efficiency (i.e. N<sub>2</sub>O reduction) is the most timely and effective measure for the mitigation of the climate impact of Nr in China. On a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, the improvement and abatement scenarios both reduce the warming effect by 28% and 14% in 2020, respectively; the reduction effects transfer to 35% and 31% in 2050. Hence, reductions in agricultural N<sub>2</sub>O and industrial NO<sub>x</sub> emissions have a comparatively large mitigation potential in the long term.</p><p>The detailed comparisons between SRES and RCP scenarios are showed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig 6</xref>. All RCP scenarios on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis show a net warming effect, in contrary to our improvement scenario. However, the advantage of our improvement scenario diminishes with time. On a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, its warming effect in 2020 (379.4&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) nearly approaches that of the lowest RCP scenario (RCP2.6, 356.4&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e), or even in 2050 (613.6&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) surpasses that of the highest RCP scenario (RCP8.5, 499.6&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e). The warming effect of our abatement scenario on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis is lower than that of the RCP8.5 in 2020 and 2050. However, on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, its warming effect in 2020 (452.3&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) and in 2050 (646.1&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e) become higher than that of RCP8.5 (423.5 and 499.6&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e in 2020 and 2050, respectively). The comparison results between SRES and RCP indicate that, (i) our reported SRES scenarios reveal the obvious mitigation potential on climate change but only on a short timescale not on a long timescale. (ii) the objectives of our scenarios in 2020 (i.e. realizing the total quantity control for NO<sub>x</sub> and improving the N use efficiency with 20%) is well-targeted to the concentration levels of RCP. However, the objectives in 2050 are too cautious to meet the emission under the RCP scenarios. More aggressive target should be made for the year of 2050.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>China is mobilizing the largest anthropogenic Nr in the world due to agricultural, industrial and urban development. The climate effects of different Nr compounds are experiencing either the aggravation or the transformation processes. Based on the understanding of the dynamic of Nr on climate system, the investigation of possible changes and future trends is more meaningful than current status. Therefore, in this section, we analyze the dynamics and development trajectory of each climate forcer related to Chinese Nr, figuring out the key different points of China from other regions. Here, the differences between the SRES and BAU scenarios are defined as mitigation potential; while the differences between the SRES and RCP scenarios (here using RCP6.0) are defined as mitigation pressure. We further discuss the mitigation potential and mitigation pressure of individual N-related climate forcers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><p>The strong GTP and long lifetime of N<sub>2</sub>O makes it the largest and most lasting contributor to global warming in China. Agriculture is responsible for about 80% of the climate warming effect of N<sub>2</sub>O. The high N fertilizer input and low N use efficiency in China's agricultural fields are responsible for the increasing N<sub>2</sub>O emissions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. Our scenario analysis shows that a larger mitigation potential for climate change could be realized through improving N use efficiency to reduce agricultural N<sub>2</sub>O emissions. Many approaches can be taken to enhance N use efficiency, for example, systematic crop rotation, wise use of fertilizer, and expanded use of nitrification inhibitors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>. Although the agricultural activities are the largest contributor, emission of N<sub>2</sub>O from chemical industries also shows a large increase potential; and the control options are the most-effective in this sector<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. Hence, the all-around measures to reduce N<sub>2</sub>O emission from agriculture and industry could lead to the co-benefits of climate mitigation and positive environmental effect through protecting ozone layer.</p><p>The realistic trajectory of NO<sub>x</sub> reflects a compilation of environmental policies and economic activities<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. NO<sub>x</sub> emissions in many industrialized countries are expected to decrease<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. For example, the NO<sub>x</sub> reductions in Europe in 2010 can be partly attributed to the global economic recession, and partly to the European NO<sub>x</sub> emission controls<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. Due to rapid economic development and the coal-dominated energy consumption structure, however, large increases in NO<sub>x</sub> from China have persisted over the past several decades<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. According to our results, the ozone-CH<sub>4</sub> effect of NO<sub>x</sub> emissions in China is the largest cooling agency at a short time horizon, but is nearly negligible at a longer time horizon. The ozone-CH<sub>4</sub> effect varies greatly across different regions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. Investigations have shown that the ozone-CH<sub>4</sub> effect is more sensitive to ozone precursor changes from tropical regions (e.g. East Asia) than from mid-latitude and high-latitude regions (e.g. Europe and North America)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>. Therefore, control strategies that reduce emissions of ozone precursors in China have a significant impact on the net climate forces from ozone and CH<sub>4</sub>. However, if only considering NO<sub>x</sub> alone, NO<sub>x</sub> emissions exert a negative force from decreased CH<sub>4</sub>, which far exceeds the smaller positive force from increased ozone, resulting in a net cooling effect. The scenario of NO<sub>x</sub> emissions reduction alone lead to a positive force and a net warming effect from overwhelming increased CH<sub>4</sub>, and as a result fails to produce mitigation potential for climate warming. Combined reductions in NO<sub>x</sub> and other ozone precursor emissions (such as CO) are beneficial, because they can produce a net cooling effect through the stronger negative force from decreased ozone<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. Hence, in order to obtain co-benefits from reducing radiative forces and mitigating air pollution, simultaneous emission reductions of various ozone precursors at the regional scale are feasible. In addition, the indirect radiative force on climate change by ozone effects on plant production has proved to contribute more to global warming than the direct radiative force of elevated ozone levels<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. The effect of NO<sub>x</sub> on plants is the secondary contributor to climate warming at both timescales. In China, the combined climate effects of current NO<sub>x</sub> emissions on ozone-CH<sub>4</sub>, aerosol and the ozone-induced C sink were estimated at &#x02212;336 &#x000b1; 290 and 98 &#x000b1; 97&#x02005;Tg CO<sub>2</sub>e on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis, respectively. From the results of our scenario analysis, the NO<sub>x</sub> reduction has a secondary mitigation potential. Therefore, reduction of NO<sub>x</sub> in China can provide the co-benefits of climate-change mitigation and air pollution reduction in the long run. In especial, the NO<sub>x</sub> emission reduction still exist a large mitigation pressure when comparing with the RCP scenarios. China should confirm the implementation of total NO<sub>x</sub> quantity control required by taking policy measures. Meanwhile, continued push to improve the denitration level is an essential measure for mitigating NO<sub>x</sub> pollution.</p><p>China is a large agricultural country with an enormous animal population and tremendous N fertilizer consumption. The characteristics of NH<sub>3</sub> emissions reflect the intensity of synthetic fertilizer use and unique patterns of animal densities and types in China<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>. As the human population continues to demonstrate considerable growth, food production and associated NH<sub>3</sub> emissions are likely to increase as well<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>. Increased NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> produce radiative effects resulting from sulfate-nitrate aerosol and single-nitrate aerosol, respectively. The cooling effect of NO<sub>x</sub> through the direct aerosol effect is larger than NH<sub>3</sub> on a 20-y basis, but its depletion rate with time is faster than the rate of NH<sub>3</sub>. Global model studies demonstrated that the increasing nitrate aerosol force would counteract the expected decline in the sulfate force by 2010<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. The future nitrate aerosol loads are projected to depend strongly on the emission strength of NH<sub>3</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. It can be deduced that a larger increase in nitrate aerosols in China will be accompanied by larger increases of NH<sub>3</sub>, as opposed to the smaller increases in Europe, the U.S. and Australia<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. Although the cooling effect of nitrate aerosols is negligible in the long term, the future air pollution from nitrate in the atmosphere can not be ignored.</p><p>Overall, the net cooling effects of NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub> are short-lived and NO<sub>x</sub> even plays a warming role on the long timescale. Nonetheless, the multiple environmental problems resulting from NO<sub>x</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub>, such as air pollution, eutrophication, etc., are more remarkable than the climate impact in China. In this regard, it is important to assess the trade-offs between the environmental and climate effects of the Nr compounds in the future studies.</p><p>China&#x02014;especially the east region&#x02014;is one of the global heavy N-deposition areas<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. Under the action of N deposition, our results show forest land in China is the single largest C sink, followed by grassland and cropland. The N status of different ecosystems in China can be reflected and further analyzed from the flux factors of CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S6</xref>. For example, N is usually found to be a limiting factor in plant growth in grassland ecosystems in China, and it is mostly unintended fertilization that has stimulated plant growth there<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>; while almost all croplands can be regarded as N-saturated ecosystems due to continual application of chemical N fertilizers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>, as a results, the N-induced flux factor of CO<sub>2</sub> is only 0.45&#x02013;1.7&#x02005;kg CO<sub>2</sub>/kg N. Additionally, there have been very different response patterns of forest ecosystems in China depending on the forest type, the N status of the soil, and the level of N deposition. In N-saturated mature tropical forests, high N addition can reduce soil respiration and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>, and decrease CH<sub>4</sub> uptake rate<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref>. However, in N-limited pine forests, elevated N deposition has no significant effect on soil respiration or CH<sub>4</sub> uptake<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. Overall, the N-induced flux factor of CO<sub>2</sub> in forest lands in China is 5&#x02013;27&#x02005;kg CO<sub>2</sub>/kg N, much lower than that of the United States, with 24&#x02013;65&#x02005;kg CO<sub>2</sub>/kg N<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>. Throughout the whole of China, the terrestrial system acts as a net C sink due to N deposition. However, the potential for sustaining more terrestrial C storage as a result of atmospheric N deposition is limited<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>. As the N deposition increases, the net primary productivity induced by per-unit N deposition has leveled off or declined since the 1980s, indicating that part of the deposited N may not be invested to stimulate plant growth, but instead leave the ecosystem by various pathways<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>. In addition, globally N fertilizer application-induced CO<sub>2</sub> uptake began to level off in the 1980s whereas N<sub>2</sub>O emission continued to grow<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>. As a result, the climate benefits of the enhanced C sequestration would likely be eliminated due to increased N use<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>. Finally, fertilized N will show an increasing warming effect in the future. This trend is more obvious in China. Excessive N-fertilization limits C sequestration. The declining rate of manure recycling to fields causes more N discharge into water or emitted into the air<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">54</xref>.</p><p>N saturation in forest land and excessive N fertilization in cropland in China limit the C sequestration capacity. The effect of N enrichment on C sequestration, as a result, has appeared to diminish in recent years. Hence, through the results of our scenario analysis, there is a certain GHG mitigation pressure in C sequestration through improving N management or reduction gaseous Nr emission in China. Efficient forest development and improved field management have shown the large potential of C sequestration in China's forest and cropland<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">55</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref>. Rational N fertilizer application, no-tillage and preferential crop residues management are widely recognized measures for enhancing C sequestration<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref>. Climate and environmental quality trade-offs and co-benefits, especially if they are applied nationwide in the near term, provide strong additional motivation for reducing N fertilizer use without yield loss in China.</p><p>Overall, anthropogenic Nr in China's environmental system has an obvious warming effect on a long timescale. The reductions in agricultural N<sub>2</sub>O and industrial NO<sub>x</sub> emissions have a comparatively great mitigation potential for climate change in the long term; while a certain mitigation pressure appears in N-induced C sequestration only if realizing the efficient forest development and improved field management. The mitigation pressure of climate warming of anthropogenic Nr is still under great pressure with time. In 2050, more aggressive targets and more powerful measures should be taken to maintain in a specific radiative forcing level.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Climate forcers related to Nr</title><p>Nr can exert a series of effects on GHG fluxes and on climate systems during its cascade flow. We needed to distinguish these &#x0201c;direct&#x0201d; biogeochemical consequences (i.e., radiative forcing) of atmospheric Nr emission from the &#x0201c;indirect&#x0201d; bio-geophysical climate feedbacks of terrestrial N dynamics through terrestrial GHG fluxes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>. We considered six climate-driving forcers of Nr (designated as E1&#x02013;E6 below) and show detailed interpretations in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Supplementary Information</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Fig. S1</xref>). The common metric GTP is used to reconcile the climate change impacts of diverse climate forcers into the common unit of equivalent CO<sub>2</sub> (CO<sub>2</sub>e) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S1</xref>) for the inter-comparison of the relative contributions over 20-y and 100-y timescales, respectively.</p><p>The climate forcers E1&#x02013;E3 refer to climate change impacts through the effects of the atmospheric Nr species (including N<sub>2</sub>O, NO<sub>x,</sub> and NH<sub>3</sub>) on trapping heat or scattering solar energy. So far, there has been no official national inventory of gaseous Nr species for China. The results from many published studies show a certain inconsistency due to the different approaches used. Rather than calculating the Nr emissions inventory, we compiled Nr emissions from the existing regional and global emissions inventories associated with China, including IIASA GAINS, EDGAR v4, RCPs, and MACCity. The data covered total volumes and sectoral structures of Nr emissions within the period 2000&#x02013;2005 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S2</xref>).We defined the uncertainty (i.e., standard deviation) using the variation ranges of all these inventories. The estimated results are proved to be comparable with the published local studies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S3</xref>).</p><p>The climate forcers E4&#x02013;E6 refer to climate-change impacts through the feedback of the atmospheric NO<sub>x</sub> and terrestrial Nr enrichment (N deposition and N fertilization) on GHG's biogenic fluxes. We collected the monitoring data of N deposition rates from different sites around China mainly covering the period 2000&#x02013;2005 from the extant studies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S4</xref>). Through the application of ARCGIS 10, an explicit spatial map of N deposition rate around China was developed using the spatial interpolation technique (kriging). The deposition to each land cover type is obtained by overlapping with the nationwide land-use distribution map. In addition, the fertilization of cropland was adopted from the results of Cui <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. Because of the greater heterogeneity of global terrestrial ecosystems, we reviewed and aggregated the data for N-induced GHG emission/uptake of China (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S5</xref>). N-induced GHG emission/uptake factors were estimated for different ecosystem types (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S6</xref>). In this section, we only accounted for the change in CO<sub>2</sub> and CH<sub>4</sub> fluxes, except for N<sub>2</sub>O, which has been included in the previous atmospheric Nr emission inventory.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Uncertainty analysis</title><p>The quantification of the significances of climate forcers E1&#x02013;E6 were calculated normally through multiplying the effective Nr volumes by the corresponding metric GTP, so as to reconcile and inter-compare the diverse climate forcers. We used the Monte Carlo Sampling (MCS) and Latin Hypercube Sampling (LHS) methods to simulate and propagate the uncertainties through the calculations, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S7</xref>). These methods are based on the principle that the empirical process of actually drawing many random samples and observing the outcomes can assess the behavior of a statistic in random samples. The uncertainties of parameters, activity data, and formulas are propagated through the sequence of calculations. In the MCS approach, we assumed each value in the uncertainty range had equal likelihood and no correlation between the variables. A population of 10,000 estimates was built and ranked in order. The median and 90% confidence intervals were reported. The LHS approach was further used to calculate the uncertainties in our research. All variables were divided into 300 equal intervals. An ensemble of 300 sets of all parameters was selected randomly and ranked in order. The mean and standard deviation were reported. The results of the uncertainty analysis using MCS and LHS were similar. Hence, we only discuss the results of the LHS method here.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Scenario analysis</title><p>Based on the possible or expected changes of different driving forcers, we set up a new set of three scenarios to depict the future trend of climate change (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1">Table S8</xref>). Short-term projections (to 2020) were developed using a &#x0201c;baseline&#x0201d; path of development, which considered abatement options consistent with China's situation and policy. For long-term projections (to 2050), we applied a &#x0201c;storyline&#x0201d; approach similar to that used in the IPCC Special Report on Emission Scenarios (SRES) scenarios<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. The situation in 2005 was used as the reference and those in 2020 and 2050 as the target years. (i) SRES I&#x02013;Business as Usual (BAU) scenario is based on the assumption that Nr emissions will maintain the annual increase rate of 2000&#x02013;2005 with no change. (ii) SRES II&#x02013;Improvement scenario, builds on the BAU scenario and assumes that the N use efficiency of cropland will increase with an aspirational target of 20% until 2020<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">57</xref> and a further 20% until 2050, which approaches the level of developed countries<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. (iii) SRES III-Abatement scenario, is designed to cut 10% of NO<sub>x </sub>emissions in accordance with the reduction target of the &#x0201c;Twelfth Five-Year Plan&#x0201d; in 2020, and assumed that the nationwide NO<sub>x</sub> removal rate reaches 80% in 2050. Because of the limited C storage of terrestrial ecosystems, the N-induced C sequestration potential is projected to decline 50% and be negligible with the increased N use in 2020 and 2050. The values in 2010, 2030 and 2040 are calculated on the basis of the logistic growth model. In addition, we compared our SRES scenarios with the published Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP), with four scenarios based on different concentration levels (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0 and RCP8.5, with the numbers referring to different radiative forcing levels) rather than emissions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Y.S., S.C. and X.J. contributed equally to this work. S.C., Y.-G.Z. and Y.S. conceived of the study. Y.S. and S.C. prepared meteorological inputs. Y.S., S.C. and X.J. performed research and analyzed data; S.C., Y.S., X.J., Z.C. and Y.-G.Z. wrote the paper. All authors gave comments on the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d33e25" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Supplementary information</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-s1.doc"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by the National Key Basic Research Program (2014CB953800). We thank the IIASA for the use of the GAINS Model database GAINS-CHINA; the JRC-IES for the use of the EDGRA v4.2 and the ECCAD-GEIA database to gain other emission inventories related to reactive nitrogen.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>The global nitrogen cycle in the twenty-first century</article-title>. <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source>
<volume>368</volume>, <fpage>20130164</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Transformation of the nitrogen cycle: Recent trends, questions, and potential solutions</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>320</volume>, <fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>892</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Erisman</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seitzinger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bleeker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Butterbach-Bahl</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Reactive nitrogen in the environment and its effect on climate change</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Env Sust</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>290</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kroeze</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Bouwman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The role of nitrogen in climate change</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Env Sust</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<source>European Nitrogen Assessment. Nitrogen as a threat to the European greenhouse balance.</source> (Cambridge Univ Press, Cambridge Univ Press, <year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">EPA. <source>Reactive Nitrogen in the United States: An Analysis of Inputs, Flows, Consequences and Management Options.</source> (EPA Science Advisory Board, <year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pinder</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Climate change impacts of US reactive nitrogen</article-title>. <source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>7671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7675</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Groffman</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Centennial-scale analysis of the creation and fate of reactive nitrogen in China (1910-2010)</article-title>. <source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>2052</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2057</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G. X.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Nitrous oxide emissions from terrestrial ecosystems in China</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere -Global Change Science</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J. X.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Reducing Nitrous Oxide Emissions to Mitigate Climate Change and Protect the Ozone Layer</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Technol</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>5290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5297</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24749524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Atmospheric Reactive Nitrogen in China: Sources, Recent Trends, and Damage Costs</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Technol</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>9420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9427</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22852755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>The nitrogen cascade</article-title>. <source>Bioscience</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>356</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nitrogen Limitation on Land and in the Sea-How Can It Occur</article-title>. <source>Biogeochemistry</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Human alteration of the global nitrogen cycle: Sources and consequences</article-title>. <source>Ecol Appl</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>737</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>The carbon balance of terrestrial ecosystems in China</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>458</volume>, <fpage>1009</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>U1082</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19396142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H. Q.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>China's terrestrial carbon balance: Contributions from multiple global change factors</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cy</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>GB1007</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Soil carbon sequestrations by nitrogen fertilizer application, straw return and no-tillage in China's cropland</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C. Q.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Effect of nitrogen deposition on China's terrestrial carbon uptake in the context of multifactor environmental changes</article-title>. <source>Ecol Appl</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22471075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shine</surname><given-names>K. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fuglestvedt</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hailemariam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Stuber</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Alternatives to the global warming potential for comparing climate impacts of emissions of greenhouse gases</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>
<volume>68</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>The representative concentration pathways: an overview</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">IPCC. <source>IPCC expert meeting report on emission scenarios. Meeting Report.</source> (2005). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipcc.ch/pdf/supporting-material/expert-meeting-2005-01.pdf">http://www.ipcc.ch/pdf/supporting-material/expert-meeting-2005-01.pdf</ext-link>. (Assessed: <fpage>15th </fpage><month>May</month><year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">UNEP. <source>Drawing Down N2O to Protect Climate and the Ozone Layer. A UNEP Synthesis Report</source>. (<year>2013</year>) Avaiable at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unep.org/pdf/UNEPN2Oreport.pdf">http://www.unep.org/pdf/UNEPN2Oreport.pdf</ext-link>. (Accessed: 4th <month>April</month><year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ashmore</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Assessing the future global impacts of ozone on vegetation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>964</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Felzer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Future effects of ozone on carbon sequestration and climate change policy using a global biogeochemical model</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>373</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Greaver</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A review of nitrogen enrichment effects on three biogenic GHGs: the CO<sub>2</sub> sink may be largely offset by stimulated N<sub>2</sub>O and CH<sub>4</sub> emission</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1117</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19694782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Response of Greenhouse Gas Emissions to Nitrogen Deposition in Terrestrial Ecosystem</article-title>. <source>Adv Mater Res-Switz</source>
<volume>518&#x02013;523</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Estimates of synthetic fertilizer N-induced direct nitrous oxide emission from Chinese croplands during 1980&#x02013;2000</article-title>. <source>Environ Pollut</source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>635</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19762135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>F. Y.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Popkin</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A new stage of the nutrition transition in China</article-title>. <source>Public Health Nutr</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12027281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Reductions in nitrogen oxides over Europe driven by environmental policy and economic recession</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>256</fpage>; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep00265</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22355768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;vblad</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tarras&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>T&#x000f8;rseth</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>[Chapter 3: Nitrogen oxides]</article-title>. <source>EMEP Assessment Part I. European Perspective The Cooperative Programme for Monitoring and Evaluation of the Long-range Transmission of Air Pollutants in Europe</source>, [L&#x000f6;vblad, G., Tarras&#x000f3;n, L., T&#x000f8;rseth, K. &#x00026; Dutchak, S. (ed.).] [<fpage>48</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>] (Norwegian Meteorological Institute, Oslo. <year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burrows</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nuss</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Granier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Niemeier</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Increase in tropospheric nitrogen dioxide over China observed from space</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>437</volume>, <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16136141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fuglestvedt</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isaksen</surname><given-names>I. S. A.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Estimates of indirect global warming potentials for CH<sub>4</sub>, CO and NO<sub>x</sub></article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>437</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berntsen</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Response of climate to regional emissions of ozone precursors: sensitivities and warming potentials</article-title>. <source>Tellus B</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Net radiative forcing due to changes in regional emissions of tropospheric ozone precursors</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res-Atmos</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>D24306</fpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Global and regional temperature-change potentials for near-term climate forcers</article-title>. <source>Atmos Chem Phys</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2485</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sitch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Huntingford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Indirect radiative forcing of climate change through ozone effects on the land-carbon sink</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>448</volume>, <fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>U794</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17653194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>A high-resolution ammonia emission inventory in China</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cy</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>GB1030</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Projections of air pollutant emissions and its impacts on regional air quality in China in 2020</article-title>. <source>Atmos Chem Phys</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>3119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3136</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seinfeld</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mickley</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>General circulation model assessment of direct radiative forcing by the sulfate-nitrate-ammonium-water inorganic aerosol system</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res-Atmos</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>1097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1111</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Nitrate aerosols today and in 2030: a global simulation including aerosols and tropospheric ozone</article-title>. <source>Atmos Chem Phys</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>5043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5059</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Enhanced nitrogen deposition over China</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>494</volume>, <fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>462</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23426264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>S. Q.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Response of ecosystem carbon exchange to warming and nitrogen addition during two hydrologically contrasting growing seasons in a temperate steppe</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1544</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1556</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Nutrient Imbalances in Agricultural Development</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>324</volume>, <fpage>1519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1520</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Nitrogen addition reduces soil respiration in a mature tropical forest in southern China</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>412</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Methane uptake responses to nitrogen deposition in three tropical forests in southern China</article-title>. <source>J Geophys Res-Atmos</source>
<volume>113</volume> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Response of soil respiration to simulated N deposition in a disturbed and a rehabilitated tropical forest in southern China</article-title>. <source>Plant Soil</source>
<volume>296</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zaehle</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Dalmonech</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Carbon-nitrogen interactions on land at global scales: current understanding in modelling climate biosphere feedbacks</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Env Sust</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>311</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nitrogen deposition as an important nutrient from the environment and its impact on ecosystems in China</article-title>. <source>J Arid Land</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<source>Global greenhouse gas balance induced by nitrogen addition: Modeling annual fluxes of CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O from 1948 to 2008. American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting 2010,San Fracisco. Cambridge, MA SAO/NASA Astrophysics Data System</source> (abstract #B31A-0285) (2010, December).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>On fertilizer-induced soil carbon sequestration in China's croplands</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>850</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An estimate of greenhouse gas (N<sub>2</sub>O and CO<sub>2</sub>) mitigation potential under various scenarios of nitrogen use efficiency in Chinese croplands</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2970</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>J. X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z. Q.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Net ecosystem carbon budget, net global warming potential and greenhouse gas intensity in intensive vegetable ecosystems in China</article-title>. <source>Agr Ecosyst Environ</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kahrl</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Greenhouse gas emissions from nitrogen fertilizer use in China</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Policy</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>694</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Net mitigation potential of straw return to Chinese cropland: estimation with a full greenhouse gas budget model</article-title>. <source>Ecol Appl</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>634</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>647</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20437953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prather</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Akimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Indirect long-term global radiative cooling from NOx emissions</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1722</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Carbon sequestration and its potential in agricultural soils of China</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem Cy</source>
<volume>24</volume> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b57"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<source>Our Nutrient World: The Challenge to Produce More Food and Energy With Less Pollution.</source>
<volume>114</volume> (Centre for Ecology and Hydrology, Edinburgh, <year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Emission inventory of gaseous Nr.</title><p>Uncertainty bars represent the min and max ranges of Nr compounds. The data are collected from a variety of inventory models, including IIASA GAINS, EDGAR v4.2, RCPs, and MACCity.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Climate change impact of Nr in China.</title><p>The warming effect is represented in red color, while the cooling effect is represented in blue color. Uncertainty bars represent the variation ranges of climate effects on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and GTP<sub>100</sub> basis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>N deposition into terrestrial ecosystems and net C exchange due to N deposition.</title><p>(a), Spatial distribution of N deposition rate in China. (b), N deposition into cropland ecosystem. (c), N deposition into forest ecosystem. (d), N deposition into grass land ecosystem. (e), N deposition into wetland ecosystem. (f), Net C exchange (NCE) due to N deposition. The blue color represents C uptake; the red color represents C emission. The spatial maps of N deposition rate around China were developed from the spatial interpolation technique through the application of ARCGIS 10.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Relative contribution to climate change of Nr from agriculture and industry.</title><p>The effect of agriculture is represented in yellow color, while the effect of industry is represented in green color. Uncertainty bars represent the variation ranges of climate effects on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and GTP<sub>100</sub> basis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Scenario analysis on climate forcers related to Nr in China, on a GTP<sub>20</sub> and GTP<sub>100</sub> basis for the year of 2020 and 2050.</title><p>E1: N<sub>2</sub>O &#x02192; N<sub>2</sub>O effect; E2: NO<sub>x</sub> &#x02192; ozone-CH<sub>4</sub> effect; E3: NO<sub>x</sub>, NH<sub>3</sub> &#x02192; Aerosol effect; E4: N deposition &#x02192; CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub> effect; E5: N fertilization &#x02192; CO<sub>2</sub>, CH<sub>4</sub> effect; E6: NO<sub>x</sub> &#x02192; ozone &#x02192; CO<sub>2</sub> effect. The differences between SRES II, SRES III and BAU scenario are defined as mitigation potentials, with green column; while the difference between SRES II, SRES III and RCP scenario are defined as mitigation pressures, with orange column. The detailed mitigation potentials and pressures of SRES II and SRES III are represented on the left and right of the points, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-f5"/></fig><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Climate change impact of Nr in China between 2005&#x02013;2050.</title><p>(a), climate effect on a GTP<sub>20</sub> basis. (b), climate effect on a GTP<sub>100</sub> basis. The values in 2010, 2030 and 2040 are estimated on the basis of the logistic growth model.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep08118-f6"/></fig></floats-group></article>