<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">China is facing a great challenge of controlling air pollution, especially in urban cities and regions because of their differences in environmental protection and socioeconomic development. Chinese government has paid a great attention to the challenges since recent decade. National monitoring and report system for daily air quality has been established for major urban cities across the country (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). Findings from the study show that the average API significantly increased in most cities of the 120 reported cities from 2012 to 2013. A significantly higher proportion of cities that had an API &gt;100 (defined as a “slightly polluted,” but being risk of disease and mortality for vulnerable populations) for ≥60 days in a year increased from 2012 to 2013 (4 vs. 18%, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The proportions of cities that had a maximum API &gt;300 (defined as a “severely polluted,” being risk of disease and mortality for all populations) increased from 2012 to 2013 (13 vs. 29%, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The variations in API were significantly and spatially clustered across the country. Overall, North and Northwest China had higher API than the rest of the country. Although several studies examined the differences in air quality across local regions and cities, the present analysis is the first to use the newest released air quality data from 120 major cities and to test its spatial and temporal differences across the nation. Huang and his colleagues, using data from the city of Xi’an (located in the northwest of China), examined the trend of air quality (assessed by PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>) across 13 monitoring districts (stations) within the city. Their results showed that the mean PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> concentration appeared decreased but no statistically significant change from 2013 to 2014 (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). However, a significant clustering distribution of PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> across the 13 districts were observed (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>). Kai et al. evaluated air quality in Guangzhou (located in south central China), compared it with additional 11 large cities of China. They used air quality data monitored for a period of 6 years from 2000 to 2005, assessed by mean API and individual air pollutants of SO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, total suspended particular (TSP), PM10, and CO. Their findings suggested a significant variation in API and individual air pollutants among the 12 cities (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>). Findings of our study add further new evidence using the largest dataset of 120 cities from the national surveillance system, and confirmed a significant increase in API in most cities from 2012 to 2013.
</p>
