<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Newly-laid 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> eggs (&lt;1 day old) were collected randomly from the laboratory colonies to create seven sets of mite colonies for experiments. In each set, 50–100 eggs were individually transferred into an ELISA well provisioned with pollen collected from 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">cornifrons</italic> nests. The seven sets of mite colonies were placed into environmental chambers (Percival Scientific, Perry, IA; Fisher Scientific, Dubuque, IA) with seven constant temperatures (i.e. 16.1±0.28°C, 20.2±0.73°C, 24.1±0.06°C, 27.5±0.33°C, 30.0±0.08°C, 32.4±0.51°C, and 37.8±0.48°C). Temperature inside each environmental chamber was recorded with a HOBO data logger (HOBO
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> onset
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> UX 100 Temp/RH, Cape Cod, MA). Developmental stage (i.e., egg, larva and nymph) of each 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> was checked and recorded daily. A stereomicroscope (Olympus SZ-ST, Tokyo, Japan) was used to distinguish life stages of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> based on size, shape, and quiescence periods between two stages (i.e., larva to nymph and nymph to adult). The adult stage was identified based on the presence of seta on abdomen and sclerotized structure underneath the abdomen [
 <xref rid="pone.0161319.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Checking and recording the developmental stages of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> needed to take 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> development out of the chambers. To minimize the potential effect of temperature changes on 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> development, recording developmental stages was done within 10 min. under 20±0.5°C, 60±10.2% RH.
</p>
