<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although some high-leverage methods are thought to have ‘the potential to transform the politics of the climate problem’ (
 <xref rid="bibr104-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Victor, 2008</xref>: 325), the political implications of such technologies have so far not been given the same attention as environmental risks. Possible environmental risks such as disruption to global precipitation patterns or damage to the ozone layer have naturally been the central concern for climate scientists modeling responses to solar geoengineering (
 <xref rid="bibr54-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr83-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Polson et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr90-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ricke et al., 2010</xref>; Rob, 2008). The major political concern to figure in the debate so far has been the risk of a ‘moral hazard’ effect: that having a ‘Plan B’ for tackling climate change might ‘reduce the incentive to take adequate steps to prevent global warming’ (
 <xref rid="bibr26-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Corner and Pidgeon, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr60-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lin, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr88-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reynolds, 2015</xref>). Security issues in particular have remained largely peripheral to the debate about climate engineering and climate risk. Thus for Nobel Prize-winning chemist Paul Crutzen, an early advocate of research into solar radiation management (SRM) methods, ‘the main issue with the Albedo modification method is whether it is environmentally safe, without significant side effects’ (
 <xref rid="bibr30-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Crutzen, 2006</xref>: 212). Similarly, a recent study asks ‘could solar geoengineering be designed and deployed in such a way that it could substantially and equitably reduce climate risks?’, but expressly excludes risks related to ‘governance’ (
 <xref rid="bibr56-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith and Irvine, 2016</xref>; see also, for example, 
 <xref rid="bibr70-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moreno-Cruz and Keith, 2013</xref>). Although there is concern about ‘whose hand should control the thermostat’ (
 <xref rid="bibr59-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lin, 2012</xref>: 173) and the potential for international conflicts (see, for example, 
 <xref rid="bibr54-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr97-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">Scientific American</italic>, 2008
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr110-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zürn and Schäfer, 2013</xref>), in the main, geophysical risks have eclipsed geopolitical ones.
</p>
