<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The new PHYDA dataset, along with modeling of the historical forced climate, has allowed us to construct a more comprehensive theory of Southwest megadroughts than has heretofore been possible. This theory unifies SST and radiative forcing mechanisms that act together to cause megadroughts. We confirm the hypothesis that anomalously frequent periods of cold Pacific SSTs can lead to megadroughts (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>), but we also find that these SST patterns in the past were unusually cold and unforced. Over the past 1200 years, this phenomenon is at least twice as important for explaining Southwest megadroughts as an Atlantic forcing or an exogenous radiative forcing (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2, A and D</a>). Yet, we explain the clustering of megadroughts before circa 1600 CE as a result of changes in each of these climate phenomena: Cold Pacific SST fluctuations are more frequent and more cold (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Figs. 1</a>, D and G, and 3), the north Atlantic is warmer (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1, E and H</a>), and periods of positive radiative forcing are more common (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1, F and I</a>). Each of these factors contributes to droughts (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>), and their changes lead to an increase in the occurrence of megadroughts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results imply that ENSO variability, in addition to local positive radiative forcing, has the capacity to induce megadrought conditions at any time in the future. There is evidence that these two factors acting together may explain the drying trend in the Southwest since the early 1980s [e.g., (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>)]. However, the predictability of a contemporary megadrought may be limited, given that state-of-the-art global climate models have difficulty reproducing important features of ENSO [e.g., (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>)]. Of perhaps greater concern for the long-term future is the possibility that radiative forcing could gradually come to dominate the hydroclimate of the Southwest, with the recurrence of megadroughts becoming almost assured (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). The results presented here provide paleoclimatic verification of the capacity of radiative forcing to increase the odds of megadrought. Yet, if the past is a useful guide to the next few decades, then megadroughts could also arise through unforced and unpredictable ENSO variability.
 </p>
</sec>
