<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linear regression analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We performed a decadal-scale linear regression analysis to assess the relative importance of climate drivers in explaining decadal hydroclimate over the period 800–1925 (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>); for this panel, decadal-scale PDSI was the predictand and decadal-scale NINO3.4, AMO, and total forcing were the predictors. We performed the univariate and multivariate regressions within a bootstrap sampling framework that sampled both the choice of averaging and the values in the time series: The ensemble mean time series shown in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> were averaged at 9-, 10-, and 11-year block averages and randomly sampled with replacement such that 999 (3 × 333) total regressions were performed for each predictor/predictand(s) option. The bootstrap sampling used here (and for all the panels in 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>) allowed us to incorporate the uncertainty associated with the choice of averaging time and to more accurately estimate regression parameters with a relatively small sample size (
  <span class="italic">n</span> ≈ 110 at decadal time scales). Before computing the regressions, the averaged time series were detrended to remove autocorrelation (the removal of which was confirmed). The adjusted 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> values (adjusted for the number of predictors) for all 999 bootstrap regressions are summarized with box plots in 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> (B and C), we performed a similar decadal-scale, bootstrap regression analysis but with NINO3.4, AMO, and NASW averaged temperature as predictands and the total forcing as the predictor. We also showed the distribution of regression parameter values β
  <sub>1</sub> (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>), as in the regression equation 
  <span class="italic">y</span> = β
  <sub>0</sub> + β
  <sub>1</sub>
  <span class="italic">x</span> + ε. These bootstrap-generated distributions provide an estimate of the confidence in β
  <sub>1</sub>, although they are not identical to formal linear regression confidence intervals, which rely on assumptions that we did not make with the bootstrap approach. Note that the predictors here have not been standardized because we used the magnitude of the regression parameters in the main text; thus, the relative importance of the predictors cannot be deduced from 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>. Note also that because this analysis only captures linear relationships, there may be further nonlinear causal factors that are not accounted for.
 </p>
</sec>
