<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our simulations repeatedly showed humidity to significantly affect the impact absorption capabilities of spider orb webs while temperature made little difference. Absorbing the impact of flying prey is nevertheless the first of a series of actions within the web that affects whether spiders can capture and retain certain prey. The retention of prey intercepted, and their ultimate recognition by the spider are equally, or perhaps more, important actions (
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Blackledge 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Tarakanova and Buehler, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Blamires 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2018
 </xref>). Prey retention is driven by the adhesiveness of the gluey silks of the spiral threads (
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Tarakanova and Buehler, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Blamires 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2018
 </xref>), which are dynamically affected by the interplay between temperature and humidity (
 <xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Stellwagen 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Opell 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2017
 </xref>), as well as UV radiation (
 <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Stellwagen 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2015
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). It is well known now that at high temperature and humidity, water infiltrates the gluey silks of spider orb webs and mobilizes the glycoproteins in the glues (
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Sahni 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Stellwagen 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2014
 </xref>). However, if humidity rises too high, the gluey silks overlubricate and lose their adhesion (
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Sahni 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2011
 </xref>). At what specific temperature and humidity this phenomenon occurs differs substantially among different spider species (
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Opell 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2018
 </xref>), so it will be very difficult to incorporate into future models but worth attempting.
</p>
