<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sites</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We surveyed reef fish assemblages and coral reef benthic assemblages in March 2014 at a total of 13 (fish) and 11 (benthic) sites across 5 atolls in the Chagos Archipelago (decimal minutes: 05.237333 S 71.81498 E to 07.26195 S 72.44333 E, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0191448.g001" href="#pone.0191448.g001">Fig 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s001" href="#pone.0191448.s001">S1 Table</a>). Locations included the fully submerged Blenheim Reef atoll, reefs fringing islands on the west side of the Great Chagos Bank (GCB) and the large, well formed Peros Banhos and Salomon atolls. Reef types were defined based on the Andrefoute et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref034">34</a>] classification of coral reefs and included forereefs and terraces on the outside of the atolls and pinnacles and inner slopes in the atoll lagoons (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s001" href="#pone.0191448.s001">S1 Table</a>). These were categorised as exposed (outside atolls) or protected (inside lagoons) from oceanic seas. The British Indian Ocean Territory Administration Section of the Foreign and Commonwealth Office, UK Government, granted the research permit to the Darwin Initiative 2014 Expedition to work within the whole Territory. Permission was granted to all authors to visit and dive in the strict nature reserves of the Chagos Archipelago Marine Park.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0191448.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0191448.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Map of the Chagos Archipelago showing atolls surveyed and locations of dive survey sites.</div>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0191448.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Benthic surveys</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Underwater video transects were recorded using a Sony HDRCX550 camera in a Light and Motion Bluefin housing with Fathom 90 wide angle port and red filter, onto which red lasers with a spacing of 10 cm were mounted to provide scale. Surveys were conducted at each site which ranged in depth from 5–25m. The video aimed for a constant speed (~0.1 m s
   <span class="sup">-1</span>), with a 10 min transect within each of four depth zones (25–20 m, 20–15 m, 15–10 m, 10–5 m) approximately 1 m above the substrate [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref035">35</a>]. Percentage cover of all hard coral and 
   <span class="italic">Acropora</span> spp. alone, dead coral (defined as recently dead coral skeleton with intact corallite structure), soft coral, crustose coralline algae (CCA), fleshy macroalgae, turf algae, calcareous substrate, sand/rubble and all other benthos were assessed by randomly selecting 20 video frames from each depth range, and recording what lay beneath 15 randomly selected points per frame, for a total of 300 points per transect (thus 1,200 points per site), assigned using Coral Point Count software [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref036">36</a>]. The rugosity of the reef along each transect was estimated visually using a six point scale following Polunin and Roberts [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref037">37</a>], ranging from no vertical structural complexity to highly-developed reefs with large coral colonies, caves and crevasses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish surveys</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All fish species from 13 pre-selected families that span the full range of trophic groups, from piscivores to detritivores (see 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s002" href="#pone.0191448.s002">S2 Table</a>) were counted in 50 x 5 m transects. Two dives were conducted at each site which spanned approximately 300 m along the reef edge. In each dive 2–3 transects were run parallel to the reef edge (5–6 replicate transects in total per site). Transects were placed randomly at different depths to span the depth range of the reef, but a maximum dive depth of 26m was imposed by dive safety regulations. Fish counts at each site therefore had relatively broad depth ranges, depending on the reef profile (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s001" href="#pone.0191448.s001">S1 Table</a>). This design was used to maximise survey coverage of the fish assemblage on the reef. The fish survey sites corresponded to the dive sites at which the benthic video transects were placed; both methods spanned the same depth range at each site. Siganids (rabbitfishes) were not observed at all and therefore a total of 12 families were counted (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s002" href="#pone.0191448.s002">S2 Table</a>). The density and size classes of species were estimated using standard underwater visual census (UVC) techniques for coral reef fishes [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref038">38</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref039">39</a>]. The size of all species &gt;5 cm total length (TL) were estimated in 5 cm size classes (e.g. 6–10 cm TL, 11–15 cm TL, 16–20 cm TL etc), to obtain biomass values based on published length—weight relationships [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref040">40</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref042">42</a>]. Biomass was calculated as a derived variable for the fish assemblage because it is a good indicator of energy flow within the coral reef ecosystem. A fixed size category for the smallest species was used because: simplifying counting procedures across a wide range of species improves accuracy [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref039">39</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref043">43</a>]; any differences in biomass in these small species between sites will be smaller than the 5 cm size class accuracy used; and to enable these small species to be included in total biomass calculations. Fixed size classes were as follows: i) all Chaetontidae species were assigned a length size class of 6–10 cm, with the exception of 
   <span class="italic">C</span>. 
   <span class="italic">xanthocephalos</span>, 
   <span class="italic">C</span>. 
   <span class="italic">lineolatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Heniochus</span> spp. which were recorded as 11–15 cm; ii) small acanthurids, 
   <span class="italic">Ctenochaetus</span> spp., 
   <span class="italic">Acanthurus nigrofuscus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">A</span>. 
   <span class="italic">leucosternon</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Zebrasoma scopas</span>, were assigned a length size class of 11–15 cm; iii) 
   <span class="italic">Centropyge</span> spp. (Pomacanthidae)–were assigned a length size class of 6–10 cm. A total of 110 species were identified and assigned to 12 functional trophic groups (piscivores, omnivores, corallivores, invertivores, planktivores, detritivores, grazer-detritivores and 5 herbivore categories, 
   <span class="italic">sensu</span> Green and Bellwood [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref044">44</a>]) using a classification system for the WIO [
   <a rid="pone.0191448.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref045">45</a>] (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s002" href="#pone.0191448.s002">S2 Table</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For analyses, the data were organised into a series of matrices: i) fish species numerical density and biomass (13 sites); ii) fish functional group numerical density and biomass (13 sites); iii) benthic habitat variables (11 sites) that were natural log-transformed and standardised (11 variables).</p>
  <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish assemblages</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial autocorrelation in fish assemblages across the Chagos Archipelago was tested by implementing a Mantel test using the ade4 package [
    <a rid="pone.0191448.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref046">46</a>] in R [
    <a rid="pone.0191448.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref047">47</a>] on a matrix of geographic distances between sampling sites and a dissimilarity matrix based on fish density computed using the Bray-Curtis index. The Mantel statistic was further calculated within Peros Banhos, GCB and Salomon atolls, to test for a relationship with geographic distance between sites within atolls. Correlations between both numerical density and biomass matrices were tested for significance using 9999 permutations.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to visualise variation in the composition of fish assemblages across the archipelago, we used non-metric multidimensional scaling (nMDS) on Bray-Curtis dissimilarity distance measures obtained from fish data matrices of both abundance and biomass. To determine which of the fish trophic groups were significantly related to the ordination, we carried out random permutation testing using 9999 permutations. To further examine for groupings within the fish assemblage data, a Ward cluster analysis based on Euclidean distances was performed on hellinger-transformed data, using similarity profile analysis (SIMPROF) to test the significance of clustered groups [
    <a rid="pone.0191448.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref048">48</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec008" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relationships between datasets</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested for co-linearity within benthic variables and identified variables that were correlated at 
    <span class="italic">r</span> ≥ 0.7. Three variables (calcareous substrate, sand/rubble, and other benthic) were removed from further analysis and no remaining pairwise correlations between variables greater than 
    <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.53 were found. The remaining 8 variables were further tested by a variance inflation factor (VIF) analysis which found that each of the retained environmental variables resulted in a VIF of &lt;10.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Adonis function within the Vegan package [
    <a rid="pone.0191448.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref049">49</a>] was used to examine for significant relationships between categorical variables (atoll, reef type and exposure) and the fish assemblages surveyed, also using permutation testing set at 9999 permutations. We used the envfit function within the Vegan package to estimate the direction and strengths of the correlation between the nMDS of fish species and the reef benthic variables surveyed.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we used a variation of the BIO-ENV [
    <a rid="pone.0191448.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref050">50</a>] routine, termed BIO-BIO, to identify the subset of fish species which best correlated to the overall biological pattern of the dissimilarity matrix, using both numerical density and biomass data. They produced similar results, thus density alone was presented.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
