<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies predicting the potential distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">solenopsis</italic> under climate change have focused on local areas (India) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180913.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] and only one climatic variable (e.g., temperature) using a temperature-driven phenology model with GIS [
 <xref rid="pone.0180913.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. However, in the present paper, the potential distribution areas of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">solenopsis</italic> around the world were predicted based on the MaxEnt model and 7 climatic variables. The current study have resulted in the creation of a more accurate potential map under current and future climate because these environmental factors could more clearly reveal the survivabiligy of the pest. In addition, our habitat suitability map are roughly corresponds to the map created by the CLIMEX model under current climate conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0180913.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. However, our study differs substantially in terms of both methodology and some habitat suitability areas. Compared to our map, the study of Wang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic> may be overestimate or underestimate the extent of suitable habitat around the world. Several studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0180913.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0180913.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>] suggest MaxEnt model was slightly more accurate than the CLIMEX model, which could be due to it directly used species presence locations and finer resolution climatic dataset. However, CLIMEX use relatively simple functions to model species responses to climatic factors and coarse resolution climatic dataset. In addition, the sampling spatial bias usually leads to environmental bias because of the over-representation of certain environmental features of the more accessible and extensively surveyed areas. Nevertheless, Wang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic> did not take into account sample bias in their study. Another important factor is that only native distribution sites were employed in CLIMEX. However, the result of Shabani and Kumar [
 <xref rid="pone.0180913.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>] suggest, it is best to have entire data records rather than only native data in species distribution modeling. The map of potential distribution range of species will be distorted when only native species distribution sites are considered in species distribution moedlling.
</p>
