<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We thank R. Flad and J. Wright for providing comments on the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> This research was supported by National Science Foundation grants BCS-1632207 (to J.d.G.) and SMA-1347973 (to R.K.B.). J.d.G. also received support from the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for Scholarly Exchange (JS027-A-15). R.K.B. received additional support as the William D. Lipe Chair in Research at the Crow Canyon Archaeological Center. 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> J.d.G. assembled chronometric and site data. R.K.B. wrote the code and performed the simulations. J.d.G. and R.K.B. wrote the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper, the Supplementary Materials, and through the following repository: A research compendium (
  <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
   <italic class="italic">47</italic>
  </xref>) containing all code and data to reproduce the analysis, as well as the specification of the computing environment, is available as data file S3, in a publicly available GitHub repository (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/bocinsky/guedesbocinsky2018" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/bocinsky/guedesbocinsky2018</ext-link>), and archived with Zenodo at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1239106" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1239106</ext-link>. See the README.md file in data file S3 for details on reproducing the analysis. This code is written in R—a free and open source software environment for statistical computing. Because of the sensitive nature of archaeological site locations, table S2 does not include locational data; the entire dataset—including data excluded from the present analysis because they were from sites outside of our study area, or crops not discussed here—is archived in the Digital Archaeological Record (ID: 428089) at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6067/XCV8MK6G05" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.6067/XCV8MK6G05</ext-link>. Because of the difficulty of accessing the China Vegetation Atlas (
  <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
   <italic class="italic">57</italic>
  </xref>) in the United States, we have archived it in the Digital Archaeological Record (ID: 442484) at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6067/XCV85B05BG" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.6067/XCV85B05BG</ext-link>.
 </p>
</ack>
