<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material substitution effect</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the material substitution effect for building construction, civil engineering, and furniture production, the volume of the life-cycle reduction in carbon emissions from fossil fuel consumption attributable to the substitution of HWPs for non-wooden materials was evaluated. However, it is necessary to determine a figure for the volume of HWP substitution for non-wooden materials. Thus, the BAU scenario was taken as a baseline, and the increase in HWP volumes in the Mod and the Agg scenarios as compared to the BAU scenario were taken to be the volume of substitution for non-wooden materials. For building construction, civil engineering, and furniture production, the annual carbon emissions reduction (tC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) attributable to material substitution was evaluated by multiplying, respectively, the increase in the floor area of new wooden building construction (m
  <span class="sup">2</span> year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and the increase in the consumption of each HWP (m
  <span class="sup">3</span> year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), by the carbon emissions reduction intensity (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>, kgC m
  <span class="sup">−3</span>). The carbon emissions reduction intensities are shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>.
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Carbon emissions reduction intensities attributable to fossil fuel consumption, as a result of HWP substitution for non-wooden materials</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Material substitution</th>
      <th align="left">Unit</th>
      <th align="left">Value</th>
      <th align="left">References</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Building construction: substitution of wooden buildings for non-wooden buildings</td>
      <td align="left">kgC m
       <span class="sup">−2</span>
      </td>
      <td char="." align="char">60.560</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Civil engineering: substitution of wooden piles for cement and sand piles</td>
      <td align="left">kgC m
       <span class="sup">−3</span>
      </td>
      <td char="." align="char">46.773</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Civil engineering: substitution of wooden guardrails for metal guardrails</td>
      <td align="left">kgC m
       <span class="sup">−3</span>
      </td>
      <td char="." align="char">64.477</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Furniture: substitution of wooden furniture for metal furniture</td>
      <td align="left">kgC m
       <span class="sup">−3</span>
      </td>
      <td char="." align="char">43.168</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>, the carbon emissions reduction intensity attributable to the substitution of wooden building for non-wooden building (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) was taken from MiLCA [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. It was calculated by subtracting the emission intensity for wooden building (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) from the emission intensity for non-wooden building (reinforced concrete, steel reinforced concrete, steel and concrete blocks) (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>), from the weighted average, based on 2013 building construction floor space (m
  <span class="sup">2</span>). The emission reduction intensity attributable to the substitution of wooden piles for non-wooden piles in civil engineering was taken from [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. The emission intensity for wooden piles (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) was subtracted from the average value (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) of the emission intensity per unit of improved area for cement and sand piles, to generate an emission reduction intensity per unit of HWP-use volume (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−3</span>). The emission reduction intensity attributable to the substitution of wooden guardrails for metal guardrails in civil engineering was taken from [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. The emission intensity for wooden guardrails (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was subtracted from the emission intensity for metal guardrails (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), to give a reduction intensity per unit of HWP-use volume (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−3</span>). The reduction intensity attributable to the substitution of metal furniture with wooden furniture was taken from MiLCA [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. The emission intensity for wooden furniture (kgC item
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was subtracted from the emission intensity for metal furniture (kgC item
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), to generate a reduction intensity per unit of HWP-use volume (kgC m
  <span class="sup">−3</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
