<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">From a management perspective, prevention, usually involving some form of risk assessment, is clearly the most cost-effective solution to invasions (Simberloff et al. 
 <xref rid="b267" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Therefore, considerable focus should be on prevention including the identification of the source and receiving areas for introductions (such as ports). Internationally, risk assessment is accepted as an essential policy instrument for managing biological risk. Risk is quantified by examining the invasiveness, impacts and potential distribution of species, areas which are all being improved by the adoption of genomic approaches. Thereafter (i.e. in a postborder context), substantial focus on interventions across the stages of invasion is critical for management success both in relation to typical population processes (such as those involved in emergence from lag phases) (Kueffer et al. 
 <xref rid="b161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Ricciardi et al. 
 <xref rid="b235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Simberloff et al. 
 <xref rid="b267" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) and to changes in the environment associated with climate change and human adaptation to such change. Likewise, understanding when invasion success may be driven by factors other than climate change, such as local adaptation to climates, evolution of increased competitive ability and enemy release (Blossey and Notzold 
 <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1995</xref>; Chun et al. 
 <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Van Kleunen et al. 
 <xref rid="b301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Hill et al. 
 <xref rid="b137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), is also important for managing invasions. Prioritization of management actions to species of greatest risk (Randall et al. 
 <xref rid="b232" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Byrne et al. 
 <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Forsyth et al. 
 <xref rid="b108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) is critical given the requirement for effective outcomes with investment of limited resources. As hybridization has been demonstrated to facilitate invasiveness, assessment of genetic risk is an important management tool (Byrne et al. 
 <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>), particularly in the context of managed relocation as a climate change adaptation strategy (Schwartz et al. 
 <xref rid="b260" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
