<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Given uncertainty in scenarios of future climate, impact assessments should incorporate data from a range of climate models that are effective in simulating historical climate over the area of interest. CSIRO compared the output of 40 global climate models (GCMs), and identified a subset of eight that they recommend for use in climate impact assessments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. These eight are representative of the range of results from all 40 models, for the Australian region, and are effective in reproducing historical conditions. Of the eight climate models, six had data at a resolution of 30 arc seconds, for the Representative Concentration Pathway 8.5 (RCP8.5)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>. These models, and descriptions of changes they project for mean annual temperature (MAT) and annual precipitation (AP) for 2070, are as follows. (1) CanESM2 (The Second Generation of Canadian Earth System Model) projects an extremely hot, dry future, with warming &gt;4 °C throughout central Australia, and &gt;5.5 °C in parts of Western Australia. AP is projected to decline throughout central and Western Australia, and increase in north-east Queensland, with few changes in the south-east; (2) ACCESS1.0 (The Australian Community Climate and Earth System Simulator) projects a hot, dry future. Warming exceeds 2.5 °C across most of Australia, and &gt;3.5 °C in central Australia. Drying is projected over most areas, including the horticultural zone in south-eastern Australia (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>), although higher rainfall is likely in central Australia; (3) MIROC5 (Model for Interdisciplinary Research on Climate) projects moderate warming, not exceeding 3 °C, and slight changes in AP with declines in north-east Queensland and south-west Australia; (4) HadGEM2 (Hadley Centre Global Environmental Model Version 2) projects a hot future with warming typically &gt;2.5 °C, and &gt;3.5 °C in central regions. AP is projected to increase in central Australia, and decline elsewhere including the horticultural zone; (5) NorESM1 (The Norwegian Earth System Model-Part-1) projects moderate warming, with most of the continent exceeding 2 °C. Little change in AP is projected, particularly in the south-east, although there is drying in south-west WA; (6) GFDL-ESM2M (Global Coupled Climate Carbon Earth System Model Part-1) projects a hot, very dry future, with warming in central regions exceeding 3.5 °C. Drying is projected across most of the continent, with AP forecast to decline more than 20% in many areas.
</p>
