<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is thus an urgent need to understand the relationship between climate change and IAS distributions, especially those that may have a major impact on biodiversity. Some authors have tackled this issue through opinion or review papers based on key examples (Hellmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Walther et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) or used models to project the likely effects of climate change on the distribution of certain IAS. However, such studies are restricted to a single species or taxa. Some have conducted that climate change increases the area occupied by IAS (Barbet‐Massin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Gilioli, Pasquali, Parisi, &amp; Winter, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Kriticos, Sutherst, Brown, Adkins, &amp; Maywald, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>), while others show that climate change limits IAS distributions (Bellard et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Bradley, Oppenheimer, &amp; Wilcove, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Xu, Feng, Yang, Zheng, &amp; Zhang, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Moreover, the multiplicity of species studied, the variable approaches used, and the resulting variability in projections make it difficult to get a clear picture of the future effects of climate change on invasions. Large‐scale analyses of their geographic responses to global climate change are rare (Bellard et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Peterson, Stewart, Mohamed, &amp; Arau, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Thus, the key question about the likely effects (direction and strength) of climate change on IAS distributions remains unanswered.
</p>
