<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20790-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Atmosphere</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the evaluation of the atmospheric component of N96ORCA1, we compare 50‐year means (years 50 to 100) against the equivalent from N216ORCA025, as in the previous sections. In the troposphere, N96ORCA1 is generally somewhat colder than N216ORCA025 (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0016" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0016">16</a>). Akin to the SST (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0004">4</a>), this leads to a cold bias in the NH, while the warm bias in the SH is much smaller in N96ORCA1. At tropopause levels, it is again N96ORCA1 that is colder, by ~1 K.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20790-fig-0016" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 16</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a and b) Zonally averaged annual mean air temperature in Kelvin. (c and d) The bias against ERA‐Interim (Dee et al., 
    <a rid="jame20790-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0014">2011</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-31" xlink:href="JAME-10-2865-g016" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For global mean precipitation, the largest biases are in the region of the Intertropical Convergence Zone. The geographical pattern of the biases is mostly resolution independent (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0017" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0017">17</a>). Because of a misrepresentation of the position of the Intertropical Convergence Zone and its seasonal cycle, some tropical regions are too dry (equatorial Pacific, northern tropical Atlantic and Africa, and the Indian subcontinent) while others are too wet (western tropical Pacific and western tropical South America). Some of the equatorial dry biases are stronger in N96ORCA1 (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0017" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0017">17</a>b). The annual global mean precipitation in N96ORCA1 is 3.07 mm/day (3.13 mm/day in N216ORCA025 or 2% more). These values are somewhat too large compared with observational estimates that tend to be just below 3.0 mm/day (Behrangi et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0004">2014</a>; Wild et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0074">2012</a>). This excess global mean precipitation is a long‐standing issue with the UM and other global atmospheric models (Collins et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0010">2010</a>). Indeed, several of the regional annual mean precipitation biases found in N96ORCA1 are common to CMIP5 climate models in the ensemble average (Flato et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0021">2013</a>), for instance, the biases over the oceans mentioned above, the dry bias over the Indian subcontinent, or the dry‐wet dipole over Siberia.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20790-fig-0017" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 17</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Annual mean precipitation climatology. All values in millimeters per day. (a) Absolute values in N96ORCA1; (b) difference between N96ORCA1 and N216ORCA025; (c) error in N216ORCA025 against observations (GPCP2; Adler et al., 
    <a rid="jame20790-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0001">2003</a>); and (d) error in N96ORCA1 against observations.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-33" xlink:href="JAME-10-2865-g017" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As an indicator for the representation of land surface processes in N96ORCA1, we use the volumetric soil moisture. Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0018" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0018">18</a> shows a comparison for the NH summer between the 50‐year mean from the two resolutions and the remotely sensed soil moisture (1996–2015 average) from the combined ESA‐CCI product (Dorigo et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0018">2017</a>; Gruber et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0028">2017</a>; Liu et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0045">2012</a>). Both resolutions capture the global patterns reasonably well (for instance, dry Sahara and wet NH midlatitudes) while they span a wider range of values than the observations: the dry regions are drier and the wet regions wetter than in the ESA‐CCI data. The N96ORCA1 simulation appears to have slightly wetter soil (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0018" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0018">18</a>c), mostly where the simulations show a too high soil moisture to begin with. We suspect that differences in precipitation (cf. Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0017" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0017">17</a>) rather than systematic differences in the land‐surface model are responsible. While most of the wettest regions in the tropics are masked out in the ESA‐CCI data (because of the high cloud cover), the overestimation of high soil moisture is manifest in Southeast Asia and in midlatitude South America. It is likely that this is a result of the excess precipitation in these regions (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20790-fig-0017" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0017">17</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20790-fig-0018" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 18</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Volumetric soil moisture (m
    <span class="sup">3</span>/m
    <span class="sup">3</span>) in the top soil layer of N96ORCA1 (a), N216ORCA025 (b; both 50‐year means), and in satellite observations (d; 20‐year mean). The difference between the two models is shown in (c). Shown are boreal summer means (June‐July‐August).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-35" xlink:href="JAME-10-2865-g018" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The gross primary productivity of the land‐based ecosystems, in the global total (carbon), is 119 ± 6 Pg/year in a recent observation‐based estimate (Jung et al., 
  <a rid="jame20790-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0035">2011</a>). As simulated by JULES in N96ORCA1, it is 111.1 Pg/year, slightly below the observed value. This might be related to the low soil moisture in some subtropical regions discussed above. In the N216ORCA025 simulation, it is even lower (102.0 Pg/yr), possibly related to the lower soil moisture.
 </p>
</sec>
