<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20790-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Top of Atmosphere Radiation Budgets</div>
 <sec id="jame20790-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global Mean</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We begin by considering the time‐dependent global and hemispheric radiation balance on centennial time scales, including surface and planetary albedo. Since our simulations have a continuous year 2000 forcing, these time series are not meant to reproduce observed variability. Rather, we believe that this analysis is instructive to understand the evolving and differing biases in N96ORCA1 and N216ORCA025.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0001">1</a>a shows how the N96ORCA1 model, starting from PD conditions, reaches a temporally stable top of atmosphere (TOA, at 85 km) net radiation balance between +0.3 and +0.4 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> after 300 to 400 years. The N216ORCA025 model appears to reach an equilibrium somewhat earlier (after about 150 to 200 years) and at a more positive value (+0.5–0.6 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>) that is closer to observed estimates for recent decades (Allan et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0002">2014</a>). As well as analyzing total net radiation, it is also important to consider the shortwave and longwave components of the TOA radiation budget as these may tell a different story to the net radiation.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20790-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Global radiation budgets at the top of the atmosphere (TOA) for (a) net incoming radiation (downward positive), (b) outgoing longwave (upward positive), and (c) outgoing shortwave radiation (upward positive), from the N96ORCA1 (blue) and N216ORCA025 (green) simulations. The graphs are 11‐year running means.</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="JAME-10-2865-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figures 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0001">1</a>b and 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0001">1</a>c show the evolution of TOA outgoing longwave radiation (OLR) and outgoing shortwave radiation (OSR) in the two models. While both start from almost identical initial states, they quickly diverge in terms of global mean OLR. In N96ORCA1 OLR initially drops during the first 20–40 years, as the ocean mixed layer cools relative to its initial conditions. After this adjustment, OLR slowly increases in N96ORCA1 in line with a gradual increase in global mean SST (see Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0010">10</a>), stabilizing after ~400 years. In contrast, the N216ORCA025 model does not show an initial drop in OLR (and a much smaller drop in global mean SST; see Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0010">10</a>); rather, there is an immediate increase in OLR. This different behavior over the first ~20–40 simulation years is due to the rapid development of a warm upper ocean/SST bias in the N216ORCA025 model across the Southern Ocean, with spatial mean SSTs increasing by ~1.3 °C in the first 30 years of simulation (not shown). This results in a dipolar pattern in SST biases (relative to observations), warm over the Southern Ocean balancing cold elsewhere with respect to global mean values and, therefore, no initial adjustment in either global mean SST or OLR. There is a tendency for the Southern Ocean surface to also warm in N96ORCA1 but at a significantly slower rate than N216ORCA025. By year 30, N96ORCA1 Southern Ocean mean SSTs are 0.3 °C warmer than the initial conditions and 1 °C cooler than N216ORCA025. In terms of global mean SST, the weaker Southern Ocean warming in N96ORCA1 does not balance the cooling SST trend over the rest of the globe and an adjustment of global mean SST and OLR does occur. Beyond the first ~40 years, both models exhibit a gradual increase in global mean OLR. There is a suggestion that the N216ORCA025 OLR stabilizes around year 275, at a value of ~242 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>, although the period of stable OLR is too short to be conclusive. What is clear is that the apparent stabilization of net TOA radiation from year ~150 onward in N216ORCA025 is not a result of the TOA radiation components stabilizing but rather due to near cancellation of opposite signed trends in global mean OLR and OSR.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As with OLR, global mean OSR also shows opposite initial trends between N96ORCA1 (increasing over the first 20–40 years) and N216ORCA025 (decreasing over the same period). The increase in N96ORCA1 is associated with an increase in sea ice cover during this adjustment period, as the ocean loses heat (cools). This is seen in the increase in surface albedo in that model (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0003">3</a>c), which primarily occurs in the NH (Arctic sea ice increasing, Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0003">3</a>d). The inverse (negative) OSR trend in N216ORCA025 is connected to a rapid decrease in surface albedo (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0003">3</a>), with this primarily occurring in the Southern Hemisphere (SH; Antarctic sea ice loss) as a consequence of the warm SST bias in N216ORCA025 over the Southern Ocean. After this adjustment period, both models exhibit a gradual decrease in OSR, again associated with a decrease in surface albedo, with the trend being stronger in N216ORCA025, primarily in the SH.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A continuous decrease in sea ice (and therefore planetary albedo) is expected in a coupled simulation using continuous year 2000 forcing, as this model will have a positive net TOA radiation balance (as seen in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0001">1</a>). It is for this reason we use the period 50–100 years into the respective simulations to compare against observations. This period is after the initial ocean mixed layer adjustment (in N96ORCA1) but early enough in the simulation so the integrated forcing of the model will be similar to that experienced by the real climate system during the period ~1980 to 2010, when the bulk of observations have been made. Over the first 50–100 years of the two simulations OLR and OSR are within the uncertainty range of observations in Loeb et al. (
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0046">2009</a>), Stephens et al. (
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0065">2012</a>), and L'Ecuyer et al. (
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0044">2015</a>) suggesting the model experiences a radiative forcing representative of recent decades.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jame20790-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hemispheric Means and Hemispheric Gradients</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earth loses energy in the NH (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0002">2</a>a, solid lines) and gains energy in the SH (dashed lines). As a consequence, an interhemispheric, northward energy transport is required (Marshall et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0048">2013</a>). In terms of TOA net radiation this NH to SH gradient is ~1.2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> more negative in N96ORCA1 (about −4.6 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>) than in N216ORCA025 (about −3.4W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>; see Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0002">2</a>b). This results from (i) the SH receiving more radiation in N96ORCA1 (dashed lines in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0002">2</a>a) and (ii) the NH losing more energy at TOA (full lines in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0002">2</a>a) in N96ORCA1. To evaluate the hemispheric gradients of TOA radiation and better understand the cause of differences between the two models, we look at the hemispheric components and gradients of both OSR and OLR.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20790-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a, c, e) Global radiation budgets at the top of atmosphere (TOA) for either hemisphere (Northern Hemisphere: solid; Southern Hemisphere: dashed). (b, d, f) Same for the hemispheric difference (Northern Hemisphere minus Southern Hemisphere). Otherwise as Figure 
     <a rid="jame20790-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0001">1</a>. Note that for net radiation (panels a and b) downward radiation is positive, while for outgoing radiation (the other panels) upward radiation is positive. LW = longwave; SW = shortwave.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="JAME-10-2865-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stephens et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0064">2016</a> and Voigt et al. (
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0070">2013</a>) show that observed SH and NH mean OSR are almost equal (e.g., central estimates in Stephens et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0064">2016</a>, are SH OSR 99.7 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> and NH OSR 99.6 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>), while the NH to SH OLR gradient is ~1.3 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> (Stephens et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0064">2016</a>; SH OLR 238.9 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>, NH OLR 240.2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>; although is important to note that observed estimates of OSR and OLR are subject to an uncertainty of ±2 to 3 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>). Considering OSR, in both hemispheres N216ORCA025 is 1–2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> less reflective than N96ORCA1, with the SH OSR likely more accurate in N96ORCA1 and the NH OSR more accurate in N216ORCA025 (cf. sea ice extent in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0015" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0015">15</a>). Put another way, the N216ORCA025 model is not sufficiently reflective to solar radiation in the SH, where N96ORCA1 performs better. In the NH the N96ORCA1 model is likely too reflective and N216ORCA025 is more accurate. Nevertheless, both models have very similar NH to SH OSR gradients of ~1.5 to 2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> (NH more reflective than SH), in contrast to the near‐zero gradient in observations. Problems simulating the hemispheric gradient in OSR have been documented in numerous studies (e.g., Trenberth and Fasullo, 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0069">2010</a>; Bodas‐Salcedo et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0007">2012</a>; Hwang and Frierson, 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0032">2013</a>) and can result both from errors in simulating climatological cloud‐radiation interactions over the Southern Ocean, particularly model underestimates of the prevalence of supercooled liquid clouds in the region (Bodas‐Salcedo et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0006">2016</a>; Kay et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0037">2016</a>), and from biases in simulated historical anthropogenic aerosol radiative forcing, which is primarily a NH phenomenon (Ghan et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0025">2016</a>; Myhre et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0053">2013</a>; Regayre et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0058">2018</a>). How much, one or both, of these problems contributes to the OSR error in HadGEM3‐GC3.1 requires further analysis.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With respect to hemispheric OLR, the evolution of NH mean OLR is rather similar in both models, with slightly higher values in N216ORCA025. The models differ more in the SH, where after 100 years, N216ORCA025 OLR is ~2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> greater than N96ORCA1 (240 vs. 238 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>, with a central observational estimate in Stephens et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0064">2016</a>, of 238.9 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>). The N216ORCA025 model (as shown in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0009">9</a>) develops a warm Southern Ocean SST bias, which is partly due to an underestimate of SH atmospheric reflectivity and an associated overestimate in surface downwelling solar radiation (i.e., simulated OSR in N216ORCA025 is ~98 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> compared to a central observed estimate of ~99.7 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>). A positive bias in SH OLR is consistent with (and also a consequence of) such a Southern Ocean warm bias. Over the NH N216ORCA025 OLR is at the upper end of the observed range (~242 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> at year 100 compared to a central observed estimate of 240.2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>). The hemispheric OLR gradient in N216ORCA025 is therefore quite accurate but results from both hemispheres emitting too much OLR. In contrast, N96ORCA1 is closer to the central observed OLR estimates for both the NH and SH, slightly overestimating in the NH and underestimating in the SH, leading to a hemispheric gradient that is ~1 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> more positive than N216ORCA025 and observations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The combination of similar hemispheric OSR gradients, but different OLR gradients, leads to the difference in hemispheric gradient (NH minus SH) of net TOA radiation between the two models: −4.6 (N96ORCA1) and −3.4 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> (N216ORCA025), compared to a central observed estimate of −1.8 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>. The bulk of these errors against observations are associated with a common positive bias in the NH minus SH OSR gradient, which may have different drivers in the two models (i.e., SH atmosphere not sufficiently reflective in N216ORCA025, NH atmosphere too reflective in N96ORCA1). The more realistic (weaker) net TOA radiation gradient in N216ORCA025 arises from a weaker (more realistic) NH minus SH OLR gradient, which unfortunately results from the N216ORCA025 SH emitting OLR too strongly due to the warm surface Southern Ocean bias.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total planetary albedo (
   <span class="italic">α</span>
   <sub>p</sub>) in the period 50–100 years of the two simulations (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0003">3</a>a) bounds the observational estimate (
   <span class="italic">α</span>
   <sub>p</sub> = 0.293; Stephens et al., 
   <a rid="jame20790-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20790-bib-0066">2015</a>). Both models show a decrease in planetary albedo, with the N216ORCA025 model consistently lower by ~0.5%. A significant fraction of this trend in planetary albedo can be attributed to decreases in surface albedo, associated with loss of sea ice and snow cover due to the positive net TOA radiation balance in both simulations. This decrease is greater in N216ORCA025, mainly due to a greater decrease in the SH associated with the surface ocean warm bias in that model. Considering hemispheric albedos, the NH surface albedos (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0003">3</a>d) are quite similar in both models, while the NH planetary albedo is clearly higher in N96ORCA1. This is consistent with the N96ORCA1 NH OSR being 1–2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> greater than in N216ORCA025 (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20790-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0002">2</a>e) and suggests the OSR difference is primarily due to atmospheric (i.e., cloud‐aerosol‐solar radiation) differences between the two models.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20790-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Time series (11‐year running means) of (a) the global planetary albedo at the top of the atmosphere (TOA) and (c) the global surface albedo. Same quantities for either hemisphere shown in (b) and (d). Color coding as in Figure 
     <a rid="jame20790-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20790-fig-0002">2</a>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="JAME-10-2865-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
