<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Since high [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] will favor photosynthetic carbon assimilation and depress photorespiration in plants with the C3 pathway of photosynthesis, it is generally assumed that C3 plants will benefit from increased carbon gain that will translate into increased biomass and yield. Many aspects of plant metabolism, molecular physiology, structure and development are modified by growth under high atmospheric [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>], not least because the assimilation of carbon is tightly linked to primary nitrogen assimilation (Terashima et al. 2015 and articles cited therein). Moreover, increased [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] reduces the density of stomata and also decreases the aperture of the stomatal pores resulting in decreased evapotranspiration (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mansfield et al. 1990</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B129" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vavasseur and Raghavendra 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim et al. 2010</xref>). Stomatal development is also controlled by both [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] and the phytohormone abscisic acid (ABA; 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Woodward 1987</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B139" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Woodward and Kelly 1995</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tanaka et al. 2013</xref>). Several components have been identified in the signaling pathway that reduces stomatal apertures in response to elevated [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] including β-carbonic anhydrases (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hu et al. 2010</xref>), the HT1 protein kinase, the RHC1 MATE transporter and the NtMPK4 protein kinase (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hashimoto et al. 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Marten et al. 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B124" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tian et al. 2015</xref>). The generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) is involved in both high [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>]-induced decreases in stomatal density, requiring the presence of ABA, PYR/RCAR and ABA receptors (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chater et al. 2015</xref>). Despite extensive research efforts over the last 50 years, the complex interplay between metabolic and environmental signals that determine the plant response to high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is far from resolved, particularly at the whole plant level. Much of our current understanding of the responses of crop growth to high atmospheric [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] has come from either studies in free air CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment (FACE) sites or chamber (closed or open-top) experiments. Unfortunately, such studies have not always yielded consistent results. CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment does not necessarily enhance plant growth or yield and differences in the responses of these traits have been reported even within the same species (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ainsworth and Long 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Luo et al. 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Leakey et al. 2009a b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hasegawa et al. 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bishop et al. 2015</xref>). Nevertheless, these studies provide the essential foundation data underpinning crop models, predicting future changes in crop production and their implications for food security.
</p>
