<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Crop models have a central role in informing agro-industry and policymakers about the risks and potential of adaptation strategies to counter climate change, as well as directing plant scientists and breeders towards the required traits in improved varieties and cropping systems’ management practices to mitigate global climate change impacts. Crop model inter-comparison studies have identified large uncertainties and biases (e.g. 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Asseng et al. 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bassu et al. 2014</xref>), and unfortunately they do not often incorporate current knowledge of plant responses to growth under high atmospheric [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Durand et al. 2017</xref>). This review summarizes current crop models and the complexity of analysis, within the context of our current knowledge on the impacts of a high [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] on the C3 crop plant soybean (
 <italic class="italic">Glycine max</italic>), and the C4 crop maize (
 <italic class="italic">Zea mays</italic>), which has an internal CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrating mechanism. Maize and soybean are used to produce a wide range of food and non-food products including pharmaceuticals and biofuels, as well as important sources of livestock feed. Here, we consider the projected impacts of a future high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> world on the global production of maize and soybean. Currently, maize is the most important grain crop and soybean the fourth most important in terms of global production. Since 1960, soybean and maize grain yields increased 7.6 and 2.6 times, respectively. Together, the USA, Brazil and Asia (mainly China and India) account for respectively 92% and 84% of the world soybean and maize production. However, while the land area on which grain legumes, such as soybean, are grown has gradually increased over the past 50 years, this is still only a quarter of that planted to cereals, such as maize (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foyer et al. 2016</xref>). In addition, while increases in cereal production over this period have been predominantly due to increases in yield, driven by the introduction of new varieties and improvements in agronomic practices, increases in grain legume production are due to both increases in land area planted and grain yield (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foyer et al. 2016</xref>). For soybean in particular, grain yields have increased in proportion to the land area planted. Moreover, year-on-year increases in soybean yields are slowing while area planted is increasing, suggesting that more marginal land is being planted.
</p>
