<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Homogeneity in sulfur isotopic compositions of sulfate in the atmosphere</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a> shows the difference in δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values between the two sites by subtracting the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> value of each Dome C sample from that of each DDU sample collected in the closest time period. It is obvious that most of the values do not statistically deviate from 0‰ within the propagated analytical error. Excluding the specifically low δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values at Dome C in November, the residual values exhibit no systematic trend and averaged 0.5 ± 2.6‰. The δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values were thus surprisingly homogeneous between Dome C and DDU throughout the year, ensuring that the isotopic fractionation for δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> during transport towards inland is far smaller than the observed variability ranging from 8.2 to 18.6‰. Moreover, the annual weighted averages of the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values were 15.8 ± 0.5‰ and 17.0 ± 0.4‰ for Dome C and DDU (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>), respectively, which are consistent with the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values of 13.7–16.6‰ observed for surface snow over the transect between Syowa Station and Dome Fuji by Uemura 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. This result indicates that the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> signature is preserved in snow SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> without any significant postdepositional effect.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This result suggests that the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values in the Antarctic atmosphere are not significantly influenced by isotopic fractionation during transport and are therefore controlled by the relative importance of sulfur sources. Fifteen years after advocating the possible change in the signature by isotopic fractionation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, these results bring back the applicability of the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> signature for reconstruction of sulfur sources, i.e., the relative importance of mb-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> and nmb-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span>, through the past climate changes.
 </p>
</sec>
