<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondary sulfate plays an important role in aerosol and cloud interactions and influences solar radiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. In Antarctica, because of isolation from major anthropogenic SO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions over the continents, the main source of non-sea-salt (nss-) SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> is dimethyl sulfide (DMS) produced by marine phytoplankton living in the Southern Ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Therefore, the nss-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> preserved in Antarctic ice cores is used as a record of past marine biogenic activity, and its response and feedback to climate change are debated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been shown that nss-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> flux recorded in Antarctic ice cores has not significantly changed throughout the last eight glacial cycles, which is concluded to indicate a nonsignificant change in marine biogenic activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. However, this conclusion is inconsistent with the implication derived from marine sediment cores that shows lower productivity at latitudes higher than 50°S during the last glacial period than during the current warm period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. To unravel the cause of this paradox, identification of the sulfur sources of those nss-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> preserved in ice cores potentially provides helpful insights. The stable sulfur isotopic composition of nss-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> (δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub>) is a potential tool for quantitative estimates of the relative importance of marine biogenic (mb-) and nonmarine biogenic (nmb-) SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span>. Indeed, the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values in snow and ice in East Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> have provided estimates of 80–90% dominance of mb-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> in nss-SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> for the last several hundred years.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the dependence on its sulfur sources, the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S signature could be modified by isotopic fractionation via oxidation of SO
  <sub>2</sub> to SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span>. Although Alexander 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> observed the δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values in deep ice cores that showed ca. 4‰ lower values during the last glacial period than during the current warm period, they interpreted those δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values to be the result of significant isotopic fractionation through SO
  <sub>2</sub> oxidation, which caused progressive washing out of isotopically heavier SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2− </span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> and transport of the remaining SO
  <sub>2</sub> with low δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values to inland. On the other hand, Uemura 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span> examined remarkably uniform δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> (14–17‰) in surface snow over the transect between Syowa Station (69°00′S, 39°35′E) and Dome F (77°19′S, 39°42′E), concluding the absence of considerable isotopic fractionation during transport under present-day climate. However, surface snow observations are not sufficient to draw firm conclusions on the reasons for this homogeneity, as inhomogeneous snow deposition throughout the year and remobilization of snow by wind mask real atmospheric spatial and temporal variations. It is thus necessary to observe the differences in this signature between inland and coastal sites before the deposition of SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span>, i.e., for SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> in atmospheric aerosol samples, to clarify the mechanisms that cause constant flux throughout the ice ages.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address the above discussion, we performed a year-round observation of δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values of atmospheric SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> at Dome C (75°06′S, 123°12′E; 3233 m a.s.l.) and Dumont d’Urville Station (DDU) (66°40′S, 140°01′E; 40 m a.s.l.), inland and coastal sites in East Antarctica, respectively, by utilizing continuous aerosol samples at those sites. Furthermore, we utilized δ
  <span class="sup">34</span>S
  <sub>nss</sub> values to estimate changes in sulfur sources in both the present and the past Antarctic atmosphere to infer the major nonmarine sulfur sources that remain to be identified.
 </p>
</sec>
