<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Despite substantial research over the past few decades, soil moisture‐precipitation (hereafter SMP) feedbacks remain among the most uncertain processes in the field of land‐atmospheric interactions (Santanello et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Seneviratne et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Soil moisture influence on precipitation at seasonal to interannual scales has been investigated with the concept of moisture recycling (Dirmeyer et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Eltahir &amp; Bras, 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>; van der Ent et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), here referred to as direct SMP feedback. There has also been an increasing attention toward understanding indirect SMP feedback at subdaily to daily scales, which is also the focus of our study. Indirect SMP feedback can be narrowed down to the influence of soil moisture condition on boundary layer characteristics and convective initiation. Several studies have investigated such local effects of soil moisture using two main types of approaches. Some focused on the temporal effect of soil moisture on rainfall based on one‐dimensional frameworks, which can yield both positive and negative effects (Alfieri et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Duerinck et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Findell &amp; Eltahir, 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Gentine et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Guillod et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). A positive temporal feedback appears when the increase of moisture is more critical for the cloud formation and precipitation, often under low stability in the free troposphere. A negative temporal feedback usually appears under a strong stability barrier at the top of planetary boundary layer, which requires larger sensible heat to allow sufficient turbulent mixing (Hohenegger et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Another line of research considers spatial soil moisture gradients (C. M. Taylor &amp; Lebel, 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>) whereby locally drier soils induce a mesoscale atmospheric circulation such that increased convergence over the drier region, which leads to convection (C. M. Taylor et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Conceptually, temporal and spatial feedbacks may interact: Rainfall may produce spatial heterogeneities in soil moisture that subsequently lead to further rainfall events over the drier regions, thereby increasing precipitation occurrence over a wider area (Guillod et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; H. Hsu et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
