<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are numerous direct and indirect impacts reported on crop production due to the overall impacts of climatic attenuations. The yield of crops, particularly in rainfed conditions, depends on the climate to a larger extent. Global warming may adversely affect the biodiversity and exacerbate the desertification due to an increase in evapotranspiration and a likely decrease in rainfall in dry lands (although it may increase globally) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. The direct impacts will have implications for the morphology, the physiology, and the phenology of a plant. Increased temperatures will have profound effects on crop development. Higher temperature exposure beyond the threshold level will eventually affect the quality and the quantity of yields of desirable crops, while weeds infest the areas and pests proliferate [
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The impacts depend on the relative warming at different growth stages: seed germination, seedling emergence, leaf production, leaf expansion, leaf area duration, flower initiation, flower development, pollination, ripening, maturity, vernalization, and dormancy. Varying precipitation patterns augment the likelihood of short-run crop failures and long-run production declines [
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The strong negative impacts of warming that limit plant growth, metabolism, and productivity worldwide have been reported by various researchers [
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Detailed evidence of significant impacts on the biophysical changes and socio-economic stresses have also been noted by many scientists around the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0180706.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>].
</p>
