<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">This is a timely article that deals with an aspect of climate change that is rarely discussed in a realistic sense, namely carbon capture by bio-engineering plants. In general, previous discussions have focused on the relative impractical nature of employing carbon-capture technologies on a scale sufficiently large to have any significant impact on the amounts of CO2 and methane in the atmosphere. Using back-of-the-envelope calculations DeLisi attempts to show that biological carbon capture could be a practical solution to mitigating CO2 build-up. I am not equipped to deal fully with the math, which should be left to someone more familiar with the practical aspects of plant metabolism. However, the important take-home message from my perspective is that this is an area worth a much fuller exploration. Trees are probably not the ideal example as most of the trees in the world are in forests that could not easily be manipulated or are sufficiently slow growing that it would take decades for them to reach a point where thy might have a significant impact. However, 
 <italic>agricultural crops grown for food</italic> production might be a better short-term target. 
 <italic>First, many are already understood genetically sufficiently well that further modification might be relatively straightforward</italic>. They are grown in vast amounts and while converting CO2 to carbonate may not be the ideal way of storing the captured carbon other final products such as carbohydrates might be feasible. Second, they are probably a better choice that most trees because 
 <italic>much research would likely be needed to produce trees with the desired properties.</italic> Time would be a big issue as typically tree geneticists start their work but have retired and relied on first- or second-generation students to explore the results of their genetic studies. 
 <italic>With highly polyploid chromosomes manipulating their genomes can be very tricky</italic>. Nevertheless, despite the criticisms above, this is a very useful article that with a small amount of rewriting to mention the practical details of tree biology and introducing 
 <italic>the idea that other species some of which might be food plants might offer more practical advantages</italic>, might have some impact. In light of the current situation as many ideas as possible need to be aired and tested. We have precious little time left to try and resolve the crises that will arise if climate change continues unabated. The last paragraph is particularly timely. 
 <italic>A couple of small points: 1.</italic> Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 <italic>. This is a nice figure, but the numbers are a little difficult to read. 2. P3, line 18. Should read “a net difference of” 3.</italic> Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>
 <italic>. The colors are a little difficult to distinguish</italic>. Perhaps, two of the lines could be dotted for clarity.
</p>
