<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Identifying and tracking environmental disturbance is important and can inform on both direct human induced (e.g., pollutants) and climate change stressors. Since bacterial communities are capable of a rapid growth (doubling time up to 3 h in the present study) and can be readily influenced by changes to their environment, they could potentially represent interesting candidates as indicators of environmental disturbance. A number of OTUs that were relatively rare members of the natural bacterial assemblage became more abundant after the environmental disturbance induced by tDOM addition. Such proliferations of rare bacteria in response to environmental disturbance (e.g., tDOM, or pollutants) have been previously noted (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Atlas et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Campbell et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lindh et al., 2015</xref>). In our study, we also identified some OTUs which were only detected when tDOM was added, indicating that they were most likely bacteria specifically coming from the soil extract, and have the possibility to be incorporated into the marine community, as seen in previous studies (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Traving et al., 2017</xref>). These bacteria were found in the soil extract (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM11" class="xref">S4</xref>), and were recorded throughout the experiment in tDOM addition mesocosms. It should, however, be noted that the repeated addition of 1 μm-filtered fresh seawater (re-fill water) could have had a potential impact on the results, particularly the temporal development during the experiment. In the present study the technical constraints meant that some bacteria were regularly added to the system. Nevertheless, the additions of re-fill water to the mesocosm volume of 946 L of seawater resulted in a dilution factor of ∼50:1, and the fresh seawater was added to all mesocosms providing a normalizing effect across the treatments.
</p>
