<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">We analyse daily output of the CMIP5
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup> for: 27 historical simulations (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>), 18 RCP4.5/8.5 projections and ten +4 K sea-surface temperature (SST) and 4 × CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> atmosphere-only (AMIP) simulations. The historical simulations cover the period 1850–2000; the forcings are consistent with observations and include changes in: atmospheric composition due to anthropogenic and volcanic influences, solar forcing, emissions or concentrations of short-lived species and natural and anthropogenic aerosols or their precursors, as well as land use. RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 projections are projections of future climates (2006–2100) forced by two representative concentration pathway (RCP) scenarios. These result in a radiative forcing of 4.5 and 8.5 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>, respectively, in year 2100, relative to pre-industrial conditions. AMIP simulations cover the 1979–2005 period and are performed by prescribing SSTs and sea ice boundary conditions to an atmosphere-only model. +4 K simulations impose a uniform 4 K warming to observed SSTs, while the 4 × CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> simulations impose quadrupled atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations relative to the pre-industrial control value of 280 ppm. We additionally analyse a 32-member ensemble of simulations from the CESM
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup>. This covers the 1950–2100 period, and follows an RCP8.5 scenario starting from 2006. As the historical part of the simulations is much shorter than for the other datasets, we analyse 
 <italic class="italic">d</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">θ</italic> trends over the whole CESM period as opposed to performing separate analyses for historical and future trends.
</p>
