<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The same five treatments were applied to the incubation experiments as were used in the field: control (water only), 5, 15, 30 and 90 g/L of glucose. In total, the three sites along the urban to rural transect included five treatments and five field replicates for a total of seventy-five samples. For the N addition plots at Heshan station, there were five glucose treatments, three N levels, and three replicates (one for each plot) for a total of forty-five samples. For each replicate, 50 g of soil was placed in a 200 ml Erlenmeyer flask with a vented rubber stopper. The glucose solutions (and water in the case of the control) were used to bring the soils to 40% WHC, and then they were incubated at 25 °C for 24 hours. After the incubation period, soil respiration was measured with an infrared gas analyzer (LI-6262 Licor Biosciences) at 13, 19, 25, and 31 °C. Fluxes were calculated from the linear portion of the curve generally between 30 and 90 seconds after the jar was sealed, and adjusted for chamber volume, soil weight and chamber temperature. The CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> flux measurements were then fit to the Michaelis-Menten model with nonlinear least squares regression to determine V
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> and kM using Matlab (2015b). Temperature sensitivity (Q10) was determined by the following equation:
 <disp-formula id="Equ2" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">2</label>
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <tex-math id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$Q10=R2/R1{}^{\tfrac{10}{{T}_{2}-{T}_{1}},}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M4" display="block" class="math">
    <mi class="mi">Q</mi>
    <mn class="mn">10</mn>
    <mo class="mo">=</mo>
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">2</mn>
    </mrow>
    <mo class="mo">/</mo>
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">1</mn>
    </mrow>
    <msup class="msup">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mspace width=".1em" class="mspace"/>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mstyle displaystyle="false" class="mstyle">
       <mfrac class="mfrac">
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mn class="mn">10</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <msub class="msub">
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mi class="mi">T</mi>
          </mrow>
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mn class="mn">2</mn>
          </mrow>
         </msub>
         <mo class="mo">−</mo>
         <msub class="msub">
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mi class="mi">T</mi>
          </mrow>
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mn class="mn">1</mn>
          </mrow>
         </msub>
        </mrow>
       </mfrac>
       <mi class="mi">,</mi>
      </mstyle>
     </mrow>
    </msup>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_1941_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>where R1 and R2 are soil respiration parameters (R
 <sub class="sub">soil</sub>, V
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> or kM where applicable) measured at temperatures T1 and T2, respectively.
</p>
