<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The experiment was set up according to a block design comprising 24 blocks (tables) with six replicates per rainfall treatment, each containing nine plants of which two were not exposed to herbivory (control) and seven were exposed to one of the two herbivore species. On each of three plants, 10 early L2 larvae of 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> were introduced (L1 larvae of 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> are difficult to handle as they are mining in the leaves), and on each of four plants, 10 early L1 larvae of 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> were introduced. The 216 plants in total were randomly allocated to blocks and treatments within blocks. The insect herbivores were allowed to move and feed freely on the plants. Plants were not touching preventing dispersal of insects to adjacent plants. When caterpillars of 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> reached the third instar, their numbers were reduced to three per plant to ensure sufficient resources for caterpillar development. When larvae reached their final instar (fifth for 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> and fourth for 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic>), plants with the same herbivore species within blocks were placed together in a netted cage (40 × 40 × 60 cm; Vermandel, Hulst, The Netherlands). At this point, exposure to downpours ended. This was done at day 7 on plants with 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> and at day 14 on plants with 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> after phase 2 had started. Pupae of 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> and 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> were collected per cage and transferred to Petri dishes. Development time until eclosion and offspring sex were recorded. Newly emerged adults were frozen immediately and weighed individually on a Mettler‐Toledo (Columbus, Ohio, USA) microbalance. The number of caterpillars that survived to the pupal (
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic>) and the adult stage (
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic>) was counted. Development time from L1 (
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic>) or L2 (
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic>) to adult eclosion was recorded in days.
</p>
