<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Study Area and Data Processing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anhui Province, an inland province in Southeast China (114.54°–119.37° E, 29.41°–34.38° N), was selected as the case study area for the application of the relative sensitivity indicator. Anhui Province has a high incidence of many infectious diseases, and encompasses different climates because it locates across the basins of the Yangtze and Huai Rivers (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-00767-f003" href="#ijerph-12-00767-f003">Figure 3</a>). The northern part of the province is part of the North China Plain, which is more temperate and with more clear-cut seasons. In contrast, the southern part is warmer and has more rainfall. In terms of administrative districts, Anhui Province is composed of 17 cities and 61 counties (hereafter all administration units are referred to as counties).
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-00767-f003" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Location of the study area and its sub-areas.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-00767-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both the infectious diseases data and climate data at the county level were collected. Monthly cases of thirteen infectious diseases at the county level from 2004 to 2010 in Anhui Province were collected from an Internet-based infectious disease reporting system coordinated by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (China CDC). The system provides a standardized platform for data collection throughout the entire nation, and ensures data quality and reliability much better than before. In Anhui Province, the infectious diseases include: dysentery, hand, foot and mouth disease (HFM), hepatitis A, hemorrhagic fever, typhoid fever, malaria, meningitis, influenza, schistosomiasis, Japanese encephalitis, avian influenza, leptospirosis and cholera. Months without reported incidences of a disease were excluded. The monthly incidence of each disease was calculated by dividing monthly cases through the corresponding population for each county except for HFM. For this illness, we divided the monthly cases by the number of children younger than 9 years old (0, 9) because of the special population that suffers from this disease [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-00767">22</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also collected monthly data concerning climate variables for each county at a spatial resolution of 5 km. The dataset was generated based on field observation, remotely sensed data and reanalysis data from the Land Surface Model over the Chinese mainland (which dates from 1960 to 2010) [
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-00767" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-00767">23</a>]. In the study, three climate variables for the study periods were considered; monthly average temperature (MAT), monthly accumulated precipitation (MAP), and monthly average absolute humidity (MAAH). Moreover, county-level historical mean values (
  <span class="italic">HC
   <sub>i</sub>
   <span class="sup">mean</span>
  </span>) and the standard deviation (
  <span class="italic">HC
   <sub>i</sub>
   <span class="sup">std</span>
  </span>) of the three climate variables from 1973 to 2003 (30 years) were also calculated for identifying the exposure and non-exposure groups. Considering the statistical requirements of the linear regression method and the hypothesis test, only counties with at least 20 months of data concerning infectious disease, of which more than 5 and 7 months are in exposure and non-exposure groups, respectively, were regarded as the effective counties to be analyzed. The calculations were carried out using MATLAB 7.10.0 (R2010a).
 </p>
</sec>
