<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change and its impact on food security are additional strains on the agriculture sector in Africa. The last Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) highlighted that: “warming of the climate system is unequivocal, and since the 1950s, many of the observed changes are unprecedented over decades to millennia. The atmosphere and ocean have warmed, the amounts of snow and ice have diminished, and sea level has risen. Changes in many extreme weather and climate events have been observed since about 1950. Recent climate changes have had widespread impacts on human and natural systems.” Moreover, “continued emission of greenhouse gases will cause further warming and long-lasting changes in all components of the climate system, increasing the likelihood of severe, pervasive and irreversible impacts for people and ecosystems.” In this context, crop productivity, which is directly tied to climate variability, appears particularly exposed to current and future climate change impacts. Indeed, “many studies covering a wide range of regions and crops show that negative impacts of climate change on crop yields have been more common than positive impacts.” Moreover, “rural areas are expected to experience major impacts,” and “all aspects of food security are potentially affected by climate change, including food production, access, use, and price stability.” At the turn of the twenty-first century, West Africa has been identified among the primary observed climate change hot-spots, and among the most persistent and early emerging prominent hot-spots foreseen for the twenty-first century, because of the observed and projected widespread increase in mean temperature and extreme hot-season occurrence (Turco et al., 
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Given the particularly strong deep connection between crop production and climate variability in West Africa since agriculture is mostly rain-fed and crop management (use of fertilizers and pesticides combined with modern cultivars) remains low (Dingkuhn et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>), the detected sensitivity to recent and future climate change makes the region a hotspot even in terms of food production and security.
</p>
