<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What are the advantages and shortcomings of MOOCs in climate change and health education?</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, there was no a priori goal of enrolment for the three MOOCs, except that the MOOC-PM was targeted to reach policy makers in particular. The MOOC-AFR was aimed at people from or working in francophone West Africa. The reach with over 7000 registered students (for more details, see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]) was more than overwhelming - which was accompanied with a certain anxiety on how to handle the number of participant requests - which turned out fine in the end as the majority of interaction was based on peer-to-peer communication and peer support between participants. In an evaluation that we conducted (for more details, see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]), we have found that the three MOOCs have reached people from diverse educational and geographical backgrounds, such as researchers and implementers in the field, decision-makers, and citizens from low-resource environments who are most vulnerable to climate change effects on health. Notably, the MOOC-AFR sparked high interest from African countries with many participants from low-resource countries, as compared to the other two MOOCs [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. The focus of the MOOC-AFR was on the local environmental and socioeconomic context of Burkina Faso, and respective mitigation and adaptation strategies.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This African focus on the MOOC content was potentially an enabling factor to the high number of participants from low-resource countries - which is striking considering the constraints low-resource countries are faced with, such as low broadband penetration and comparatively high costs for Internet access through mobile data networks, as compared to average monthly income levels. Furthermore, the scarcity of courses on climate change and health especially with a focus on low-resource countries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11﻿</a>] may have also been an enabling factor.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, a gaping lack remains, regarding what the participants really learned from the respective MOOCs, especially of those who stopped the online courses early. The chain of evidence from the participation in the MOOC to the translation into real change and impact is difficult to uncover. Yet, this should not be a discouraging argument as developing new face-to-face curricula takes time and reaches only a few minds, particularly in the Global North. More studies are needed to ascertain the long-term effects and real penetration of knowledge gained by MOOC participants, as well as how to measure the effectiveness of a MOOC. As learners are global and have a diverse range of a priori knowledge and skills, many students may not be interested in completing a MOOC. Depending on the participants objective for taking part in the MOOC, some may rather specifically pick MOOC sections, as they see fit and need for themselves. A reason may be that the diversity of the learners may not follow traditional learning trajectories, that is reflected in evaluation measures such as course completion. This leads also to another question: How to best cater to such different learner types? One answer may be adaptive learning which allows adapting content to different learner types based on answers given throughout course quizzes or other student-based feedback, for example. However, each adaptive learning path has to be specifically developed which may require a certain time-investment from MOOC creators. A mean to ensure that participants have covered the course objectives may be via examination, such as officially verified exams, called proctored exams. Offering such exams for MOOCs, again, require financial and personnel resources. Insights on the effectiveness and benefits of adaptive learning also remain limited, as only few MOOCs have adopted this method. Evaluation of learning and acquiring knowledge and skills via MOOCs is complex and more research is needed to understand strengths and weaknesses of MOOCs to further guide best practices.</p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MOOCs shift access to education from a centralized and local, to a decentralized and global realm. The translation from a face-to-face course into a MOOC that typically consists of a collection of averagely 8-min long videos framed by exercises and collaborative activities involves time and effort. Some MOOC-platforms schedule about 1 year from the planning of a MOOC from scratch to the actual realization of the MOOC. Our MOOCs were developed in a shorter time frame as the face-to-face courses served as the base for the MOOC outline and contents, but the translation into a MOOC-format still involved considerable time and effort.</p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MOOCs offer a variety of formats such as teacher-centered videos (the case for our MOOCs), interview-based videos or micro-teaching – learning sessions that comprise only a few minutes each - that may be especially adequate for knowledge and skills transfer in a working environment where time is more constrained but still allows for short MOOC sessions. Another possibility that we explored was to blend MOOCs with face-to-face courses. To this end, participants from MOOCs were invited to one of our previously run presence courses. Within the face-to-face course we interwove video segments of the MOOC to transfer theory-based contents which were followed up by group work and other in-group activities to strengthen this knowledge. Informal feedback that we received of this blend of face-to-face with MOOC elements was quite positive by course participants and thus may constitute a potential cross-utilization of MOOCs for presence-courses, for example, to incorporate MOOCs as a fruitful add-on for Ph.D. programs. But again, more research would be needed in this area, also with regards to what constitutes a beneficial blend of MOOC segments and face-to-face interactions.</p>
</sec>
