<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">The present study investigates distribution changes of dominant 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> vectors of human malaria in the greater European area for the 21st century under climate change. It builds on previous work of Sinka et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>] and Kuhn et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>] who modelled the current distribution of dominant 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> vectors in Europe using environmental and climatic variables. Variables in these studies included i.a. monthly temperature and precipitation values, elevation, and land cover classes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. The focus of the present study is to assess future vector distribution changes due to climate change using state-of-the art RCM simulations. As in Sinka et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>] Boosted Regression Trees (BRTs, [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]) are applied to relate climate variables and land-cover classes to vector occurrences. Bias-corrected temperature and precipitation from two different GCM-RCM setups under two emission scenarios are used to assess regional climate suitability of 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> vectors in Europe and the Mediterranean area under future climate change. Only changes of the climatic influences on the vector distribution are considered in the regional projections, since environmental effects such as land use changes are currently not implemented in the standard RCM generation. Finally, potential malaria transmission stability during the 21st century is assessed, which builds on the vector stability index of [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>].
</p>
