<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The issues of climate change and its impact on food security are increasingly recognised in different parts of the world, including Africa. Africa is epitomised as the most vulnerable continent to climate changes (Bwalya 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Other studies also project that Africa is highly vulnerable to climate changes (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [IPCC] 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Liliana 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Vogel 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; World Bank 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). The studies mainly found that climate changes have a severe impact on agricultural land, which ultimately affects food security. The IPCC (
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>) reports that in sub-Saharan Africa, agricultural productivity will decline from 21% to 9% by 2080. Liliana (
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>) indicates that about two-thirds of Africa’s arable land is expected to be lost by 2025 because of the lack of rainfall and drought. South Africa is not immune to these impacts. It is worth noting that global population is continuing to rise and the rates at which climate change and production of agriculture and food have been increasing are not equal. The World Food Programme (WFP 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>) report shows that crop production yield per hectare is, on average, increasing at a rate below that of global populations, implying that food production, which has been unable to meet global demand, will struggle to do so in the immediate future, leaving millions of people and numerous countries facing the stark reality of having reduced food security. Against this backdrop, the article seeks to examine the impact of climate change on food security in South Africa. The need to conduct the current article is further accentuated by the recent occurrence of drought and the lack of rainfall that affected South Africa in 2016.
</p>
