<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the MDB has relatively few native freshwater fish species, those present represent a diversity of size, form and life history requirements [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. We selected a set of morphological, behavioral, trophic and reproductive traits aimed at identifying the complementary functional aspects of the fish assemblage niche. The functional traits used were: (i) Maximum temperature in the warmest month within the range of species occurrence (TMAX), (ii) minimum temperature in the coldest month within the range of species occurrence (TMIN), maximum total body length (MAXL), (iii) vertical position in water column (benthic–VPBEN; non-benthic–VPNBEN), (iv) longevity (LONG), (v) age at maturation (AGEMAT), (vi) movement classification: non-movement–NON MOV; potamodromy–POTAMO (fishes that migrate between different sites in freshwater); amphidromy–AMPHID (fishes that regularly migrate between freshwater and the sea, in both directions, but not for the purpose to breeding); catadromy–CATAD, (freshwater fishes that migrate to the sea for the purpose of breeding), (vii) parental care (PARC), (viii) total fecundity (TFEC), (ix) egg size (EGGS), (x) trophic guild (herbivorous-detritivorous–HERB-DET; omnivorous–OMNI; invertivorous–INV; invertivorous-piscivorous–INV-PISC). A brief description of each functional trait can be found in Table C in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0225128.s001">S1 File</xref>. Trait assignments were based on a number of sources, including species accounts in comprehensive texts (i.e. [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]), species descriptions from the primary literature, state agency reports, university reports, graduate theses, and electronic databases available on the World Wide Web (e.g. FishBase). All trait information was assigned based on a majority of evidence rule, with preference given to adult female measurements where possible (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]) for more details on trait assignments).
</p>
