<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5359591</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep44860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep44860</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Optimum soil frost depth to alleviate climate change effects in cold region agriculture</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>Yosuke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Yukiyoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n2">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>Tomoyoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Hokkaido Agricultural Research Center, NARO</institution>, Memuro, Hokkaido, 082-0081, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Hokkaido Agricultural Research Center, NARO</institution>, Sapporo, Hokkaido 062-8555, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>hirota@affrc.go.jp</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p>Present address: Office of Strategic Management, Headquarters, National Agricultural and Food Research Organization (NARO), Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8517, Japan.</p></fn><fn id="n2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Present address: Institute for Rural Engineering, NARO, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8609, Japan.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>03</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>44860</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>02</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>On-farm soil frost control has been used for the management of volunteer potatoes (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.), a serious weed problem caused by climate change, in northern Japan. Deep soil frost penetration is necessary for the effective eradication of unharvested small potato tubers; however, this process can delay soil thaw and increase soil wetting in spring, thereby delaying agricultural activity initiation and increasing nitrous oxide emissions from soil. Conversely, shallow soil frost development helps over-wintering of unharvested potato tubers and nitrate leaching from surface soil owing to the periodic infiltration of snowmelt water. In this study, we synthesised on-farm snow cover manipulation experiments to determine the optimum soil frost depth that can eradicate unharvested potato tubers without affecting agricultural activity initiation while minimising N pollution from agricultural soil. The optimum soil frost depth was estimated to be 0.28&#x02013;0.33&#x02009;m on the basis of the annual maximum soil frost depth. Soil frost control is a promising practice to alleviate climate change effects on agriculture in cold regions, which was initiated by local farmers and further promoted by national and local research institutes.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Anthropogenic climate change has become a major societal concern, and knowledge about effective adaptations to climate change are gradually accumulating in public and private sectors in agriculture worldwide<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>. For example, in the Tokachi region, the largest potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) production area in Japan, soil frost depth has decreased since the late 1980s because of climate change<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. Shallow soil frost development was found to facilitate the overwintering of unharvested small potato tubers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Therefore, volunteer potatoes have become a serious weed problem in the local rotation cropping system and in seed production<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. To overcome this problem, local farmers in the Tokachi region began to remove snow cover during winter by using agricultural machineries such as tractors and bulldozers to enhance the freeze-kill of potato tubers. However, the lack of knowledge and experience occasionally hindered the control of the depth of soil frost penetration<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Subsequently, a national research institute in collaboration with some local research institutes developed a web-based decision support system that assisted in controlling the annual maximum soil frost depth (D<sub>max</sub>). This system involves (1) real-time visualisation of the daily predicted soil frost depth by using a mathematical model to determine soil temperature at an arbitrary depth under the snow cover<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref> and (2) an alerting service suggesting the recommended timing for conducting snow cover manipulation at each field. This system suggested that, for soil frost control, the D<sub>max</sub> should range from 0.3 to 0.4&#x02009;m in order to ensure the eradication of potatoes with minimised labour, cost, and risk in agriculture (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Thus, controlling soil frost depth by using a scientifically sound method has enabled the management of volunteer potatoes over an area of several tens of hectares per farming household without requiring agrochemicals or heavy labour in summer<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. At present, volunteer potato management by using the soil frost control method has become common among the farmers in and around the Tokachi region, eastern Hokkaido, northern Japan.</p><p>In addition to volunteer potato management, soil frost control is thought to have multiple effects on agriculture in cold regions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>. For centuries, soil frost has been considered to have adverse effects on agriculture, such as soil erosion during the snow-melting period<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref> and delays in the initiation of agricultural activity because of the excessive wetting of soil in the early spring. Recently, there are concerns of temporarily large emissions of a greenhouse gas (nitrous oxide) immediately after snowmelt during soil thaw<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>. In addition, snowmelt water is known to immediately infiltrate the soil when the soil frost depth becomes shallow<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, leading to an increased risk of water pollution by the leaching of residual nitrate in the surface soil<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. These events caused by climate change suggest that a new optimum soil frost depth needs to be determined to avoid the negative effects on local agriculture and environment. In this study, we analysed the results obtained during field studies conducted in the Tokachi region to estimate an optimum soil frost depth. The suppression of volunteer potatoes was considered as the intended positive effect of the soil frost control, whereas smaller ratio of snowmelt water infiltration and increased nitrate loss from the surface soil were considered as the adverse effects. Because the majority (52%) of global potato production area is located between 44&#x000b0;N to 58&#x000b0;N<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref> and the Tokachi region is located around the southern boundary of the zone, our findings might help overcome the volunteer potato problem in the potato-producing cold regions, while avoiding the negative consequences.</p><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><p>The mean number of potato sprouts in spring (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>; sprouts ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) at the field plot (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S1</xref>) was modelled by considering the number of potato tubers remaining after harvest in autumn (<italic>Unharvested</italic>; tubers ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and the D<sub>max</sub> (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>; m) as follows:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq1"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e210" xlink:href="srep44860-m1.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>The ratio of volunteer potato emergence defined as <inline-formula id="d32e213"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e214" xlink:href="srep44860-m2.jpg"/></inline-formula> changed 0.24 times (=exp (&#x02212;14.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.1)) by every 0.10&#x02009;m increase in the <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Indeed, the emergence ratios of volunteer potatoes at the <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> of 0.20, 0.25, 0.30, and 0.35&#x02009;m were 0.04, 0.02, 0.01, and&#x02009;&#x0003c;0.01, respectively. These results indicated that the current soil frost depth used (0.3&#x02013;0.4&#x02009;m) declines the emergence ratio to an unrecognisable level (&#x0003c;0.01).</p><p>The mean ratio (<italic>q</italic>; dimensionless) of snowmelt infiltration (<italic>Inf</italic>; mm) to the total amount of snowmelt water (<italic>SnowMelt</italic>; mm) at the experimental plot (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) was modelled by considering the D<sub>max</sub> (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>; m):</p><p><disp-formula id="eq3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e254" xlink:href="srep44860-m3.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>The mean infiltration ratios of snowmelt water to soil at the <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> of 0.10, 0.20, 0.30, 0.40, and 0.50&#x02009;m were 0.95, 0.80, 0.48, 0.16, and 0.04, respectively, indicating a remarkable decline between 0.20 and 0.40&#x02009;m of <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>). The <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> causing half of the infiltration ratio was around 0.29 to 0.30&#x02009;m.</p><p>Nitrate retention to the surface soil because of deep soil frost development is expected to have similar dependency on the infiltration ratio of snowmelt water since it is highly soluble in water and would be transported in the soil solution. However, we found a remarkably different relationship<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2c</xref>). The mean nitrate content in the surface (0&#x02013;0.4-m deep) soil after snowmelt (<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>; kg N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was modelled by considering the D<sub>max</sub> (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>; m) and nitrate content in the surface soil before snowfall (<italic>AutumnN</italic>; kg N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) at the experimental plot (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>) as follows:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e308" xlink:href="srep44860-m4.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>The nitrate retention ratio defined as <inline-formula id="d32e311"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e312" xlink:href="srep44860-m5.jpg"/></inline-formula> changed 1.45 times (&#x02009;=&#x02009;exp (3.7&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.1)) by every 0.10&#x02009;m increase in <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>. Indeed, the mean (with 95% confidence interval) nitrate retention ratios at the <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> of 0.10, 0.20, 0.30, 0.40, and 0.50&#x02009;m were 0.15 (0.08&#x02013;0.23), 0.22 (0.13&#x02013;0.31), 0.32 (0.19&#x02013;0.44), 0.47 (0.24&#x02013;0.69), and 0.67 (0.26&#x02013;1.09), respectively. The <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> that caused half retention of nitrate at the surface soil was estimated to be 0.42 and deeper than 0.32&#x02009;m when considering the mean and 95% confidence interval, respectively. This high uncertainty of soil nitrate retention ratio likely reflects the large spatial variability of the amount of snowmelt infiltration depending on the microtopography of the ground surface. In addition, measured and modelled nitrate retention ratio of over 1.0 can suggest the presence of nitrate discharge. Nitrification can be thought to occur after snowmelt where deep soil frost development easily releases decomposable organic matter such as cellular components of microbes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>, because soil freezing does not significantly damage nitrifiers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. The measured soil nitrate profiles before snowfall and after snowmelt, as well as the time series of daily mean air temperature, snow cover thickness, and soil frost depth, are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>Considering the results of parameterisation on snow cover manipulation experiments as shown above and those obtained by agricultural/environmental implications, the optimum range of soil frost depth was suggested to be 0.28&#x02013;0.33&#x02009;m of D<sub>max</sub> as follows (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>). The shallow limit of the optimum D<sub>max</sub> (0.28&#x02009;m) was relatively easy to determine by considering that it allowed the effective management of the emergence ratio of volunteer potatoes at around 0.01 or less. In this case, the infiltration ratio of snowmelt water was 0.53 and the nitrate retention ratio was 0.42. Conversely, another limit of optimum D<sub>max</sub> (0.33&#x02009;m) was difficult to determine reasonably because the nitrate retention ratio had large uncertainty in response to the D<sub>max</sub>. In addition, no exact thresholds were available to avoid flooding snowmelt water, soil erosion, and delaying agricultural activity initiation in response to the D<sub>max</sub>. Therefore, in the present study, we proposed the D<sub>max</sub> limit to be simply the intersection point, i.e. 0.33&#x02009;m (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>), indicating that the D<sub>max</sub> balanced these two factors to avoid notable nitrate leaching. In this case, the infiltration ratio of snowmelt water was 0.35 and the nitrate retention was 0.51. Thus, we tentatively but quantitatively suggested the optimum range of the D<sub>max</sub> as 0.28&#x02013;0.33&#x02009;m based on these considerations to eradicate volunteer potato emergence while managing nitrate leaching and snow-melt water infiltration. Further implications of the optimum D<sub>max</sub> are discussed in the following section.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>The proposed range of optimum D<sub>max</sub> (0.28&#x02013;0.33&#x02009;m) was relatively narrower and shallower than the previously proposed value (0.3&#x02013;0.4&#x02009;m)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref> owing to the additional considerations to the possible adverse effects of deep soil frost penetration on agriculture and environment. Higher nitrate retention ratio by deeper soil frost penetration can be an interesting trend, because soil frost control to manage volunteer potatoes could also allow the alleviation of groundwater pollution by nitrate. However, the D<sub>max</sub> shallower than 0.35&#x02009;m might be preferable to not enlarge the risk in temporarily increasing greenhouse gas (nitrous oxide) emissions from soil immediately after soil thaw<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). Furthermore, importantly, the proposed D<sub>max</sub> range was determined by our field data, which were mainly obtained at Andisol fields. Because Andisol is characterised by high permeability, the range of D<sub>max</sub> might be similar to those in other fields having, for example, sandy soil. In contrast, soils having lower permeability might show smaller infiltration ratio of snowmelt water to soil even though the D<sub>max</sub> is considerably shallower. The smaller infiltration ratio of snowmelt water to soil can allow higher retention ratio of nitrate at the surface soil layer. Therefore, the deeper limit of the optimum D<sub>max</sub> might be less than 0.33&#x02009;m as determined in our study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>) in the case of soils having lower water permeability. In other words, our proposed optimum D<sub>max</sub> might be applicable as a reference to achieve volunteer potato control with minimised adverse effects on the soil frost control for different soil types. If the D<sub>max</sub> of 0.28&#x02009;m is very deep for the fields to infiltrate surface-flooding snowmelt water, the target D<sub>max</sub> should be modified based on the allowable level of volunteer potato emergence for individual farmers. Thus, maintaining the D<sub>max</sub> within the optimum range might allow adaptation to and mitigation of climate change effects. For the extended application of soil frost control as the mitigation measure for climate change, further studies are needed to establish the relationships between seasonal dynamics of greenhouse gas (nitrous oxide) emission and soil management<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>.</p><p>The management of volunteer potatoes by using the soil frost control method is a promising strategy to adapt to climate change, which was initiated by some local farmers and supported by national and local research institutes, and it has become widely accepted by many local farmers and researchers. Soil freezing is known to be largely suppressed by thick snow cover, i.e. the D<sub>max</sub> can be estimated using the freezing index (the summation of daily mean air temperatures for days with temperature of below 0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until the snow cover thickness becomes 0.20&#x02009;m or more)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. Therefore, our on-farm soil frost control might likely be applicable in regions where air temperature drops sufficiently (mean air temperature, &#x02212;12 to &#x02212;5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C during December to February) and the continuous snow cover appears early in winter when the mean precipitation reaches 50 to 150&#x02009;mm during December to January<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Since the principle of soil frost control is to simply offset the heat-insulating effect of thick snow cover in order to expose soil surface to cold air, it can be easily performed over a large area of several tens of hectares by using common agricultural machineries by individual local farmers in a less time-consuming and labour-saving manner<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. That is, the effectiveness of the soil frost control method has certain limitations depending on the magnitude and rate of climate change<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. As mentioned above, if cold winter is accompanied by extremely short snowfall, the ambient D<sub>max</sub> would be greater than 0.33&#x02009;m; deep soil frost development would have adverse effects, because soil frost depth cannot be controlled without snowpack. In contrast, in the case of warm winter, soil freezing would be limited, and hence would not be sufficient to achieve the control of volunteer potatoes. However, the climate change scenarios for the Tokachi region<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>, i.e. mean air temperature in winter changes from current (&#x02212;8&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) to the late 21<sup>st</sup> century (2081&#x02013;2100; &#x02212;5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C), suggest that the D<sub>max</sub> of around 0.3&#x02009;m can be achieved<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. Therefore, the optimum D<sub>max</sub> determined in the present study could contribute to the improvement and provision of more options to perform multiple and immediate adaptation actions over different regions and times in potato-harvested bare fields. In addition to bare fields, the soil frost control method and concept of optimum D<sub>max</sub> can be applied for the overwintering condition such as fields cultivated with winter wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. Furthermore, the soil frost control method can be utilised to prevent ground water pollution by facilitating soil nitrate remaining on the surface layer<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref> regardless of whether the fields were cultivated with potato or not. Scientists in the national and local research institutes need to provide scientific background for perspective practices of farmers in order to establish user- and environmental-friendly effective adaptation actions against climate changes in agriculture.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Statistical modelling</title><p>The optimum soil frost depth was estimated by re-analysing published data regarding the emergence ratio of volunteer potatoes and snowmelt water infiltration to soil; further, an on-farm snow cover manipulation experiment was conducted to determine nitrate retention at the surface soil owing to deep soil frost penetration. To characterise the responses to the annual maximum soil frost depth (D<sub>max</sub>), the generalised linear model (GLM) approach<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> was applied.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Volunteer potatoes</title><p>We assessed published data regarding the D<sub>max</sub> (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>; m), numbers of unharvested potato tubers and emerged sprouts, and resulting emergence ratio of volunteer potatoes during the on-farm snow cover manipulation experiment conducted at 4 sites in the Tokachi region over 2 years (2010&#x02013;11, 2011&#x02013;12)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. For the statistical modelling, the reported numbers of remaining potato tubers after harvest and emergence of potato sprouts per unit square meter area (m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) were multiplied by 10,000, and then rounded off to the closest whole number to convert to the unit (ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and to an integer value (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S1</xref>). In addition, the year of study and snow cover manipulation treatment at the same field were regarded as an independent study plot. Next, because a potato tuber has 0, 1, or several sprouts, i.e. there is no upper limit for the numbers in the emerged sprouts, we assumed that the observed variation in the potato sprouts per hectare (<italic>Sprouting</italic>) follows the Poisson distribution of mean <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq6">eq. 4</xref>). We set <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> as the explanatory variable, and the number of unharvested potato tubers per hectare (<italic>Unharvested</italic>) as the offset term in the linear predictor. Subsequently, the log link function was applied (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq7">eq. 5</xref>). The coefficients in eq. 5 (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>s</italic>0</sub>, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>s</italic>1</sub>) were estimated using the &#x02018;glm&#x02019; function of the R software package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>.</p><p><disp-formula id="eq6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e540" xlink:href="srep44860-m6.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p><disp-formula id="eq7"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e543" xlink:href="srep44860-m7.jpg"/></disp-formula></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Snowmelt water infiltration</title><p>We re-assessed published data on the relationship among the D<sub>max</sub> (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>; m), amount of infiltrated water to soil, and amount of snowmelt water during the snow cover manipulation experiment at the Memuro Research Station (Hokkaido Agricultural Research Center, NARO: 143&#x02009;&#x000b0;05&#x02032;E, 42&#x02009;&#x000b0;53&#x02032;N) in the Tokachi region for over 4 years (2005&#x02013;06<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>, 2006&#x02013;07<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>, 2007&#x02013;08<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>, and 2008&#x02013;09<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>). In these studies, soil frost depth was controlled by removing the snow cover in early winter. The cumulative daily downward water flux at 0.5-m soil depth during the snowmelt period was set to the amount of infiltrated water to soil (<italic>Inf</italic>; mm). Similarly, the cumulative decrease in snow-water equivalent during the snowmelt period was set to the amount of snowmelt water (<italic>SnowMelt</italic>; mm). These values were slightly different from the published data<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> because they were rounded off to the closest whole number to convert to an integer value for statistical modelling (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S2</xref>). In addition, the year of study was regarded as an independent study plot. Based on the fact that the amount of infiltrated water to soil was no more than that of snowmelt water, i.e. data <italic>Inf</italic>/<italic>SnowMelt</italic> were between 0 to 1, we assumed that the observed variations in the <italic>Inf</italic> follows the binomial distribution of mean <italic>q</italic> and of the upper limit <italic>SnowMelt</italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq8">eq. 6</xref>). We set <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> as the explanatory variable in the linear predictor and then applied the logit link function (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq9">eq. 7</xref>). The coefficients (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>q</italic>0</sub>, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub><italic>q</italic>1</sub>) in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq9">eq. 7</xref> were estimated using the &#x02018;glm&#x02019; function of R software package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>.</p><p><disp-formula id="eq8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e627" xlink:href="srep44860-m8.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p><disp-formula id="eq9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e630" xlink:href="srep44860-m9.jpg"/></disp-formula></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Nitrate retention to the surface soil</title><p>We conducted an on-farm experiment to evaluate the nitrate retention in the surface soil after snowmelt at fields with different annual maximum soil frost depths (<italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub>; m). The snow cover manipulation experiment was conducted at two experimental fields at the Memuro Research Station. The soil type is classified as Andisols derived from volcanic ash, which is the major soil type in the Tokachi region. Soil nitrate content at 0&#x02013;0.40&#x02009;m depth (kg N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) before snowfall and after snowmelt was set to <italic>AutumnN</italic> and <italic>Spring N</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>). For the statistical modelling, the year of study and experimental field examined were regarded as an independent study plot. Next, because nitrate content is a continuous value and should not have negative values, we assumed that the variations in the observed nitrate content in the surface soil after snowmelt follows the Gamma distribution of shape parameter <italic>s</italic> and rate parameter <italic>r</italic> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10">eq. 8</xref>), which are related to the mean <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> with <italic>s</italic>/<italic>r</italic> and the variance with <italic>s</italic>/<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>. According to the definition of the dispersion parameter &#x003d5;, these parameters are related to the variance with <italic>&#x003bc;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x003d5;; thus, <italic>s</italic> is 1/&#x003d5; and <italic>r</italic> is 1/&#x003d5;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>. We set <italic>D</italic><sub>max</sub> as the explanatory variable and <italic>AutumnN</italic> as the offset term in the linear predictor. Subsequently, the log link function was applied to the linear predictor (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq11">eq. 9</xref>). The parameters in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10">eq. 8</xref> (<italic>s, r</italic>) and the coefficients in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq11">eq. 9</xref> (&#x003b2;<sub><italic>N</italic>1</sub>, &#x003b2;<sub><italic>N</italic>2</sub>) were estimated using the &#x02018;glm&#x02019; function of R software package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>.</p><p><disp-formula id="eq10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e731" xlink:href="srep44860-m10.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p><disp-formula id="eq11"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e734" xlink:href="srep44860-m11.jpg"/></disp-formula></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Experiment in the winter wheat field</title><p>In 2008 and 2009, winter wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) was cultivated in an experimental field where the effect of tillage intensity on crop productivity and greenhouse gas fluxes of soil were tested<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Basal nitrogen fertilizer was applied at 60&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> following local conventional agricultural practices. Snow cover thickness was not manipulated during December 2008 to March 2009, i.e. no snow cover manipulation treatment was performed at the conventional tillage (CT) and reduced tillage (RT) plots, which have 8-m width from east to west and 48-m length from north to south (both were 384&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup> in size). These plots were 13&#x02009;m apart from each other from east (RT) to west (CT). The soil frost depth was measured once weekly or more by using the frost tube method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>, and the annual maximum soil frost depth (D<sub>max</sub>) was found to be 0.12&#x02009;m and 0.14&#x02009;m at the CT and RT plots, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>). In the succeeding year, 2009&#x02013;2010, winter wheat was cultivated in a similar manner, and a snow cover manipulation experiment was conducted alternately for 3 snow cover compaction and ambient control plots; each experimental plot had a size of 64&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>. Snow cover compaction was performed twice a month in December 2009 and January 2010 by using a tractor<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>; the mean D<sub>max</sub> of triplicated plots was 0.49&#x02009;m and 0.47&#x02009;m at the treatment plots compared to 0.05&#x02009;m and 0.04&#x02009;m at the control plots of CT and RT, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>). Soil samples were collected from each plot from 0&#x02013;0.40&#x02009;m by using a hand-auger at 0.10-m intervals in mid-December and early May to estimate the nitrate content in the surface soil before snowfall and after snowmelt. Well-mixed fresh soil samples were shaken with 2&#x02009;<italic>M</italic> of potassium chloride solution for 60&#x02009;min to extract nitrate, and its concentration in the extract was determined using the copper-cadmium reduction method by using a flow analysis system (QuAAtro; SEAL Analytical Gmbh, Norderstedt, Germany). The mean soil nitrate content (mg N kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry soil) for the 0.10-m thick soil was converted to the unit of kg N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> by separately determining the layer-dependent bulk density, which was 0.77, 0.88, and 1.23&#x02009;g&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> for the 0&#x02013;0.10, 0.10&#x02013;0.30, and 0.30&#x02013;0.40&#x02009;m depths of the CT plot, respectively, compared to 0.76, 0.77, and 0.58&#x02009;g&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> for the 0&#x02013;0.10, 0.10&#x02013;0.20, and 0.20&#x02013;0.40&#x02009;m depths of the RT plot, respectively.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Experiment in the corn field</title><p>In the experimental field located at the east of the RT plot, corn (<italic>Zea mays</italic> L.) was cultivated in summer in 2009 following the local conventional practice. After harvest in late August, 50&#x02009;kg&#x02009;N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of ammonium sulphate was applied using a broadcaster to enhance corn residue decomposition. This field (approximate size, 1 ha) was maintained bare during winter and divided into two parts for a treatment (snow cover manipulation) and a control (ambient snow cover) plot. The snow cover compaction treatment was conducted twice a month during December 2009 and January 2010. The mean D<sub>max</sub> in the control and treatment plots was 0.03&#x02009;m and 0.42&#x02009;m, respectively. Soil core samples were collected from each plot from 0&#x02013;1.0&#x02009;m depth by using an engine-auger in late November and early April to estimate the nitrate content in the surface soil before snowfall and after snowmelt. The core sample was cut in 0.10&#x02009;m-intervals in the field, and a portion of fresh soil samples was shaken with 2&#x02009;<italic>M</italic> of potassium chloride solution for 60&#x02009;min to extract nitrate. The concentration of nitrate in the extract was determined, and the mean soil nitrate content (mg N kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry soil) for the 0.10-m thick soil was converted to the unit of kg N ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as described above. The bulk density of the control and treatment plots was assumed to be the same as 0.83, 1.01, 0.95, 0.67, 0.91, 1.15, 1.12, and 1.10&#x02009;g&#x02009;cm<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> for the 0&#x02013;0.1, 0.1&#x02013;0.2, 0.2&#x02013;0.4, 0.4&#x02013;0.5, 0.5&#x02013;0.6, 0.6&#x02013;0.7, 0.7&#x02013;0.8, and 0.8&#x02013;1.0&#x02009;m depths, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Additional Information</title><p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Yanai, Y. <italic>et al</italic>. Optimum soil frost depth to alleviate climate change effects in cold region agriculture. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>
<bold>7</bold>, 44860; doi: 10.1038/srep44860 (2017).</p><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d32e34" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Material</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep44860-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was financially supported by J.S.P.S. KAKENHI Grant Numbers JP15K14831 (to T.H., Y.I. and Y.Y.), JP25292153 (to T.H. and Y.I.).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">IPCC. Summary for policymakers. In. <article-title>Climate Change 2014: Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability. Part A: Global and Sectoral Aspects</article-title>. <source>Contribution of Working Group II to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>[eds <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>.. ] Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Decreasing soil-frost depth and its relation to climate change in Tokachi, Hokkaido, Japan</article-title>. <source>J. Meteorol. Soc. Japan</source>
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>833</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Soil frost control: Agricultural adaptation to climate variability in a cold region of Japan</article-title>. <source>Mitig. Adapt. Strateg. Glob. Chang</source>. <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Effective killing of volunteer potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) tubers by soil frost control using agrometeorological information&#x02014;An adaptive countermeasure to climate change in a cold region</article-title>. <source>Agric. For. Meteorol</source>. <volume>182-183</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pomeroy</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Maule</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An extension of the force-restore method to estimating soil temperature at depth and evaluation for frozen soils under snow</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res. Atmos</source>. <volume>107</volume>, <fpage>4767</fpage> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The cold vadose zone: Hydrological and ecological significance of frozen-soil processes</article-title>. <source>Vadose Zo. J</source>. <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>2136</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Laflen</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>WEPP: A new generation of erosion prediction technology</article-title>. <source>J. Soil Water Conserv.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage> (<year>1991</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>McCool</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Simulating snowmelt and soil frost depth by an energy budget approach</article-title>. <source>Trans. ASABE</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1394</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flessa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D&#x000f6;rsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Beese</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Seasonal variation of N<sub>2</sub>O and CH<sub>4</sub> fluxes in differently managed arable soils in southern Germany</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res.</source>
<volume>100</volume>, <fpage>23115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23124</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pennock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Desjardins</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pattey</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Upscaling chamber-based measurements of N<sub>2</sub>O emissions at snowmelt</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Soil Sci.</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>125</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Accumulation of nitrous oxide and depletion of oxygen in seasonally frozen soils in northern Japan&#x02014;Snow cover manipulation experiments</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol. Biochem.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1786</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tsuruta</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawamoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>N<sub>2</sub>O emission and CH<sub>4</sub> uptake in arable fields managed under conventional and reduced tillage cropping systems in northern Japan</article-title>. <source>Global Biogeochem. Cycles</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>GB40205</fpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Comparison of snowmelt infiltration under different soil-freezing conditions influenced by snow cover</article-title>. <source>Vadose Zo. J</source>. <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Effects of snow cover on soil freezing, water movement, and snowmelt infiltration: A paired plot experiment</article-title>. <source>Water Resour. Res.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Influence of rain, air temperature, and snow cover on subsequent spring-snowmelt infiltration into thin frozen soil layer in northern Japan</article-title>. <source>J. Hydrol.</source>
<volume>401</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Water and nitrate movements in an agricultural field with different soil frost depths: Field experiments and numerical simulation</article-title>. <source>Ann. Glaciol.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Water infiltration into a frozen soil with simultaneous melting of the frozen layer</article-title>. <source>Vadose Zo. J</source>. <volume>12</volume>, No. 1 (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Global distribution of the potato crop</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Pot Res</source>. <volume>78</volume>, <fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>412</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Batlle-Aguilar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Comparison of hydraulic and chemical methods for determining hydraulic conductivity and leakage rates in argillaceous aquitards</article-title>. <source>J. Hydrol.</source>
<volume>532</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toyota</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Effects of successive soil freeze-thaw cycles on soil microbial biomass and organic matter decomposition potential of soils</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>829</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toyota</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Effects of successive soil freeze-thaw cycles on nitrification potential of soils</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci. Plant Nutr.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>837</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Snow cover manipulation in agricultural fields: As an option for mitigating greenhouse gas emissions</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Res</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>545</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ishijima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Variations of atmospheric nitrous oxide concentration in the northern and western Pacific</article-title>. <source>Tellus B</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPCC. limate Change 2014. Synthesis Report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [eds Core Writing Team, Pachauri R. K. &#x00026; Meyer L. A.] IPCC, Geneva, Switzerland, 151pp (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Projection of climatic change over Japan due to global warming by high-resolution regional climate model in MRI</article-title>. <source>SOLA</source>, <volume>1</volume>, <fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage> (<year>2005</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inatsu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tominaga</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katsuyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Soil-frost depth change in eastern Hokkaido under +2 K-world climate scenarios</article-title>. <source>SOLA</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shimoda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nishio</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Possible soil frost control by snow compaction on winter wheat fields</article-title>. <source>J. Agric. Meteorol</source>. <volume>71</volume>, <fpage>276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>An introduction to statistical modelling for data analysis</article-title> (In Japanese, original title translated) (Iwanami Shoten, <year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">http://www.r-project.org/</ext-link> (<year>2014</year>) (Date of access: 01/03/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Effects of soil frost depth and soil temperature on downward soil water movement during snowmelt period.</article-title>
<source>J. Japanese Soc. Soil Phys.</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage> (in Japanese with English summary) (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kuwao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Comparison of soil frost and thaw depths measured using frost tubes and other methods</article-title>. <source>Cold Reg. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> Conceived and designed the experiment: Y.Y. Y.I., and T.H. Performed the experiments: Y.Y. and Y.I. Analysed the data: Y.Y. and T.H. Drafted the manuscript: Y.Y., Y.I. and T.H.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Outline of the &#x02018;on-farm soil frost control&#x02019; technique and a conceptual diagram showing the optimum soil frost depth for the management of volunteer potatoes.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep44860-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Parameterisations of the relationships between the annual maximum soil frost depth and(<bold>a</bold>) emergence ratio of volunteer potatoes, (<bold>b</bold>) snowmelt water infiltration ratio to soil, and (<bold>c</bold>) nitrate retention ratio at the surface soil.</title><p>Solid line indicates the predicted value with 95% confidence interval. See also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Tables 1, 2, and 3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep44860-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Derivation of the optimum soil frost depth (0.28&#x02013;0.33&#x02009;m) in relation to the ratio of volunteer potato emergence (red), snowmelt water infiltration (blue), and nitrate retention to the surface soil (purple).</title><p>Solid lines indicate the predicted value with 95% confidence interval.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep44860-f3"/></fig></floats-group></article>