<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Climate change has altered the global distribution of many species. Accordingly, we have assessed here the potential shift in the distribution of 
  <italic class="italic">Gypsophila bermejoi</italic> G. López under distinct scenarios of future climate change, this being a species endemic to the Iberian Peninsula. For strict gypsophiles, climatic changes affecting their potential area of distribution could be critical if the new range is not overlapped with suitable soils. Thus, the narrow bioclimatic niche and the endemic nature of this plant could make this species particularly vulnerable to climate change. We used the Maximum Entropy (MaxEnt) method to study the potential distribution of this taxon under four different scenarios of climate change, pin-pointing relevant changes in the potential distribution of this plant and enabling possible future areas of refuge to be assessed. Such scenarios are defined according to four Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) [, which represent different trends in the concentration of atmospheric carbon dioxide. As a result, we predict notable changes in the potential distribution of 
  <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic>, and the overlap between soil and bioclimatic suitability would be affected. We also used a Principal Component Analysis (PCA) to model the bioclimatic niche of this species, comparing it with that of its parental taxa. The evolution of bioclimatic suitability was assessed at the current locations of 
  <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> and as this plant is a strict gypsophile, we generated suitability maps for sites with gypsum soils. Ultimately, this study identifies relevant changes in the potential distribution of 
  <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> under specific climatic scenarios, observing remarkable differences in the outcomes of the different climate change scenarios. Interestingly, in some scenarios the bioclimatic suitability of 
  <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> will be enhanced at many locations and even in the worst scenario some possible refuge areas were identified. 
  <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> behaves more like a hardy survivor than as early victim.
 </p>
</abstract>
