<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">The concept of occupational heat stress refers usually to local workplace heat stress. In order to evaluate occupational heat stress, four thermal climate factors (air temperature, humidity, air velocity and heat radiation) should be measured; available weather station data may serve this purpose. Yet the use of meteorological data for the assessment of occupational heat stress in the context of climate change, faces challenges because not all the important climate factors (e.g. solar radiation in W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) have traditionally been directly measured in all weather stations (Parsons 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">2013</xref>). The measurements at a weather station usually include air temperature, barometric pressure, humidity, wind speed, wind direction, and precipitation. Moreover, it is not straightforward to translate outdoor measurements into the assessment of indoor workplace conditions, as indoor environments can be different (de Dear and Brager 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">1998</xref>; Błażejczyk et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2014</xref>; Yang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" class="xref">2014</xref>). For example, weather stations are placed as distant as possible from any obstacles and local heat sources (e.g. workplace heat) and air velocity is usually measured at the standard height of 10 m. In addition, internal metabolic heat production in the body (physical work intensity), and clothing (e.g. protective clothing) impact on the exchange and balance of body heat with the external environment. Therefore, there is an urgent need to improve assessment methods linked to meteorological data for estimating the size of the problem and for developing appropriate interventions at individual, workplace and societal level (Kjellstrom and McMichael 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
