<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different model structures considered in this study allow for a comparison of the importance of internal ecosystem component dynamics versus external drivers or connections between components, and allow for an assessment of how model complexity affects model performance. The ARHMM is a relatively simple modeling approach that undertakes a fixed structure, which is not able to account for any ecosystem interactions and predicts the component based only on its prior value and relationship to a hidden variable (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g002" href="#pone.0209257.g002">Fig 2A</a>). The ARHMM was the worst performing structure and was only best able to predict a single ecosystem component; even for that component, its improvement was slight and unlikely significant compared to the other two model structures (
  <a rid="pone.0209257.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0209257.t002">Table 2</a>). The ARDBN performed better than the ARHMM due to the inclusion of a single ecosystem interaction on the predicted ecosystem component. There were some similarities in the performance between the ARHMM and ARDBN, which is likely due to the autoregressive link being present in both models. The ARDBN outperformed the DDDBN for some ecosystem components, although, these improvements over the DDDBN were usually slight. The dynamics of ecosystem components better predicted by the ARDBN suggest a dependence on their prior condition. Alternatively, other factors, such as habitat availability, which we did not include in the model, might be driving their temporal variations to a greater extent than other ecosystem effects. The improved performance in the ARDBN model for some of the ecosystem components (most notably tilefish, greater amberjack and Vermillion snapper recruitment) suggests higher influence of the prior status and a single ecosystem interaction (e.g. AMO for tilefish and Vermillion snapper, and dissolved oxygen for greater amberjack; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g003" href="#pone.0209257.g003">Fig 3</a>) compared to multiple ecosystem interactions for these ecosystem components. The best performing model, the DDDBN, accounted for up to three ecosystem interactions, two hidden variables and their changes over time, but it did not have an autoregressive link. This suggests the need to include ecosystem effects and distributional heterogeneity, when building predictive models of diverse and heavily exploited ecosystems, such as the Gulf of Mexico. One of the biggest differences between this dynamic Bayesian network modeling approach and other more traditional approaches is the incorporation of two hidden variables. Hidden variables capture changes in ecosystem variance that might not be represented within the model structure. Indeed, the accurate performance of the DDDBN and ARDBN models was likely due, at least in part, to the inclusion of the two hidden variables that reduced the likelihood of introducing spurious interactions into the analysis and allowed for more plausible network structures. The comparative evaluation of different structures, in terms of modeling the Gulf dynamics, showed that predictive performance of the ecosystem components was improved when multiple interactions within their environment were included, compared to prediction based more upon the previous state of the ecosystem com- ponent.Specifically, the DDDBN model suggests the importance of accounting for the effects of temperature and AMO on the dynamics of higher trophic level species. Also, the importance of factors like dissolved oxygen concentration on some of the economically important species (e.g. menhaden) suggests the environment plays a significant role in fishery dynamics; perhaps an even greater role than management actions for some fishery species [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref044">44</a>]. For example, gray triggerfish has almost consistently decreased in abundance over the past decades, despite implementing a rebuilding plan with regulations to reduce fishing pressure [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref025">25</a>]. In the DDDBN model, gray triggerfish recruitment is influenced by the dynamics of the HV AMO, pink shrimp and oxygen concentration, the latter two having a generally decreasing trend in recent years (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0209257.s004" href="#pone.0209257.s004">S2 Fig</a>). The combination of these physical and biological associations might be controlling, to some extent, the population dynamics of gray triggerfish. Most importantly, our study highlights AMO as a proxy for a number of complex processes that simultaneously affect the biology of the Gulf ecosystem. Also, our results emphasize the importance of hypoxia in terms of influencing fisheries productivity and trophic structure of the system [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref026">26</a>]; [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref045">45</a>]. Similarly, it has been shown for other systems that more complex models result in better predictive performance [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref046">46</a>]. For the North Sea, similar data-driven techniques have been applied to model fish biomass and a more complex model-ing structure was found to perform better in terms of predicting species dynamics across space and time [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref014">14</a>]. In general, studies have suggested that non-linear modeling approaches (i.e. classification trees and neural networks) are better able to capture and model complex patterns, found in ecological data [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref047">47</a>]. The DDDBN model represents a flexible framework of medium complexity between single-stock assessments and multi-species mechanistic models, such as Ecopath with Ecosim and Atlantis. Moreover, the DDDBN model struc-ture does not rely upon an assumption of steady state, which is unlikely to be met in ecosystems. This allows the model structure to use changes in temporal distributions and structure to inform the model and its predictions. By extending our DDDBN to model temperature scenarios, we allow for probable climate change impacts to be predicted. Ecosystem components varied in their sensitivity and directional response to increasing temperature. The variability to changes in temperature is potentially the result of ecosystem components-specific effects and interactions within their environment. In addition, differences in the predicted temperature responses could be explained by the specific thermal tolerance of the ecosystem component, its prey, its predators, or the multiple interacting stressors within its habitat. Despite this variability, we see some universal response across trophic levels that could provide insights about ecological stability and resilience in a changing climate. Changes in temperature had large impacts on zooplankton and shrimp dynamics and all reduced their values with increasing temperature. Spring zooplankton biovolume showed less prominent decrease with increasing temperature over the 30- year study period; whereas, fall zooplankton biovolume was systematically lower under all increased temperature scenarios with the higher increases in temperature predicting greater decreases in fall zooplankton biovolume. The projected dynamics of the spring zooplankton (calculated from the open ocean survey) are influenced by temperature changes but perhaps even more strongly controlled by the AMO current warm phase (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g001" href="#pone.0209257.g001">Fig 1A</a>), which potentially led to the projected sta-bility in the scenario trends compared to the DDDBN output (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g007" href="#pone.0209257.g007">Fig 7A</a>). The AMO has been invoked as the explanatory factor for a number of biological phenomena in the Atlantic Ocean and GoM [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref029">29</a>]; [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref048">48</a>]. In addition, AMO has some indirect influence on the extent and magnitude of hypoxia, thus impacting concentrations of zooplankton in the nearshore waters [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref026">26</a>]. The fall zooplankton survey covers stations located on the continental shelf, where it has been shown that oxygen concentrations can affect the structure of biological communities, having positive effects on some living marine resources and negative on others [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref049">49</a>]. There is some evidence about the tolerance of low oxygen concentrations between the co-dominant zooplankton species in the GoM: 
  <span class="italic">Acartia</span> spp. and 
  <span class="italic">Centropages</span> spp., with the latter being more abundant in low oxygen waters [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref049">49</a>]. Variability of the zooplankton community with environmental conditions has implications for the quality of the food environment for larval and planktivorous fish [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref049">49</a>]. White shrimp and brown shrimp recruitment had consistent reductions for all temperature scenarios with reductions larger when temperatures were increased more. Brown shrimp reductions were more pronounced, compared to the white shrimp, for all temperature scenarios (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g006" href="#pone.0209257.g006">Fig 6</a>). Laboratory studies have suggested that brown shrimp might be more sensitive to temperature changes and survival of juvenile shrimp within coastal waters of Texas (here, brown shrimp was influenced by Texas SST) decreases with high temperatures, supporting the dramatic decreases predicted in our model for brown shrimp [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref050">50</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref051">51</a>]. The white shrimp showed similar responses to 1.0°C and 1.5°C temperature increases, but larger decreases in the 3.0°C increase SST scenario. In the model, white shrimp was not directly influenced by temperature, but was driven by changes in fall zooplankton biovolume that is influenced by Florida shelf SST. The brown and white shrimp results are consistent with the observed temperature changes within the different shelf areas (Texas and Florida SST) and their trends in the last 5 years (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g001" href="#pone.0209257.g001">Fig 1</a>, increasing for Texas and more or less stable for Florida). These results suggest that ecosystem responses to any future changes in temperature will be influenced by the spatial habitat. Spatial variations in temperature potentially lead to spatial variability in productivity, which subsequently causes further forcing on higher level trophic species and mixture of responses at spatial scales. These decreases in shrimp and zooplankton will have implications for the availability of the food environment for upper trophic level species, including finfish of high economic importance [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref049">49</a>]. The response to increasing SST was more variable and less intense for upper trophic levels; although, King mackerel showed the largest increase of any ecosystem component in all three temperature scenarios (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g006" href="#pone.0209257.g006">Fig 6</a>). This response might be a result of habitat preferences of the King mackerel and its high temperature tolerance [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref052">52</a>]. A study of mackerel landings reported higher catches with increasing warmer temperatures, specifically during La Nina winters [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref053">53</a>]. In addition, the mackerel was driven by the dynamics of NPP, which was predicted to be relatively stable with some increase from early 2000 (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0209257.s003" href="#pone.0209257.s003">S1 Fig</a>), potentially explaining the positive response in this fish species. For some higher level trophic species, such as cobia, we were not able to see any definitive changes in response to increased SST. Cobia dynamics were influenced by AMO, so similarly, such results could be explained with the current AMO warm phase, masking the full effect from temperature change. It has been shown that AMO has influenced North Atlantic fisheries since the early 1900s [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref029">29</a>] and is correlated with community- wide fishery responses in seven northwestern Atlantic ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref028">28</a>]. Similarly, we were not able to detect significant impact on the red snapper, following increases in temperature. According to [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref054">54</a>], changes in coastal wetland habitats due to sea level rise and changes in rainfall and freshwater flow patterns may be among the most important drivers of climate change impact on species like the red snapper. Generally, red snapper are widely distributed although they have a high affinity for certain habitat types at various stages in their development [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref055">55</a>]; thus, we would not necessarily expect their population dynamics to be specifically sensitive to temperature. In our model, the red snapper was influenced by the dynamics of dissolved oxygen, which might play a more significant role for this species population dynamics, compared to SST. These results suggest that some ecosystem components will be negatively impacted, others such as the King mackerel may benefit from the effects of climate change or may be more resilient to changes in their environment such as the red snapper, showing little impact from increasing temperatures. This finding is consistent with other ecological predictions of climate change effects on marine ecosystems, using a variety of methods [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref056">56</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref058">58</a>]. Our study highlights that to assess potential “winners and losers” in a changing environment, factors like trophic associations and interactions with physical factors, affected by climate change, must be taken into consideration to evaluate the population dynamics and processes in a comprehensive manner. In addition, our study is a useful, independent comparison to mechanistic approaches designed to derive the same predictions in the GoM, such as the Climate Vulnerability Analysis [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref056">56</a>]. There were some high SSEs (
  <a rid="pone.0209257.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0209257.t002">Table 2</a>) and some outliers from the observed data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209257.g004" href="#pone.0209257.g004">Fig 4</a>), that the DDDBN model did not capture well. In addition, there was some similarity in accuracy from the different models that might be attributed to the similar effects of changing climate on many species [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref058">58</a>]. In particular, stock assessment estimates are subject to multiple sources of uncertainty, which can be categorized into three types: observation, structural and estimation, according to [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref059">59</a>]. In some cases, process error is considered to be a special case of structural uncertainty, however that is being accounted for here by using state-space models that simultaneously estimate the variances, associated with observation and process errors, using maximum likelihood [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref060">60</a>]. Estimation uncertainty can be characterized by calculating Hessian- based confidence intervals or as we have done here by bootstrapping or in a Bayesian context as probability intervals from the posterior distribution of estimates. Our comparative evaluation of multiple model structures that reflect different hypotheses of the GoM ecosystem complexity is one way of dealing with structural uncertainty. Of particular importance is the use of multiple lines of evidence to support conclusions, considering alternative hypothesis, and accounting for uncertainty [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref059">59</a>]. The data preparation and analysis, specifically standardization and non-parametric bootstrap, increase confidence in these results and the modeling structure applied. Most importantly, we account for the observation uncertainty by introducing hidden variables into the models, which allow for simpler models to be learned that are less prone to over- fitting and more efficient for inference. In most domains, the observed variables represent only some characteristics of a system, which can have a negative effect on the learning procedure. In this work, the hidden variable was chosen to most easily reflect the complex interdependencies between and among ecosystem components and their environment and account for any spurious relationships that might degrade the precision and accuracy of the results. One aspect of the underlying model structure that could be further improved would be to include socio-economic variables, for example commercial fishery landings, that would allow the model to provide information to managers that includes predicting socioeconomic impacts. The model could also be expanded to include other ecosystem components, such as protected species and microbial data to address issues like biodiversity and survival and support management strategies for protected species population recovery. In addition, the model could be developed on a more localized scale to investigate impacts from hypoxia and eutrophication. Marine populations are being threatened by both natural and anthropogenic sources and in order to understand issues between sustainability and management, populations cannot be addressed in isolation, but in relation to their interactions and associations with external factors. Data-driven techniques allowed us to strengthen our knowledge on the mechanisms involved in shaping the functional ecological network within the GoM, making them less prone to error, by not introducing assumptions about a complex system. The DDDBN modeling approach that accounted for multiple ecosystem interactions and their changes over time further highlighted the importance of distributional heterogeneity and ecosystem components-specific effects, when building predictive models of such diverse and exploited ecosystems. We explored potential ecosystem changes in response to increasing temperature in the GoM by applying temperature scenarios to the DDDBN model. The applied methods here have extended our knowledge into the complexity of the region and its ecological structure and resilience that will potentially help addressing applied questions in the field of fisheries management. Future work will involve extending the applied network model further into the future to explore the effect of alternative management strategies on specific economically important species and using summer versus winter SST values to address seasonal differences in spawning. In addition, projections from climate models (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0209257.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0209257.ref060">60</a>]) could be used in combination with the DDDBN model to investigate downscaling outputs.
 </p>
</sec>
