<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate projections are emerging as critical inputs for many applications and decision support. However, assessment of reliability of climate projections remains a major challenge; the challenge is greater at regional scales. At the same time, accurate projections of regional climate systems, like the Continental Indian Monsoon (CIM), are critical for assessing the sustainability of a large section of the world's population and to determine the future of the global climate system. However, significant uncertainties still exist regarding the reliability of the projections from the dynamical climate models, especially for regional systems like the south Asian summer monson
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>. Conceptually, any assessment of reliability of projections has to be based on their present-day (current-era) performance. The climate models today generally possess superior skill in seasonal forecasting
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref> than statistical models, and can be evaluated in hindcast mode; however, evaluation of reliability of climate projection will remain a challenge, especially over areas with contribution from natural climate variability
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>, such as the Indian monsoon
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>. In spite of their common basic mechanism, monsoons over different regions are subject to diverse forcings
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>; thus the responses of the various regional monsoons to a changing climate are expected to vary
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>. Estimates of impacts from anthropogenic climate change rely on projections from climate models. Uncertainties in the climate projections are a strong limiting factor in estimation of impacts and hence policy design, especially at regional scales.
</p>
