<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results|discussion" id="s8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="s9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal Development of Response Diversity in Farmers’ Fields.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that the diversity of yield responses to weather patterns that are critical to yield (i.e., the proxy for the climate resilience of crops) is declining in farmers’ wheat fields in most European countries. A rapid remedy is not expected because the trend of response diversity in the cultivar trials was not much better. In farmers’ fields, the overall diversity of responses to weather began to decline in the first decade of the millennium (country-level 
   <span class="italic">P</span> values &lt;0.001 if not specified), with the sharpest decline occurring in Czechia since 2002 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>). The decline in Germany began in 2003, in Spain in 2005 or earlier (data not available), in Slovakia in 2006, and in Denmark in 2009 (
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.023), leading to the lowest response diversity among the countries. The response diversity also showed a continuous declining trend from 1991 to 2014 in Czechia. This development may have contributed to the stagnation and increased variability in wheat yields in most of Europe during the same period, which has been mainly attributed to climate change (
   <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>
   <a href="#r39">*</a>–
   <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). The only country with a recent increase in response diversity was Finland, which also exhibited the greatest response diversity (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>) and no observed increase in yield variability (
   <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>) despite the lowest number of cultivars (
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="s1" href="#s1">
    <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
   </a>) among the countries. Through the entire period from 1991 to 2014, the response diversity slightly increased in Finland, Belgium, and France (
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001), but since 2006 Belgium was characterized by sharp variations and no increase (
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.35), and there was no clear evidence of an increase after 2008 in France (
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.13).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The diversity of crops in response to weather represents climate resilience, as confirmed by our data on the relation between the accumulated number of weather response clusters of cultivars and the interannual yield variability, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>. The decline in yield variance due to response diversity depended on cultivar, location, and year. Even if the response diversity of wheat generally declined, the diversity of wheat cultivars grown (i.e., type diversity) tended to slightly increase in the farmers’ fields in most countries (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>). For the 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> values associated with the weather patterns (PCs) see 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>, and for the critical agroclimatic variables see 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal Development of Response Diversity in Cultivar Trials.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identified a general declining trend in the response diversity of wheat cultivars not only in the farmers’ fields but also in the cultivar trials. The decline was smaller and less consistent in the trials than that in farmland, indicating an unexploited potential to draw upon the cultivars tested in the countries. The yield responses of the nine weather response clusters of cultivars identified (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
   </span>) to the nine critical weather patterns determined as the agroclimatic principal components (PCs) (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
   </span>) varied from +12 to −56% (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>). The total number of weather response clusters of wheat cultivars in European trials increased until 1999, remained constant until 2004, and thereafter gradually declined. The total number of cultivars increased until 2001 and began to decline in 2009. As exceptions to this trend, the low number of cultivars in Finland has remained constant, and the strong increase with mainly United Kingdom-originating cultivars in Denmark abruptly and sharply declined from 80 cultivars in 2000 to ∼25 mainly Danish cultivars in 2014. The sharp decline in Denmark was promoted by wheat yield losses due to an exceptionally warm winter of 2007 with late incidents of frost (
   <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). This event led to replacement of the foreign cultivars with local ones, likely contributing to the decline in response diversity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal Development of Weather Response Clusters.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the available sets of cultivars in northern and central Europe, a shift toward yield stability and benefit from late high solar radiation and less penalty from late heat and precipitation (cluster 3 replacing clusters 1 and 5) occurred as a response from breeders to the increased average temperatures during the late growing seasons of the 2000s (
   <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). In contrast, in southern countries after 2000, a cluster that suffers from high minimum temperatures in summer, early drought, and heat at heading (cluster 5) more than the previously dominant clusters took over, aggravating the risk to yield loss (
   <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>). This development cannot be explained as a response of cultivar selection to climate change but may rather represent unintentional adverse side effects to selection for other traits. The response to rain appears to be a sneaking risk for the entire continent: No single wheat cultivar cluster responded positively to abundant precipitation (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>). Wheat yield is generally sensitive to even a few days of exposure to water logging (
   <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>) and to wet weather that favors diseases and thus results in low yield (
   <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). The yields of individual cultivars under scarce precipitation were even doubled compared with those under abundant precipitation (PC1 in 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>). These empirical findings are in line with simulations that suggested that heat stress rather than drought sensitivity is the limiting factor to the adaptation of wheat to climate change in Europe (
   <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resilience Deserts and Hotspots.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found a low diversity of weather response clusters—a response diversity “desert”—in trials of Czechia; smaller deserts were detected in Germany and Spain, and a durum wheat desert was found in Italy (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> and 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>), which is the main durum producer in the world and is where most (1.6 million ha) of European durum wheat is cultivated. A single cluster (cluster 8) with all 44 durum wheat cultivars with &gt;20 observations (apart from three durum cultivars in cluster 7 and one cultivar in cluster 3) dominated Italy. Durum suffers from heat at heading and high winter temperatures because cold temperatures are required for vernalization in the Italian durum germplasm (
   <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). There is also an alarming similarity among northern and central European countries (apart from Slovakia), as well as among the southern European countries, in the development of the dominant weather response clusters of wheat cultivars (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A response diversity hotspot was found in Slovakian cultivar trials, including one promising unique cluster (cluster 6) and a cluster currently nearly unique (cluster 7) to Slovakia.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In particular, the members of the currently most common cluster 6 benefited from high radiation, avoidance of drought, and warm autumn and winter, and a single cultivar in cluster 7 benefitted from above-average precipitation. All these characteristics represent positive responses to weather patterns, which European clusters generally suffered from or did not respond to (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>). This and other observed complementarities could be exploited to enhance resilience through cultivation and breeding. However, the properties of the cultivars that were adapted to different conditions, such as day length, maritime versus continental conditions, and length of the growing season, limit their utilization across Europe.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Possible Causes of Decline and Differences in Response Diversity.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Repeated selection for few desirable characteristics from a continuously homogenizing and declining cultivar or genetic pool could be the reason for the observed decline in response diversity. While no genetic erosion in terms of loss of alleles was observed for wheat before the 1990s (
   <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>, 
   <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>), such a decline in alleles was found for durum after that period (
   <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>) and such a decline cannot be excluded for wheat in general. An activity called “face-lifting” of cultivars by breeders was identified as the cause of the decline in response diversity of Finnish barley in the main cultivation areas (
   <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>, 
   <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>). The homogenization of the genetic pool could be a consequence of a lack of incentives for breeders to introduce divergent material with uncertain benefits. The observed decline in response diversity coincides with an increasing dominance of crop improvement by private breeders, which accelerated in Europe around 2000. Increased competition and demand for cost efficiency increases the pressure for a shortened breeding cycle, irrespective of technology developments, and may contribute to the greater similarity among new cultivars launched in the market (
   <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>, 
   <a rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" href="#r49">49</a>). Periods of cultivar import from surrounding countries varied with a focus on local breeding in Belgium and led to a high diversity in weather responses. Conversely, a turn to mainly local cultivar selection in Denmark narrowed the response diversity and thus reduced the climate resilience of this export-oriented agricultural country.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The obvious explanation for the alarming decline and gaps in response diversity in European wheat is the absence of the explicit perspective of resilience to intensifying climatic variability and extremes in the wheat value chain. The prioritization of the yield potential of individual cultivars under current or projected average long-term climatic conditions, with a focus on harvest index and disease resistance (
   <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>), may have been influenced by early climate projections that did not consider uncertainty and variability. Since crop responses are nonlinear and exhibit thresholds in yield and quality (
   <a rid="r50" ref-type="bibr" href="#r50">50</a>) and the climatic variability is increasing (
   <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>), the benefit of response diversity will be even greater than that suggested by past yield data. An enhancement of response diversity through increased awareness of the significance of diversity in weather responses within the available set of cultivars is therefore of primary importance for wheat production and food security.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Enhancing Climate Resilience of European Wheat Through Response Diversity.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There appears to be greater cultivar diversity in the trials at the European (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
   </span>) than at the country level, but the substantial differences in conditions aggravate the direct utilization of cultivars across Europe. Funding for targeted research and an economic incentive to companies to utilize more cultivars from the European list of approved cultivars might diversify the cultivars used in national trials. Specific parts of wheat genome were also shown responsible, for example, for temperature response (
   <a rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" href="#r51">51</a>), which can be used in breeding a wheat cultivar portfolio with sufficient response diversity for Europe. Yield losses due to weather are currently not recorded in cultivar trials, which creates a tendency to not learn from the diversity of responses to weather variability. An option for immediate improvement thus is to document yield losses due to extreme weather events, and perhaps include them in a separate analysis.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The costs to breed a selection of genuinely different cultivars are likely higher than the costs to breed a homogenous selection. A broader selection also poses additional costs to traders even if indirect benefits through lower risks and reduced contract area requirements may also follow. For farmers, several cultivars do not necessarily cause additional costs but may even temporally equalize work demand. The benefits from response diversity may be greatest to the weakest actors in the wheat supply chain, such as farmers (yield stability) and disadvantaged consumers (price stability), while the public actor in charge of food security might benefit most. The development in response diversity of wheat appeared, indeed, less alarming in countries with traditions in private–public breeding partnerships such as Finland and Belgium, while in Germany, with low response diversity, private breeders have dominated for more than a century.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Farmers’ demand could act as the incentive to breeders to diversify weather responses among wheat cultivars, but farmers currently focus on yield potential and quality. There is, however, no inherent trade-off between yield potential and diversity in weather responses. Yield stability is a complementary breeding goal in addition to yield potential and the average yield in the long term. While the example given here (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>) is mainly illustrative, in Finnish regions with high barley cultivar diversity where yield variations among years were low, also the average yield was greater than that in the regions with low cultivar diversities (
   <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>). Risk aversion varies among farmers, but the notable share (46%) of yield-independent subsidies in farm income in Europe (
   <a rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" href="#r10">10</a>) acts as a disincentive to innovations for yield security. For instance, the subsidies in Czechia are lower than in most European Union countries, and most of the farmland is rented, which creates a notable cost relative to the subsidies. Consequently, the demand by farmers for drought-resistant cultivars is clearly articulated in that country. Therefore, a cultivar portfolio with diversity in responses to weather could be a prerequisite for subsidies or loss compensation to farmers, and for a reduced price of an insurance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main challenge for enhancing the diversity in crop responses to weather events and thus the climate resilience lies in the required shift of the perspective to cover this aspect. The actors in wheat supply chains must shift the focus from individual cultivars and yield potential in good conditions to a portfolio of cultivars to include complementary responses to critical weather events. The lack of awareness and experience of the diversity approach keeps the focus on individual cultivars, which have a more limited yield stability potential than a portfolio of cultivars with diverse responses. The shift in perspectives toward resilience could be achieved through simple tools to demonstrate and communicate the diversity in cultivar responses between breeders, farmers, and traders (
   <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>), good examples rewarded by recognition (
   <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>), and “learning-by-doing” facilitated by the economic incentives or, likely most effectively, regulation. Initiating a dialogue within wheat value chains, for example by national emergency supply agencies, involving also research and policy makers, could help enhance the resilience of wheat supply chains and food systems (
   <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>). Diversity in responses provides a practical means to enhance robustness under weather variability and adapt to the uncertainty in climate change through portfolios of not only cultivars but also crops (
   <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>) and even marketing channels (
   <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
