<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resilience Deserts and Hotspots.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found a low diversity of weather response clusters—a response diversity “desert”—in trials of Czechia; smaller deserts were detected in Germany and Spain, and a durum wheat desert was found in Italy (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>), which is the main durum producer in the world and is where most (1.6 million ha) of European durum wheat is cultivated. A single cluster (cluster 8) with all 44 durum wheat cultivars with &gt;20 observations (apart from three durum cultivars in cluster 7 and one cultivar in cluster 3) dominated Italy. Durum suffers from heat at heading and high winter temperatures because cold temperatures are required for vernalization in the Italian durum germplasm (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). There is also an alarming similarity among northern and central European countries (apart from Slovakia), as well as among the southern European countries, in the development of the dominant weather response clusters of wheat cultivars (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A response diversity hotspot was found in Slovakian cultivar trials, including one promising unique cluster (cluster 6) and a cluster currently nearly unique (cluster 7) to Slovakia.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In particular, the members of the currently most common cluster 6 benefited from high radiation, avoidance of drought, and warm autumn and winter, and a single cultivar in cluster 7 benefitted from above-average precipitation. All these characteristics represent positive responses to weather patterns, which European clusters generally suffered from or did not respond to (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>). This and other observed complementarities could be exploited to enhance resilience through cultivation and breeding. However, the properties of the cultivars that were adapted to different conditions, such as day length, maritime versus continental conditions, and length of the growing season, limit their utilization across Europe.
 </p>
</sec>
