<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 3: Grouping the Responses to the Agroclimatic Variables Using PCA.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PCA was used to identify a simplified structure that best explained the variance in the data on the yield responses of the cultivars to agroclimatic variables. We also established the agroclimatic variables that behaved in similar ways. The first PC (i.e., agroclimatic factor) always accounts for most of the variability, and the last PC accounts for the least variability; therefore, only a few PCs are needed to contain most of the information. PCs with eigenvalues above one were retained, and the last PC was deleted based on interpretation and cross validation (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>, 
  <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>). Nine PCs explained 70% of the total variation (varied from 15 to 5%). An orthogonal varimax rotation was used to achieve a more meaningful and interpretable solution. An oblique promax rotation was also tested but was found unnecessary based on relatively low correlations between PCs. The sampling adequacy, tested with the Kaiser–Melkin–Olkin (KMO) measure, was middling, with a KMO value of 0.77 (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We excluded 149 cultivars that were missing more than one-third of the yield response observations to the 43 agroclimatic variables to reduce the number of imputations and thus to improve reliability. A small number of cultivars (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 17) were excluded as outliers because their score for one of the significant PCs was more than six SDs beyond the sample mean score (
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>). Multiple imputations (MI) with 100 replicates for missing data (10%) were used to obtain the PC scores, which were used to further analyze each cultivar. A multivariate normal approach via the Markov chain Monte Carlo method was used for the MI. The effects of the imputations on the PCA structure were studied by basing the PCA on a correlation matrix without imputations and were found to be negligible. Therefore, the imputations were retained in the data, and the PC scores calculated using the regression method were used in further analyses (
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>). PC scores were left unstandardized to give less weight to a possible noise element and decrease the sensitivity of the clustering results to the number of PCs retained (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>). The effects of standardization and the use of truncated Mahalanobis distances were also examined but were found less interpretative.
 </p>
</sec>
