<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal Development of Response Diversity in Cultivar Trials.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identified a general declining trend in the response diversity of wheat cultivars not only in the farmers’ fields but also in the cultivar trials. The decline was smaller and less consistent in the trials than that in farmland, indicating an unexploited potential to draw upon the cultivars tested in the countries. The yield responses of the nine weather response clusters of cultivars identified (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>) to the nine critical weather patterns determined as the agroclimatic principal components (PCs) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
  </span>) varied from +12 to −56% (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1804387115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>). The total number of weather response clusters of wheat cultivars in European trials increased until 1999, remained constant until 2004, and thereafter gradually declined. The total number of cultivars increased until 2001 and began to decline in 2009. As exceptions to this trend, the low number of cultivars in Finland has remained constant, and the strong increase with mainly United Kingdom-originating cultivars in Denmark abruptly and sharply declined from 80 cultivars in 2000 to ∼25 mainly Danish cultivars in 2014. The sharp decline in Denmark was promoted by wheat yield losses due to an exceptionally warm winter of 2007 with late incidents of frost (
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). This event led to replacement of the foreign cultivars with local ones, likely contributing to the decline in response diversity.
 </p>
</sec>
