<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of this study reveal that for consumers, attitude, perceived behavioral control, and food neophobia have significant effects on their purchase intention. Scholars have identified that when consumers have positive feelings about their experiences, their attitudes toward products are more positive [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Therefore, this study shows that edible insect companies can enhance consumer knowledge and experience of edible insect products. For foods that consumers are not familiar with or that they have never eaten before, or edible insect foods that they are afraid of trying, edible insect companies can educate consumers about edible insects, as well as edible insects with high protein and nutrients. Consumers can also reduce fear or uncertainty about eating edible insect products through product experience. Furthermore, edible insects can be considered as sustainable food because insects are simply far less demanding than beef, e.g., 7 times less feed, 50 times less water, and 100 times fewer greenhouse gases [
 <xref rid="B100-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. The cultivation of edible insects can reduce the environmental burden and contribute to environmental protection more than the conservation of traditional livestock [
 <xref rid="B101-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. In addition, edible insect products are also sold in other countries. For example, the French company Micronutris sells the cricket 
 <italic>sigillatus</italic>, tablette-tenebrio’s chocolate, and aldente-aenebrio pasta and crackers [
 <xref rid="B102-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], and the Fazer chain bakery are going to start selling ‘insect bread’ and offer a product called Fazer Cricket Bread [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>], and so on. Fazer is one of the largest corporations in the Finnish food industry. Edible insect companies can cook insect foods in a familiar cooking style [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] or introduce insect foods into common products [
 <xref rid="B90-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. These methods can increase consumer interest and acceptability of insect foods, thereby increasing the intention to purchase.
</p>
