<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A comparison of our results to published literature on phenological advancement rates in shorebird species and sites across the Arctic revealed similar rates and explanatory patterns. Advancement rates were generally ≤0.5 days/year for most species, but with greater advancement in late‐laying and opportunistic species (Grabowski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Høye et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Liebezeit et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; McKinnon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). For example, at Prudhoe Bay, Alaska, phalaropes characterized as late‐laying opportunistic species, exhibited greater phenological advancement (0.8 days/year) than Pectoral Sandpiper (0.5 days/year), an early‐laying opportunistic species, and Semipalmated Sandpiper (0.4 days/year), an early‐laying conservative species (Liebezeit et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Similar results were also found at Bylot Island, Canada (McKinnon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), where White‐rumped Sandpiper (
 <italic class="italic">Calidris fuscicollis</italic>), a late‐laying opportunistic species, was the only species to significantly advance egg laying dates (0.1 days/year). Other species investigated at this site were early‐laying conservative species (i.e., American Golden‐Plover and Baird's Sandpiper [
 <italic class="italic">Calidris bairdii</italic>]). At other sites in Northeast Greenland and on Herschel Island in Canada, early‐laying conservative species such as Ruddy Turnstone (
 <italic class="italic">Arenaria interpres</italic>), Sanderling (
 <italic class="italic">Calidris alba</italic>), Dunlin, and Baird's Sandpiper advanced egg laying dates by 0.4–1.0 days/year; however, no late‐laying or opportunistic species were available at these sites for comparison (Grabowski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Høye et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>); therefore, it is unknown if the patterns at these sites contradict or conform to our observed patterns. Overall, these comparisons illustrate that, in general, early‐laying conservative species were the least adaptable throughout their range; however, more work is needed to verify these qualitative patterns.
</p>
