<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Some limited entry fisheries have resulted in sustainable harvest (ECR-1) (Townsend 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" class="xref">1990</xref>, Hilborn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2003</xref>), generally when institutional systems provide incentives to individual operators to motivate sustainable harvest (Hilborn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2005</xref>). However, solely restricting access in order to manage fisheries does not guarantee sustainable harvest or conservation of biodiversity or habitat (ECR-2) (Hilborn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2005</xref>). Limited entry per se does not incentivize fishers to respond to fishery stressors (ERC-3) and avoid discards, for example, as evidenced in the US west coast trawling fishery that discarded 40 percent of catches (Hilborn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2005</xref>). Successful examples exist, however, under mandatory controls to avoid by-catch, such as the East Australian longline fishery that uses limited entry spatial zones to conserve Bluefin tuna (Hobday et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">2010</xref>). In regard to social resilience, limited entry as a management system usually fails to address stewardship (SCR-3) due to the low level of access rights, but may be flexible for engaging in alternative livelihoods (SCR-2) for the same reason (Allison and Ellis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2001</xref>). The top-down nature of restricting access frequently hinders community-based management (SCR-6), and in some cases also produces a mismatch between management and biological scales, as in the example of the Atlantic tuna fishery (Berkes 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2006</xref>). A detailed analysis of effective multi-level governance (SCR-4) has been conducted in the Australian Great Barrier Reef fisheries (Fidelman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2013</xref>). In this region, the potential of a multi-level approach to help the system adapt to climate change appears to be threatened by a complex and fragmented governance system (Fidelman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
