<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper has argued that the storyline approach to regional climate change information avoids the straightjacket that hampers the standard confidence-based approach, by allowing a reframing of the climate risk question from the prediction space into the decision space. While in principle such a reframing is possible from probabilistic estimates of risk, the challenge for regional climate change information is that the level of epistemic uncertainty is sufficiently high that subjective choices must inevitably be made, and the range of users sufficiently inhomogeneous that there is no consensus on values. Under such conditions, probabilistic ‘rational-choice’ approaches to decision-making are ineffective [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C63">63</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C64">64</a>] and the decision framework needs to be one where the subjective and ethical choices are both flexible and transparent [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C65">65</a>]. Since epistemic uncertainty is inherently deterministic and subjective, there is no imperative to represent it probabilistically [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C23">23</a>], and probabilistic representations can give a false impression of objectivity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reframing of the risk question from the prediction space to the decision space may seem uncomfortable from a physical science perspective, but is in fact quite orthodox from the perspective of statistical inference. Despite the widespread use of 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-values as an ostensibly objective measure of statistical significance, the inference derived from data concerning a particular hypothesis is far from a straightforward matter and involves many assumptions [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C66">66</a>]. In the Neyman–Pearson framework, the inference problem is regularized by placing it in a decision context between two alternative hypotheses, which takes into account the possibility of both type 1 and type 2 errors [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C67">67</a>]. In the Bayesian framework, the strength of evidence between these alternative hypotheses (
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) provided by the data 
  <span class="italic">D</span> is given by 
  <div id="RSPA20190013M6.1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">6.1</span>
   <div id="DM9" class="math">
    <div class="mfrac">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">H</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">|</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mi">D</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">H</span>
        <span class="mn">1</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">|</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mi">D</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">D</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">|</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">H</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">D</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">|</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">H</span>
        <span class="mn">1</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">H</span>
         <span class="mn">2</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">H</span>
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">,</span>
   </div>
  </div> which follows directly from Bayes' theorem. The Bayes factor 
  <span class="italic">P</span>(
  <span class="italic">D</span>|
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>2</sub>)/
  <span class="italic">P</span>(
  <span class="italic">D</span>|
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>1</sub>) is independent of the prior likelihoods 
  <span class="italic">P</span>(
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) and 
  <span class="italic">P</span>(
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>1</sub>), so can be considered objective, but it does not represent any sort of absolute knowledge—only an increment in knowledge, relative to the prior beliefs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moving the climate risk problem out of the domain of pure climate science requires humility on the part of climate scientists. To quote Funtowicz &amp; Ravetz [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C63">63</a>, pp. 750–751]—who used sea-level rise as an example—‘the traditional domination of “hard facts” over “soft values” [is] inverted… traditional scientific inputs… become “soft” in the context of the “hard” value commitments that will determine the success of policies for mitigating the effects of [climate change]’. Indeed, it has been argued that humility is one of the four core elements—the others being integrity, transparency and collaboration—that should be intrinsic to the production of regional climate information [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C68">68</a>]. In this way, the goal is not so much to be authoritative, which has something of a gatekeeper connotation, but to be trustworthy [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C69">69</a>]. This involves a loss of control, because one's trustworthiness is a judgement made by others.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This perspective also involves an acknowledgement that climate-relevant decisions, especially at the local scale, are not usually made on the basis of climate change alone but involve many other changing factors, most of which are highly uncertain. If climate impacts 
  <span class="italic">I</span> are a product of hazard 
  <span class="italic">H</span>, vulnerability 
  <span class="italic">V</span> and exposure 
  <span class="italic">E</span>, then, conceptually, the anthropogenic changes in 
  <span class="italic">I</span> can be represented as 
  <div id="RSPA20190013M6.2" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">6.2</span>
   <div id="DM10" class="math">
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
    <span class="mi">I</span>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
    <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">H</span>
     <span class="mi">V</span>
     <span class="mi">E</span>
    </div>
    <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mi">H</span>
    <span class="mi">V</span>
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
    <span class="mi">E</span>
    <span class="mo">+</span>
    <span class="mi">H</span>
    <span class="mi">E</span>
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
    <span class="mi">V</span>
    <span class="mo">+</span>
    <span class="mi">V</span>
    <span class="mi">E</span>
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
    <span class="mi">H</span>
    <span class="mo">.</span>
   </div>
  </div> It may well be that the largest terms on the right-hand side of (6.2) are the first two, where it is the combination of climate and weather 
  <span class="italic">variability</span> with changing vulnerability and exposure that is the main determinant of climate risk [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C70">70</a>]. In this case, the decision framework is not so much that of dealing with climate change as it is that of bringing climate information into decisions that need to be made in any case. There are calls for this sort of complex-systems thinking in other areas of science, such as public health [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C71">71</a>, p. 2602]: ‘Instead of asking whether an intervention works to fix a problem, researchers should aim to identify if and how it contributes to reshaping a system in favourable ways’.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To return to Kuhn [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C22">22</a>], the construction of regional climate change information is not most usefully viewed as a search for an objective truth, but rather as a search for more complete descriptions of the realities that people have experienced and may experience in the future, and how those depend on contingent factors that are under human control. Kuhn's version of the Bayesian perspective described above, and the cutting of the Gordian knot it enables, is as follows [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C22">22</a>, p. 170]: ‘If we can learn to substitute evolution-from-what-we-know for evolution-toward-what-we-wish-to-know, a number of vexing problems may vanish in the process’. The role of climate scientists is to bring physical knowledge of the climate system into such an enterprise.
 </p>
</sec>
