<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although there is high confidence in thermodynamic aspects of climate change (global warming, sea-level rise, atmospheric moistening, melting of ice), the levels of confidence concerning dynamical aspects of climate change, such as the location and strength of storm tracks, are much lower [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C1">1</a>]. None of the three key lines of evidence used in climate change science—predicated by accepted theory, detected in observations and consistently represented in climate models—applies to aspects of climate change that are closely related to large-scale atmospheric circulation. This includes, notably, mean precipitation changes over many of the most populated regions on Earth (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F1" href="#RSPA20190013F1">figure 1</a>). It is in striking contrast to thermodynamic aspects of change, at least when sufficiently aggregated [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C3">3</a>], where all three lines of evidence apply [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C2">2</a>]. 
  <div id="RSPA20190013F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Projected changes in precipitation (in %) over the twenty-first century under a high climate forcing scenario (RCP8.5). Stippling indicates where the multi-model mean change is large compared with natural internal variability in 20 year means (greater than two standard deviations) and where at least 90% of models agree on the sign of change. Hatching indicates where the multi-model mean change is small compared with internal variability (less than one standard deviation), but this does not mean that individual model changes are small. From the Summary for Policymakers of [
     <a rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C2">2</a>]. (Online version in colour.)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rspa20190013-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of agreed upon theoretical predictions is related to the fact that different drivers of change can act in opposite directions, so the result is often a small difference of large terms [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C4">4</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C5">5</a>]. Lack of detection in observations is related to the small signal-to-noise ratio of forced circulation changes, reflecting the fact that climate variability is primarily a dynamical phenomenon [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C6">6</a>]. Lack of model agreement is related to both these issues, and to the fact that circulation changes are often quite sensitive to model biases, which can be substantial [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C7">7</a>–
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C9">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, thermodynamic aspects of climate can be described by extensive quantities (e.g. heat content or ocean volume), which can be readily aggregated, and strong conclusions can be drawn from thermodynamic principles alone, often in terms of global budgets [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C10">10</a>]. By contrast, circulation aspects of climate are inherently regional, and involve dynamics (Newton's second law) as well as thermodynamics. Since dynamics is also inherently chaotic, the challenge of atmospheric circulation should come as no surprise.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ways must therefore be found to construct useful scientific information on the regional scale, and even on the local scale, that reflect an appropriate level of uncertainty yet retain the relevant information about climate risk. It has recently been argued [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C11">11</a>] that 
  <span class="italic">storylines</span>—physically self-consistent unfoldings of past events, or of plausible future events or pathways—provide a potential way forward, both for the interpretation of the observed record and for the description of plausible futures. However, storylines are inherently subjective and thus would seem to be at odds with more probabilistic approaches, which give the appearance of objectivity. The purpose of this paper is to place storylines within a broader epistemological framework.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is first shown (§2) how the standard, confidence-based framework for the construction of climate information prioritizes reliability (the avoidance of type 1 errors, or false alarms) over informativeness (the avoidance of type 2 errors, or missed warnings), and thus has ethical implications. It follows that there is no such thing as value-free climate science. In §3, the difference between epistemic and aleatoric (random) uncertainty is shown to be critical to the treatment of climate risk. Since epistemic uncertainty is deterministic and inherently subjective, it follows that there is no objective basis for a probabilistic approach, and no such thing as objective climate information. This motivates a reframing of the climate risk question from the ostensibly objective prediction space into the explicitly subjective decision space (§4). Finally, it is shown in §5 how such a reframing can be cast within the mathematical framework of a causal network, thereby reconciling storyline and probabilistic approaches.</p>
</sec>
