<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">There have been only a few studies to date examining the effect of climate change alone on human health burdens from air quality; for PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> studies have focussed on long-term exposure, whilst for O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> studies have considered either short-term or long-term exposure. Fang et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>] quantified the effect of climate change induced changes in PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> and O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> air quality over the twenty-first century (2090s–1990s) under the moderate SRES A1B scenario on global premature mortalities due to long-term exposure. PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> concentrations increases due to elevated sulphate concentrations and reduced precipitation over the major emission source regions, led to an increase in global annual premature mortality associated with chronic exposure to PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> of approximately 100,000 deaths (95% confidence interval, CI, of 66–130,000) with corresponding years of life (YLL) lost increasing by nearly 900,000 (95% CI, 576,000–1,128,000) years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>]. Higher O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> in polluted regions also increased annual premature mortality due to respiratory disease from chronic O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> exposure by 6,300 deaths (95% CI, 1600–10,400) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>]. On average, across 50 U.S. cities, higher O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> under the SRES A2 high climate scenario increased total daily mortalities by 0.11–0.27% from 2000s to 2050s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">83</xref>]. For the same period Tagaris et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">84</xref>] estimated that climate change under the SRES A1B scenario increased combined PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> (long-term exposure) and O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> (short-term exposure) related annual U.S premature mortalities by 4,300 deaths. Examining climate policies that reduced the global mean temperature change from 6 °C to ~1.5 °C produced ~50,000 avoided premature mortalities for the USA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>]. Over Europe, Orru et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>], estimated annual premature mortalities due to short-term exposure to O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> to increase over most of Europe but decrease over the northernmost Nordic and Baltic countries, with the largest change being a 34% increase over Belgium under the SRES A2 climate scenario in the 2050s, due to regional reductions in cloud cover and soil moisture. In a sensitivity study over the UK, Heal et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">86</xref>] found that a 5 °C increase of year-round temperatures increased the total UK health burden due to short-term exposure to O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> by an additional 500 premature deaths (4%), assuming no change in population and no threshold for O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> effects.
</p>
