<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1. β-Adrenergic Agonists</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using Life Cycle Analysis (LCA) modeling, Stackhouse 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2012) found that the use of βAAs, in combination with antibiotics, ionophores, and hormone implants, as is common in US feedlots, decreased the carbon footprint of Angus beef production by 9% [
  <a rid="B109-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109-animals-05-00361">109</a>], and therefore advocated their use as a potential mitigation option. Cooprider 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2011) calculated that feedlot cattle fed ractopamine hydrochloride along with hormone implants and antibiotics had a 31% decrease in emissions per finished steer given the improved feed efficiency [
  <a rid="B114-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114-animals-05-00361">114</a>]. However, anecdotal reports of changes in behavior and more cattle deaths when βAAs were being fed has led researchers to investigate [
  <a rid="B109-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109-animals-05-00361">109</a>]. One recent study found that cattle fed βAAs along with a growth implant (trenbolone acetate and estradiol) engaged in more agonistic behavior including bulling and pushing [
  <a rid="B115-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115-animals-05-00361">115</a>]. A large-scale investigation by two major US agricultural universities examined datasets provided by feedlot operators also confirmed the field observations, finding that the cumulative death rate is as much as 90% greater in animals administered a βAA, and that 40%–50% of deaths among groups administered a βAA could be explained by administration of the drug [
  <a rid="B110-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110-animals-05-00361">110</a>]. Imports of animal products containing beta agonists is banned in many countries, including the EU, Russia, and China [
  <a rid="B116-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116-animals-05-00361">116</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The βAA ractopamine hydrochloride is also fed to swine, where the side-effects that have been elucidated to date include elevated heart rate, difficulty walking [
  <a rid="B117-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B117-animals-05-00361">117</a>], increased aggression [
  <a rid="B118-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B118-animals-05-00361">118</a>], abnormal behavior [
  <a rid="B119-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119-animals-05-00361">119</a>], and hoof lesions [
  <a rid="B120-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B120-animals-05-00361">120</a>]. Observations at slaughter plants additionally find that difficulty walking due to ractopamine may contribute to a greater incidence of non-ambulatory (or “downed”) pigs, those too weak to stand and walk on their own accord [
  <a rid="B117-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B117-animals-05-00361">117</a>]. The number of studies investigating the animal welfare effects of βAAs is, thus far, small, but given the problems identified already, calls for their increased use clearly should be made more cautiously.
 </p>
</sec>
