<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As species that have evolved the greatest tolerances to high temperatures may have done so at the expense of acclimation capacity (Stillman, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>), we further tested whether there is a trade‐off between CTMax and thermal acclimation ability in these species of salamanders. Critical thermal maximum data were obtained using methods similar to Layne and Claussen (
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1982</xref>), where loss of righting response is considered the endpoint. This point is reached when a salamander is turned onto its back and is unable to right itself within 30 s (Hutchison, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1961</xref>). At the start of each trial, individual salamanders were placed into a small container with 2 cm of water and an open top. A 150‐watt infrared‐heat lamp was placed 27 cm from the surface of the water and increased water temperature by 0.5°C/min until the end point was reached. An air bubbler was used to circulate the water. Deep body temperatures of salamanders are found to closely follow water temperature at rates of 1.0°C/min or less (Feder &amp; Lynch, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1982</xref>; Hutchison, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1961</xref>), therefore, the water temperature at the endpoint of each trial was considered the CTMax result for that individual (as measured by digital thermometer; Fluke 51 II, Everett, WA, USA) (Brattstrom, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1968</xref>; Lutterschmidt &amp; Hutchison, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>). Further, to reduce the affect of diet on thermal physiology, salamanders were not fed for 6 days prior to measurements of CTMax (Hutchison, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1961</xref>). Each salamander was weighed before the trial to within 0.001 g.
</p>
