<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="anchor" id="dtblC1">
 <label>Table C.1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Text relating to challenges to modelling agricultural impacts of and adaptations to climate change identified by 
   <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Rötter et al. (2018)</xref> and its relation to themes identified in workshop data. 
   <bold>TS</bold> = challenges identified by 
   <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Rötter et al. (2018)</xref> as specific to tropical plant production systems.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0020">Table C.1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Text extracts from 
     <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Rötter et al. (2018)</xref> relating to modelling challenges
    </th>
    <th>Themes</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Economic models need to be combined with Crop Simulation Models in whole-farm assessments to better evaluate management practices</td>
    <td align="left">Collaboration; Interactions</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Management and land use does not only respond to climate change, but also to changing socio-economic conditions, such as liberalization of markets or changes in dietary habits. Crop Simulation Modelling thus needs to be integrated into a larger modelling framework.</td>
    <td align="left">Collaboration; Interactions; Scale interactions</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Statistical Models are constrained in many cases by the availability of adequate, representative yield data</td>
    <td align="left">Data availability; Data quality</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Substantial mismatches between Crop Simulation Models and Statistical Models may indicate knowledge gaps regarding the mechanisms/processes that cause under-/overestimation of yield, et cetera</td>
    <td align="left">Data availability; Interactions</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Despite some efforts, the effect of tillage on carbon storage has so far only been modelled with limited success, mainly due to insufficient field data to develop mechanistic descriptions in the models</td>
    <td align="left">Data availability; Interactions</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">At larger scales, Crop Simulation Modelling is severely hampered by lack of data for parameterization and calibration and management systems are often unknown. Large uncertainties persist — especially related to variability in managerial practices and spatial response patterns.</td>
    <td align="left">Data availability</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Likewise, important tropical crops have been much less investigated in experiments regarding their exposure to agro-climatic extremes than those for temperate systems. Even with some progress in data availability, there is a need for both — more experiments and modelling — (as propagated by TROPAGS, see 
     <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) to understand the underlying mechanisms. 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Data availability</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">A key constraint to realistically upscaling the productivity of such systems (and how it is affected by climate change) to region level is, for instance, that fields of smallholder systems are not clearly defined, and a wide range of crop types can be found within a field. 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Data availability</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Besides improving crop models, fast track methods are needed to characterise and inventory smallholder fields as a basis for upscaling. Thereby the typical simplistic focus of modelling climate change impacts on sole crops (usually maize) in smallholder systems of Africa can be overcome. 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Data availability</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">We need much better understanding of how climate effects scale with changes in low input systems 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Data availability</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Still, by far the majority of Crop Simulation Models deal with single season, single crop runs</td>
    <td align="left">Dynamic change</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">There is also an increasing interest in the role that agricultural management has on environmental impact, such as carbon sequestration or GHG emissions. However, carbon stocks need years to build up, thus long-term simulation over multiple years that also reflect the current deviation from the equilibrium state are necessary to capture that</td>
    <td align="left">Dynamic change</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">While ensemble approaches helped to make model predictions more robust and quantify the uncertainties, the next logical step was to improve responses to heat and the fundamental temperature functions in individual models, to eventually reduce the uncertainty by proposing improved functions and parameterization</td>
    <td align="left">Interactions modelling</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">… and also lack information on critical interactions of factors such as weather, soil and management practices</td>
    <td align="left">Interactions modelling</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">So far, crop models are not capable of capturing the multi-species interactions within one ‘field’ and the associated services delivered 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Interactions modelling</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Moreover, many systems are integrated crop-livestock systems, which makes the common use of the model output variable ‘yield produced per unit area’ difficult 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Interactions modelling</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">One advantage of this method (use of statistical models) is that it inherently covers also indirect yield limiting factors, which are linked to climate variables, like pest and diseases. Process-based crop models so far largely ignore their effects, and thus fail to estimate farmer yields accurately in regions and years where biotic stresses are significant</td>
    <td align="left">Scope</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">While these (multi-model ensemble approaches) can be the basis for systematically exploring critical parameters and assumptions, they do not compensate for exploring missing mechanisms</td>
    <td align="left">Scope</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Global model runs suggest strong effects of climate change on the crop production systems in the Global South, especially in Africa. However, such runs were done mainly for water limited and/or nutrient-limited yield, hence, with yields not limited by biotic stresses. That makes the results of little use to understand the actual effect of climate change on these systems, as many tropical plant production systems are heavily restricted by combinations of severe abiotic and biotic stresses 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Scope</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Many tropical systems are arguably more complex including agroforestry/intercropping. Unfortunately, crop models have been rarely tested/applied in such systems. 
     <bold>TS</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Scope</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
