<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="anchor" id="dtblD1">
 <label>Table D.1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>comparison of agricultural adaptation modelling challenge themes, themes drawn from 
   <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adger et al. (2018)</xref> (See S2.1 for description of themes), CC adaptation challenges previously identified for grassland and for animal health modellers, and broader climate-related challenges identified for these modelling disciplines. The 
   <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adger et al. (2018)</xref> theme ‘Developing new CCRA methods’ is not included in the table as it would associate with all themes within the ‘Capacity’ category in the current study.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0025">Table D.1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Category (current study)</th>
    <th>Theme (current study)</th>
    <th>Themes from 
     <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adger et al. (2018)</xref>
    </th>
    <th>Grassland modelling (adaptation specific)</th>
    <th>Grassland modelling (general climate change)</th>
    <th>Animal health &amp; disease modelling (adaptation specific)</th>
    <th>Animal health &amp; disease modelling (general climate change)</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="7" align="left">Capacity</td>
    <td align="left">Collaboration</td>
    <td align="left">Inter-disciplinary and trans-disciplinary approaches</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Links to other disciplines to explore impacts of changes in grasslands on the nutritional value of the sward for animals, &amp; on the economics of systems; Fit-for-purpose models (use of model platforms &amp; modular approaches for model integration)</td>
    <td align="left">Links to other disciplines to understand health interactions with other aspects of production; improved regional economic modelling of CC &amp; socio-economic impacts of health changes &amp; adaptive responses</td>
    <td align="left">Terminology and measurements: differences in international and interdisciplinary collaboration; Fit-for-purpose models (use of model platforms and modular approaches for model integration)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Data availability</td>
    <td rowspan="2" align="left">Data on adaptations (availability and quality); Socio-economic drivers (data availability); Biophysical knowledge (data availability)</td>
    <td rowspan="3" align="left">Collation of data on adaptation strategy, their efficacy and impacts</td>
    <td rowspan="3" align="left">Data for models (including availability, accessibility, quality); fitting model &amp; data scale</td>
    <td align="left">Data on costs and efficacy of both health issues &amp; interventions</td>
    <td align="left">Implicit in other challenges, e.g. need for data on different systems, on pathogen, pest &amp; host ecology, at different scales &amp; in relation to model scope</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Data quality</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Need for data collection protocols, agreed standards, approaches and terminology</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Data accessibility</td>
    <td align="left">DATA ACCESSIBILITY NOT MENTIONED</td>
    <td align="left">Collating adaptation options related to different health conditions</td>
    <td align="left">Issues relating to data ownership and sharing in a competitive context</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Novel scenarios</td>
    <td align="left">Scenarios</td>
    <td align="left">Context specific adaptation scenarios based on stakeholder needs</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Creating adaptation scenarios</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Resources for modellers</td>
    <td align="left">RESOURCE LIMITS NOT MENTIONED</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Uncertainty</td>
    <td align="left">Uncertainty</td>
    <td align="left">Implicit across challenges in terms of need to improve data and modelling capacity</td>
    <td align="left">Implicit across challenges in terms of need to improve data &amp; modelling capacity &amp; adequacy for stakeholder requirements – including using ensemble modelling approaches</td>
    <td align="left">Ability to model a range of climate change scenarios and the robustness of adaptive solutions across these; uncertainty in uptake likelihood for adaptation strategies</td>
    <td align="left">Implicit across challenges in terms of need to improve data and modelling capacity and adequacy for stakeholder needs/expectations, including accuracy</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="7" align="left">Content</td>
    <td align="left">Discrete events modelling</td>
    <td align="left">Mentioned only in relation to collaboration with disaster risk management research</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Modelling the impact of extreme events</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Dynamic change modelling</td>
    <td align="left">Interdependence; Time lags in adaptation</td>
    <td align="left">Dynamics of uptake and implementation, threshold changes and carry-over effects</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Incorporating implementation of adaptations over time</td>
    <td align="left">Pathogen and vector spread</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">External limitations modelling</td>
    <td align="left">Interdependence; Scope</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Implicit in need to extend model scope and to link models of different types</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Implicit in need to extend model scope and to link models of different types</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Interactions modelling</td>
    <td align="left">Interdependence</td>
    <td align="left">Management driven by/a driver of biophysical change; Interactions between management changes and other systemic processes, &amp; between different management changes</td>
    <td align="left">Modelling livestock &amp; pasture interactions; Modelling plant responses to environmental change</td>
    <td align="left">Capturing farm and policy level strategies and their impacts; Improved modelling of environmental impacts on health, and of the biophysical processes via which adaptations cause change</td>
    <td align="left">Impacts of climate on health; Impacts of health on GHG emissions; Impacts of health on production; Interactions between health conditions, pathogens and interventions</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Management modelling</td>
    <td align="left">Cognitive bias</td>
    <td align="left">Inclusion of realistic decision making</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Scale interactions</td>
    <td align="left">Interdependence</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Model &amp; data scales – model linking, scaling data etc.</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Modelling across spatial &amp; temporal scales</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Scope</td>
    <td align="left">Scope; Diversity and number of factors</td>
    <td align="left">Novel adaptations (e.g. novel breeds) and systems (e.g. silvopasture)</td>
    <td align="left">Modelling different regions &amp; production systems (to assess CC impacts); Challenges on incorporating into models (nutrient balances, GHGs, ecosystem services, soil variables &amp; processes, pests &amp; pathogens, overwintering, multi-species swards, nutritional variables)</td>
    <td align="left">Capturing farm and policy level strategies and their impacts</td>
    <td align="left">Variation in capacity between systems and nations; Nutrition and health; Pathogen, vector and host ecology; Genetics of health; Land use change and health</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="4" align="left">Use</td>
    <td align="left">Communication</td>
    <td rowspan="4" align="left">Communication; Ethics; Expectations; Experience of decision makers; Interests</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Fit-for-purpose modelling – engaging stakeholders to improve model relevance and understanding</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Fit-for-purpose modelling – engaging stakeholders to improve model relevance and understanding</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Engagement approach</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Fit-for-purpose models: Information on models and their capabilities made easily available for stakeholders, including limitations</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">Stakeholder involvement – to gain local info of disease patterns, &amp; build trust &amp; relevance through engaging in model development; Fit-for-purpose models: Info on models &amp; their capabilities made easily available for stakeholders, inc. limitations</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Role of modellers</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">User focus</td>
    <td align="left">Included in the need for context specific scenarios relevant to stakeholders</td>
    <td align="left">Making models fit-for-purpose in relation to stakeholder needs</td>
    <td align="left">Improved evaluation of model assumptions and performance, particularly for empirical models</td>
    <td align="left">Fit-for-purpose modelling meeting stakeholder needs; Validation of empirical relationships under CC</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
