<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Future Climate Generation</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot2dot1-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1. Introduction of LARS-WG Model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LARS-WG (Long Ashton Research Station Weather Generator) is a random weather generator that can be used to simulate the historical and future meteorological data of a single station. It is a dimensionality reduction tool based on the GCM to generate local-scale climate scenarios. It uses the daily meteorological data of a given location to calculate a set of parameters for fitting probability distribution and their correlations. A synthetic weather time series of arbitrary length is generated by using the randomly selected values from the appropriate distribution [
   <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-00692">32</a>]. The model has been validated in Europe, America, and Asia with reliable high performance [
   <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-00692">33</a>]. The LARS-WG 6.0 used in this paper combines the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project 5 (CMIP5) in the IPCC Fifth Assessment Report for climate prediction. The process of weather generation is divided into the following three steps [
   <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-00692">32</a>,
   <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-00692">33</a>,
   <a rid="B34-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-16-00692">34</a>]:
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(1) Model calibration: Statistical characteristics of historical meteorological parameters, including maximum temperature (Tmax), minimum temperature (Tmin), rainfall, and radiation (Rad) were analyzed through the "station analysis" function and stored in the corresponding parameter files.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(2) Model validation: The synthetic meteorological data with the same statistical characteristics as the historical meteorological data were generated by the parameter files of historical meteorological data in the process of model calibration. According to the comparison between the statistical characteristics of historical meteorological data and synthetic meteorological data, the simulation capability and applicability of the LARS-WG model were evaluated.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(3) Generation of synthetic meteorological data: The synthetic meteorological data corresponding to the GCM climate scenario are generated by using the parameter files in the calibration process of the model.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2dot2-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. Calibration of models and generation of future meteorological parameters</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, the daily Tmax, Tmin, rainfall, and Rad of 26 meteorological stations (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f002" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f002">Figure 2</a>) in Heilongjiang Province from 1960 to 2015 were used as historical input data for LARS-WG calibration and verification. The historical meteorological data was obtained from the China National Meteorological Information Center (
   <span xlink:href="http://data.cma.cn/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://data.cma.cn/</span>). In order to evaluate the performance of LARS-WG, the Kolmogorov–Smirnov (K-S) test was performed on testing the equality of the seasonal distributions of dry and wet series (WDseries), distributions of daily rainfall (RainD), distributions of daily Tmax (TmaxD), distributions of daily Tmin (TminD), and distributions of daily Rad (RadD) calculated from the history data and downscale data, and a 
   <span class="italic">t</span> test was performed on testing equality of the monthly mean rainfall (RainM), monthly mean of Tmax (TmaxM), monthly mean of Tmin (TminM), and monthly mean of Rad(RadM). For each station, the number of WDseries tests was eight, and the number of tests for other parameters was 12. The smaller the average number of meteorological station parameters 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05, the better the performance of LARS-WG [
   <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-00692">35</a>]. 
   <a rid="ijerph-16-00692-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-00692-t001">Table 1</a> shows that LARS-WG can well simulate the above parameters, and the model is more capable of simulating the monthly distribution of each parameter than the monthly mean of each parameter in the study area of this paper.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data based on a GCM are widely regarded as the most acceptable model for studying climate change. Under different GCM scenarios, the magnitude of variation of meteorological factors is uncertain. Therefore, two RCPs under four GCMs in CMIP5 supported by LARS-WG 6.0 are selected to simulate future climate change. The main information of the four GCMs used is shown in 
   <a rid="ijerph-16-00692-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-00692-t002">Table 2</a> [
   <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-00692">36</a>]. RCP 8.5 and RCP 4.5 represent radiation forcing values of 8.5 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> and 4.5 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> by 2100, respectively [
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-00692">37</a>]. The meteorological data of two RCPs under the output of four GCMs by LARS-WG include daily Tmax, daily Tmin, daily rainfall, and daily Rad from 2021 to 2080.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
