<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot3-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. CH
  <sub>4</sub> Simulation
 </div>
 <sec id="sec2dot3dot1-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1. Introduction of DNDC Model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DNDC model is a geobiochemical model that is used to simulate greenhouse gas emissions from different agroecosystems. It has been widely used to simulate CH
   <sub>4</sub> emissions from paddy fields all over the world over the past 20 years. Numerous studies have shown that DNDC can be used to estimate CH
   <sub>4</sub> emissions from paddy fields at a regional scale [
   <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-00692">38</a>,
   <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-00692">39</a>,
   <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-00692">40</a>,
   <a rid="B41-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-16-00692">41</a>]. The model also has a good simulation performance in the study area and near latitudes [
   <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-00692">22</a>,
   <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-00692">40</a>,
   <a rid="B42-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-16-00692">42</a>]. The model consists of two parts. The first part includes three sub-models: soil climate, crop growth, and soil organic matter decomposition. According to the input meteorological, soil, crop, and farming management data, the dynamic changes of soil temperature, water, redox potential, chemical substrate concentration, and other factors in soil environmental conditions are simulated. The second part includes three sub-models of nitrification, denitrification, and fermentation, which simulate the effects of various factors in soil on microbial activity and chemical reaction rate, and calculate greenhouse gas emissions [
   <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-00692">18</a>]. The latest version of the DNDC model is DNDC95, which was used in this paper.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3dot2-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2. Calibration and Validation of DNDC </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A field experiment was used to calibrate and validate the simulation capability of the DNDC model for CH
   <sub>4</sub> emissions in this study area. The experiment was conducted in 2017 at the National Rice Irrigation Experiment Center in Suihua City, Heilongjiang Province (127°40′ E, 46°57′ N). The annual average temperature is 2~3 °C, the annual average rainfall is 500~600 mm, and the frost-free period is 128 days. The soil is loam. The bulk density of 0–10-cm soil is 1.26 g/cm
   <span class="sup">3</span>, the clay content is 21%, the porosity is 0.45%, the organic matter content is 41.8 g/kg, and the pH is 6.4. The rice variety was “Longqing 3” (
   <span class="italic">japonica</span>), which is the main local cultivar, with a planting density of 30 cm × 10 cm. It was transplanted on 20 May 2017 and harvested on 20 September 2017. Except for mid-season drainage from 1 July to 7 July 2017, the water layer was maintained in paddy fields during the rice growth period. The chemical fertilizers that were used were urea (N 46%), superphosphate (P
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>5</sub> 12%), and potassium chloride (K
   <sub>2</sub>O 60%), respectively. A total of 135 kg/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span> of N, 45 kg/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span> of P
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>5</sub>, and 80 kg/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span> of K
   <sub>2</sub>O were used. For N fertilizer, the ratio of types of fertilizer was 4.5:2:1.5:2 in the sequence of basal fertilizer: tillering fertilizer: promoting flower fertilizer: preserving flower fertilizer. K
   <sub>2</sub>O fertilizer was used twice as the basal fertilizer and 8.5 leaf age, respectively, with a ratio of 1:1. P
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>5</sub> fertilizer was applied once as the basal fertilizer. The maximum biomass values of grain, leaf, stem, and root were 4600 kg C/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span>, 1859 kg C/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span>, 1957 kg C/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span>, and 1370 kg C/hm
   <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively. The content of C and N in each part was determined by Element Analyzer (Flash 2000 HT, Thermo Fisher Science, USA), and the methods for measuring are described in reference [
   <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-00692">43</a>] and [
   <a rid="B44-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-16-00692">44</a>]. The C/N ratios of grain, leaf, stem, and root adjusted by DNDC model parameters were 46, 58, 58, and 72, respectively. The nitrogen fixation index of local rice calculated by our research group was 1.26. The daily meteorological data in the year of the experiment were derived from the automatic weather station of the experiment station, including daily Tmax, Tmin, rainfall, average wind speed, average humidity, and radiation. For the observation and calculation methods of CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, refer to reference [
   <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-00692">30</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above meteorological data, soil parameters, crop parameters, and farming measures parameters were input into the DNDC model, and the crop parameters were adjusted by the turn-and-just method. The model was calibrated and validated by comparing the measured CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes and the simulated CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes. A determinant coefficient (R
   <span class="sup">2</span>), root mean square error (RMSE), and model efficiency coefficient (EF) were used to evaluate the “goodness of fit” of the DNDC model for CH
   <sub>4</sub> flux simulation. The root mean square error (RMSE) is used to measure the consistency between the simulated and observed CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes. The EF value is less than or equal to one; a positive value indicates that the simulated values describe the trend in the measured data better than the mean of the observed values [
   <a rid="B45-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-16-00692">45</a>]. The calculation formulas are as follows:
   <div id="FD1-ijerph-16-00692" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
    <div id="mm1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
       <span class="mi">M</span>
       <span class="mi">S</span>
       <span class="mi">E</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="msqrt">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="mfrac">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">F</span>
            <span class="mi">s</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">−</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">F</span>
            <span class="mi">o</span>
           </div>
           <div class="msup">
            <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
            <span class="mn">2</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mi">n</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="FD2-ijerph-16-00692" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
    <div id="mm2" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">E</span>
       <span class="mi">F</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="munderover">
           <span class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">O</span>
            <span class="mi">i</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">−</span>
           <div accent="true" class="mover">
            <span class="mi">O</span>
            <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <div class="msup">
          <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">−</span>
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="munderover">
           <span class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msup">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">S</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">−</span>
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">O</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
             <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
            </div>
            <span class="mn">2</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="munderover">
           <span class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">O</span>
            <span class="mi">i</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">−</span>
           <div accent="true" class="mover">
            <span class="mi">O</span>
            <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <div class="msup">
          <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where, 
   <span class="italic">F
    <sub>s</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">F
    <sub>o</sub>
   </span> in Equation (1) denotes the simulated and observed CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes in the site experiment, and 
   <span class="italic">n</span> is the total number of CH
   <sub>4</sub> observations. In Equation (2), 
   <span class="italic">O
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span> are the observed CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, 
   <span class="italic">S
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span> are the simulated CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, and 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm3" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">O</span>
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> is the mean of the observed CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3dot3-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3. Calibration and Validation of DNDC Sensitivity Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CH
   <sub>4</sub> emissions from paddy fields are affected by many factors, some of which may be more sensitive than others [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-00692">46</a>]. Sensitivity analysis help to better understand the sensitivity of the model to various parameters and provide support for the calibration and validation. Therefore, sensitivity analysis of the DNDC model was performed to evaluate the response of simulation results to input parameters [
   <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-00692">18</a>,
   <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-00692">22</a>]. Climate, soil, and crop parameters of the site experiment were taken as the initial conditions for sensitivity analysis, and a single input parameter was changed within the default range of the DNDC model system, while all the other input parameters remained unchanged. Each input parameter was run 500 times to ensure the reliability of the results. For those more sensitive factors, attention should be paid during the model simulation to improve the reliability of the data.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3dot4-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.4. Constructing Regional Simulation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DNDC model needs meteorological data, soil data, crop parameters, and farmland management measures to simulate CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes from paddy fields. In this study, the annual CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes from 26 meteorological stations in the study area were simulated by the DNDC model. For CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes from 2021 to 2080, the average values of four GCMs under two RCPs were calculated respectively, and then, the spatial and temporal variations of CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes were expressed by spatial interpolation. The period 1960–2015 was divided into three periods: 1960–1979 (1970s), 1980–1999 (1990s), and 2000–2015 (2010s). The period 2021–2080 was divided into 2021–2040 (2030s), 2041–2060 (2050s), and 2061–2080 (2070s).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the simulation of the period 1960–2015, the daily meteorological data of 26 meteorological stations in Heilongjiang Province from 1960 to 2015 were selected, including daily Tmax, Tmin, average relative humidity, average wind speed, and rainfall. For the simulation of 2021–2080, the daily meteorological data of 26 meteorological stations were output by LARS-WG, including daily Tmax, Tmin, rainfall, and Rad. Considering the change of CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration under climate change, the background CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration in 1960 was 317 ppm and the growth rate was 1.58 ppm/a. For future climate simulation, the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> background concentrations were 411 ppm and 415 ppm under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 in 2021, respectively, and 531 ppm and 758 ppm in 2080, respectively [
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-00692">37</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The soil physical and chemical properties parameters at soil depths of 0 to 30-cm input for the simulation were derived from the HWSD (
   <span xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/land-water/databases-and-software/hwsd/en/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.fao.org/land-water/databases-and-software/hwsd/en/</span>), including: soil type, bulk density, clay content, organic matter content, porosity, and pH value. Paddy cultivation in different regions of the study area were derived from the “
   <span class="italic">Compilation of Paddy Field Irrigation Experiment Data in Heilongjiang Province</span>”, which included the date of paddy field preparation and paddy puddling, transplanting, mid-season drainage, fertilization regime, and harvest date of 30 experiment stations in 542 experimental years from 1952 to 2002. In order to reduce the uncertainty of the simulation results, the following assumptions were made in this study. (1) Transplanting was used for rice planting. The cultivation techniques of rice seedlings nurseries in upland bed in Heilongjiang Province began in the 1950s, and were well promoted with the development of plastic film technology in the 1960s and 1970s. This technology is in line with the cold rice cultivation environment and rice growth physiology. (2) There was no change in rice transplanting and harvesting time. Due to seedlings nursery and upland bed cultivation technology, the rice transplanting date was more flexible and less affected by temperature. Farmers in different regions depended on experience to determine fixed transplanting and harvesting dates. (3) The stubble remained 10% after harvest. In the historical period, the straw harvested in the study area was used for living fuel and animal feed. Currently, crop straw burning is prohibited in Heilongjiang Province. In the future, straw will be developed into new energy, decorative materials and other uses. (4) Setting up mid-season drainage. This technology has been widely used by farmers in the study area because it reduces the ineffective tillering of rice, improves the fertilizer utilization rate, improves soil aeration, and effectively reduces CH
   <sub>4</sub> emissions [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-00692">46</a>]. (5) There was no change in rice varieties during the study period.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3dot5-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.5. Climatic Tendency</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climatic tendency of CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes is expressed by a linear equation by using the least square method. The formulas is as follows:
   <div id="FD3-ijerph-16-00692" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
    <div id="mm4" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <div accent="true" class="mover">
         <span class="mi">Y</span>
         <span class="mo">^</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mi">i</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">t</span>
       <span class="mo">+</span>
       <span class="mi">b</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm5" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="mover">
          <span class="mi">Y</span>
          <span class="mo">^</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mi">i</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> is the fitting value of CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, 
   <span class="italic">t</span> is the corresponding year, and 
   <span class="italic">a</span> and 
   <span class="italic">b</span> are the regression coefficients.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">a</span> × 10 is the climatic tendency, which represents the change rate of CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes every 10 years (10a). The positive value indicates an increasing trend, while the negative value indicates a decreasing trend.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
