<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Calibration and Validation of DNDC and Sensitivity Analysis</div>
  <sec id="sec3dot1dot1-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1. Calibration and Validation of DNDC for CH
    <sub>4</sub> Fluxes
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparisons of the CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes observed in the site experiment with those simulated by DNDC are shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f003" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f003">Figure 3</a>. Except for individual differences, the simulation results of DNDC are in good agreement with the observed results. Regression analysis shows that the regression coefficient R
    <span class="sup">2</span> is 0.89, the slope of regression equation is close to one, and the intercept is relatively small. The correlation between simulated and observed values was very high (
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001). The RMSE value and EF value are 0.35 and 0.87, respectively. The RMSE value is relatively small, and the efficiency coefficient of the model is high, which indicates that the simulation value can well reflect the actual change rule of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes. In conclusion, DNDC can well simulate and predict the seasonal variation of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes in this study area.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot1dot2-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.2. Sensitivity Analysis of Factors to CH
    <sub>4</sub> Fluxes
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The response of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes to climate factors was studied by fluctuating 10% of the air temperature, rainfall, and atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration. As shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f004" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f004">Figure 4</a>, higher air temperature and higher atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration promote the increase of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes. This may be because the increase of air temperature is beneficial to the decomposition of soil organic matter and the activity of methanogens [
    <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-00692">7</a>]. Increased atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration provides more metabolic substrates for methane production [
    <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-00692">9</a>,
    <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-00692">10</a>]. The change of annual rainfall has little effect on CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes. With the decrease of rainfall, the CH
    <sub>4</sub> flux increases slightly.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A sensitivity analysis of soil parameters showed that soil clay content was the most sensitive factor affecting CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes, followed by soil porosity and SOC (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f005" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f005">Figure 5</a>). Soil with high clay content limits CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes due to the adsorption of clay, which limits the use of dissolved organic carbon by microorganisms. The increase of porosity will promote the oxidation of methanogens to produce CH
    <sub>4</sub>, and SOC will provide more substrates for methanogens to produce CH
    <sub>4</sub>. Since paddy fields are flooded most of the time during the rice-growing period, the change of soil moisture and dryness is small, and the soil condition is relatively stable; therefore, the effects of soil bulk density, field water capacity, and pH on CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes are small [
    <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-00692">22</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A sensitivity analysis of crop parameters showed that CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes were more sensitive to maximum yield, plant C/N ratio, and thermal degree days for maturity (TDD), but less sensitive to the N fixation index (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f006" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f006">Figure 6</a>). With the increase of the above parameters, CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes showed an increasing trend. This is because with the increase of TDD, more dry matter can be accumulated in crops with the same proportion of biomass distribution in different parts of the plant. Increasing the maximum yield also increases biomass accumulation in plants, since it is beneficial for increasing plant droppings and root exudates, which provides more carbon sources for CH
    <sub>4</sub> production. Increasing the plant C/N ratio also provides more carbon sources for methanogens.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Temporal and Spatial Distribution Characteristics of CH
   <sub>4</sub> Fluxes
  </div>
  <sec id="sec3dot2dot1-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. Climate Change During the Study Period</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The historical and future changes of climate parameters in the study area are shown in 
    <a rid="ijerph-16-00692-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-00692-t003">Table 3</a>. During the 1970s–2010s, the daily Tmin, daily Tmax, annual rainfall, and atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration showed an increasing trend, while the annual Rad showed a decreasing trend. During the 2030s–2070s, the predicted daily Tmin, daily Tmax, annual rainfall, and atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration continued to increase, and the increase of four meteorological parameters under RCP 8.5 was greater than that under RCP 4.5. However, the annual Rad continued to decrease, and the reduction under RCP 8.5 was greater than that under RCP 4.5.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot2dot2-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.2. Temporal and Spatial Distribution Characteristics of CH
    <sub>4</sub> Fluxes under Historical Climate.
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial distribution of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes and its climatic tendency in the study area from 1960 to 2015 is shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f007" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f007">Figure 7</a>. CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes ranged from 98.27 kg C/ha to 215.94 kg C/ha, with an average of 145.56 kg C/ha. CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes in the 1970s, 1990s, and 2010s were 125.80 kg C/ha, 146.42 kg C/ha, and 170.57 kg C/ha, respectively. CH
    <sub>4</sub> emission fluxes showed a decreasing trend from west to east. The high-value areas were mainly distributed in the western part with an average of more than 175 kg C/ha. The low-value areas were mainly distributes in the northern area, with an annual average value of less than 120 kg C/ha. The climatic tendency was between 8.78–14.43 kg C/ha/(10a) with an average of 11.88 kg C/ha/(10a). The average CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes from 26 meteorological stations in the study area showed a fluctuating and increasing trend (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f008" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f008">Figure 8</a>). Among them, the northern and western parts increased at a higher rate, with a climatic tendency rate of more than 14 kg C/ha/(10a).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the 1970s to the 1990s, the CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes showed an increasing trend. The climatic tendency was between 9.87–13.40 kg C/ha/(10a), with an average of 11.42 kg C/ha/(10a). Among them, the climatic tendency in the central part was relatively low, while the climatic tendency in the eastern, southern, and western regions were relatively high. From the 1990s to the 2010s, the average climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes was slightly higher than that of the 1970s–1990s, and the climatic tendency was between 8.62–17.37 kg C/ha/(10a), with an average of 12.62 kg C/ha/(10a). In the eastern region, the increasing rate slowed down, while in the northern part, the increasing rate increased dramatically. The climatic tendency of the northern part was greater than 17 kg C/ha/(10a).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot2dot3-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.3. Spatial and Temporal Distribution Characteristics of Methane Emission Fluxes in Future Climate</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taking the mean of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes from 1960 to 2015 as the background value of historical CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes, the temporal and spatial variation characteristics of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes in the study area under future climate change were studied. From 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f009" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f009">Figure 9</a> and 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f010" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f010">Figure 10</a>, it can be seen that under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5, CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes ranged from 160.00 to 318.68 kg C/ha and 167.15 to 442.07 kg C/ha between 2021–2080, with average values of 213.46 kg C/ha and 252.19 kg C/ha, respectively. Compared with historical background values, CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes increased by 67.50 kg C/ha and 106.23 kg C/ha between 2021–2080 under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5, respectively. The average CH
    <sub>4</sub> flux under RCP 8.5 increased more than that under RCP 4.5. The spatial distribution of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 between the future was similar to the historical distribution of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes, and it tended to decrease from west to east. However, under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5, the climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes between 2021–2080 ranged from 10.89 to 18.46 kg C/ha/(10a) and 24.21 to 44.02 kg C/ha/(10a), respectively. The average climatic tendencies were 13.40 kg C/ha/(10a) and 29.86 kg C/ha/(10a), respectively. Compared with the historical climatic tendency, the climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes increased by 1.52 kg C/ha/(10a) and 17.98 kg C/ha/(10a) respectively between 2021–2080 under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5. The climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes under RCP 8.5 was higher than that under RCP 4.5. The spatial distribution of the climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes was different from that between 1960–2015. The climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes decreased from west to east between 2021–2080. The high-value area was mainly distributed in the west, while the low-value area was mainly distributed in the east.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under RCP 4.5, the CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes of each GCM in different periods were quite different, while the difference of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes of each GCM in different periods was small under RCP 8.5 (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f011" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f011">Figure 11</a>). Under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5, the climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes in the 2030s–2050s ranged from 12.45 kg C/ha/(10a) to 24.34 kg C/ha/(10a) and 21.11 kg C/ha/(10a) to 35.59 kg C/ha/(10a), with an average of 16.34 kg C/ha/(10a) and 24.09 kg C/ha/(10a), respectively. The climatic tendency distribution of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 was similar. However, the climatic tendency under RCP 8.5 was higher than that under RCP 4.5. In the 2050s–2070s period, the climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 ranged from 7.31 kg C/ha/(10a) to 10.51 kg C/ha/(10a) and 20.31 kg C/ha/(10a) to 44.33 kg C/ha/(10a), with an average of 8.61 kg C/ha/(10a) and 28.86 kg C/ha/(10a), respectively. Compared with the 2030s–2050s stage, the climatic tendency under RCP 8.5 continued to increase spatially and temporally, with a big increase in the central part, while the increase in the northern part was smaller. However, the climatic tendency under RCP 4.5 tended to decrease, and was even less than the climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes in the historical period. The decreases in the north and west parts were larger. Overall, the spatial distribution of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes in the 2030s, 2050s, and 2070s stages under RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 showed a decreasing trend from west to east temporally, and showed a continuous increasing trend spatially. The climatic tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> fluxes varied greatly in different periods. Under RCP 4.5, the climate tendency of CH
    <sub>4</sub> flux decreased, while under RCP 8.5, the climate tendency increased.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-ijerph-16-00692" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Effects of Climate Factors on CH
   <sub>4</sub> Fluxes
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the uncertainty of future meteorological data is high, in order to study the effects of climate factors on CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, the correlation analysis and regression analysis of historical meteorological data and CH
   <sub>4</sub> emission fluxes at each station in the study area were carried out. From 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f012" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f012">Figure 12</a>, CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes increased with the increase of Tmax, Tmin, and atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration, and were significantly correlated with them (
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001). The CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes decreased first and then increased with the increase of rainfall and Rad, and the correlation between them was not significant. Therefore, the increase of Tmax, Tmin, and atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration at each station in the study area from 1960 to 2015 (
   <a rid="ijerph-16-00692-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-00692-t003">Table 3</a>) promoted the increase of CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes. Compared with historical average, the Tmin, Tmax, and the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration in the 2070s period increased by 1.90 °C, 2.17 °C, and 92.80 ppm (
   <a rid="ijerph-16-00692-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-00692-t003">Table 3</a>), respectively, resulting in a 92.8 kg C/ha increase in CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, which was an increase of 64%. Under RCP 8.5 in the 2070s, the Tmin, Tmax, and atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration increased by 3.71 °C, 3.86 °C, and 172.69 ppm (
   <a rid="ijerph-16-00692-t003" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-00692-t003">Table 3</a>), respectively, resulting in an increase of 172.69 kg C/ha in CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, with an increase of 118%, which was greater than that under RCP 4.5. The above analysis showed that increasing temperature and atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration can accelerate CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to further study the effects of atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration and temperature on CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, the four simulation scenarios are as follows: (1) the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration and temperature do not change; (2) the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration increases, but the temperature does not change; (3) the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration does not change, but the temperature changes; and (4) both the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration and temperature change. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-00692-f013" href="#ijerph-16-00692-f013">Figure 13</a> showed the response of SOC content in the 0–20-cm soil layer, biomass (including leaf, stem, and root), and CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes to climate changes under RCP 4.5 in the site experiment. Increased atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration and successive years of stubble returning would lead to the increase of SOC content in the 0–20-cm soil layer and the accumulation of plant biomass year by year. The decomposition of SOC would be promoted by the increase of air temperature, and the plant biomass will be increased in the coming 20 years. Compared with scenario one, the CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes in scenario two, scenario three, and scenario four increased by 13.74%, 16.31%, and 32.78% at the end of the simulation. CO
   <sub>2</sub> enhanced the root system of crops through plant photosynthesis [
   <a rid="B47-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-16-00692">47</a>], provided more metabolic substrates for CH
   <sub>4</sub> production, and increased the aerenchyma of plants by increasing the biomass, thus providing a channel for CH
   <sub>4</sub> emissions [
   <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-00692">48</a>]. Previous studies have shown that CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes had a significant correlation with the biomass of crops [
   <a rid="B49-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-16-00692">49</a>]. Increasing soil temperature would promote the decomposition of SOC and increase the activity and amount of methanogens. Compared with CH
   <sub>4</sub> production, the CH
   <sub>4</sub> oxidation process is less affected by temperature [
   <a rid="B50-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-16-00692">50</a>]. Under future climate scenarios, atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration and temperature will affect the CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes of paddy field through the joint effects of soil and plant.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
