<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overexploitation of natural resources is one of the greatest anthropogenic pressures impacting the structure and functioning of marine ecosystems over short time scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Changes in fish communities showing shifts in the trophic-web and declines in mean trophic level have been observed in Europe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. The ecosystem approach to fisheries (EAF) aims to achieve sustainable fisheries by combining broad ecological sustainability of stocks with the socio-economic viability of the fishing industry at local and regional scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. This approach is design to ensure a sustainable state of marine food webs (i.e. no overexploitation), allowing continued fishing to support human well-being. While current fisheries management relies mostly on single species assessment models, recent studies have underlined the importance of implementing EAF to explore fishing management scenarios
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. However, EAF requires ecosystem models to be parameterised over a historical time period to enable forecasts of future fish biomass.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing-induced ecosystem changes often coincide with rising temperatures driven by climate change, requiring climate-change effects to also be considered in model forecasts. An integrated methodology including the temperature tolerances of species is therefore needed to assess the impact of climate change on fisheries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, on ecosystem diversity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, and the social-ecological responses to potential ecosystem changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both climate variability and climate change affect marine ecosystems: ‘climate variability’ is a natural short-term fluctuation over a long-term average
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span> such as ocean-atmosphere coupling phenomena and decadal oscillations. Climate variability has often been identified as a major driver of ecosystem dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, and quantified using indicators such as the Pacific Decadal Oscillation (PDO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, El Niño-Southern Oscillation (ENSO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, Atlantic Multidecadal Oscillation (AMO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> and North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. Climate change, on the other hand, refers to the long-term anthropogenic-mediated modifications of the Earth’s climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span> caused by global increases in gas emissions and its subsequent consequences (e.g. rising temperatures). Global-scale climate models showed a rapid increase of ocean temperature in the last forty years with a global average increase of 0.11 °C per decade
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Climate change has been recognised as one of the greatest threats to biodiversity of this century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, affecting the integrity of ecosystem resources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although oceans exhibit a slower warming trend than land, the distributions of pelagic, demersal and benthic marine species have shown higher rates of poleward migrations than terrestrial species due to fewer physical barriers in the oceans
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. However, even in the marine environment, physical barriers (e.g. current, gyre, trenches), lack of suitable habitat (e.g. topography, depth, oxygen) and antagonistic trophic interactions (e.g. competition and predation) can represent barriers to temperature-driven poleward dispersal
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. These barriers to dispersal make some species more vulnerable to climate change than others
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Poleward distribution shifts are increasing the relative presence and abundance of warm-water species in mid- to high-latitude regions (such as the Bering Sea, Barents Sea, Nordic Sea, North Sea, and Tasman Sea) and thus affecting community functioning and diversity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predicting the impact of climate change is challenging given the specific responses of marine organisms at regional scales, and the cascading effects of these responses (synergistic or antagonistic) on the entire ecosystem
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. Anthropogenic pressures, such as fishing, pollution, eutrophication and habitat modification, are increasing ecosystem vulnerability by decreasing resilience, adding even more complexity to the process of assessing the impact of climate change at a local scale
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. Species populations and distributions are also regulated by competition, predation and environmental and human pressures. Ecosystem modelling approaches address these complexities directly and can help to understand and predict ecosystem shifts. Despite being more realistic, however, predictions from complex models that include ecological interactions usually have a high degree of uncertainty
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reducing uncertainty in predictions of climate-induced changes in ecosystems is therefore needed to understand their societal consequences. A better understanding of the nature and scale of the response of marine species to climate change will improve predictions of the ecological and economic impacts on human systems, and contribute towards management mitigation strategies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. In cold water ecosystems, for example, local native species might be negatively affected by higher temperatures, but the increase in the abundance of warm water species may allow exploitation of new stocks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we used an Ecopath with Ecosim (EwE) ecosystem model of the West Coast of Scotland (WCS)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> to assess the combined impacts of fishing and rising temperature on species consumption. The model (which included 41 functional groups
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>) was parameterised with species thermal tolerances and used to simulate the impact of fishing by comparing status-quo and maximum sustainable yield (MSY) scenarios, and to assess the impact of climate change on important commercial stocks. The impact of climate change was tested using future rising temperature under IPCC Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) scenarios, while keeping fishing pressure constant at rates deemed consistent with single species MSY. Results were presented for target species identified as either depleted stocks (Atlantic cod, whiting and herring), increasing stocks (saithe and hake), and other important contributors in terms of landings (haddock, mackerel, horse mackerel and Norway lobster), as well as certain top-predators (grey seals) that exert top-down control on the ecosystem
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
