<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation scenarios</div>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exploring the effect of future scenarios requires the Ecosim model to reproduce or hindcast the historical observations. Thus, the “status quo” scenario represented the future projections using the model drivers such as fishing mortalities (F
  <sub>status_quo</sub>) and water temperature set to that of the last year of the historical observed data (2013). The effect of sustainable fishing for the target species was then assessed comparing biomasses and catches of the “status quo” scenario with that of a “maximum sustainable yields” (MSY) scenario which used single-species fishing mortalities at the maximum sustainable yields (F
  <sub>MSY</sub>) determined by ICES (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). When not available for VIa, F
  <sub>MSY</sub> values of neighbouring stocks were taken as best available estimates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequently we tested the impact of rising temperature under IPCC-RCP scenarios while keeping fishing pressure constant at rates consistent with MSY. Future SST projections were extracted from the Royal Netherlands Meteorological Institute Climate Explorer portal (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://climexp.knmi.nl" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://climexp.knmi.nl</span>) within the study area rectangle from the climate changing multi-model global ensemble means for 2.6, 4.5, 6.5 and 8.5 greenhouse gas concentration scenarios (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.5 and RCP8.5 scenarios). Thirty-two model outputs, sourced from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 5 (CMIP5), were extracted for the study area with temperatures fluctuating around the mean by 6–7 °C (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4</a>). The mean projected rates of increase for all of the RCP scenarios (bold colour lines for 2006–2100 in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4</a>) were then applied as anomalies to the observed DIT to predict future temperature. As a calculated mean across thirty-two global model outputs, the SST rates extracted under the RCP scenarios (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4</a>) were de-trended from the impact of climate variability and showed a smaller variability than DIT (black points in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). A 3-year moving average of the historical standard deviation (STDEV) was applied to the anomalies to replicate the variability of the historical DIT trend.
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Atlantic Multidecadal Oscillation (AMO) is calculated as an anomaly of the SST and shows a stronger effect in the North Atlantic region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. The smoothed/unsmoothed AMO signal (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/timeseries/AMO/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/timeseries/AMO/</span>) defined from de-trended patterns of SST variability in the North Atlantic, shows clear positive and negative phases with a frequency of 60–70 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>. In 2012 the AMO reached the end of its positive ‘warming’ phase and approached the start of the “cooling phase” (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). Thus, to predict the future AMO trend, the smoothed observed pattern was mirrored from 2007 to 2100 to allow the re-occurrences of historical phases at intervals of approximately 60–65 years (between the lowest values of the historical negative phases, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). Finally, the AMO projections were added to the temperature projections (DIT + STDEV + AMO) to simulate the effect of this climate index on the future water temperature projections (2014-2100 in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
