<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The initial model (Supplementary Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>–
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S6</a>), without temperature as an ecosystem driver, showed a relatively high sum of squares (SS) between predicted and observed data for the baseline (1620) and also when including fishing (1219) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison across selected stepwise fitting interactions and the model baseline, showing the number of total parameters estimated (Vulnerabilities (Vs) + number of anomaly spline points (PP_anomaly)), the model sum of squares (SS), the SS percentage of contribution to the fitting, the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) and the AIC weights.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>Name</th>
      <th>Parameters estimated</th>
      <th>SS</th>
      <th>contribution to SS fitting</th>
      <th>AIC</th>
      <th>Akaike weight</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="3">without temperature</td>
      <td>Baseline</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1620</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>256</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1219</td>
      <td>25%</td>
      <td>−151</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Fishing + 24 Vs + 3 PP_anomaly</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">27</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">614</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">62%</span>
      </td>
      <td>−
       <span class="bold">1079</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">0.61</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="10">with temperature</td>
      <td>Baseline</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1515</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>158</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Baseline + 33 Vs</td>
      <td>33</td>
      <td>1033</td>
      <td>32%</td>
      <td>−323</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Baseline + 5 PP_anomaly</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>1484</td>
      <td>2%</td>
      <td>139</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>1126</td>
      <td>26%</td>
      <td>−266</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing + 33 Vs</td>
      <td>33</td>
      <td>793</td>
      <td>48%</td>
      <td>−702</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing + 5 PP_anomaly</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>1038</td>
      <td>32%</td>
      <td>−372</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing + 24 Vs + 3 PP_anomaly</td>
      <td>27</td>
      <td>632</td>
      <td>58%</td>
      <td>−1040</td>
      <td>0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Fishing + 33 Vs + 5 PP_anomaly</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">38</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">607</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">60</span>%
      </td>
      <td>−
       <span class="bold">1076</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">0.25</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing + 36 v + 3pp</td>
      <td>39</td>
      <td>606</td>
      <td>60%</td>
      <td>−1075</td>
      <td>0.15</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Fishing + 36 v + 4pp</td>
      <td>40</td>
      <td>603</td>
      <td>60%</td>
      <td>−1073</td>
      <td>0.06</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>In bold the best fitted models.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model was fitted to observed time-series identifying the best fitted model by the lowest Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Adding fishing, the strength of trophic interactions expressed as vulnerabilities (Vs), and the impact of a primary productivity anomaly (PP_anomaly) applied to ecosystem primary producers, increased the fit of the model reducing the SS by 62% and reducing the AIC from 256 to -1079 (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The Akaike weight for this interaction also indicated a 0.61 probability that this is the best fitted model when not including temperature (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Optimum temperatures and thermal tolerances of each functional group were then added into the model as response functions to water temperature (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). The species temperature tolerances ranked by optimum values (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>) show the preference of lower optimum temperatures and tolerances for north Atlantic boreal species such as herring (blue, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>), and Atlantic cod, haddock, grey and harbour seals, saithe and kelp, and higher optimum temperatures and tolerances for more widely distributed eurythermal species such as horse mackerel, Norway lobster (red, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>), blue whiting, sprat and mackerel. The tolerances around optimum temperatures for eurythermal species were heterogeneous across species often showing lower tolerances for benthic-demersal groups (epifauna, anglerfish, flatfish, other benthopelagic species, poor cod, and Norway lobster) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Species thermal response functions (for Norway lobster, a eurythermal species (red, optimum temperature = 13.8 °C) and for herring, a boreal species (blue, optimum temperature = 4.6 °C)). The intercept between water temperature (e.g. 10.5 °C) and the species response functions determined the consumption rate scaling factor (i.e. 0.54 and 0.7 for Norway lobster and herring respectively). (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Cumulative temperature tolerance graphs ranked by optimum temperature (bold black line) also showing maximum (upper limit of dark orange bar) and minimum (upper limit of white bar) temperatures and the 90
     <span class="sup">th</span> (upper limit of light orange bar) and 10
     <span class="sup">th</span> (upper limit of blue bar) percentiles for each functional group.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2017_13220_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e811" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The addition of temperature response functions by functional group (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>) (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S8</a>) combined with depth integrated water temperature (DIT, black points in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) reduced the AIC for the baseline (i.e. no fishing) to 158 from 256 and for the model with fishing interactions to -266 from -151 (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The addition of temperature as an ecosystem driver with the related functional group temperature niches also allowed the simulation of future DIT temperature scenarios (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Depth integrated temperature (DIT) data used in Ecosim simulations. Historical DIT data (black points) were used to parameterise the model whilst status quo (constant water temperature measured in 2013 – black solid line) and modified climate changing multi-model ensemble means (RCP2.6–solid purple line; RCP4.5–solid blue line; RCP6.5–solid green line; RCP8.5–solid red line) were used for predicting future scenarios.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2017_13220_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e839" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The best-fit model with temperature showed an improvement in fit as predicted by the SS of 60% reducing the AIC from 158 to -1076 (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). It included fishing, 33 vulnerabilities (Vs, Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S7</a>) and a PP_anomaly function with 5 spline points (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). In comparison with the baseline model, the inclusion of the trophic interactions only (e.g. 33 vulnerabilities) improved the SS of the model fit by 32% (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Only including the anomaly (with 5 spline points) had the lowest effect (2%), reducing the AIC to 139 from 158 (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The Akaike weights indicated a range of models with an AIC of approximately -1076 which could be the best fitted model (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Temporal trends of predicted (black line) and observed (points) phytoplankton biomass vs the primary production anomaly (PP_anomaly, dashed line) showing the potential effect of the PP_anomaly on improving the phytoplankton fitting; (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Loess function showing correlation of PP_anomaly and smoothed AMO; (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) correlation between AMO and depth integrated temperature (DIT).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2017_13220_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e879" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within the 33 estimated vulnerabilities, four top-predators showed sensitive top-down control on their prey (i.e. v
  <span class="italic">ij</span> &gt; 2): grey seals, cetaceans, mature cod and saithe, whist pelagic fish (i.e. benthopelagic fish and other pelagic fish groups) as well as large and small zooplankton, and benthic groups such crabs, other benthic crustaceans, and scallops were all bottom-up controlled with 1 &lt; v
  <span class="italic">ij</span> &lt; 2 (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S7</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PP_anomaly function estimated by the model hindcast from 1985-2013 is significantly correlated with the smoothed AMO climate function (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>, Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). Both smoothed and unsmoothed AMO were significantly correlated with Sea Surface Temperature (SST) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>, Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). No correlation was found between the PP_anomaly and the NAOI or the SST (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>).
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spearman correlation values and statistical significance within SST, AMO, NAOI and PP_anomaly.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>R
       <span class="sup">2</span>, 
       <span class="italic">p-value</span>
      </th>
      <th>SST</th>
      <th>AMO_smoothed</th>
      <th>AMO_unsmoothed</th>
      <th>NAOI</th>
      <th>PP_anomaly</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>SST</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">0.65</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">0.67</span>
      </td>
      <td>0.36</td>
      <td>0.50</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>AMO_smoothed</td>
      <td>***</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">082</span>
      </td>
      <td>−0.22</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">0.72</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>AMO_unsmoothed</td>
      <td>***</td>
      <td>***</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td/>
      <td/>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>NAOI</td>
      <td>**</td>
      <td>–</td>
      <td>**</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0.25</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>PP_anomaly</td>
      <td>**</td>
      <td>***</td>
      <td>**</td>
      <td>–</td>
      <td>1</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Symbols indicate the levels of significance: ***p &lt; 0.001, **p &lt; 0.01, *p &lt; 0.05 and –no significance.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
