<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The planktonic foraminifera SCOR does not show positive covariation with a Cenozoic SCOR curve for the coccolithophores, another important calcifying plankton group. Instead, their raw patterns are negatively correlated (Spearman's 
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic> = −0.28) and first differences are not significantly correlated (
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic> = 0.15, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.06). Although preservation can affect the local relative abundance of these two groups in the sediment [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], it does not explain the different SCOR patterns, because expansion or contraction of the global extent of deep-sea carbonate deposition would cause the preserved global occupancy of both calcifying groups to increase or decrease in similar ways. Aspects of the Cenozoic coccolithophore SCOR pattern have been linked to proxy records of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] and suggest that these calcifying phytoplankton could thrive in a high-CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> world [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Cooling and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> decline across the Eocene–Oligocene transition were accompanied by a lowering of the carbonate compensation depth, which has been attributed to changes in the supply of weathering products to the ocean [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Like the coccolithophores [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], however, planktonic foraminifera show declining SCOR across this transition, which is opposite to that expected if SCORs were biased upwards by enhanced deep-sea preservation. On the other hand, if species absence/presence were random with respect to global abundance, then SCOR would suffer from increased short-term volatility, but Poseidon experiments show that even under such conditions, SCOR can track relative changes in global abundance (electronic supplementary material, figure S5). For the 25 sites common to both databases, the age models for the NSB data may deviate from those in the DOT record, but the age models are not systematically offset (electronic supplementary material, figure S7); hence, the presence of age model noise should weaken any statistical associations and bias against our results. Finally, we note that although the number and global coverage of sites in the NSB data decrease with age, this temporal decay of spatial sampling coverage in itself does not create a systematic bias in SCOR (electronic supplementary material, figure S8).
</p>
