<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One should note that the vulnerability of infrastructure in general to climate change has recently become a topic of debate and research among engineers, researchers, and policy makers [
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Here, we evaluate the vulnerability of 89,089 simply supported steel girder bridges (hereinafter SSSG bridges) in the U.S. due to clogged joints and climate change effects by focusing on the capacity of the main load carrying girders. The superstructure of the 89,089 bridges analyzed comprise of steel-concrete composite sections (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec004">Materials and methods</xref>). The NBI database classifies bridges by the type of material they were built with–steel, concrete, wood, masonry as well as the type of their structural design such as girder, truss, arch, suspension, stayed, box girder, among others [
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The girder type, which consists of two or more longitudinal beams that span over the piers to support the superstructure weight and the traffic load, is by far the most common design type of bridges built in U.S. as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0223307.g003">Fig 3</xref>. For instance, among the Interstate highway bridges, which carry the largest volume of the nation’s traffic, the girder bridge type corresponds to approximately 60% (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0223307.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). We acknowledge that other types of steel bridges are configured with expansion joints and in such case clogging of the joints in these bridges could give rise to global as well as local problems. This could include for example rib-to-deck joints in orthotropic bridge systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]; however, these types of bridges were not the focus of this study.
</p>
