<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2e" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessment Framework Development</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each risk factor was assessed for each species using information from the literature regarding the natural history of the species and anticipated changes due to climate change. A summary of each species' risk level associated with climate change for each risk factor narrative, as well as confidence scores can be found in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108899.s001" href="#pone.0108899.s001">Appendices S1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108899.s002" href="#pone.0108899.s002">S2</a>. For each risk factor, for each species, we also included a subjective confidence score (1 = low to 5 = high confidence). We recognize that a species might have increased extinction risk due to climate change, but it might not increase enough to change risk categories.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We described changes in risk using two systems: a numeric scoring system that had maximum values for each factor of 5, and a graphical depiction of the change in risk using arrows because we thought they were more intuitive for rapid visual assessment of changes and patterns. Risk factors were scaled from 0 to 5 to match PIF scaling. For the three habitat factors (1–3), we allowed for the possibility of improved conditions due to climate change. Improvement resulted in negative scores (or down–arrows) to show reduced risk. The factors, and their subdivision and scoring, are shown in 
  <a rid="pone-0108899-t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone-0108899-t001">Table 1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For our purposes, we decided that an increase in risk score of 10 (equivalent to 4 ↑s; the arrows indicate the direction and degree of effect) was sufficient to increase by a single risk category because a score of 10 would mean that a species is at extreme risk in two of the six categories. This assignment is a first approximation based on best professional judgment cf. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Panjabi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Panjabi1">[32]</a>, but should be revisited as more information about shorebird ecology and vulnerability to habitat changes becomes available.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the importance of our decision for how much change in risk is sufficient to cause a change in risk category, we did a sensitivity analysis. Specifically, we assessed the sensitivity of our results – which species were placed into which risk category – to the amount of change in extinction risk that was required for a species to change risk categories. We did this by making the criterion for changing categories more sensitive, requiring the accumulation of only 3 arrows to make the transition between risk categories. We also evaluated the effect of making the criterion less sensitive, evaluating the effects of requiring 5, 6 and 7 arrows to allow a species to change risk categories. If our method is insensitive to this criterion, we would expect little change in categorization with changing criteria.</p>
</sec>
