<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many species of shorebirds are the focus of conservation efforts aimed at reversing population declines e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Morrison2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Morrison2">[9]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Nebel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Nebel1">[100]</a>, so there is a need to prioritize conservation actions that can have the largest impact on the species most in need. The system currently in use for prioritizing shorebird conservation efforts in the United States was developed in 1999–2001 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>, and did not explicitly include vulnerability to the impacts of a changing climate, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Godet1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Godet1">[101]</a>. Many studies have shown that climate change poses risks to populations of plants and animals and that impacts to vulnerable species are already occurring, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Parmesan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Parmesan1">[102]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-MacLean1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-MacLean1">[104]</a>. It is expected that such adverse impacts will become more severe and widespread in the future as the climate continues to change. One major application of the system developed in the present study would be to revise the priority scores given to shorebird species by updating the threat scores with the information presented here regarding vulnerability to climate change. We recommend that the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service revise shorebird priority scores as suggested here, so that the impacts of a changing climate can be more fully integrated into efforts to conserve shorebirds. In addition to applying this information to shorebird species, the same approach could also be applied to other birds. The Partners–in–Flight prioritization system also could be updated to include the approach presented here, if the information on relative risks were collected for other species. This would allow a similar update to reflect vulnerability to climate change across a wide range of bird taxa. We do note that the species assessments and criteria assigned in this manuscript should be considered as first approximations, and will undoubtedly be revised with further discussion by a wider audience. Our primary goal was to establish a system for evaluating the increased risk to species from climate change with respect to existing threat assessments, and to start a discussion about the appropriate values for various species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shorebird populations and flyways across the planet are currently being affected by other stressors, many of them unknown, in addition to climate change, e.g., 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-International1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-International1">[5]</a>. These impacts are resulting in severe population reductions 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Morrison1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Morrison1">[6]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Bart1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Bart1">[8]</a>. Based on our analyses, adding the stresses and risks imposed by a changing climate to this already threatened baseline renders shorebirds even more vulnerable to extinction. If we are correctly to understand the risks to which shorebirds are exposed, and to identify and implement effective conservation strategies and actions, it is important that we understand these vulnerabilities, particularly those that will occur due to climate change. The purpose of this study was to assess the climate change risks to shorebirds and incorporate these into existing vulnerability evaluations so that we gain a better understanding of the entire panoply of risk factors to which these species are exposed, and their resulting overall vulnerabilities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on our results it appears that shorebirds, as a group, are likely to be highly vulnerable to the changing climate. These vulnerabilities are due to a number of factors. First, many species breed, migrate through, or winter in areas that are likely to be severely impacted by climate change (particularly arctic tundra, coastal breeding, and wintering, and migration stopover sites). Second, the extensive migrations that many of them undertake expose them to risks of changing weather patterns (increased frequencies and intensities of hurricanes, for example) 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Klaassen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Klaassen1">[98]</a>. Shorebirds that require particular staging areas might be more vulnerable to climate change than are those species using stopover sites 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Iwamura1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Iwamura1">[95]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Warnock2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Warnock2">[105]</a>. Lastly, the ecological synchronicities that many shorebirds depend on (e.g., the complementary timing of the arctic snowmelt and invertebrate prey availability) might suffer disruptions 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-GrattoTrevor1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-GrattoTrevor1">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Galbraith1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Galbraith1">[21]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-SmallLorenz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-SmallLorenz1">[24]</a>. Our results reflect these vulnerabilities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of the 52 shorebird taxa (49 species, 3 split into 2 populations) that breed in North America and that we evaluated, 45 (87%) were predicted to exhibit an increased extinction risk when the risks posed by climate change were added to their current vulnerabilities as estimated in the U.S. Shorebird Conservation Plan 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>. No species was reclassified into a lower–risk category, although prior to the analysis it had been a possibility. The factors responsible for these increased vulnerabilities were risks of: loss of breeding habitat (particularly for arctic– and coastal–breeders); loss of coastal and inland migration stopover habitats due to sea level rise and drought; and loss of coastal wintering habitat due to sea level rise. Of particular note, for high-Arctic breeders, there is minimal latitude and land for northward range expansion. Extreme weather events were also projected to increase vulnerabilities due to negative effects on habitat, migration mortality, and disruption of ecological synchronicities, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Saino1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Saino1">[94]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increased vulnerabilities of 10 species could not be accommodated using the existing PIF scoring system and we had to create an even higher level of risk than is currently available. These Critical species (including coastal Snowy, Piping, and Wilson's plovers, and inland species such as Mountain Plover and Long–billed Curlew) are already at a high risk level due to other stressors (particularly anthropogenic habitat destruction) and their populations are already declining and jeopardized 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Panjabi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Panjabi1">[32]</a>. The addition of climate change to their risk factors raises them to an even higher level of vulnerability, which may pose even higher threats to their continued existence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also of concern is that the addition of climate change to the vulnerability calculations elevates another 18 species to the highest U.S. Shorebird Conservation Plan risk category. Thus, a total of 28 of 49 species are now at the highest risk category under the U.S. Shorebird Conservation Plan, or they exceeded this risk level and had to have an additional category created. The degree to which species changed risk categories was sensitive to our rules of category change. To some degree, as with population viability analyses using stochastic simulation models, which rule we use for category change is a value judgment 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Reed2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Reed2">[106]</a>. Regardless of what rules are used, however, our analysis suggests that shorebirds will have increased vulnerability under climate change, perhaps to a large extent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our assessment of extinction risk might be criticized because it does not allow for adaptive capacity in shorebird populations. That is, shorebirds might modify their breeding, migratory, and/or wintering habitat use, foraging, and/or timing to accommodate the changing climate. We already know that some shorebirds in Western Europe have apparently truncated their fall migrations to winter in the Baltic, rather than in oceanic Atlantic countries, such as the UK 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-MacLean1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-MacLean1">[104]</a>. Previously, the winter conditions in the Baltic were so harsh that birds had to move farther to exploit the milder conditions of the UK, Holland, etc. Thus, the ameliorating winter conditions in the Baltic have encouraged changes in migration distance 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-MacLean1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-MacLean1">[104]</a>. Similarly, In North America, some migratory populations of Hudsonian Godwits have advanced their timing of migration during warm periods, which allows their breeding to synchronize with peak food abundance, while other populations have not 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Senner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Senner1">[107]</a>. There also is some evidence that Semipalmated and Pectoral sandpipers and Red–necked and Red phalaropes have been observed breeding earlier during warm years 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Liebezeit1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Liebezeit1">[108]</a>. As another example of adapting to changing conditions, Dunlin nestlings can exhibit accelerated growth during periods of low food availability during warm conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-McKinnon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-McKinnon1">[109]</a>. However, it would be unwise of us to assume that such adaptive capacities were likely to apply across all shorebird species because there is evidence that high Arctic shorebird species may have little capacity for adaptation due to low genetic variability resulting from bottleneck events from previous climate shifts 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Meltofte1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Meltofte1">[110]</a>. Time constraints can also cause conflicts among competing life–history requirements, as has been reported in Pied Flycatchers 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Both2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Both2">[111]</a>. Clearly more research needs to be done to determine the degree to which climate adaptation might occur in shorebirds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What would it take to accurately and precisely predict change in extinction risk due to climate change for migratory shorebirds, or for any species, rather than taking the relatively coarse approach we did in this paper? Certainly there have been detailed assessments of expected regional changes in shorebird populations in response to climate change 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Rehfisch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Rehfisch1">[112]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-AielloLammens1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-AielloLammens1">[113]</a>, and one could create models to link species to landscapes via simulation. But what would be required for accurate, reliable predictions? Strictly speaking, to build a convincing case for an accurate prediction, the first thing we would need is accurate models of climate change. Although there are many models of climate change, and they agree in general with climate trends, there is still a great deal of uncertainty in the exact amount of changes in expected temperature and precipitation, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Arajo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Arajo1">[114]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Davidson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Davidson1">[115]</a>, particularly at the fine geographic scale that would be needed to understand biotic responses, including the effects of changes in wind patterns 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Gill1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Gill1">[116]</a>. Because hydrological models are complex (i.e., non–linear, with feedback and chaotic dynamics), more accurate data are unlikely to improve model predictions 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Vano1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Vano1">[117]</a>. In addition, accurate regional and local downscaling of global climate models might not be possible 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Anagnostopolos1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Anagnostopolos1">[118]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Wilby1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Wilby1">[120]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next requirement is accurate models linking climate change to hydrologic responses, so we could accurately determine changes in hydrology, amount of sea level rise, the degree to which plant communities will change in response to climate change, in both inland and coastal regions,. Accurate models that allow these predictions do not exist 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Vano1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Vano1">[117]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-He1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-He1">[121]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-OGorman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-OGorman1">[123]</a>. Even if we had accurately developed models, we also would need accurate assessments of species' ranges as well as niche–based models for each species we want to evaluate that accurately predicts, with a very high level of variability in distribution explained, the distribution of species, cf. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Reed2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Reed2">[106]</a>. We do not yet have these, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Pearson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Pearson1">[124]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Essl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Essl1">[127]</a>, and it is not clear to what extent or rate different bird might respond behaviorally to climate change 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Devictor1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Devictor1">[128]</a>. Finally, we need models that accurately depict community–wide biotic responses to climate change, including accurate anticipation of inter–specific interactions, how local species invasions and extinctions will affect resource availability, how they might change as niches shift 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Smith1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Smith1">[129]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brantley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brantley1">[133]</a>. We do not have these either, and we might be unlikely to accurately anticipate shifting realized niches for a variety of practical reasons 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Williams1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Williams1">[134]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Veloz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Veloz1">[136]</a>. These challenges are exacerbated by migration because the relationships must be known in breeding, non–breeding, and migration habitats 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Knudsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Knudsen1">[137]</a>. These relationships we just described are depicted in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108899-g003" href="#pone-0108899-g003">Fig. 3</a>. Even the highly restrictive requirements we just presented might ultimately be insufficient, because they do not take into account human responses to climate change. For example, what will be the human responses in changes to agricultural practices, relocation away from coastal areas, and so–called adaptive response measures, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Olesen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Olesen1">[138]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Lloyd1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Lloyd1">[140]</a>, and how will they affect the capacity for ecosystems and shorebirds to respond?
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0108899-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0108899.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Digraph showing relationships (arrows) for which we need accurate information in order to accurately predict species–specific shorebird responses to climate change.</div>
   <p>By accurate, we mean variation explained between nodes is &gt;90% or near that, not merely determining statistically significant relationships. Subheadings specify the relationships, and ‘species response’ includes adaptive responses as well as non–adaptive responses. ‘Fine spatial extent’ refers to downscaling climate change estimates to the spatial scale at which species respond; factors at this scale affect species' responses directly and indirectly. The digraph is nested within the contexts of future introductions of exotic, invasive species, and human responses to climate change to indicate that all of the relationships from the digraph can be affected by these particular occurrences or responses.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0108899.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consequently, we suspect that detailed regional and local biological forecasting of the effects of climate change, even if the correct (but currently unknown) IPCC scenario is selected, is likely to be only generally accurate. Therefore, we think that the relatively coarse assessment of changes in extinction risk that we present here is a useful level of assessment for species at a continental scale; see 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Gardali1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Gardali1">[31]</a> for another example of a categorical risk assessment at a smaller geographic scale. We stress that the somewhat bleak picture we paint regarding prediction accuracy at small spatial scales should not be used as an excuse to not make models or predictions, or to avoid planning for climate change. Rather, we encourage model development and testing, followed by model revision as more data become available. As with all models, we suggest treating the structure, parameter values, and predictions as hypotheses to test. We also support alternative modeling approaches that might be effective at accommodating model uncertainty, such as robust decision-making 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Veloz2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Veloz2">[141]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
