<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the models in LANDIS‐II, we developed and applied a simple flow analysis to determine the carbon storage and emissions during and following harvest through local product creation. Although not a comprehensive life cycle assessment (Oneil et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), we included emissions from harvesting equipment, emissions from transportation of wood (stem wood and biomass) to wood products facilities, emissions from biomass products that decompose in our analysis timeframe, and storage from wood products. To calculate carbon emissions from harvesting activities, we followed the methodology outlined by Markewitz (
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>) combined with local operator and machine productivity rates for restoration thinning. To determine carbon emissions from transportation, we used local knowledge of individual truck load mass (stem wood and residual biomass separately), average distance traveled to product facilities (wood products and chipped wood separately), average fuel economy of transport vehicles, and U.S. Energy Information Administration's carbon dioxide emissions coefficients (U.S. Energy Information Administration 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). To account for carbon storage and emissions from resulting forest products and waste associated with this production, we made several key assumptions. (1) The approximate amounts of wood products were as follows: pallets, 55%; single family homes (post 1980), 20%; manufacturing, 5%; railroad ties, 15%; and furniture, 5% (Stephen Horner, 
 <italic>personal communication</italic>) and each product had a carbon half‐life as indicated in Skog and Nicholson (
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>), (2) Chipped wood/biomass used for soil amendments was an emission for the length of analysis assuming decomposition rates for that material of ~10%/yr (Harmon et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). (3) Any residual biomass material created from processing wood products was an emission for the length of our analysis. We used local industry knowledge of proportions of wood vs. soil amendment products and the proportions of waste created when making wood products. Additional information can be found in Appendix 
 <xref rid="eap1979-sup-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>.
</p>
