<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animal handling and ethics</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The research was conducted in accordance with the Animal Welfare Act of 1970 and the most recent revision of the Ornithological Council’s guidelines in the use of wild birds in research, and by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC). Birds captured in Delaware Bay fell under the federal banding permit issued to the Endangered and Nongame Species Program, Division of Fish and Wildlife, NJ DEP (22803). Captures in New Jersey were done under federal banding permit (21241US), issued to New Jersey Audubon by the United States Geological Service/Bird Banding Laboratory. Individuals captured in Quebec fell under the protocol approved by the “Comité institutionnel de protection des animaux” under permit 2011-M29-2 and 2015-M29-1, and the capture of individuals in the Mingan Archipelago was approved by the Animal Care Committee of Environment and Climate Change Canada (SCF2018-01-YA, SCFQ2017-06, SCFQ2016-07). For Sanderling and Red knots captured in Chaplin, Canada, all animal handling and research protocols were approved by the University of Saskatchewan Animal Care Committee (AUP 20120021) and conducted under Canadian Wildlife Service Scientific Permit (12SKS009). Birds trapped in Texas, fell under the Texas Parks &amp; Wildlife Department Permit (SPR-0911-341), and trapping on the Padre Island National Seashore was approved by the National Park Service under permits 2015-SCI-0006, 2015-SCI-0007, and 2016-SCI-0005. All activities related to bird capture and tagging in Maine were reviewed and approved by University of Maine IACUC (A2013-01-02) and were performed under federal and state permits to the U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service and the Maine Department of Inland Fisheries and Wildlife. At James Bay, birds were banded under a permit from Environment and Climate Change Canada (Permit 10884), and banding and tagging was approved by Environment and Climate Change Canada’s Wildlife Eastern Animal Care Committee (protocol 14CF01, 15CF01, 16CF01 and 17CF01), as well as by Trent University’s Animal Care Committee (23904). Birds captured in Nunavut were approved under the Canadian Wildlife Service Scientific Permit to Capture and Band Migratory Birds (10565M), the Canadian Wildlife Service National Wildlife Area Permit (NUN-NWA-14-03), the Canadian Wildlife Service Scientific Research Permit (NWT-SCI-13-01), the Government of Nunavut Wildlife Research Permit (WL2015-032), and by Environment and Climate Change Canada Western and Northern Animal Care Committee Approval (15JR01). Birds captured and tagged at the Bay of Fundy were approved under Mount Allison University Animal Care protocol (12–10).</p>
</sec>
