<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of migration</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pre-breeding departure timing was highly synchronized across years and showed a narrow time window, whereas in the post-breeding season the departures were distributed over a longer period (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Large numbers of shorebirds stage in Delaware Bay (New Jersey and Delaware, USA) before making their final non-stop flight into their Arctic breeding grounds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>. After the breeding season, the Southern James Bay region (Canada, ON), is one of the key stopover sites on the Southern edge of the Arctic breeding sites
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. The mean date of departure from Delaware Bay was (day of year) 148.4 ± 3.5 days (mean ± SD; 148 = 28 May), and all species departed close to this date (day of year 148.2 ± 2.9 days for red knots; 148.9 ± 3.8 days for ruddy turnstones; 150.9 ± 3.8 days for sanderlings and 146.6 ± 9.8 days for semipalmated sandpipers). The mean date of departure from Southern James Bay during the post-breeding season for adults was 231.9 ± 15.6 days (mean ± SD, 232 = 20 Aug). These departure dates did not vary significantly across species (GLMM, 
  <span class="italic">X</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 1.6, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.64), but differed between adults and juveniles (GLMM, 
  <span class="italic">X</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 52.2, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.004), with juveniles leaving about 19 days later.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Timing of migration for the four species combined, as determined from individual departure dates from Delaware Bay (pre-breeding) and the southern James Bay region (post-breeding), separated by year. The white dots represent the relative frequency of individuals departing the sites and the lines and shaded areas represent estimated model means and 95% confidence intervals. The timing is highly synchronized during the pre-breeding season, but not during post-breeding.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45862_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1116" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
