<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wind data</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the wind data of the National Centers for Environmental Prediction (NCEP). The flow-assistance experienced by each individual was calculated using the R-Package RNCEP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>
  </span>. Since we recorded when and where an individual is present and the destination (i.e., different receiver station) is known, we used the latitudes and longitudes of the receiver stations as the start- and end-point for each trajectory, with the corresponding departure times. Using this information, we downloaded the –u (west-east) and –v (south-north) wind components, which were combined in a single wind vector incorporating the strength and the direction of the wind, from which we obtained a tailwind component. The calculations were based on wind components for the following pressure levels: ‘surface level’, 925, 850 and 700 hPa, corresponding to between 0 and 3000 m altitude. The RNCEP tailwind model was set to calculate the heading and tailwind component at the most optimal pressure level upon departure, and this pressure level was reassessed every 3 hr, and the heading and tailwind component recalculated by the model. In this way, we obtained an estimate of the wind assistance experienced by birds every 3 hr, assuming that they travelled at the most profitable pressure level.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Airspeed (m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was calculated by subtraction of the wind vector (wind assistance) from the track vector (ground speed, see above) to estimate individual airspeed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>
  </span>. Some track segments (&lt; 3% of total sample) had airspeeds &gt; 25 m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, which were the result of occasional false detections of tags (e.g., near simultaneous apparent detections of a bird at towers hundreds of kilometers apart). These false detection patterns were identified by examining plots of detections for each bird by latitude and time and longitude and time, and values associated with unrealistic movement patterns were removed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
  </span>. Airspeeds below a threshold of &lt; 5 m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span> were considered as possible undetected stopovers or detours through areas with no tower coverage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>
  </span>, and were excluded from airspeed analyses. Our power curve calculations (see below) indicate that the power required to fly below these speeds increases exponentially making these speeds unlikely. In order to identify the costs associated with airspeeds, we calculated the power curves for the four species using the program Flight 1.24, which is available (free) from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://books.elsevier.com/companions/9780123742995" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://books.elsevier.com/companions/9780123742995</span> (see Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a> for details).
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the hypothesis that long-distance migratory shorebirds would be more wind selective in the post-breeding season, we calculated wind support for each individual at the actual departure time and location, and calculated the wind support for the same departure time for the period up to 10 days earlier.</p>
</sec>
