<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate model simulations</div>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HiFLOR is a high-resolution coupled GCM that can recover many aspects of the highest TC intensification rates observed in nature and capture the connection between low-frequency climate oscillations and TC behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. A recent study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> showed that HiFLOR, when nudged toward observed SSTs, can skillfully reproduce the observed year-by-year variations of the frequency of Category 4 and 5 hurricanes (maximum wind speed ≥ 113 kts) in the Atlantic basin (
  <span class="italic">r</span> ≈ 0.64) and other basins to a lesser extent. HiFLOR’s seasonal predictions of major hurricanes were also skillful in the Atlantic basin, and the high positive correlations between HiFLOR predictions and observations are still among the highest documented for a dynamical climate model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. The confirmed presence of important modes of internal climate variability within HiFLOR as well as the resolved relationship between TCs and the large-scale climate instills some confidence that HiFLOR can diagnose whether observed changes are unusual compared to expected natural variability.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For an initial exploration of whether anthropogenic climate may be contributing to the increase in TC intensification, we follow the methodology of Murakami et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> and examine TC variations from a suite of HiFLOR multicentury experiments with different levels of anthropogenic forcing. Four HiFLOR experiments are run using anthropogenic forcing (e.g., CO
  <sub>2</sub>, aerosols, and ozone) and natural forcing (e.g., volcanic aerosol loading and solar insolation) representative of the years 1860, 1940, 1990, and 2015 (1860CTL, 1940CTL, 1990CTL, and 2015CTL; Methods).
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To compare the control simulations to observations, Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a> shows the logarithm of the 24-h intensity change probabilities observed between 1982 and 1998 in IBTrACS and ADT-HURSAT and those simulated in the 1990CTL. As a technique to account for the typical error associated with measuring TC intensity, the probability of each bin was calculated using 1000 subsamples that incorporated random error (Methods). To verify the quality of the control simulations, the 17-year period between 1982 and 1998 was selected for analysis because it is the longest available period with observational data that is centered on a control simulation. The 1990CTL data matches the shape of the IBTrACS curve but the distribution is not as broad as either of the observational datasets, indicating that HiFLOR underestimates the frequency of rapid weakening and intensification. A discrepancy in the probability of the highest intensity changes was also documented by Bhatia et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> but the differences appear larger in Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>, possibly due to the lack of SST nudging or the different years sampled.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HiFLOR underestimates the climatological rates of intensification, which will impact estimates of the amplitude of internal variability from this model. In order to mitigate the effects of systematic biases in HiFLOR intensity changes on estimating the internal variability of intensification rates, we utilize a statistical downscaling technique known as quantile mapping
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Specifically, we test two methods: quantile delta mapping
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> (QDM) and bias correction quantile mapping
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> (BCQM) (Methods). All subsequent analysis only incorporates the QDM algorithm because it is more adept at preserving relative changes in distributions of meteorological variables from different climate change simulations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows the effects of both quantile mapping algorithms. In this case, random error is not included in the probability estimates because we aim to nudge HiFLOR to the best guess of the intensity distribution. Clearly, the bias corrections are aligning the tails of the 1990CTL more closely with the tails of the observations. When we explore the potential influence of anthropogenic forcing on TC intensification rates, it is critical that HiFLOR provides a realistic picture of natural climate variability. Bias-corrections increase the probability of extreme intensity changes in the HiFLOR control simulations, which broadens the intensity change distribution. Thus, the bias-corrections enhance the annual variations in RI ratio and the range of the RI ratio slopes in the HiFLOR simulations, which translates into more stringent statistical tests for establishing significant observational trends.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The effects of quantile mapping on 24-intensity change probability densities. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Common logarithm of the probability densities calculated from IBTrACS (black), ADT-HURSAT (blue), HiFLOR 1990CTL (ORIG), HiFLOR QDM-corrected 1990CTL, and HiFLOR BCQM-corrected 1990CTL 24-h intensity changes. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Global and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Atlantic basin results are plotted. QDM and BCQM are quantile mapping designed to bias correct 1990CTL to more closely represent the distribution of IBTrACS. ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS probabilities are computed using the 17-year period centered around 1990 (1982–1998). HiFLOR probability density curves are generated using 250 years of intensity changes from the 1990CTL. Data is binned in 20 knot increments between −110 and 110 knots, and each bin entry is plotted as a dot on a curve. All distributions are bounded below by 10
     <span class="sup">−5</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8471_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e741" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test for observed RI trends that are outside of natural, internal climate variability, overlapping (not independent) 28-year RI ratio slopes in the bias-corrected HiFLOR control simulations are compared to the ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS RI ratio slopes between 1982 and 2009. Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a> shows how the probability distribution of RI ratio slopes changes when selecting 28-year segments from HiFLOR 1860CTL that are independent and not independent. The plotted bins show the independent sample has a slightly broader distribution but in general, the probabilities of the bins are similar to those in the overlapping bins.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> contains a box and whisker plot that shows the distribution of RI ratio slopes for the QDM-corrected 1860CTL. The observed slopes during 1982–2009 are overlaid on each plot. Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a> is similar to Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> but shows the box and whisker plots for all of the HiFLOR control simulations. Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a> portrays the corresponding cumulative distribution functions (CDF) of the RI ratio slopes for all of the control simulations as well as the observed RI ratio slopes in ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS. In the Atlantic basin, the slope of the RI ratio for ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS are both above the 99th percentile of the slopes of any of the bias-corrected HiFLOR control simulations. Therefore, the large positive slope of RI ratio in both observational datasets is outside HiFLOR’s estimate of expected internal climate variability, which suggests the model’s depiction of climate oscillations like the AMO cannot explain the observed trend.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Observed trends in RI ratio vs. 1860CTL natural variability. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Box and whisker plot represents the distribution of slopes of RI ratio in the QDM-corrected 1860 HiFLOR control simulation. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Global and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Atlantic basin results are plotted. Each slope is calculated by applying least squares regression analysis to annual RI ratio values in overlapping 28-year periods. Thus, the number of slopes for a control simulation is the number of available years subtracted by 28 (i.e., 1860CTL has 1422 slopes). The red line in each box indicates the median of the slopes. The box is bounded by the 25th and 75th percentiles of the data, and the whiskers bracket approximately 99% of the data. Red plus signs indicate outliers whose values are outside of whiskers’ range. IBTrACS and ADT-HURSAT trends in annual mean RI ratio between 1982 and 2009 are respectively represented by blue and green dotted lines and the corresponding 
     <span class="italic">p</span> values are listed below each line
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8471_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e784" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the global data, IBTrACS data indicates a trend that is well above the bounds of the observed natural variability of RI ratio in any HiFLOR control simulation, but the noted temporal and spatial heterogeneities leads us to question the validity of this result. The slope of RI ratio for ADT-HURSAT is approximately the 80th percentile of the HiFLOR 1860CTL, indicating the observed trend is not significant compared to modelled climate variability. Importantly, ADT-HURSAT observed data also yields an RI slope that is still relatively unusual compared to the HiFLOR preindustrial natural variability. This emerging trend is consistent with an increasing trend in the global intensity of TCs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. In the near future, ADT-HURSAT will be extended to 2016, and it is therefore vital for future analysis to determine whether the global trend also becomes significant.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to explore whether the observed changes between 1982 and 2009 could be attributable to anthropogenic forcing, we compare RI ratio in the three climate change simulations to the preindustrial 1860CTL. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> shows the percent difference in RI ratio between 1860CTL and the HiFLOR simulations with stronger anthropogenic forcing (1940CTL, 1990CTL, and 2015CTL). The analysis only involves HiFLOR simulations so bias corrections and random error are not applied to the data (Methods). Grid boxes that are not statistically significant are demarcated with a white “X”. The prevalence of red boxes throughout the maps conveys that a larger percentage of TCs are undergoing RI in 1940CTL, 1990CTL, and 2015CTL than in 1860CTL. There are no significant blue grid boxes in the 1990CTL and 2015CTL maps, and the number of gridboxes that record significant increases in RI ratio is 41 (9.7% of all shaded gridboxes) in 1940CTL, 156 (34.7% of all shaded gridboxes) in 1990 CTL, and 164 (38.2% of all shaded gridboxes) in 2015CTL. Historical radiative forcing changes applied to HiFLOR clearly lead to more frequent large intensification rates, but the available simulations do not allow us to strictly attribute the identified growth in RI during the period 1982–2009 to anthropogenic forcing. An ensemble of experiments that simulate anthropogenically forced climate change during this specific period, including changes in RI ratio, would be better suited for more comprehensive attribution analysis. Thus, for now, we can only conclude that anthropogenic forcing significantly increases extreme TC intensification rates in the HiFLOR model compared to preindustrial (1860CTL) conditions.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Anthropogenic forcing’s effects on RI ratio in HiFLOR. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">c</span> Simulated changes in RI ratio by the 1940CTL (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), 1990CTL (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), and 2015CTL (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) relative to the 1860CTL. Percent difference in RI ratio between HiFLOR 1860CTL and each climate change simulation is plotted in each 5° × 5° grid box. Data is only plotted in a grid box if at least one TC passes through the grid box every 50 years in the two experiments used to calculate percent difference. Red (blue) squares indicate grid boxes where a larger (smaller) percentage of 24-h intensity changes exceed 30 knots in the climate change simulations than in the 1860CTL. Grid boxes that achieve a 
     <span class="italic">p</span> value of 0.05 using a binomial proportion test are considered statistically significant. White “Xs” are located in grid boxes that are not statistically significant
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8471_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e823" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the two most reliable long-term observational records available for TC intensity changes, the proportion of 24-h TC intensification rates greater than 30 knots significantly increases in the Atlantic basin between 1982 and 2009. Results averaged over all basins show a significant increase in TC intensification rates in IBTrACS but not in ADT-HURSAT. By itself, a 28-year upward trend in a TC intensification metric does not necessarily reflect the effects of anthropogenic climate forcing because of the intrinsic natural variability of the climate system. Here, we use bias-corrected TC intensification rates simulated by HiFLOR to demonstrate that natural variability cannot explain the magnitude of the observed upward trend in the Atlantic basin. These conclusions are possible because HiFLOR is a unique climate model that can successfully simulate the most intense TCs and highest intensification rates in multicentury simulations.</p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study is limited by the ability of a climate model to accurately represent natural variability as well as the uncertainty around the trends in relatively short observational records. However, this study represents a crucial first step in quantifying the precise roles of stochastic processes, anthropogenic warming, and natural variability when assessing changes in TC intensification rates. Further analysis with additional high-resolution climate models and a longer and more reliable observational record is required to confirm these conclusions. Regardless, these trends provide another example of the potentially serious repercussions of anthropogenic warming for TCs.</p>
</sec>
