<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Society is faced with significant challenges when tropical cyclones (TCs) rapidly intensify. These storms quickly rise through the Saffir–Simpson intensity scale
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, occasionally jumping from a category 1 (64–82 knots) to category 5 (&gt;137 knots) hurricane within a couple of days. Storms that undergo rapid intensification (RI; defined as the 95th percentile of 24-h intensity changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>) reach major hurricane status (wind speeds greater than 95 knots, categories 3–5 on the Saffir–Simpson Scale) about 80% of the time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> and are associated with the highest forecast errors. As a result, RI can lead to disastrous scenarios when coastal areas are not given adequate notice to evacuate and prepare for an extremely intense TC (e.g., Hurricane Audrey, 1957)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The destruction and forecast error associated with TCs that undergo RI has inspired new research on whether RI frequency will be altered due to climate change. A recent statistical-dynamical downscaling study found that the number of TCs that undergo RI before U.S. landfall is projected to significantly increase in the late 21st century compared to the late 20th century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. A separate study involving climate change simulations produced by a high-resolution global climate model (GCM) projected a dramatic increase in the global incidence of RI due to global warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. The agreement in these two studies with different methodologies as well as the theoretical backing by a third study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span> suggests we should investigate whether climate change has already increased the probability of TCs rapidly intensifying. An anthropogenically forced signal in recent observational data would provide evidence that these model projections are well-grounded and therefore, substantial coastal mitigation and adaptation strategies would be required in the near future.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although TC frequency has stayed approximately constant over recent decades, there is growing evidence that the proportion of TCs which become major hurricanes has significantly increased
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Therefore, intensification metrics that capture the relative, rather than the absolute, frequency of the highest intensification rates are useful for understanding whether the probability of RI events is increasing. For example, a recent study showed the 95th percentile of 24-h intensity changes significantly increased in the central and eastern tropical Atlantic basin during the period of 1986–2015
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Another intensification metric that is not dependent on TC frequency, the intensification rate of intensifying storms, exhibited significant growth between 1977 and 2013 in the West Pacific basin
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. In both basins, the studies showed the large-scale environment becoming more conducive to TC intensification with time. Specifically, areas with the largest increase in sea surface temperatures (SSTs) and potential intensities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> appear to be collocated with the largest positive changes in intensification rates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we build on these results by evaluating Atlantic and global TC intensification trends using different metrics and additional observational datasets. We focus primarily on the Atlantic basin because it is the basin with the most consistent high-quality observations. There are currently no published findings on global trends in TC intensity changes, so these results are also included to provide a more comprehensive perspective. To separate anthropogenic trends and normal climate fluctuations, we use a state-of-the-art coupled GCM, the high-resolution forecast-oriented low ocean resolution model (HiFLOR). Specifically, we simulate the year-to-year variations in TC intensification from a suite of HiFLOR multicentury experiments that serve as a proxy for natural climate variability and compare the magnitude of the trends in the simulated climate to those in observations . The recent increase in high-intensification rates in the Atlantic basin is outside the range of normal climate variability defined by HiFLOR, which suggests anthropogenic forcing increases the likelihood of TCs rapidly intensifying.</p>
</sec>
