<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observational trends</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus far, TC intensification trend analysis has exclusively focused on International Best-Track Archive for Climate Stewardship
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> (IBTrACS) data (Methods), which likely adds systematic biases to published results. IBTrACS is composed of TC best-track data from different operational agencies whose TC intensity observations became more reliable when global satellite coverage was introduced in the early 1980s (except for the Indian Ocean which did not gain continuous satellite coverage until 1998)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Over much of the globe, satellite data quality has improved through increasing resolution and decreasing view angles, which enhances the accuracy of the most recent intensity estimates. The recent addition of more in situ measurements in the Atlantic and the East Pacific leads to lower errors in these basins, which results in additional spatial and temporal inhomogeneities in the observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to gauge the impact of these inhomogeneities on TC intensification trends, we first compare the probability of 24-h wind speed changes in IBTrACS and a more homogeneous record of TC intensity, the Advanced Dvorak Technique-Hurricane Satellite-B1 (ADT-HURSAT)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> (Methods). Kossin et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> developed ADT-HURSAT in order to maintain the same protocol to determine TC intensities throughout all ocean basins during the period 1982–2009. ADT-HURSAT incorporates artificially degraded intensity estimates in certain regions so its data quality is consistent both spatially and temporally, which is better suited for trend analysis. However, this increased data consistency means the best technology and analysis techniques are not utilized in ADT-HURSAT, which leads to individual intensity estimates with higher average errors than those in IBTrACS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. However, for the scope of our study, which involves assessing rates of change throughout a time series, temporal consistency is preferable to accuracy in individual estimates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> shows the empirical probability density plots calculated from ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS 24-h intensity changes, using a logarithm transformation on the probabilities to better illustrate differences in the tails of the distributions. Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> shows the more traditional probability density plots. For all of our analyses, we impose criteria involving storm longevity, location, and intensity to ensure only intensity changes derived from well-defined storms are included in our results (Methods). For the global results, we entirely exclude the north and south Indian Oceans from the sample because of the well-known absence of quality satellite data in the region until 1998
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Nevertheless, our conclusions do not significantly change when these basins are introduced into the analysis.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Observed 24-intensity change probability densities. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Common logarithm of the probability densities calculated from IBTrACS (black) and ADT-HURSAT (blue) 24-h intensity changes. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Global and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Atlantic basin results for the period 1982–2009 are plotted. Data are binned in 20 knot increments between −110 and 110 knots. The dashed lines indicate the 90% confidence interval (between 5th and 95th percentiles of the data) (Methods). All distributions are bounded below by 10
     <span class="sup">−5</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8471_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e513" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As expected, the differences in the ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS intensity change distributions are larger for the global data, while the two datasets show more agreement in the Atlantic basin. For the global results, TCs in ADT-HURSAT maintain their intensity for a larger percentage of cases than in IBTrACS but also have significantly more instances of intensification rates between 50 and 90 knots (resulting in a “shelf” in this part of the distribution). IBTrACS curves appear almost linear in both plots which imply that probability densities are exponentially distributed. Thus, IBTrACS suggests that TC intensification and dissipation are likely controlled by statistically random environmental and internal processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. Meanwhile, ADT-HURSAT’s shelf-like pattern suggests that RI is a special process that could preferentially augment the probability of the highest intensification rates. The former interpretation is much more likely considering the ADT-HURSAT algorithm exhibits well-documented problems during TC eye formation (Methods).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As discussed in Bhatia et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, the discrepancies among basins and datasets cannot be attributed to specific physical processes or data deficiencies. A summary of the potential explanations for this behavior are included in the Methods section. We here argue that the agreement among the observational datasets in the Atlantic basin provides some level of confidence in the trend analysis in this basin. On the other hand, both observational datasets have larger uncertainties in global intensity changes. Therefore, any conclusions stemming from the global trend analysis must be treated with caution.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows Atlantic basin and global trends in 24-h intensity changes between 1982 and 2009. The 28-year period is selected for analysis because it is the longest continuous sample where ADT-HURSAT produces relatively reliable global intensity data. Quantile regression is calculated for every 5% quantile between 5% and 95% (Methods). IBTrACS shows significant trends in all quantiles except the ones between 35% and 45%. The 95th percentile shows the largest trend of about +4 knots decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. The negative slopes for the lower percentiles and positive slopes for the upper quantiles suggests a broadening of the intensity change distribution, implying less TCs maintaining a steady intensity and more TCs exhibiting high-intensity fluctuations. ADT-HURSAT shares a similar pattern for the slopes of the quantiles but the trends are more muted. Despite being relatively small in magnitude, ADT-HURSAT quantile slopes greater than the 50% quantile are statistically significant and positive, with the 90th percentile having the largest slope of approximately 1 knot decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Quantile regression of 24-h intensity changes. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">d</span> Slope of the quantiles for 24-h intensity changes during the period 1982–2009. Slopes are shown for IBTrACS (
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">c</span>) and ADT-HURSAT (
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span>) globally (
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span>) and in the Atlantic basin (
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span>). The black dots represent the slope derived from least squares regression of intensity change as a function of year for each quantile from 0.05 to 0.95 in steps of 0.05. Shading represents the 5th and 95th percentiles of the regressions with randomly perturbed observational data (Methods). The red solid line shows the (constant value) trend in the mean as measured by ordinary least squares regression, and the red dotted lines show the 90% confidence interval
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8471_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e576" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the global data, ADT-HURSAT trends are clearly much smaller than those in IBTrACS, yet IBTrACS trends are likely more susceptible to data homogeneity problems. Therefore, it is our interpretation that the weaker global trends shown by ADT-HURSAT are more likely to be correct. This conclusion is particularly notable because multiple studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> have assumed that IBTrACS is reliable during the time frame considered in our study when in reality, there is likely a spurious trend masked by the data. It is possible that resolution and algorithm issues with ADT-HURSAT prevent it from resolving the intensity changes and have slightly dampened largest trends. However, it is much more likely that the influx of new satellites has enabled better detection of intensity changes in the later years of the time series and thus, artificially enhanced the slope of the extreme quantiles in IBTrACS.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Atlantic basin, the quantile regression for ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS yields similar results for extreme intensity changes. For both observational datasets, the 95th percentile shows the largest trend. This quantile increases by over +4 knots decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in ADT-HURSAT and +3 knots decade
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in IBTrACS. The upward trend in TC activity during the 1990s is typically attributed to the Atlantic Multidecadal Oscillation (AMO), which features multidecadal fluctuations in SSTs in the Atlantic basin
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. In the late 1990s, the phase of the AMO shifted from negative to positive which coincides with warming in parts of the Atlantic basin where TCs develop
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Therefore, the AMO phase favored RI at the end of the time series. In addition to the AMO behavior, the reliability of the observational data in the Atlantic basin suggests the positive trend in intensification rates during 1982–2009 is likely robust. IBTrACS has its lowest errors in the Atlantic basin because of the plentiful in situ observations that are incorporated into the best-track analysis. ADT-HURSAT relies on best-track positions to accurately assign a scene type and find an eye, which suggests that the additional reconnaissance in this basin could also help with ADT-HURSAT’s intensity estimates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a complement to quantile regression, we also analyze how the annual rapid intensification ratio (RI ratio) has changed from 1982 to 2009. RI ratio is defined as the number of 24-h intensity changes greater than 30 knots divided by the total number of intensity changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, and it reflects changes in the probability of the highest TC intensification rates. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> illustrates the Atlantic basin and global trends in RI ratio for ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS. For both observational datasets, slopes are positive and significant in the global and Atlantic basin data. Much like Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, the Atlantic basin trends for the observational datasets are very similar. Over the 28-year period, the percentage of 24-h intensity changes that exceed an intensification rate of 30 knots approximately triples in IBTrACS and ADT-HURSAT. IBTrACS shows a similar rise in RI ratio for the global data but ADT-HURSAT has a much smaller slope.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Rapid intensification ratio trends. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Observed trends in the rapid intensification (RI) ratio of ADT-HURSAT (black) and IBTrACS (blue) over the 28-year period 1982–2009 using 
     <span class="bold">a</span> global and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Atlantic data. RI ratio is defined as the number of 24-h intensity changes above 30 knots divided by the total number of 24-h intensity changes. Trends in the time series of the annual mean RI ratio are denoted by dashed lines. The slopes of the trend lines as well as their 90% confidence intervals are provided. The slopes and confidence intervals are calculated using 1000 randomly perturbed samples of the observational data. Shading represents the 5th and 95th percentiles of the 1000 regressions with these randomly perturbed observational data (Methods)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8471_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e637" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> shows the annual RI ratio of the two observational datasets plotted against each other. In the Atlantic basin, 35.7% of the variance in IBTrACS RI ratio is explained by ADT-HURSAT RI ratio. For the global data, the percentage explained drops to 1.8%, further highlighting the lack of agreement between the two observational datasets at global scales. The variations in the slope of RI ratio among the global observations as well as the lack of a published theory
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> that explains the source of a significant positive slope in global TC intensification metrics highlight the uncertainty in the global results. Conversely, the recent uptick in intense TCs and RI magnitude in the Atlantic basin appears more plausible because of the AMO shifting phase.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ordinary trend analysis over a relatively short period (1982–2009) may mistake multidecadal natural variability for a long-term trend. For a more refined estimate of the possible influence of natural variability on observed trends and to quantitatively assess whether the recent increase in Atlantic RI ratio can be explained by natural variability alone, we compared the observed trends to those in a TC-permitting GCM that can simulate multidecadal climate variability in the Atlantic basin. Global results are also presented with the caveat that the ADT-HURSAT data are likely more realistic because of the homogeneous time series.</p>
</sec>
