<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed data</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the International Best Track Archive for Climate Stewardship (IBTrACS)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, v03r09, and the Advance Dvorak Technique-Hurricane Satellite-B1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> (ADT-HURSAT) for the period 1982–2009. For our IBTrACS analysis, we only consider best-track data from the National Hurricane Center for the Atlantic and east Pacific and the Joint Typhoon Warning Center for the remainder of the globe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. One of the benefits of only using data from these U.S. agencies is they follow the same definition of maximum winds: the highest 1-min average at 10 m height over a smooth surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Best-track data start as operational estimates of the intensity and track of a TC and are refined at the end of a TC’s lifetime with a combination of in situ (e.g., dropsondes, scatterometers, and buoys), radar, and satellite measurements. Best-track intensity and position estimates are available every 6 h at the four synoptic times (0000, 0600, 1200, and 1800 UTC) and are recorded to the nearest 5 knots (1 kt = 0.5144 m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and 0.1° latitude/longitude
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The creation of ADT-HURSAT consists of four main steps. Geostationary satellite imagery is first analyzed from International Satellite Cloud Climatology Project (ISCCP)-B1 data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Then, the data are centered on IBTrACS TCs and subsampled to be both spatially and temporally homogeneous. Finally, a simplified version of the advanced Dvorak technique
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> is used to evaluate the data and determine a maximum TC wind speed. ADT-HURSAT data are produced every 3 h based on satellite data that has been uniformly subsampled to a horizontal resolution of 8 km, and wind speeds are recorded to the nearest tenth of a Dvorak “T-number” (depending on the current intensity, between 1 and 3 knots).
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although ADT-HURSAT and IBTrACS represent the two most reliable multi-decadal observational datasets for TC intensification trend analysis, they both have limitations. In IBTrACS, Atlantic and East Pacific in situ observations have rapidly improved in the last 30 years, while other basins were rarely able to obtain aircraft reconnaissance. In fact, the west Pacific was the only other basin that had access to aircraft reconnaissance but these observations stopped in 1987. As a result, the number of measurements available in different basins varies considerably, leading to temporal and spatial inconsistencies in IBTrACS observational quality. Better intensity estimates at the end of the historical record potentially causes heightened detection of the larger intensity changes. Additionally, best-track estimates are also susceptible to human error because they are assembled at operational centers.</p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared to IBTrACS, ADT-HURSAT employs reduced-resolution satellite imagery, both in space and time. The omission of in situ measurements to accompany the coarsened satellite imagery is especially problematic for ADT-HURSAT identifying “scene type” changes when an eye is forming. As a result, there is a well-documented unphysical plateau at the eye formation stage of TC development in intensity observations from ADT-HURSAT. Low intensity changes are present for long periods of time and then the ADT-HURSAT is forced “to catch up” with higher intensity changes once it finally detects an eye. Thus, peak TC intensities (and changes) may not be fully resolved by ADT-HURSAT, especially in the cases of a transient, small eye. However, these deficiencies remain consistent throughout the time series, which suggests that there is a low likelihood of a systematic bias in ADT-HURSAT trends. It is also possible that larger eyes and a longer mean duration of the “plateau” period for TCs in the Atlantic basin could lead to minimal effects of these deficiencies.</p>
</sec>
