<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Climate changes drive diverse impacts on coastal zones. There is evidence that the sea surface temperature (SST) has been increasing since the end of the XIX century [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], at an annual rate of about 0.11 °C from 1970 onwards, although the inter-annual variation was extremely high. In more recent periods, increases in the SST in coastal zones worldwide have been documented (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]), being the estimates for the end of the XXIst century even higher than average for the global ocean (0.6 to 2 °C compared to estimates up to 4 °C in certain coastal zones) [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Some of the shallow or intertidal coastal habitats, such as saltmarshes, mangroves, and tidal flats, will be particularly exposed to extreme events like heat (or cold) waves, which will probably further increase the thermal stress in these environments. Global warming interferes directly with organisms but have also other effects on coastal processes. The volume of the ocean increased due to its thermal energy and due to the melting of ice caps that induced sea-level rise. Estimates of the mean sea level rise of 3 mm year
 <sup>-1</sup> have been proposed, implying an increase of about 40 to 75 cm by 2100 [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Ocean acidification is also a human-induced major driver, resulting from increasing CO
 <sub>2</sub> concentration in the atmosphere, and with impacts on a wide diversity of organisms, namely corals, planktonic organisms, and calcifying structure’s organisms. Estimates for 2100 indicate a decrease in 0.3 to 0.4 pH units [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Expected climate conditions also include an increase in the frequency of extreme events, especially storm surges, as well as changes in the water cycle dynamics that, depending on the geographical area, may be expressed as a strong reduction in rainfall and, consequently in drought events, or an intensification of rainfall during short periods, which also induce a severe regime shift [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
