<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic> is an ectotherm species, dependent on warm and humid conditions for reproduction and disease transmission. Despite these physiological constraints, it is not well-understood to what extent climate and climate change have contributed to the global expansion of 
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic>. Moreover, it is not clear whether climatic factors have affected its abundance, critical for an epidemic threshold. Socio-economic factors have been found to correlate with the immature-stage population of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitos in the USA through variations in the number and the type of breeding sites, e.g., storage and disused containers (tires, food/drink containers) (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). In general, the lower the neighborhood income, the higher the 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> mosquito production (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). However, from malaria studies, socio-economic development is found to decrease the global distribution of malaria (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). The concurrent contributions of changes in climate and socio-economic development have been difficult to disentangle. A number of attempts have been made to map the spatial presence of two 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> vectors (
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. albopictus</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>). However, despite these comprehensive efforts on its presence, vector abundance is still poorly understood. There is no spatial map on 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes'</italic> vector abundance global distribution from either empirical data or from modeling. Neither can we find the vector's abundance seasonal patterns globally.
</p>
