<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coping measures</div>
 <p id="p0130" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a rid="tbl1" ref-type="table" href="#tbl1">Table 1</a>, smallholder farmers sold their assets (livestock and/or poultry) to cope with food shortfalls as indicated by 24.6% and 26.6% of respondents in Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively. Whenever households sell the livestock/poultry and other assets, they buy food from the market to supplement the food shortage. All respondents who indicated selling their livestock/poultry and other assets bought food (grains and cereals) to cope with the food shortfall. It was however realized that, 80% of smallholder farmers that sold their key productive assets failed to rebuild (restock) the assets after the catastrophe (drought, food shortfall) had halted. Continuous selling of productive assets such as livestock, poultry and land is a source of dwindling tangible assets and endangers households to chronic livelihood and food insecurity. An interviewee indicated that, “
  <span class="italic">the erratic rainfall regime which has resulted in food shortfalls exhausted (poor and vulnerable) smallholder farmers coping strategies making them fall back on the consumption of seed and sale of key assets (farm implements, land, livestock/poultry) for their survival</span>”. These events have significantly reduced the coping ability (or adaptive capacity) of smallholder farmers and endangered future food production and availability. For this reason, majority of smallholder farmers (92%), believe that severe food and livelihood insecurity will result from depletion of assets through continuous use of coping strategies.
 </p>
 <p id="p0135" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Employing appropriate agronomic practices such as depending on wells and dugouts for cultivating vegetables (and also for animals to drink), harvesting immature food crops and performing traditional cultural sacrifices (to reverse the calamity e.g. drought) were reported by 15.2% and 7.4% of smallholder farmers in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively during this study. The use of agronomic practices as coping measures was also documented by (
  <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">Dovie, 2010</a>), he observed that, farmers plant early, use drought tolerant crops and revive old traditions as the main coping strategies of rural farmers.
 </p>
 <p id="p0140" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">About 0.4% and 26.6% of smallholder farmers in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively, reported relying on forestry products, wild fruits and wildlife as coping measures to ecological and climate change. The great disparity between Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre reliance on wild/forestry products is due to the fact that, the Soe Kabre community is located very close to a forest, hence they have access to a whole range of forest products/wild fruits in contrast to the Gowrie Kunkua community which is located in between two urban towns without forest.</p>
 <p id="p0145" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Approximately 21.9% and 5.4% of smallholder farmers in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively, reported diversifying their livelihoods into craftsmanship viz a viz weaving baskets/hats, smocks and paid non-farm jobs viz tailoring, masonry, etc. The results indicate that, over 60% of smallholder farmers in the savanna ecological zone undertake several non-arable farming livelihood activities in reaction to ecological/climate change (particularly droughts). An interviewee asserted that, “
  <span class="italic">livelihood diversification is practiced more at the moment than three (3) decades ago; it enables us to buy food for our families during the dry season</span>”. A further scrutiny of livelihood diversification revealed that, off-farm livelihood activities such as petty trade, shea nut picking and butter processing, pito brewing and malt processing and basket and hat weaving are mainly female livelihood activities. Male non-farm livelihood activities were selling livestock and poultry, stone quarrying, sand mining, fishing, masonry, carpentry, motor/bicycle fitting/repairs among others. Livelihood activities such as weaving, charcoal production and petty trade were practiced by both men and women. These findings are in tandem with (
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Berlie, 2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0150" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another 3.1% and 4.9% of households in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively reported depending on support from family and friends. In total, approximately, 8% of smallholder farmers in this study indicated they have sought assistance or depended on their family and/or friends for the past five (5) years (2011–2015) as a coping strategy to climate/ecological change and its negative effects on their livelihood activities. An interviewee asserted that, “
  <span class="italic">Smallholder farmers depend on social capital (alliances and networking) including Community Based Organizations, Susu/savings association, religious associations etc that offer support to its members in the form of labor on farms, food, credits and animals</span>”. More households (40%) in the Gowrie Kunkua belonged to social networks than the Soe Kabre community (36%).
 </p>
 <p id="p0155" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Smallholder farmers do not only receive assistance from family/friends but also government and Non-governmental organizations. Approximately, 10.2% of smallholder farmers in the Gowrie Kunkua community and 6.9% of households in the Soe Kabre community reported receiving remittance from both government and non-government social projects in the form of Conditional Cash Transfers (CCT) such as the Ghana Social Opportunity Project (GSOP), the Livelihood Empowerment Against Poverty Program (LEAP) as well as other Conditional Cash Transfer (CCT) or social intervention programs. In total, 34.7% of smallholder farmers in this study confirmed that they have received assistance from government and NGOs at least once in the last five (5) years (2010–2015).</p>
</sec>
