<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4.5" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Off-farm adaptation strategies</div>
 <sec id="sec4.5.1" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Migration</div>
  <p id="p0200" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Approximately 50.7% and 40% of households in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively indicated that they migrated at least once in the last five (5) years as a strategy to reduce the effects of climate and ecological change on their livelihoods. A discussant at a FGD asserted that, “
   <span class="italic">during the dry season, people migrate temporarily to Southern Ghana to work in the cocoa growing areas, chop bars and drinking spots and head portage in order to meet their basic needs and remit back home</span>”. This study through an interview with a key informant revealed that, in recent times, people in the savanna ecological zone migrate to Southern Ghana to work on farms to earn income and accumulate food. This study further revealed that, some of the migrants in addition to working on people's farms, harvest vertiver grass straw for weaving baskets since the vertiver grass species are depleting in the savanna ecological zone. Findings of 
   <a rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib7">Awumbila and Ardayfio-Schandorf (2008)</a> confirm this study. It is important to add that these activities that migrant farmers engage in are low income paid jobs and others pay with food produce not in cash. Smallholder farmers indicated that, the major trigger of their migration is the recurrent droughts coupled with inherent poor soil fertility in the savanna ecological zone, which have contributed significantly to reductions in agricultural productivity over the years. This finding is in tandem with (
   <a rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib50">Rademacher-Schulz and Mahama, 2012</a>; 
   <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Van der Geest, 2011</a>). For instance, data from MoFA suggest that average yields for millet and sorghum were 1.4 mt/ha and 1.2 mt/ha respectively, for 2010, compared with 0.8 mt/ha and 1.0 mt/ha for the same crops in 2012 and a further decline of 0.6 mt/ha and 0.9 mt/ha for 2014. Soils in the savanna ecological zone are deficient in nitrogen, phosphorus and sulphur (
   <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Antwi-Agyei, 2012</a>). As indicated by an interviewee, “
   <span class="italic">the soil quality for crop production is very poor</span>”. Studies by (
   <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">McLeman; Smit, 2006</a>; 
   <a rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib42">Myers, 2002</a>; 
   <a rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib28">Gemenne, 2011</a>) also confirm that people migrate in response to harsh climate conditions as a coping mechanism. Discussant at an FGD said “
   <span class="italic">We migrate to southern Ghana so that we can work and earn money to enable us buy food, pay our school fees and health insurance since we have a long dry season in which we sit and do nothing”.</span> These assertions all indicate that households migrate in anticipation of droughts and poor soil quality to secure a sustainable livelihood for themselves and their families. Migration (inter and intra village migration, rural-rural, rural-urban and regional migration) is a critical coping strategy employed by smallholder farmers in the study communities. A focus group discussant remarked that “
   <span class="italic">the rainfall problem in this community has become so bad that our harvest is always not enough to feed our families, so most people migrate to Tamale, Kumasi and Kintampo to work on people's farms to earn money or sometimes food. The youth also migrate to the big cities (Accra and Kumasi) to work as “Kayaye” (head potters), roasting kebabs, working in chop bars and restaurants to take care of their family needs”.</span> Damaging coping strategies such as out-migration of the entire households were practiced especially when elementary coping strategies are exhausted. From the interviews and group discussions, it is obvious that, smallholder farmers migrate due to ecological and climate change effects such as erratic rainfall, droughts, poor soil fertility and food shortfalls (
   <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">Dovie, 2010</a>; 
   <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Antwi-Agyei, 2012</a>). An interviewee commented that “
   <span class="italic">there are other factors aside the poor rainfall problem that makes people to migrate… lack of jobs and low infrastructure development are the other factors that compounds our already fragile environmental problems”</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.5.2" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Decreasing food consumption and altering diets</div>
  <p id="p0205" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Decreasing food consumption and altering diets is now a crucial coping strategy of smallholder farmers in the savanna ecological zone of Ghana. The results show that 67% and 64% of smallholder households/farmers in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively reduced/decreased their food intake or altered their diets as a coping strategy to climate and ecological change (livelihood and food insecurity). Vulnerable households indicated they usually depend on food provided by churches and social intervention programs of NGOs. A female remarked during a household interview: 
   <span class="italic">“When my family's food is running low (food shortfall), the elderly people usually eat once a day so that the children can eat twice a day. We also sometimes eat food that is not our preference”.</span>
  </p>
  <p id="p0210" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Connected to altering diet is the reduction in food consumption by the members of the households. Since the 1990s, when rainfall pattern became more erratic, households in the savanna ecological zone have been decreasing food consumption as a key coping strategy to ecological and climate change (droughts, food shortfall) and during the dry season (
   <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Antwi-Agyei, 2012</a>). Decreasing food consumption and altering diets as a coping strategy requires crucial assessment since this strategy poses dangerous consequence on the health and well-being of affected households. This situation makes the affected more vulnerable to negative effects of climate and ecological change by predisposing such households to many diseases that will make them more susceptible to climate and ecological stress (
   <a rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib32">Heltberg et al., 2009</a>; 
   <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Antwi-Agyei, 2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
