<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Research methods</div>
 <p id="p0090" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The empirical data from this study spans six months of ethnographic fieldwork. A study of this kind, which seeks to examine the lived experiences of farmers affected by climate variability and ecological changes cannot properly be carried out with only quantitative methodology or analysis. Immersed ethnography is one of the best methodological approaches to use in exploring smallholder farmers lived experiences (responses to climate and ecological change effects on their livelihoods) (
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Nyantakyi-Frimpong and Bezner-Kerr, 2015</a>). It is particularly vital in assisting us understand many dimensions of social relations (e.g., peer-to-peer learning, diffusion and adoption of innovation) that could not have been easily understood when the approach adopted was basically closed ended questionnaire surveys (
  <a rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib55">Schroeder, 1999</a>). Again, the ethnographic approach has the virtue of solidity (
  <a rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib60">St. Martin and Pavlovskaya, 2009</a>) and is precisely valuable when the researcher seeks to completely understand smallholder farmers' lived experiences in all its entirety and complexities (
  <a rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib55">Schroeder, 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib64">Watts, 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Nyantakyi-Frimpong and Bezner-Kerr, 2015</a>). 
  <a rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52">Roncoli et al. (2009)</a> and 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Nyantakyi-Frimpong and Bezner-Kerr (2015)</a> have especially stressed the utility of an ethnographic methodology and the need for participatory methods of data collection in obtaining farmer beliefs about climate change and their livelihood adaptation.
 </p>
 <p id="p0095" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, the sampling technique employed in this study was purposeful and aimed to select information rich cases for in-depth scrutiny. Information rich cases offered the researchers an opportunity to learn a great deal about important issues which yielded greater insights and in-depth understanding (
  <a rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib48">Patton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">Creswell, 2013</a>). The study employed a combination or mixture of purposeful sampling strategies. This was necessary because triangulating or combining sampling strategies is flexible and enables the research findings to capture multiple perspectives, interest and needs (
  <a rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib48">Patton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">Creswell, 2013</a>). First of all, the study employed criterion sampling to review and select all cases and/or districts that met a predetermined criterion (exposed to climate anomaly-drought). Inclusion criterion for this study are districts in Ghana that have been predisposed to climate and ecological change risks and abnormalities (erratic rainfall pattern, drought, high temperature). The Bongo district (study district) was tinted as the most vulnerable district in Ghana to climate change hence its selection. Due to limited resources and time, the study employed purposeful random sampling to select 75 households in each of the two (2) (Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities) rural villages/communities in the Bongo district.
 </p>
 <p id="p0100" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From June to December 2015, we conducted village-level fieldwork by living and working with smallholder farmers in their farms and engaging in daily farming practices with the farmers. Daily farming practices such as land preparation, planting, sowing, weeding, soil and water conservation, contour construction, stone bonding, animal grazing/feeding, termites hunting, crop harvesting and crop residue management. Data collection integrated a sequential, multi-method triangulation technique (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Creswell and Plano Clark, 2011</a>). The fieldwork started with oral historical interviews with the community elders (clan heads, chief/earth priest, sectional/divisional heads/sub-chiefs) in the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities, and then continued with a survey of 75 households in each of the two communities. Households are defined “as constituting of a group of people who own the same productive resources, live together and feed from the same pot” (
  <a rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib65">Yaro, 2006</a>). Through transect walks and community institutional and resource mapping (CIRM), we randomly surveyed every fourth household until we obtained the required sample size. The 75 households represented approximately 48% and 42% of all households the Gowrie Kunkua and Soe Kabre communities respectively.
 </p>
 <p id="p0105" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on initial analysis of the survey data, we used qualitative techniques including in-depth interviews, focus group discussions and participant observations to help position and offer profundity to the quantitative findings (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Creswell and Plano Clark, 2011</a>). The qualitative data gathering and analysis process was iterative. The kinds of additional information or informants required were usually decided as the data gathering and analysis evolved concurrently (
  <a rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib48">Patton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib40">Miles and Huberman, 1994</a>). We conducted at least two focus group discussions in each community comprising about 5–10 farmers of different socio-economic backgrounds, to ensure triangulation of the key issues emerging from the household questionnaire. Following analyses and synthesis of these data sets, a total of 15 key informants (7 in each community) were chosen for in-depth interview into the issues raised at focus group discussions. Focus group discussants and Key Informants were purposefully selected based on their farming knowledge and experience of ecological/climate change as presented during the household questionnaire survey.
 </p>
 <p id="p0110" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interview time varied significantly from 3 hours 30 minutes to 5 hours 30 minutes. They were conducted on/near farms or homes of the respondents and in the local language (Gurune) which we understand and speak. We earlier on employed the services of the Gurune language department of the University of Education (Winneba) to assist in interpreting key English language terminologies and concepts such as vulnerability, adaptation and resilience which do not have exact translation or meaning in the Gurune language. Ethical approval for this study was obtained from the Ethical clearance committee of the University for Development Studies.</p>
</sec>
