<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Overall, future precipitation/water resource projections suggest that in Canada, the North will become wetter and the South drier especially in summer [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. However, limited research has been carried out regarding potential future drought occurrence across Canada and most investigations have focused on the particularly drought-prone Canadian Prairies. A first-order assessment of future drought occurrence over southern Canada (2041–2070) by Bonsal and Regier [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] found future annual precipitation will increase over most of the southern region of Canada but this will be more than offset by increased temperatures that lead to higher evaporation so increases in drought are likely. The future mean PDSI estimates indicate the prevalence of more frequent drought for the southern half of the Canadian Prairies in the latter half of the 21stcentury with persistent negative PDSI values expected after 2040 [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. This suggests the possibility of a regime shift to a more arid climate in the southern Prairies due to the effects of projected summer temperature increases. Future projections of PDSI also revealed that multi-year droughts lasting 10 or more years are more likely than what has been historically observed. Projections suggest approximately three such events per 100 years as compared to the approximately once every 100 years that has been observed. Similar results for the southern Canadian Prairies were also documented by PaiMazumder 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] using simulations from the Canadian Regional Climate Model for the period 2041–2070. Although published studies for the rest of Canada are limited, the authors noted that in more northern areas of the Prairies, drought events are projected to be less severe and less frequent. Considerable uncertainty exists with respect to future precipitation events, particularly on a regional and intra-seasonal basis. Bonsal 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] found considerable range in projections in their assessment of changes to the temporal and spatial characteristics of future (2011–2100) PDSI and SPI using statistically downscaled daily temperature and precipitation data over the southern Canadian Prairies, from three GCMs with different greenhouse gas emission scenarios.
</p>
