<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Length distribution of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">auratus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">N</span>. 
  <span class="italic">doulgassi</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean length of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">auratus</span> recorded on mesophotic reefs was larger than those recorded on shallow reef, with the mean total length of fish on mesophotic reef slightly below the MLL for retention of this species (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206778.g005" href="#pone.0206778.g005">Fig 5a</a>). Mesophotic reefs also had a greater proportion of legally sized fish at 48% compared to shallow reefs 13%. The distribution of lengths also varied between shallow and mesophotic reef with 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">auratus</span> at both depths having a unimodal distribution. However, the mode length on mesophotic reef was greater than that recorded on shallow reef (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206778.g005" href="#pone.0206778.g005">Fig 5a</a>). A Kolmogorov–Smirnov test comparing the length distributions between depths rejected the null hypothesis, suggesting there was a significant difference in the distribution of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">auratus lengths</span> (D = 0.46, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = &lt;0.001; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206778.g005" href="#pone.0206778.g005">Fig 5a</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0206778.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0206778.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Lengths of two of the prominent fishery targeted species.</div>
   <p>a) the length distribution histogram for the total lengths of 
    <span class="italic">C</span>. 
    <span class="italic">auratus</span> at shallow (green) and mesophotic (blue) depths. A boxplot below summarises the distribution of total lengths for 
    <span class="italic">C</span>. 
    <span class="italic">auratus</span> at shallow (green) and mesophotic (blue) depths. b) The length distribution histogram for the total lengths of 
    <span class="italic">N</span>. 
    <span class="italic">douglassi</span> at shallow (green) and mesophotic (blue) depths. Boxplots below summarise the distribution of total lengths for 
    <span class="italic">N</span>. 
    <span class="italic">douglassi</span> at shallow (green) and mesophotic (blue) depths. The MLL for each species has been indicated by a dashed line on each plot.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0206778.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean lengths of 
  <span class="italic">N</span>. 
  <span class="italic">douglassi</span> were very similar between mesophotic and shallow reef (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206778.g005" href="#pone.0206778.g005">Fig 5b</a>). The proportion of fish above the MLL for 
  <span class="italic">N</span>. 
  <span class="italic">douglassi</span> was similar for at both depths. The length distributions appeared to be bi-modal and at both shallow and mesophotic reef with the modes not overlapping (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206778.g005" href="#pone.0206778.g005">Fig 5b</a>). However, Kolmogorov–Smirnov tests comparing lengths at the two depth categories for 
  <span class="italic">N</span>. 
  <span class="italic">douglassi</span> showed no significant difference between depth categories (D = 0.20, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.19; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206778.g005" href="#pone.0206778.g005">Fig 5b</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
