<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reef mapping</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the extent, distribution and structure of rocky reefs in the study region, swath acoustic bathymetry and derived habitat data were collated from previous surveys [
  <a rid="pone.0206778.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206778.ref009">9</a>]. In addition, targeted acoustic surveys were conducted in the region [
  <a rid="pone.0206778.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206778.ref061">61</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All acoustic surveys were conducted using a 125 kHz Geoswath interferometric swath system. Position and vessel motion for sonar acquisition was provided using a POS MV (Applanix, Canada) with Real-time Kinematic height and positional Virtual Reference Station corrections through SmartNet across the Telstra Mobile 3G network using Hypack (Hypack USA) acquisition software. Real-time ephemeris data were saved in POSPac log files for post-processing and calculating a 3 min forward-backward smooth for improved SBET in Single Base Station Mode. Mean SBET positional accuracies were improved to be better than 0.1 for X, Y and Z at nadir. Smoothed best estimates of trajectory were applied to Geoswath data before rough processing using amplitude, box, across-track and along-track filters in GS+. Data were exported as GSF for further data cleaning and cube modelling of soundings and production of a final digital elevation model. Backscatter data were output from GS+ in XTF data and then mosaiced using the Sidescan Solo module within Fledermaus FMGT. Reef extent was hand digitised from hillshaded bathymetry and derived slope layers and identified as ‘reef with profile’.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Spatial Analyst tool and Benthic Terrain Modeller add-on in ArcGis v10.3.1 were used to analyse the cleaned bathymetric data. 50 m and 100 m radius buffers around individual stereo-BRUVS were used to calculate the mean, standard deviation and range for relief, rugosity, ruggedness, curvature and slope. Due to the 200 m separation between stereo-BRUVS, this ensured there were no overlaps. Pearson’s correlations were used to assess data obtained from the 50 m and 100 m radii for correlation.</p>
</sec>
