<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies demonstrated the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> species under changing climate scenarios more in terms of general spatial distribution across bioclimatic domains within areas of interest, with little or no consideration of the influence of ecological subregions [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. In this study we estimate future spatial distribution of dominant malaria vectors and relative climate impacts under low and high emissions scenarios that may affect malaria risk pattern under different ecosystem in tropical region, using a case study of Nigeria. This study builds on an earlier study [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] by assessing prospective changes in the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> sensu lato and its two major siblings: 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> sensu stricto, and 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">arabiensis</italic> across bioclimatic domains within ecological zones and administrative regions in the country, in relation to elemental conditions under both low and high emissions scenarios in 2041–2060 and 2061–2080, respectively. The choice of low and high emissions scenarios may have implications for policies towards the type and level of preparedness and intervention needed to reduce malaria burden caused by malaria vectors within states and regions along ecological gradients, in a world with and without climate policies [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. MaxEnt, a well-established and successful method for species distribution modelling [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] was used based on its reliable usage and high performance among other modelling methods [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] for estimating disease vectors distribution and disease transmissions [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>].
</p>
