<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 2</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Range of likely seasonal total phosphorus loads exported from three UK catchments in the future. Box and whisker plots show the range of likely winter and summer total phosphorus (TP) loads predicted by Data-Based Mechanistic models (DBM) and process-based Hydrological Predictions for the Environment model (HYPE). TP loads for Newby Beck catchment, Eden, winter and summer from DBM 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> and HYPE 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>; TP loads for Blackwater catchment, Wensum, winter and summer from DBM 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold> and HYPE 
   <bold class="bold">d</bold>; TP loads for Wylye catchment, Avon, winter and summer from DBM 
   <bold class="bold">e</bold> and HYPE 
   <bold class="bold">f</bold> for present day conditions (Base), and future conditions representing 2050s (2040–2069) and 2080s (2070–2099) from UK Climate Projections 2009 Weather Generator, high emissions scenarios (2050H and 2080H respectively). HYPE results are mean of all runs with behavioural parameter sets. 
   <italic class="italic">Box</italic> indicates inter-quartile range (25th–75th percentile), with median marked as 
   <italic class="italic">red line</italic>; 
   <italic class="italic">whiskers</italic> extend 1.5 times interquartile range beyond box, or to furthest data point if smaller. Outliers (beyond 
   <italic class="italic">whiskers</italic>) are marked as 
   <italic class="italic">red</italic> +. Observed winter and summer TP loads for 2012/13 are marked as 
   <italic class="italic">black squares</italic>. Winter and summer TP loads predicted using rainfall from high-resolution climate model are marked as 
   <italic class="italic">red filled circles</italic> (baseline conditions) and 
   <italic class="italic">red unfilled circles</italic> (2100s)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_232_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e930" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
