<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-16-02661" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Simulation of the Climate Models</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used daily minimum and maximum near-surface air temperatures data of 32 GCMs from CMIP5 [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-16-02661" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-16-02661">25</a>]. Basic information about these models is provided in 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-16-02661" href="#app1-ijerph-16-02661">Table S1</a>. Since the ensemble mean of these GCM models can filter the uncertainty due to the inter-model variability, it is the best representation of the response to the imposed external forcing. Its predictions are better than those of any individual member [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-02661" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-02661">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-16-02661" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-16-02661">27</a>]; therefore, it was used to reflect the simulated extreme high-temperature changes in this study. We selected only the first run for the multi-ensemble models so that all the models were treated equally. All the model data were interpolated to a common 1° × 1° horizontal grid using a bilinear interpolation algorithm for ensemble analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The period of 1985–2005 is referred to as the present-day period. The preindustrial period in this study is 1861–1900. The CA includes Kazakhstan (KAZ), Uzbekistan (UZB), Turkmenistan (TKM), Kyrgyzstan (KGZ), and Tajikistan (TJK).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on previous research [
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-02661" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-02661">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-02661" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-02661">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02661" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02661">30</a>], we used a time-slice approach based on which the spatial state at a specific warming point related to 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="mm2" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">Δ</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">T</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">I</span>
        <span class="mi">N</span>
        <span class="mi">D</span>
        <span class="mi">C</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> (or 2.0 °C, 1.5 °C) is taken from decadal time slices with the respective mean warming for each model separately. In detail, the time series of the globally averaged surface air temperature was smoothed using a 21-year running mean to filter out the interannual variability of the individual model. The used 21-year time slice includes the median year during which the global mean surface temperature exceeded a given warming target (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="mm3" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">Δ</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">T</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">I</span>
        <span class="mi">N</span>
        <span class="mi">D</span>
        <span class="mi">C</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, 1.5 °C, or 2.0 °C; see 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-16-02661" href="#app1-ijerph-16-02661">Table S2</a>), the 10 years preceding, and the following median year. This method can also be applied for other climate indicators, and thus can relate various indicators to mean global warming.
 </p>
</sec>
