<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change scepticism</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One factor that is crucial for people’s 
  <span class="italic">motivation to mitigate</span> climate change is the extent to which people believe or doubt that climate change is real and will have serious effects. If people are sceptical about climate change, it is unlikely that they will act upon it. In line with this reasoning, some studies showed that higher levels of scepticism are associated with lower levels of endorsement of mitigation [
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref012">12</a>]. Others, however, have found no relationship between scepticism and mitigation [
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref014">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is some evidence that people low in scepticism are more likely to take actions to 
  <span class="italic">adapt</span> to climate change than those high in scepticism [
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref015">15</a>]. However, it is also plausible that people who are sceptical about the reality and relevance of climate change may endorse adaptation measures. More specifically, if adaptation is understood as a possible future alternative to costly and unnecessary (from a sceptical point of view) mitigation efforts in the present, endorsing adaptation is an excuse for not taking any mitigation actions now [
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref016">16</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref018">18</a>] (see also [
  <a rid="pone.0124843.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124843.ref019">19</a>]). In other words, it is possible that climate change sceptics favour adaptation over mitigation because it allows them to stall and block mitigation efforts.
 </p>
</sec>
