<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive capacity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maintaining and improving livelihoods is one of the farmers’ objectives. These require that farmers adapt to changing policy contexts and environment in which they operate. In this context, adaptation is an active decision-making process framed by risk attitude and perception. The risk attitude and perception is influenced both by farmer characteristics and external factors (Maredia &amp; Minde 
  <a rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0029">2002</a>). The role of adaptive capacity, adaptation process and their implication on use of GHG emissions as an indicator in sustainability metrics is particularly relevant in this context. Such reality creates the need to reassess traditional policy instruments in terms of their adaptability to better reflect climate-related externalities of production and consumption (Banuri &amp; Opschoor 
  <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coping capacity defines the ability of people, organisations and systems to face and manage adverse conditions, emergencies and disasters using available skills and resources (UNISDR 
  <a rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0046">2015</a>). Coping strategies are short-term responses to a specific shock such as drought, while adaptive strategies entail long-term change in behaviour patterns as a result of shock or stress (Krantz 
  <a rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0027">2001</a>). The capacity to cope requires continuous awareness, resources and good management both in normal times and during adverse conditions (UNISDR 
  <a rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0046">2015</a>). Coping capacities may thus contribute to reduction of disaster risks. However, some coping strategies such as the use of MS as dairy cattle feed without supplementation may be ecologically undesirable (Volenzo 
  <a rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0047">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reducing farmers’ vulnerability in terms of exposure to risks associated with climate change increases their propensity to engage in more productive economic activities (Siegel 
  <a rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0036">2005</a>). However, high adaptive capacity does not necessarily translate into adaptation actions that reduce vulnerability (IPCC 
  <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">2007</a>; Moser &amp; Ekstrom 
  <a rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0032">2010</a>). Differences in knowledge, attitudes, beliefs and value system could account for this conclusion. The observation suggests that other interventions, such as advocacy, sustained publicity and education, are necessary ingredients in spurring sustainability in climate change action.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The challenging task in planning adaptation activities is finding ways to combine different measures in a meaningful way to avoid maladaptation. The most attractive adaptation measures are those that offer benefits in the near future and reduce vulnerabilities in the long-term (Mimura et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0031">2014</a>). This includes the use of integrated adaptation–mitigation–sustainable development (AMSD) frameworks. As an integral part of wider development goals in transition to sustainability, AMSD frameworks are critical in policy formulation, decision-making, governance and behaviour development (Bizikova, Robinson &amp; Cohen 
  <a rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0007">2007</a>). Adaptation–mitigation–sustainable development planning frameworks include the creation of local implementation pathways that increase opportunities for social learning processes and capacities for effective adaptation and mitigation (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">2010</a>). Crop–dairy integration as one of the potential applications from AMSD frameworks, alongside nutrient recycling in MS-based adaptation strategies, invariably reduces methane emission risks and increases carbon sinks, as adaptation co-benefits. This has the potential of contributing to productive and resilient agricultural production systems (Volenzo 
  <a rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0047">2015</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
