<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sustainable adaptation to climate change risks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Definitions of sustainability vary across sectors, but the common theme is to change the way resources are exploited, and how hazards are managed so that adverse impacts downstream or, for subsequent generations, are reduced. Some of the sustainable development indicators pertain to climate change variables, such as level of GHG emissions (Kates, Parris &amp; Leiserowitz 
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">2005</a>). Sustainable principles call for integration of economic and development policies so that in case of conflict between the two, ecological interests are given a preference (UNEP 
  <a rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0045">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of MS, different supplementation regimes and their effect on methane emissions can be used in exploring and extending sustainability concept to emission and mitigation of GHGs. In dairy production, energy and protein supplementation reduces methane emissions at herd level (Mills et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0030">2003</a>). Thus, supplementation mitigates the negative externalities imposed through CH
  <sub>4</sub> emissions and the resultant radiative forcing risks. However, the domino effect of price and production risks in smallholder agriculture with respect to GHG emissions has received little attention. This linkage could be important in the assessment of poverty–maladaptation–environmental degradation nexus.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dairy sub-sector accounts for about 7% of Kenya’s GDP and 17% of agricultural gross domestic product, in addition to supplying domestic requirements for meat and dairy products (ASDS 
  <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2009</a>). Dairy enterprise is one of the few agricultural systems that produce a consistent cash flow over most of the year (Omore et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0033">1999</a>), with small-scale farmers accounting for 80% of the total milk production and 70% of the total marketed milk in the country (ASDS 
  <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2009</a>). The sub-sector employs about 500 000 people directly and 10 million people indirectly (ASDS 
  <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2009</a>). The sub-sector has grown with annual milk production rising from 2.1 billion litres in 2000 to 5.1 billion litres (valued at KES 100 billion) in 2008 (ASDS 
  <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">About 40% of dairy cattle in Kenya are found in semi-intensive farming systems (ILRI 
  <a rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0020">2009</a>). This feature, coupled with information that these production systems have the highest maize densities, indicates a high potential for benefits from maize–livestock integration (ILRI 
  <a rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0020">2009</a>). The changing climatic conditions, particularly rainfall and temperature patterns, portend adverse impacts on the agricultural sector and other socio-economic sectors in Kenya. Current projections indicate that such impacts will worsen in the future if significant reductions in the anthropogenic GHGs emissions that are responsible for climate change are not made (GOK 
  <a rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0015">2010</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
