<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many species of shorebirds are the focus of conservation efforts aimed at reversing population declines e.g. 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Morrison2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Nebel1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[100]</xref>, so there is a need to prioritize conservation actions that can have the largest impact on the species most in need. The system currently in use for prioritizing shorebird conservation efforts in the United States was developed in 1999–2001 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[1]</xref>, and did not explicitly include vulnerability to the impacts of a changing climate, e.g. 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Godet1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[101]</xref>. Many studies have shown that climate change poses risks to populations of plants and animals and that impacts to vulnerable species are already occurring, e.g. 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Parmesan1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[102]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-MacLean1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[104]</xref>. It is expected that such adverse impacts will become more severe and widespread in the future as the climate continues to change. One major application of the system developed in the present study would be to revise the priority scores given to shorebird species by updating the threat scores with the information presented here regarding vulnerability to climate change. We recommend that the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service revise shorebird priority scores as suggested here, so that the impacts of a changing climate can be more fully integrated into efforts to conserve shorebirds. In addition to applying this information to shorebird species, the same approach could also be applied to other birds. The Partners–in–Flight prioritization system also could be updated to include the approach presented here, if the information on relative risks were collected for other species. This would allow a similar update to reflect vulnerability to climate change across a wide range of bird taxa. We do note that the species assessments and criteria assigned in this manuscript should be considered as first approximations, and will undoubtedly be revised with further discussion by a wider audience. Our primary goal was to establish a system for evaluating the increased risk to species from climate change with respect to existing threat assessments, and to start a discussion about the appropriate values for various species.
</p>
