<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our assessment of extinction risk might be criticized because it does not allow for adaptive capacity in shorebird populations. That is, shorebirds might modify their breeding, migratory, and/or wintering habitat use, foraging, and/or timing to accommodate the changing climate. We already know that some shorebirds in Western Europe have apparently truncated their fall migrations to winter in the Baltic, rather than in oceanic Atlantic countries, such as the UK 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-MacLean1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[104]</xref>. Previously, the winter conditions in the Baltic were so harsh that birds had to move farther to exploit the milder conditions of the UK, Holland, etc. Thus, the ameliorating winter conditions in the Baltic have encouraged changes in migration distance 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-MacLean1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[104]</xref>. Similarly, In North America, some migratory populations of Hudsonian Godwits have advanced their timing of migration during warm periods, which allows their breeding to synchronize with peak food abundance, while other populations have not 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Senner1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[107]</xref>. There also is some evidence that Semipalmated and Pectoral sandpipers and Red–necked and Red phalaropes have been observed breeding earlier during warm years 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Liebezeit1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[108]</xref>. As another example of adapting to changing conditions, Dunlin nestlings can exhibit accelerated growth during periods of low food availability during warm conditions 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-McKinnon1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[109]</xref>. However, it would be unwise of us to assume that such adaptive capacities were likely to apply across all shorebird species because there is evidence that high Arctic shorebird species may have little capacity for adaptation due to low genetic variability resulting from bottleneck events from previous climate shifts 
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Meltofte1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[110]</xref>. Time constraints can also cause conflicts among competing life–history requirements, as has been reported in Pied Flycatchers 
 <italic class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0108899-Both2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[111]</xref>. Clearly more research needs to be done to determine the degree to which climate adaptation might occur in shorebirds.
</p>
