<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text position="float" content-type="box" orientation="portrait" class="boxed-text">
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Impact Summary</title>
 </caption>
 <p class="p">What limits species' geographic ranges on the landscape? One process of interest when trying to answer this question is gene flow, which is the movement of genetic material between populations, as might occur in plants when seeds or pollen move across the landscape. One hypothesis that has been proposed is that gene flow from populations in other environments prevents populations at range edges from adapting to their local habitats. Alternatively, it has been suggested that these populations might benefit from gene flow, as it would provide more genetic material for natural selection to act upon.</p>
 <p class="p">We tested these predictions in an annual wildflower, 
  <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic>. We simulated gene flow by pollinating plants from the range edge with pollen from other populations. Then we planted the resulting seeds into common gardens in the home sites of the range edge populations and recorded their germination, survival, and reproduction. The weather during our experiment was much warmer than historic averages in our garden sites, and perhaps because of this, we found that gene flow from warm locations improved the performance of range edge populations. This result highlights the potential role of gene flow and dispersal in aiding adaptation to warming climates. We also found some positive effects of gene flow that were independent of climate. Even after we statistically controlled for adaptation to temperature and precipitation, plants that were the result of gene flow pollinations produced more seeds and fruits than plants with both parents from the same population. Rather than preventing adaptation, in our experiment, gene flow generally had positive effects on fitness.
 </p>
</boxed-text>
