<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-smoking policy tests</div>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once the main (explanatory) model was completed, three policies were tested: 1) an increase in the excise tax (from $0.44 to either $1.44 or $2.20, representing the actual and two proposed excise tax rates in North Dakota at the time of this research); 2) an increase in funding for comprehensive tobacco control programs (from $9.80 per capita—the CDC recommended level for North Dakota [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]—to $20 per capita, chosen somewhat arbitrarily as roughly double the 2014 value), which was modeled as affecting anti-tobacco media and promotions from the tobacco industry; and 3) improving compliance of retailers regarding sales to minors (from 78% compliance to high school adolescents and 73% compliance to middle school adolescents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>], both to 95% compliance).
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Policies were added to the model as follows. Increases in the excise tax were modeled as reducing the average smoking quantity which in turn reduces initiation and progression rates, and separately as increasing cessation rates. Increased funding for comprehensive tobacco control programs was modeled as lowering tobacco marketing and as increasing perception of health risks. Improved retailer compliance was modeled as reducing perceived cigarette availability, which in turn reduces initiation and progression rates. Policies were implemented in simulation year 2015, and results were simulated through 2032 (allowing approximately 20 years of actual, historical data and 20 years of simulated projections). Each policy was tested in isolation in different simulation runs, and a final simulation run tested all policies together. Policies were evaluated with respect to the projected smoking prevalence resulting from each simulation run, in terms of the percent change in smoking prevalence among adolescents (averaged across middle and high school students). As mentioned in 
  <a rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec8">Model Validation</a>, parameter uncertainty produces some uncertainty in the projected smoking prevalence, so the relative 
  <span class="italic">ranking</span> of effectiveness across policies is of more use than the exact numerical projections, provided that the same ranking is preserved across sensitivity testing of different plausible parameter values.
 </p>
</sec>
