<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various anti-smoking policies and programs have been effective at reducing smoking rates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. However, there is still progress to be made, particularly among adolescents since the majority of smokers initiate in their adolescent years [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. This is a critical period during which to intervene to reduce the smoking-related burden in the general adult population [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. Successful strategies for reducing smoking rates include excise taxes on cigarettes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>] and comprehensive tobacco control programs (which include media campaigns, cessation resources, and interventions) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Another common policy is legislating age restrictions on purchasing cigarettes, though the evidence is mixed as to whether age restrictions in isolation are actually effective in decreasing smoking prevalence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. A related issue is retailer compliance [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]; enforcement efforts aimed at retailers are successful at reducing sales to minors, but this does not necessarily translate into reduced smoking [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A prominent challenge in evaluating the effectiveness of these policies is the uncertainty in their true causal effect on smoking rates, which stems from the limitations of observational data. Specifically, it is rare that an appropriate control group is available for a given policy; and even in this case, the true effects of the policy itself are difficult to tease apart from other influences of the outcome, such as larger economic trends. Thus, confounding is a pervasive challenge in accurately evaluating anti-smoking policies. A further challenge in existing policy research is the limited ability to account for feedback in complex systems. For example, there is a positive feedback loop between smoking behavior and nicotine dependence: smoking behavior leads to the development of nicotine dependence symptoms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>] and nicotine dependence in turn increases and perpetuates later smoking behavior [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. However, conventional regression analyses artificially and inappropriately impose a uni-directional relationship, selecting one as the outcome and the other as a predictor, with only a few notable exceptions that examined the mutual directionality of this relationship [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation methods can overcome many of the limitations found in observational data, and thus represent an important complementary tool to study anti-smoking policies. Previous simulation work has been done using discrete Markov models to estimate the reduction in smoking prevalence and smoking-attributable deaths that could result from tax increases and comprehensive tobacco control policies in both Louisiana [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>], the Netherlands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>], and Brazil [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Additionally, system dynamics modeling has been utilized to model the effects of excise tax policy and smoking cessation interventions in New Zealand [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>] as well as anti-tobacco education in schools [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">System dynamics has a wide range of applications. It decomposes complex systems and can make projections on various effects and consequences of a given decision. Thus, system dynamics is especially useful for studying health policy, agriculture, economics, and climate. Examining the effects of smoking policies among adolescents can be readily applied to system dynamics methodology given that this problem is complex, dynamic, and contains multiple feedback loops. A system dynamics model, which is essentially a formalized set of hypotheses (e.g. about the causes of smoking behavior), can be used to test causal hypotheses and effects within the simulation framework. Thus, system dynamics can overcome many of the methodological limitations of existing studies on smoking policy, provided the model reasonably approximates reality, after calibrating it to the population of interest and performing a series of validation tests (
  <a rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec8">Model Validation</a>). In particular, system dynamics can manipulate a single variable at a time and examine its effect on the system, whereas this is difficult or impossible with statistical analysis of observational data due to the presence of confounders that covary with other variables. In addition, system dynamics is able to account for mutual relationships between variables (i.e. feedback loops), whereas conventional statistical analyses must impose a unidirectional relationship between the variables. Since smoking behavior is driven by a variety of influences and feedback loops, this makes system dynamics a promising tool for studying population-level trends in smoking behavior as well as policies aimed at reducing smoking rates. Very little system dynamics work has been done examining the effects of smoking policies among adolescent populations in particular.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The current study presents a system dynamics model of adolescent smoking behavior and anti-smoking policies. As commonly done in system dynamics, an “explanatory model” was built first with the goal of replicating trends in real data (youth smoking rates from 1992 to 2014); Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> shows this historical data as well as the simulation data from the explanatory model (described in detail below). Second, a “policy model” was built to evaluate and compare the effects of three separate anti-smoking “policies:” 1) an increase in excise taxes for cigarettes; 2) increased funding for comprehensive tobacco control programs as recommended by the Center for Disease Control (CDC) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]; and 3) stricter enforcement of retailers’ compliance with age restrictions on cigarette sales. The model was tailored to the case study of North Dakota, USA, which has one of the lowest cigarette tax rates in the USA [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>] at $0.44/pack—a rate that has remained unchanged since 1993—and at the time of this research was considering legislation that would have substantially increased that tax rate (North Dakota Tobacco Tax Increase, Initiated Statutory Measure 4). Each of these policies were evaluated with respect to their impact on the reduction in youth smoking rates approximately 20 years into the future. 
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Actual vs. simulated data on past-month smoking prevalence. Values are averaged across middle and high school populations. Simulated data are from the “base” stock-and-flow model shown in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Actual data are from the Monitoring the Future (MTF) Study, 1992–2014
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13011_2019_219_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
