<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Causal loop diagram</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CLD presented in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> contains three major positive feedback loops (in which a change in smoking prevalence perpetuates itself via social pressure to smoke, exposure to secondhand smoke, and nicotine dependence) and two major negative feedback loops (in which a change smoking prevalence limits or counteracts itself through awareness of health risks and through enactment of anti-tobacco policies). In isolation, each of the positive feedback loops would produce exponential growth in smoking prevalence, and each of the negative feedback loops would produce exponential decay or goal-seeking behavior. In the full model, these positive and negative feedback loops interact in important ways to produce the simulated behavior that replicates the actual historical data (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The initial rise in smoking prevalence from 1992 to approximately 1995 is produced by the positive feedback in the system – namely the increase in parental and peer smoking and exposure to secondhand smoke, and their reinforcing effects on adolescent smoking rates via increased susceptibility to smoking and smoking initiation rates. However, negative feedback relationships dominate the system starting in the mid-1990’s, as smoking rates start to decelerate, then peak, then decline until the present. Specifically, the Tobacco Master Settlement Agreement in 1998 which banned cigarette advertisement to minors, alleviated the social pressure loop, which resulted in lower initiation rates and reduced susceptibility to smoking.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation model</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The explanatory simulation model (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) contains the essential feedback loops presented in the CLD and described above, along with additional detail such as modules for tobacco marketing (which affects social pressure and price) and other tobacco products (whose effects are limited in this model to nicotine dependence). By and large, the feedback loops produce the behavior observed in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> as explained in the CLD results section; and the stock-and-flow simulation model offers additional insight into how this system produces the observed behavior. That is, modules in the explanatory simulation model were turned “on” and “off” as part of the process of calibrating the simulated data with the real data. Specifically, the negative feedback loops due to heightened perception of health risks of smoking and due to the marketing restrictions from the Master Settlement Agreement were necessary for the model to better match the observed decline in smoking prevalence after the year 2000. Additionally, the model behavior was affected to a large degree by price effects, i.e. how cigarette prices affect smoking rates; adjusting cigarette price to the average income in North Dakota for each year of the simulation resulted in a closer match of the simulated data to the observed data. This highlights the importance of price effects to the system as a whole.
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The full simulation model was subjected to the validity tests described in Methods. Sensitivity tests showed that the model was most sensitive to changes in the effect of social pressure on the initiation rate (producing at most a 25% change in the overall 
   <span class="italic">level</span> of the youth smoking rate), and less sensitive to the exact value for other parameters. However, the 
   <span class="italic">shape</span> of the behavior over simulated time did not change in any case, indicating that the model is fairly robust to changes in uncertain parameters.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Policy tests</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows the results of the policy simulations if they had been implemented in 2015, and projects the current (past-30 day) smoking rate until year 2032 (nearly 20 years after implementation). Though even the base case (no policy changes) shows a decline in the fraction of adolescents who currently smoke cigarettes, each policy further decreases current smoking prevalence. Increasing the excise tax from $0.44 (base case) to $1.44 and $2.20 decreased the simulated prevalence of past-month smoking by 22.3 and 32.6%, respectively, in 2032, relative to the 2032 base case projections (no policy). In contrast, increasing funding for comprehensive tobacco control programs from $9.8 per capita (base case) to $20 per capita decreased the simulated smoking prevalence by 7.0% of the 2032 base case prevalence, and increasing retailer compliance with sales restrictions to 95% (from the base case of 78% for middle school students and 73% for high school students) decreased the simulated smoking prevalence by 3.2% of the base case prevalence in 2032. Finally, all three policies implemented together (with the higher $2.20/pack excise tax) decreased the simulated smoking prevalence by 42.7% in 2032, consistent with an additive effect of each policy. 
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Policy simulations for policy tests for: increases in the excise tax per pack of cigarettes (
      <span class="bold">a</span>); increasing per-capita funding for comprehensive tobacco control programs (
      <span class="bold">b</span>); increasing retailer compliance with sales laws (
      <span class="bold">c</span>); policies A – C implemented together (
      <span class="bold">d</span>). Line type indicates the policy, with 1 (solid line) representing the base case simulation in all panels. Y-axis shows the current (past-30 day) smoking rate, averaged across middle school and high school students
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13011_2019_219_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
