<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">The ongoing increase in greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions is resulting in frequent occurrences of extreme weather and climate events, glacier retreat, sea level rise and deteriorating human health. Therefore, a 2 °C increase in global surface temperature from pre-industrial levels is considered to be a risk-level threshold
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Consequently, if the rise in global surface temperature cannot be restricted to 2 °C, human society will probably face major climate-related disasters induced by global warming
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. The Paris Climate Agreement (2015) proposed a goal of reducing greenhouse gas levels and emphasised that global mean surface temperature increases should be restricted to 2 °C, or even 1.5 °C, compared to the pre-industrial level. Predicting the response of various components of the Earth’s system to a temperature rise of 2 °C has received much attention
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. As a modulator of the Earth’s climate, the cryosphere is a particularly crucial component. Anisimov and Nelson
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup> investigated permafrost distribution in the NH using a frost index under a global mean temperature rise of 2 °C and doubling of CO
 <sub>2</sub> levels. Their projected permafrost extent was 18.34 × 10
 <sup>6</sup>, 18.74 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> and 19.17 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> km
 <sup>2</sup>, respectively, as obtained using the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (GFDL) model, the Goddard Institute for Space Studies (GISS) model and the United Kingdom Meteorological Office (UKMO) model. The near-surface permafrost area in the NH has been estimated using Community Climate System Model Version 4 (CCSM4), revealing that, the permafrost areas during the 2030–2049 period would be 9.3 × 10
 <sup>6</sup>, 9.0 × 10
 <sup>6</sup>, 8.1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> and 8.7 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> km
 <sup>2</sup>, respectively, under RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0 and RCP8.5
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. Slater and Lawence
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> compared the permafrost extent estimated by soil temperature and surface frost index in Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) models. Their results show that permafrost estimation based on CMIP5 models has evident uncertainty, which is closely related to the different structure and parameterisations in different land surface models (LSMs). Furthermore, current models still have limitations in representing subgrid-scale permafrost distribution (e.g. sporadic and isolated permafrost) because of parameterisation uncertainty regarding the occurrence of soil freeze or thaw in LSMs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Koven 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup> suggested that the model differences can be traced to the differences in the coupling between either near-surface air and shallow soil temperatures or shallow and deeper (1 m) soil temperatures. Wang 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> suggested that the permafrost over the Qinghai–Tibet Plateau will significantly degrade in the Bayan Har Mountains and Tanggula Mountains by 2050 under the high-emission scenario. Although previous studies have demonstrated that the permafrost will degrade because of temperature rises caused by greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions, the likely extent of permafrost degradation under a particular risk-level threshold remains to be determined.
</p>
