<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This uncertainty is especially complicated for soil moisture availability, which is dictated by the combination of weather, vegetation, soil and landscape attributes. In dryland ecosystems, soil moisture controls most ecosystem processes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>. Reduced primary productivity occurs primarily during periods of reduced soil moisture and not directly to an absence of precipitation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>. Conditions that diminish harvest yields due to below-normal levels of soil moisture, particularly during the growing period, have traditionally been called agricultural drought (in contrast, for example, to meteorological drought which is a period of below-normal precipitation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>). The notion of reduced soil moisture has been extended to ecosystems and is referred to as ecological drought
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>. Ecological drought is commonly described as a ‘prolonged and widespread deficit in naturally available water supplies […] that create multiple stresses across ecosystems' (US Geological Survey, US Climate Science Centers and the Science for Nature and People Partnership) and has recently garnered widespread attention as one of the topics defining twenty first century climate change
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>. Because of the complexity of the water cycle, soil moisture and ecological drought projections show large uncertainties among GCMs
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>. Soil moisture projections and drying trends are better constrained in subtropical drylands because these are closely linked to the well-represented Hadley Circulation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>. Much of the existing research on climate change impacts to drylands has focused on climatic aridity and meteorological droughts, or has been restricted to subtropical drylands. As a result, much less is known about impacts of climate change on soil moisture and ecological droughts, and in particular in temperate drylands.
</p>
