<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015">
 <label>Table 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Main policies informing climate adaptation in Fukuoka City.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="al0050">Table 3</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Policy</th>
    <th>Year introduced</th>
    <th>Responsible organisation</th>
    <th>Identified areas requiring adaptation action</th>
    <th>Proposed adaptation actions relevant to Fukuoka City</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Fukuoka City Climate Change Countermeasures Action Plan</td>
    <td>2016</td>
    <td>Fukuoka City Environment Division</td>
    <td>Flooding/heavy rainfall; pressure on water resources; health risk from heat hazard; biodiversity loss; effects on agricultural produce.</td>
    <td>Hazard mapping and public communication; developing emergency reservoirs; protection of greenspaces and rivers; promotion of behaviour change.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Fukuoka City New Green Basic Plan</td>
    <td>2009</td>
    <td>Fukuoka City Housing Division, Green City Promotion Section</td>
    <td>Flooding/heavy rainfall; heat island effects.</td>
    <td>Preservation of wind corridors; connecting mountains and sea via ‘green corridors’; creation of ‘green network’; development of green areas for stormwater retention; focus on special measures in Tenjin-Hakata Station ‘hot area’.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Fukuoka City Urban Planning Masterplan</td>
    <td>2014</td>
    <td>Fukuoka City Housing Division, Urban Planning Section</td>
    <td>Flooding/heavy rainfall; heat island effects.</td>
    <td>Preservation of greenspaces and rivers; creation of ‘green network’; developing emergency reservoirs (as per New Green Basic Plan).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Fukuoka Prefecture Climate Change Countermeasures Action Plan</td>
    <td>2017</td>
    <td>Fukuoka Prefecture Environment Division, Environmental Protection Section</td>
    <td>Flooding/landslides from heavy/intense rainfall; health risks from heat hazard; effects on agricultural produce.</td>
    <td>Understand green infrastructure and ecosystem service potential in adaptation via research; behaviour and practice change among agricultural workers; hazard mapping and public communication; stormwater management.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>National Plan for Adaptation to the Impacts of Climate Change</td>
    <td>2015</td>
    <td>Government of Japan</td>
    <td>Reduction in crop quality, drought; species extinction; flooding/landslides from increased rainfall; increases in storm surge and high wave risk; increased summer heat waves.</td>
    <td>Promotion of development of local adaptation plans; provision and development of local-level climate data and locally-specific information; support model projects and knowledge-sharing.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Climate Change Adaptation Act</td>
    <td>2018</td>
    <td>Government of Japan</td>
    <td>7 priority areas: agriculture, forestry, fisheries; water environment and resources; natural ecosystems; natural disasters; human health; industries and economic activity; life of citizens.</td>
    <td>Municipalities mandated to form Local Climate Change Adaptation Plans, and also to assign a Climate Change Adaptation Center for data collection and provision.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
