<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the best examples of polyploidy contributing to invasion success is tetraploid spotted knapweed, 
 <italic class="italic">Centaurea stoebe</italic>. Although both diploids and tetraploids were introduced into the USA from Europe, invasive populations are dominated by tetraploids (Treier et al. 
 <xref rid="b296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Tetraploids are pre-adapted to a wider range of climates compared to diploids, and following introduction, they may have further adapted to their introduced environment (Treier et al. 
 <xref rid="b296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Henery et al. 
 <xref rid="b134" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). A classic example of hybridization and polyploidy coinciding with invasion is 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina anglica</italic>. This species is a recently formed allopolyploid (12×) that is highly invasive compared to its parental species, is able to colonize a broader range of habitats and exhibits substantial phenotypic plasticity (Thompson 
 <xref rid="b290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1991</xref>; Ainouche et al. 
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>), despite a strong genetic bottleneck that occurred during its formation (Baumel et al. 
 <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2001</xref>). Neo-allopolyploids often undergo extensive alterations to their genome and transcriptome, and genomic studies of 
 <italic class="italic">S. anglica</italic> are dissecting the genetic, epigenetic and expression changes following hybridization and genome duplication (Salmon et al. 
 <xref rid="b252" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Ainouche et al. 
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Chelaifa et al. 
 <xref rid="b59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). However, the mechanism by which 
 <italic class="italic">S. anglica</italic> has become invasive remains elusive, and it is not known whether the success of this species reflects fixed heterosis and restored fertility of the hybrid following genome duplication, or phenotypic novelty due to epigenetic and transcriptome remodelling.
</p>
