<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the majority of research examining the effects of climate change on food systems has focused on crop yields (Lobell and Asner, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Hertel et al., 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Lobell et al., 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), this systematic literature review highlights that multiple environmental variables linked to climate change also significantly impact crop quality as measured by secondary metabolites associated with flavor attributes and health claims for human consumers (Wolfe et al., 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Liu, 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Specifically, findings provide evidence that shifts in seasonality, water stress, geography, light factors, altitude, herbivory and microbes, temperature, and soil factors that are linked to climate change can result in both increases and decreases up to 50% in secondary metabolites. A gap was found regarding evidence on the direct effects of carbon dioxide on tea quality, highlighting a critical research area for future study. The reviewed studies provides evidence that environmental factors linked to climate change can result in changes in the following biochemical measures of tea quality: phenolic catechins (i.e., epigallocatechin gallate, epicatechin gallate, epigallocatechin, and catechin gallate), total phenolic concentration, antioxidant activity, caffeine, theaflavin, thearubigin, tannins, carotenoids, terpene alcohols (i.e., linalool and geraniol) and other aromatic volatiles, fatty acids, chlorophyll, enzymes, and enzymatic activities. It is important to note that while an increase in many secondary metabolites represents an increase in crop quality, it may represent a decrease in crop quality for other secondary metabolites including those with off flavors or whose increased consumption by human consumers may result in toxicity (Kfoury et al., 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). While this systematic review provides evidence that multiple environmental parameters are impacting tea quality, the directionality and magnitude of these impacts is not clear with contradictory evidence between studies. Findings build on a recent literature review highlighting the importance of understanding climate change effects on tea production (Marx et al., 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) by providing evidence on the multi-directionality of changes in crop quality in response to shifts in environmental factors that are shifting with global change. As crop quality is a key determinant of health in the food system, findings have broader implications for other culturally-relevant crops managed and used by people for food, medicinal, and aesthetic purposes including fruits, vegetables, tree nuts, and beverage crops (Ahmed and Stepp, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).
</p>
