<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Due to limited observational data, it is challenging to distinguish between the impact of climatic variability and anthropogenic disturbances on the phytoplankton in coastal waters. Paleoecological methods, using geochemical and biological information preserved in the sediment to reconstruct the short‐ or long‐term environmental change, have supported significant findings in marine research, although a series of biological, chemical, and physical factors (e.g., water depth, temperature, salinity, grain size, and degradation) during sedimentation and preservation can impact the results (Fischer &amp; Wefer, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). A few proxies have been widely applied to reconstruct sea temperature, terrestrial input, and phytoplankton biomass, due to their biosynthetic specificity and resistance to degradation in the sediment. Schouten, Hopmans, Schefuß, and Sinninghe Damsté (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) proposed TEX
 <sub class="sub">86</sub> (TetraEther indeX of tetraethers consisting of 86 carbon atoms) as a proxy for SST, based on the relative distribution of marine archaea isoprenoid glycerol dialkyl glycerol tetraethers (GDGTs). The selected GDGTs are membrane lipids synthesized by Thaumarchaeota, which contain different numbers of cyclopentane and cyclohexane rings. It has been demonstrated that the addition of rings into GDGTs enables archaea to adjust membrane stability in response to temperature changes (Chong, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Uda, Sugai, Itoh, &amp; Itoh, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). The long‐chain 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>‐alkanes (C
 <sub class="sub">27</sub> + C
 <sub class="sub">29</sub> + C
 <sub class="sub">31</sub>), specific to higher land plants, can help to interpret the impact of terrestrial input in marine sediments in terms of changes in rainfall, river discharge, or dust input (Eglinton &amp; Hamilton, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1967</xref>; Seki et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). A few sterols are verified biomarkers for diatoms and dinoflagellates, for example, dinosterol (4α, 23, 24‐trimethyl‐5α‐cholest‐22(E)‐en‐3β‐ol) is produced almost exclusively by dinoflagellates, and brassicasterol (24‐methylcholest‐5, 22(E)‐dien‐3‐ol) is a commonly used diatom biomarker, even though it has been reported in many algal classes (Rampen, Abbas, Schouten, &amp; Sinninghe Damste, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Volkman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>). The analysis of these compounds in the sediment core can help to reconstruct the long‐term changes in the environmental change and phytoplankton community as well as their correlation.
</p>
