<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, Cygnet Bay, located in the Kimberley, northwestern Australia (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33836-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>a), was chosen to study the phytoplankton regime shift in response to the climate change. The Kimberley is a remote coastal region with very limited anthropogenic activity and significant climatic variability. During the past several decades, SST and rainfall have been reported as the most prominent climate‐induced changes in the northwest coast of Australia. For example, annual averaged SST has warmed by ca. 0.6°C in the past 50 year (Lough, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) and annual rainfall increased approximately 50% since 1950 (Feng, Li, &amp; Xu, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Shi et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). More recently, Furnas and Carpenter (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) found that primary production in northern Australia increased more than twofold post‐1990 compared to the 1960s, but considering the paucity in data, they attributed the difference to the improvements in productivity measurements. Liu, Peng, Keesing, Wang, and Richard (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) analyzed the variation in organic matter in the sediment cores, which were collected from Cygnet Bay, and they suggested that the variability in climatic signals (rainfall and temperature) might explain the increase in marine organic matter over decadal scales. Therefore, it warrants further examination to elucidate whether the increase in phytoplankton production in the northwest of Australia since the 1990s was related to climate‐induced SST and rainfall changes. Diatoms and dinoflagellates are the dominant phytoplankton in Kimberley coastal waters (Thompson &amp; Bonham, 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) thereby allowing us to use brassicasterol and dinosterol to represent diatom and dinoflagellate biomasses. Four proxies (TEX
 <sub class="sub">86</sub> index, long‐chain 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>‐alkanes, brassicasterol, and dinosterol) were chosen and analyzed, using the dated sediment cores from Cygnet Bay, to reconstruct the variations of SST, terrestrial influence, and the diatom and dinoflagellate biomasses, respectively. Validity of biomarker reconstruction and the change in SST and phytoplankton over time are discussed in the context of historical observation data.
</p>
