<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For the species distribution model we used presence/absence information for European beech derived from an international monitoring network (ICP level I—more than 8000 plots with 1097 presence observations of European beech) as response variable that we combined with high-resolution derivations of precipitation and temperature from the WorldClim- database, which implies modelling the realized niche of the species. For the projection under future conditions, we used output from the global circulation model HADCM3 driven by the SRES scenario A2 [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] until the year 2080, which was calibrated and statistically downscaled to 30-arc-second tiles. We fitted a Generalized Linear Model (GLM) with logit link function and calibrated the model by a stepwise selection using the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) with five bioclimatic variables entering the model including: yearly sum of degree days above 5°C, iso-thermality, a yearly drought index, sum of precipitation in the warmest quarter of the year and the precipitation of the most humid month. As the threshold value for transforming predicted probabilities into binary presence information we used Cohen’s Kappa. We used the area under curve (AUC) of the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) and Cohen’s Kappa to evaluate the performance of the model. Both, AUC with a value of 0.86 and Kappa with a maximum value of 0.43, indicate good performance of the model (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0158823.s001" class="xref">S1 Fig</xref>). To validate the model we carried out a 10-fold cross-validation, for which we randomly split the data into a training and an evaluation dataset. The model appears to be robust with the cross validation means being very close to the model values and the variation within cross validation results being low (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0158823.s003" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>). The species distribution maps for current and projected climate were intersected with a map of the Geology of Europe depicting calcareous and limestone substrates. More detailed information on the statistical species distribution modelling is provided in the Supplementary Materials and Methods.
</p>
