<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The lower temperatures observed in our 5%-25% deforestation experiments are in agreement with previous modelling studies where the albedo effect outweighs the increase in CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> for high latitude deforestation [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Differently from these earlier results, our cooling is magnified in the 45%-100% scenarios by a decrease in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> caused largely by an accumulation of soil carbon over deforested areas. By 2100 our 100% simulation produced cooling of approximately 0.4 K, with an average cooling over the duration of the simulation of 0.33 K. The average cooling is similar to what was found by previous experiments where a cooling of 0.25 K is observed [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], but at 2100 we obtained cooling that was only about half of what is modeled by other simulations [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. In terms of albedo, we detected high-latitude increases ranging from 2.02% to 12.74% by 2100, with larger deforestation events producing higher increases in albedo. This is higher than the 10.7% increase of high latitude albedo at 2100 obtained by earlier efforts [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. When global albedo is considered, our average increases of 0.01 to 0.04 are smaller than what was observed by other experiments that reported a global average increase of 0.07 [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. It is likely that the discrepancies between our results and these past efforts are at least partly due to differences in the selection of the latitudinal ranges used by the different experiments [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
