<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hindcast simulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We carried out a series of experiments in which the model was subjected to temporally varying histories of the three economic forcings: (1) ex-vessel fish price (that is, the price that fishermen receive per mass of catch), which has varied over time in response to market conditions; (2) cost per unit effort, which includes capital, fuel, labour and the impact of most subsidies and (3) technological progress (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Methods</a>). Our definition of technological progress includes advances in embodied technology, including more efficient boats, more effective fishing gear, sonar and communications equipment and disembodied technology, such as better knowledge of fish behaviour and more efficient fishing practices
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>. The combined effect of embodied and disembodied technology is represented in a simple but inclusive way by a catchability parameter, which was increased at rates of 2, 5 and 8% per year, a range representative of progress estimated empirically from individual fisheries
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>, the simulated changes in global harvest do not reproduce the observed increasing 20th century trend when forced individually with reconstructed changes in price or cost alone. Given the open-access assumption, this implies that increasing demand for fish was not the main driver of the long-term 20th century increase in fish harvest, despite population growth, although a growing population may have helped to maintain demand in the face of an increasing fish supply. Nor could the reconstructed changes in the cost per unit effort of fishing have been the primary driver. In contrast, the three simulations with technical progress produce global histories of harvest with long-term 20th-century increases, more consistent with the observations. With increasing technology the model also simulates a global peak of harvest, as observed, which arises from the sequential development, overexploitation and/or collapse of fisheries throughout the world, a sequence that has occurred historically in poorly managed fisheries
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a> (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Methods</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The technological progress rate of 5% per year would appear most representative as a global, long-term average, given that it approximates the observed relative increase of harvest between 1950 and 1996 and is near the midpoint of estimates from individual fisheries
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>. Given this apparent support for a long-term average technological progress rate of roughly 5% per year, we apply it together with the historical price reconstruction to generate a standard global hindcast, shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>. The agreement of the hindcast simulation with the reconstructed fish harvest, effort and biomass (compare 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a> with 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>) is remarkable, given that these are emergent properties of the model. The effort estimated before 1970 (∼7 GW) is notably higher than that simulated by the model ensemble (1–5 GW), but given difficulties in reconstructing historical global fishing effort
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" href="#b2">2</a>, these contrasts may not be significant. The estimated rate of biomass decrease is well-reproduced by the model at ∼10% of pristine biomass per decade, but with an important difference following 1990 when the estimated rate of biomass loss slowed (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1c</a>), in contrast with the model. This divergence would be consistent with a progressive improvement in the management of many fisheries over the past three decades, a change that is not captured by the idealized OA simulations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model simulations also reproduce the first-order aspects of the 20th-century spatial changes in fish harvest, first depleting the dense biomass of highly productive coastal waters
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a>, and then moving into deeper waters of the open ocean
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4</a>). The expansion away from the coasts arises in the model as technological progress makes open-ocean waters with low biomass density more profitable, and therefore increasingly subjected to fishing effort. It should be emphasized that this model does not account for higher costs of fishing far from port, nor does it include complex ecosystem interactions, habitat alteration, fisheries management, or spatially variable economic factors, all of which played some role in the history of the global fishery. Nonetheless, it successfully reproduces the first-order features of the historical global trends in harvest, effort, and biomass. We therefore hypothesize that technological progress, at an average rate of ∼5% per year, dominated the development of the global wild capture fishery during the 20th century, while other societal, economic and climate forces had secondary impacts.
 </p>
</sec>
