<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model forcing and simulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model is forced with ocean temperature and net primary production, either from satellite-based observational estimates, or from the Institut Pierre Simon Laplace (IPSL) global climate model
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" href="#b50">50</a>, using the historical hindcast followed by the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5 scenario. The factors at play during the historical transient, according to the model framework, include the increase of catchability due to technology
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>, and an observational estimate of the global average ex-vessel fish price
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">51</a>, which has varied remarkably little (‘Ex-vessel Price variations’ in the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Methods</a>). Given that there is no currently available estimate of historical variations in cost per unit effort, we roughly approximate its potential role using its relationship with observed price, effort and harvest under open-access, and making a steady-state assumption (‘Historical global average cost per unit effort’ in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Methods</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the future projections, the OA model is integrated under four idealized scenarios, two of which assume a continuation of the same 5% per year exponential increase in fishing technology, while the other two simulate a gradual decrease in the rate of progress after 2006, reaching stabilized-technology after 2036. Given that technological progress is clearly continuing through advances such as improved fish tracking, the deployment of fish aggregating devices, and the increasing mechanization of fleets in developing nations, the technology-stabilization scenarios are included as baselines from which to estimate the long-term importance of future technological progress, rather than representing realistic future outcomes. For each of the technological scenarios, we address uncertainty in future market conditions by changing the ex-vessel price. Because the price of fish depends on the demand for fish products, which is difficult to predict given its dependence on societal preferences, available substitutes, and distribution networks
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">52</a>, we apply two end-member scenarios for ex-vessel price: linearly increasing, and constant. These represent the outcomes that might come from a larger population and/or a greater preference for seafood (increasing price), or a ready availability of substitutes from terrestrial food production (constant price), and bracket a wide range of intermediate possibilities.
 </p>
</sec>
