<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model overview</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the foundation of the model is energy production by phytoplankton, which is transferred to multiple fish size-spectra according to an efficiency that depends on gross ecosystem metabolic rates
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">44</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">45</a>. The fish spectra are defined as representing the entire range of finfish and invertebrates with individual mass greater than 10 g, commercially harvested before 2006. The spectra resolve basic life-history characteristics, including temperature-dependent growth, mortality and density-dependent recruitment. By including all commercial species within the spectra, we implicitly account for species range shifts
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" href="#b46">46</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">47</a>, evolution
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">48</a>, and changes in targeted species, all of which have been significant historically and could play important roles in the future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An economic model, coupled directly to the fish spectra at the grid scale, predicts fishing effort as a function of local profit, assuming open access to the available fish, following the classic work of ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">49</a>. Fishing effort in each grid cell changes over time according to the difference between local revenues and costs, at a rate determined by the fleet adjustment timescale. The effectiveness of fishing effort at catching the locally available biomass is determined by a catchability parameter that encapsulates both embodied and disembodied technology. Although fisheries are not strictly open access, and approximately one third of fisheries currently has some form of reasonably effective management
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>, the absence of effective management from most of the world’s fisheries throughout the 20th century makes it a good approximation at the global scale during the historical period
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a> as well as an illustrative example to consider the importance of management in future. The approximate global Maximum Sustainable Yield (MSY) is calculated by conducting transient simulations in which catchability is increased slowly, and summing the maximum harvest obtained in each grid cell. A more complete description of the model is given in ‘Model description’ in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Methods</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
