<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additional files</div>
 <sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM1_ESM.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 1: Appendix S1.</span> The number of 
       <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> territories and birds on the mountains in the study area.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM2_ESM.tiff" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 2: Figure S1.</span> A map of alpine plant communities in the study area, which include Japanese stone pine (
       <span class="italic">Pinus pumila</span>) communities (shown in blue), snowbed grassland communities (green), and alpine fellfield communities (orange). The three plant communities were extracted from a digitized vegetation map provided by the Ministry of the Environment of Japan (
       <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodic.go.jp/trialSystem/EN/info/vg67.html" class="ext-link">http://www.biodic.go.jp/trialSystem/EN/info/vg67.html</span>, accessed in September 2012).
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM3_ESM.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 3: Table S1.</span> Median and ranges (minimum to maximum) of four climatic variables under current (JMA 1996) and 24 future climate scenarios (Meehl et al. 2007) with their spatial resolutions in the study area (36.25–36.5°N, 137.5–137.7°E). WI: warmth index (Kira 1948), TMC: temperature of the coldest month, PRS: summer (May-September) precipitation, MSW: maximum snow water equivalent. Summary of the current climate was shown above the dashline, and summaries of 24 future climate scenarios were shown under the dashline.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM4_ESM.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 4: Appendix S2.</span> The code for developing a generalized additive model (GAM) of sub-model A in R. Abbreviations in the code are as follows: data.csv in line 1, dataset which include response variable and explanation variables; RpPA in line 3, presence and absence data of territories of the rock ptarmigan; AfR in line 3, area fraction of alpine fellfield communities; SgR in line 3, area fraction of snowbed grassland communities; DistR in line 3, distance from the ridge; PpR in line 3, area fraction of 
       <span class="italic">Pinus pumila</span> communities; STUDY_TIME in line 3, the number of surveys.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM5_ESM.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 5: Table S2.</span> Akaike information criteria (AIC), differences of AIC from best model (ΔAIC) and Akaike weight for each model of sub-model A, which used a generalized additive model for predicting the distribution of 
       <span class="italic">Lagopus muta japonica</span>. S(DR, AFPp) shows interaction smoothing term of distance from the ridge (DR) and area fraction of the 
       <span class="italic">Pinus pumila</span> community (AFPp). S(AFFf) and s(AFSg) indicate the smoothing terms of area fraction of fellfield community and snowbed grassland community. Null means a null model without explanatory variables.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM6_ESM.tiff" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 6: Figure S2.</span> The additive logistic fit of 
       <span class="italic">Lagopus muta japonica</span> occurrence to four explanatory variables. Values on the y axis of (
       <span class="bold">A</span>) and (
       <span class="bold">B</span>), and contour lines in (
       <span class="bold">C</span>) show the linear predictor for the variables, which indicates the extent of positive and negative effects of each explanatory variable in the model. The dashed curves in (A) and (B) are pointwise two times of standard-error bands, which can be viewed as ~95% pointwise confidence intervals. Horizontal red dashed lines in (A) and (B) indicate the zero value of the estimate for each variable. Significant effects of explanatory variables on the model are shown in red, blue, and open boxes, which indicate positive, negative, and neutral, respectively, in (A) and (B). In (C), the warmer the color, the more positive the effect of the explanatory variables. Values on each contour line in (C) show the linear predictor for the two variables.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM7_ESM.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 7: Table S3.</span> Akaike information criteria (AIC), differences of AIC from best model (∆AIC) and Akaike weight for each model of sub-model B1 which used a generalized additive model for predicting the distribution of alpine vegetation zone. S(WI, TMC) shows interaction smoothing term of warmth index (WI, Kira 1948) and minimum temperature of the coldest month (TMC). S(PRS) and s(MSW) indicate the smoothing terms of summer (May-September) precipitation and maximum snow water equivalent (MSW). Null means a null model without explanatory variables.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM8_ESM.tiff" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 8: Figure S3.</span> The additive logistic fit of the alpine vegetation zone occurrence to four explanatory variables. Values on the y axis of (
       <span class="bold">A</span>) and (
       <span class="bold">B</span>), and contour lines in (
       <span class="bold">C</span>) show the linear predictor for the variables, which indicates the extent of positive and negative effects of each explanatory variable in the model. The dashed curves in (A) and (B) are pointwise two times of standard-error bands, which can be viewed as ~95% pointwise confidence intervals. Horizontal red dashed lines in (A) and (B) indicate the zero value of the estimate for each variable. Significant effects of explanatory variables on the model are shown in red, blue, and open boxes, which indicate positive, negative, and neutral, respectively, in (A) and (B). In (C), the warmer the color, the more positive the effect of the explanatory variables. Values on each contour line in (C) show the linear predictor for the two variables.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12898_2019_238_MOESM9_ESM.tiff" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Additional file 9: Figure S4.</span> Importance of climatic and topographic variables for three alpine plant communities in sub-model B2 (random forest). The importance of each variable was identified based on increased mean square errors (increased MSE; Breiman 2001).
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
