<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions and conservation planning for 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> based on habitat predictions
 </div>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We showed that the potential habitats for 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> would dramatically decrease under different climate change scenarios, although limited potential habitats were predicted to be maintained. These sustainable potential habitats are considered as refugia for the survival of the population under future climatic conditions. Fortunately, all of these areas have already been included in protected areas; however, revision of the management policy, including raising the protection level, restricting human entry to the mountains, and tightening food waste management, are necessary for enhancing the protection of this species within these areas. Moreover, it is also necessary to monitor changes in the size of the 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> populations in the future. However, an increase in the numbers of predators (e.g., foxes) and grazing ungulates such as deer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>] may accelerate the decrease in 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> numbers before the effects of climate change become apparent.
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive management, including preventing the invasion of competitive species, assisted breeding, and assisted migration, represents an alternative strategy to reduce the impact of climate change on species and their habitats. Ecological disturbance, such as an increase in competitors, may induce a marked decline in 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> populations, even in the sustainable habitats of this species. Shifts of terrestrial mammals (e.g., Japanese red fox 
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes japonica</span>, sika deer 
  <span class="italic">C. nippon</span>, wild boar 
  <span class="italic">Sus scrofa</span>, Japanese macaque 
  <span class="italic">Macaca fuscata</span>, and Asian black bear 
  <span class="italic">Ursus thibetanus</span>) into the alpine zone with changing climate may also accelerate the decline of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span>, due to an increase in predation pressure and competition for alpine plant species as food resources. The protection of chicks has already begun through the use of artificial cages, which reduce high mortality due to heavy rain in the early fledgling period and predation by terrestrial animals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. These types of adaptive management may be required to ensure the conservation of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> under future climate conditions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A nationwide-scale assessment of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> populations is a future prospect. Nationwide-scale assessments are expected to help identify the most vulnerable populations and pinpoint candidate areas for assisted migration, as an alternative means of adaptive management. Assisted migration may be the only strategy to prevent the extinction of many montane species, particularly the alpine Rock Ptarmigan that was the focus of the present study, which face habitat loss as suitable climatic conditions migrate upward and off the top of mountain ranges [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. For the planning of conservation strategies at a nationwide scale, we believe that our modeling approach, which describes the structure of the alpine ecosystems, is useful and could be applied to other regions.
 </p>
</sec>
