<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data construction</div>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> data
  </div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the study area, the 
   <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> population size was estimated at 352–376 territories and 860–920 birds, based on the results of intermittent surveys from 1971 to 2010 (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Appendix S1). By way of comparison, the total number of 
   <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> in the 1980s was approximately 3000 birds [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. In this analysis, we used the distribution of territories as occurrence data of 
   <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span>. In Japan, 
   <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> lives in the alpine zone of the mountains above 2200 m. The mean territory size of cocks (males) during the breeding season ranges from 0.015 to 0.072 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. On the basis of this information, we defined the grid cell size for projection of the potential habitat as 300 m (0.09 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>). Grid cells that did not overlap with the territories were defined as absence.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vegetation data</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a digitized vegetation map provided by the Ministry of the Environment of Japan (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodic.go.jp/trialSystem/EN/info/vg67.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.biodic.go.jp/trialSystem/EN/info/vg67.html</span>, accessed in September 2012, Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>: Figure S1). The data were constructed based on the 6th and 7th national surveys on the natural environment (2001 and 2003), which had a scale of 1:25,000. We extracted natural alpine vegetation in three communities: Japanese stone pine (
   <span class="italic">P. pumila</span>), snowbed grassland, and alpine fellfield. We divided the study area into 60,000 grid cells, based on the stipulated 300-m grid cell size. Area fractions for each community type in the Rock Ptarmigan territories and 300-m grid cells were calculated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic data</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic data for grid cells, with a resolution of 30″N × 45″E (i.e. ~ 1 km resolution, ca. 1 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>), obtained from the Japan Meteorological Agency [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>], were used to model the current distribution of alpine vegetation. The dataset is calculated from meteorological temperature observations collected between 1953 and 1982 and precipitation data collected between 1953 and 1976. Four climatic factors considered important for forming alpine vegetation were used as explanatory variables in the species distribution model: (1) the warmth index, which is defined as the annual sum of positive differences between monthly mean temperature and + 5 °C [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] and provides a measure of effective heat quantity required for plant growth; (2) monthly mean daily minimum temperature in the coldest month (minimum temperature), which is a measure of extreme cold; (3) summer (May–September) precipitation, which provides a measure of water supply during the growing season; and (4) maximum snowwater equivalent (maximum snowwater), which provides a measure of snow accumulation. Maximum snowwater was calculated by aggregating daily changes in snowfall, rainfall, and meltwater (degree-day method) based on the daily climatic dataset supplied from the Automated Meteorological Data Acquisition System. Snow disappearance dates were derived from 10-day composites of Satellite data and climatic data for grid cells [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future climate change scenarios</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the impact of climate change by incorporating the uncertainties related to general circulation models (GCMs), we applied 24 GCMs from the World Climate Research Programme (WCRP) Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 3 (CMIP3) multi-model dataset [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>] as future climates (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>: Table S1). The climate change scenarios were generated based on scenario A1B of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Special Report on Emission Scenarios, which assumed rapid economic growth, the rapid spread of new and efficient technologies, and a balanced emphasis on all energy sources [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The A1B scenario is most commonly cited as a high emission scenario in the Fourth Assessment Report of IPCC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. We selected the A1B scenario as a possible future because we considered that we should assess the worst case first for the purpose of conservation. The A1B scenario is similar to between Representative Concentration Pathways 6.0 and 8.5 in the later climate scenarios CMIP5 in the Fifth Assessment Report of IPCC, which is second and highest emission scenarios [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. We only used the data for the period 2081–2100 because the fractional uncertainty for natural factors of internal variability (such as the El Niño Southern Oscillation, which occurs every few years or decades) is larger in shorter-term climate scenarios. Such internal variability is a noise for global warming prediction, which would emphasize or cancel the effects of greenhouse gases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. The climate of the twentieth century experiment (20c3m) was used as baseline for current climate. We calculated differences in the means and minimum daily temperatures, and ratios of precipitation between 1961 and 1980 of 20c3m and 2081 and 2100 of the A1B scenario. These differences and ratios were spatially interpolated from original spatial scales (approximately 125 km to 444 km in latitude) to 1-km grid cells using a simple linear interpolation method, and then applied to the current climatic data (i.e. climatic data for grid cells) and used as future climatic data. The four climatic variables in each grid cell were calculated using the future climate scenarios in the same manner as the calculations for current climate. When comparing the current climate to the future climate scenarios within the study area, warmth index and minimum temperature increased in all scenarios, summer precipitation increased in all but four scenarios, and maximum snowwater decreased in all scenarios (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>: Table S1).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Topographic data</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We constructed topographic data based on a 10-m-resolution digital elevation model that was supplied by the Geospatial Information Authority of Japan by using the System for Automated Geoscientific Analyses (SAGA, URL: 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.saga-gis.org/en/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.saga-gis.org/en/index.html</span>). The topographic data were constructed at 100-m resolution, which was assumed appropriate for estimating the fraction of the areas for alpine vegetation. Five topographic factors, which are thought to be important for plant growth, were calculated, namely, inclination, slope direction, curvature, topographic wetness index (TWI) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>], and distance from the ridgeline.
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in the cover and height of 
   <span class="italic">P. pumila</span> is closely related to the degree of wind exposure and snow depth in high mountains during winter, together with microtopographic change. The height of 
   <span class="italic">P. pumila</span> decreases gradually as the degree of wind exposure increases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. The degree of wind exposure is higher closer to the ridgeline on the wind-blown slope side in winter [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Thus, distance from the ridgeline was measured as the topographic factor that is considered to affect the height of the 
   <span class="italic">P. pumila</span> community.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
