<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sustainable and vulnerable populations of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> in Japan
 </div>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results showed that in the study area the majority (more than 99%) of potential habitat for 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> will disappear by 2081–2100, regardless of the uncertainty in GCMs (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). A previous study that assessed the effects of climate change on 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> showed that 80% of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> populations would disappear if the temperature rises by 3 °C [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. In the Swiss Alps, Revermann et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>], using several SDMs. predicted a decrease of up to two-thirds in the potential habitat of 
  <span class="italic">L. m. helvetica</span> by 2070, and a shift of potential habitat toward the mountain tops. Potential habitats for subspecies of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta</span> throughout Europe were predicted to decrease progressively from approximately two million square kilometers at present to approximately one million square kilometers by 2080 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. In the 2080s, 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> populations are predicted to decrease even more sharply compared with European populations of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta</span>, and thus may represent the 
  <span class="italic">L. muta</span> subspecies most vulnerable to global warming. One reason for the high vulnerability of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> is that the habitat in Japan is at the southern limit of the global distribution for this species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. A second reason is the difference in the altitude inhabited by 
  <span class="italic">L. muta</span> species in the Swiss Alps compared to Japan’s northern Alps. The highest altitudinal peak in the study area is 3190 m, whereas the highest altitudinal peak in the Swiss Alps is 4609 m. In Japan, the alpine vegetation used by 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> already extends to the top and ridges of the mountains, whereas the nival zone, which is covered in snow throughout most of the year at present, occurs above the alpine zone in Europe. Therefore, in future, the alpine vegetation in Japan has little potential habitat above the current habitat range, whereas alpine vegetation in Europe has a larger potential habitat above the current alpine zone. Consequently, the negative influence of future climate change will be larger on 
  <span class="italic">L. muta</span> habitats in Japan compared to those in Europe.
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sustainable potential habitats were predicted to occur in just three grid cells in the northwestern part of the study area under future climate conditions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>a). Our results show that both climatic factors, including cooler temperature, greater snow, and lower summer precipitation, and topographic factors, such as closer to the ridge, leeward, and gentler slope, are positively important for sustaining the potential habitat of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span>. Potential habitats with GCM-related uncertainty were predicted to occur in the central and northwestern parts of the study area (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>b). Potential habitats should be considered high-priority candidates for investment in climate adaptation practices.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some uncertainties may still remain regarding prediction of the future potential habitat of 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span>. Plant species have plasticity to environmental change, which may moderate the decreasing speed of alpine plant community distributions. SDMs are based on the hypothesis that relationships between 
  <span class="italic">L. muta japonica</span> and alpine plant communities will not change even after climate change (the hypothesis is called niche conservatism [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]). Variation among SDMs and greenhouse gas emission scenarios may also be a source of uncertainties regarding future predictions. However, we believe that these uncertainties would probably not change the general trends in our results, although detailed values may be changed.
 </p>
</sec>
