<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An improved understanding of the geographic distributions, use of maternity roost sites, and population trends in forested areas of western North America [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>] and under key climate change scenarios [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] will also help biologists and managers protect bat populations in arid regions of western North America. For example, a plausible and testable hypothesis is that fringed myotis (and other forest bat) distributions will tend to erode along the edges of current distributions in areas where fertility and population dynamics models suggest that population growth rates will be lowest (e.g. in southern New Mexico and Arizona for fringed myotis; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0180693.g003" class="xref">Fig 3</xref>). Given that in this analysis some simulated bat populations decreased to near 0 in just 77 years, biologists, resource managers, and policy makers may need to take proactive actions to support populations and species of concern that are most vulnerable to population erosion under future climate scenarios. In addition to the research discussed above, these actions might include: working with public land management agencies and private land-owners to identify and protect key maternity roost and water resources used by reproductive females and their young; minimizing human disturbance and predation at key maternity roosts, for example by installing bat gates where appropriate; taking action to prevent the spread of bat diseases into key maternity and other roost sites; protecting, and when appropriate, enhancing foraging habitat associated with forest and riparian areas near key maternity roost sites; creating artificial water resources near maternity roosts (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]); and minimizing or preventing disruptive human activity, such as recreational rock climbing and noisy forest treatment procedures near maternity sites during the late spring and summer months. All of these conservation tactics would be focused on supporting or improving fertility rates and maintaining high survival rates, and thus help maintain conditions to support stable populations.
</p>
