<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because of their small size and nocturnal habits it is difficult to estimate population sizes of bat species over large spatial scales, such as that of the Southern Rocky Mountain region, or the contiguous United States [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. As a result, there is currently a lack of high quality estimates of population sizes and trends of most North American bat species. Thus, we unequivocally emphasize that the simulation results presented here have only been used as first approximation models [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] to evaluate the conjecture that a changing climate can have non-trivial impacts on some simulated bat populations. Nevertheless, the current lack of reliable population estimates makes conservation and management planning challenging, especially in the face of other recently emerged threats to North American bat populations such as diseases (for example, white-nose syndrome) and wind energy related bat fatalities. Even under optimal conditions, temperate zone insectivorous bat species usually exhibit slow population growth rates due to the tendency of these species to give birth to one young per year and high mortality rates during a bat’s first year of life [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Given their contribution to mammalian species diversity in North America and their ecological and economic importance, it will be helpful to continue monitoring and research on the current and future impacts of changing climate conditions on bat populations in western North America. It would also be helpful to support efforts to estimate and monitor bat distributions and populations throughout North America (e.g., North American Bat Monitoring Program [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]), especially if such efforts collect and analyze reliable information on species occurrence, age structure and reproductive rates, and contribute to collecting long-term time series data over multiple decades from repeated sampling of the same study sites.
</p>
