<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The plant materials were hot pepper plants (cv. “Supermanita,” Nongwoo Bio Co., Suwon, Korea) and seeds were sown on 16 February 2016 into a plug tray (35 ml/cell) filled with commercial soil (Bio media, Hungnong Seed Co., Korea) in a glasshouse at the National Institute of Horticultural and Herbal Science, located in Wanju (35°16′N, 127°02′E, 32 m above sea level). Air temperature was maintained at 25–30°C during the daytime and at 15°C at night time. Sixty‐four days after sowing, seedlings were transplanted into 2.7 m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> containers filled with a clay loam type of soil in the extreme weather growth chambers (EWGC; Modified CEEWS model, Environmental Growth Chambers, Chagrin Falls, OH, USA). The EWGC was equipped with artificial light system, a combination of 12 400‐W metal halide lamps (MS400, Philips Lighting, Amsterdam, Netherlands) and 12 400‐W high‐intensity‐discharge (HID) lamps (LU400, GE Lighting, East Cleveland, OH, USA). The plants were grown with 30 cm spacing in each row, at a plant density of 3.3 plants/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Plants were watered twice a day, and the following fertilizer program was applied in the experiment at planting (2,000 kg/ha for composts, 135.0 kg/ha for N, 64.0 kg/ha for P
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>, and 60.6 kg/ha for K
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O). Additionally, the nutrient solution was applied approximately 1.5 L/plant weekly from 40 days after transplanting (DAT) to 171 DAT. The nutrient solution was composed of 808.8 mg/L KNO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, 944.6 mg/L Ca(NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·4H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, 153.4 mg/L NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>PO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, and 493.0 mg/L MgSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>·7H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O as macroelements. Microelement composition was 3 mg/L Fe as Fe‐EDTA, 0.5 mg/L H
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>BO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, 0.5 mg/L MnSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>·4H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, 0.05 mg/L ZnSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>·7H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, 0.02 mg/L CuSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>·5H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, and 0.01 mg/L Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>MoO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>·2H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O.
</p>
