<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Tamias speciosus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> surveyed in this study were collected from montane transects in Yosemite National Park (YNP) and the Southern Sierras (SS). Historic samples were collected by Joseph Grinnell and his colleagues from 1911 to 1916, and are preserved as dried skins in the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology (MVZ), at the University of California, Berkeley. Modern samples were collected from the same sites by the ‘Grinnell Resurvey’ team led by MVZ researchers and collaborators from 2003 to 2012 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008119.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pgen.1008119.s011" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>). We examined 100 YNP 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic> (52 historic, 48 modern), 104 YNP 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> (56 historic, 48 modern), and 90 SS 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> (52 historic, 38 modern) from each transect. We also sampled six 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">minimus</italic> (the Least chipmunk) collected east of YNP, which were used to test for potential hybridization between 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">minimus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Furthermore, we included one sample each of three other species (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">striatus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ruficaudus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">amoenus</italic>) in order to polarize SNPs identified in our focal populations. Historic DNA was extracted from toe pad tissue (~3 x 3 mm) in a separate dedicated laboratory using a previously described protocol [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. DNA was extracted from modern samples using Qiagen DNeasy Blood and Tissue kits following the manufacturer’s protocol. Genomic libraries for all samples were constructed following Meyer and Kircher [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] with slight modifications [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>].
</p>
