<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the first step of analysis, to determine the foremost lag time, the best combination of inputs and to evaluate the effects of climate variables on cholera disease modeling, GT was applied. A modeler needs much time to calibrate and test different built models for all input combinations and also, there is no idea, how many data points required for calibration. The results of GT and GA can considerably reduce the model workload and help to focus on the best selection of inputs. The GA search and optimization techniques were used to evaluate the best combination of input variables for predicting the target which was chosen by smallest the asymptotic gamma statistic (the best MSE) between 2"-1 meaningful combination for a particular output [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The gradient and V-ratio also indicate the model complexity and the degree of predictability of given outputs [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Thus, a model with low gamma and smaller gradient and V-ratio are assumed as the best scenario for modeling. We indicated the impact of climate variables on cholera disease were lagged by 21 days (21DL). Our reason for choosing different lag times for variables was evaluation of the sensitivity of the cholera disease to delay in the effect of climate events. These lag times between the changes in climatic variables and the disease emergence may acquire, due to (a) time required to grow pathogens, (b) exposure to infections, (c) incubation period, (d) disease detection and (e) report delayed. Bacterial diseases have a shorter delay time than other pathogens and react more quickly to changes in temperature and precipitation [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. For example, maximum correlation coefficients between malaria incidence and sea surface temperatures in Colombia was happened with a 6 to 8 month lag [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], while the findings of Constantin de Magny in Bangladesh were shown the short time lag (one month) between environmental variables and cholera epidemics [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
