<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For generation of local-scale daily climate scenarios, baseline parameters of the LARS-WG (calculated from observed weather data for the period 1976–2005) modified for 2021–2050 under two RCP scenario files predicted by selected GCM model. In other words, by using this technique, the future values of local precipitation and temperature were generated for the Qom. To calibrate WG, synthetic daily weather data were generated by the parameters file in the Qom sites and then the observed and synthetic data were compared. In the current study, 10 GCMs experimental outputs were used and compared with the 30-year recorded climatic values and also, LARS-WG model applied for statistical downscaling to analyze and project future climate pattern under two scenarios of RCP2.6 and RCP8.5. Several studies applied GCMs to estimate the changes in disease in their area [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Furthermore, some studies were used LARS-WG to generate daily site-specific climate scenarios for the future [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The findings of this study are in agreement with Mohammadi's findings that simulated the impact of climate change on emergency medical services clients in Tehran, Iran. In fact, they predicted a wetter and warmer climate for their study area by the year 2050 [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In another study, the effect of climate change in the Saguenay watershed in Canada was investigated by LARS-WG downscaling technique. Their results have shown a clear increase in monthly average of both minimum and maximum temperatures (2.5 °C between current and 2080s climate) but there was not any significant changes in the daily average of precipitation in the study area [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
