<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The impacts of climate change on cholera disease were simulated using a feed-forward MLP type of ANNs. To build a network, the trial-and-error approach was used and to find the optimum network, training multiple times was applied. In addition, cross-validation was carried out and performance of the network was tested to protect it against overtraining. The optimized NN has one hidden layer and Tan Axon and Momentum were set as layer’s transfer function and learning rule, respectively. Different studies applied ANNs to predict the diarrheal and cholera outbreaks in distinct areas of the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Pezeshki et al. used a multilayer perception ANNs to create a model and predict cholera disease in Chabahar, Iran. They applied monthly average of temperature, humidity and rainfall as climatic variables and their results illustrated that cholera cases were significantly related to humidity and there was a significant relationship between the cholera incidence and lack of rainfall [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Considering the importance of controlling the infectious diseases, many studies were done to estimate the effect of climate changes on infectious diseases in human societies in the future and prepare helpful prediction tools [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Accordingly, in another study, a new BPNN Model was established to predict the number of infectious diarrheas in Shanghai of China with climatic variables as input. Moreover, the results of BPNN Model were compared with SVR, RFR and MLR models. Their results indicated that BPNN model creates the best prediction results compared to the MLR, RFR and SVR models. In addition, sensitivity analysis defined that temperature-related variables (T
 <sub>max</sub>, T
 <sub>min</sub>, and T
 <sub>avg</sub>) were the effective climatic factors on infectious diarrhea while rainfall had minimum effect [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
</p>
