<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was a component of a larger qualitative investigation by the study team using semi-structured interviews to evaluate a voluntary A&amp;F initiative targeted towards team-based primary care practices in Ontario, Canada. The first study from this investigation explored why primary care clinics chose to participate in the A&amp;F program [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. The present study evaluated the subsequent implementation of the intervention. Due to considerable methodological overlap, methods and procedures for the present study are summarized here and expanded upon where relevant.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Setting and context</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Family Health Team (FHT) is a primary-care practice model in Ontario, Canada where a multi-disciplinary team of health care providers collaborate to provide patient-centred care [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. The FHT model emerged in parallel with the patient-centred medical home (PCMH) and is thought to meet similar standards and requirements [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. All FHT services are available at no cost to the patient and providers are remunerated by the Ontario Ministry of Health and Long Term Care (MoHLTC) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Team members and roles vary between practices. The multi-disciplinary, non-physician, providers on the team are salaried and may include Nurse Practitioners, Social Workers, Dietitians and other regulated and/or unregulated health professionals. The group of physicians affiliated with a FHT may organize under a range of legal structures and are remunerated under a blended capitation model [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. It would be appropriate to characterize this setting as a partnership between physicians and the FHT (which represents the interdisciplinary health professionals), as the organizational structures granted to physicians are intended to preserve physician autonomy. The FHT is typically led by an Executive Director who serves as an organizational and administrative lead. Governance of the FHT may be one of three types: i) physician led, where the affiliated physician group makes up the full board; ii) mixed, where governance is shared between the FHT and affiliated physician group; or iii) community sponsored, where governance is led by the FHT and community representatives. At the time of this study there were 184 FHTs in Ontario, serving approximately 3.5 million patients (25.4% of the Ontario population) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intervention</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2014, the Association of Family Health Teams of Ontario (AFHTO) launched Data-2-Decisions (D2D) as an A&amp;F program and strategy to support FHT efforts to measure and improve the quality of team-based primary care [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. As a not-for-profit advocacy association, AFHTO is mandated to promote the delivery of high-quality primary health care among its membership. AFHTO has engaged in a number of activities to evaluate and subsequently improve D2D as part of a fulsome change management strategy [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. While AFHTO facilitated recruitment and provided background information for this study, the funding, design, data collection, analysis, and dissemination of this evaluation were independently executed.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">D2D is a voluntary initiative, informed by the work of Barbara Starfield to include meaningful measures of quality in primary care [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. For the purposes of this study, D2D is classified as an external A&amp;F initiative since it was organized by AFHTO to provide targeted feedback to FHTs. The measures included in D2D are assessed and selected by an AFHTO sub-committee of relevant stakeholders including FHT staff, beyond Executive Directors, who would ultimately receive the D2D reports. Selected measures were intended to reflect patient centered care, access, and guideline concordant practice. Metrics included within the final category (cancer screening, childhood immunization rates and diabetes care) reflect areas of priority identified by Health Quality Ontario or AFHTO itself as well as Canadian practice guidelines [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. In other words, D2D deliberately consolidated indicators from multiple initiatives and sources believed, from the perspective of AFHTO members, to be of high-priority. An example of the feedback report, the measures of interest, source of data and rationale for inclusion are presented in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>. At the time of this study, the audit included three sources of data: FHT electronic medical records, annual patient experience surveys, and administrative data. For measures relying on administrative data, values were acquired in their raw format from the agency responsible for housing it or in summarized format extracted from a primary care group practice report produced by Health Quality Ontario [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Each participating FHT extracted their measures from the relevant source and then manually transcribed them into an online data-entry portal made available by AFHTO during the audit period. The timing of the inputs to the feedback report, relative to its release is presented in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several weeks after the audit process, AFHTO notified participants that their D2D feedback report was available on a password protected website. Notifications were distributed via email, and participants were invited to engage in an AFHTO-hosted webinar to understand the results. As presented in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>, the D2D feedback report provides a summary of a FHT’s performance relative to a group of peers. Peer status is determined by four self-reported characteristics of each participating FHT: urban or rural setting; teaching status (none, academic, non-academic); access to hospital discharge data; and roster size of the practice.
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To facilitate D2D participation, AFHTO collaborates with Quality Improvement Decision Support Specialists (QIDSS). These individuals are funded by the Ontario MoHLTC and are a shared resource among a group of FHTs to support ongoing quality improvement activities. As QIDSS’ responsibilities are exclusive to QI, they are not involved in the daily operations of the FHT. The QIDSS role varies between FHTs to meet individual practice needs. AFHTO provides QIDSS staff with specific training so that they can support D2D. As the availability of the QIDSS resource is not linked to D2D participation, these individuals may engage in separate QI activities within each practice.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interview sampling frame was drawn from FHTs that met two eligibility criteria: i) the FHT had agreed to participate in an AFHTO-led developmental evaluation of D2D, and ii) the FHT had participated in at least one iteration of the A&amp;F program. Following the release of the third iteration of the feedback report, Executive Directors (ED) from eligible FHTs were invited to participate in semi-structured interviews to discuss their experience with D2D. These leaders were targeted as informants as they were the intended recipients of the feedback report. In recognition of the role played by other team members, additional informants who were more familiar with D2D processes and procedures were invited at the discretion of the ED. Additional informants included Physician Leaders, QIDSS staff, and interdisciplinary health professionals.</p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Criterion sampling was utilized to ensure variability across FHTs for practice setting, roster size, teaching status and the Standardized Adjusted Clinical Group Morbidity Index (SAMI). The SAMI is a measure indicative of the relative complexity of patients rostered to a FHT [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. Informants were recruited via email, with the first group of practices identified by AFHTO using an in-house composite measure of quality which is included in the D2D feedback report. All subsequent recruitment groups were selected by the lead investigator (DJW) by actively monitoring representation across the four above measures [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously described, the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR) was used as the conceptual framework for this study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Two key factors served as the rationale for the use of CFIR against some alternative. First, CFIR reflects a consolidation of theories across implementation science. Second, CFIR offers researchers flexibility in selecting constructs which are considered to be relevant to the study. Furthermore, having a standardized taxonomy of constructs allowed for some comparability of findings across studies [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. In the present study, it offered a means to evaluate whether, how, and why different types of FHTs may have engaged D2D to guide their QI activities.
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interview guide for the present study was prepared from a template made available by CFIR’s developers. As described previously, the template guide was adapted to reflect the objectives of the present study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Further revisions to question structure and sequencing occurred prior to recruitment following piloting of the interview guide with a FHT leader who did not participate in the study.
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviews began by defining the study context and building rapport. Open-ended questions were then asked to explore how FHTs use D2D, their motivations for participation, and the resources required to participate. Probing questions were used to further explore areas of interest and specific points raised by informants. Next, participants were invited to complete a usability testing exercise of the online D2D feedback report. Informed by user-centred design methodology, usability testing is a technique to evaluate whether the intended users of a product or service can achieve desired tasks. In the context of the A&amp;F literature, usability of the feedback report is an issue which is addressed infrequently, despite the proliferation of electronic feedback [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Participants were encouraged to “think out loud” as they attempted to complete two distinct tasks on the D2D website [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. In the first task, participants were asked to load their team specific results in the interactive feedback report on the D2D web-page. In the second task, participants were asked to review their results for the core D2D measures. This approach offered an opportunity to ask probing questions seeking confirming or disconfirming evidence from earlier in the interviews. For example, in the main interview, participants were asked about D2D support materials. Data collected could be validated in the usability exercise by asking the user where they would look for clarity about the data, among other items. The usability testing supported two distinct outputs. First, a summary was provided to AFHTO to support future enhancements to the D2D website design. Second, data were used to support the analysis for the present study as described in the procedures below.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis</div>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Qualitative analysis was facilitated by NVivo software [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. A framework approach was utilized to analyze the transcripts based on constructs within the CFIR. As with the interview guide, a modified version of the codebook, made available by the CFIR developers was used to analyze interview transcripts. Double coding and the development of the codebook followed the procedure previously reported [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Construct selection for the frameworks was based on identified relevance to the research questions and was done following data collection, but 
   <span class="italic">prior</span> to analysis. This approach can be described as a directed content analysis that leveraged a priori constructs from an established framework and is consistent with previous uses of CFIR [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The framework for the first research question (whether D2D implementation reflected a complete feedback loop), included the CFIR constructs “Executing” and “Engaging”. Text was then analyzed inductively to classify findings into one of three stages of the feedback loop: 
   <span class="italic">audit</span>, 
   <span class="italic">feedback</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">response</span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With respect to the second question (barriers and facilitators to implementation reflective of a complete feedback loop), the framework was generated from thirteen constructs: “Relative Advantage”, “Adaptability”, “Relative Priority”, “Organizational Incentives and Rewards”, “Compatibility”, “Leadership Engagement”, “Available Resources”, “Access to Knowledge and Information”, “Opinion Leaders”, “External Change Agents”, “Reflecting and Evaluating”, “Parallel Initiatives”, and “Usability Testing”. To identify emergent themes from the data, the text was analyzed inductively, and the resulting themes were then categorized by one of three CFIR domains: 
   <span class="italic">intervention characteristics, outer setting,</span> and 
   <span class="italic">inner setting.</span>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
