<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">We define future-oriented conservation as policy, planning and management that effectively anticipates change and actively prepares for it over the long term. In order to achieve this, there are currently a wide range of possible approaches, tools, methods, strategies and processes (see Gross et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" class="xref">2016</xref>; Abrahms et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2017</xref>). For protected area policymakers, planners and managers, it can be difficult to know where to start, especially when tools or methods have been developed to suit other ecological, social and political contexts, and different possible futures. We distilled from the literature four propositions regarding how future-oriented conservation could be achieved via four transitions for conservation managers:
 <list list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par17" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">From strategies and practices based on resisting ecological change to strategies and practices that anticipate and accommodate ecological change</italic> Conservation is, almost by definition, concerned with conserving ecosystems, species or landscapes in their current state or restoring them to a previous state. Related climate adaptation literature and scientific research more generally have tended to frame the primary goal of adaptation as building resilience in ecosystems, increasing the capacity of ecosystems to maintain or return to their core characteristics despite changing climatic conditions. However, strategies based on resilience, stasis or restoration may not be sufficient in a changing climate (Baron et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2009</xref>; West et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">2009</xref>; Boyd et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2015</xref>), and may even be counterproductive if resources are directed towards maintaining features that will inevitably change (Dunlop 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2013</xref>). Anticipating and accommodating involves both practical changes and a more conceptual change, as traditional conservation ideals, goals and targets (key species, historic communities) might no longer be suitable guides for management (Tschakert and Dietrich 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2010</xref>). This is not simply substituting one source of information for another, but a shift in the social and political basis of decision-making (Adger et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2009</xref>), from objective “things” (species, ecosystems) that were previously central to conservation concern to subjective “values” that are contestable and more overtly political.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par18" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">From conservation goals and targets focusing on ecological attributes to goals and targets that also focus on social values and benefits</italic> Conservation goals that relate to specific attributes such as particular species or communities may become unreachable as ecosystems change. While including social values is sometimes noted as an important aspect of adaptive management for protected areas (e.g., Lockwood 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2006</xref>; Tanner-McAllister et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2017</xref>), we propose that a focus on social values and benefits can offer an additional management path, as benefits may persist even as ecological attributes change. For example, where an important benefit of a protected area is supply of clean water, the landscape processes that produce clean water may remain even if the species of trees or understory in a forest change. This helps people to understand that benefits can persist even if ecosystems transform. For simplicity, we deliberately merged 
    <italic class="italic">benefits</italic> (what people get) and 
    <italic class="italic">values</italic> (what people like/want) by assuming that people value something that provides benefits. This transition implies a general recognition that maintaining benefits experienced by people may be different from maintaining the current state of the ecosystems themselves (Chan et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2006</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par19" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">From understanding climate adaptation as a scientific issue to understanding it as a governance issue</italic> Scientific knowledge and technical solutions are often assumed to be the best resources and strategies to support conservation (Godet 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2006</xref>; Gabriel 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2014</xref>; Rannow et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">2014</xref>), and many partners and participants in our study reflected this view. This is consistent with Archie et al’s empirical research where conservation decision-makers noted “lack of information” as a key barrier to adaptation (Archie et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2012</xref>; see also Lonsdale et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2017</xref>). While climate change projections are improving, the impacts on specific protected areas are typically uncertain, and implementation options implied by technical analysis can be infeasible (Lemieux and Scott 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2011</xref>). Yet even with precise information, managers are confronted by a complex array of social and political challenges when making adaptation decisions that emerge from contested values, multi-layered policy challenges and institutions that are often resistant to change (Eriksen et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2015</xref>). Focusing on climate adaptation as a governance issue opens conversations about how we organise ourselves to address changing ecosystems, including identifying other (non-technical) information that may also be useful for decision-making. For example, incorporating social values and benefits requires consultation on what those benefits are, who receives them and how they are prioritised.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par20" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">From conservation practices based on problem-solving to practices based on ongoing learning</italic> All of the above imply a more dynamic and uncertain management environment; the problem of climate change cannot be “solved” in any conventional sense. Consistent with adaptive management approaches, interventions need to be informed by new knowledge from many sources, and adapt as biophysical conditions and societal values continue to change (Olsson et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" class="xref">2006</xref>; Berkes et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2008</xref>). Research on anticipatory approaches suggests management should complement activities focused on solving defined problems (e.g., a water shortage) with learning as social and ecological conditions change (e.g., water planning) (Tschakert and Dietrich 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2010</xref>; Boyd et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2015</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
