<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This study focused on exploring the variations in climatic suitability and planting regionalization for potato in northern China under climate change. The results provided a scientific basis for sustainable potato production in northern China to adapt to future climate change. However, the impacts of climate change on potato suitability and planting regionalization in northern China are complex, with many attendant uncertainties. Several areas of uncertainty identified in this study may outweigh the final results. First, because of collected data limitations, potato growth season in this study wasonly divided into 3 stages (from sowing to emergence, from emergence to flowering and from flowering to maturity), and more detailed stages of development were not fully taken into account, possibly obscuring the results. It is generally believed that the potato growth season can be divided into 6 stages: germination period (bud sprout from stem to emergence), seedling stage (emergence to bud), tuber formation period (bud to beginning flower), tuber growth period (flower to senility of stem and leaf), starch accumulation period (senescence to senility of stem and leaf) and dormancy period of the tuber (fully mature or harvested). It is noteworthy that potential differences among the growth stages were found in response to differences in the local climate and type of management system. Second, the comprehensive production effect on potato planting was ignored in this study and was therefore a source of uncertainty. In this study, the suitability of potato planting in northern China was investigated from the perspective of the development and utilization of climate resources. In practice, potato production and industrial development must be comprehensively considered in terms of climate conditions, industrial policy, market supply and demand, agricultural technology advancement, and so on. Third, as for the comprehensive climate suitability of the potato, the weight was determined by the correlation coefficient method in this study. There are many ways to determine the weight, such as the empirical method and the multi-actor statistical method [
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. It is well-known that each method has its advantages and disadvantages. Therefore, there were differences in the final results caused by the calculation methods.
</p>
