<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig3" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Simulated impact of subglacial topography and bathymetry on grounded ice volume response to different atmospheric forcing, oceanic forcing and eustatic sea levels. Ice sheet simulations are forced with (
   <span class="bold">a</span>) mid-Miocene glacial climate
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span>, an eustatic sea level fall of 70 meters below present; (
   <span class="bold">b</span>) same as for a. but with late-Pleistocene glacial climate (here LGM
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
   </span>); (
   <span class="bold">c</span>) same as for (
   <span class="bold">b</span>) but with an eustatic sea level fall of 120 meters
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Thus, (
   <span class="bold">a</span> and 
   <span class="bold">c</span>) corresponds to full mid-Miocene and full late-Pleistocene glaciation cases. The impact of atmospheric forcing on ice dynamics, i.e., the difference between (
   <span class="bold">a</span> and 
   <span class="bold">b</span>) is shown in panel d. The impact of prescribed eustatic sea level on ice sheet dynamics, i.e., the difference between (
   <span class="bold">b</span> and 
   <span class="bold">c</span>) is shown in panel e. For each of the four topographies, four simulations are carried out using different sub-ice-shelf melt rates (
   <span class="italic">bmelt</span>, blue dot and purple square) and calving thickness thresholds (
   <span class="italic">Hcalv</span>, blue circle and empty purple square). Simulations are repeated by inhibiting glacial isostasy (black bars) or by enhancing the impact of basal hydrology (grey bars). For these last two sets of simulations, only the range of volume spanned by the simulations is displayed. Individual ice volumes are reported in Tables 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>–
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a>. Colored stars are simulated ice volume for LGM or Miocene from literature. Finally, dashed lines correspond to present-day Antarctic ice volume
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span>. See Methods and Supplementary material for details on the settings of the model and simulations.
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41598_2018_29718_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e775" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
