<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We only selected sites with reliable stratigraphies in which layers possess a clear cultural attribution given by the excavators. Additionally, we collected all reliable radiocarbon dates corresponding to these layers. Some authors assume the presence of a Badegoulian as a random diffusion from France onto the IP. The number of sites is very low and the inventories are small as well [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Due to this weak and scattered presence we assume that any influence on our data can be neglected and we exclude these very rare sites from our analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For the Iberomaurusian, few sites without well documented stratigraphy, but with archaeological assemblages and reliable radiometric dates were kept in the database. For Morocco, the period between the end of the Middle Palaeolithic (around 30 ka calBP [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], and the onset of the Iberomaurusian is one of the most enigmatic phases—archaeological layers dated to this period are extremely rare and the classification of the lithic record is still doubtful. Considering these uncertainties, we decided not to include evidences from the so-called Early Upper Palaeolithic in the present study. Concerning the Iberomaurusian itself, current chronostratigraphic data support a division of the techno-complex into two phases, the transition corresponding to the transition from the cold-dry Greenland Stadial 2.1 (GS-2.1) including HS 1 to the warmer and moister Greenland Interstadial 1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Accordingly, in this work we define all evidences prior to the climatic amelioration of Greenland Interstadial 1 (Bölling/Alleröd) as Early Iberomaurusian, and all those in the Interstadial as Late Iberomaurusian. Sites without a clear chronological attribution were simply defined as Iberomaurusian 
 <italic>sensu lato</italic> in the following analyses.
</p>
