<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because of the complicated policies of nature reserve management in different countries, and because the current distribution range of 
 <italic class="italic">D. involucrata</italic> is only in China, also because 94% of future (2070) potential distribution range of this species is within China, we only discuss conservation strategies in China in this study. Climate change may threaten habitat suitability of threatened plant species within Chinese nature reserves
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b68" class="xref">68</xref>. Establishment and management of protected areas (nature reserves) must include consideration of all the current distributed sites of 
 <italic class="italic">D. involucrata</italic>, and must recognize the species’ future distribution in response to future climate conditions. Up to 56.3% of the present-day presence points of this species are outside the protected areas (nature reserves) of China (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9" class="xref">Fig. 9A</xref>). Under the present climate, 73.9% of modeled potential habitats are outside the existing protected areas (nature reserves) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9" class="xref">Figs 9B</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10" class="xref">10</xref>, and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table S5</xref>). Under future 2070-CCSM RCP 2.6 scenario, 69.3% of potential habitats in China would be outside the protected areas (nature reserves) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9" class="xref">Figs 9C</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10" class="xref">10</xref>, and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table S5</xref>). Under the other five scenarios for the year 2070, 57.6‒70.2% of potential habitats in China would be outside the protected areas (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10" class="xref">Fig. 10</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S5</xref>). On an average of all the six predicted models for the year 2070, 64.8% potential habitats in China would be outside the network of nature reserves (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9" class="xref">Figs 9C</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10" class="xref">10</xref>, and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S5</xref>). In view of the effects of global climate change on this species’ geographic distribution, we urge designation of these currently unprotected areas as priority for conservation, and particularly the establishment of the highest priority protected areas for the most suitable habitats (i.e., the high-probability ones, 0.5‒1). As seen in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f9" class="xref">Fig. 9</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>, the most urgent needs for new nature reserves are in the south-western mountainous margin of the Sichuan Basin and the central China Mountains (that is, around the Three Gorges Region). In addition, despite not harboring highly suitable habitats (threshold‒0.5), (i.e., Dalou Mountains), it is urgent to set up or enlarge the current protected areas in the southeastern mountainous margin of the Sichuan Basin, in order to maintain the current genetic corridor between the eastern and western lineages of 
 <italic class="italic">D. involucrata</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b69" class="xref">69</xref>. At present this area is the only one that effectively connects genetically both lineages (such a corridor does not exist along the northern margins of the Sichuan Basin
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b69" class="xref">69</xref>). As an additional measure, introduction/reintroduction of 
 <italic class="italic">Davidia</italic> stands would be an efficient measure to avoid the growing physical isolation of the current patches (and, thus, offsetting the effects of genetic isolation). We should bear in mind that the species is prone to genetic isolation because of its proven weak seed dispersal capacity
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b69" class="xref">69</xref>, a probably low pollen dispersal ability
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b70" class="xref">70</xref>, a poor germination
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b71" class="xref">71</xref> and low seedling recruitment rate
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. The combination of distributional, genetic, and biological information can be used to conserve 
 <italic class="italic">D. involucrata</italic> and nearby Tertiary relict species through effective and efficient management planning in the Nature Reserve system and in other management activities (e.g., translocations).
</p>
