<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Evidence for the impact of climate change on Arctic Char was presented in the form of a time-series (1981–2014; 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic> = 13) of Fulton’s condition factor (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>), a widely used index of the wellbeing or robustness (i.e., mass relative to length) of individuals or populations of fish
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> (for criticisms of the use of condition indices see refs. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>). The authors concluded that there was a significant decline in the condition factor of Arctic Char during these years as a result of climate-mediated changes in this ecosystem. We argue, however, that the statistical analysis used to assess the significance of that trend is problematic. We re-analyzed the presented data, which was graciously made available by the authors, using the same analysis as described in the paper. Here, we highlight three issues with the authors’ approach. First, the authors reported a significant quadratic regression model (
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">2, 1133</sub> = 8.47, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.0002 in our analysis), whereas the quadratic term itself was not significant (type 3 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1, 1133</sub> = 0.1659, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.684). Second, and more importantly, each individual measurement was treated by Lehnherr et al.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> as an independent data point in the analysis, artificially inflating the reported significance (a problem further accentuated by the unequal sample sizes among years). In the current data set, observations from the same year are likely to be more similar than observations from different years, violating the assumption of independent errors of multiple regression. This aspect of the data should have been treated with an alternative approach such as including a random effect of year or using the annual mean condition factor to test the hypothesis of a decline across years. For instance, the quadratic regression model working on the annual mean condition index is no longer significant (adjusted 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.0075; 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1, 10</sub> = 1.045; 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.387) and neither is a linear regression (adj. 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.047; 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1, 11</sub> = 1.597; 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.233).
</p>
