<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Each El Niño event can differ in magnitude, which is commonly measured by the corresponding SST anomalies in the eastern tropical Pacific
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. Recent projections indicate that very strong El Niño events, also called extreme or super El Niño events, are expected to increase in frequency in the future under global warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. A major impact on stratospheric circulation has been observed during the three unusually strong El Niño events that have occurred during the satellite era; i.e., the 1982/83, 1997/98, and 2015/16 El Niño events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Domeisen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> reviewed on the question that whether strong El Niño events lead to a proportionately stronger stratospheric response compared with moderate El Niño events, where discrepancy was noted. Garfinkel 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup> shown stronger response to extreme El Niño comparing with that to moderate El Niño in North Pacific Sea Level Pressure field with weak nonlinearity in the location of the extrema; Weinberger 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup> suggested that stratospheric response to extreme El Niño is weaker than proportionate amplitude of El Niño strength. But some idealized experiments have different results. Zhou 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> found that the magnitude of the simulated stratospheric response to extreme El Niño events was four times stronger than that to moderate ones in late winter and early spring; Jimenez-Esteve and Domeisen
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup> showed that strong El Niño with double amplitude of its moderate counterpart yields more than twice the impacts of moderate El Niño in North Pacific atmosphere.
</p>
