<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empirical Support for Depth Response When F = 0.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">No changes in the age-dependent cod depth distributions were evident in the simulation employing F = 0 and a constant, depth-independent M (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig05" href="#fig05">Fig. 5
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>). We therefore analyzed data on cod distributions derived from the 2006–2016 surveys, during which F = 0 and when the cod population was exhibiting the first signs of recovery from its near-total collapse in 1992 (
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>). The systematic, well-separated cumulative abundance distributions of 1970–1989 when F = 0.52 differed markedly from the compressed, overlapping distributions of 2006–2016 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Figs. 3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig06" href="#fig06">6</a>). The progressive deepening from 80 to 161 m (ages 4–12, slope = 10 ± 0.4 m⋅y
  <span class="sup">−1</span> based on CM depths) of the earlier period contrasts with the overall shallowing (slope = −1.5 ± 1 m⋅y
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) during the 2006–2016 period. Moreover, we note that the more complex response for the later period could be decomposed to a weaker deepening from 83 to 95 m for the younger fish (ages 4–7, slope = 3.9 ± 1.4 m⋅y
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and a tendency for shallowing with increasing age for ages 7–12. The deepening response of the younger fish could be a manifestation of ontogeny, whereas for the older fish it might reflect a repopulation of the more productive shallower ESS waters after a prolonged period without recovery following the initiation of the moratorium (
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>, 
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig06" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 6.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Cumulative frequency distributions of abundance (number per standardized tow) of ESS cod with depth of capture for age groups 4 y to 12 y. Data were derived from fishery independent surveys conducted during 2006–2016 (969 standardized tows). The black dotted line denotes the depths of the CM; the numerical values are given in the inset. The two broken yellow lines are the envelope (age 4 and 12) of the cumulative percent distribution for 1970–1989 (time interval of high exploitation) from 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra6" xlink:href="pnas.1802096115fig06" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
