<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A tuber slice assay was carried out to assess the macerating capacity of 
 <italic class="italic">Pectobacterium atrosepticum</italic> (Pba), 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">carotovorum</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">brasiliense</italic> (Pbr), 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">parmentieri</italic> (Ppa), and 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya solani</italic> (Dsol) isolates at five different temperatures: 18°C, 21°C, 25°C, 28°C and 32°C. Tuber slice assays are routinely used for measuring disease severity (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]), as the number of replicates required for a whole tuber assay is often impractical in a laboratory environment. We used four isolates each for Pba and Dsol, and two isolates each for Pbr and Ppa. Bacterial strains were grown overnight, washed and resuspended into 10 mM MgSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> to a final concentration of 10
 <sup class="sup">7</sup> CFU/ml
 <sub class="sub">.</sub> Maris piper tubers were surfaced sterilized for 10 mins in 5% sodium hypochlorite, rinsed in distilled water and cut into 7mm thick slices using a sterile knife. A core was removed from the center of each slice to make a well 5mm deep and 7mm in diameter. The slices were inoculated by pipetting 50μl of the 10
 <sup class="sup">7</sup> CFU/ml bacterial suspension into each well [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Three potato slices obtained from 3 different potato tubers was used for each bacterium tested and as a control, slices were inoculated with 50μl of 10 mM MgSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>. The tuber slices were placed on petri dishes and positioned randomly on wet tissue paper in a sealed box and incubated for 72 hours at the 5 temperatures. Disease severity was expressed as the mean diameter of the soft-rotted tissue area (lesion length). The entire experiment was independently replicated two times, using different cultures for inoculum in each experiment.
</p>
