<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioprospecting in the Skin and Intestinal Microbiomes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anadromous Arctic char from this high Arctic region grow more rapidly than other local salmonids and live several decades (McPhedran et al., unpublished data). Therefore, we posit that knowledge of the microbiota could be helpful in the development of sustainable and efficient aquaculture practices and to provide an alternate modality to overcome the adverse effects of antibiotics and drugs (Nayak, 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">2010</a>). As suggested above, consideration could be given to the manipulation of salt concentrations in Arctic char aquaculture to deliberately direct bacterial communities and possibly bypass dysbiotic episodes. Alternatively, individual isolates may prove valuable. Previously, lactic acid bacteria including 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus</span> have been used as probiotics and specifically for furunculosis in rainbow trout, 
  <span class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</span> (Balcázar et al., 
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">2007</a>; Pandiyan et al., 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">2013</a>). This is a serious infection of farmed fish causing skin lesions, hemorrhaging, intestinal tissue damage, and death (Ringø et al., 
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">2004</a>). Other studies have reported the beneficial effect of 
  <span class="italic">Shewanella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Vibrio</span> probiotics (Kamei et al., 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">1988</a>; Irianto and Austin, 
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">2002</a>; Díaz-Rosales et al., 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">2006a</a>,
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">b</a>). The bacteria that we detected in Arctic char skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes, especially those identified as part of the core microbiome, therefore have potential in probiotic applications for aquaculture where they could play a role in immune development and promote the health and growth of farmed fish.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many OTUs in the skin and intestinal microbiomes represented unidentified microorganisms, and it suggests that the microbial diversity associated with these wild Arctic char provides fertile ground for bioprospecting for psychrophiles and osmotolerant organisms. For example, some known organisms that are psychrophilic and halophilic are a good source for polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) (Russell and Nichols, 
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">1999</a>). Russell (
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">1998</a>) proposed that PUFA in marine psychrophiles allows them to balance the requirement for a fluid membrane at low temperatures with the retention of a requisite level of order. Given these functions, PUFA-producing bacteria may represent an alternate source for human use, with the added advantage of containing only one long-chain PUFA rather than the multiple components present in fish or algal oils (de Pascale et al., 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As indicated, taxa involved in nitrogen fixation (Cyanobacteria and Rhizobiales), nitrate oxidation (Nitrospirales), and nitrite oxidization (
  <span class="italic">Nitrospira</span>) are present in the skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">Tables S1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" href="#SM2">S2</a>). Their presence suggests that they may provide an inorganic source of nitrogen when organic nitrogen is low, such as when prey may not be as readily available during the winter under ice. Similar results have been observed by Lee and Childress (
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">1994</a>) and Shah et al. (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">in press</a>) in marine invertebrates. Isolates of Nitrospirales, 
  <span class="italic">Nitrospira</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Paracoccus</span>, identified in Arctic char that are adapted to low temperature conditions might be employed in municipal and domestic wastewater treatment facilities where wastewater temperatures fall below 10 °C in winter, and when microbial activity is normally severely depressed (Xu et al., 
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">2018</a>). Similarly, isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Pseudomonas, Shewanella, Bacillus, Arthrobacter</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Sphingobacterium</span> in the intestine-associated microbiome (
  <a rid="T4" ref-type="table" href="#T4">Table 4B</a>) could play an important role in degradation of pollutants during wastewater treatment. Some bacteria (e.g., members of the Rhizobiales) could even find utility as nitrogen fixers if used for agricultural applications under low temperature conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioprospecting need not be restricted to probiotics, however. Further exploration of identified extremophiles may be useful for other applications. For example, between 6 and 8 million tons of waste crab, shrimp, and lobster shells are produced globally, with the chitin-rich wastes dumped in landfills or the sea (Yan and Chen, 
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">2015</a>). The presence of OTUs representing 
  <span class="italic">Photobacterium</span>, in the intestine-associated microbiome of Arctic char (
  <a rid="T2" ref-type="table" href="#T2">Table 2B</a>), with members of this taxon known to aid in chitin digestion (MacDonald et al., 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">1986</a>; Ramesh and Venugopalan, 
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">1989</a>; Itoi et al., 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">2006</a>) is noteworthy. It suggests that in the future, chitin-containing seafood waste could be used as supplements for fish food in aquaculture facilities, and also used as a probiotic supplement for Arctic char and other fish.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, our results highlight the need to further explore structural and functional aspects of the microbial communities that naturally inhabit 
  <span class="italic">S. alpinus</span>. The turnover of both the skin- and intestine-associated communities together during migration represents a previously underappreciated stressor for the species that could be exploited for biotechnological applications including advanced aquaculture systems. The specific taxa observed suggest the potential for isolating useful probiotics, whilst the number of undefined taxa exposes a lack of understanding of this ecosystem, the resolution of which could benefit our understanding of Arctic marine ecosystems as a whole.
 </p>
</sec>
