<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparisons of Skin and Intestinal Microbiota Within Individual Fish</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on fish sampled at seven distinct sites on or within 200 km of King William Island, located along the lower Northwest Passage (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>; 
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>), microbiome sequences were successfully obtained for 118 skin mucosal samples and 202 intestinal samples. Grouping the skin microbiome consortia by environment showed that the freshwater samples contained significantly more Shannon diversity overall than those from saline water (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.11, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 16.0, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05), whereas log
  <sub>10</sub> Chao1 OTU richness was not significantly different between the two environment types (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.00, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 0.1, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05). In contrast, when intestinal microbiomes were grouped by environment, the saline water samples were more diverse overall than freshwater samples when log
  <sub>10</sub> Chao1 OTU richness was considered, though this difference was small (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.03, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 4.7, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). A significant difference was not observed in the intestinal microbiomes between the two environment types when Shannon diversity was considered (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.00, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 0.1, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05). Of the 320 skin and intestine samples combined, 60 individual Arctic char had both sets of microbiome data, allowing a comparison of skin and intestinal flora from the same fish (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>). When comparing across these 60 fish, skin-associated microbiomes were significantly more diverse than intestine-associated microbiomes when both log
  <sub>10</sub> Chao1 OTU richness (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.60, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 180.0, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) and Shannon diversity (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.52, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 127.4, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) were considered. In addition, though the skin and intestine communities were distinct, the skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes among individual fish appeared to be more similar at freshwater sites (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figures 2A,B</a>) compared to saline water sites (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figures 2C,D</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Phyla comparison of skin and intestinal complementary microbiomes for individual fish, shown for samples collected at 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> freshwater sites Port Perry, Swan Lake, and Koka Lake for skin-associated microbiomes, 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> freshwater sites Port Perry, Swan Lake, and Koka Lake for intestine-associated microbiomes, 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span> saltwater sites, Back House Point and Legendary River for skin-associated microbiomes, and 
    <span class="bold">(D)</span> saltwater sites, Back House Point and Legendary River for intestine-associated microbiomes. Phyla with relative abundances (RA) ≥ 0.5% are shown. Phyla present at RA &lt; 0.5% were pooled together.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fbioe-07-00032-g0002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative abundance of rarified OTUs identified to the genus level, if known, for each of the total 320 skin and intestinal microbiome samples is presented in supplemental tables (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">Tables S1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" href="#SM2">S2</a>, respectively).
 </p>
</sec>
