<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microbial Structure in the Skin and Intestinal Mucous</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The commensal microbes contributing to these Arctic char skin- and intestine-associated microbiome communities were found to be distinct from one another (
  <a rid="T2" ref-type="table" href="#T2">Table 2</a>; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">Tables S1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" href="#SM2">S2</a>). There have been few published reports on skin-associated microbiomes, especially in wild fish, possibly because of the challenges associated with ensuring aseptic collection practices and optimal preservation techniques (Kueneman et al., 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">2014</a>). Microbiome analysis on the skin of anadromous Atlantic salmon, 
  <span class="italic">S. salar</span>, showed that Proteobacteria was the dominant phylum (Lokesh and Kiron, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2016</a>), and it was also dominant in the majority of our skin samples taken from freshwater Arctic char (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2A</a>). Significant differences in the microbiome from fish caught in fresh and saline waters suggests that the skin microbial community changes as the fish swim from one environment to another. Part of the challenge, and likely reflecting the generally unstudied field, is the large proportion of unknown genera in the skin-associated microbiome; 8 of 9 organisms making up the putative core microbiome are currently unknown, and in addition, over 1% of the microbial community belonged to unknown phyla (
  <a rid="T4" ref-type="table" href="#T4">Table 4A</a>). Some of these currently unknown members likely serve important roles in the skin mucous, suggesting that metagenomic analysis could perhaps be used to assign putative roles in waste removal, osmoregulation, glycoprotein-mediated drag reduction, and in immune function, and would be of interest for future experiments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the paucity of information on skin-associated microbiomes, intestine-associated microbiomes have been better studied, although not extensively in wild, ocean-going fish (Egerton et al., 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">2018</a>). Previously reported microorganisms present in the Arctic char gut include 
  <span class="italic">Aeromonas, Flavobacterium, Pseudomonas, Lactobacillus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Vibrio</span> (Ringø and Strøm, 
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">1994</a>; Ringø et al., 
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">1995</a>; Nyman et al., 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">2017</a>). Lactic acid bacteria (phylum Firmicutes), Fusobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Gammaproteobacteria, Planctomycetes, Clostridia, Verrumicrobia and Bacilli have all been reported as a normal part of the intestine-associated microbiomes in several fish species (Ringø and Gatesoupe, 
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">1998</a>; Befring-Hovda, 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">2007</a>; Ingerslev et al., 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">2014</a>; Ghanbari et al., 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">2015</a>). The results reported here are therefore consistent with the previous literature, demonstrating that the community found in wild adult 
  <span class="italic">S. alpinus</span> intestine-associated microbiomes is not fundamentally different from other fish.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The core intestine-associated microbiome in Arctic char includes taxa from the Gammaproteobacteria class as well as three genera within the Vibrionaceae family (
  <a rid="T4" ref-type="table" href="#T4">Table 4B</a>), similar to observations from Antarctic notothenioid fish species (Ward et al., 
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">2009</a>). We also noted the presence of 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Mycoplasma. Mycoplasma</span> have been reportedly abundant in Antarctic fish and Atlantic salmon (Holben et al., 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">2002</a>; Song et al., 
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">2016</a>; Dehler et al., 
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2017</a>). Unlike in humans where 
  <span class="italic">Mycoplasma</span> and certain 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus</span> are associated with dysbiosis, these genera are proposed to be important for lipid and sugar metabolism and are therefore included in the core intestinal microbiome for Atlantic salmon (Dehler et al., 
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2017</a>). In vertebrates, 
  <span class="italic">Sphingomonas</span> have been associated with the early-life education of the immune system (Olszak et al., 
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">2012</a>; Wingender et al., 
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">2012</a>; Caballero and Pamer, 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">2015</a>; Gensollen et al., 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">2016</a>), and therefore may play a similar role in the gut of Arctic char.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Notwithstanding the distinct profiles of the skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes, they appear to share certain taxa, including psychrophilic genera, such as 
  <span class="italic">Psychrobacter, Shewanella, Flavobacterium, Acinetobacter, Photobacterium, Planctomyces</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Psychromonas</span>, and including bacteria belonging to the phyla Firmicutes and Cyanobacteria, which could contribute to geochemical cycles, including the nitrogen cycle. Certainly, both microbial community compositions were significantly influenced by the environment in which the fish were caught (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Figure 3</a>; 
  <a rid="T3" ref-type="table" href="#T3">Table 3</a>), with 
  <span class="italic">Photobacterium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Deinococcus</span> increasing over 1–2 orders of magnitude when intestine- and skin-associated microbiomes, respectively, were recovered from saline water samples. There was no apparent correlation with other measured biotic factors. Our results on wild Arctic char populations are in accord with previous reports including Atlantic salmon, in that they showed salinity-mediated turnover in microbial distributions across the skin and intestines (Schmidt et al., 
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">2015</a>; Lokesh and Kiron, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2016</a>; Dehler et al., 
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2017</a>). Manipulation of the skin and intestinal microbiomes by deliberate salinity changes in aquaculture has not yet been explored, but our results suggest that a directed turnover in taxa might be achieved by such a protocol, and should be considered to prevent or inhibit dysbiosis. Although there has been some examination of the survival of farmed 
  <span class="italic">S. alpinus</span> at higher salinities, consensus has not yet been reached on best practices for inland recirculating systems (Jørgensen et al., 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">1993</a>; Larsson and Berglund, 
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">1998</a>; Summerfelt et al., 
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">2004</a>; Duston et al., 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2007</a>). To date, existing aquaculture studies have focused on the osmoregulatory consequences of keeping stocks at low salinity or the transfer of young fish from freshwater to a potential saltwater grow-out phase (Arnesen et al., 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">1993</a>; Aarset, 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1999</a>; Duston et al., 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2007</a>), but there has been little consideration of the Arctic char skin-associated microbiome, nor of skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes together, and yet the biotechnological applications for manipulation of the microbiota by probiotics is of considerable interest.
 </p>
</sec>
