<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Future bird assemblages were based on SDM-derived projected probabilities of occurrences and were further refined by four temperature-driven dispersal scenarios (
 <italic>no range change</italic>, 
 <italic>range contraction</italic>, 
 <italic>range expansion</italic>, and 
 <italic>range shift</italic>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Under the 
 <italic>no range change</italic> scenario, projected changes in the elevational ranges of species were not taken into account and the future assemblages were based on the SDM-derived probabilities of occurrences and the current elevational ranges (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Under the 
 <italic>range contraction</italic>, 
 <italic>range expansion</italic>, and 
 <italic>range shift</italic> scenarios, we tested three scenarios in which the future elevational ranges of species were altered according to temperature changes with altitude (see below), under the assumption that species have to move upwards to track their climate niche
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>
 </sup>. Under the 
 <italic>range contraction scenario</italic>, bird species could only have an upward movement of their current lower range limit, while the upper limit remained constant. This leads to a contraction of species ranges; 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>., species could not adapt to future climatic conditions at the lower range limit and were unable to disperse upslope (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Under the 
 <italic>range expansion scenario</italic>, bird species were projected to expand their range upwards, while the lower limit of their elevational range remained the same; 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>., species could adapt to future conditions at their lower range limit and could disperse upslope (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Finally, under the 
 <italic>range shift scenario</italic>, bird species could move their complete range upwards, 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>., both the lower and upper limit changed and species fully tracked their temperature niche upslope along the mountain (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>).
</p>
