<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">O’Connor calls the third condition of production the “natural condition,” meaning those environmental conditions “external” to the economy but necessary for it to function. Soil quality, abundance of water, and all the processes that the natural world provides “outside” of the economy would be considered among these conditions. Natural conditions are considered “external” to the economy until they become recognized as having value and thus become factored into the production process [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Recently, however, scholars have referred to these as 
 <italic class="italic">ecological</italic> conditions, or 
 <italic class="italic">socionatural</italic> conditions, in order to bring out the mutually constitutive, hybrid character of social and natural systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Whether factored into production economically or otherwise, the natural world is a dynamic part of the production system, and its condition can either help or hamper the economy based on the health and sustainability of the relationship. In cranberry production, the surrounding ecological landscape, and the weather that shaped it, has an important role to play, either providing the grower with an abundance of inputs such as favorable weather conditions, adequate water, and pollinating insects, or containing a poorer composite of these factors (see below). Such conditions are not factored into the value of cranberries on a site-by-site basis, but they play an intricate role in the entire production process. The geographies of particular cranberry systems vary across systems, as does ownership of the ecological resources that are a part of them. Therefore, it is useful to think of ecological conditions as contributing to the cranberry production system in a state of mutual cooperation or friction, and the dynamic makeup of those conditions and one’s ability to access them have an impact on that relationship.
</p>
