<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">On the Tibetan Plateau, alpine grasslands are sensitive and vulnerable to both natural and anthropogenic disturbances
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>. Degradation of alpine grasslands is mainly attributed to climate warming and overgrazing there
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>. For example, Piao 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref> found that the spatial patterns of vegetation green-up and its change in response to warming are altitude dependent. As these pastures are an important ecological security by protecting the headwaters of major rivers in Asia, their ongoing degradation likely threatens the livelihood of local residents and their distinctively nomadic culture
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>, but may also have wider impacts on water security in East China and South-Asia. Assumed to effective to recover degraded pastures, metal fences were built on this plateau to control grazing by livestock
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>. However, the magnitude and direction of fencing effects on plant communities and soil properties are still under debates
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>. The questions whether a general biodiversity-productivity relationship exists for Tibetan alpine grasslands and how this relationship is affected by climatic factors are still under discussion.
</p>
