<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">LTAs play a big role in ensuring that traditions are respected and maintained for the benefit of their posterity. They are the custodians of indigenous knowledge systems (IKS) and its related technologies. IKSs is defined as a systematic body of information. It is the totality of information, skills and practices acquired by local people through past experiences, observations, informal experiments and intimate understanding of their environment (Marango 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Marango et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016b</xref>). To date, several rural people within the smallholder farmer community still bear little access and interpretive skills to make full use of modern weather forecasts transmitted through print and electronic media (Shoko &amp; Shoko 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). In the backdrop of this complexity, such people are left with no choice except to utilise their easily comprehensible IK. In fact, long before the subject of climate change came into limelight, rural people used to experience adverse weather conditions. Indigenous forms of knowledge were therefore long been used to explain incidences of meteorological phenomena such as drought, storms and floods, thereby guiding local communities (Nakashima et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Emeagwali (
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) defines IK as that which is generated by people in a particular societal setting. Previously, Nakashima et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) had indicated that IK implies knowledge and expertise amassed through generations and transformed by each successive generation, which direct human societies in their interaction with their immediate environment. IK covers different aspects of human life, which include climate, agriculture, linguistics, animal husbandry and botany (Mapira &amp; Mazambara 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
