<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Proxy records of northern African palaeoclimate are derived from a variety of sources. These range from lake-level, dust deposition, pollen and geochemical records. The data used in Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a> are derived from the database compiled and interpreted by Shanahan et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. For every 500 year interval, the climate state has been subjectively determined
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> as either wet, moderate or dry (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). As with the sensitivity metric (Eq. 
  <a rid="Equ7" ref-type="" href="#Equ7">7</a>), we date the collapse as the first time in which humid conditions are not present (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). This compilation of proxy records may provide a geographically and typographically biased sample, but is not clear what alternate approaches are availabel to estimate an end-date for the green Sahara in a probabilistic fashion.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative population levels (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>) are a summed probability distribution analysis based on a comprehensive review of the abundance of carbon-14 dated archaeological sites across northern Africa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. The underlying principle of this method assumes a monotonic relationship between the amount of data and the amount of human presence, which is reliant on the law of large numbers to overcome small-scale temporal and spatial biases. Full details on the methods are described in Shennan et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>, whilst criticisms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>, and subsequent defense
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> of the method have been presented in several publications. The population estimates used in the present analysis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> were created from a dataset comprising 3287 radiocarbon dates from 1011 “Neolithic” sites. Radiocarbon dates from state level social contexts such as Pharaonic or later Garamantian sites were not included in that analysis. The population estimates can only provide relative time series and the size of populations cannot be compared between the regions shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>. To date, these are the only explicit reconstructions of Holocene demographic trends on a trans-Saharan scale, although similar curves have been produced for the western desert in Egypt
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, it is this curve which Wright suggests corresponds with “the variable tempo and intensity of the termination of the AHP” and “local transitions to shrubland environments and accelerated rates of soil erosion”
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. We exclude African palaeoclimate reconstructions south of 13.42°N from our analysis, as this is the most southerly archaeological site used to reconstruct the population estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
