<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural length of the Holocene African Humid Period</div>
  <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before considering human agents in the context of climatic change, it is first necessary to determine the length of the Holocene AHP assuming no anthropogenic influence. Observations alone do not provide sufficient constraint on this, because of insufficiently accurate relevant chronologies. Mediterranean sapropel deposition is used as an indicator of humid conditions in northern Africa
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
   </span>, because they have some of the most accurate chronologies. Over the past 250,000 years, it is possible to tune a chronology using well-dated speleothems to provide well-constrained estimates of the onset and termination of sapropels
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
   </span>. This chronology suggests that the most recent sapropel was of much shorter duration than previous instances (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>); yet it only includes one other interglacial sapropel (at 129.5 ka). However longer records
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
   </span> that allow selection of similar orbital configurations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
   </span> cannot detect differences at the sub-millennial timescales required (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). A concerted effort would be required to develop a sufficiently accurate chronology to advance in this direction.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The relationship between sapropel formation and orbital precession using two sapropel chronologies. Precessional curves associated with sapropel formation are aligned to the start of each occurrence according to the respective chronology. The coloured segments of these curves indicate the actual duration of the sapropel. The red horizontal line indicates the precession at the termination of the most recent sapropel. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> A speleothem-tuned chronology
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
      </span> provides well-constrained estimates of the onset and termination of sapropels over the past 250,000 years. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> The past ten interglacial sapropels seen in a Mediterranean Sea level record
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
      </span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_6321_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e521" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We develop an idealised model that calculates rainfall and vegetative cover and their feedbacks (see Methods) to estimate the natural length of the Holocene AHP instead. Compared to previous models
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>, rainfall responds to imposed orbital precession
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span> and past greenhouse gas levels as measured in ice cores
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span> (which acts as a proxy for glacial-interglacial changes as well as a local, direct forcing). The model is run over the past two glacial cycles (230–20 ka) using a large ensemble of parameter settings selected at random. Parameter settings that do not exhibit six green episodes during this period are discounted for being inconsistent with the observations. The remaining ensemble members are integrated forward to the present-day (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). We find late Pleistocene behaviour alone was not sufficient to rule out the continuation of the humid period throughout the Holocene at the 5% significance level (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). This failure to accurately predict the passing of a known tipping point—despite having 200,000 years of observations—should add a cautionary note to the discussion surrounding future climate thresholds.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The last two glacial cycles. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> The input times series of radiative forcing of carbon dioxide changes
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
      </span> (black) and climatic precession
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
      </span> (red). 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Barium to aluminium ratio at Ocean Drilling Program site 968 in the Eastern Mediterranean
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
      </span>. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> The distribution of the roughly 12,000 ensemble members that exhibit seven ‘green’ events. The median (black), inter-quartile range (dark gray) and 5–95% range (light gray) are shown, along with the sapropel start (green) and end (blue) dates calculated from observations
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
      </span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_6321_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e579" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A sensitivity metric is devised for the model (see Methods) to summarise its behaviour and estimate start and end dates for the humid periods. We predict a well-defined start of the Holocene AHP (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which corresponds closely with the observed date of 14.5 ka
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>, supporting the validity of this modelling approach. The model shows several peaks during the Holocene when northern Africa would have been particularly sensitive to a perturbation (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Potential interaction between humans and the ecosystem during the end of the African humid period. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Histogram of the number of climate proxies (Fig. 
      <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>) indicating an end of the African Humid Period within a 500 year window
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
      </span>. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> The population inferred summed probability distribution
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
      </span> over the whole of northern Africa region along with its 5–95% confidence level. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> The simulated sensitivity of northern Africa diagnosed from the model. Black dots show the number of not-implausible model settings with a threshold time, 
      <span class="italic">t</span>
      <span class="sup">∗</span>, in each century (see Methods for details); the black line is a 3 point running average. The gray line vertical indicates the time of the maximum simulated sensitivity
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_6321_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e629" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The largest peak in the modelled sensitivity of the Sahara occurs at 7–6 ka (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a>). This coincides with the second period of population increase between 6.7 and 6.3 ka (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>). The dominant collapse observed for the Holocene AHP (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>) occurs 500–1000 years after this peak (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a>), which appears to be a robust model result (see Methods, Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). This refutes the hypothesis that pastoralists were “active agents in landscape denudation” and accelerated the termination of the Holocene AHP
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span>. Rather it suggests that pastoralism may have actively delayed the region’s environmental deterioration (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robustness of the delay</div>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synthesis of observed records
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span> classifies the hydroclimate state only at 500 year intervals. This choice of interval was motivated by all the chronologies being sufficiently precise to resolve it
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span>. The model inputs are orbital parameters
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span> and carbon dioxide concentrations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>, both of which have dating uncertainties substantially less than 500 years. Dating of prior humid periods is subject to errors on the order of millennia (hence the failure to constrain the AHP dates observationally). Because of this issue, the valid model parameter settings are determined by matching solely the number of prior instances rather than their timing (see Methods). We consider the possibility that either a humid period was overlooked or that a sapropel has been laid down without a humid period during the past 230 kyrs to be minimal. The uncertainty contained within the structure of the idealised model, rather than its parameters, is impossible to quantify. To explore the parameter uncertainty in the model output, the whole experiment is replicated a further twenty times with different random parameter settings. There is little variation in the temporal structure (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). In summary, the limiting factor for the precision appears to be the temporal resolution of the compiled observations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span>, though the delay appears visible despite that (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The largest issues affecting the results of the idealised model are therefore associated with its applicability to the problem. There is a rich heritage of using idealised models to study the greening of the Sahara
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>, so the application here is not without precedent. The model appears to adequately capture the past behaviour under certain parameter settings. We cannot exclude the possibility that including other natural forcing factors may be beneficial. An alternate approach would use coupled general circulation models (GCMs). These GCMs are now used operationally for decadal climate predictions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. Unfortunately, the resources needed for the multi-millennia ensembles that would be required by this research preclude their application. Additionally, GCMs have been shown to have longstanding biases in simulating the greening of the Sahara
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>, likely arising from them poor capturing of vegetation and dust feedbacks
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model ensemble is treated above as multiple plausible instances of a single physical system. The sensitivity is therefore interpreted as a single metric for all three regions shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. An alternate interpretation is that the ensemble members represent different local conditions, implying that the three sensitivity peaks in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a> each characterise a particular region. However, there is no noticeable regional pattern in the reconstructed collapse dates (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), although more southerly locations in the compilation do show a later response
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span>. However, the majority of observational records showing a collapse between 6 and 5 ka
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span> occur at similar latitudes to the archaeological sites used to estimate the human occupancy
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>. Therefore the comparison of the sensitivity metric to the palaeoclimate and population reconstructions combined across northern Africa seems appropriate (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human–environment interactions</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model results suggest that the end of the Holocene AHP was delayed by around 500 years. A logical extension from the hypothesis of anthropogenically-driven early collapse
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span> is that humans caused this delay. Whilst other possible explanations could exist, the main difference between the Holocene and previous interglacials is the existence of Human society in the Holocene. We therefore explore whether mechanisms exist that may explain an anthropogenic role in the collapse, by focusing on why pastoralism is sustainable. This approach rejects any dualist view that humans occupy a unique place in nature
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span>, advocating instead the historical dependencies between human action and environmental change
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mobility, a distinguishing feature of traditional pastoral systems
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, results in periodicity of the intensity of grazing. Grasslands can suffer from undergrazing as much as overgrazing
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
   </span>, so active management of grazing plays a major role in grassland health. This is because grazing ungulates and grasslands have co-evolved from an historical predator-prey relationship, with pack hunting predators keeping large herds of ungulates bunched and moving
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
   </span>. Healthy grasslands are maintained in precisely this way by pastoralists bunching stock and moving them frequently, fostering a mutually beneficial distribution of dung and urine
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>. Removing grazers from grasslands increases the amount of senescent vegetation, which causes the grasses to cease growing productively
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span>. Grazing livestock and their preference for the most palatable grasses provide a competitive advantage to the less palatable grasses for water and nutrients, making it important to get the balance correct between overgrazing and over-resting. Traditional pastoralists tend to be acutely aware of these subtle dynamics utilising practices that maximise grassland regeneration
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evidence from long-term studies on herding strategies has also helped to reveal the sensitive dynamic between drought, pasture availability, and herd size. Seasonal and long-term droughts, which are common in areas of pastoral rangeland, as well as disease dynamics, control the growth of herds in a way that means they are unlikely to damage pasture. If longer-term drought starts to restrict pasture, or if herd size increases beyond the carrying capacity of a rangeland, then pastoralists will move on. For example, field research in the Ngorongoro Conservation Area has shown that whilst pastures were being overgrazed in terms of optimal commercial yield, this did not result in environmental degradation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. This is important as it suggests that animal condition deteriorates before they are capable of having a seriously deleterious effect on the environment. The amount of pastoralism practiced by the Saharan occupants, and therefore the size of their herds, are unlikely to have reached such levels as to surpass carrying capacity. The inherent mobility and customary institutions employed by these populations generates a dynamic state of adaptation, which logically negates over-burdening pastoral rangeland
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent publication by Wright
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span> in which mid-Holocene pastoralists are considered “catalysts in accelerating the pace of devegetation in the Sahara” provides an illustrative example of the outdated doctrine against pastoralists. Wright
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span> uses historical analogues, such as the Rapa Nui environmental degradation, that appear inappropriate. In the instance of the island of Rapa Nui, its inhabitants were primarily farmers and fishermen, not pastoralists. Even so recent research suggests that major environmental degradation on Rapa Nui occurred only after European contact, and that pre-contact changes in land use were a result of environmental constraint, not degradation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. Using this type of analogue, one establishes a false premise i.e., where “landscapes with no previous exposure to grazing by domesticated animals have been documented as crossing ecological thresholds shortly after new grazing pressures were introduced”
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
   </span>. Northern Africa, however, was becoming a domesticated landscape from the early Holocene onwards (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Pastoralism co-evolved with dryland environments in a context where extant grazing ungulates were in abundance. Moreover recent genetic analyses of modern African cattle indicate considerable introgression from African aurochs, suggesting they underwent a hybridization with local wild stock
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span>. The introduction of pastoralist strategies, therefore, were based upon natural ecosystem interactions and the functional roles of native wildlife causing little additional burden; allowing positive management of the environment.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional responses</div>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The division of the entire Saharan population into broad regional sets (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>) allows a preliminary look at spatial variation in the timing of population change. The population curves for the Eastern Sahara, the Atlas &amp; Hoggar and Central Sahara start broadly synchronous; showing a rapid population increase after the onset of humid conditions c. 10.5 ka and during the millennial-long population decline between 7.5 and 6.5 ka (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). At the end of the AHP, however, we observe divergence in the regional demographic response. The eastern Sahara, which is today extremely arid, appears to have undergone a rapid population decline, as occupation shifted towards the Nile Valley. It has even been suggested that this subsequently gave rise to the Pharanoic civilisation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span>. To the north and west, in the Atlas &amp; Hoggar mountain region, population decline appears to have been equally rapid (c. 900 years, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). The central Sahara, on the other hand, saw a much more gradual decline in population levels that never reached the pre-Holocene population low (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). The fact that societies practicing pastoralism persisted in this region for so long, and invested both economically and ideologically in the local landscape, does not support a scenario of over-exploitation (see Methods). Additionally, the ethnographic record demonstrates how the flexibility inherent in traditional African pastoralist strategies enables them to make the most efficient use of patchy and fragile environments
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>. It is therefore likely that the origins of such strategies co-evolved with the drying environment in a way that enabled humans to live in an adaptive balance with available pasture.
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The implication that Holocene populations persisted for longer in some parts of the Sahara either suggests a spatial variation in the rate of aridification or vegetation change, or more intriguingly in the human adaptive strategies. Differential topography across the Sahara is certainly worth considering. Mountains such as the Tibesti, Tassili-n-Ajjer and Ahaggar form a major topographic feature spanning more than 2500 km from southern Algeria to northern Chad. These mountains would have acted as important water towers in contrast to the surrounding plains, providing populations living on the windward side with more persistent rain runoff during periods of increasing aridity. Some of the earliest direct evidence for the exploitation of domestic livestock
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>, use of milk products
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span>, and the construction of cattle tumuli
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>, come from the heart of the central Sahara. On the Messak plateau, for example, extensive evidence for rock art depicting livestock scenes and stone monuments with associated domestic animal remains dating to the middle Holocene attest to a highly formalized expression of a wider Saharan “cattle cult”
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. Isotopic analysis of archaeological animal bones from this region also demonstrate seasonal transhumance
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>, reminiscent of the strategies used by modern traditional pastoralists to ensure the maintenance of healthy pasture.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
