<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural length of the Holocene African Humid Period</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before considering human agents in the context of climatic change, it is first necessary to determine the length of the Holocene AHP assuming no anthropogenic influence. Observations alone do not provide sufficient constraint on this, because of insufficiently accurate relevant chronologies. Mediterranean sapropel deposition is used as an indicator of humid conditions in northern Africa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, because they have some of the most accurate chronologies. Over the past 250,000 years, it is possible to tune a chronology using well-dated speleothems to provide well-constrained estimates of the onset and termination of sapropels
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. This chronology suggests that the most recent sapropel was of much shorter duration than previous instances (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>); yet it only includes one other interglacial sapropel (at 129.5 ka). However longer records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span> that allow selection of similar orbital configurations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> cannot detect differences at the sub-millennial timescales required (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). A concerted effort would be required to develop a sufficiently accurate chronology to advance in this direction.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The relationship between sapropel formation and orbital precession using two sapropel chronologies. Precessional curves associated with sapropel formation are aligned to the start of each occurrence according to the respective chronology. The coloured segments of these curves indicate the actual duration of the sapropel. The red horizontal line indicates the precession at the termination of the most recent sapropel. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> A speleothem-tuned chronology
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span> provides well-constrained estimates of the onset and termination of sapropels over the past 250,000 years. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> The past ten interglacial sapropels seen in a Mediterranean Sea level record
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_6321_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e521" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We develop an idealised model that calculates rainfall and vegetative cover and their feedbacks (see Methods) to estimate the natural length of the Holocene AHP instead. Compared to previous models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>, rainfall responds to imposed orbital precession
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> and past greenhouse gas levels as measured in ice cores
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> (which acts as a proxy for glacial-interglacial changes as well as a local, direct forcing). The model is run over the past two glacial cycles (230–20 ka) using a large ensemble of parameter settings selected at random. Parameter settings that do not exhibit six green episodes during this period are discounted for being inconsistent with the observations. The remaining ensemble members are integrated forward to the present-day (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). We find late Pleistocene behaviour alone was not sufficient to rule out the continuation of the humid period throughout the Holocene at the 5% significance level (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). This failure to accurately predict the passing of a known tipping point—despite having 200,000 years of observations—should add a cautionary note to the discussion surrounding future climate thresholds.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The last two glacial cycles. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> The input times series of radiative forcing of carbon dioxide changes
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
     </span> (black) and climatic precession
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
     </span> (red). 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Barium to aluminium ratio at Ocean Drilling Program site 968 in the Eastern Mediterranean
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span>. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> The distribution of the roughly 12,000 ensemble members that exhibit seven ‘green’ events. The median (black), inter-quartile range (dark gray) and 5–95% range (light gray) are shown, along with the sapropel start (green) and end (blue) dates calculated from observations
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_6321_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e579" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A sensitivity metric is devised for the model (see Methods) to summarise its behaviour and estimate start and end dates for the humid periods. We predict a well-defined start of the Holocene AHP (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which corresponds closely with the observed date of 14.5 ka
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, supporting the validity of this modelling approach. The model shows several peaks during the Holocene when northern Africa would have been particularly sensitive to a perturbation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Potential interaction between humans and the ecosystem during the end of the African humid period. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Histogram of the number of climate proxies (Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>) indicating an end of the African Humid Period within a 500 year window
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
     </span>. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> The population inferred summed probability distribution
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
     </span> over the whole of northern Africa region along with its 5–95% confidence level. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> The simulated sensitivity of northern Africa diagnosed from the model. Black dots show the number of not-implausible model settings with a threshold time, 
     <span class="italic">t</span>
     <span class="sup">∗</span>, in each century (see Methods for details); the black line is a 3 point running average. The gray line vertical indicates the time of the maximum simulated sensitivity
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_6321_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e629" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The largest peak in the modelled sensitivity of the Sahara occurs at 7–6 ka (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a>). This coincides with the second period of population increase between 6.7 and 6.3 ka (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>). The dominant collapse observed for the Holocene AHP (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>) occurs 500–1000 years after this peak (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a>), which appears to be a robust model result (see Methods, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). This refutes the hypothesis that pastoralists were “active agents in landscape denudation” and accelerated the termination of the Holocene AHP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Rather it suggests that pastoralism may have actively delayed the region’s environmental deterioration (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
