<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robustness of the delay</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synthesis of observed records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> classifies the hydroclimate state only at 500 year intervals. This choice of interval was motivated by all the chronologies being sufficiently precise to resolve it
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. The model inputs are orbital parameters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> and carbon dioxide concentrations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, both of which have dating uncertainties substantially less than 500 years. Dating of prior humid periods is subject to errors on the order of millennia (hence the failure to constrain the AHP dates observationally). Because of this issue, the valid model parameter settings are determined by matching solely the number of prior instances rather than their timing (see Methods). We consider the possibility that either a humid period was overlooked or that a sapropel has been laid down without a humid period during the past 230 kyrs to be minimal. The uncertainty contained within the structure of the idealised model, rather than its parameters, is impossible to quantify. To explore the parameter uncertainty in the model output, the whole experiment is replicated a further twenty times with different random parameter settings. There is little variation in the temporal structure (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). In summary, the limiting factor for the precision appears to be the temporal resolution of the compiled observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, though the delay appears visible despite that (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The largest issues affecting the results of the idealised model are therefore associated with its applicability to the problem. There is a rich heritage of using idealised models to study the greening of the Sahara
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, so the application here is not without precedent. The model appears to adequately capture the past behaviour under certain parameter settings. We cannot exclude the possibility that including other natural forcing factors may be beneficial. An alternate approach would use coupled general circulation models (GCMs). These GCMs are now used operationally for decadal climate predictions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Unfortunately, the resources needed for the multi-millennia ensembles that would be required by this research preclude their application. Additionally, GCMs have been shown to have longstanding biases in simulating the greening of the Sahara
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, likely arising from them poor capturing of vegetation and dust feedbacks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model ensemble is treated above as multiple plausible instances of a single physical system. The sensitivity is therefore interpreted as a single metric for all three regions shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. An alternate interpretation is that the ensemble members represent different local conditions, implying that the three sensitivity peaks in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5c</a> each characterise a particular region. However, there is no noticeable regional pattern in the reconstructed collapse dates (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), although more southerly locations in the compilation do show a later response
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. However, the majority of observational records showing a collapse between 6 and 5 ka
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> occur at similar latitudes to the archaeological sites used to estimate the human occupancy
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. Therefore the comparison of the sensitivity metric to the palaeoclimate and population reconstructions combined across northern Africa seems appropriate (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
