<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="notes" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Data Availability</div>
 <p>Data from the joint Norwegian-Russian Barents Sea Ecosystem Surveys (BESS) are not Open Access due to Russian Law, permitting publication of data collected on Russian territory. The data from the surveys, led by the Institute of Marine Research (IMR, Norway, contact person: Jan Erik Stiansen; 
  <span class="email">jan.erik.stiansen@imr.no</span>) and Knipovich Polar Research Institute of Marine Fisheries and Oceanography (PINRO, Russia, contact person: Evgeny Shamray; 
  <span class="email">shamray@pinro.ru</span>), are collected by 4-5 ships every year since 2003, and the data sets are interchanged between the two parties and integrated immediately after the cruise. During the following 6-10 months, harmonizing between the data from the two parties takes place by quality checks of the data and methods: e.g. taxonomical experts meet to discuss and agree on the taxonomical classification and classification level of different species groups. Norwegian raw data are stored in the Norwegian Marine Data Center and can be openly accessed through this web page: 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nmdc.no/nmdc/datasets" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.nmdc.no/nmdc/datasets</span>. Access to the entire BESS data set can be granted through contracted collaboration in joint projects including IMR and PINRO. Researchers can access the data in the same manner as the authors; i.e. authors obtained the BESS data set through contracted collaboration in joint projects including IMR and PINRO. With regard to the trait data, these are published open access in MEPS 495:205-218. The direct link to these data is 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.int-res.com/articles/suppl/m495p205_supp/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.int-res.com/articles/suppl/m495p205_supp/</span>.
 </p>
</div>
