<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Functional groups</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Any system may become vulnerable if ecologically relevant functional groups have low redundancy. For instance, in the species rich (&gt;3000 species) Great Barrier Reef ecosystem, one parrotfish species (
  <span class="italic">Bolbometopon muricatum</span>) was the main consumer of reef carbonates. In regions where fishing reduced this species severely, the reefs shifted from steady-state calcification towards carbonate accumulation [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref034">34</a>]. Mapping of FR is therefore a simple and transparent way to assess the sensitivity of an ecosystem to species loss.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analyses suggest that six functional groups of demersal fish play contrasting functional roles in the Barents Sea ecosystem. Although the species within each functional group are not functionally identical, there is less intragroup than intergroup variation in trait values. The species that make up a particular functional group have many functional and life history traits in common. A significant intergroup variation in longevity and TL values was observed, and although none of the functional traits that were used inform explicitly about the biogeographic affiliations of each species, a clear intergroup variation in such affiliation was evident. In fact, the functional dendrogram (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207451.g003" href="#pone.0207451.g003">Fig 3</a>) consisted of two main branches and all the Arctic and arcto-boreal taxa occured in the uppermost branch, and all but one of them occurred either in the Long demersals or the Lumpsuckers. This suggests that an Arctic affiliation requires particular functional adaptation, as supported by a recent study which showed that typically Barents Sea Arctic fish species are small-sized, bottom-dwelling and benthivorous [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref035">35</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The species occurring in a particular functional group represent a unique combination of functional trait values, which discriminates them from species belonging to the other functional groups. For instance, the Long demersals group consists mostly of small, relatively short-lived, demersal, benthos-feeders found at below-average trophic levels. Half of the species in this group were either Arctic or arcto-boreal. The Long demersals are reported to be largely non-migratory [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref024">24</a>]. They are therefore likely proficient at utilizing the local benthic resources including small-sized food items. An elongated or eel-like shape may facilitate digging into the sediment for prey. Some of the Long demersals (e.g., the elongated 
  <span class="italic">Artediellus atlanticus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Gymnocanthus tricuspis</span>) are reported to prey on burrowing animals, whereas others (including species of the eel-like genera 
  <span class="italic">Lumpenus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Lycodes</span>) are known to dig holes into sediment [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref024">24</a>]. Although the European eel (
  <span class="italic">Anguilla Anguilla</span>) conduct a spawning migration across the Atlantic Ocean from Europe to the Sargasso Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref036">36</a>], the eel-like shape is not ideal for long migrations. This partly explains the non-migratory behaviour of many of the Long demersals. Apart from the abundant polar cod (
  <span class="italic">Boreogadus saida</span>) and a few species of low abundance (e.g., Arctic cod 
  <span class="italic">Arctogadus glacialis</span>, navaga 
  <span class="italic">Eleginus nawaga</span> and Arctic flounder 
  <span class="italic">Liopsetta glacialis</span>) none of the truly Arctic fish species are migratory [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref037">37</a>]. There is therefore very little horizontal energy flux in Arctic fish communities. Species from the Long demersals group have been recorded in the stomachs of a wide range of predators, including seabirds, seals and elasmobranchs, as well as large bodied, teleost fish species including long rough dab (
  <span class="italic">Hippoglossoides platessoides</span>), Greenland halibut (
  <span class="italic">Reinhardtius hippoglossoides</span>) and Atlantic cod [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>]. This suggests that the Long demersals play an important functional role in the ecosystem by converting energy and matter from the benthos (including endobenthos) to species at higher TL.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Elasmobranchs are demersal generalists found at above-average trophic levels, as they prey on benthos, fish and in some instances dead organic material (i.e., they are scavengers; [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref039">39</a>]). Most species members of the Elasmobranch group have a flat body shape, a property they share with the flatfish from the Large demersals group. Fish with a flat body shape have a negative buoyancy [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref040">40</a>], which naturally promotes a benthic affiliation. Flat shaped fish species may glide efficiently above the seabed [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref041">41</a>], but since they need to spend energy in order to move up and stay above the seabed [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref040">40</a>], the flat shape does not encourage long migrations. A recent tagging experiment carried out in British waters revealed that the common skate, 
  <span class="italic">Dipturus batis</span>, a close taxonomic relative, showed a strong site fidelity [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref042">42</a>]. Although the rabbit fish, 
  <span class="italic">Chimaera monstrosa</span>, conducts spawning migrations during summer time [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref024">24</a>], their traits suggest that they are mostly stationary and proficient at exploiting local resources. The elasmobranchs are generally large and long-lived, which suggests that they store large amounts of energy over long periods of time and therefore are a predictable ecosystem component. They do however have low resilience to fishing and other sources of increased mortality [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref043">43</a>]. Several of the Elasmobranchs are scavengers [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref044">44</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref045">45</a>], a property that they presumably benefit from in the Barents Sea where commercial fishing provides discards. This opportunistic feeding behaviour, combined with a low number of natural enemies, suggests that this group is an important structural ecosystem component [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref046">46</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref047">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Lumpsucker group consists of three round-bodied plankton feeders occurring at below-average trophic levels. One of the species (
  <span class="italic">Cyclopterus lumpus</span>) is boreal, semipelagic, eurybatic and up to 50 cm long, whereas the two other species (
  <span class="italic">Eumicrotremus spinosus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">derjugini</span>) are Arctic, demersal, shallow-water and less than 14 cm long [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref024">24</a>]. The latter are among the few plankton feeding Arctic fish found in the Barents Sea. Contrary to what one would expect from the body shape, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">lumpus</span> is a good swimmer, performing extensive migrations between the open ocean (where it feeds) and coastal areas (where it reproduces) [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref048">48</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref049">49</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Cyclopterus lumpus</span> is one of the few species that utilize comb jellies (
  <span class="italic">Ctenophora</span>) as food [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref050">50</a>]. This may be an important contribution to the overall ecosystem functioning as ctenophores are expected to become more abundant with climate warming [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref051">51</a>]. The two Arctic lumpsuckers are slow swimmers and feed on hyperiids [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref052">52</a>], they have no major seasonal migrations, but contribute to local communities throughout the year. 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">lumpus</span> is eaten by Greenland shark, Atlantic wolfish 
  <span class="italic">Anarhichas lupus</span>, Greenland halibut, sea birds, seals, whales and other mammals [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref053">53</a>], 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">spinosus</span> has been observed in the stomachs of elasmobranchs (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">Amblyraja radiata</span>; [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref054">54</a>]), Atlantic cod (
  <span class="italic">Gadus morhua</span>) and spotted wolffish (
  <span class="italic">Anarhichas minor</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>]. The Lumpsuckers therefore provide a small but important functional group, linking planktonic species to large members of several other functional groups, in both Atlantic and Arctic waters in the Barents Sea.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Semipelagics consisted of boreal, pelagic-demersal species, and they comprised the species with a certain degree of pelagic affinity, the purely pelagic species (capelin 
  <span class="italic">Mallotus villosus</span>, Atlantic herring 
  <span class="italic">Clupea harengus</span> and polar cod 
  <span class="italic">Boreogadus saida</span>) being excluded from our analyses. The Semipelagics are plankton feeders found at below-average trophic levels. They use both the pelagic and demersal habitats, and although many are schooling species they commonly do not perform long migrations. Nevertheless, since the Semipelagics are, in general, streamlined in shape, they are good swimmers and have a relatively large spatial range. Unlike the adults of many of the other fish species in the Barents Sea (except for a number of strictly pelagic and highly migratory species not included in the present analyses), they prey on small food items such as zooplankton (both benthic and pelagic), euphausiids and fish eggs and larvae [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>]. As prey species, they transfer this energy to larger predators such whales, seals, sea birds, squids, elasmobranchs and large number of teleost fish which mostly belong to the Large demersals group [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>]. In contrast to the long demersals, which transfer energy from the benthos towards higher TL, the Semipelagics play a role as foraging species, preying on plankton and being important food sources for predators at higher TL.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Redfish group consisted of boreal, benthopelagic, normally (fusiform) shaped and relatively large species, all belonging to the family 
  <span class="italic">Sebastidae</span>. They are found at above-average trophic levels, and have the highest average longevity among the functional groups. Redfish move between the bottom and the pelagic water layers, and the two largest members of the group (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">mentella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">norvegicus</span>) perform extensive migrations [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref055">55</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref056">56</a>]. Redfish prey on smaller (mostly pelagic) fish, zoobenthos and large zooplankton (e.g., shrimps and euphausiids). They have been found in the stomachs of various elasmobranchs and also teleost fish belonging to various functional groups, including long rough dab, Northern wolfish (
  <span class="italic">Anarhichas denticulatus</span>), Arctic rockling (
  <span class="italic">Gaidropsarus argentatus</span>), blue whiting (
  <span class="italic">Micromesistius poutassou</span>), haddock (
  <span class="italic">Melanogrammus aeglefinus</span>), Greenland halibut and Atlantic cod [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref038">38</a>]. Redfish are therefore important members of the Barents Sea food web as they interact with and connect many other ecosystem components, including large crustaceans and several functional groups of fish [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref017">17</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref056">56</a>]. Furthermore, due to their high longevity, they provide this ecosystem function over a long time span, and their presence represents a stable ecosystem component.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As their name implies, the Large demersals are relatively large, demersal species found at above-average trophic levels. They feed on a variety of benthos and fish species [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>]. They are all boreal, and all produce high numbers of pelagic eggs. Their potential to distribute their offspring across large areas is therefore high in comparison to members of other functional groups. Although some of the species in this group are apparently non-migratory (e.g., the roughhead grenadier, 
  <span class="italic">Macrourus berglax</span>), most of them are migratory, with good swimming capabilities. Furthermore, the Large demersals are primarily omnivorous [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref035">35</a>], and many of them are found across a much larger latitudinal range than for example members of the Long demersals. The Atlantic cod for instance is found across most shelf areas of the North Atlantic [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>], whereas many of the Long demersals and Lumpsuckers are restricted to limited areas of the Barents Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref057">57</a>]. It can therefore be presumed they can respond quickly to environmental change [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref058">58</a>]. Large demersals prey on many species, and as adults have, in general, few predators [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref033">33</a>], which is indicative of high trophic levels. Recent food web analyses confirm that several of the Large demersals (e.g., cod and haddock) play very important roles as connectors both within and between food web compartments in the Barents Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref017">17</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
