<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatio-temporal variation in functional redundancy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study period 2004–2012 was characterized by a warming of the water masses in the Barents Sea, expressed by the expansion of warm Atlantic and mixed water masses and retreating cold Arctic water masses [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref015">15</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref016">16</a>]. This enabled a north-eastward movement of large, boreal, omnivorous fish species, replacing small-sized Arctic benthivorous fish (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">borealization</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref012">12</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref017">17</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref035">35</a>]. Consequently, the functional groups developed differently in space during the study period. Several of the functional groups that consisted of mainly boreal species increased their redundancy in the northeast. This is supported with the results from a recent study showing that fish species having a strong swimming capacity, omnivorous diet and a large latitudinal range have a high capacity to redistribute in response to environmental change [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref058">58</a>]. Fast-swimming fish include species that migrate pelagically [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref061">61</a>], and in the last two decades a reduction in sea ice concentration and an increase in seawater temperature in the Bering Sea coincided with a shift from an ecosystem characterized by tight benthic-pelagic coupling to a pelagically dominated one [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref062">62</a>]. We focus on demersal fish species, large, long-lived, migratory, demersal predators, including cod, haddock, long rough dab and beaked redfish typically carried out the borealization of traditionally Arctic areas of the Barents Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref012">12</a>]. In contrast to the typical Arctic fish species [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref035">35</a>], most of these demersal, boreal species that move into the Arctic have a certain pelagic affiliation, as they have some pelagic species in their diet [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref024">24</a>]. A recent study showed that boreal species that move into the Arctic have a more generalistic feeding pattern than the Arctic ones [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref017">17</a>]. This indicates that the ongoing borealization promotes a higher degree of both vertical and horizontal energy flux in the former Arctic parts of the Barents Sea.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the functional groups consisting of boreal species, the functional groups consisting of primarily Arctic species became less redundant in time and space, a pattern that was particularly prominent in the period 2004–2010. For instance, the Long demersals, which was the most species rich functional group and displayed the highest redundancy, underwent a reduction in FR throughout the Barents Sea. Although this group remained redundant in most parts, the reduction nearly caused a total loss of redundancy in the southeast, partly explaining a previous reduction in FD [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref013">13</a>]. In the period 2004–2012, the area covered by Arctic fish communities in the Barents Sea diminished and became increasingly more restricted to the north-easternmost parts [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref012">12</a>]. A further northward retraction of true Arctic species is most likely restricted by the extent of the shallow Barents Sea shelf area. The environmental conditions in the Arctic Central Basin appear to be inappropriate for most fish, as only 13 fish species have been recorded there [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref005">5</a>]. This may be due to the greater depths, or because the nutrient level is insufficient in these almost permanently ice-covered areas [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref063">63</a>]. Several other Arctic shelf seas however still display Arctic environmental conditions. For instance, the adjacent Kara Sea is cold [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref064">64</a>] and ice covered most of the year [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref065">65</a>]. Indeed, many of the Arctic fish species found in the Barents Sea are also present in the Kara Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref066">66</a>], and may continue to reside there if the appropriate environmental conditions persist.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The apparent decline in the Lumpsucker redundancy was probably partly caused by the fact that the most widespread of the group members (lumpsucker, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">lumpus</span>) showed a strong biomass reduction in the Barents Sea in the period 2007–2010 [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref067">67</a>]. This species is also mostly found in the pelagic zone in the autumn when the Joint Norwegian-Russian ecosystem survey is conducted [
  <a rid="pone.0207451.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207451.ref024">24</a>], resulting in relatively low catchability when using demersal trawl gear. The two other group members (
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">derjugini</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">spinosus</span>), both preferring cold waters, are only found on shallow banks in the north and east, and may therefore encounter difficulties if the water masses at the banks heat up. The future state of the small Lumpsucker group requires further attention, as the group possesses a specific role in the ecosystem which, if lost, may reduce the amount energy from sinking organic matter that is fed directly back into the higher trophic levels.
 </p>
</sec>
