<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Crau is a unique ecosystem due to its extreme ecological conditions. Here, the dry Mediterranean climate (500 - 600mm precipitation per year, 14.5°C annual mean temperature [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]) is combined with exceptional soil characteristics. In 40-60cm depth, a water impermeable conglomerate layer prevents recruitment of ground water [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Hence hot and dry, the Crau is representing one of the last xeric steppes in Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. This grassland provides home for endangered and endemic species [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. It is, however, highly threatened by land use and intensive agricultural efforts over decades [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Numerous artificial irrigation ditches were built to use large parts of this dry area for fruit cultivation and hay production, altering its ecosystem irreversibly [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. The study object, the Canal de Vergières (CdV) is still in agricultural usage. It is managed by dredging and cutting off the bank vegetation frequently to maintain flow velocity and provide free access to grazing sheeps. This should have a large impact on odonate larval as well as adult populations which are highly specialized and restricted to the characteristics of the sediment, chemistry and bank vegetation of their habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Nevertheless as it seems, an unexpected high odonate species richness has been observed here over decades [
 <xref rid="pone.0178014.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], most likely by offering an important freshwater habitat within this arid ecosystem.
</p>
