<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="eva12738-abs-0001" class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Abstract</div>
 <p>Unobserved diversity, such as undetected genetic structure or the presence of cryptic species, is of concern for the conservation and management of global biodiversity in the face of threatening anthropogenic processes. For instance, unobserved diversity can lead to overestimation of maximum sustainable yields and therefore to overharvesting of the more vulnerable stock components within unrecognized mixed‐stock fisheries. We used DNA from archival (otolith) samples to reconstruct the temporal (1976–2011) genetic makeup of two mixed‐stock flounder fisheries in the Åland Sea (AS) and the Gulf of Finland (GoF). Both fisheries have hitherto been managed as a single stock of European flounders (
  <span class="italic">Platichthys flesus</span>), but were recently revealed to target two closely related species: the pelagic‐spawning 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> and the newly described, demersal‐spawning 
  <span class="italic">P. solemdali</span>. While the AS and GoF fisheries were assumed to consist exclusively of 
  <span class="italic">P. solemdali</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> dominated the GoF flounder assemblage (87% of total) in 1983, had disappeared (0%) by 1993, and remained in low proportions (10%–11%) thereafter. In the AS, 
  <span class="italic">P. solemdali</span> dominated throughout the sampling period (&gt;70%), and 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> remained in very low proportions after 1983. The disappearance of 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> from the GoF coincides in time with a dramatic (~60%) decline in commercial landings and worsening environmental conditions in 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus’</span> northernmost spawning ground, the Eastern Gotland Basin, in the preceding 4–6 years. These results are compatible with the hypothesis that 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> in the GoF is a sink population relying on larval subsidies from southern spawning grounds and the cause of their disappearance is a cessation of larval supply. Our results highlight the importance of uncovering unobserved genetic diversity and studying spatiotemporal changes in the relative contribution of different stock components, as well as the underlying environmental causes, to manage marine resources in the age of rapid anthropogenic change.
 </p>
</div>
