<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12738-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What had been previously considered as a single‐stock fishery is in reality composed of two distinct species of flounders, each of which can dominate local assemblages at different points in time. The use of historical samples allowed us to discover a hidden turnover of flounder assemblages and to demonstrate this turnover coincided temporarily both with the decline in flounder stock and with the decline of environmental conditions in the northernmost spawning grounds of 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span>. In the GoF, 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> has almost completely disappeared before scientists and managers even noticed their presence. The decrease in flounder abundance in the GoF does not reflect the gradual decline of a single population, but rather the disappearance of 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> and the successive decline of 
  <span class="italic">P. solemdali</span>, which in turn are determined by the degradation of environmental conditions at local and regional scales. Our results highlight the importance of studying spatiotemporal changes in the relative contribution of different stocks to mixed‐stock fisheries, and the underlying environmental causes, to manage marine resources in the age of rapid anthropogenic change. Of particular concern is the fact that the decline of 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> in the northern Baltic Sea could have led to stronger fishing pressure on 
  <span class="italic">P. solemdali</span>, which itself is demonstrated to have suffered from anthropogenic environmental changes (Jokinen et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0034">2015</a>, 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0035">2016</a>). Furthermore, as the conditions for pelagic reproduction will likely continue to deteriorate as a result of ongoing environmental changes (Vuorinen et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0066">2015</a>), there are also concerns over possible local extinctions of 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> within the Baltic Sea (Momigliano, et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0044">2017b</a>). Altogether, our results call for an immediate re‐assessment of the conservation status of the two flounder species in the Baltic Sea by the International Union for the Conservation of Nature. The genetic test developed by Momigliano et al. (
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0042">2018</a>) and further refined in this study provides the means for monitoring both flounder species independently where they co‐occur, and could be employed for real‐time mixed‐stock analyses of the catch (Dahle et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0018">2018</a>). This will enable to estimate demographic changes, resilience to climate change and exploitation, and responses to management for each species separately, creating the bases for the effective adaptive management of 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. solemdali</span> in the Baltic Sea.
 </p>
</sec>
