<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12738-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sampling areas</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two areas, representing the Åland Sea (the western Åland Archipelago; Finnish National Square 49) and the Gulf of Finland (the Helsinki area; Finnish National Squares 54/53), were selected for the study (henceforth referred to as “AS” and “GoF,” respectively; Figure 
  <a rid="eva12738-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12738-fig-0001">1</a>). The two sampling locations were selected for two main reasons. First, in both areas we had access to a large number of samples obtained at multiple time points, and we were therefore able to obtain reasonable sample sizes (≥48 individuals) at regular intervals for the past decades (see next paragraph for details). Second, and most importantly, based on bathymetry and water circulation patterns (see Figure 
  <a rid="eva12738-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12738-fig-0001">1</a>b,c and Supporting information Figures 
  <a rid="eva12738-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#eva12738-sup-0001">S2–S5</a>) we predict that larval subsidies from the EGB are likely to be transported by currents to the GoF, but not to the AS. The low salinity precludes the possibility of pelagic spawning in both areas (Figure 
  <a rid="eva12738-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12738-fig-0001">1</a>a), and hence, 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> occurring in the AS and the GoF are likely to be the result of either larval subsidies or adult spillover from the EGB. 
  <span class="italic">P. flesus</span> larvae are spawned in deep waters of the EGB, and they can maintain neutral buoyancy only below the 10 psu isohaline. Initial dispersal is therefore expected to happen along deep‐water currents. Prevailing deep‐water currents in spring flow northward in the Easter Gotland Basin (Yi et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0067">2013</a>). South of the Åland archipelago, the depth of the Northern Baltic Sea decreases to less than 60 m, and the deep‐water current flowing northward from the EGB is deflected eastward toward the GoF (Yi et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0067">2013</a>; Figure 
  <a rid="eva12738-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12738-fig-0001">1</a>b). While we do not have access to circulation data for past four decades, data from the past two decades (accessed through E.U. Copernicus Marine Service Information, 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://marine.copernicus.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://marine.copernicus.eu/</span>) suggest this pattern is consistent through time (see examples in Figure 
  <a rid="eva12738-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12738-fig-0001">1</a>b and Supporting information Figures 
  <a rid="eva12738-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#eva12738-sup-0001">S2</a>–S5). Therefore, deep‐water currents could transport pelagic propagules from southern spawning grounds into the GoF, but not to the AS. In the western Åland archipelago, there is also a prevailing and strong north to south flow of surface freshwater from the Bothnian Bay in spring (Maslowski &amp; Walczowski, 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0041">2002</a>; Yi et al., 
  <a rid="eva12738-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12738-bib-0067">2013</a>, see also Figure 
  <a rid="eva12738-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12738-fig-0001">1</a>c and Supporting information Figures 
  <a rid="eva12738-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#eva12738-sup-0001">S2–S5</a>), which would present an additional barrier to the northward dispersal of flounder eggs and larvae.
 </p>
</sec>
