<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Climate-driven collapses of coastal marine populations pose major threats to marine ecosystems and the services they provide worldwide
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. Many coastal fisheries have recently collapsed from climate driven stressors with significant economic losses and alteration of ecosystem function
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. Following collapse, species, fisheries, and ecosystems often show no signs of recovery
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. Yet, some populations appear to be resistant to these events, or able to rapidly recover
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. A key factor influencing the extent of climatic impact and the resilience of affected populations is the spatial scale and heterogeneity of extreme events. Mass mortalities can be widespread resulting in a decline of affected species with slow recovery
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. However, mortality has also been reported to be sometimes patchy, resulting from local adaptation or spatial refuges allowing for quicker recovery
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, while documented evidence of these mortality events continue to mount, understanding and predicting the key oceanographic factors that allow for recruitment survival and adaptation in nearshore ecosystems remains lacking and thus require significant attention.
</p>
