<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Along with the development of new agronomic technologies, more changes in climate will require greater efforts to develop cultivars that are tolerant to drought, high temperatures and improved response to rising CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammer et al., 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boote et al., 2011</xref>). Because of the regional variations in climate change, there is a need for improved crop varieties, management practices and cropping systems that are specific to local conditions to adapt to the future climates. Attempts are already being made by plant breeders to identify key plant traits responsible for improved performance under climate change. At this juncture an assessment of benefits of incorporating such traits in pearl millet for the target environments would be useful for making appropriate research investments. Using weather, soil and agronomic management data, crop simulation models can be used to assess crop growth and yields with new technologies and study their yield advantages for target locations (
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boote et al., 2001</xref>). Since these crop models incorporate genetic traits representing parameters, they can be used to propose genetic improvement of crops or to assess the possible benefits of new or modified plant traits on crop performance in a target environment (
 <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Landivar et al., 1983</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boote and Tollenaar, 1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boote et al., 2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boote, 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yin et al., 1999</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammer et al., 1996</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammer et al., 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammer et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammer et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tardieu, 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">White and Hoogenboom, 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Messina et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Suriharn et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh et al., 2014a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh et al., 2014b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh et al., 2014c</xref>). Significant progress has been made on understanding the crop responses to climate change factors using simulation models and, these models provide an excellent opportunity to assess the benefits of genetic improvement of crops under climate change. Thus crop models provide a broader picture of impacts of climate change on crop performance. However, most crop models at current state of development do not simulate the impacts of pests and diseases and direct and indirect effects of extreme weather events such as high intensity rainfall storms and extended water-logging. As of today the authors of this paper have not come across any studies in the literature on use of pearl millet modeling framework to hypothesize genetic improvement of the crop to achieve higher yields, especially under climate change scenarios.
</p>
