<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Drought tolerance has also been conferred to the accumulation of compatible solutes (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rontein et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chen and Murata, 2008</xref>). These solutes decrease the leaf water potential without affecting turgor pressure. This will help leaf cells draw water from the soil. Accumulation of glycine-betaine has been observed in higher plants during drought, salinity and low temperature stress (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rontein et al., 2002</xref>). Using transgenic potato lines with increased betaine aldehyde dehydrogenase, an enzyme for glycine betaine biosynthesis, 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al. (2011)</xref> has been able to induce drought stress tolerance in potato. In another study 
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vasquez-Robinet et al. (2008)</xref> revealed increased accumulation of sugar alcohol and 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ambard-Bretteville et al. (2003)</xref> found elevated proline levels in potato leaves in response to drought stress. At molecular and genomic levels, drought induces expression of numerous stress-related genes that encode proteins including transcription factors and enzymes involved in drought stress tolerance (reviewed by 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shinozaki and Yamaguchi-Shinozaki, 2007</xref>). The products of drought-induced genes are involved in initial stress response and in creating cellular level stress tolerance. Drought stress stimulates the synthesis of abscisic acid (ABA), a phytohormone. ABA is a well-known signaling molecules for closing stomata and inducing expression of several stress-related genes. ABA-induced expression of stress-related genes have been confirmed through exogenous ABA application. However, there are several drought-induced genes which are insensitive to exogenous ABA application suggesting that drought-related genes are governed through both ABA-dependent and ABA-independent mechanisms. 
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vasquez-Robinet et al. (2008)</xref> reported that drought tolerant cultivars upregulate the expression of chloroplast-localized antioxidant and molecular chaperones. The ability of potato plants to tolerate drought stress is believed to be governed by upregulation DREB1A (Dehydrin responsive element binding protein) regulons (
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schafleitner et al., 2007</xref>). To support this, 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Watanabe et al. (2011)</xref> compared AtDREB1a transgenic potato with non-transgenic ones and observed increased drought tolerance in DREB1a transgenic lines. Transgenic potato plants overexpressing 
 <italic class="italic">ScCBFI</italic> gene from 
 <italic class="italic">Solanum commersonii</italic> exhibit increased drought tolerance as indicated by improved overall plant performance and extensive root development following drought stress (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pino et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
