<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contrail variability</div>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variability in cloud properties—conveniently illustrated with the help of probability distribution functions (PDFs)—arises from variations in meteorological conditions and from cloud heterogeneity. Both sources of variability affect OD and hence RF and are not fully captured by global models. Large variability in microphysical and optical properties was observed in aircraft measurements of young (age &lt;10–30 min) contrails
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. In addition to satellite observations, high-resolution lidar
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> and cloud models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span> show marked variability in properties and RF of ageing persistent contrails.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> displays schematically the characteristic shapes of variability of four key meteorological drivers of AIC development. Those PDFs drive a contrail microphysical model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span> simulating in ice supersaturated conditions the dilution and spreading of contrails along with depositional growth and sedimentation of ice crystals within them. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> also depicts the resulting model PDF of contrail OD and its cumulant, along with an observed cumulative PDF
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. The model PDF derives from an analysis of satellite observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span> and contains many optically thin and even invisible portions within contrails. This indicates that contrails that are non-detectable by passive remote sensing and invisible by ground-based observers may exert a non-negligible RF despite their low OD, since they are likely associated with large coverage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Variability in contrail optical depth. Probability distributions (PDF) of contrail optical depth, OD, and (top) the cumulative distribution (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) simulated by an idealised contrail model. The model PDF (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) was obtained (i) by solving an equation governing the evolution of the ice crystal size distribution accounting for mixing-induced dilution, shear-induced spreading, sedimentation and growth by vapour uptake and (ii) by imposing on this solution variability in meteorological factors described by probability distributions (inset) of air temperature, 
     <span class="italic">T</span>, ice supersaturation (accounting for unresolved vertical air motion variability), 
     <span class="italic">s</span>
     <sub>i</sub>, vertical shear of horizontal winds, 
     <span class="italic">σ</span>, and thickness of ice supersaturated layers, Δ
     <span class="italic">z</span>, all constrained by atmospheric observations and numerical weather analyses. Simulation results
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
     </span> are compared with satellite observations
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
     </span> of contrails over the eastern North Pacific in the year 2001. According to the model analysis
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
     </span>, the measurements detected only 39% of all contrails over the whole OD range, 49% are subvisible (OD &lt; 0.02) and 11% are not optically thin (OD &gt; 0.3). By comparing simulated and observed PDF, detection efficiencies, 
     <span class="italic">ε</span>, were inferred: 11.5% for data in the range 0&lt; OD ≤ 0.05; 49% for 0.05 &lt; OD ≤ 0.1; 94.5% for 0.1 &lt; OD ≤ 0.2; and 100% for OD &gt; 0.2, partly overlapping with values derived with other methods and in other conditions
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
     </span>. After adjusting the model PDF for inefficient detection using these efficiencies (horizontal arrow), it replicates the observed cumulant (stepped curve). Overall, applying the detection efficiency curve is consistent with a single cut-off OD value of 0.04, the upper limit OD value of the hatched area marking undetected (and partly invisible) contrails. The mean OD of all simulated contrails is 0.15, translating into 0.29 when corrected for non-detectable contrails. The corrected OD is roughly in line with the observed mean value, 0.24, that overestimates the model mean value of all contrails by ≈63%
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4068_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1227" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
