<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiative characteristics of small ice crystals in AIC</div>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiative transfer parameterisations commonly used in climate models are designed to represent effects of natural cirrus that are composed of ice crystals, whose mean maximum dimensions hardly fall below 10 µm. In dense flight corridors, AIC might on average be composed of such small ice crystals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" href="#CR118">118</a>
  </span>. As neither geometric optics nor Mie theory accurately describe such cases, other optical models might be employed to provide more realistic parameterisations of ice crystal scattering properties in contrails and contrail cirrus. Shapes of small ice crystals are largely unconstrained by direct observations (Box 
  <a rid="Sec7" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec7">2</a>), constituting a significant drawback in applying advanced optical parameterisations. Before being implemented in global models, such parameterisations might be tested in regional models providing more detailed information on ice crystal size and habit distributions. This better constrains SW radiative transfer calculations and helps improve estimates of AIC RF and climate sensitivity.
 </p>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Solar radiation fluxes declined from the 1950s to 1980s and partially recovered since mid-1980s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">119</a>
  </span>. A statistically significant increase in broadband (wavelength-integrated) SW radiation at the Earth’s surface in cloudless scenes has been observed at several locations across the continental U.S.A. in the period 1996–2007 (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">120</a>
  </span>). The observed trend was almost entirely due to an increase in the diffuse irradiance, while the direct component remained virtually unchanged, ruling out a concomitant decrease in atmospheric aerosol OD as the sole cause of the increase. Recent analyses using diffuse SW spectral measurements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" href="#CR121">121</a>
  </span> confirmed this trend coined as ‘clear-sky whitening’. Ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" href="#CR121">121</a>
  </span> hypothesised that while a decreased aerosol load did increase the total SW irradiance, an increase in subvisible contrail-generated ice crystal ‘haze’ repartitioned this increase from the direct into the diffuse component. Formation and spreading stage processes including radiative effects of small ice crystals must be understood well to explore this plausible hypothesis.
 </p>
</sec>
