<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Short-term solutions</div>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding how changes in fuel composition affect engine reliability and safety presents engineering and scientific challenges
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Replacement fuels are limited to those that pass both technical and safety requirements. Alternatives to kerosene from crude oil include synthetic fuels (produced by Fischer–Tropsch chemical conversion processes from coal, natural gas or biomass) and biofuels (from feedstock, algae or biomass)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>
  </span>. To meet technical and safety standards, those can be implemented rapidly only when blended with kerosene. Alternative fuels need to be assessed in terms of their environmental footprint including lifecycle analyses to ensure an overall carbon offset.
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As pure synthetic fuels and biofuels contain next to no sulphur and aromatic species, their use would lead to a substantial reduction in ice forming aqueous plume and soot particles (Box 
  <a rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec4">1</a>). The use of kerosene-biofuel blends reduces soot particle emissions only moderately (≈−50%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span> and exerts a rather small impact on ice crystal numbers (−35%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, since lower nucleated ice numbers due to reduced soot particle emissions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) are partly compensated by enhanced sublimation losses (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). This means that they are unlikely to bring about a large reduction in AIC effects. The same is expected for kerosene-synthetic fuel blends. While a higher hydrogen content in kerosene-biofuel blends relative to conventional jet fuel (+8%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span> slightly increases contrail formation threshold temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> (0.5–1 K), and thereby causes contrails to form more frequently, this does not lead to a significant increase in ice crystal numbers at the end of the formation stage (&lt;5%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. The effect of alternative fuels on contrail ice crystal formation is currently being investigated in airborne measurements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pure biofuels cannot satisfy current supply demands and research into emissions arising from the use of pure synthetic fuels is still in the demonstration stage. It is therefore meaningful to explore the capability of modifications to propulsion technology to reduce in-flight soot emissions. Lean combustion technology (employing high air to fuel ratios during fuel combustion) produces low soot particle emissions by number in ground-based measurements (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> in ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>
  </span>). Other technical options to reduce contrail ice formation have been proposed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span>; their viability has not yet been demonstrated and they may become operative only in the long term.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prospect of reducing in-flight soot particle numbers more than 10-fold using pure alternative fuels or lean combustion motivates climate mitigation studies of soot-poor contrail cirrus formed on low levels of ambient upper tropospheric aerosol particles (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">3</a>). The sulphur level in kerosene can be reduced without direct impact on engine performance, albeit with minor enhancements (≈0.1 %) in CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. Substantial reduction of the total number and mean size of exhaust soot particles along with desulphurisation of jet fuel is an efficient root level solution to curb AIC effects including potential indirect effects on natural clouds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
  </span>. In the context of mitigation, this places investigations of climatic effects of aircraft particulate emission reductions right into the crosshairs of scientific scrutiny. To assess the associated benefits in an optimal way, aircraft emission inventories used in climate models should capture realistically the various sources of variability in soot particle emissions by number.
 </p>
</sec>
