<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Each species was characterized based on pollination syndrome (wind vs. animal), origin (native vs. non‐native to the forest vegetation type of Heilongjiang [see below]), fruit type (fleshy vs. nonfleshy) (Table 
 <xref rid="ece33207-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>). Pollination syndrome and fruit type for each species were based on the description from 
 <italic class="italic">Flora of China</italic> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://frps.eflora.cn/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://frps.eflora.cn/</ext-link>), field observations, or judged from the morphology of the flowers. Showy flowers with conspicuous perianths were classified as animal‐pollinated species. Flowers with fewer or absent perianths, exposed stigmas with large surface area, high pollen quantity, and no nectar were classified into wind‐pollinated species. Fruit type was divided into fleshy fruits and nonfleshy fruits. Capsules, follicles, nutlets, samaras, nuts, dry arils, achenes, and cones were categorized as nonfleshy fruit. Berries, pomes, hesperidia, drupes, and sorosises were categorized as fleshy fruit. The main forest vegetation type of Heilongjiang province is Temperate Mixed Needleleaf and Deciduous Broadleaf Forest Region, which includes the main part of Heilongjiang province and Jilin province. Therefore, we defined a given species as “native” or “non‐native” if it was documented as “native” or “non‐native” in the local flora of the same vegetation region, including the 
 <italic class="italic">Flora of Heilongjiang</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Flora of Jilin</italic>. There were 43 native species and nine non‐native species in our study. There are many other phenological traits (e.g., leaf drop date, fruit date) which may be correlated with leaf‐out and flowering dates. However, data on leaf drop date and fruit date are unavailable and are not included them in this study. Naturally some functional types (e.g., pollination, fruit type) will not affect the growth of leaves because they are not organs for reproduction. Therefore, we only tested leaf‐out response to temperature/winter precipitation between non‐native and native species.
</p>
