<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Coastal western North America (West Coast) receives much of its annual precipitation in the form of orographic heavy rain and snow produced by atmospheric rivers (ARs)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. These “rivers in the sky” deliver intense pulses of water vapor onshore and largely drive the hydroclimate of this region
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. This is particularly true in California, where against the backdrop of recent dryness and persistently mounting anomalous warmth, the notorious volatility of the state’s water resources
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup> has been on display. Only four wet years have occurred so far in the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century (water years 2005, 2011, 2017 and 2019). The most recent period included five years of historic drought (2012–2016) with the first three years constituting an exceptionally dry period (water years 2012–2014) in the instrumental record spanning over 120 years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. Water year 2014, which tied for the driest year on record, was followed by 2015 – the year of unprecedented warmth and snow drought
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup> (5% of normal snow accumulation in the Sierra Nevada
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>). These dry years were followed by the wettest water year on record for much of California
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> – 2017 – a wet season marked by widespread flooding
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> and AR activity unprecedented in seven decades of record
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. This deluge was then followed by a dry water year 2018, especially in Southern California, parts of which received less than 1/3 of normal precipitation. Yet, even 2018 was punctuated with anomalously warm flood-producing storms
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. Currently, a long series of alternating cold frontal and warm AR storms is resulting in a very wet water year 2019 in California featuring AR-driven flooding
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
