<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">The CoSMoS modeling system is a comprehensive, physics-based approach for determining coastal flood exposure in dynamic, high-energy open coastal and estuarine environments. While the scientific approach has been heavily vetted
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>, like any model it is imperfect, with key limitations, a few of which are discussed here. First, the wave climate and derivation of future storm conditions is based on a series of four GCMs from the CMIP5 suite of models
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> and 2 Representative Concentration Pathways (RCP) scenarios (4.5 and 8.5) that project atmospheric conditions to 2100. While we have tested and utilize GCMs that yield the best results compared to observations of wind, pressure and waves for the California coast during the hindcast period, past fidelity does not guarantee future performance. Each of over 40 commonly used GCMs provides but one possible realization of the future climate based on unique internal model physics and an assumed emissions trajectory. Therefore, the accuracy of the wave and storm climate derived from each realization is highly uncertain and difficult to quantify. Further, unlike tropical cyclones which are not resolved, the representation of the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO) in CMIP5 GCMs has advanced but projections of the magnitude and frequency of future end member events, El Niño and La Niña, varies widely across GCMs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. The precise 21
 <sup>st</sup> century behavior of ENSO, which is the dominant control on short-term climate variability and coastal hazards across the Pacific Basin
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>, will play a significant role in the timing and frequency of extreme flooding events when coupled with SLR. In addition to eustatic SLR, the uncertain future evolution of the time-varying spatial distribution of sea level across the Pacific Basin due to factors such as ENSO
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup> and the Pacific Decadal Oscillation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>
 </sup> will also contribute to local coastal hazard risk. Future work in leveraging the new CMIP6 suite of models may provide a more accurate representation of 21
 <sup>st</sup> century climate variability and storm conditions, and continued advances in computational efficiency and ensemble projections can utilize a larger volume of models and RCP scenarios in developing wave climates and uncertainty estimates. Similarly, atmospheric rivers (ARs)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>
 </sup> are poorly resolved in the older generation of GCMs due to their narrow width (~100 km), and while not associated with extreme wave conditions they do account for 15–50% of annual storm surge maxima along the U.S. West Coast
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, the effect of ARs on flooding in estuaries (in particular San Francisco Bay) where storm surge is a larger component of extreme water levels, may be underrepresented. A current limitation of CoSMoS is also its coupling with fluvial discharge, which is currently done via a 1-D, one-way coupling, where discharge rates are determined based on an empirical relationship between atmospheric conditions and discharge data, where it exists
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. A dynamic coupling with a watershed-based model that incorporates fluvial and coastal current interaction, wave and surge penetration, locally-downscaled future precipitation trends from GCMs and time-dependent factors that influence flow rates such as seasonal precipitation and soil conditions would surely improve flooding projections in these locations.
</p>
