<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to Astrom et al. even just to maintain heat-related mortality at present levels, substantial adaptation efforts are needed [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Heat health action plans need to be developed and implemented in Germany and elsewhere to prevent adverse heat health impacts [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. However, heat health action plans are not known by both practitioners and the population, particularly the elderly [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. In order to engage stakeholders in preventive action and develop feasible health interventions, including heat health action plans, it is important to examine the perceptions of stakeholders on the underlying health issue [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. According to the WHO, heat health action plans should be designed with stakeholders at all levels [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], including general practitioners (GPs). This is because GPs are valued as trusted persons, who take a central role in giving heat health advice and promoting preventive behavior [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Furthermore, they can take on a unique role in reaching the elderly, especially those who are socially isolated. For many socially isolated people, their GP is one of the few social contacts they have [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. In addition, adjusting medication during heat waves is a task which is exclusively tied to the profession of medical doctors [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>].
</p>
