<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Against the foregoing background, we analyze the CF hazard along the European coasts both for present and future climate according to the business-as-usual (RCP8.5) scenario. A precise CF hazard probability assessment can, in practice, only be site specific because the actual CF hazard depends strongly on the local interactions between topography, fluvial or pluvial flooding, and ocean (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). Furthermore, the final CF risk estimate also depends on the existing flood protection and the exposed population and assets. Modeling these local details would, however, preclude a continental-scale analysis. Thus, we do not analyze the effective CF, but we limit ourselves to modeling the probability of potential CF, which, for the sake of brevity, we express as CF probability only: We follow the approach of previous studies (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>13</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>) and model the probability of co-occurring high sea levels and heavy precipitation. Although flooding can also be driven by very extreme sea level or precipitation only, analyzing the probability of their co-occurring high values allows for focusing on CF and understanding their changes. At the end of the 21st century, SLR will be the primary threat for coastal areas (fig. S1) (
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>20</italic>
 </xref>), and societies are already aware that, although challenging, they will need to adapt to this impact of climate change by raising dikes, constructing new flood protection, or abandoning coastal areas (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>19</italic>
 </xref>). However, CF may pose an additional hazard beyond mean SLR that has yet to be considered (
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>10</italic>
 </xref>). Therefore, for the projections, we focus on the additional CF hazard caused by the meteorological CF drivers, without considering mean SLR.
</p>
