<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Archaeological records</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Archaeological data comprise reported fish remains found in published or publicly available sources. This included two archaeological sites along the Kenyan coastline: Shanga (750–1400 CE) [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref045">45</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref046">46</a>] in the northern region and Vumba Kuu (1300–1500 CE) [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref041">41</a>] in the southern region (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211224.g001" href="#pone.0211224.g001">Fig 1</a>). Excavations conducted at Vumba Kuu and Shanga under research permits obtained from the Kenya Ministry of Science and Technology and the Vice President’s Office and the National Museums of Kenya respectively. Both the Shanga and Vumba Kuu fish remains assemblages were analyzed using standard zooarchaeological methods [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref047">47</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref048">48</a>], aided by morphological comparison with modern fish skeleton collections at the National Museums of Kenya. We collated fish species abundance data according to the human settlement phases to determine changes between 750 and 1500 CE. At Shanga, distinct stratigraphic layers represented sequential building construction phases of approximately 50 years in length (i.e. 750-800CE). These phases outline the development of Shanga from the 8th to 15th century, a period of growing coastal urbanization and trade at both local and regional scales. At the height of this period, people inhabited Vumba Kuu for approximately 200 years. Excavations at Vumba Kuu did not yield evidence of distinct phases of occupation. We recorded the presence of each species in each phase that ranged from approximately 50 to 200 years (i.e. 750–800 CE). The final year of the settlement phase was used to represent the last year a species was observed.
 </p>
</sec>
