<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing extinction risk methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared the results of our framework to identify fish species threatened with local extinction with those of three other established extinction risk methods. The extinction risk methods were functional vulnerability [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref056">56</a>], vulnerability to fishing [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref023">23</a>], and the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) Red List status.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Functional vulnerability is the decrease in functional diversity following the local extinction of several species from the same functional group [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref057">57</a>]. To assess functional vulnerability we classified species into functional groups defined in Wilson et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref056">56</a>], using existing literature and Fish Base [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref049">49</a>]. Functional groups directly differentiate among groups of species based on trophic guilds, dietary specialization and life history characteristics. We used the number of species threatened with local extinction per group as a simple surrogate for functional vulnerability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vulnerability to fishing is the assessment of the intrinsic extinction vulnerabilities of a species to fisheries exploitation. To assess vulnerability to fishing, we classified species into vulnerable groups as defined by Cheung [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref023">23</a>] using the existing literature, Fish Base [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref049">49</a>] and expert knowledge. Vulnerability to fishing uses a fuzzy logic expert system that takes into account eight life-history and ecological characteristics (body size, longevity, age at maturity, von Bertalanffy growth parameter, natural mortality, fecundity, spatial behavior, geographic range) that makes species vulnerable to fisheries exploitation. Species were placed into categorical groups based on level of vulnerability to fishing from the estimate produced from the fuzzy logic system [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref023">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The IUCN red list assessment is a global assessment of a species risk of extinction and is widely accepted as the definitive index. The IUCN approach is to assess a species’ risk to extinction using five quantitative criteria to establish the Red List of Threatened Species [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref058">58</a>]. These criteria are used to classify species into different levels of extinction risk such as endangered, vulnerable or least concern [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref058">58</a>]. Species are assigned a status or category of extinction risk based is based on a combination of extinction theory, threatening processes and species differences [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref059">59</a>]. All Red List status data are from the IUCN Red list website.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We classified the species our analysis found as threatened with local extinction into their respective functional group, vulnerability to fishing groups and IUCN Red List status using data available in FishBase [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref049">49</a>] and IUCN Red list. Each respective extinction risk method was used to determine a level of extinction risk for each species. We compared our prediction for the species identified as potentially locally extinct from the Bayesian extinction analysis with the extinction risk assigned under the three other extinction risk methods.
 </p>
</sec>
