<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec018" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Value and application of the framework</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our approach has advantages over existing extinction risk assessments as it can be used for data poor species and estimates probability of extinction at a species level. Our Kenyan case study highlights the importance of exploring and incorporating historical and disparate data sources. First the archaeological data produced a list of unaccounted for species, species that are no longer present in contemporary records. Secondly, extracting heterogeneous occurrence data from disparate sources enabled a reconstruction of species absence/presence over time overcoming the IUCN’s issue regarding minimum quantitative data requirements. The naturalists’ species list verified the occurrence of historically exploited species by taxonomic specialists between 1712 and 1940. Thirdly, the reconstruction of species occurrence showed the decline and possibly the local extinction of historically exploited species from Kenya’s reefs today.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Bayesian extinction analysis proved a suitable approach for data poor species, i.e. when certain sightings are rare. Our framework succeeded in comparing heterogeneous data from disparate sources and accounted for uncertainty, in a demonstrable way. The Bayesian extinction analysis proved an effective model by explicitly accounting for several sources of uncertainty. Specifically the model accounted for the varied observation error among disparate data sources. The observation errors were as follows: true and false sightings and survey effort. The model accounted for the variability among types of sightings and survey effort. Another source of uncertainty that was accounted for was uncertainty around the prior, the prior belief that the species still occurs.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The framework used should be of value to conservation management efforts. The assessment of local extinction was carried out at a species level at a local scale which will allow easier application into species management policies and regulations. Furthermore, the framework proved an inexpensive and effective for identifying threatened species when historical data, particularly archaeological records, were available. Such assessments are especially critical for data- poor areas where inexpensive management advice is needed the most. Combining these data and applying Bayesian extinction risk methods can strengthen other species assessment efforts.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local extinction rates are increasing among marine species [
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211224.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211224.ref002">2</a>] and here we have added fifteen new species potentially disappearing from Kenya’s reefs. Some of these species are likely to play important roles in ecological processes and services that may erode as they disappear. The first step towards avoiding local extinction is providing status information at a scale where decision-makers and managers can intervene. This is frequently at the local to national fisheries levels where policies can introduce size limits, protection of breeding seasons and locations, and outright bans to protect species most at risk.
 </p>
</sec>
