<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Correlation analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationships between bird occurrence and landscape structure were first analysed in a univariate way, testing the correlation between the 16 particular landscape metrics and the LOP values for the 5 different breeding bird guilds. Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a> summarizes the results of the correlation analysis for the five guilds. The table contains the three landscape metrics that showed the strongest correlation with the particular target variable LOP.
  <div id="Tab5" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spearman rank correlation coefficients</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Target variable</th>
      <th>Most correlated landscape metrics</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>LOP of farmland guild</td>
      <td>SIDI (−0.388)**
       <span class="break"/>SHAPE_MN (−0.352)**
       <span class="break"/>ED (−0.288)**
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>LOP of grassland guild</td>
      <td>SHAPE_MN (−0.187)*
       <span class="break"/>CONTIG_MN (−0.172)
       <span class="break"/>PD (0.144)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>LOP of hedgerow guild</td>
      <td>SIDI (0.625)**
       <span class="break"/>LPI (−0.620)**
       <span class="break"/>ED (0.580)**
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>LOP of forest guild</td>
      <td>SHAPE_MN (0.534)**
       <span class="break"/>SIDI (0.413)**
       <span class="break"/>ED (0.336)**
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>LOP of settlement guild</td>
      <td>SIDI (0.703)**
       <span class="break"/>ED (0.664)**
       <span class="break"/>LPI (−0.614)**
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Spearman correlation coefficient values are presented in parentheses; the statistical significance is also indicated; for landscape metric abbreviations, see Table 
     <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>
    </p>
    <p>*Statistically significant at the 5% error level; **Statistically significant at the 1% error level</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, the three most strongly correlated landscape metrics of the farmland guild are Simpson’s diversity index (SIDI), the shape index distribution (SHAPE_MN) and the edge density (ED). All three act in the opposite direction of the LOP and are statistically significant at the 1% error level, that is, the higher the value of the metrics, the lower the occurrence of farmland birds. Greater 
  <span class="italic">diversity</span>, greater 
  <span class="italic">shape mean</span> and greater 
  <span class="italic">edge density</span> were correlated with the reduced occurrence of typical farmland birds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlation analysis results of the other four guilds can be interpreted in an analogous manner. With the exception of the grassland bird guild, all selected landscape metrics were significantly correlated with the particular guild LOP. In the case of the grassland birds, the only significant landscape metric was the 
  <span class="italic">shape mean</span>, with a 5% error.
 </p>
</sec>
