<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bird monitoring used in this study was performed in the AgroScapeLabs Quillow, a central observation area of the Leibniz Centre for Agricultural Landscape Research, which is located in the north-eastern German lowlands in the federal state of Brandenburg (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). With a size of 290 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>, the investigation area includes the catchment of the Quillow, i.e. a small stream. The climatic conditions of the area are characterized by a transition between the mild oceanic and continental climate with hot and dry summers and cold winters. The long-term temperature mean measured from 1961 to 1990 varies between 7.6 °C in the west and 8.2 °C in the east of the area (Deutscher Wetter Dienst 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2013</a>). The average precipitation ranges between approximately 470 and 595 mm. The study area is shaped by the glaciations of the Pleistocene (Weichselian Glacial) and post-glacial processes. The soil conditions and landscape structure are typical for the northern portion of central continental Europe. The broad range in soil fertility and a highly heterogeneous distribution of different soil types determine the regional agricultural land-use capabilities. The elevation of the Quillow catchment is between 0 and 100 m above sea level, and the area is dominated by arable land (62.2%), accompanied by forests (12.7%), grasslands (11.9%) and other habitats. The area is typically “agricultural”, with soils of mostly medium and high yield potential (Stackebrandt and Manhenke 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">2002</a>). Conventional farming is dominant, with an average farm size of 346 ha, and winter wheat and oilseed rape are dominant crops. The population density is quite low (36 inhabitants/km
   <span class="sup">2</span>), with a decreasing trend. Parts of the investigation area belong to a landscape conservation area. The significance of the region for birds is high, as BirdLife International identifies the region as one of the Important Bird and Biodiversity Areas (IBAs) in Europe (Heath et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2000</a>).
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Location of the Quillow investigation area in the north-eastern German lowlands in the federal state of Brandenburg</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10661_2017_5837_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bird observation data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bird monitoring was performed from 1999 to 2002 using the point-count method (Drapeau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1999</a>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Bird surveys were applied five times per year within the main breeding period, from April to June, with intervals of approximately 2 weeks. In 1999, only four observations took place. It is assumed that these numbers of surveys per year cover the actual occurrence of breeding birds in this study area. A regular sample grid of 125 observation points was chosen. On each of five straight parallel transects with a distance of 3000 m, 25 sample points with a distance of 500 m on the transect were selected. The same points were used every year. The basic principle of this method is the stationary recording of species by direct sight and/or sound for 10 min at the sample point. The observations were assigned to three experienced ornithologists and began in the early morning (5 a.m. to 8 a.m., depending on the season) and were finished not later than at 1 p.m. The observation points at one line were visited in a systematic way one after another. However, to avoid rough systematic errors, the surveys during the season started from different ends of the transects, and the transects were judiciously changed among the ornithologists within the years. Although the sampling approach was not completely random, the collected observation data may be considered representative for the study area because of the density and allocation of observation points and the frequency of observations. To avoid double counts from adjacent observation points, only those individuals were documented that occurred within a maximum distance of 250 m. In the following, the term “sample plot” is used for a circular area of ca. 20 ha with the observation point in the centre and a radius of 250 m. Every point represents an independent sample plot and is individually documented by an acquisition sheet as well as its location in coordinates to ensure reproducibility and comparability. From the multitude of data collected at each count, we use here only three: bird species, occurrence (presence/absence) and date.
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Design of the bird monitoring within the Quillow area</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10661_2017_5837_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The procedure for the data analysis is summarized in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Detailed information is presented in the subsequent chapters as well as in the Online Resource (
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 1</a>).
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Analytical framework for analysing the relationship between bird occurrence and landscape structure</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10661_2017_5837_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Definition of breeding bird guilds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The definition of breeding bird guilds with different habitat requirements focuses on the typical components that constitute rural landscapes in the area, with the aim to cover most of the typical habitat types and common bird species identified in the bird survey. The guild classification corresponded to the following five main habitat types typical of agricultural landscapes: farmland, grassland, hedgerow, forest and settlement. The species selection for a particular breeding bird guild refers to species selected in the National Strategy on Biological Diversity of Germany (BMU 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2007</a>) and to classifications in the literature (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), as far as possible. Three typical species were chosen to characterize a specific guild. The selection additionally depended on the species’ frequency in the bird monitoring data. Only frequent and persistent species were selected. In Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, the guilds and three respective bird species are listed. For each guild, maps describing the spatial distribution of their occurrence, their abundance and the level of persistence (LOP) of occurrence values are shown in the Online Resource (
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 2–A 6</a>).
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Assignment of three bird species to guilds in the study area</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th rowspan="2">Guild</th>
       <th colspan="2">Representative species</th>
       <th rowspan="2">Reference</th>
       <th rowspan="2">Presence
        <span class="sup">a</span> in the Quillow observation area
       </th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th>English name</th>
       <th>Scientific name</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Farmland</td>
       <td>Eurasian skylark</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Alauda arvensis</span>
       </td>
       <td>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Gödeke et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Yellow wagtail</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Motacilla flava</span>
       </td>
       <td>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>79%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Corn bunting</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Emberiza calandra</span>
       </td>
       <td>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Gödeke et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Grassland</td>
       <td>Meadow pipit</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Anthus pratensis</span>
       </td>
       <td>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Hoffmann (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2011</a>)
       </td>
       <td>84%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Whinchat</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Saxicola rubetra</span>
       </td>
       <td>Gödeke et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2010</a>); Hoffmann (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2011</a>)
       </td>
       <td>74%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Northern lapwing</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Vanellus vanellus</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>); Hoffmann (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2011</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Hedgerow</td>
       <td>Red-backed shrike</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Lanius collurio</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>58%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Yellow hammer</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Eurasian chaffinch</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Fringilla coelebs</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Forest</td>
       <td>Wood nuthatch</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Sitta europaea</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Gödeke et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Coal tit</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Parus ater</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Gödeke et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Marsh tit</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Parus palustris</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>);
        <span class="break"/>Gödeke et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>79%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Settlement</td>
       <td>Blue tit</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Parus caeruleus</span>
       </td>
       <td>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Great tit</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Parus major</span>
       </td>
       <td>Lutze et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Eurasian tree sparrow</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Passer montanus</span>
       </td>
       <td>Flade (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>)
       </td>
       <td>100%</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>
      <span class="sup">a</span>Relative occurrence out of 19 separate investigation dates (19 = 100%)
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Description of bird occurrences</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The occurrence of a guild at a sample plot is expressed by the presence (1) or absence (0) of the three characteristic species, neglecting the actual number of individuals. The occurrences were summarized as follows: in each of the surveys, a maximum of three was possible on each sample plot when all species of the guild could be observed, and 0 when no species was observed. These values are taken to construct a so-called level of persistence (LOP) for every guild at each sample plot, which is the sum of all presence/absence values over the whole survey area and duration, with a theoretical minimum of 0 and a theoretical maximum of 57 (3 years with five surveys, 1 year with four surveys and three species per guild). It is true that the LOP approach introduced here has no direct ecological meaning. Due to its construction, it may be considered a further development of the common presence-absence approach. The addition of the frequency of bird occurrences at particular points may furthermore indicate the habitat quality of the sample areas in an aggregated quantitative way. A high LOP value means that species of a guild are frequently observed, so the area is considered to be a rather preferred habitat of that guild. The LOPs were derived for each of the five guilds, and statistical analysis was conducted for each guild for all sample plots. In total, 120 of the 125 potential sample plots were visited at all occasions and used for the analysis. Five sample plots were excluded due to missing data.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial landscape data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analyses were conducted using SPSS Statistics 22 software from IBM and ArcMap 10.2.2 software from ESRI. Landscape metrics were calculated based on the spatial data of the “Comprehensive Biotope and Land use Map” of the Federal State of Brandenburg (MLUL 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2014</a>). These classified data are based on colour infrared aerial photographs from 2009 combined and harmonized with data from 1995 (Schade et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2014</a>). The biotope map from 2009 was chosen because of relevant improvements in the consideration of linear biotopes compared to the map from 1995. Because no significant changes in main land use structures between the two biotope mapping reference years occurred, it is assumed that the improved biotope map from 2009 represents the structural conditions in the landscape during the bird data collection period (1999–2002). The utilized interpretation key consists of 12 main land cover classes for the Federal State of Brandenburg (Walter 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">2012</a>), of which 11 occur in the investigation area (Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>) and are represented on the map as polygons or lines (flowing waters, standing water bodies, hedgerows and tree rows, built-up areas and traffic facilities).
   <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Biotope types covered by the sample areas (sample plots with a 250-m radius) in the study location (Quillow catchment)</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>Land cover classes</th>
       <th>Land cover distribution Quillow sample plots</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>Flowing waters</td>
       <td>0.00%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Standing waters</td>
       <td>0.86%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Ruderal vegetation</td>
       <td>1.49%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Bogs and marshes</td>
       <td>0.78%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Grasslands</span>
       </td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">6.88%</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Bushes, tree rows</td>
       <td>1.04%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Forests</span>
       </td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">17.59%</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">Arable land</span>
       </td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">69.62%</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Urban green and open space</td>
       <td>0.5%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Special biotopes</td>
       <td>0.00%</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Built-up areas, traffic facilities</td>
       <td>1.19%</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>The italic entries are the 3 biggest landcover classes</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat data were pre-processed, i.e. the polygon and line layer were joined to cover the area as accurately and in as much detail as possible. For this purpose, line data were buffered with a buffer distance of 5 m to ensure that line elements were not discarded during the conversion from polygon to raster format. The processed spatial information had a standard deviation of 0.99% with respect to the original polygon data. The standard deviation of the habitat coverage and original and combined data sample plots was less than 1% and was 0.92% smaller than the whole sample area. The sample plots were tested for representativeness using the biotope inventory of the whole area. The total classification comparison revealed a significant correlation of 0.993 between the sample plots and the total Quillow investigation area (original and combined data set), which was confirmed by Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient at the 5% error level. Therefore, the sample plot area was considered to represent the entire Quillow observation area reasonably well (Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape metrics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The application of landscape metrics was realized by using the raster version of the environmental software package FRAGSTATS, version 4.2 (McGarigal 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>). For this purpose, all vector data were converted to raster data with a target cell size of 10 m, and all calculations were accomplished using raster data with this cell size. The cell size of 10 m was considered appropriate to display the most suitable habitats (e.g. hedgerows) as very important, whereas small habitat fragments of only a few square metres were neglected. While converting from vector to raster data, the dominant biotope type was assigned to the target raster cell. The spatial data processing during the whole analysis is illustrated in the Online Resource to this paper (
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 1</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To establish a spatial relationship between the landscape metrics and the occurrence of breeding bird guilds in individual sample plots, the landscape metric values were calculated using the exhaustive sampling moving window strategy. The moving window strategy is a well-known geographical method for creating continuous crossovers between distinct map cells (Hoffmann et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2016</a>). A circle with a radius of 250 m for the moving window was selected due to the 500 m distance between neighbouring observation points. Consequently, a unique environment could be assigned to any sample plot. The result of applying this moving window procedure is a continuous surface for each metric, which reflects how an organism with that perceptual ability would perceive the structure of the landscape as measured by that metric (McGarigal 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>). The border of the investigation area was not treated as an edge or border during the analysis. The eight-cell neighbourhood rule was used to identify connected raster cells of the same type (e.g. all surrounding cells were considered).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, an initial selection of 16 different landscape metrics was performed according to their utility for landscape assessment, their coverage of different structural landscape aspects and their potential relevance for wildlife resources (Trani and Giles 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">1999</a>). The initial selection covered the main properties of habitat composition and configuration. The following indices were considered: connectance index (CONNECT), effective mesh size (MESH), interspersion juxtaposition index (IJI), landscape division index (DIVISION), landscape shape index (LSI), number of patches (NP), patch cohesion index (COHESION), patch density (PD), percentage of like adjacencies (PLADJ), edge density (ED), largest patch index (LPI), patch richness density (PRD), Simpson’s diversity index (SIDI), contiguity index distribution (CONTIG_MN), perimeter-area fractal dimension (PAFRAC) and shape index distribution (SHAPE_MN). To calculate values for each sample plot, the metric values were averaged within the sample plot boundary (
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 1</a> in the Online Resource). Table 
   <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a> explains the interpretation of the six indices that were entered into the final statistical models for the different bird guilds. The FRAGSTATS manual (McGarigal 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>) contains additional information on all 16 metrics.
   <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Meaning and interpretation of the landscape metrics (abbreviations in brackets) included in the final model solutions (McGarigal 
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>)
     </p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>Metric</th>
       <th>Unit</th>
       <th>Description</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>Contiguity index distribution (CONTIG_MN)</td>
       <td>None
        <span class="break"/>0 ≤ CONTIG_MN ≤ 1
       </td>
       <td>Assesses the spatial connectedness, or contiguity, of cells within a patch to provide an index on patch boundary configuration and thus patch shape (LaGro 1991); CONTIG equals 0 for a one-pixel patch and increases to a limit of 1.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Edge density (ED)</td>
       <td>m/ha</td>
       <td>ED = 0 when there is no edge in the landscape, that is, when the entire landscape and landscape border, if present, consists of a single patch.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Largest patch index (LPI)</td>
       <td>%</td>
       <td>The largest patch index quantifies the percentage of total landscape area comprised by the largest patch. As such, it is a simple measure of dominance.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Patch density (PD)</td>
       <td>
        <span class="italic">N</span>/100 ha
       </td>
       <td>Patch density has the same basic utility as number of patches as an index, except that it expresses number of patches on a per unit area basis that facilitates comparisons among landscapes of varying size.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Shape index distribution (SHAPE_MN)</td>
       <td>None
        <span class="break"/>SHAPE_MN ≥ 1
       </td>
       <td>SHAPE = 1 when the patch is square and increases without limit as the patch shape becomes more irregular. On the landscape level, the mean of all patches in the landscape is calculated.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Simpson’s diversity index (SIDI)</td>
       <td>None
        <span class="break"/>0 ≤ SIDI ≤ 1
       </td>
       <td>SIDI = 0 when the landscape consists of only 1 patch (i.e. no diversity). SIDI approaches 1 as the number of different patch types increases and the proportion of the area among patch types becomes more equitable.</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Descriptive statistics and visual analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To obtain a visual overview of the bird sample data and to describe the validity of the data, various descriptive statistics were performed. Bird population abundances are influenced by several external factors, such as habitat quality, resource availability and species-related reproductive differences, which are not included in our data. The data from particular sampling events were summarized to obtain information on how many bird species were present in the whole observation area per year and to compare the years. Hence, relatively permanent and temporarily occurring bird species could be identified, as could trend information over individual years (Table 
   <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). The breeding bird monitoring resulted in a total of 135 bird species sighted over the 4 years of observation, with a total number of 42,361 bird individuals observed during 20,007 sightings.
   <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Annual breeding bird monitoring values</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>Year</th>
       <th>Number of species</th>
       <th>Species cumulative values</th>
       <th>Sum of bird sightings</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>1999</td>
       <td>108</td>
       <td>108</td>
       <td>4,043</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>2000</td>
       <td>114</td>
       <td>124</td>
       <td>5,315</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>2001</td>
       <td>115</td>
       <td>132</td>
       <td>4,961</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>2002</td>
       <td>112</td>
       <td>135</td>
       <td>5,688</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Total</td>
       <td/>
       <td/>
       <td>20,007</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The breeding bird guild representatives selected for our analyses sum to 17,549 individual observations (41% of the total) registered during 8,432 listed individual sightings; the 15 selected species represent 42% of the observed individuals of the overall bird community. The composition of the different guilds is shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>. Farmland birds constituted the largest group, with a share of 57%, followed by the hedgerow species, with 27%. The numbers underpin the prior characterization of the investigation area as an agricultural landscape. The detailed information for the particular bird species used in our analysis as guild representatives is shown in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. The individual plot observation results were then further processed per guild to obtain information on the LOP for each sample plot.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Percentage distribution of breeding bird guilds related to representative species presence</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10661_2017_5837_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To obtain a visual impression of the spatial distribution of the selected bird guilds in the investigation area, the occurrence information for the guilds in the sample plots was displayed on spatial maps of related landscape metrics. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> contrasts the spatial distribution of the farmland and the grassland guild together with the distribution of the landscape metric with the statistically strongest relationship. A version of Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> coloured for better visual differentiation is available in the Online Resource (
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 7</a>).
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Distribution maps for the farmland (
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">b</span>) and grassland (
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span>) guild occurrence in the investigation area in combination with landscape metric maps: 
      <span class="bold">a</span> level of persistence (LOP) for the farmland guild; 
      <span class="bold">b</span> farmland bird occurrence plotted against Simpson’s diversity index landscape metric; 
      <span class="bold">c</span> LOP for the grassland guild; 
      <span class="bold">d</span> grassland bird occurrence plotted against the shape mean landscape metric
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10661_2017_5837_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytical statistics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main objective of the statistical analysis of the bird occurrence data was to determine whether it was possible to predict the guild occurrence within the sample areas based on the values of the specific landscape metrics around the sample areas. The occurrence of a guild in a sample plot was expressed by the occurrence of its 3 characteristic species and their LOP values. The derived LOP values serve as a target variable for subsequent analytical statistics. Due to the statistical properties of the LOP values and of the considered landscape metrics, only analytical methods without special requirements concerning the statistical distributions of the included features were applied.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pairwise relationships between landscape metrics and the LOPs for the particular guilds were analysed with Spearman rank correlation coefficients. The classification of “preferred” and “less preferred” habitats was then accomplished with a binary logistic regression using input data derived from the LOPs. The binary logistic regression was selected as a principal analytical method because the analytical focus was on the qualitative distinction between rather unsuitable habitats (less preferred) and rather suitable habitats (preferred) based on landscape metrics. The binary logistic regression model is able to predict a binary response dependent on one or more independent inputs and has no particular requirements concerning the scale level of these inputs. Practically any appropriate quantitative or qualitative variable including landscape metrics may serve as input. The binary logistics regression allows a direct and transparent interpretation of input effects, and it is furthermore possible to evaluate the reliability of the classification and to rank the importance of inputs. Mathematically, the binary logistic regression function takes values between 0 and 1, and the binary response is assigned to the function values using a cut point between 0 and 1. In most practical situations, 0.5 serves as the cut point. Mathematical details and the implementation in SPSS are described by Field (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, the binary response (preferred vs. less preferred habitats) is derived from the LOPs as a dependent variable, and a set of landscape metrics is used as independent variables. Among the landscape metrics, those three metrics were selected as inputs that showed the greatest Spearman correlation coefficient with the particular LOP. In case of obviously functionally dependent landscape metrics (absolute values of pairwise correlation coefficients equal to or close to 1), only one of them was used as input in order to keep the inputs as mutually independent as possible. The number of input variables was limited to three to enable a transparent interpretation of the mutual interconnections.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The members of the two alternative classes (preferred vs. less preferred habitats) were taken from the cases that fell below the 25% quartile of the LOPs and above the 75% quartile of the LOPs of every particular guild and observation point. The “lower” class indicates rather unsuitable habitats (less preferred), and the “upper” class indicates rather suitable habitats (preferred). Each class contains approximately 30 cases. Within SPSS, the binary logistic regression was executed with the variable selection method “Enter”, i.e. all independent input variables are entered in a single step (Field 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2013</a>). To evaluate and compare the general classification success and the goodness of fit of the logistical regression models, the share of correct classifications was determined and Nagelkerke 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> values were calculated.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The statistical significance of individual input variables in the guild models is derived from the 
   <span class="italic">p</span> value of the Wald chi-square statistics. The 
   <span class="italic">p</span> values indicate the strength of evidence of the relationship between target and input (Thompson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2009</a>). To interpret the effect of inputs (the various landscape metrics) as having the same scale, standardized regression coefficients were calculated according to the method proposed by King (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2007</a>). The absolute values of standardized coefficients indicate stronger predictors in the equation.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
