<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The decline of biological diversity in European landscapes is well documented by many regional and Europe-wide studies (Defra 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2013</a>). Of all landscape types, agricultural landscapes are facing particularly pressing problems, as indicated by the strongest decline of indicator species, the most important being farmland birds (Defra 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2013</a>). This trend is projected to continue, as some studies show (Pereira et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">2010</a>; de Baan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2013</a>). A multitude of factors have been identified as contributing to farmland bird decline, especially factors related to the type and intensity of land use and management (Butler et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2010</a>; Defra 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2013</a>; Langgemach and Ryslavy 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2010</a>). Some of these factors are difficult to measure, and many are correlated with each other. The problem of identifying the effects of the various driving forces is further complicated by the fact that the ongoing agricultural land use changes simultaneously act at multiple scales. They can be observed, for example, at the field scale (e.g. changes in the management of crop species) (Guerrero et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2012</a>), at the farm scale (e.g. changes in crop rotations) (Smith et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">2010</a>) and at the landscape scale (e.g. simplified habitat diversity and geometries) (Danhardt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2010</a>). All these changes impact landscape composition (occurrence and frequency of different habitat types) and configuration (spatial arrangement of habitats). These effects can partly be expressed quantitatively with measurable or computable indices, i.e. landscape metrics. Landscape metrics can take into account structural landscape traits at different scales (Uuemaa et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">2013</a>), many of which are potentially important for farmland bird species. Landscape metrics also include landscape-wide information, thus covering the whole landscape. This is more advantageous than focusing on a selection of habitats that are considered relevant for the occurrence of specific bird species under study. A landscape-wide approach is supported by recent work conducted by Mimet et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2014</a>). See also Fischer and Lindenmayer (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2006</a>), who refer to this as a “landscape-centred approach”, in contrast to the classical “habitat-centred approach”. Additionally, metrics allow generalization from the specific habitat types within specific study areas when habitat information for the metrics includes only the number, diversity, geometry and spatial configuration of the habitat types, but no ecological details pertaining to the specific habitat quality are available.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Suitable landscape data can be retrieved from digital maps, which are becoming abundant and available for many regions, based on aerial photos, satellite images, ground mapping, etc. Modern methods, including GIS and spatial statistics, allow for area-wide analyses of landscape metrics and, if time series are available, the characterization of trends. Because many of these data already exist, the calculation of landscape metrics is often well established (Uuemaa et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">2013</a>; Sundell-Turner and Rodewald 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2008</a>), demanding much less effort than the monitoring of farmland bird populations. In fact, while area-wide assessments of farmland bird occurrences, as indicators of biodiversity, are reasonable and desirable, equivalent bird monitoring schemes are out of reach because of prohibitively high resource needs. In this situation, it is important to derive and validate relationships between bird species occurrences and structural landscape features to consider landscape metrics as indicators of farmland bird occurrence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We suggest that the combination of empirical bird occurrence data and landscape data (i.e. landscape metrics) has the potential to improve area-wide assessments of landscapes as habitat for birds. Thus, to contribute to the development of an appropriate methodology, we draw on an extensive set of bird occurrence data of an agricultural landscape (approximately 20,000 observations on the presence of species, with more than 42,000 observed bird individuals during 4 years of monitoring), and we test a variety of landscape metrics as potential indicators of defined groups of bird species.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generalizations of case studies are needed to address the habitat suitability for birds on a landscape scale. What is the essence of locally detected relationships between bird occurrence and landscape characteristics that may be transferable to other regions? Answers to this question may help support the efficiency of empirical work (e.g. bird monitoring schemes), the design of meaningful biodiversity supporting schemes (e.g. changes in habitat configurations) and the comparison and assessment of landscape and land use development scenarios. While it is obvious that appropriate conservation means depend on the specific regional or local situation (Whittingham 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">2011</a>), methods to generalize case study findings may be helpful to design local strategies. However, only a few attempts have been made to combine landscape metrics with generalized bird occurrence data (Hiron et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2015</a>; Rüdisser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another important limitation of bird studies for more general assessments is exclusively focusing on selected species, as the analysis may be too focused on specific habitat needs, which are difficult to translate to other species. According to the niche concept, one single species can only serve as an indicator for a particular range of ecological conditions (Koskimies 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">1989</a>). Habitats that seem unimportant for the selected species within the study area may be ignored, which also limits the ability to draw general conclusions for other landscape settings. A promising approach to generalize studies on bird occurrence at the landscape scale is the comprehensive analysis of well-defined species groups, composed of species with overlapping habitat requirements. These “bird guilds” automatically represent a more general type of relationship between birds and habitats. This approach is based on the possibility of identifying guilds as groups of species that require similar habitat requisites, depending on the research question (Brooks and Croonquist 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">1990</a>; Flade 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>). Guilds can thus be classified according to various aspects, e.g. the representation of both specialists and generalists within one guild (O’Connell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">1998</a>). The guild approach has been recommended by several authors for a more holistic assessment of bird communities (O'Connell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2000</a>; Karp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2011</a>; Marja et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2013</a>), and guilds have been widely used as indicators of ecological conditions (O'Connell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2000</a>; Bryce et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2002</a>), functional diversity (Tscharntke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">2008</a>) and the biotic integrity of different land use systems (Karp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the year-to-year variability of spatial crop distribution patterns, the crop-related habitat configuration in agricultural landscapes is very dynamic. While the crop distribution patterns change from year to year, due to crop rotation, other landscape features are far more stable, e.g. most non-crop habitats. Hence, multiyear data of bird occurrences are needed to account for the spatial variability and to separate the effects of the yearly crop distribution from the effects of the more generic landscape configuration. It seems sensible to allow the variation of cropping patterns, i.e. the spatial effect of crop rotations, in the analysis of bird data because it reflects the very nature of agricultural landscapes, especially arable areas.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examples of the potential of landscape metrics as indicators include conservation planning (Sundell-Turner and Rodewald 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2008</a>), habitat connectivity (Luque et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2012</a>; Pascual-Hortal and Saura 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2006</a>), fragmentation (Fuentes-Montemayor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2013</a>), species richness in general (Schindler et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">2013</a>), gene flow (van Strien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">2014</a>) and ecosystem services (Syrbe and Walz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2012</a>; Frank et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2012</a>). According to Uuemaa et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">2013</a>), the main focus of applying landscape metrics in previous years was the evaluation of changes in land use/land cover. The guild approach, in conjunction with landscape patterns, is regarded as useful to analyse the functionality, degree of degradation and restoration possibilities of different habitats in landscapes (van Halder et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">2008</a>; Bishop and Myers 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2005</a>; Melles et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2003</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we present a methodological approach to relate bird occurrence data to landscape characteristics that may serve as an example to generalize and assess landscapes as habitats for birds. This approach combines the above-mentioned options to generalize case studies, i.e. defining guilds to represent the habitat requirements of biodiversity indicators; including all habitats within a landscape through the use of a digital “habitat map”, using only 12 habitat classes in our case; using metrics to express the landscape structure; and drawing on multiyear bird sample data. The combination of these components can represent a holistic, innovative methodological approach contributing to the current state of landscape suitability assessments for biodiversity indicators. The identification of relationships between bird occurrence and landscape structural characteristics may have the potential to:
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Develop hypotheses that relate bird species occurrence probabilities to landscape metrics, to be tested in other landscapes</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Allow assessments of landscapes in terms of bird habitat where no monitoring data are available</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Explain the occurrence or absence of bird groups using landscape structural characteristics, and</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Assess ex ante the effects of structural changes in agricultural landscapes on birds</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our specific objectives are to:
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Examine whether the classification of single bird species into bird guilds is a suitable approach for differentiating the habitat requirements of birds in landscapes</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Describe the statistical relationship between landscape structure, expressed using landscape metrics, and the suitability of agrarian landscapes as habitats for bird guilds</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Identify a particular set of landscape metrics for every specific guild that indicates the habitat suitability of the landscape</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
