<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape metrics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The application of landscape metrics was realized by using the raster version of the environmental software package FRAGSTATS, version 4.2 (McGarigal 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>). For this purpose, all vector data were converted to raster data with a target cell size of 10 m, and all calculations were accomplished using raster data with this cell size. The cell size of 10 m was considered appropriate to display the most suitable habitats (e.g. hedgerows) as very important, whereas small habitat fragments of only a few square metres were neglected. While converting from vector to raster data, the dominant biotope type was assigned to the target raster cell. The spatial data processing during the whole analysis is illustrated in the Online Resource to this paper (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To establish a spatial relationship between the landscape metrics and the occurrence of breeding bird guilds in individual sample plots, the landscape metric values were calculated using the exhaustive sampling moving window strategy. The moving window strategy is a well-known geographical method for creating continuous crossovers between distinct map cells (Hoffmann et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2016</a>). A circle with a radius of 250 m for the moving window was selected due to the 500 m distance between neighbouring observation points. Consequently, a unique environment could be assigned to any sample plot. The result of applying this moving window procedure is a continuous surface for each metric, which reflects how an organism with that perceptual ability would perceive the structure of the landscape as measured by that metric (McGarigal 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>). The border of the investigation area was not treated as an edge or border during the analysis. The eight-cell neighbourhood rule was used to identify connected raster cells of the same type (e.g. all surrounding cells were considered).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, an initial selection of 16 different landscape metrics was performed according to their utility for landscape assessment, their coverage of different structural landscape aspects and their potential relevance for wildlife resources (Trani and Giles 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">1999</a>). The initial selection covered the main properties of habitat composition and configuration. The following indices were considered: connectance index (CONNECT), effective mesh size (MESH), interspersion juxtaposition index (IJI), landscape division index (DIVISION), landscape shape index (LSI), number of patches (NP), patch cohesion index (COHESION), patch density (PD), percentage of like adjacencies (PLADJ), edge density (ED), largest patch index (LPI), patch richness density (PRD), Simpson’s diversity index (SIDI), contiguity index distribution (CONTIG_MN), perimeter-area fractal dimension (PAFRAC) and shape index distribution (SHAPE_MN). To calculate values for each sample plot, the metric values were averaged within the sample plot boundary (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Fig. A 1</a> in the Online Resource). Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a> explains the interpretation of the six indices that were entered into the final statistical models for the different bird guilds. The FRAGSTATS manual (McGarigal 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>) contains additional information on all 16 metrics.
  <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Meaning and interpretation of the landscape metrics (abbreviations in brackets) included in the final model solutions (McGarigal 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Metric</th>
      <th>Unit</th>
      <th>Description</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Contiguity index distribution (CONTIG_MN)</td>
      <td>None
       <span class="break"/>0 ≤ CONTIG_MN ≤ 1
      </td>
      <td>Assesses the spatial connectedness, or contiguity, of cells within a patch to provide an index on patch boundary configuration and thus patch shape (LaGro 1991); CONTIG equals 0 for a one-pixel patch and increases to a limit of 1.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Edge density (ED)</td>
      <td>m/ha</td>
      <td>ED = 0 when there is no edge in the landscape, that is, when the entire landscape and landscape border, if present, consists of a single patch.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Largest patch index (LPI)</td>
      <td>%</td>
      <td>The largest patch index quantifies the percentage of total landscape area comprised by the largest patch. As such, it is a simple measure of dominance.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Patch density (PD)</td>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">N</span>/100 ha
      </td>
      <td>Patch density has the same basic utility as number of patches as an index, except that it expresses number of patches on a per unit area basis that facilitates comparisons among landscapes of varying size.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Shape index distribution (SHAPE_MN)</td>
      <td>None
       <span class="break"/>SHAPE_MN ≥ 1
      </td>
      <td>SHAPE = 1 when the patch is square and increases without limit as the patch shape becomes more irregular. On the landscape level, the mean of all patches in the landscape is calculated.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Simpson’s diversity index (SIDI)</td>
      <td>None
       <span class="break"/>0 ≤ SIDI ≤ 1
      </td>
      <td>SIDI = 0 when the landscape consists of only 1 patch (i.e. no diversity). SIDI approaches 1 as the number of different patch types increases and the proportion of the area among patch types becomes more equitable.</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
