<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial landscape data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analyses were conducted using SPSS Statistics 22 software from IBM and ArcMap 10.2.2 software from ESRI. Landscape metrics were calculated based on the spatial data of the “Comprehensive Biotope and Land use Map” of the Federal State of Brandenburg (MLUL 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2014</a>). These classified data are based on colour infrared aerial photographs from 2009 combined and harmonized with data from 1995 (Schade et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2014</a>). The biotope map from 2009 was chosen because of relevant improvements in the consideration of linear biotopes compared to the map from 1995. Because no significant changes in main land use structures between the two biotope mapping reference years occurred, it is assumed that the improved biotope map from 2009 represents the structural conditions in the landscape during the bird data collection period (1999–2002). The utilized interpretation key consists of 12 main land cover classes for the Federal State of Brandenburg (Walter 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">2012</a>), of which 11 occur in the investigation area (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>) and are represented on the map as polygons or lines (flowing waters, standing water bodies, hedgerows and tree rows, built-up areas and traffic facilities).
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Biotope types covered by the sample areas (sample plots with a 250-m radius) in the study location (Quillow catchment)</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Land cover classes</th>
      <th>Land cover distribution Quillow sample plots</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Flowing waters</td>
      <td>0.00%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Standing waters</td>
      <td>0.86%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Ruderal vegetation</td>
      <td>1.49%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Bogs and marshes</td>
      <td>0.78%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">Grasslands</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">6.88%</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Bushes, tree rows</td>
      <td>1.04%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">Forests</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">17.59%</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">Arable land</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">69.62%</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Urban green and open space</td>
      <td>0.5%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Special biotopes</td>
      <td>0.00%</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Built-up areas, traffic facilities</td>
      <td>1.19%</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>The italic entries are the 3 biggest landcover classes</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat data were pre-processed, i.e. the polygon and line layer were joined to cover the area as accurately and in as much detail as possible. For this purpose, line data were buffered with a buffer distance of 5 m to ensure that line elements were not discarded during the conversion from polygon to raster format. The processed spatial information had a standard deviation of 0.99% with respect to the original polygon data. The standard deviation of the habitat coverage and original and combined data sample plots was less than 1% and was 0.92% smaller than the whole sample area. The sample plots were tested for representativeness using the biotope inventory of the whole area. The total classification comparison revealed a significant correlation of 0.993 between the sample plots and the total Quillow investigation area (original and combined data set), which was confirmed by Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient at the 5% error level. Therefore, the sample plot area was considered to represent the entire Quillow observation area reasonably well (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
