<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, there is no direct evidence that body size decreases in birds and mammals are an adaptive response to climate change. Of the three studies investigating size declines using long-term individual-based data (Teplitsky et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b90" href="#b90">2008</a>; Ozgul et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b70" href="#b70">2009</a>; Husby et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">2011</a>), none found evidence of selection for smaller size, and instead hinted this was due to a change in environment quality. Consequently, in these cases, evolutionary change could not be expected to be the basis of phenotypic change in size. However, these three studies represent a very small amount of data relative to the number of studies reporting recent changes in size, and further investigation of the origin (plastic and/or genetic) and nature (adaptive or not) of size declines is needed. These conclusions are in line with findings for changes in phenology in birds and mammals, for which evidence for microevolution is also very scarce, although the adaptive nature of the change in phenology is more firmly established in birds (Boutin and Lane 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">2014</a>; Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bergmann's rule may not provide the most pertinent framework for the study of size changes in the context of climate change. In the absence of well-identified underlying mechanisms for it, Bergmann's rule is not too helpful in interpreting recent temporal size trends. Instead of focusing on whether body size changes are in agreement with Bergmann's rule (Bergmann's rule as a pattern), we need to focus on Bergmann's rule as a mechanism and identify the factors that are at the basis of size changes.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, Bergmann's rule may not hold at all geographical and temporal scales. This rule received the most support from large-scale studies. The pattern of larger body size at higher latitudes is supported by a majority of mammal and bird species, when studied across a large regional or continental scale (Ashton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">2000</a>; e.g. Ashton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">2002</a>; Meiri and Dayan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">2003</a>; Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>). Blackburn et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">1999</a>), in their re-definition of Bergmann's rule, concluded that it is a pattern emerging across species, ‘in a monophyletic higher taxon’. The relation between temperature and body size change through time has also received much support at large temporal scales. There is some evidence that many mammal species decreased in body size since the last glacial maximum (e.g. Smith et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b87" href="#b87">1995</a>). The trend is also apparent at larger temporal scales in the fossil record (reviewed in Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>). Yet, as reported in this review, support for a decrease in body size over the last few decades in response to climate change is not as strong, especially in mammals (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>). Overall, we found that 54% of the species reviewed here decreased in size over the last few decades (60% of birds and 8% of mammals). These numbers are below what is reported for geographical trends over large spatial scales (Ashton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">2000</a>; Ashton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">2002</a>; Meiri and Dayan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">2003</a>; Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>). Moreover, the range of temperature varies across the type of studies: Bergmann's rule in space was studied over significantly larger temperature gradients than the recent change in temperature accompanying climate warming (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>). This suggests that the 
  <span class="italic">pattern</span> of Bergmann's rule is emerging across a minimum temperature gradient, whether this gradient operates in space or time (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a>). The 
  <span class="italic">mechanisms</span> driving Bergmann's rule, however, are necessarily operating at the individual level, assuming that Bergmann's rule through time is adaptive and that individuals following the rule are selected for. Though an intuitive assumption, we have shown here that demonstrating the adaptive or evolutionary nature of Bergmann's rule is not straightforward, partly because of the complexity of the mechanisms and interacting factors acting upon body size.
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The temperature gradients (spatial versus temporal) over which size trends were quantified; Data for geographical gradients are from the reviews of Ashton et al. (
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">2000</a>) for mammals, and Ashton (
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">2002</a>) for birds. If the temperature gradient was not directly reported in the study, it was estimated from the latitudinal gradient. Data for temporal gradients are from this review. We used the global change in temperature anomaly to estimate the change in temperature when it was not readily available from the publication. On average, geographical trends were studied over a temperature gradient of 12.29
    <span class="bold">°</span>C, a gradient significantly larger than the recent climate warming (average temperature increase of 0.93
    <span class="bold">°</span>C in this review, 
    <span class="italic">t</span>-test 
    <span class="italic">P &lt;</span> 0.0001).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0007-0156-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="fig02" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>A theoretical framework for the effect of study scales on Bergmann's rule in space and time; 
    <span class="italic">X</span>-axis: temperature observed across either a geographical gradient or a temporal gradient; 
    <span class="italic">Y</span>-axis: body size. Each dot represents an individual. The dotted lines represent reaction norms at the population level. At the population level, there is no relation between body size and temperature, as the gradient in temperature within a population may be too low to detect such a pattern. However, individuals are still selected for an optimal temperature. Bergmann's rule, the decrease in body size with temperature is a pattern emerging at larger geographical or temporal scales.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0007-0156-f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has recently been suggested that body size decrease is a universal response to climate change (e.g. Gardner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2011</a>; e.g. Sheridan and Bickford 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" href="#b85">2011</a>). However, the evidence we have collated here indicates that recent size declines in the context of climate warming are highly system- and context dependent. No general pattern or rule is to be expected, because organisms respond differently in terms of the direction, amount and rate of size change. Thus, the response of species interactions within communities may even be more complex. Hence, our challenge is to better understand the adaptive and evolutionary basis of these size changes before we can evaluate the resilience of ecological interactions that are affected by these size changes.
 </p>
</sec>
