<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological responses to global change fall into three categories: extinction, change in distribution and adaptation (genetic or plastic) to the new environmental conditions. Alterations in species distribution and abundance that track the shifting climate have been widely documented in a number of plant and animal species (Parmesan and Yohe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b73" href="#b73">2003</a>; Root et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">2003</a>). Similarly, there is a reasonable amount of evidence for the relation between climate warming and changes in the phenology of species (Stenseth et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b88" href="#b88">2002</a>; Walther et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b96" href="#b96">2002</a>; Bradshaw and Holzapfel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">2006</a>; Parmesan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b72" href="#b72">2006</a>; Boutin and Lane 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">2014</a>; Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">2014</a>). Recently, changes in body size associated with climate change have also received growing interest in the context of current climate warming (Gardner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2011</a>; Sheridan and Bickford 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" href="#b85">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size is known to vary with latitude in a number of taxa, from invertebrates to endotherm species. The tendency of individuals within the geographical range of a species to be larger in body size under colder climatic conditions is known as Bergmann's rule (Bergmann 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">1847</a>; Mayr 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">1956</a>), and is best supported in endotherms, namely birds and mammals (Ashton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">2002</a>; Meiri and Dayan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">2003</a>; Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>). For example, a trend of increasing body size with latitude has been found in 65% to 71% of mammals and 72% to 76% of birds (Meiri and Dayan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">2003</a>; Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>). A corollary to Bergmann's rule is the trend of increasing body size with altitude. Bergmann's and the altitude rules are often associated, based on the assumption that the underlying mechanism of both these geographical trends has a thermoregulatory basis. The increase in body size would be a response to a decrease in temperature with latitude or altitude, respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A decrease in size with climate warming has been observed in a number of species, over large time scales (reviews in Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>; Blois et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">2008</a>). In these studies, the change in size was correlated with a change in the environment, a temperature increase in most cases. There is thus a decent amount of data providing support for the relation between climate warming and decrease in size over large time scales (e.g. since the Last Glacial Maximum 20,000 years ago). Such a temporal trend is expected in analogy with its geographical equivalent, Bergmann's rule. In theory, a comparison across different geographical and temporal scales can be achieved by studying the relations between a trait such as body size and an environmental factor such as temperature (Polly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b75" href="#b75">2011</a>). It is assumed that the functional relation between this trait and the environmental factor does not vary across scales. In other words, the direction and extent of trait variation observed across the geographical range of a species are expected to be similar through time, provided the driving environmental factor varies to a similar extent in both space and time. Given the general nature of Bergmann's rule in endotherms, a decrease in size in these organisms is expected with ongoing climate warming. Accordingly, it has been suggested by some that data from the past could help at better predicting the future response of species to climate warming (Berteaux et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">2006</a>; Millien et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2006</a>; Chown et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">2010</a>; Kerr and Dobrowski 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" href="#b46">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A decrease in body size in response to climate warming has recently been deemed as the third response (along with changes in distribution and phenology) to global change (Gardner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2011</a>). A decrease in size over the last decades has been reported in a number of organisms (Gardner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2011</a>; Sheridan and Bickford 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" href="#b85">2011</a>). It is often assumed that morphological changes occurring in the context of climate change are adaptive, microevolutionary responses, that allow species to better cope with the ongoing climate warming. However, such an interpretation of phenotypic trends relies on two currently unaddressed questions: (i) are these phenotypic changes adaptive? and (ii) if so, are they due to evolution or plasticity?
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address the first question, we need to establish if a decrease in size under a warmer climate improves fitness. The main adaptive mechanism for Bergmann's rule is a decrease in the surface area to volume ratio, reducing heat loss in colder conditions. However, the selection pressure and underlying mechanisms driving Bergmann's rule vary across different groups of animals (Blackburn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">1999</a>; Meiri 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b58" href="#b58">2011</a>; Olalla-Tarraga 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b68" href="#b68">2011</a>; Watt and Salewski 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" href="#b97">2011</a>). Bergmann's rule can thus be considered both 
  <span class="italic">sensu stricto</span> and 
  <span class="italic">sensu lato</span>. In both, a decrease in size is related to an increase in temperature. With a narrow definition of Bergmann's rule, body size decrease is mechanistically linked to energy and heat dissipation, and is adaptive. In a broader sense, the decrease in size may be driven by other factors (e.g. food availability, length of the growth season) than temperature. With that latter definition, size declines may still be adaptive, but not necessarily. Assessing the adaptive nature of size changes thus does not validate Bergmann's rule either way, but is important for assessing the mechanisms that can enhance population persistence in the context of global change. Inferring the direction of selection is also necessary to evaluate the adaptive nature of size changes, whether selection pressures are due to climatic or other environmental variables.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second question relates to the nature of the size changes, namely whether they are plastic or evolutionary. Adaptive plasticity is a short-term response to environmental changes: organisms express different phenotypes depending on environmental conditions, but it does not involve genetic changes. These different phenotypes are expected to confer higher fitness of individuals in the environment they are expressed in. In turn, microevolution is a longer term response to environmental change. It involves a change in the genetic composition of the population, resulting from directional selection on phenotypes (and thus on genetic variation). There is increasing awareness, however, that microevolution can be fast (Hendry and Kinnison 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">2001</a>; Hairston et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">2005</a>), and rapid evolution in response to global change could occur (Berteaux et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2004</a>; Bradshaw and Holzapfel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">2006</a>). As both microevolutionary and plastic responses can occur rapidly, there is a risk of confounding the two when studying phenotypic changes through time (Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">2008</a>; Hendry et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">2008</a>). Hence, caution must be used when interpretating temporal phenotypic trends to avoid adaptive storytelling (Gould and Lewontin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">1979</a>). Therefore, we need to establish the adaptive nature of size changes and their plastic or genetic basis (Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">2008</a>; Hansen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">2012</a>; Merilä and Hendry 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we review the evidence that (i) decreases in body size through time have occurred with recent climate warming in accordance with Bergmann's rule, (ii) these size trends are adaptive in nature, with smaller individuals being selected and (iii) these trends have either a plastic or a genetic basis.</p>
</sec>
