<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An adaptive plastic response to climate change is a developmental change triggered by a change in temperature or a related climatic factor, that leads to increased fitness (see section above ‘are these trends adaptive?’). Several methods can be used to investigate phenotypic plasticity. One approach is to use of common garden experiments (also recommended by Urban and Phillips 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b92" href="#b92">2014</a>), where individuals from the same population can be submitted to different environmental conditions, or the opposite (several populations, one experimental environmental conditions). There are very few examples in which the effect of temperature on body mass was directly tested in an experimental setting for mammals (see also Barnett and Dickson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">1984</a>). Riek and Geiser (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b82" href="#b82">2012</a>) induced a larger size (both head length and body length) in fat-tailed dunnarts (
  <span class="italic">Sminthopsis crassicaudata</span>) reared in a cold environment (16°C) compared to individuals reared in a warm environment (22°C). No other experimental evidence for developmental phenotypic plasticity induced by exposure to cold has been done for birds or mammals but generally, this experiment suggests that developmental plasticity in response to temperature is possible.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When experiments are not practical, other methods are available for analysing long-term population trends in the wild. First, the animal model allows us to assess plasticity: a phenotypic trend in the absence of a genetic changes implies plasticity. A second approach is to detect fine grain responses, given that plasticity allows a rapid response that closely tracks environmental variations. One possibility is to assess if temperature explains better variation in size than time alone, as done by Charmantier et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">2008</a>) for laying date in great tits. In their study of the stone marten (
  <span class="italic">Martes foina</span>) in Denmark, Yom-Tov et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b108" href="#b108">2010a</a>) found that there was no overall significant size decrease over the last 150 years. A closer look at the data revealed that skull size decreased during two periods of temperature increase that were separated by a short cooling period. Despite the correlation, these size decreases were not significantly related with mean annual temperature. A third, more direct, approach is the analysis of individual plasticity by (i) using a derivation of the Price equation to directly estimate the contribution of plasticity to a trait change in a variable environment (Coulson and Tuljapurkar 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2008</a>) or (ii) using within-subject centring, a statistical procedure that can discriminate within- from between-subject effects, and can thus be used to distinguish population from individual plasticity (Van de Pol and Wright 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b94" href="#b94">2009</a>). Using a similar approach, Phillimore et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" href="#b74">2010</a>) compared intra- and interpopulations responses to temperature to assess whether local adaptation or plasticity were explaining differences in spawning date among 
  <span class="italic">Rana temporaria</span> in Britain. This approach, however, is not commonly used, because most field studies focus on within-population variability and not among-population variability.
 </p>
</sec>
