<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Species distribution models (SDMs) are spatial representations of species presence probability or abundance. They are created using responses to environmental predictor variables, spatial relationships such as convex hulls or interpolation, or a combination of the two. SDMs are easily projected across landscapes, and can therefore be helpful in circumstances where acquiring occurrence data on the distribution of species is not achievable, or when the ecological variables related to the distribution of the species have changed (reviewed by Guisan and Thuiller 2005
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>). The change may result from long-term shifts in environmental variables, as illustrated by the range shift between the paleo and current distributions of the Japanese Treefrog, 
 <italic>Dryophytes japonicus</italic>, in North East Asia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. SDMs can also be used to predict variations in the distribution of species due to future anomalies resulting from climate change
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Ecological models thus allow determining the range of species in conditions where it would not be otherwise doable or when the range boundaries are not known
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. For instance, eight new localities of 
 <italic>Vipera ursinii graeca</italic> were found through landscape and climate modelling, doubling the known range of the species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Spatial modelling for some clades without clear geographic boundaries, such as fish or birds
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> is inherently more complex. However, species like amphibians are perfect model species as they do not disperse over long distances
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>, nor do they migrate over numerous climatic zones, and thus have generally continuous distribution patterns
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
