<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We examined the state of health adaptation in 10 OECD countries, based on systematic web searches and self-reporting of adaptation. Our findings demonstrate that some countries have begun to show evidence of comprehensive, strategic public health adaptation planning. Nevertheless, there are still significant steps to be made both in groundwork and health adaptation action [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. National governments are central actors in public health adaptation and are well positioned to play a key role in national adaptation planning [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Developed countries’ national governments have high adaptive capacity, resources and human capital, but these do not necessarily translate into adaptation itself, and health adaptation in OECD countries remains varied. National governments are often constrained by existing institutional arrangements, such as conflicting mandates or fragmentation, or low political or public prioritization of climate change [
 <xref rid="B43-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>]. Moreover, there remains a potential gap between planned adaptation discussed in adaptation strategies and if and how the adaptation initiative is implemented in practice [
 <xref rid="B89-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. In this section we discuss the roles national governments have taken in public health adaptation to climate change based on our findings in relation to governing structure, identify options for approaches to public health adaptation that incorporate cross-sectoral collaboration, vertical coordination and national adaptation planning, and discuss this study’s limitations.
</p>
