<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="other3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Healthy homes and neighbourhoods for all</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where people live is perhaps the single most important determinant of their health. Stark disparities in health outcomes between neighbourhoods that are within walking distance of one another have been documented in high and low income countries because of inequitable distributions of power, money, and resources.
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a> Health hazards that originate within the home are a major cause of health problems. The hazards include injury; exposure to chemical substances, mould and damp, and pests and infestations; poor access to water and sanitation; proximity to pollution sources; and inadequate protection from extreme weather.
  <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite this, and the fact that focusing healthcare resources on neighbourhood based primary care can achieve remarkable results, much of the healthcare sector continues to concentrate its activities in hospitals and specialty care far removed from these places and issues.
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a> Global initiatives to increase investment in the community conditions that drive health outcomes have often been opposed by powerful interests, including some health insurers and health professional organisations.
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As healthcare organisations recognise that health is driven by home and neighbourhood contexts, they are applying new strategies that are centred outside clinics and hospitals and focus on root causes of disease, in some cases achieving short term financial benefits as well. These approaches are often led by patient organisations and community leaders and include local primary care as well as purchasing, hiring, and investment strategies that support improved health outcomes for disadvantaged communities (
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box3" href="#box3">box 3</a>).
  <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>
 </p>
 <div id="box3" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="boxed-text" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Box 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Healthy homes and neighbourhoods </div>
  </div>
  <p>
   <span class="bold">Chagas Ecohealth</span>
   <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">
    <span class="bold">23</span>
   </a>
  </p>
  <p>Chagas Ecohealth is a collaboration of community residents, health ministries, researchers, and others working to develop strategies to stop the spread of Chagas disease in central America using an approach rooted in local ecology and community driven problem solving. Worldwide, around 40 000 new cases of Chagas disease occur each year, and in Guatemala alone, over four million people are at risk of transmission of the disease by triatomine insects (“kissing bugs”).</p>
  <p>Traditional approaches to preventing the transmission of Chagas relied on annual insecticide spraying of homes, which is expensive, damaging to the environment, and has short lived effects. One collaborative intervention in Guatemala showed that targeted home improvements using local labour and materials greatly reduced levels of triatomine infestation in homes, and that improvements were sustained over time. The intervention also contributed to other health benefits, to local economic activity, and to a reduction in the use of substances that harm the environment.
   <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>
  </p>
  <p>
   <span class="bold">Nationwide Children’s Hospital</span>
   <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">
    <span class="bold">24</span>
   </a>
  </p>
  <p>In partnership with Community Development for All People (CD4AP) and other groups in Columbus, the US state of Ohio developed an intervention to improve housing conditions in a neighbourhood that had been historically disadvantaged through systematic racial segregation and economic exclusion. Nationwide Children’s Hospital provided over a quarter of the $22.6m investment from community partners, and CD4AP brought strong representation from residents, many of whom were patients of Nationwide, to the development of the intervention.</p>
  <p>Together, the partnership renovated buildings, developed new housing, and created programmes to ensure affordability for renters. </p>
  <p>Early outcomes include a reduction in vacancy rate (the chief concern of residents) from over 25% to 6%, and associated increases in rates of graduation and decreases in homicides, with additional improvements in health expected over the long term.
   <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">24</a>
  </p>
 </div>
</sec>
