<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological implications of future wetland change for wetland biota</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The broad range of ecological roles played by wetlands means that altered hydrology across whole landscapes will reverberate in many ways, ranging from shifts in wildlife habitat to water storage to patterns of nutrient transfer and transformation. Patterns of soil inundation, for example, determine rates of carbon sequestration and release, nitrogen transformations, and other nutrient cycles. Likewise, changes in temporal pulses of peak water affect local pond metabolism and primary productivity, the structure of plant communities, and patterns of wildlife connectivity [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref006">6</a>]. Montane wetlands serve as critical habitat for a wide variety of species, many of which are adapted and sensitive to particular hydrologic regimes that are projected to shift under future climates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For wetland-reliant species like amphibians and invertebrates that require minimum durations of water availability to breed and complete aquatic life stages, the projected changes in wetland hydrologic response are likely to reduce the number of sites available for breeding, may affect larval densities, individual correlates of fitness such as size at metamorphosis, and reduce recruitment success [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref029">29</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref050">50</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref051">51</a>]. While many species will be affected by changes in both the timing and frequency of drying, those that metamorphose within a single summer may be more sensitive to changes in the timing of wetland drying. In contrast, species that require multiple years to complete larval development are likely to be most sensitive to changes in the frequency of drying [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>]. In wetlands not at risk of drying entirely, ecological effects may also depend on how thermal conditions in ponds change as the climate warms and water levels drop [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref052">52</a>]. Finally, as the distribution of wetland hydroperiod changes, so will the spatial distribution of suitable wetland habitats. This may affect important drivers of population and community dynamics such as population connectivity, synchrony, and rates of recolonization [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref053">53</a>]. Increased reproductive failures due to drying would further alter local and regional extinction rates [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref029">29</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref054">54</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For amphibians in particular, already known to be in decline in many montane regions, climate impacts are likely to interact with non-climate threats such as disease, pollution, and the presence of introduced fish [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref055">55</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref058">58</a>]. Amphibians and invertebrates are also important prey for many montane species, so population declines in these assemblages could propagate up food webs, negatively affecting the birds, non-avian reptiles, and mammals that rely on them as prey [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref059">59</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref060">60</a>]. Overall, species’ exposure will depend on what kinds of wetland habitat they use, the current distribution of wetland types across landscapes, and the degree of change in spatial and temporal hydrologic patterns under future climates [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
