<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climatic factors affecting marine ecosystems, such as SST, are expected to show a climate change‐driven trend against a background of interannual variability. In analysing their future changes, the key question we address is whether the trend is equally substantial across all hotspots and, if so, how can we characterize potential significance for ecosystems? We suggest that the answer most relevant to the development, implementation and evaluation of climate adaptation strategies is to find a measure of the timeframe over which the climatic stressor can be expected to put substantial pressure on ecosystems. We additionally suggest that reference to recent conditions is likely to be of greater relevance for policy issues than reference to the natural variability of the system prior to any anthropogenic influence (i.e. to the pre‐industrial period). Because of rapid socio‐economic development in recent decades, current social and business structures are aligned with contemporary variability. Furthermore, many areas of the world's oceans are already experiencing climate change with quantifiable impacts on marine resources (i.e. Frusher 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) and have consequently begun adapting to this change. Consequently, a period characterized by variability unperturbed by anthropogenic forces is already in the distant past for many areas and not at all reflective of the conditions and resources that present‐day societies are reliant upon.With these considerations in mind, we select the period 1990–2009 as a baseline and define the range of ‘baseline variability’ as an averaged value over this period plus or minus two standard deviations from the mean (for a normal distribution, this encompasses 95% of the variation). We further assume that a climate stressor would be more likely to apply pressure to an ecosystem if it regularly falls outside of this range of variability during the 21st century. As a measure of such behaviour, we use the number of years in decades 2010–2019 and 2020–2029 when the climate stressor is outside of the range of its baseline variability (1990–2009). We categorize deviation from baseline variability as ‘substantial’ if, in any given decade, 5 of 10 years are outside of this range.
</p>
