<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nitrogen fixation feedback</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The enhanced loss of fixed nitrogen via denitrification can only lead to a sustained net decline in the ocean’s inventory of fixed nitrogen, because nitrogen fixation only partly compensates the nitrogen loss. This, apparently, is contrary to the geochemical view that, on long timescales, nitrogen fixation feeds back on nitrogen losses and ‘nitrate gets topped up when scarce relative to phosphate’ (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>). In our simulation, nitrogen fixation is performed by diazotrophs with a maximum growth rate less than half of that of ordinary phytoplankton and zero growth at temperatures lower than 15 °C, but not limited by fixed nitrogen
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. It starts to increase within 25 years after the onset of the rise in denitrification, but does so at a slower rate catching up with annual rates of nitrogen loss only well after year 5000 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). The initial delay is consistent with the time it takes for water to upwell from the oxygen minimum zones (with denitrification) to the surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. Simulated global nitrogen fixation more than doubles within a few hundred years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). It expands its range with the poleward migration of the 15 °C isotherm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). Areas of enhanced denitrification, however, remain located in the tropical oceans (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>). As shown in Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c, d</a>, lowest values of N* = NO
  <sub>3</sub> – 16 PO
  <sub>4</sub> (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>) that measures the nitrate excess relative to the stoichiometric equivalent of phosphate, are simulated in regions of ongoing denitrification in the tropical oceans, whereas positive N* values are found in the surface waters of the tropical and subtropical oceans, roughly coinciding with areas of nitrogen fixation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). Surface waters at high latitudes, particularly in the Southern Ocean, and almost all of the deep ocean waters, however, display negative N* values. This illustrates that part of the denitrification signature is upwelled in the Southern Ocean, where high nutrient levels and low surface temperatures and light levels do not present favourable conditions for nitrogen fixation. Deep-water formation south of the Southern Ocean biogeochemical divide
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span> ensures that any upwelled low-N* waters can be transported into the deep ocean without supporting nitrogen fixation. It thereby acts as a loophole through which denitrification-induced nitrogen deficits can escape the surface-ocean nitrogen-fixation feedback and preserve significant oceanic nitrate deficits in the ocean interior.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Simulated nitrogen-cycle changes (year 8000 minus year 2000). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Annual mean vertically integrated nitrogen fixation, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> annual mean vertically integrated denitrification, 
     <span class="bold">c</span> surface concentrations in N* = NO
     <sub>3</sub> – 16 PO
     <sub>4</sub>, and 
     <span class="bold">d</span> zonally averaged N*. Green contours refer to the maximum extent of suboxic waters (O
     <sub>2</sub> &lt; 5 μM) in year 2000, magenta contours to the maximum extent of suboxic waters in year 8000
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10813_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e684" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
