<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sampling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We examined 1,674 individuals representing 398 Palearctic species, with 83% of these taxa represented by multiple individuals. Species coverage was not uniformly distributed across orders and families due to specimen availability; nearly two-thirds of resident passerines were represented, versus less than 38% of non-passerine birds. We used frozen tissue (typically pectoral muscle) from museum specimens; all but six tissues were linked to vouchered specimens. All tissue specimens originated from either the ornithology collection at the Burke Museum of Natural History and Culture (87.5%) or from the Zoological Museum of Moscow University (12.5%), and were collected in the field during the past 20 years. To capture geographical variation, individuals collected from widely dispersed sites were preferentially sampled for each species whenever possible (see Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a> for distribution of collecting sites). Additional sequences from North American congeners were also contributed (see below). As a taxonomic reference, we followed Clements [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>], including corrections and updates up to 8 October 2007 with the exception of treating 
   <span class="italic">Corvus cornix </span>as conspecific with 
   <span class="italic">C. corone </span>[
   <span class="italic">sensu </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>]].
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Distribution of collecting sites</span>. Map of the eastern Palearctic region detailing the collecting sites for all specimens used in this study. Red circles indicate sampling sites. Sampling intensity is indicated by the brightness of each circle.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1742-9994-6-29-1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laboratory methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extraction, PCR, and sequencing reactions follow the procedures described in Kerr et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>]. Only sequences greater than 500 bp and containing fewer than 10 ambiguous base calls were included in analyses. The sequence from one 
   <span class="italic">Anas crecca </span>specimen was omitted from analysis due to suspicion that it was actually an 
   <span class="italic">A. crecca </span>× 
   <span class="italic">A. carolinensis </span>hybrid based on morphology and molecular results. Collection data, sequences, and trace files are available from the project 'Birds of the eastern Palearctic' at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodinglife.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.barcodinglife.org</span>. All sequences have also been deposited in GenBank (Accession nos 
   <span ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="GQ481247" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GQ481247</span> - 
   <span ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="GQ482920" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GQ482920</span>). A complete list of the museum catalog numbers, BOLD process identification numbers, and GenBank accession numbers for each specimen analyzed is included in Additional file 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We supplemented the data gathered in this study with sequences from North American congeners (accessible from the "Birds of North America - Phase II" project folder at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodinglife.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.barcodinglife.org</span>) to examine divergences within transcontinental species and between sister species pairs. This added 849 sequences from 227 species, of which 66 species were shared with the Palearctic dataset. A list of BOLD process identification numbers and GenBank accession numbers for these sequences are listed in the Additional file 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2" href="#S2">2</a>. In total, 2,523 sequences from 559 species were included in the analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the discriminatory power of COI barcodes, we compared three different methods commonly deployed in DNA barcoding studies: neighbour-joining (NJ) clusters, distance-based thresholds, and character-based assignment. We avoided more computationally intensive methods in favour of programs that could be executed in real time. For the clustering method, we used MEGA version 3.1 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>] to construct an NJ tree using the Kimura 2 parameter distance model (K2P). More sophisticated tree-building methods exist, but since we are concerned about terminal branches, not deeper branching patterns, this method is sufficient. Support for monophyletic clusters was determined using 500 bootstrap replicates. Species were accepted as being monophyletic providing they comprised the smallest diagnosable cluster with greater than 95% bootstrap support [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>]. Though bootstrap support cannot be determined for species represented by a single sequence, they were included in the analysis to observe if they created paraphyly in neighbouring taxa. Species that could be divided into two or more well-supported clusters were flagged as potentially cryptic taxa.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the threshold-based approach, we blindly grouped sequences into provisional species clusters using a molecular operational taxonomic unit (MOTU) assignment program originally developed for nematodes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B47" href="#B47">47</a>]. The program, 'MOTU_define.pl' v2.07 (R. Floyd and M. Blaxter, unpublished; available from 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nematodes.org/bioinformatics/MOTU/index.shtml" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nematodes.org/bioinformatics/MOTU/index.shtml</span>), clusters sequences together based on BLAST similarity using a user-defined base difference cut-off. Rather than use an arbitrary cut-off value, we determined the optimum threshold, or OT [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B36" href="#B36">36</a>], by pooling our new data with the published North American bird dataset [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">3</a>] and generating a cumulative error plot using all species with multiple representatives (see Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>). We adopted a liberal threshold of 11 base differences based on this result, which approximately equates to 1.6% divergence. Program parameters only included sequences greater than 500 bp with a minimum alignment overlap of 400 bp; however, this did not exclude any sequences from analysis.
  </p>
  <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Cumulative error plots</span>. Cumulative error plots of type I (false positive) and type II (false negative) errors for different divergence thresholds. Plot is based on 979 Holarctic bird species. The optimum threshold occurs at 1.6% divergence.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1742-9994-6-29-2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the character-based identification method, we used the character assignment system CAOS, which automates the identification of conserved character states (in this case, different nucleotides) from a tree of pre-defined species [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B48" href="#B48">48</a>]. The system comprises two programs: P-Gnome and P-Elf [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B48" href="#B48">48</a>]. P-Gnome is used to identify the diagnostic sequence characters that separate species and uses them to generate a rule set for species identification; P-Elf classifies new sequences to species using the rule set. We used the programs PAUP v4.0b10 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B49" href="#B49">49</a>] and MESQUITE v2.6 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>] respectively to produce the input NJ trees and nexus files for P-Gnome in accordance with the CAOS manual. We executed P-Gnome using several subsets of our data. First, we tried all of the Palearctic species included in this study to determine if diagnostic characters could be identified to separate a wide range of species. The input tree for P-Gnome requires that all species nodes be collapsed to single polytomies, which is an arduous task for large numbers of species. We only used a single representative from each species to circumvent this issue with the drawback that intraspecific variation is ignored during rule generation. To test the character-based method on a finer scale, we ran the program independently on the three largest genera sampled: 
   <span class="italic">Emberiza </span>(n = 23), 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>(n = 13), and 
   <span class="italic">Turdus </span>(n = 13). For species with multiple representatives, the shortest sequence was omitted from rule generation and used later to test species assignment.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the first two tests (NJ and MOTU), all species exhibiting type I error, wherein a single species produced two or more discernable clusters of sequences, were compiled. Additional lines of evidence (e.g. alternative genes, morphological differences, song differences, etc.) were sought from previous studies to support or refute the likelihood of species differences in such cases. However, no formal recommendations are made here. We also performed the two-cluster test using Lintre [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B51" href="#B51">51</a>] to determine if sequences from these species had evolved in a clock-like manner. For type II errors, wherein multiple species grouped together to form one well-supported cluster, sequences from each cluster were run through P-Gnome to ascertain if diagnostic characters could be identified that distinguish these close species.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
