<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23" class="p">Our results should be interpreted cautiously, given some of the inherent uncertainties associated with SDMs being projected into the future. A primary source of uncertainty in our study is the quality and quantity of species occurrences. In this study, the distribution ranges for about 20% of the focal species were modelled with low quantities of five to 10 occurrences. Using such small numbers for modelling is challenging and likely to reduce prediction accuracy. However, we minimised model uncertainty by avoiding model complexity using fewer predictors (i.e. equal to or less than the number of occurrences) which should reduce the risk of model over-fitting
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, we used SDM algorithms that proved to have good performance with low numbers of occurrences
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>. Since our data was collected from different sources with different sampling approaches, it certainly contained sampling bias, which often results in environmental bias (i.e. over‐representation of certain environments) and, in turn, results in truncated response curves and ultimately yields less reliable predictions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>. We used, however, a spatial filtering approach to address such potential bias in the species occurrence data. Another sources of uncertainty comes from model extrapolation, projecting models onto non-analogue environments that were not used for calibration
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>
 </sup>. To minimise model extrapolation bias and improve the prediction reliability, we projected the current distributions onto the future climate scenarios using the ‘clamping’ option, which allows some extrapolation onto non-analogue environments, but in a constrained manner. We acknowledge that there is also another more conservative approach, which completely avoids model extrapolation, however, such an approach can produce truncated response curves and even less reliable projections
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>
 </sup>. We are not claiming that our projections have no extrapolation bias (they certainly have), however, this extrapolation bias is restricted and reasonable from a practical stand point. A further source of uncertainty is variable selection and availability. Information, for example, on how vegetation variables (VCF) might change in the future is not available, accordingly we assumed it to remain (i.e. static variable) unchanged. It is therefore crucial to understand that our projections are only valid under the assumption we had to make. However, since most of the species with distribution ranges shaped by VCF were bats, which have the ability to disperse and track changes in VCF that could happen in the future, we do not expect that changing VCF in the future will significantly change the conclusions of our study.
</p>
