<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes>
 <title>Data Availability</title>
 <p>The following sources were used to acquire the data: Population data (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://senegal.opendataforafrica.org/SNSEI2015/social-economic-indicators-of-senegal-2015" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://senegal.opendataforafrica.org/SNSEI2015/social-economic-indicators-of-senegal-2015</ext-link>), Brent price data (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eia.gov/dnav/pet/pet_pri_spt_s1_m.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.eia.gov/dnav/pet/pet_pri_spt_s1_m.htm</ext-link>) and climate reanalysis data (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://rda.ucar.edu/datasets/ds627.1/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://rda.ucar.edu/datasets/ds627.1/</ext-link>) is publicly available on the websites as cited in the document. Climate projections are available from the excel document submitted with this article. Biomass data: Nansen results available from publicly available reports (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://brage.bibsys.no/xmlui/handle/11250/106981" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://brage.bibsys.no/xmlui/handle/11250/106981</ext-link>). The reports are entitled "Survey of the pelagic fish resources off north west Africa. Part I: Senegal - The Gambia". Only autumn survey results were used for the study. An overview of all surveys conducted is available at "
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hi.no/filarkiv/2016/12/dfn_survey_info_1993_2016.pdf/nb-no" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.hi.no/filarkiv/2016/12/dfn_survey_info_1993_2016.pdf/nb-no</ext-link>". Contact person is Ines Dias Bernardes. Parts of the data cannot be shared publicly because of ownership by third parties. Researchers can apply for access to harvest, biomass and fish price data at the Centre of Oceanographic Research of Dakar-Thiaroye (CRODT). The public institution CRODT is a subgroup of ISRA (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isra.sn" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.isra.sn</ext-link>), which is the main research institute in Senegal and belongs to the Ministry of Agriculture. The data should best be requested in French language. The variables to be requested are the artisanal fisheries price time series, the national biomass survey data (2007-2009) for Sardinella aurita and the catch and effort time series. Data for part of the years has already been published in annual reports, see "
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.oceandocs.org/handle/1834/9068" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.oceandocs.org/handle/1834/9068</ext-link>". The expert to contact for the dataset is Djiga Thiao (Coordinator of the Fisheries Information System) (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Djiga_Thiao" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Djiga_Thiao</ext-link>). To our knowledge, we did not enjoy special access privileges.
 </p>
</notes>
