<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This analysis has shown that global land use could evolve in diverging directions in the future, either following the historical expansion of cropland and pasture, or moving toward a reversing trend in agricultural land use. These future developments will have multiple implications for greenhouse gas emission, biodiversity, and potential for carbon uptake and bioenergy production. Decomposing drivers of change, we find that the most influential ones would be changes in agricultural productivity, consumption preferences, and population development. Land-use regulation also has a large potential to affect future land use, but is currently underrepresented in models and should receive more attention in future assessments. The possibly beneficial effects of increased trade on global land use are uncertain and partly contradict earlier findings
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, and also require further research. Some other drivers included in the SSPs storylines may also deserve scrutiny, but are not yet quantified by global land-use models, due to technical difficulties in quantifying their impact (urban migration, inequalities, farming structure, and governance). Beyond the global dynamics addressed here, regionally diverging trends may lead to smaller effects (e.g., for dietary change due to leakage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>), or to different results for the controversial land-saving of higher crop yields
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, consistent with the SSP scenario logic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, we considered here only socio-economic drivers and did not include climate impact and mitigation elements, such as yield impacts from change in temperature and precipitation, CO
  <sub>2</sub> prices, or afforestation deployment for carbon sequestration. Analysis elsewhere has shown the potentially large area demand of land-based mitigation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, higher intensification of croplands, and possible interaction with the food and agricultural system
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences across models can be explained by two main causes. First, modelers have differing quantitative interpretation of storylines. Each modeling team follows their own assumptions in terms of future productivity change, extent of diet shifts, or area protection, depending on their own assessment of past developments and possible future evolution. In some cases, drivers are not or poorly represented, such as land-use regulation, although it has a large potential to restrict future agricultural land expansion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Currently, global models tend to only exclude certain areas from agricultural conversion, mostly focusing on official protected areas and their assumed expansion according to international targets, but ignore specific national and sub-national regulations on land-use zoning or deforestation rates (e.g., sugar cane zoning and forest code land reserve quotas in Brazil) and, as also shown here, land-use regulation is necessary to assure the land-saving effect of agricultural intensification
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Although the effectiveness of such approaches can be poor
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>, these regulations and land-tenure aspects are relevant to short- and medium-term conversion quantities and locations. Therefore, future model development should include more explicitly land-use regulation and its facets at various spatial scales, and also its interaction with agricultural productivity and food security. Changes in international trade is another example of parsimonious implementation, with some models considering solely adjustments to current tariffs, whereas some others assume more fundamental restrictions and amplification of global trade in a long-term perspective.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second cause for differences in model results comes from parameterization choices and input data selection. These would gain from being further compared, harmonized, and improved through model intercomparison exercises
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. However, differences in model design also play a role and reflect the various areas of focus between the tools (geochemical cycles, agricultural markets, and economy-wide analysis) and the representation of system behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. For instance, drivers behind land productivity change (prices, research investments, technology adoption, etc.) can greatly vary depending on whether the model is primarily dealing with agricultural development or deforestation. Demand feedback
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> can be omitted in models focusing on production optimization, but in this analysis we see that the spread in results also arises from diverging sensitivities in demand feedbacks, even missing in one of the models. To cope with diversity of model views, use of ensemble analyses is recommended rather than single model assessments and these now became mainstream in climate policy
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, food
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> and biodiversity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, and in the SSP analysis of future land use
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. This study highlights the different sensitivity of the model responses to scenario drivers and could be used to improve the model design in the future, develop recommendation and best practices, and guide users of the model results when comparing individual model results against the whole ensemble.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although global land-use models have the ambition to include the relevant drivers and processes to project future large-scale land-use dynamics, the identification of key determinants of future land use needs to account for aspects currently poorly addressed by the models. Local land-management regulations, as discussed above for protected areas, are poorly represented in current models, although they can play important roles at fine scale. Land tenure, processes of intensification and technology transfer, and integration of crop cultivation and livestock with forestry and other land uses (urbanization, recreational areas, and mining) are other underrepresented factors relevant for future land projections. To identify the gaps and shortcomings in global-scale models, more rigorous model validation and evaluation on smaller scales are necessary.</p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of the factors that we identified as key elements for future land use have been analyzed earlier. Single model studies have highlighted the importance of dietary transitions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, increased crop yields
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>, and livestock efficiencies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>, or have shown the combined effects of demand side, production, and land-use regulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Beyond these earlier studies, this systematic multi-model analysis allows to compare the relative effect across the drivers and across the models. Furthermore, this study adds an analysis of interactions between factors: an increase in agricultural efficiency can reduce demand for cropland but can also trigger higher demand. Yield increase is therefore shown to be more effective in reducing land use when combined with land-use regulation and consumption changes. Similarly, land-use regulation can decrease expansion into cropland but may form a risk to food security, if not bundled with increased productivity and consumption shifts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consumption changes, better land management, and increased agricultural productivity therefore appear robust and effective measures to reduce the demand for agricultural land, in particular when bundled together. As land-use development is closely tied to challenges related to biodiversity, food security, or climate, the targeting of these measures appear as a key component of the long-term sustainability agenda.</p>
</sec>
