<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="pr0080" class="p">The upper BNB is located in the northwestern part of Ethiopia; it is the largest tributary of the Nile River and covers a drainage area of 175,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Its extent goes from the escarpment of the Rift Valley in the east to the Sudanese border in the west and from Lake Tana in the North down to Ambo (see 
 <xref rid="fg0010" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). The upper BNB covers 17% of Ethiopia's surface area, generates 43% of the country's total average runoff, and is home to about 25% of its total population (
 <xref rid="br0530" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taye and Willems, 2012</xref>). The BNB's elevation ranges from 350 m asl near the Sudanese border to 4,230 m asl in the central part of the basin (
 <xref rid="br0170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Betrie et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0540" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taye et al., 2015</xref>). The climate of the basin varies significantly according to the altitude and is governed by the seasonal migration of the Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone, or ITC (
 <xref rid="br0400" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mccartney et al., 2012</xref>). Annual rainfall varies from 400 mm near the Ethiopia–Sudan border to 2,200 mm in the Didesa and Dabus sub-basins. The eastern part of the BNB has a bimodal rainfall regime with the short rainy season (
 <italic class="italic">belg</italic>) lasting from February to May and the long rainy season (
 <italic class="italic">kremt</italic>) lasting from June to September. The western part of the BNB has a unimodal rainfall regime with the kremt lasting from June to September. The Blue Nile River discharge regime is highly seasonal with over 80% of its annual discharge occurring from July to October, and only 4% from January to April (
 <xref rid="br0370" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim and Kaluarachchi, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0510" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sutcliffe and Parks, 1999</xref>). The upper BNB contributes roughly from 60 to 70% of the total annual flow component of the main Nile (
 <xref rid="br0430" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nawaz et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
