<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165" class="p">Worldwide, the 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Global Biodiversity Information Facility (2016)</xref> is another web-based platform that can be used to map plant distributions. The ‘explore species’ under the ‘data’ tab can be used to generate all recorded occurrences, many of which appear to be linked to coordinates. GBIF can include cultivated distributions (i.e. plants grown in cities) and these may conceivably be used as analogues for determining the risks of susceptibility or potential resilience within a climatic range, especially in regard to temperature. In turn, taxa that are deemed resilient could be used as analogous species to identify other potentially suitable plants that are typically associated within the same ecological niches. We have cross-linked geospatial layers such as MAT and MAP (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al., 2005</xref>) with recorded coordinates of certain taxa to analyse rainfall and temperature ranges. However, this information has to be used with caution. 
 <italic class="italic">Cedrus deodra</italic> (distribution from 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Global Biodiversity Information Facility, 2016</xref>; climate modelling from 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Worldclim, 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 10</xref>) may not do particularly well in the climate currently experienced by Melbourne yet young and old trees thrive in the Melbourne Gardens today. This is perhaps an example of a plant extending well beyond its presumed ecological niche due to reduced competition from other species and influences in its natural habitat (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gallagher et al., 2010</xref>). With this strong caveat in mind, our analysis so far shows that around 35% of our collections are unlikely to be suited to the climate in 2090 (
 <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 11</xref>).
</p>
