<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0035" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Baseline climate change assumptions</div>
 <p id="p0195" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second scenario (
  <span class="bold">CC</span>) adds climate change to the baseline socioeconomic assumptions. Work done in the Agricultural Model Intercomparison and Improvement Project (AgMIP) has explored various dimensions of uncertainty around climate change impacts on agriculture. First, there is uncertainty on future GHG concentration levels, which will depend on economic growth and technological development. There is also uncertainty to the effects of increasing GHG levels in the atmosphere on changing temperatures and precipitation patterns and the ultimate impact of these changes on crop yields (
  <a rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0450">Rosenzweig et al., 2014</a>, 
  <a rid="b0455" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0455">Ruane et al., 2018</a>, 
  <a rid="b0555" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0555">von Lampe et al., 2014</a>). We use the 
  <span class="bold">CC</span> scenario not as a projection of climate change impacts, which ideally would include multiple climate models to give a range of potential outcomes, but more as a benchmark to provide context of the potential benefits of increased agricultural investment. As such, we designed the 
  <span class="bold">CC</span> scenario to be a more “extreme” climate scenario to explore diverse alternative climates similar to other modeling exercises (
  <a rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0300">Mason-D’Croz et al., 2016</a>, 
  <a rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0325">Nelson et al., 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0330">Nelson et al., 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0200" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The IPCC’s Fifth Assessment report (
  <a rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0250">IPCC, 2013</a>) provides a range of future climate scenarios called Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs). Through 2030, there are limited differences in atmospheric concentration of GHGs across the four RCPs ranging from concentration levels between 445 ppm and 480 ppm in 2030 compared to approximately 375 ppm in 2005. Radiative forcing by 2030 ranges from 2.9 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> to 3.3 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> compared to 1.9 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> in 2005. The RCPs begin to diverge more significantly by mid- and end-of century (
  <a rid="f0010" ref-type="fig" href="#f0010">Fig. 2</a>). In the 
  <span class="bold">CC</span> scenario, we have chosen to apply RCP 8.5, the most severe of the RCPs, and which a rising radiative forcing pathway leading to 8.5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (∼1370 ppm CO
  <sub>2</sub> eq) by 2100 (
  <a rid="b0535" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0535">van Vuuren et al., 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b0540" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0540">van Vuuren et al., 2006</a>).
  <div id="f0010" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>CO
     <sub>2</sub> equivalent concentration and radiative forcing for IPCC's four RCPs and a NoCC (constant 2005 climate) scenario. 
     <span class="italic">Source:</span> Based on 
     <a rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0400">Robinson et al. (2015)</a>; Data downloaded from the RCP Database version 2.0.5 (
     <a rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0240">IIASA, 2015</a>. RCP 2.6: 
     <a rid="b0540" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0540">van Vuuren et al., 2006</a>, 
     <a rid="b0535" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0535">van Vuuren et al., 2007</a>. RCP 4.5: 
     <a rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0070">Clarke et al., 2007</a>, 
     <a rid="b0470" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0470">Smith and Wigley, 2006</a>, 
     <a rid="b0575" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0575">Wise et al., 2009</a>. RCP 6.0: 
     <a rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0165">Fujino et al., 2006</a>, 
     <a rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0200">Hijioka et al., 2008</a>. RCP 8.5: 
     <a rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0395">Riahi and Nakicenovic (2007)</a>. 
     <span class="italic">Note:</span> NoCC—no climate change or constant 2005 climate; Red line represents the 2030 endpoint for achieving SDGs. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="gr2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0205" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate models vary in how they simulate the effects of a given GHG concentration pathway on temperature and precipitation. In this report, we focus our analysis on the climate realization from the Hadley Center’s Global Environment Model (
  <span class="bold">HGEM</span>; 
  <a rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0270">Jones et al., 2011</a>). We selected HGEM because this climate model projects the most severe global consequences to agriculture from climate change with respect to changes in temperature and precipitation under RCP 8.5 (
  <a rid="f0015" ref-type="fig" href="#f0015">Fig. 3</a>) and thus represents the most negative global climate scenario of those scenarios that were available from the freely available dataset of the ISI-MIP fast track initiative (
  <a rid="b0560" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0560">Warszawski et al., 2014</a>). At the other extreme, the “No-Climate-Change” (
  <span class="bold">NoCC</span>) case presents a future climate with no additional climate change.
  <a rid="fn2" ref-type="fn" href="#fn2">2</a>
  <div id="f0015" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Change from 2000 in annual precipitation (mm) and maximum temperature (°C) for HGEM using RCP8.5 by 2030, 2050, and 2100. 
     <span class="italic">Source:</span> Climate data comes from CMIP and ISI MIP (
     <a rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0450">Rosenzweig et al., 2014</a>, 
     <a rid="b0495" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0495">Taylor et al., 2012</a>, 
     <a rid="b0560" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0560">Warszawski et al., 2014</a>) and are downscaled for use in the crop models.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="gr3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0210" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the 
  <span class="bold">NoCC</span> scenario, aggregate crop productivity in Africa is assumed to increase by 38 percent between 2010 and 2030 (
  <a rid="b0480" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0480">Sulser et al., 2015</a>). The changing temperatures and precipitation represented in 
  <a rid="f0015" ref-type="fig" href="#f0015">Fig. 3</a> would lead to a negative biophysical shock that would decrease 2030 yields in Africa by about seven percent, excluding possible economic adaptations. The negative effects of climate change in Africa are higher than for the average across developing countries or the global average (five and six percent respectively).
 </p>
</sec>
