<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0095" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Caveats and critical assessment</div>
 <p id="p0385" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we explore the potential contributions of a scenario of higher future investments within the CGIAR with a particular focus on the impacts on the population at risk of hunger. We have taken a novel approach attempting to integrate the R&amp;D and agricultural productivity literature directly to a global economic modeling framework to better link projected economy-wide gains in agricultural production to the kinds of investments needed to achieve these gains. Our modeling efforts include a broad multi-model ensemble designed to capture key feedback dynamics between agriculture and other sectors of the economy by integration of GLOBE into the IMPACT framework. The inclusion of this linkage allowed for a better assessment of some of the potential benefits of investments in agriculture in Africa, which suggested an estimated reduction of 1.2% (2 million) fewer people at risk of hunger in Africa than would have been estimated without income feedbacks from GLOBE (for more detailed comparison of results with and without connection to GLOBE in 
  <a rid="s0130" ref-type="sec" href="#s0130">Appendices Table S5</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0390" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our objective with this multi-model ensemble was to expand the scope of analysis, but we recognize that results are in part dependent on the models selected. Research from AgMIP suggests that there can be significant differences in outcomes between models even when assuming the same scenario inputs (
  <a rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0450">Rosenzweig et al., 2014</a>, 
  <a rid="b0555" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0555">von Lampe et al., 2014</a>). A multi-model ensemble that included multiple similar models (crop, economic, climate), would allow us to explore model uncertainty at each coupling point. Baseline productivity growth and investment levels, as well as future food demand are directly tied to scenarios of economic growth. This analysis only used SSP2, and we would expect the magnitude of the challenge of eradicating hunger would vary significantly based on the socioeconomic scenarios used. Nevertheless, given recent results from work by 
  <a rid="b9015" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9015">Hasegawa et al. (2018)</a>, which explores future hunger across a broader range of economic and climate scenarios, and including land-use and trade policies that were not included in this analysis, we believe our conclusion that increased investments in agriculture are necessary but insufficient to achieve SDG2 would be robust in such an exercise.
 </p>
 <p id="p0395" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential gains from Agricultural R&amp;D are also susceptible to uncertainty in future state capacity and fragility. The SSPs focus their narratives on long run trends in the global economy, which, while helpful for exploring scenarios around climate change and long run drivers in the food system like agricultural R&amp;D, do not include other drivers that are important to global food security. For example, extreme events, both social and environmental, will almost certainly complicate progress towards SDG2. These events and crises can displace millions while destroying capital (human, physical, natural, social) and limiting the capacity of societies to effectively function. Poor governance and weak and corrupt states can prevent the effective application of science, technology, and best practices. The recent uptick in global food insecurity can be attributed in large part due to state failure and internal conflicts (
  <a rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0130">FAO, 2017</a>, 
  <a rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0150">FSIN, 2018</a>). Peace and stability, broadly, are prerequisites for development, without which gains from research are unlikely to be achieved.
 </p>
 <p id="p0400" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainty in this analysis also stems from the fact that global economic models rely on aggregated national statistics and must represent detailed economic behavior in a fairly stylized way. The global food system is rapidly transforming with the development of more complex and integrated processing value chains (
  <a rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0385">Reardon et al., 2018</a>). We believe that by coupling a highly disaggregated agricultural partial equilibrium model like IMPACT to GLOBE was an important advance to better assess economy-wide impacts of investments. However, we also recognize that the kinds of investments we considered are focused more on primary production, even as we tried to simulate certain investments like improved infrastructure that would see their impact more generally throughout the value chain. Future research linking global models like IMPACT and GLOBE to more granular analysis of value chains could highlight important complimentary interventions that could ensure there is full capacity throughout the value chain for the increased production modeled in this work. Hunger in this analysis, as well as those we’ve compared to provide context define hunger in terms of calories. For a better assessment on changes to food security, which should be the ultimate goal for policymakers, more research will be needed to move beyond calorie supply, and to consider dietary and nutritional quality. Both IMPACT and GLOBE simulate economic behavior of a single representative consumer. National averages can mask significant distributional differences within countries and there would be significant gains from trying to bridge scales of analysis through linking to more detailed value chain and disaggregated household analyses.
 </p>
 <p id="p0405" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the side of cost estimation, we had to work in a data sparse environment with limited long-run data on investments, which complicates the empirical estimation of returns to R&amp;D (
  <a rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0095">Esposti &amp; Pierani, 2003</a>). We applied a methodology with a structural theory of how investments in R&amp;D are converted to changes in sector productivity, the PIM. However, this approach has its drawbacks in that the parameters needed to represent research lags and knowledge decay are not observed directly and are difficult to estimate as they are endogenous with respect to investment decisions (
  <a rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0050">Bitzer and Stephan, 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0190">Hall et al., 2010</a>). 
  <a rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0035">Baker and Shittu (2007)</a> highlighted the importance of better understanding endogenous technical change, and further research is still needed to better understand the way that research institutions respond to changes in R&amp;D investment levels and how basic research and absorptive capacity can increase or decrease with respect to investment decisions. Better understanding these relationships will be critical for closing the modeling feedback loop, to begin to consider the potential effects of income changes and economic development on R&amp;D investment streams.
 </p>
 <p id="p0410" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, with our focus on public investments through the CGIAR, we assumed that private and other public investments (e.g. NARS) stayed at baseline levels and would not adjust to higher spending in the CGIAR. However, it is unlikely that the rest of the agricultural R&amp;D ecosystem would not adjust their behavior. More research would be needed to explore this. It is possible that these increases could crowd out other investments, decreasing non-CGIAR investments, which in turn could diminish regional capacity to fully benefit from research done in the CGIAR. Alternatively, it could spur complementary research investments, leading to an even greater impact from additional investments. From a policy perspective, the latter case is obviously preferred, so applied research in this realm would be useful to ensure greater impacts and efficacy.</p>
</sec>
