<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0055" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comprehensive agricultural sector investments to help end hunger in Africa</div>
 <p id="p0285" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> investment portfolio represents a broad array of additional investments across different parts of the agricultural system. If these investments were to occur simultaneously, we would expect the total additional cost for all developing countries to be about $52 billion per year from 2015 to 2030 (
  <a rid="t0025" ref-type="table" href="#t0025">Table 5</a>), an amount comparable to assumed baseline infrastructure investments. The additional direct investments in agriculture (excluding infrastructure) account for about $26 billion per year, of which about $8 billion per year would be in Africa and West Asia. The total investment cost for Africa and West Asia, including infrastructure, is almost $15 billion per year (29 percent of total investment across all developing countries).
  <div id="t0025" position="float" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Total additional cost of Comprehensive Investment Scenario (billion 2005 USD).</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th rowspan="2">Region</th>
      <th colspan="4">Direct investment in agriculture
       <span class="hr"/>
      </th>
      <th rowspan="2">Infrastructure
       <span class="break"/>(5)
      </th>
      <th rowspan="2">Total
       <span class="break"/>(6)
      </th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th>Agricultural R&amp;D
       <span class="break"/>(1)
      </th>
      <th>Irrigation expansion
       <span class="break"/>(2)
      </th>
      <th>Water use efficiency
       <span class="break"/>(3)
      </th>
      <th>Soil &amp; water management
       <span class="break"/>(4)
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Africa South of the Sahara</td>
      <td>0.67</td>
      <td>2.76</td>
      <td>0.41</td>
      <td>1.76</td>
      <td>4.52</td>
      <td>10.1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>North Africa and West Asia</td>
      <td>0.01</td>
      <td>0.83</td>
      <td>0.61</td>
      <td>1.28</td>
      <td>2.06</td>
      <td>4.8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Africa and West Asia</td>
      <td>0.67</td>
      <td>3.59</td>
      <td>1.02</td>
      <td>3.04</td>
      <td>6.57</td>
      <td>14.9</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Other Developing Countries</td>
      <td>0.07</td>
      <td>4.34</td>
      <td>9.25</td>
      <td>4.19</td>
      <td>19.36</td>
      <td>37.2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>All Developing Countries</td>
      <td>0.74</td>
      <td>7.93</td>
      <td>10.27</td>
      <td>7.23</td>
      <td>25.94</td>
      <td>52.1</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="italic">Note:</span> Additional investments are specified only in developing countries.
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0290" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To achieve the additional productivity enhancements projected in the COMP scenario illustrated in 
  <a rid="f0020" ref-type="fig" href="#f0020">Fig. 4</a>, total CGIAR investments in agricultural R&amp;D would start to diverge from the baseline in 2015, increasing to more than $3.1 billion by 2030, almost double the investment level in 2030 in the baseline scenario ($1.7 billion) (
  <a rid="f0025" ref-type="fig" href="#f0025">Fig. 5</a>). This amounts to an average annual investment of $0.74 billion per year in additional investments in CGIAR research. These investment increases will not be uniform across regions, with nearly 90 percent of additional investments ($0.67 billion per year) needed in SSA.
  <div id="f0025" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>CGIAR investment streams in the COMP and Baseline scenarios (billion 2005 USD).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="gr5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0295" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plausible investments in agricultural research to boost yields by 2030 will not be sufficient to eliminate hunger in Africa. Additional investments to improve the productive capacity of agriculture and boost the sector’s efficiency will be required. These investments are also critical towards improving the sustainability of the agriculture sector ensuring that gains achieved by 2030 can be maintained moving further into the 21st century. The additional agricultural investments considered in this analysis include investments to improving the capacity of water resource management (more efficient irrigation technologies, implementation of soil water management technologies), as well as further expansion of irrigation beyond the assumed expansion in the baseline.</p>
 <p id="p0300" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The additional investments needed to expand irrigation, and improve water resource management throughout the developing world are significant, more than $25 billion per year (columns 2–4 in 
  <a rid="t0025" ref-type="table" href="#t0025">Table 5</a>), nearly doubling baseline investments for irrigation expansion (
  <a rid="t0020" ref-type="table" href="#t0020">Table 4</a>). About $7.7 billion, or about 31 percent, of this additional investment will be in Africa and West Asia. Most of this investment in Africa and West Asia will be in irrigation expansion ($3.6 billion, 47 percent) and soil management ($3 billion, 40 percent). Within this region almost two thirds of the investments are concentrated in SSA.
 </p>
 <p id="p0305" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agricultural markets throughout the developing world suffer from market inefficiencies due to poor infrastructure. To reduce these inefficiencies, and thereby reduce transportation and marketing costs it is necessary to invest in building new infrastructure as well as improving and maintaining current infrastructure. These investments enhance productivity along the value chain, increase the speed of moving commodities to markets while also improving storage capacity, all of which improve market efficiency by better matching supply and demand over time. In this scenario, infrastructure investments focus on expanding and improving energy and transportation infrastructure. The cost of infrastructure investments is based on 
  <a rid="b0435" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0435">Rosegrant et al. (2018)</a>, where infrastructure investments across the developing world in road network expansion and improvement, rail expansion, and increased electrification were estimated to cost almost $26 billion per year between 2015 and 2030. Investments in Africa and West Asia account for about $6.6 billion (25 percent) of the total infrastructure investments with the majority dedicated to the improvement of road connections.
 </p>
</sec>
