<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0040" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comprehensive agricultural investment scenario assumptions</div>
 <p id="p0215" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third scenario presented is a comprehensive investment scenario (
  <span class="bold">COMP</span>) for agriculture and the rural sector, which combines investments in agricultural research, resource management, and infrastructure in developing countries. This scenario is drawn from related work (
  <a rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0445">Rosegrant et al., 2017</a>) assessing the potential impact of various investment levels across the CGIAR on agricultural development and sustainability.
 </p>
 <p id="p0220" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> scenario was selected for this analysis for three main reasons. First, it responds to the question of what outcomes could be achieved through increased public funding to agricultural R&amp;D. The CGIAR has a long history of successfully converting research into agricultural and economic development (
  <a rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0105">Evenson and Rosegrant, 2003</a>, 
  <a rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0390">Renkow and Byerlee, 2010</a>) and this scenario builds on this network having been developed jointly with experts across the CGIAR system and embodies an optimistic, but plausible, scenario of the potential for improvements to the agricultural sector in a future with higher investments. Second, the investments represented in this scenario are well suited to responding to the problem of underinvestment in public goods technologies, in which the CGIAR specializes. 
  <a rid="b0490" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0490">Tassey (2005)</a> identified the four primary causes of underinvestment as: 1) technical complexity; 2) long time horizons between investments and returns; 3) challenges of scale and scope of research; and 4) leakages. The CGIAR specializes in the provision of global goods technologies and the heart of its mission is to work on the types of research most likely to see underinvestment. It also plays a critical role in developing and helping diffuse technologies by building regional research capacity that, in turn, should increase the region’s ability to absorb new technologies (
  <a rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0005">Aghion &amp; Jaravel, 2015</a>). Third, with limited knowledge of what the future will bring, we believed it was better to look at a scenario that would help prepare for the future (
  <a rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0350">Nordmann, 2014</a>, 
  <a rid="b0545" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0545">Vervoort and Gupta, 2018</a>), instead of trying to predict the “best path forward.” Given the broad future uncertainty, we also believed it reasonable to follow portfolio theory and consider a broad and diversified mix of investments (
  <a rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0290">Markowitz, 1952</a>, 
  <a rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0295">Markowitz, 1991</a>). The 
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> scenario is just such a mix, encompassing investments across the agriculture sector.
 </p>
 <p id="p0225" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the interventions specified in 
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> are assumed to begin after 2015, with the scenario projection horizon going to 2050. The 2030 results presented in the following sections show the outcomes of these interventions at the midpoint of the overall scenario. While we focus on investments in Africa, the analysis includes investments in all developing regions, recognizing the importance of spillovers in technology and market effects to eliminating hunger in any one region and the difficulty and high cost of trying to do so in isolation.
 </p>
 <p id="p0230" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> scenario considers the role of improving agricultural productivity throughout the developing world, focusing on the potential gains in reducing yield gaps from increased CGIAR investment in agricultural R&amp;D. The target yield improvements were quantified through consultations with CGIAR scientists on plausible yield gains from increases in research budgets. These yield gains were quantified for the developing world at the country level, differentiated across irrigated and rainfed systems, and incorporated knowledge on varying regional production levels and local research and extension capacity.
 </p>
 <p id="p0235" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="f0020" ref-type="fig" href="#f0020">Fig. 4</a> summarizes the target improvements in crop productivity globally and specifically in Africa. Agricultural productivity in Africa lags significantly behind the rest of the world and, therefore, the productivity gains possible in this region are significant in percentage terms. Africa in general is projected to be catching up with the rest of the world in the coming decades and productivity gains are generally projected to increase at a faster rate than the global average. Assuming some level of convergence may be optimistic, given that African cereal yields have not grown at a rate significantly faster than the global average since 1990 (
  <a rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0120">FAO, 2016a</a>), however it is consistent broadly with the SSP 2 narrative, which projects economic convergence (
  <a rid="t0010" ref-type="table" href="#t0010">Table 2</a>).
  <div id="f0020" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Target crop productivity improvements in Africa and globally by 2030 (percent change from the baseline climate change scenario, HGEM). 
     <span class="italic">Note:</span> These figures summarize productivity improvement assumptions in the COMP scenario. All productivity targets were specified at the country level and disaggregated by irrigated and rainfed management. The World value includes Africa.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="gr4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0240" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> also considers the critical role of water in sustainable intensification of the global food system. Expanding the area equipped for irrigation is a powerful option in terms of both increasing crop yields as well as reducing the risk of production volatility due to changing weather. At the same time, however, water can be a scarce resource and the expansion of irrigation in a sustainable fashion requires investments in water use efficiency. Water use efficiency investments in all targeted regions increases efficiency by 15 percentage points. 
  <a rid="t0015" ref-type="table" href="#t0015">Table 3</a> summarizes the targeted increases in irrigated area, water use efficiency, and soil water availability.
  <div id="t0015" position="float" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Scenarios target increases by 2030 in irrigated area and soil water availability, by region (percent increase relative to baseline).</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Region</th>
      <th>Irrigated area</th>
      <th>Water use efficiency</th>
      <th>Soil water availability</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Africa South of the Sahara</td>
      <td>30</td>
      <td>30</td>
      <td>15</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>North Africa and West Asia</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>25</td>
      <td>5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Africa and West Asia</td>
      <td>13</td>
      <td>27</td>
      <td>14</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Other Developing Countries</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>25</td>
      <td>6</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>All Developing Countries</td>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>25</td>
      <td>8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>World</td>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>20</td>
      <td>6</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0245" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High transportation and marketing costs reduce the potential revenues that producers can make while increasing the prices that consumers face. The 
  <span class="bold">COMP</span> scenario also includes investments in improvements to transportation (roads, rail, and ports) and energy infrastructure (expansion and improvement of electrical network), which are major constraints to transportation and storage of agricultural production. These scenario assumptions were represented as declines in the price wedges between the farm-gate price and the prices consumers face.
 </p>
</sec>
