<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Rather than through overt acts of racial discrimination, structural racism creates racial disparities in educational attainment, income, and wealth in more subtle ways by perpetuating uneven access to resources (Bonilla‐Silva, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>; Lopez, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Omi &amp; Winant, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Shearer, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012b</xref>). Structural racism, involving “the totality of the social relations and practices that reinforce white privilege” (Bonilla‐Silva, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>, p. 9), contributes to increased vulnerability among U.S. nonwhite populations. In the United States, white households earned 65% more income and possessed 13 times greater wealth in 2014 than African American households (Pew Research Center, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), which were more likely than white households to suffer home foreclosure following the 2009 recession (Rugh &amp; Massey, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Such disparities can lead to color‐blind adaptation planning in practice, which, in the United States, further exacerbates inequalities in access to the resources needed to adapt to a changing climate (Hardy, Milligan, &amp; Heynen, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). On the Eastern Shore of the Chesapeake Bay, the social and political isolation of three African American communities reduced their access to resources that could be used to adapt to frequent flooding, as well as their representation in government decision making (Miller Hesed &amp; Paolisso, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Efforts to reduce vulnerability, therefore, can benefit from attention to differences of populations along lines of race, class, gender, ethnicity, and other axes of social difference. In non‐U.S. contexts, similar but regionally specific social processes can lead to inequitable adaptation planning (Graham, Barnett, Fincher, Mortreux, &amp; Hurlimann, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Sultana, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0159" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
