<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Slow temperature variations over Quaternary glacial-interglacial cycles have been dictated by changes in Earth’s orbital obliquity, precession, and eccentricity, as well as slow feedbacks involving atmospheric composition and ice sheets. Although questions remain surrounding the interaction between orbital forcing and greenhouse gas and ice sheet dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, the present research focuses on the climate’s direct short-term response to orbital forcing, which has been explored to varying degrees in past research
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Primarily, this paper focuses on the climate response to obliquity, or the axial tilt of the earth, which varies by up to ~2.5° with a period of 40 ka.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in Earth’s obliquity affect the latitudinal and seasonal distribution of insolation. Because this forcing is well known, it presents a good target to explore the climate system’s response. Reduced obliquity results in positive annual mean insolation anomalies in the tropics while higher latitudes have increased insolation in winter and strongly decreased insolation in summer (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> in ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>). These anomalies amplify the annual mean equator-to-pole insolation gradient and diminish the seasonal insolation cycle in both hemispheres. Unlike precession, obliquity’s seasonally-varying insolation anomalies do not locally sum to zero in the annual mean.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modeled temperature response to obliquity. Annual mean surface air temperature anomaly (°C) for 
     <span class="bold">a</span> CM2.1, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> CESM, and 
     <span class="bold">c</span> HadCM3 for the low–high obliquity experiments. Annual, zonal-mean anomalies for 
     <span class="bold">d</span> surface air temperature and 
     <span class="bold">e</span> insolation. In (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), hatching indicates anomalies which are not significant at a 0.05 level according to a two-tailed 
     <span class="italic">t</span>-test (i.e., the means of the two 100-year model outputs are not found to be significantly different). Surface air temperature is calculated at 2 m for CM2.1 and CESM and 1.5 m for HadCM3. Global mean temperature anomalies are −0.54 °C for CM2.1, −1.07 °C for CESM, and −0.48 °C for HadCM3
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_3800_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e394" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, the climate response to obliquity is explored in model experiments and proxies. Model results show larger temperature responses at high latitudes than low latitudes, helped by radiative feedbacks and heat transport. In order to compare these modeled climate responses to signals preserved in proxy records, a linear reconstruction methodology is employed in which the results of the single-forcing model experiments are scaled by past climate forcings to produce a time-varying estimate of past climate change based on the model results. Results show that the model-based linear reconstruction has a larger direct obliquity response in Antarctica than suggested by Antarctic ice cores. The mismatch between the linear reconstruction and Antarctic ice cores is diminished when the linear reconstruction is averaged over austral winter or spring, offering evidence for a seasonal bias in the Antarctic ice cores. A seasonal bias in the Antarctic ice cores would not dramatically alter the recording of climate signals due to ice sheets and greenhouse gases—which make up the bulk of the climate response—but could alter the apparent magnitude and timing of climate responses to orbital forcing, which has implications for our understanding of past climate.</p>
</sec>
