<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linear climate reconstructions</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the effects of each forcing in the past, and to allow for comparison with proxy time series data, a linear reconstruction methodology is employed. Model output from the single-forcing experiments is scaled by past forcings using an updated version of the method described in the appendix of
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>: anomalies from orbital experiments (consisting of simulations for high and low obliquity, simulations with precession at the two solstices and two equinoxes with increased eccentricity, and a simulation with zero eccentricity) are scaled by orbital parameters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>; Anomalies from the CO
  <sub>2</sub> experiment are scaled by the radiative forcing of CO
  <sub>2</sub> from a combined CO
  <sub>2</sub> record from EPICA Dome C and Vostok
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span> as well as the radiative forcing of CH
  <sub>4</sub> from EPICA Dome C
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>, computed according to the equations in Table 6.2 of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Third Assessment Report
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>; Anomalies from the ice sheet experiment are scaled by sea level changes, which is used as an analog for ice sheet volume. The sea level record is a stack of seven different sea level records computed using different methods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. Potentially, uncertainties in the magnitude of obliquity variability in the sea level record could affect the results of this paper, especially if obliquity variations unrelated to sea level are also being recorded in the sea level record. However, the use of a multi-record stack rather than an individual sea level record should help reduce the impact of potential uncertainties in any particular method. It should also be noted that the climate response to ice sheets may relate to both ice sheet area and volume, but a linear scaling with sea level has been used here for simplicity. An additional source of uncertainty concerns the timing of individual ice sheet changes relative to the global mean sea level record. In the present work, the linear reconstruction assumes that all ice sheets vary synchronously with the global mean sea level record. However, evidence suggests that after the LGM, at least, Antarctic ice melt may have lagged considerably behind the global sea level changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Differences between the timing or characteristics of Antarctic ice sheet changes and global sea level anomalies could affect results of this analysis, especially considering that orbital-scale variations are present in the sea level curve (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>).  Also note that the global mean sea level curve contains precession-scale variability approximately in line with Northern Hemisphere summer insolation; this means that the precession signal in the linear reconstruction is already largely in phase with the Antarctic ice core signals, even in the annual mean reconstruction (Supplementary Figs. 6-8).  While it is unclear how realistic this is, the seasonal averaging of the linear reconstruction still generally shifts the timing of the direct precession signal and reduces mismatch in the current analysis.  Furthermore, without quantitative knowledge of the ice sheet differences over the past few glacial periods, it is unclear how to account for this limitation in the present work. Finally, regarding greenhouse gases, by treating CH
  <sub>4</sub> as an equivalent amount of radiative forcing due to CO
  <sub>2</sub>, the effect of CH
  <sub>4</sub> can be approximated without the need for a dedicated CH
  <sub>4</sub> simulation, which can be computationally expensive. The sea level stack was already aligned to LR04, and the other forcing time series (CO
  <sub>2</sub>, CH
  <sub>4</sub>, and orbit) are left on their published age models.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The computed 'linear reconstructions' estimate the contribution of individual forcings in producing past climate change, and can be summed together to compute a model-based estimate of total temperature change at any location. The linear reconstruction methodology used here has been updated from previous work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> primarily in four ways: a slightly different data set of orbital parameters is used here (we use the same data set that was used to align the LR04 benthic stack)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>, greenhouse gas values from EPICA Dome C/Vostok are used instead of those from Vostok alone, a sea level stack is used rather than a single record, and linear reconstruction anomalies are computed relative to the preindustrial simulation rather than a zero eccentricity state.
 </p>
</sec>
