<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Short-lived mammalian species, like the red squirrel, have the advantage of fast generation times, which may improve their chance of survival as each generation provides scope for micro-evolution.
 <xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">70</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">77</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">78</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">99</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">100</sup>
 </xref> Conversely, large mammals with long generation times, and indeed those small mammal species, like bats, which have long generation times, are predicted to have less ability to respond genetically to any new selective pressures,
 <xref rid="R101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">101</sup>
 </xref> making them more susceptible to extinction
 <xref rid="R102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">102</sup>
 </xref> than are species with short generation times. The issue is compounded because large species have greater range requirements.
 <xref rid="R103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">103</sup>
 </xref> There are many species of mammals with longevities such that individuals alive now ought still to be alive in 2030, and a few species for which individuals alive now could be alive in 2100.
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">8</sup>
 </xref> Clearly, the survival of those individuals, and probably those species, cannot depend on genetic adaptation. Instead, for those that also cannot shift their ranges, survival is likely to be entirely dependent on sufficient phenotypic plasticity to buffer effects of climate change.
</p>
