<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">High temperatures can increase the occurrence of heart attacks and strokes in susceptible patients because of increased blood viscosity (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>). Heat can induce events such as heart failure or stroke. Proposed mechanisms between heat and cardiovascular mortality include increased surface blood circulation and sweating. This leads to increased cardiac workload, dehydration and salt depletion, haemoconcentration, elevated blood viscosity, and the risk of thrombosis (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>) Moreover, heat stress was suggested to induce the release of interleukins modulating local and systemic acute inflammatory responses (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>). These inflammatory responses can result in heart failure by increasing damage to heart tissue and inflammation (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>). Significant increases in extreme heat are projected to continue in coming decades, consistent with observed global trends in past decades (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>). The A2 scenario was selected to cover a wide range of temperature rise. This scenario family describes a very heterogeneous world. The use of other scenarios can provide the possibility of comparing and estimating diverse more conditions future. The underlying theme is self-reliance and preservation of local identities. Fertility patterns across regions converge very slowly, which results in continuously increasing global population. Economic development is primarily regionally oriented and per capita, economic growth and technological change are more fragmented and slower than in other storylines (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>). In the next decades, temperature increases and the frequency of hot days will also increase. These results suggest that more CVD mortality can be expected in the future.
</p>
