<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="simple" class="list">
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
  <p class="p">The incorporation of invertebrate responses in the design of current and future precipitation manipulation experiments: invertebrate responses remain under-studied in rainfall manipulation experiments, with the majority of studies considering only the responses of plants to short-term rainfall alterations of limited scope – altered frequency scenarios, for instance, remain critically under-represented (
   <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Johnson et al., 2016</xref>). This under-representation, coupled with the idiosyncratic nature of the responses detailed to date, makes it difficult to identify solid trends and predict how grasslands will respond to a wide range of precipitation scenarios. Achieving such a goal will require an increased number of studies from which to draw patterns from, across a broader range of precipitation scenarios.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <label class="label">(2)</label>
  <p class="p">A focus on long-term studies: aside from the identities of the different components of the system, the timescale over which precipitation alterations are studied may also be important. The relatively short term nature of many field experiments to date obfuscates our ability to make more realistic predictions about how grassland communities will respond to future changes (
   <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beier et al., 2012</xref>). Such studies are needed in order to capture changes in the direction of responses over time and lags in the manifestation of responses – particularly given the potential for short-term studies to have misleading results compared with those over longer timescales (
   <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Suttle et al., 2007</xref>; 
   <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wilcox et al., 2016</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <label class="label">(3)</label>
  <p class="p">Greater geographical representation: this should be prioritized to determine the extent to which findings can be extrapolated across different biomes (the studies we review here are mostly from the UK and USA; 
   <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beier et al., 2012</xref>; 
   <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">White et al., 2012</xref>). Given how many plant and insect responses are likely to depend on the underlying water-status of the system, research across ecotypes will be an essential target for enabling progress the field.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <label class="label">(4)</label>
  <p class="p">Examination of multiple climate factors at once: there is a need for experiments reflecting the reality of global change which will involve the simultaneous alterations of many factors (
   <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Villalpando et al., 2009</xref>; 
   <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beier et al., 2012</xref>). This is especially important given the potential for synergisms between factors, as may be expected between increased temperatures and reduced water availability. On the other hand, the effects of one factor may serve to moderate those of another (e.g., 
   <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lee et al., 2014</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
