<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Social bases of energy and climate opinions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Decades of survey research on the social bases of environmental concern has established robust patterns with regard to respondent age, sex, education and politics. Concern about environmental problems, across many different topics, tends to be higher among younger, female and better educated respondents. In some data one or more of these effects may be relatively weak or not significant, but they almost always point in the same direction. The most consistently dominant predictors of environmental concern, however, are ideology or political identity: conservatives less often view environmental problems as serious.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g003" href="#pone.0217608.g003">Fig 3</a>
  </span> and 
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g004" href="#pone.0217608.g004">Fig 4</a>
  </span> show that these propositions apply to views on renewable energy and climate change. In each figure the (a) panels depicts 2018 New Hampshire data, and the (b) panels the 2018 Oregon data. Generally similar results also occurred in the North Country and nationwide surveys, and in earlier years from the New Hampshire and Oregon projects (not shown). Younger, female and better educated respondents more often prioritize renewable energy, and more often agree that humans are changing Earth’s climate. Across each of these four panels, ideological or political indicators have by far the strongest effects, with liberal-conservative or Democrat-Republican gaps of 53 or 44 points on renewable energy, and 71 or 50 points on climate. Age differences are less strong but also consistent, with young versus old gaps of 13 or 17 points on renewable energy, and 16 or 22 points on climate.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Weighted percentages for “renewable energy higher priority” broken down by respondent age, sex, education and ideology or party on surveys conducted in 2018: (a) statewide New Hampshire, and (b) northeast Oregon.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Weighted percentages for “climate change happening now, caused mainly by human activities” broken down by respondent age, sex, education and ideology or party on surveys conducted in 2018: (a) statewide New Hampshire, and (b) northeast Oregon.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g003" href="#pone.0217608.g003">3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g004" href="#pone.0217608.g004">4</a> confirm that in 2018, renewable-energy and climate-change views have similar demographic predictors, which resemble those known for many other environment-related topics. Both exhibit steep political gradients, and milder but also significant age gradients. In detail, this four-way comparison reveals something else. Although the ideological or partisan gaps regarding renewable energy on both surveys are wide, they are less wide than the corresponding gaps regarding climate change. So renewable energy opinions do strongly correlate with politics, but not as strongly as climate-change opinions—as inferred indirectly from regional comparisons in Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g001" href="#pone.0217608.g001">1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g002" href="#pone.0217608.g002">2</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
