<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Four survey projects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analyzed here come from four projects summarized in 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0217608.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0217608.t001">Table 1</a>
  </span>. For each project, trained personnel at the Survey Center of the University of New Hampshire conducted cell and landline telephone interviews with randomly-sampled participants. The nationwide POLES survey took place in two stages just before and after the 2016 presidential elections, with little difference in the main response patterns.[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref023">23</a>] The North Country survey took place in summer 2017, interviewing residents of four rural counties in northern New England.[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref024">24</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref025">25</a>] Two other regional projects, covering New Hampshire and northeast Oregon, each involved a series of surveys carried out with independent random samples from 2010 or 2011 to 2018. Many papers present results from the various Oregon surveys up to 2015 [
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref026">26</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref027">27</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref028">28</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref029">29</a>], and New Hampshire surveys up to 2017.[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref030">30</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref031">31</a>] Results from the 2018 Oregon and New Hampshire surveys are described for the first time in this paper.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.t001</span>
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Four survey projects.</div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0217608.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0217608.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Polar</span>, 
       <span class="italic">Environment</span>, 
       <span class="italic">and Science</span> (POLES, nationwide). The POLES survey involved random-sample telephone interviews (cell and landline) with respondents from all US states, carried out in two stages: before the 2016 presidential elections (August, 
       <span class="italic">n</span> = 704) and immediately afterwards (November/December, 
       <span class="italic">n</span> = 707). Response rates in four subsamples of the POLES survey ranged from 15 to 30%, calculated by AAPOR definition 3.[
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref032">32</a>] Several papers have focused on POLES results.[
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref033">33</a>][
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref034">34</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Granite State Poll</span> (GSP, New Hampshire statewide). These landline and cell telephone surveys interview independent, statewide random samples of New Hampshire residents four times each year. Along with standard background and political questions, the GSP often carries items about environment or science. New Hampshire responses on environmental questions commonly fall close to national benchmarks. Several recent papers make comparisons between New Hampshire and nationwide surveys.[
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref014">14</a>][
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref035">35</a>] The GSP from April 2010 to October 2018 conducted 20,786 interviews that included our climate-change question, and from July 2012 to October 2018 conducted 7,707 with the question about renewable energy. Median response rate over this period was 21.5 percent.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Communities and Forests in Oregon</span> (CAFOR, northeast Oregon). Under the CAFOR project, landline and cell telephone surveys involving independent random samples of northeast Oregon residents were conducted in four stages: September/October 2011 (
       <span class="italic">n</span> = 1,585 from Baker, Union and Wallowa Counties); August/October 2014 (
       <span class="italic">n</span> = 1,752, from the same three counties along with Crook, Grant, Umatilla and Wheeler Counties); October/November 2015 (
       <span class="italic">n</span> = 651, repeating the seven counties from 2014); and September 2018 (
       <span class="italic">n</span> = 1,097) in just the three original counties. Median response rate of the CAFOR surveys was 38 percent. For consistency, our analysis in this paper focuses on 3,782 interviews from only those counties (Baker, Union and Wallowa) that were surveyed in all four years. Voting patterns in all of these northeast Oregon counties tend to be politically conservative, and surveys find lower-than-national recognition of anthropogenic climate change.[
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref014">14</a>][
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref023">23</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">North Country</span> (northern New England). In summer 2017, researchers with the Carsey School of Public Policy (University of New Hampshire) conducted this random-sample cell and landline telephone survey of 1,650 residents in four contiguous northern New England counties, collectively termed the North Country: Coös and Grafton Counties, New Hampshire; Essex County, Vermont; and Oxford County, Maine. Designed to assess changes in residents’ perceptions of their rural communities, the 2017 survey (response rate of 19%) replicated some questions from earlier surveys, but also included new environmental and climate items. Some results are analyzed in papers by Hamilton et al.[
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref024">24</a>][
       <a rid="pone.0217608.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref025">25</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With each individual survey, probability weights were calculated for adjustments toward more representative results. Following standard formulas, the weights compensate for potential bias arising from sampling design (household size; number of phones in each household; deliberate oversampling of smaller areas or subpopulations of interest) or from differential responses with respect to population age/sex distributions of the places being polled at that time. Consequently, after weighting the results should reasonably represent target populations. Effects of this weighting tend to be substantively minor. For example, support for renewable energy development among POLES respondents equals 67 percent before weighting and 72 percent after; among North Country respondents the corresponding results are 75 percent before and 78 percent after. Weighted results, which better represent regional or nationwide populations, appear in all tables and graphs of this paper.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although research objectives varied across projects, and to a lesser extent across stages within each project, many surveys carried two standard questions asking about renewable energy and climate change. 
  <span class="bold">
   <a rid="pone.0217608.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0217608.t002">Table 2</a>
  </span> gives the wording of these 
  <span class="italic">renew</span> and 
  <span class="italic">climate</span> questions, along with codes used for modeling later. The surveys asked also about respondent background characteristics, for the most part with identical wording. One exception is that the New Hampshire surveys asked respondents for their ideological identification, here coded from –2 (extremely or fairly liberal) to +2 (extremely or fairly conservative). The Oregon surveys recorded political party identification but not ideology, so our analysis employs a simple three-party scheme from –1 (Democrat) to +1 (Republican) with these data. Political and education variables are centered at zero for use with interaction terms later. 
  <a rid="pone.0217608.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0217608.t002">Table 2</a> summarizes the independent variables as well.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.t002</span>
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Energy, climate change and background questions asked on multiple iterations of the New Hampshire Granite State Poll (GSP) and northeast Oregon Communities and Forests in Oregon (CAFOR) surveys over 2010 or 2011 to 2018; on two iterations of the nationwide POLES survey in 2016; and on the one-time North Country survey in 2017.</div>
   <p>Shown with codes used for logit regression analyses in 
    <a rid="pone.0217608.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0217608.t003">Table 3</a>. Order of response choices for 
    <span class="italic">renew</span> and 
    <span class="italic">climate</span> were rotated across interviews.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0217608.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0217608.t002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Renew</span>—Which do you think should be a higher priority for the future of this country, increased exploration and drilling for oil, or increased use of renewable energy such as [tidal,] wind or solar? Reference to tidal energy occurred only in the New Hampshire surveys, although tests indicate that this word made no difference.
       <span class="break"/>Increased use of renewable energy such as [tidal,] wind or solar (1)
       <span class="break"/>Increased exploration and drilling for oil (0)
       <span class="break"/>don’t know/no answer (0)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Climate</span>—Which of the following three statements do you think is more accurate?
       <span class="break"/>Climate change is happening now, caused mainly by human activities (1)
       <span class="break"/>Climate change is happening now, but caused mainly by natural forces (0)
       <span class="break"/>Climate change is not happening now (0)
       <span class="break"/>Don’t know/no answer (0)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Age</span>—Respondent’s age in years
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Sex</span>—Male (0) or female (1)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Education</span>—High school or less (–1), some college or technical school (0), college graduate (1), or postgraduate (2)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Ideology</span> (New Hampshire GSP surveys)—Extremely or fairly liberal (–2), somewhat or leaning liberal (–1), moderate not leaning (0), somewhat or leaning conservative (1), extremely or fairly conservative (2)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Party</span> (Oregon CAFOR surveys)—Democrat (–1), Independent (0), Republican (1)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Year</span>—Year of survey, from 2010 (New Hampshire) or 2011 (Oregon) to 2018
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the New Hampshire and Oregon series, as will be seen, response patterns on the renewable energy and climate questions both changed over time. 
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g001" href="#pone.0217608.g001">Fig 1</a>
  </span> charts responses to renewable-energy (
  <span class="italic">renew</span>) responses from the most recent year of each project: 2016 for the US POLES survey, 2017 for North Country, or 2018 for northeast Oregon and New Hampshire. Large majorities of the respondents on each survey, between 64 and 82 percent, consider increased use of renewable energy to be a higher priority. The lowest number, 64 percent favoring renewable energy, represents northeast Oregon—politically a very conservative region, where 67 to 73 percent of the voters in each county supported Trump in 2016. Despite that region’s general conservativism, support for renewable energy is only 8 points lower in northeast Oregon than it is nationwide (64 versus 72).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Should increased exploration and drilling for oil, or increased use of renewable energy such as wind or solar, be a higher priority for the future of this country?</div>
   <p>Results from the most recent years of four survey projects.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two highest values in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g001" href="#pone.0217608.g001">Fig 1</a>, 78 or 82 percent favoring renewable energy, represent recent surveys in comparatively moderate and mixed regions: the North Country (counties voting from 38 to 57 percent for Trump) or New Hampshire (counties voting from 38 to 56 percent for Trump). The 
  <span class="italic">renew</span> response “Increased exploration and drilling for oil” echoes a campaign slogan—“Drill, baby, drill”—popularized by Republicans during the 2008 US presidential race, then revived in 2012 and 2016. Despite substantial Republican presence in every region assessed, this response was chosen by less than a quarter of the respondents.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g002" href="#pone.0217608.g002">Fig 2</a>
  </span> charts response to the climate-change question (
  <span class="italic">climate</span>) in parallel fashion. Again, only the most recent years of each project are shown; in New Hampshire the 
  <span class="italic">climate</span> question was asked more frequently than 
  <span class="italic">renew</span>, so we have more observations. US, New Hampshire and North Country results are quite similar: 64 to 67 percent agreeing with the scientific consensus that climate change is happening now, caused mainly by human activities. In contrast, fewer than half of the northeast Oregon respondents (48 percent) accept this consensus. The gap between northeast Oregon and US views on this item is 16 points (48 vs. 64), double what we saw on renewable energy. The Oregon respondents are comparatively more likely than nationwide or other regional respondents to think climate is changing mainly for natural reasons (38 percent) or even that it is not changing (6 percent), despite summer warming that has worsened the wildfires affecting their region.[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref028">28</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref029">29</a>]
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Is climate change happening now, caused mainly by human activities?</div>
   <p>Is it happening now, but caused mainly by natural forces? Or is climate change not happening now? Results from the most recent years of four survey projects.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparisons between renewable-energy and climate-change views in Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g001" href="#pone.0217608.g001">1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g002" href="#pone.0217608.g002">2</a> suggest that renewable energy development is viewed favorably by many people who do not believe that human activities are changing the climate. Moreover, the aggregate results imply that renewable energy views correlate less strongly with politics. The next section tests this inference directly, and explores how other characteristics correlate with these views.
 </p>
</sec>
