<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Trends over time</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 2012 through fall of 2018, 13 New Hampshire surveys with a combined total of 7,707 interviews carried the renewable-energy question, as did four northeast Oregon surveys (2011–2018) with 3,782 interviews. 
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" href="#pone.0217608.g005">Fig 5</a>
  </span> tracks these regional-survey results, along with results on the same question from the POLES and North Country surveys. Unlike Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g001" href="#pone.0217608.g001">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g004" href="#pone.0217608.g004">4</a> which depict only the most recent years of each project, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" href="#pone.0217608.g005">Fig 5</a> and subsequent graphs employ all available data for the analysis shown. The number of observations fluctuates, because some questions were not asked on some surveys. The upper line in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" href="#pone.0217608.g005">Fig 5</a>, drifting up about 21 points, tracks the percentage of New Hampshire respondents who prioritize renewable energy. The lower line shows an upward drift of about 14 points among northeast Oregon respondents. Nationwide results from the POLES surveys (1,411 interviews) appear slightly lower than contemporary New Hampshire results; North Country results (1,650 interviews) match New Hampshire almost exactly. Error bars depict the 95 percent confidence intervals for each survey. We see minor survey-to-survey variations, within the range of sampling error, but the main visual impression is how stable percentages appear, from one survey to the next. Their short-term stability reflects use of consistent sampling and interview methods, repeating a straightforward question. An earlier paper based on Oregon data through 2015 and New Hampshire through 2017 observed similar upward trends,[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref023">23</a>] which are now seen continuing in these longer time series.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Weighted percentages and 95 percent confidence intervals for “renewable energy higher priority” on two nationwide and 18 regional (New Hampshire, North Country or northeast Oregon) surveys.</div>
   <p>Combined 
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 14,550.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have more data on the climate-change question, which was asked on the same POLES, northeast Oregon and North Country surveys, but also on other nationwide surveys in 2011, 2012 and 2014, along with 35 New Hampshire surveys 2010–2018. 
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g006" href="#pone.0217608.g006">Fig 6</a>
  </span> tracks these regional and national results. On climate change, New Hampshire public opinion is never far from national opinion, and might be viewed as a reasonable proxy. Hamilton et al. describe the older national surveys in more detail, and tracked New Hampshire results through spring of 2015.[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref014">14</a>] 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g006" href="#pone.0217608.g006">Fig 6</a> updates that analysis with data from POLES 2016, North Country 2017, and New Hampshire and Oregon through 2018. This graph also notes some major events that were widely proposed, at the time, to potentially shift public opinion on climate change. The most recent such events in this timeline are the disastrous US hurricane seasons of 2017 (Harvey, Irma and Maria) and 2018 (Florence and Michael). But these hurricane seasons, like the earlier events of Hurricane Sandy (2012), the IPCC 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> report (2013), and Pope Francis’ encyclical on climate change (2015), produce no visible change. Together with science communication, however, such events might contribute to the cumulative rise.[
  <a rid="pone.0217608.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217608.ref035">35</a>]
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Weighted percentages and 95 percent confidence intervals for “climate change happening now, caused mainly by human activities” on five nationwide and 40 regional surveys.</div>
   <p>Combined 
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 31,932.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both the renewable-energy results in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" href="#pone.0217608.g005">Fig 5</a> and the climate-change results in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g006" href="#pone.0217608.g006">Fig 6</a> exhibit minor survey-to-survey fluctuations, within sampling error bars. Overall, however, they show substantial consistency around upward trends. Northeast Oregon acceptance of ACC remains well below national or northeastern levels, but drifts similarly upward over this period. Multivariate analysis will later establish that the trends of both Oregon and New Hampshire series in Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" href="#pone.0217608.g005">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g006" href="#pone.0217608.g006">6</a> are statistically significant.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Replication of the overall percentages seen in Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" href="#pone.0217608.g005">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g006" href="#pone.0217608.g006">6</a> extend to more detailed analyses as well, although sample-to-sample variation increases as we look at smaller subsamples. For example, 
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g007" href="#pone.0217608.g007">Fig 7</a>
  </span> tracks climate-change percentages separately for each political party, across 34 New Hampshire surveys. The four parties exhibit roughly parallel upward trends. Separation into five levels of ideology from liberal to conservative (not shown) paints a similar picture as well.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Weighted percentages “climate change happening now, caused mainly by human activities,” by respondent political party on 34 New Hampshire surveys.</div>
   <p>Combined 
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 19,020.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g008" href="#pone.0217608.g008">Fig 8</a>
  </span> shows a different breakdown, graphing New Hampshire renewable energy (13 surveys) and climate change (35 surveys) trends separately by age group. Linear trends rather than separate data points are depicted because survey-to-survey variations in mall subsamples otherwise make the graphs hard to read. The pro-environmental or scientific positions within each age group nevertheless show clear upward trends. Millennials, roughly age 18 to 39, stand apart at the top of each panel: they are consistently more likely than older groups to favor renewable energy, or to think that humans are changing the climate. Moreover, support among Millennials has been rising steadily: now past 90 percent on energy and 75 percent on climate.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Linear (ordinary least squares) trends by age group on statewide New Hampshire surveys for (a) “renewable energy higher priority” 2012–2018, or (b) “climate change happening now, caused mainly by human activities” 2010–2018.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents 65 and older start out this period below anyone else, but their trends climb upward as well, reaching 75 percent on energy and 60 percent on climate. Toward the end of this period, in both panels there appears to be some convergence of old and middle-aged respondents. Middle-aged percentages start halfway between young and old, but rise less steeply than the others.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <span class="bold">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g009" href="#pone.0217608.g009">Fig 9</a>
  </span> we calculate the corresponding age-group trends from Oregon data. The wider gap between renewable-energy and climate views in this region is obvious from the different height of lines in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g009" href="#pone.0217608.g009">Fig 9A and 9B</a>. Renewable energy support also rises more steeply than ACC acceptance. A tertiary detail, in which Oregon results echo New Hampshire, is the apparent convergence of middle-aged and older views, as middle-aged views rise less steeply.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217608.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217608.g009</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Linear (ordinary least squares) trends by age group on northeast Oregon surveys 2011–2018, for (a) “renewable energy higher priority”, or (b) “climate change happening now, caused mainly by human activities”.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217608.g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
