<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In order to facilitate the simultaneous quantification of gross rates of all major N turnover processes in the beech-soil-microbe system, the intact soil-root-mesocosms were labelled with either 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N/
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-enriched glutamine, 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> or 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>. To enable homogeneous distribution of isotopes in the root-soil system, we applied an isotope injection method developed for large soil cores [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] and optimized and adapted it for the Tuttlingen soil. For this purpose, we conducted pre-experiments in March 2011 using Brilliant Blue FCF colour dye instead of 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N enriched label solution. Various injection patterns and depths, numbers of injections per mesocosm and solution volumes per single injection were tested to achieve homogeneous 3-dimensional distribution of label solution in the soil-root-system at minimized amounts of injected liquid to minimize label artefacts such as stimulation of N turnover and leakage of labeled solution at the bottom of the beech-soil-mesocosms. In this pre-experiment, mesocosms were harvested one day after dye application by removing soil stepwise from bottom to top in layers of 2 cm. The distribution of the colour dye in the soil was monitored visually. Outflow at the bottom of the labelled beech-soil-mesocosms was examined by storing the beech-soil-mesocosms on white paper sheets. To inject dye and later 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N solution we used custom-made stainless steel side port cannulas with lasered depth check marks. In this labelling optimization experiment the following setup facilitated homogeneous colour dye distribution with only minimal leakage: 16 single amounts of 3 ml solution each were injected into the beech seedling-soil-mesocosms to a depth of 1 and 3 cm each, and another 8 injections of 3 ml each to a depth of 6 cm. Additionally, 10 ml of 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N-labelled solution were homogeneously spread on top of the soil surface. Hence, the total amount of added label solution was 130 ml, applied to 2.3 kg dry soil contained on average in the beech-soil-mesocosms. Paper calibres indicating injection patterns and depths were constructed to fit onto the stainless steel cylinders in order to ensure reproducible labelling. Before 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N-labelling, the litter layer was removed from the top of the soil surface and later replaced. An earlier study showed that the litter layer is of very minor significance for N nutrition of beech natural regeneration [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>].
</p>
