<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Change Scenarios</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change scenario data through years from 1981 to 2100 were obtained as the output from five global climate models (GCMs; CanESM2, CNRM-CM5, GFDL-CM3, HadGEM2-ES and MIROC5) from the fifth phase of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5; 
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">Meehl et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" href="#B123">Taylor et al., 2012</a>). We used output for climate models driven by three representative concentration pathways (RCPs), that lead to radiative forcing levels of 2.6, 4.5 and 8.5 W m
  <span class="sup">-2</span> by the end of the century (
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">Moss et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" href="#B131">Van Vuuren et al., 2011</a>). These pathways include one mitigation scenario (RCP2.6), one stabilization scenario (RCP4.5) and one high emission scenario (RCP8.5) (
  <a rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" href="#B131">Van Vuuren et al., 2011</a>). The resulting climate variables were down-scaled to a 0.2° × 0.1° longitude-latitude grid by a quantile-quantile type bias correction algorithm for daily mean temperature, relative humidity, shortwave radiation and wind speed (
  <a rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" href="#B105">Räisänen and Räty, 2013</a>) and parametric quantile mapping for daily precipitation (
  <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">Räty et al., 2014</a>). Gridded harmonized FMI meteorological data by 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">Aalto et al. (2013)</a> were used. Long-wave radiation data were interpolated by a bilinear interpolation method. Global mean CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations from the RCPs 2.6, 4.5 and 8.5 were linearly interpolated to monotonously increase through the calendar years. The changes of temperature and precipitation from a baseline period 1981–2010 to periods 2011–2040, 2041–2070, and 2071–2099 in Finland varied considerably between data from five down-scaled CMIP5 climate models (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). PREBAS was run with all three RCPs, while JSBACH input was taken from RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. The RCP8.5 output of HadGEM2-ES was not included in JSBACH runs.
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Annual and seasonal projected change in precipitation sum (%) versus change in mean temperature (°C) in Finland. Changes calculated from the reference period 1981–2010 to periods 2011–2040 (bottom), 2041–2070 (middle) and 2071–2100 (top) from regionally down-scaled data from simulations with three levels of climate forcing (RCP) driving five down-scaled CMIP5 global climate models (GCM). Seasons ANN annual (left), DFJ winter, MAM spring, JJA summer, and SON autumn (right).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpls-10-00343-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
