<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Provisioning Services: GPP and Supply of Harvestable Wood</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We aggregated the results from the two ecosystem models in order to account for the uncertainty inherent in the use of different assumptions, e.g., JSBACH simulations do not account for forest management. In this paper we focus on presenting the results on the whole-country level. Data on grid-based results of the biophysical variables for each ecosystem model and each climate scenario separately are available online (
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">Metadata, 2018a</a>,
  <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">b</a>). These online metadata descriptions include links to the Climateguide.fi service, where maps of the grid-based results can be found by selecting the category “Terrestrial ecosystems,” and the variable of interest “GPP,” “NEE,” etc. The maps are displaying results from each ecosystem model (JSBACH, PREBAS), climate model, and climate forcing level RCP separately. Seasonal patterns of GPP simulated by PREBAS and JSBACH aggregated to the national level were almost identical, and temporal trends of annual totals were also parallel. This is remarkable in light of earlier results, as ecosystem models tend to vary quite much in their GPP estimates globally and in the northern latitudes (
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Anav et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115">Shao et al., 2013</a>). However, it has to be noted that the current version of the JSBACH photosynthesis model has been modified for boreal conditions using partly the same empirical evidence as PREBAS (e.g., 
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">Mäkelä et al., 2004</a>; 
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">Kolari et al., 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change simulations of forest growth did not account for growth restrictions due to limited access to nutrients, mainly nitrogen or phosphorus. Forest growth in higher CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations may become nutrient limited in nutrient deficient sites (e.g., 
  <a rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" href="#B138">Wieder et al., 2015</a>). As PREBAS projections of future growth were made assuming current forest practices continue in the future (
  <a rid="B121" ref-type="bibr" href="#B121">Sved and Koistinen, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">Minunno et al., 2019</a>), here no provision was made for potential adaptive responses by the forest owners, e.g., aiming for more variation in stand structure, stand age or silvicultural management (
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">Blennow, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">Montoro Girona et al., 2017</a>), introducing new tree species or varieties (
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">Laakkonen et al., 2018</a>; 
  <a rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119">Sousa-Silva et al., 2018</a>), or striving to maximize positive synergies between ecosystem services (
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">Kuuluvainen and Gauthier, 2018</a>). Current total volume of growing tree stock in Finland is 2.5 billion m
  <span class="sup">3</span> with a total annual increment of 107 million m
  <span class="sup">3</span>, which corresponds to annual average 6.8 and 3.2 m
  <span class="sup">3</span> ha
  <span class="sup">-1</span> in southern and northern Finland, respectively. Total volume of roundwood harvested from forests was a record high 72.4 million m
  <span class="sup">3</span> in 2017, about 17% higher than the average of the preceding ten-year period (
  <a rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" href="#B128">Vaahtera et al., 2018</a>). Current forest policies in Finland aim to increase the annual cut to over 80 million m
  <span class="sup">3</span> in the next decades. Our simulations indicate that these plans could be feasible in a changing climate, however, increased cutting levels would also imply a lower growing stock than that in our simulations which assumed continuing the current harvest intensity. This would have further implications on C sequestration that need to be explored separately. We did not study the impact of climate change and cutting regimes on biodiversity indicators, such as the amount of dead wood, but others have found significant effects of bioenergy extraction on dead wood levels (e.g., 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">Hof et al., 2018</a>) and conflicting objectives of wood production and biodiversity conservation (
  <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">Mönkkönen et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Angelstam et al., 2019</a>). In their comprehensive review on the retention approach for forestry, 
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">Lindenmayer et al. (2012)</a> argued that the practice of permanently retaining significant elements of the original forest is crucial for maintaining multiple forest values, such as biodiversity and carbon stocks. Recently, partial harvest methods were found adequate for regeneration for sustainable forest management in Canadian boreal forests (
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">Montoro Girona et al., 2017</a>, 
  <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">2018</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
