<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Current global climate is approximately 0.85°C warmer than 100 years ago and has a projected increase of 1.5–2°C in the mean temperature by 2100 (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Pecl et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The resulting changes in the temperature and precipitation regimes have already led species: (a) to alter their physiology to tolerate warmer or drier conditions; (b) to change some of their crucial life cycle events to those period of favorable climate (e.g., the timing of breeding or migration); and (c) to shift their distributional ranges in order to track their usual and/or appropriate conditions in the space (Araújo &amp; Peterson, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Bellard, Bertelsmeier, Leadley, Thuiller, &amp; Courchamp, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Pecl et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). More worrying yet, some species that could not respond to the climate change effects by the three above‐mentioned alternatives have been reported extinct due to climate change direct effects (Pecl et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref> and references therein). Therefore, the community impacts of shifting species are recognized as one of the primary drivers of biodiversity loss (Sala et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>), although biodiversity gains generated by the redistribution and establishment of new native species also impact the structure of biological communities (Primack et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). The assessment of these climate change impacts on biodiversity mostly depends on extensive historical information of species distributions, which is unavailable or imprecise for most species in the biodiverse tropics. Therefore, the use of Ecological Niche Models (ENM; or Species Distribution Models: SDM; Araújo &amp; Peterson, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) has become a widely used tool to anticipate the climate change effects on species distribution of a wide range of taxa and also to generate conservation strategies based on a dynamic changing climate in different regions of the world (Araújo, Alagador, Cabeza, Nogués‐Bravo, &amp; Thuiller, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Aryal et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Cuevas‐Yáñez, Rivas, Muñoz, &amp; Córdoba‐Aguilar, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Fois, Cuena‐Lombraña, Fenu, Cogoni, &amp; Bacchetta, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Lemes &amp; Loyola, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
