<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although the use of ENMs to assess the impacts of climate change on the species distribution has been predominantly performed on a species‐specific basis (e.g., Martins, Silva, de Marco, &amp; Melo, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Nabout, Oliveira, Magalhães, Terribile, &amp; de Almeida, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Vasconcelos, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Vasconcelos &amp; Nascimento, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), there is an increasing use of ENMs to generate richness estimates from each species model of a given taxa when occurrence records are available for a high number of species (e.g., Brown &amp; Yoder, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; García‐Roselló et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Vasconcelos, Rodríguez, &amp; Hawkins, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In such cases, not only the species individual response is evaluated, but different community ecology metrics can be assessed regarding the influence of different climate change scenarios. The most common community ecology metric used is the alpha diversity (i.e., the richness values of the sampling units considered) (Jones &amp; Cheung, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Loyola et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). A less explored metric, which evaluates some different aspects of the community structure, is the application of the beta diversity index (e.g., Molinos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). In summary, beta diversity is the variation in species composition among sites, which can be decomposed into replacement and nestedness components (see review in Legendre, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Considering the different expected effects of climate change on species distributions, a predominance of species range expansions would lead to a decrease in the beta diversity of the whole community due to a homogeneization of the species composition across a region. Then, an application could be the selection of fewer areas in the future to represent all species in the context of conservation biogeography (Legendre, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Socolar, Gilroy, Kunin, &amp; Edwards, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Among a wide range of beta diversity indices, Legendre and De Cáceres (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and Legendre (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) have reviewed and proposed a new index that evaluates the 
 <italic class="italic">local contribution to beta diversity</italic> (LCBD hereafter), which is an indicator of ecological uniqueness of the sites for beta diversity. Moreover, the LCBD index can be properly estimated and mapped for macroecological purposes. However, there is little incorporation of this index when evaluating the beta diversity structure of communities modeled under different climate change scenarios.
</p>
