<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The long-term study of wild vertebrate populations, whereby individuals are studied throughout their life histories, has provided enormous opportunity to understand a range of evolutionary and ecological questions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B1" href="#B1">1</a>]. Cavity-dwelling passerine birds have provided an ideal system for long-term study because they can be caught and handled easily, can be marked, tracked and measured from hatching to death, have short generation times and are sensitive to environmental change. A wealth of quantitative genetic studies have demonstrated a genetic basis for many of the life history traits commonly measured for passerines such as body size, timing of breeding and clutch size [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>]. However, identifying the genomic regions which contribute to variation between individuals and between populations has, until very recently, been restricted by the lack of genetic resources in wild species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genomics era has provided an unprecedented explosion in the amount of sequence data available [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>]. Recent advances in genomics, in particular next generation sequencing, mean that generating sequence data for non-model organisms has become accessible both in terms of timescale and price [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>]. The integration of classical quantitative genetic studies with genomic data therefore provide an exciting opportunity for molecular ecologists to begin to understand the processes governing the evolution and maintenance of quantitative trait variation in wild populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) is a small (~17 g) cavity nesting passerine species widespread and abundant in woodland across Eurasia. As they are highly amenable to using nest boxes, great tits have become a model study organism in behavioural ecology and evolutionary biology, particularly with regard to studying the evolutionary ecology of life history and morphological traits such as clutch size [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>], lifetime fitness [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B9" href="#B9">9</a>], fledgling mass and adult body mass [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B10" href="#B10">10</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>]. More recently, quantitative genetic approaches have been extended to examine phenotypic plasticity in response to climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B16" href="#B16">16</a>], the heritability of personality traits [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B17" href="#B17">17</a>] and reproductive senescence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wytham Woods, near Oxford, United Kingdom, has been the site of a continuous long-term study of great tits since the late 1940s, with nest boxes for great tits first erected in 1947 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>]. The birds have been intensively monitored, with basic morphological characteristics (adult body mass, adult wing length and fledgling mass), age, sampling origin within the woods and (social) pedigree relationships recorded for most individuals since the early 1960s. In addition, there is extensive information regarding life history traits such as breeding attempts, first egg date, egg mass, clutch size, hatching date, hatching success, fledging success, fledging size and recruitment success for those birds that recruit to the breeding population (see, for example, McCleery 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>] and references therein). More recent phenotyping projects have included measuring basal metabolic rate, personality [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>], malarial infection and social network data for small subsets of individuals (Sheldon, unpublished data). Finally, blood has been sampled and stored for the majority of individuals alive since 2005, and for a subset of individuals alive between 1997 and 2005. The combination of extensive phenotypic data, pedigree information and blood samples (DNA) available from the Wytham Woods population provides tremendous opportunity to integrate the findings of previous 'classical' quantitative genetic studies of traits such as clutch size, body mass and personality in this species with quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping to locate the regions of the genome contributing to variation in these traits [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">3</a>]. Such mapping requires development of a set of markers spaced evenly across the genome. Next generation sequencing provides an efficient method for large-scale single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) discovery [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">25</a>], either by sequencing whole or partial genome (DNA) sequences or by sequencing transcript (cDNA) libraries generated from mRNA. Transcriptome sequencing (otherwise known as "RNA-seq") enables, in addition to SNP discovery, (i) the assembly and analysis of gene sequences likely to be contributing to key differences between individuals, (ii) analysis of tissue-specific gene expression, (iii) a greater depth of sequence coverage than would be possible from whole genome sequencing, (iv) the ability to infer the function of genes through comparative genomics and annotation, (v) the ability to find SNPs in known genes, including those that result in a change of protein, (vi) the ability to examine rates of molecular evolution in coding sequences, and (vii) the opportunity to test whether SNPs that explain phenotypic variation are in genes that show evidence of adaptive evolution between species. However, cDNA sequencing fails to cover regions of the genome that lacks genes, and because mRNA sequences are present in highly variable copy numbers within the cell, analysis is generally biased towards genes which are highly expressed. While normalisation of mRNA pools before sequencing enhances the probability of sequencing rare transcripts, including alternative splice variants, and gives the opportunity to infer elements of gene structure such as exon-intron boundaries, it restricts downstream analyses of transcript abundance. Transcriptome sequencing therefore complements whole or partial genome sequencing approaches.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite their prevalence in evolutionary and ecological studies, until recently the great tit had few genetic resources available, with only twenty two microsatellite markers cloned from the species and fewer than fifty full or partial gene sequences deposited in the NCBI nucleotide database 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore</span>. However, in 2009 over two billion base pairs of genomic sequence was generated from ten great tits sampled from two populations in the Netherlands. The sequences were assembled into 550,000 contigs that cover an estimated 2.5% of the great tit genome [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>]. In addition, the same research group has recently completed a low-coverage whole genome sequence of a single individual (van Bers, pers. comm). To complement this recently derived genomic sequence data, we have generated high read depth transcriptomic sequence data from the Wytham Woods population. In this paper, the sequencing, de novo assembly and analysis of the great tit transcriptome is described, highlighting the power and speed at which next generation sequencing enables the generation of sequence data in a wild species.
 </p>
</sec>
