<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blast against zebra finch, chicken and self</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate transcriptome coverage and to identify genes which have been sequenced, the great tit contigs were aligned with 
  <span class="italic">Gallus gallus </span>(chicken/red junglefowl) and 
  <span class="italic">Taeniopygia guttata </span>(zebra finch) sequences. The latest 
  <span class="italic">Taeniopygia guttata </span>(version 3.2.4.58) and 
  <span class="italic">Gallus gallus </span>(version 2.58) genome (DNA), predicted gene (cDNA) and predicted peptide (protein) databases were downloaded from the Ensembl ftp site 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ensembl.org/info/data/ftp/index.html</span>. The great tit contigs were blasted against each database using stand-alone BLAST (version 2.2.22 for 64 bit Windows). The blastn program was used for searching against DNA and cDNA databases and blastx against peptide databases, with a cut-off expectation value (e-value) of 10
  <span class="sup">-5 </span>and all other settings as default. The best alignment was retained for each contig.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine whether the assembly contained contigs with high sequence similarity (which could be suggestive of sequences from the same gene being assembled into more than one contig), contigs were clustered using blastclust 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/staff/tao/URLAPI/blastall" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/staff/tao/URLAPI/blastall</span> with options-S 95.0-b F-p F-W 30 and -L 0.95 or 1.0, the latter option specifying alignments across either 95% or the whole length of the shortest contig. Contigs were also blasted against each other, with a cutoff e-value of 10
  <span class="sup">-5</span>. Contig pairs with a single alignment which does not extend over the full length of the shortest contig may represent different genes which share a conserved protein domain. In contrast, multiple alignments between two contigs may indicate that the contigs represent different splice variants of the same gene, or that one contig is an incompletely processed form of the mRNA sequence containing introns and other features not present in the final mRNA molecule (i.e., pre-mRNA) while the other contig is the final mRNA (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2a</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
