<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sequencing of the great tit transcriptome represents an exciting application of next generation sequencing technology to the genome of a species which, until recently [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>], had very few genetic resources. Although the downstream analysis of the great tit assembly was vastly enhanced by the availability of both zebra finch (
  <span class="italic">Taeniopygia guttata</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] and chicken (
  <span class="italic">Gallus gallus</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B31" href="#B31">31</a>] complete genome sequences, the assembly of 454 reads was possible without a reference genome (i.e., de novo assembly) due to both the length of sequences (mean ~300 bases) and the high coverage (25×). The resultant great tit transcriptome assembly of 95,979 contigs, encompassing 85,997,184 bases, is a valuable tool for future genomic work in this and other closely related species, in particular for molecular evolution studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">32</a>] and to enable the development of a panel of markers for QTL mapping and genome wide association studies. This illustrates the power of next generation sequencing to begin to illuminate the genetic architecture and evolution of quantitative traits at a genomic level in non-model and wild species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As illustrated by the number of high quality SNPs detected, transcriptome or genomic sequencing is also a rapid method for detecting variation in a population. In addition to SNPs, the microsatellites identified in the transcriptome are a useful resource, as they provide new markers for this species. By seeing which of these markers are also found in the zebra finch assembly, it should be possible to determine which are the most conserved microsatellites in passerines. Such conserved microsatellites provide a good system for studying microsatellite evolution without any biases due to them being cloned in one species. Finally, because the microsatellites documented here are in or close to genes (given that the majority of contigs either align with genes (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>) or map to within 5,000 bp of a gene (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T5" href="#T5">5</a>)), they are ideal markers for candidate gene studies or other population genetic studies requiring a modest number of variable markers which are uniformly distributed across the genome.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mapping the great tit contigs to the zebra finch and chicken cDNA databases resulted in around one third of contigs aligning with known genes, despite almost all contigs aligning to the zebra finch and chicken genomes (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a>). Given that all sequences were sequenced from complementary DNA, it seems surprising that a larger proportion of contigs did not match known genes. A number of possible explanations why some contigs did not map to known genes include: (i) the contigs are great tit genes without homologues in zebra finch or chicken, (ii) they are contigs of great tit genes which are highly divergent from their zebra finch and chicken homologues and therefore do not match in a blast search, (iii) they are non-great tit sequences, (iv) they are from genes which are unannotated in both zebra finch and chicken and (v) they are sequences of preprocessed mRNA (pre-mRNA).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is very possible that a small number of contigs are either great-tit specific genes (i) or have undergone substantial sequence evolution since the divergence of zebra finch and great tit 40-45 million years ago (ii), but this explanation cannot account for most of the contigs that did not match the cDNA databases, because these contigs still matched genomic sequences. For the same reason, it appears highly unlikely that a substantial proportion of the contigs represent non-great tit sequences (iii). Given the comprehensive annotation of the chicken genome in particular, it also seems improbable that many contigs are as-yet unidentified genes (iv). The most intriguing explanation is that a high proportion of the non-gene contigs represent pre-mRNA (v). Of the contigs which did not align with zebra finch genes but did align with regions of the genome, many aligned to regions very close to genes. Further, many of the 'non-cDNA' contigs aligned within intronic regions, providing strong support that these contigs encode pre-mRNA rather than mRNA sequences.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Normalisation of the mRNA library prior to cDNA synthesis and sequencing is likely to have contributed to the presence of pre-mRNA sequences in the great tit assembly, due to the amplification of low copy number transcripts. The read depth of contigs identified as likely pre-mRNA transcripts is substantially lower than the read depth for contigs aligning with zebra finch genes (cDNA), suggesting that without normalisation the difference would be even larger. Thus, pre-mRNA sequences are less likely to be sequenced (and assembled into contigs) in non-normalised studies. However, the ability to align contigs to an assembled genome sequence (either the species itself or one closely related, in this case, zebra finch) and use this information to annotate contigs as mRNA, pre-mRNA and alternatively spliced transcripts provides a valuable tool. Even in the absence of an assembled genome to align to, it may be possible to align contigs with each other and infer elements of gene structure such as exon-intron boundaries (see Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>). Indeed, the presence of contigs covering non-coding regions may actually offer some advantages for downstream applications. In particular, it is now possible to type SNPs with different properties-for example, SNPs which map to intronic, 5' UTR, 3' UTR, and intergenic regions are valuable "neutral" contrasts to synonymous or non-synonymous SNPs located within coding regions, which are likely to be under stronger selection.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high number of pairs of contigs with multiple blast alignments, compared to the number of contigs with SNP strings, suggests that the assembly software usually splits splice variants into discrete contigs, rather than combining sequences from multiple splice variants into one contig (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2b</a>). Our results may underestimate the overall number of alternatively spliced genes in the transcriptome; recent estimates suggest that at least half of all mammalian genes with more than one exon may be alternatively spliced [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>]. One explanation for the small proportion of contigs identified as potential alternatively spliced genes is that contigs do not necessarily cover the total gene sequence, and different contigs may map to different parts of the same gene. Thus, signals of alternative splicing such as SNP 'strings' may be relatively rare given the overall coverage of the transcriptome. On the other hand, a large number of sequences (&gt; 1 million) were not assembled; it may also be possible that some of these sequences represent minor splice variants which have not been sequenced with sufficient depth to have been assembled into contigs. An exciting area for future research would be to examine splice variants in more detail; for example, looking to see if different types of genes (e.g. immune genes) have evolved to have splice variants more often than others.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 454 sequences from each of the eight tissues are deposited in the Sequence Read Archive (SRA), reference SRA026719.</p>
</sec>
