<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplementary Material</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="S1" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Additional file 1</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S1</span>. Contigs with high coverage aligning with zebra finch or chicken genes. an excel table listing great tit contigs with high sequencing coverage which align with zebra finch and/or chicken genes. 
    <span class="bold">Table S2</span>. Unique GO terms associated with contigs expressed in only one tissue. an excel table listing the unique GO terms associated with contigs expressed only in one tissue. 
    <span class="bold">Table S3</span>. Classification of unique GO terms into children of the three namespaces. an excel table listing the classification of all the GO terms uniquely associated with contigs expressed in one (or all) tissues into the 65 GO terms which are 'children' of the three namespaces (molecular function, biological process and cellular component). 
    <span class="bold">Table S4</span>. Microsatellites detected in the great tit transcriptome. an excel table listing repeats detected in the great tit assembly. Repeats are listed along with at least 10 bases of flanking sequence on each side (up to a maximum of 200 bases of flanking sequence)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1471-2164-12-283-S1.XLS" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for file</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="S2" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Additional file 2</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S1</span>. Distribution of zebra finch genes across the zebra finch genome. Counts are plotted within 500,000 base pair bins. No genes map to Tgu16 and one gene maps to TguLG5 (not shown). Note that Tgu-22, 25, 26 and 27 are presented out of numeric sequence at the bottom of the plot, to make visual comparison with Figures 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a> and 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">4</a> easier. an encapsulated postscript (eps) file showing the distribution of zebra finch genes across the zebra finch genome
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1471-2164-12-283-S2.EPS" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="postscript" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for file</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="S3" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Additional file 3</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S2</span>. Example 'is_a' and 'part_of' pedigree mapping of the GO term GO:0022857 (name: transmembrane transporter activity). The 'is_a'-only mapping is shown light grey; GO:0022857 is a subtype of GO:0005215 (transporter activity), which is a subtype of the root term GO:0003674 (molecular function), while GO:0022857 can also be mapped to the root term GO:0008150 (biological process) through 'part_of' relationships. a powerpoint (ppt) file with an example pedigree mapping of the GO term GO:0022857 to its 'parent' terms through "is_a" and "part_of" relationships
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1471-2164-12-283-S3.PPT" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-powerpoint" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for file</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
