<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gene Ontologies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gene Ontology (GO) terms are available for a large number of zebra finch genes, providing the opportunity to infer the function of those contigs in the great tit assembly which align with zebra finch genes. The latest Ensembl 
  <span class="italic">T. guttata </span>(version 3.2.4.58) gene database was downloaded from the Ensembl website 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ensembl.org/index.html</span> using the MartView interface of the BioMart data management system 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomart.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.biomart.org</span>. The Gene Ontology full ontology relationship file was downloaded from the Gene Ontology website (OBO version 1.2; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/GO.downloads.ontology.shtml" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.geneontology.org/GO.downloads.ontology.shtml</span>). Using the full ontology file and the outputs from blasting the great tit assembly against the 
  <span class="italic">T. guttata </span>cDNA database, GO terms for each great tit contig were inferred. Note that 74% of the 18,191 zebra finch unique transcript identification numbers downloaded from Ensembl have been assigned GO terms, so GO terms could not be assigned to all contigs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For contigs previously identified as tissue-specific or expressed in all tissues (see "Tissue specificity" above), tissue-unique GO terms were identified by finding GO terms associated with tissue-unique contigs which were not associated with contigs from any other tissue. To investigate whether individual tissues were associated with specific GO terms, the 'pedigree' of each of these tissue-unique GO terms was determined from the GO full ontology file. All GO terms are assigned a domain ('namespace', or equivalently 'root term') of either biological process, molecular function or cellular component [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">40</a>]. Note that although all GO terms map to one namespace through subtype 'is_a' relationships, it is possible to map to alternate namespaces through 'part_of' relationships. For each GO term, we extracted the full "pedigree" of the term by finding all possible paths from the GO term to the root term following (i) 'is_a' and 'part_of' relationships, and (ii) by following only 'is_a' relationships. An example pedigree is shown in Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3" href="#S3">3</a> Figure S2.
 </p>
</sec>
