<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mapping non-gene contigs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contigs may align with a region of the zebra finch genome but not have significant blast alignments with any of the genes in the zebra finch cDNA database, either because some genes are not yet annotated in zebra finch, or because they are aligning to non-exonic gene features, i.e. introns, 5' untranslated regions (5' UTR) or 3' UTR. It is generally assumed that transcriptome sequencing preferentially sequences mRNA, and that other RNA species such as pre-mRNA, the precursor molecule to mRNA, are either not amplified or are present in such small quantities in the cell that sequencing them is unlikely (although see Bakel 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B41" href="#B41">41</a>]). To determine whether non-coding contigs represent pre-mRNA, the location of the nearest gene was calculated by finding the shortest distance between the genome location of known zebra finch genes and the position of the contig alignment to the zebra finch genome (that is, the shortest distance to the start of the 5' UTR or the end of the 3' UTR). The contig was classified into one of six classes according to its genome location relative to the closest mapped gene; class A-contig is downstream from the nearest gene, class B-contig is upstream from the gene, class C-contig is downstream but overlapping one end of the gene, class D-contig is upstream but overlapping one end of the gene, class E-the contig spans the gene, class F-the gene spans the contig (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T5" href="#T5">5</a>). Note that "upstream" and "downstream" refer to the orientation of the zebra finch genome assembly, for example, position 345 on Tgu1 is upstream from position 350 on Tgu1. Contigs in classes C, D, E and F were further classified to determine whether the 5' and 3' ends of the contig aligned to the 5' UTR, exons, introns or 3' UTR of the gene.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to determine whether non-coding contigs were closer to genes than expected by chance, the distribution of contigs relative to genes in the zebra finch genome was assessed by simulating the random placement of contigs onto the zebra finch genome and calculating the minimum distance from the start or end of a contig to the start or end of a gene. Contigs were selected at random, placed at a randomly chosen position in the genome, and the minimum distance to a gene calculated. One million replicates were performed to generate a distribution of the distance between randomly placed contigs and the nearest gene, i.e., the distribution expected if contigs were not cDNA generated from mRNA (i.e., gene sequences) but were random fragments of genomic DNA. The observed and simulated distributions were compared with a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that class A and B contigs do not overlap annotated coding regions in the zebra finch genome, these "non-gene" contig sequences may represent non-coding RNA, although it is possible that they instead represent gene sequences which are unannotated in the zebra finch genome, or that the start or end position of genes is imprecise or differs between great tit and zebra finch. To assess the alignment between class A and B contigs with non-coding RNA, non-coding RNA sequences (including miRNA (micro), rRNA (ribosomal), snoRNA (small nucleolar), snRNA (small nuclear) and misc_RNA (miscellaneous)) were downloaded from the Ensembl website 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ensembl.org/index.html</span> using the MartView interface of the BioMart data management system 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomart.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.biomart.org</span>. The downloaded sequences were blasted against class A and B contig sequences (blastn with stand-alone BLAST, e-value 10
  <span class="sup">-5</span>, all other settings default). The best alignment was retained for each contig.
 </p>
</sec>
