<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metagenomics of non-great tit sequences</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of the 1,913 contigs which did not align with any zebra finch or chicken genome, cDNA or protein sequences, 80 aligned to RefSeq RNA sequences. Of these, 17 aligned to vertebrate_birds, suggesting they are likely to represent true great tit sequences. Of the remaining 63 contigs that did not align to vertebrate_birds, 22 aligned to another vertebrate group (vertebrate_fish, vertebrate_amphibians, vertebrate_mammalian or vertebrate_reptiles), suggesting that these contigs represent great tit genes without an annotated vertebrate_bird homologue in the RefSeq RNA database. A further 26 contigs aligned with species from two or more kingdoms, and alignments were typically short (&lt; 100 bases) or did not span more than 20% of the contig sequence. Of the remaining 15 contigs which aligned with species from a single kingdom, one aligned with bacterial species, and 14 with plant species. The 'bacterial' contig aligned with 57 different bacterial genera. The remaining 14 contigs aligned with 
  <span class="italic">Populus trichocarpa </span>(twelve contigs), or both 
  <span class="italic">P. trichocarpa </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Sorghum bicolor </span>(two contigs) sequences, and appear most likely to represent non-great tit sequences. The two 
  <span class="italic">S. bicolor </span>alignments and two of the 
  <span class="italic">P. trichocarpa </span>alignments were shorter than 80 bases and covered less than 12% of the contig, suggesting the alignments are unlikely to represent 
  <span class="italic">Populus </span>or 
  <span class="italic">Sorghum </span>but may be plant contamination of some kind. Note that while 
  <span class="italic">P. trichocarpa </span>and 
  <span class="italic">S. bicolor </span>are model species with full genome (and transcriptome) sequences, sequences from trees common in the ecology of the great tit (oak, ash, beech, hazel, sycamore) are not well represented in the RefSeq RNA database. Eleven of the remaining twelve contigs were assembled from skin reads, and the other from a combination of skin and testes reads. The remaining alignments with 
  <span class="italic">P. trichocarpa </span>were of reasonable length (109-438 bases) and identity (84-94%), suggesting there may be sequences from a plant species related to 
  <span class="italic">P. trichocarpa </span>in the great tit assembly (oak, beech and hazel are more closely related to 
  <span class="italic">P. trichocarpa </span>than ash or sycamore).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alignments with 'environmental' sequences (i.e., sequences from species important in the ecology of the great tit, see Methods) provide some evidence to suggest that the great tit assembly includes sequences from flea and tick (ectoparasites that commonly inhabit bird nests). Forty-six contigs aligned with ribosomal RNA sequences from 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus</span>. Twenty-eight contigs aligned with ribosomal RNA sequences from 
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus ciliatus </span>(a grey squirrel flea), with some but not all of these contigs also aligning with sequences from the hen flea 
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus gallinae</span>. However, contigs aligning to 
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus ciliatus </span>and to 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus </span>showed no evidence of tissue specificity; all ten of the most significant contig alignments with 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ciliatus </span>were expressed in two or more tissues. Similarly all ten of the most significant contig alignments with 
  <span class="italic">I</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ricinus </span>were expressed in two or more tissues. Of the 1,091,610 singletons not assembled into contig sequences, 3,656 aligned with 60 'environmental' sequences. Alignments with flea (
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus </span>spp) and tick (
  <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus</span>) sequences were the most prevalent (1,524 and 829 alignments), in addition there were 700 alignments with badger (
  <span class="italic">Meles meles</span>)-hair from which is frequently incorporated into nests-and 364 with beech (
  <span class="italic">Fagus sylvatica</span>). Thus, there is limited evidence that small amounts of RNA from other species have been included in the great tit sequences. There was little evidence to suggest that the great tit assembly includes sequences from any common endoparasites, nor from the great tit's common food source the winter moth (
  <span class="italic">Opheroptera brumata</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
