<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We noted incidence of flowering time overlap in the four contact zones described above and surveyed past flowering records using herbarium specimens collected from 25 Colorado Rocky Mountain sites, between 1907 and 2009 to broaden our geographic sampling. Herbarium databases were hosted by the University of Colorado (Boulder, CO), Colorado State University (Fort Collins, CO), and the Rocky Mountain Herbarium (Univ. of Wyoming; Cheyenne, WY). Flowering status was obtained from labels, digital images of specimens, and visual examination for specimens housed at the Carter Herbarium of Colorado College (Colorado Springs). We searched all 
 <italic class="italic">Salix glauca</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> S. brachycarpa</italic>, or 
 <italic class="italic">S. glauca‐brachycarpa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium viscosum</italic> specimens in these four databases to identify locations above tree‐line (&gt;3,300 m altitude) where both species were collected in flower during the same year. Twenty‐five sites met these criteria, with 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic> occurring within a 200 m altitudinal range. A paired (by site) 
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>‐test was used to test whether collection date of flowering specimens (Julian Day) differed between 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic> across the range of conditions encompassed in this sample. To test whether flowering overlap of 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic> may reflect a shared sensitivity to temperature at budburst, we performed a second analysis (ANCOVA 
 <italic class="italic">lme</italic> in the 
 <italic class="italic">nlme</italic> package (Pineiro et al. 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and ANOVA in the 
 <italic class="italic">car</italic> package (Fox et al. 2013)) on specimen collection date with temperature (statewide average minimum temperature in June of the collection year (NOAA; Western Regional Climate Center), species and their interaction as fixed effects and spatial variation (latitude at the center of the county where collections were made) as a random effect. Statewide temperature data were used to distinguish warm seasons from cold ones because local data were not available for all sites and collection years. The proportion of variance explained by the fixed and random effects was calculated via 
 <italic class="italic">r.squaredGLMM</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">MuMIn</italic> package (Bartoń and R Development Core Team 2015)). All statistical analyses were conducted using R statistical language (R Development Core Team 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0204" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), unless otherwise noted.
</p>
