<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study presented the overview of climate change and health studies done in the Philippines. Selected research articles and grey literature were descriptively analyzed to summarize their general characteristics, methods, findings, limitations, and recommendations, as well as to categorize their research themes. Based on the results, recommended research priorities for funding, limitations of the review, and pointers about research agenda setting are discussed as follows.</p>
 <sec id="sec4dot1-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Research Gaps and Priorities</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were actually not enough studies retrieved, thus making the identification of research gaps not as straightforward as it could be. When looking at the research themes with the least number of studies, there were apparent gaps in research topics on the “Vulnerability to Disease and Injury Due to Climate Variability and Climate Change”, “Adaptation to Protect Health”, “Health Impacts Heavily Mediated through Human Institutions”, and “Co-Benefits”. These research topics remain broad but can potentially produce valuable findings and offer key solutions to several existing problems. For a country with considerable vulnerability to extreme weather events and climate change, prioritizing health vulnerabilities and health adaptation research is an easy recommendation because it potentially addresses present and near-future issues [
   <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-02624">48</a>]. These can also generate tangible evidence and technology that can be relatively appreciated by policy-makers and the general public.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another topic that can potentially be appreciated by the general public is co-benefits research. It is a good priority topic for funding, as such studies can quantify co-health benefits in reducing greenhouse gas emissions from major sources like transportation, food and agriculture, energy generation, and industries [
   <a rid="B49-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-16-02624">49</a>]. This research also touched on air pollution research, such as measurements of the impacts of climate-altering pollutants on health, which were not retrieved from the literature search. These can pave the way for creating and supporting mitigation policies and legislations across non-health sectors [
   <a rid="B49-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-16-02624">49</a>]. The lack of co-benefit studies retrieved may be explained by the complex interdisciplinary approach required from sectors who do not usually collaborate with one another. Thus, apart from providing research funding, workshops and events for establishing climate change research collaborations may be considered to be organized in the future to initiate an exchange of ideas.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recurring study limitation was data unavailability and poor quality. Local sources of secondary data on health outcomes and meteorological parameters were reported to have limitations on their quality, accuracy, and reliability. These sources are also not openly available, and have limitations due to the current data privacy policies. A possible reason behind this is that these data sources are not made to cater for modeling studies. Since many time-series analysis studies rely on such data, better data monitoring and storage should be included as a priority project alongside such research projects. Exploring the possibility of developing open and anonymized health outcomes and climate change data from existing local databases can unlock a revolution of modeling studies.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from developing better databases, a possible research topic that can be prioritized is the development of standardized and reproducible modeling scheme(s) so that studies can be compared and combined. This considers the limitations in the geographical setting and political setup of the Philippines. Beyond modeling or ecological studies, quantifying causality through (nested) cohort studies, although complex and expensive, can be considered to be developed.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot2-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Limitations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of limitations can be noted from this scoping review. The studies presented only included quantitative studies, although there were six qualitative and mixed-method studies retrieved. These kinds of studies, although small in number, can provide different insights, particularly in regard to the perceptions, habits, and adaptation practices of people. These are data that cannot be clearly captured using quantitative methods.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also, the selection of quantitative studies excluded disaster risk reduction (DRR) studies. For example, flooding-related studies were not selected because they were mainly related with DRR. In reality, DRR and climate change studies have commonalities and share risk pathways to health outcomes [
   <a rid="B50-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-16-02624">50</a>]. Exclusion of studies with no measurements of health outcomes may have also averted the inclusion of relevant studies related with climate change.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indeed, IPCC research themes provided a simple guide in identifying potential research priorities for funding. However, it fails to provide specific health topics to focus on. From the retrieved studies, dengue was the most researched, but this does not necessarily mean that dengue has been studied well without analyzing the quality of the research and evidence found. The descriptive nature of the scoping review limits such analyses. A possibility method of narrowing down the amount of health topics to focus on is by considering the top causes of mortality and morbidity, or what are the current political priorities. Topics that can have implications to climate change can be the selected as the priority topics. In this way, selection of topics to be funded by the government remains valuable and of interest to the government.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature search was not exhaustive enough because it was limited to what was available online. Although there were some literature retrieved from the consultation, this undermines other studies from academic institutions and other unrepresented agencies working on climate change research.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot3-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Research Agenda-Setting</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The full process conducted in the research agenda setting for climate change and health comprised: (1) scoping review, (2) stakeholder analysis, and (3) consultation meetings. The sole purpose of the scoping review in the agenda-setting was to provide the needed background for the stakeholders in guiding their decision-making in selecting the final research priority topics for funding and generating the roadmap for climate change and health research. Although scoping reviews can be a standalone tool in setting research agenda, this was not done because of the possible disconnection with the local stakeholders’ interests, knowledge, and skills. The power in selecting the final research agenda was still with stakeholders and driven by their own individual or group interests. However, overall, the findings from the scoping review allow the stakeholders to see how their interests fit in the current evidence and gaps, thus discouraging any possible redundancies. Furthermore, any disconnections between the stakeholders and scoping review findings can be beneficial for the funding agencies in possibly considering support of the development of human resources for climate change and health through scholarships and training.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
