<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The methodology used was based on the approach outlined by Arksey and O’Malley, and search strategies by Herlihy et al. [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-02624">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-02624">12</a>]. The review comprised: (1) identifying a broad research question, (2) identifying relevant studies, (3) selecting studies, (4) charting the data, (5) collating, summarizing, and reporting the results, and (6) consulting stakeholders. The research team came up with the broad question, “What are the characteristics, methodologies, and findings of the studies on climate/weather exposure and human health outcomes done in the Philippines?”
 </p>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Search Strategy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature search was limited to online-based databases or search engines. Initially, a literature search was done using PubMed/MEDLINE, Embase, and the Web of Science on March 7, 2018. For grey literature, additional online databases and search engines were used, including the Health Research and Development Information Network (HERDIN), which is a research database of the Philippine Council for Health Research and Development, as well as OpenGrey, ProQuest, and Google on April 5–6, 2018. Grey literature were searched to expand the possibly small number of published articles in scientific journals. The search terms comprised broad terms on climate factors and health outcomes (
   <a rid="ijerph-16-02624-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02624-t001">Table 1</a>) [
   <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02624">10</a>,
   <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-02624">11</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature search was limited from 1980 to 2017 (37 years) to possibly consider studies in the past. References of screened full-text articles and grey literature were manually searched for additional literature.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Eligibility Criteria</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For published articles, only full-text original or research articles were selected, while grey literature were limited to full-text theses, dissertations, technical reports, and discussion papers. Clear statements of associations between climate factors and health outcomes were required. Climate factors were meteorological parameters, extreme weather events, air pollution, and atmosphere-ocean interaction phenomena. The Philippines had to be explicitly mentioned as a study site. In the case of multi-site studies, findings specifically for the Philippines should be present in the results or discussion section. Initially, both quantitative and qualitative studies were considered to further widen the selection pool of articles and papers; however, quantitative studies were only presented here to clearly articulate the results. Mixing the results and discussion with qualitative and/or mixed methods studies may limit the depth of the discussion. Only articles and grey literature written in English were included, because it is the language used in academia or business in the Philippines.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Screening</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The abstracts and executive summaries were reviewed by two individuals looking for the keywords related to climate factors, human health outcomes, associations between exposures and outcomes, and the Philippines as the study site or one of the study sites. Studies with Filipino participants done outside the country were excluded (e.g., studies with overseas Filipino workers as participants). After the initial screening, each reviewer separately reviewed the full texts of the articles and papers. An eligibility criteria review was done to examine their content in terms of associations made between health outcomes and climate factors in the Philippines. For the purposes of this study, an association was loosely defined as any explicit textual statement on the attempt to relate health outcome(s) with climate factor(s). The results of the screening were discussed by two reviewers to reach a consensus on which should be included in the final selection list.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Characterization</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The selected articles and papers were categorized based on the human health outcomes, climate factors, research design, methodologies, and country affiliations of the first authors which were researched. Further data on the study results were extracted to identify the specific details on the type of research and depth of the findings. To identify research themes, five climate and health themes by Smith et al. in one of the chapters of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Fifth Assessment Report were adopted [
   <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02624">13</a>]. Apart from the purposes of brevity, this was selected because the eligibility criteria followed Smith et al.’s concept of linking primary exposure pathways by which climate change affects health outcomes. To guide the categorization of the articles, excerpts from their study objectives and results were used as a basis from which to identify which theme they fell under (
   <a rid="ijerph-16-02624-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02624-t002">Table 2</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Consultation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Initial results of the review were presented to 20 stakeholders from various offices in the Philippines with initiatives or interests in climate change and health, including government agencies, academia, and non-profit institutions, on May 16, 2018. Recommendations and feedback were sought. Some government institutions shared their studies for possible inclusion in the analysis.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot6-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Data Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were encoded in a single Microsoft Excel 2013 spreadsheet (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, WA, USA). Descriptive statistics were calculated for summary using MS Excel 2013. Excerpts from selected studies were coded by one author and validated by another.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot7-ijerph-16-02624" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Ethical Considerations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the lead institution (Alliance for Improving Health Outcomes, Inc) did not have an ethical review committee, the research protocol received ethical approval from the St. Cabrini Medical Center, Asian Eye Institute Ethics Review Committee (Makati City, Philippines), Protocol No. 2018-006.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
