<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-ijerph-12-14994" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Independent Measures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Climate change beliefs.</span> Climate change certainty is measured with two questions: “Do you think that climate change is happening?” (yes, no, don’t know); and “If you answered either yes or no, how sure are you?” (not at all sure, somewhat sure, very sure, extremely sure). The two measures are combined into a 9-point scale ranging from (1) extremely sure climate change is not happening to (9) extremely sure climate change is happening. A scale comprised of four dichotomous items represents the number of perceived local climate health impacts that respondents believe will occur in Maryland. The question “Which—if any—of the following health problems will become more common in Maryland in the future because of climate change?” includes four response categories: respiratory and breathing problems; infectious diseases such as West Nile virus; heat stroke; and injuries from storms or other extreme weather events. The responses were added to create an additive scale from 0–4 correct responses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Social vulnerability and health susceptibility.</span> Seven measures represent socioeconomic characteristics that capture social vulnerability and health susceptibility: gender, income, education, racial and/or ethnic minority group, age 65 years or older, and household members with chronic medical conditions and/or disabilities (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-14994-t006" href="#ijerph-12-14994-t006">Table S2</a>). Household pre-existing medical conditions and disabilities were measured thus: “Has a doctor ever diagnosed you or another member of your household with the following conditions?” Survey participants were given a list of five conditions: coronary heart disease; obesity; diabetes; respiratory illness, including asthma; or a physical or mental disability. Responses were summed into a composite score from 0 to 5, then split into a three-category variable: (0) no diagnosed medical conditions; (1) one diagnosed condition; (2) two or more diagnosed conditions. Age is coded as a dichotomous variable for those age 65 or greater.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Exposure to hazards.</span> Flood risk is captured by household location within a 100-year floodplain using 2015 FEMA Digital Flood Insurance Rate Map data obtained from the state of Maryland [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-12-14994">41</a>]. Exposure to higher temperatures due to location in a highly populated urban area [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-14994">5</a>] is represented by the percent of the population designated urban in U.S. Census-designated zip code tabulation areas in 2010 [
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-12-14994">42</a>]. The Census classifies urban areas primarily based on population density. While recent studies may use modeled climate data estimates for measurements of urban heat island intensity [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-12-14994">43</a>], in this study we employ the Census urban-rural designation as a rough proxy for exposure to higher temperatures due to the urban heat island effect based on early research demonstrating a direct relationship between population density and temperatures [
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-12-14994">44</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
