<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Descriptive results by vulnerability group</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figures 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a> shows the confidence intervals at 95 % level for selected indicators across vulnerability categories. For the climatic indicators we find that temperature and, to some extent, precipitation determine higher exposure in the very highly vulnerable category. Though in this category the confidence interval for precipitation overlaps with those in the moderately to highly vulnerable categories; temperature is significantly different compared with the rest of the vulnerability categories.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Descriptive results of selected indicators by vulnerability group. 
     <span class="italic">Filled square</span> represents the average and 
     <span class="italic">filled rectangle</span> represents upper and lower limits of the 95 % confidence interval
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40064_2015_1536_Fig5_HTML" id="MO11" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Descriptive results of selected indicators by vulnerability group. 
     <span class="italic">Filled square</span> represents the average and 
     <span class="italic">filled rectangle</span> represents upper and lower limits of the 95 % confidence interval
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40064_2015_1536_Fig6_HTML" id="MO110" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Descriptive results of selected indicators by vulnerability group. 
     <span class="italic">Filled square</span> represents the average and 
     <span class="italic">filled rectangle</span> represents upper and lower limits of the 95 % confidence interval
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40064_2015_1536_Fig7_HTML" id="MO111" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the adaptive capacity indicators we find that agricultural land tenure (i.e. the proportion of households owning agricultural land with respect to total agricultural land) is not significantly different between the moderately vulnerable to the very highly vulnerable categories. In these groups on average 71 % of farmers own the land where they work. This figure increases to 85 % for the less vulnerable category. There is, however, a significant difference between the less and very highly vulnerable groups. In addition, for the proportion of the population working in agriculture, silviculture or hunting, 25.53 % work in cantons in the less vulnerable category. This figure increases to 52.35 % in the rest of the vulnerability categories.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The indicator for institutional capacity is highest for the moderately vulnerable category, and lowest for the highly and very highly vulnerable categories. Significant differences may appear in confidence intervals using levels slightly lower than 95 %. Public funds per capita for environmental protection are highest for the less vulnerable category (32.18 US dollars) but there is wide variation across cantons. For the rest of the categories funds per capita are on average 12.45 US dollars.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion of households with access to garbage collection service is highest in the less vulnerable category (82.08 %). This is significantly different compared with the moderately vulnerable (64.43 %), the vulnerable (56.89 %), and the highly and very highly vulnerable (45.51 %) categories. Similarly, on average the proportion of households with sewage treatment service is 81.55 % in the less vulnerable category but is 43.67 % in the very highly vulnerable category. A similar result is observed for the proportion of households receiving water through a public piped system: the proportion is 67.54 % in the less vulnerable category, 33.95 % in the highly vulnerable category, and 27.8 % in the very highly vulnerable.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding human capital as part of adaptive capacity, there is high variation in the proportion of population affected by natural disasters, where the average is 16.54 %. No significant differences are found across vulnerability categories. In addition, less than 10 % of the population across all vulnerability categories has private health insurance: 55 % of the population is not under social security coverage.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is also a high variation on the minimum distance to a large town in the less vulnerable category and the confidence intervals overlap across all categories.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the sensitivity indicators, adult illiteracy rate is significantly higher in the very highly vulnerable category (13.12 %), and lower in the less vulnerable (4.99 %) and moderately vulnerable (8.75 %) categories. For the remaining categories, the illiteracy rate averages 10.01 %. For crowded households, this proportion is lowest for the less vulnerable category (14.19 %) and is significantly different for the rest of the vulnerability categories (highly vulnerable 23.33 % and very highly vulnerable, 27.93 %). Population density is significantly larger in the less vulnerable category (180 inhabitants per square km) compared with the very highly vulnerable category. However, there is a high variation where no pattern is identified and confidence intervals overlap across all categories.</p>
</sec>
