<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Extreme climate change will almost certainly require relocation of potato production from the semi-arid east to rain-fed production in the west, with all the necessary capital investments in farming businesses and regional infrastructure [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. To investigate the impact of such a shift on the aggressiveness of 
 <italic class="italic">Pectobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> spp. in tubers, we reassigned the potato-containing cells in Scotland, England and Wales, respectively, to the (land) grid cells with the highest summer (June to August) mean precipitation rate under each climate change scenario. In other words, we ‘moved’ the potato crops in each country (typically on the semi-arid eastern seaboard; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205711.g003" class="xref">Fig 3</xref>) to the wettest locations in that country (typically more westerly locations; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205711.g002" class="xref">Fig 2B</xref>). In reality, the determinants of land suitability for potato production are complicated by a large number of climate, soil, water abstraction and other crop management factors, but we proceed under the simplifying assumption that movement to areas of higher rainfall will be a key driving factor in the future, for the purposes of simulation. We repeated all climate change projections, and results for future climates were taken relative to those for baseline conditions and presented as percentage changes to current aggressiveness in tubers for each of the four pathogens: i.e., relative change = (severity
 <sub class="sub">future</sub>−severity
 <sub class="sub">current</sub>) / severity
 <sub class="sub">current</sub> × 100. Results are summarized using stem plots to compare median changes to severity in current (actual) potato crop locations and median changes to severity in optimized crop locations. This gave a total of 96 data values per CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions scenario: 4 pathogens × 4 months × 3 countries × 2 crop distributions.
</p>
