<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Change and Crop Quality</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts of climate change on agricultural systems threaten crops with notable implications for farmer livelihoods and human health (Odada et al., 
   <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">2008</a>; Pachauri et al., 
   <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">2014</a>; Campbell et al., 
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">2016</a>). Since the 1950s, agricultural systems have experienced gradual systematic changes in average climate conditions including unprecedented multi-decadal warming, increased inter-annual variability of the Earth's surface temperatures, changes in average precipitation, greater weather variability, and more extreme weather conditions (Pachauri et al., 
   <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">2014</a>). These climatic changes have decreased agricultural productivity and shifted the geographic range of many crops (Lobell and Asner, 
   <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">2003</a>; Porter and Semenov, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2005</a>). Concurrently, productivity of some crops has increased with a rise in temperatures (Ewert et al., 
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2005</a>). Increasing atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO
   <sub>2</sub>) has decreases concentrations of micronutrients zinc (Zn) and iron (Fe) as well as protein for C
   <sub>3</sub> grains and legumes (Myers et al., 
   <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">2014</a>). While the literature provides substantial evidence on the impact of climate change on crop yields (Lobell and Asner, 
   <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">2003</a>; Hertel et al., 
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">2010</a>; Lobell et al., 
   <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">2011</a>), fewer studies have focused on the effects of climate change on crop quality (Porter and Semenov, 
   <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2005</a>; Ahmed and Stepp, 
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crop quality is a multi-dimensional parameter that refers to the nutritional, health, and sensory attributes of crops as measured by the presence, absence, and/or concentrations of phytonutrients, minerals, and primary and secondary metabolites (i.e., bioactive food components or phytochemicals) as well as associated bioactivity, shelf life, and organoleptic properties (i.e., color, visual appeal, aroma, taste, and texture) (Mattos et al., 
   <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">2014</a>; Ahmed and Stepp, 
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">2016</a>). Secondary metabolites are non-nutrient plant constituents that impact crop quality through an influence on flavor, appearance, stability (Tomás-Barberán and Espin, 
   <a rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103">2001</a>) and health-promoting attributes including mitigating micronutrient deficiencies (Johns and Sthapit, 
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">2004</a>) and the risk of diet-related chronic disease including cancer, heart disease, and diabetes (Liu, 
   <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">2013</a>). Over 100,000 secondary metabolites have been identified in five chemical classes including phenolics, terpenes, alkaloids, and other nitrogen-containing compounds, phytosterols, and organosulfur compounds (Goldberg, 
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">2003</a>; Swift et al., 
   <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">2004</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants have evolved secondary metabolites to protect themselves from various abiotic and biotic stressors (Fraenkel, 
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">1959</a>; Coley et al., 
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">1985</a>). Since the synthesis of secondary metabolites represents a metabolic cost, plants tend to produce these compounds in notable concentrations if they have the ecological cue to do so based on interactions between environmental (Lower and Orians, 
   <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">2003</a>; Björkman et al., 
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">2011</a>; Kowalsick et al., 
   <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">2014</a>), agricultural (Ahmed et al., 
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">2013</a>), genetic (van-Dam and Vrieling, 
   <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">1994</a>), and physiological factors (Coley et al., 
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">1985</a>; Glynn et al., 
   <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">2007</a>). Each crop has specific secondary metabolites that characterize crop quality while the presence of other secondary metabolites is viewed as deleterious for crop quality due to off-flavors or toxicity attributes. Climate change factors have resulted in a decrease of multiple secondary metabolites in a range of food and beverage crops including coffee (Villarreal et al., 
   <a rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115">2009</a>), tea (Ahmed et al., 
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">2014a</a>,
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">b</a>; Kowalsick et al., 
   <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">2014</a>), grapes (Xu et al., 
   <a rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" href="#B120">2011</a>), brown rice (Britz et al., 
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2007</a>), kale (Zietz et al., 
   <a rid="B126" ref-type="bibr" href="#B126">2010</a>), tomatoes (Kacjan-Maršič et al., 
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">2010</a>), and peanuts (Casini et al., 
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">2003</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tea as a Model System for Examining Climate Effects on Crop Quality</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This review article employs tea (
   <span class="italic">Camelia sinensis</span>; Theaceae) to understand how climate change impacts crop quality of a culturally-relevant beverage plant. Tea, the botanical source of all white, green, oolong, black and pu-erh tea beverages, was selected as a study system because of its prevalence in diets globally, its production in over 50 countries on five continents (FAOSTAT, 
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">2016</a>), and because it is a plant that is cultivated for its quality based on secondary metabolites (Ahmed et al., 
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">2010</a>). Polyphenolic catechin, methylxanthine (i.e., caffeine), and volatile secondary metabolites, coupled with carbohydrates and amino acids, contribute to tea quality through influencing the flavor and appearance of tea (Drewnowski and Gomez-Carneros, 
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">2000</a>; Scharbert et al., 
   <a rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95">2004</a>) as well as its health claims including anti-oxidative, anti-inflammatory, neuro-protective, cardio-protective, anti-cancer, anti-microbial, and anti-atherosclerotic activities (Trevisanato and Kim, 
   <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">2000</a>; Lin et al., 
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">2003</a>; Clement, 
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">2009</a>). Tea is further suitable as a study system to examine the effects of climate change because it is a woody perennial that experiences multiple decadal effects of climate change. Successful tea cultivation tea is dependent on climatic conditions including temperature, rainfall, humidity, and solar radiation (Wijeratne, 
   <a rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B118">1996</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marx et al. (
   <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">2017</a>) identified 14 articles highlighting that shifts in rainfall and solar radiation influence tea yields and quality with implications for farmer livelihoods. For example, Biggs et al. (
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2018</a>) demonstrate that climate change is impacting farmer livelihoods across four major tea-growing regions of Assam, India. Boehm et al. (
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">2016</a>) show that a decrease in solar radiation in the previous growing season is associated with lower tea yields. However, the literature is missing a systematic review that synthesizes the evidence of environmental effects on tea quality and, the directionality of changes in quality parameters.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study addresses the aforementioned knowledge gap through a systematic literature review that examines the following question: 
   <span class="italic">What are effects of environmental variation related to climate change on tea quality?</span> Given the lack of studies examining long-term effects of climate change on tea quality, we synthesize studies that examine the effects of environmental factors that are shifting with climate change. This review can inform future research by identifying literature gaps and new research questions while serving as a model for literature reviews on climate change effects on crop quality.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
