<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Rocky intertidal habitats are among the most vulnerable to rises in sea level because many are backed by steep inclines (such as hard cliffs) and are thus unable to retreat landward (Jackson &amp; McIlvenny 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Two forms of management are likely to be particularly effective. First, the creation of hard and rock‐armoured defences, such as breakwaters, gabions and offshore barriers, can be used to absorb wave energy and reduce local erosion (French 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>) and are colonized by intertidal organisms. However, intertidal communities on existing hard defences are less diverse than those on natural rocky shores because the defences lack environmental heterogeneity, tending to be smooth and steeply grading (Table 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). Creation of microhabitat features (e.g. shaded vertical surfaces and water‐retaining features that mimic rock pools) increases the diversity of algal and macrobenthos communities and increases the potential for artificial barriers to compensate for loss of existing rocky intertidal habitat (Table 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). An alternative approach is to promote ecologically engineered offshore barriers, such as those created by reef‐building oysters and mussels (Borsje 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). These can attenuate wave energy and stabilize intertidal flats behind them, although their effectiveness may be limited in high‐energy environments (Table 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). Oyster reefs have declined by 85% over the past 100 years (Beck 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), and the creation of ecologically engineered reefs has the dual benefit of increasing habitat extent and providing a self‐sustaining barrier that can keep pace with sea‐level rise (Rodriguez 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The decision as to which type of barrier to create depends on whether the goal is to create a specialist ecological community (ecologically engineered reef), or provide suitable habitat for a wider algal and macrobenthos community (artificial barriers).
</p>
