<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Creation of new coastal habitats adjacent to existing ones is likely to be the most effective long‐term option. Managed realignment, where sea defences are relocated landward and the old, seaward defences are breached to allow tidal inundation (French 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>), is the most commonly used method to create intertidal flats and saltmarshes. While not strictly 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> management, it often within the remit of a site manager to consider such an option and we therefore provide a brief overview of its efficacy. The most important factor in the success of these schemes is the surface elevation of the site, since this determines the colonization and subsequent composition of communities. Most sites selected for managed realignment are low‐lying with respect to sea level (Crooks 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). This maximizes the length of time the habitat remains unvegetated and thus suitable feeding habitat for wading birds (Table 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>), but is not desirable if the aim is to quickly establish vegetated saltmarsh (Garbutt 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). While benthic infaunal and saltmarsh plant species can often colonize quickly (Mossman 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), natural communities can be more difficult to recreate (Mossman, Davy &amp; Grant 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Artificial planting of rare species accelerates vegetation development, and may be particularly beneficial if the plant species host rare invertebrates (Woodell &amp; Dale 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>). Plant colonization may be constrained by poorly drained and oxygenated sediments (Mossman, Davy &amp; Grant 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), which may be improved by the establishment of effective creek networks (Crooks 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) or the creation of more varied topography through constructing raised and lowered areas (Table 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). The grazing of saltmarshes can also generate habitat heterogeneity and may be particularly desirable when vegetation is dominated by invasive high‐marsh grasses (Bos 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). In these situations, extensive grazing can increase plant diversity and create habitat more suitable for waterfowl, potentially mitigating for some sea‐level‐induced impacts (Clausen, Stjernholm &amp; Clausen 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
