<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To evaluate possible effects of climate change on huemul distribution, we modeled outcomes of current huemul distribution on layers of five future Global Climate Models (GCM) for the years 2050 (mean of years 2030–2060) and 2070 (mean of years 2060–2080). We selected these databases because GCM climatic projections could have regional variations (
 <xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yan et al., 2017</xref>). Databases were obtained from Worldclim and correspond to results of Phase 5 of Coupled Models Intercomparison (CMIP5). The GCM we used belong to: (1) CCSM4 (NCAR-UCAR, USA), (2) HadGEM2-ES (Met Office Hadley Centre, UK), (3) IPSL-CM5A-MR (Institute Pierre-Simon Laplace, France), (4) MRI-CGCM3 (Meteorological Research Institute, Japan), and (5) NorESM1-M (Norwegian Climate Centre, Norway). Climatic projection models are currently presented in four scenarios known as Representative Concentration Routes (RCP) that indicate the evolution of the range of greenhouse gas concentrations under different states of production of those gases (
 <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moss et al., 2010</xref>). RCP scenarios were named in relation to their radiative value, which corresponds to the balance alteration between incoming and outgoing radiation from the atmosphere, causing changes in atmospheric constituents, as is the case of carbon dioxide (
 <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moss et al., 2010</xref>). These scenarios have been projected until the year 2100, and have values ranging from 2.6 to 8.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (
 <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Vuuren et al., 2011a</xref>). From the four RCP available scenarios, we only used RCP4.5 and RCP6.0 for years 2050 and 2070. Scenarios RCP2.6 (the most optimistic; 
 <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stocker et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Vuuren et al., 2011b</xref>) and RCP8.5 (the least optimistic; 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Riahi et al., 2011</xref>) would not be fulfilling the predictions, but current climatic variables are getting closer to values estimated by RCP4.5 and RCP2.6 models, showing an incremental increase in temperature from 2.0 to 4.9 °C (
 <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raftery et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
