<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Antarctic Peninsula has been one of the most rapidly warming regions of the world during the twentieth century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> where 
  <span class="bold">~</span>75% of the ice shelves have already retreated over the past 50 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. This retreat durably affects the stability of the regional glaciers and the ice sheet mass balance, which ultimately contributes to the eustatic sea-level rise. Specifically, in the eastern Antarctic Peninsula (EAP), the rapid warming observed since the 1970s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> have had marked consequences on regional glaciers and ice shelves. One of the first major events occurred in 2002 when the Larsen B ice shelf in eastern Antarctic Peninsula (EAP) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) collapsed and lost an area of ~3250 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> by calving huge icebergs to the ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. A series of smaller—but significant—events occurred earlier in the northern part of the EAP with the collapse of the Larsen A and the Prince Gustav ice shelves in 1995, as well as that of the Larsen Inlet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> in 1989 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Since 2010, a giant crack has continuously incised the Larsen C ice shelf until it broke off in 2017 to form a massive iceberg of ~6000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (~9–12% of the total ice shelf)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, thus drawing the premise of unprecedented major collapses in the near future.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The Antarctic Peninsula and the recent shifts of the ice shelf boundary. Shown is the drastic retreat of ice shelves (Larsen A and B) along the EAP margin since 1986, the recent crack of the Larsen C since 2010, the study site (JPC-38) (63.717°S, 57.411°W, 760 m water depth) (blue star) and the JRI ice core (black star)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
     </span>. The arrows show the circulation of the CDW (orange) and WDW (light brown) around the Peninsula. Reanalyzed data and model simulations have been computed along the EAP margin (i.e., in the gray area). Dark and light blue lines correspond to the bathymetry at 2000 and 1000 m depth and delineate the continental shelf from the abyssal Weddell Sea basin
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8195_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e489" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Such successive events were initially hypothesized to have been mainly driven by Antarctic surface warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Indeed, a surface air temperature (SAT) increase of 2–3 °C has been observed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> between the 1960s and the late 1990s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), which could have directly impacted surface ice-melt
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, increased hydrofracturation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, and indirectly glacier acceleration via enhanced precipitation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. However, an increase in the ocean heat content
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> can also substantially reduce the ice sheet extent through basal and frontal melting, ice shelves thinning and iceberg calving
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Although the oceanic impact remains difficult to quantify due to the lack of observational data, recent studies suggested that the effects of subsurface ocean warming could have contributed to more than 50% of the total ice loss in some Antarctica areas during the last few years, especially in the EAP region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>SAT, Ekman pumping, and SOT variations in the EAP during the instrumental period. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Monitored SAT (°C) at the Esperanza (black) and Marambio (green) stations since 1950 and 1970
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
     </span>. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Annual mean wind-forced Ekman pumping
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
     </span> (normalized series) along the EAP between 1950 and 2010 based on the reanalysis data from 20CR Project version 2
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
     </span> (orange) and ERA-interim
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
     </span> (blue). 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Smoothed Annual mean SOT (°C) from 1993 to 2010 using GLORYS (dark red)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
     </span> and between 1979 and 2010 using EN4 (light red)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
     </span> along the EAP margin at 50–400 water depth. Black arrows indicate the major ice shelf collapse events. The smooth fit (also represented in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) is an interpolate curve fit with a geometric weight applied using a Stineman function to the data. The weight is applied to 20% of the data (±10% of the data range, i.e., around the current point)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8195_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e588" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indeed, the intrusion of relatively warm Circumpolar Deep Waters (CDW) onto the Antarctic shelf has been shown to promote ice shelf basal melting around Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. The warm deep water is upwelled across the continental shelf and channeled toward the grounding ice line through cavities and troughs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. In the Weddell Sea, the CDW enters as a coastal current from the east and circulates clockwise as Warm Deep Water (WDW) along the EAP shelf
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. However, the recent and past activity of this warm water mass, including its temperature change and modification along its pathway to the continental shelf by mixing with shelf waters (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>, Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), are not well known, nor its impact on the ice shelf extent. In particular, variations in the intensity and position of the circumpolar Southern Westerly Winds (SWW) along the EAP may strongly modulate the upward transport of WDW onto the shelf through Ekman pumping.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we combine recent and geological records spanning the past 9000 years to investigate the variability of environmental conditions of the EAP on multiannual-to-millennial timescales and its effect on the ice shelf boundaries. Our results suggest that the ocean thermal forcing, tied to the circulation of the relatively warm WDW, has played a central role on the regional ice shelf instability during both the instrumental period and Holocene; a slight ocean warming contributing to substantial ice shelf collapse and regression. When extrapolating these results to the most pessimistic Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) emission scenario, we show that a slight subsurface ocean warming will further accentuate the current erosion of the EAP ice shelf by the end of the twenty-first century.</p>
</sec>
