<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean impact on recent ice shelf collapse</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using reanalysis data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, we first computed the variations of the Ekman pumping along the EAP margin since 1950 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) to decipher the link between wind forcing, in terms of strength and position, and evaluate its impact on the SOT. Ekman pumping anomalies experienced mainly negative values until the late 1970s and after the early 2000s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>), indicating a downward velocity. This dominant downwelling regime over our study area probably results from a northern position of the convergence zone between the SWW and the southerly winds, blowing northward along the south EAP (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). Conversely, the anomalies switched toward positive values during the 1980s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>) to peak in the 1990s, thus implying a shift toward a dominant upwelling regime. This shift from regionally downwelling to upwelling conditions is probably tied to the intensification and poleward displacement of the SWW circulation at that time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, which would have enlarged its influence at the expense of the northward wind fields. As such, dominant SWW, offshore winds would have favored the upward transport of deeper water masses.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reanalyses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> concomitantly document a sharp increase in subsurface ocean temperatures (SOT) (50–400 m water depth) on the continental shelf reaching up to +0.6 °C, thus sharing a similar pattern with the computed Ekman pumping during the same period of time. Nevertheless, a certain time lag is sometimes observed between SOT and Ekman pumping variations, especially in the early 2000s. The subsurface temperature should quickly respond to variations in wind-driven upwelling of warmer deep ocean water. However, we suggest that the response is slowed down because of heat exchange between the upwelled water and the much colder atmosphere and surface waters. Other factors like a significant change in the temperature of the deep-water masses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> may also have participated to the delay between the two records. We therefore argue that the SOT increase and associated warming of the EAP shelf resulted from two synergistic processes: (i) the enhanced penetration of warm deep waters on the shelf due to intensified wind-driven upwelling linked to a regional or global shift of the surface wind fields
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>), and (ii) the warming of Southern Ocean subsurface waters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> and CDW during the last century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also find that the most rapid and abrupt SOT warming reconstructed around the EAP ice shelf over the last centuries concurred with the Larsen B ice shelf collapse, thus strongly suggesting that a slight SOT increase, in concert with atmospheric warming, has been pivotal in controlling the Larsen B ice shelf instability. While we miss robust observation data prior the 1970s, the continuous SOT increase during phases of smaller collapses may imply that SOTs have potentially contributed to other smaller ice shelf collapses along the EAP and around Antarctica. Comparatively, cold SOTs as observed in the early 2000s, probably due to a dominant downwelling forcing, during a period of pronounced SAT cooling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, likely prevented further large ice shelf to collapse. Our results suggest that both the ocean (through wind-driven circulation and off-shelf water temperature changes) and atmosphere (through SAT and wind stress changes) forcing have closely acted together over the last decades to either strongly destabilize the EAP ice shelves or, inversely, to limit their dislocation.
 </p>
</sec>
