<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reanalysis data</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quality of reanalysis is relatively low before 1979 in the high latitudes of the Southern Hemisphere as few data were assimilated in this region due to the lack of observations. There is no observation data for the sub-superficial waters covering the last decades and century. We acknowledge that the reanalyses data that we use to reconstruct the wind-driven forcing on the SOT in this study are therefore relatively uncertain but should be robust enough to mirror the penetration of the WDW at least over the last decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. The Ekman pumping has been computed along the EAP continental shelf using surface wind velocities coming from the recent twentieth century reanalysis NOAA (20CR) Project version 2
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, consisting of an ensemble of 56 realizations with 2° x 2° gridded 6-hourly weather data from 1950 to 2010, and from the ERA-Interim version 2.0
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> reanalyses (see code in Supplementary file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). The definition of the Ekman pumping used is:
  <div id="Equa" class="disp-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M9" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${{w}}_{\mathrm{e}} = {\mathrm{curl}}\left( {\frac{{\mathbf{\tau}} }{{\rho _0f}}} \right)$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M10" display="block" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">w</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">curl</span>
     <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="bold" class="mi">τ</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msub">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">ρ</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mn">0</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mi">f</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8195_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where 
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">τ</span>
  </span> is the wind stress vector, 
  <span class="italic">ρ</span>
  <sub>0</sub> is a reference density of freshwater, 
  <span class="italic">f</span> is the Coriolis parameter. The unit of Ekman pumping 
  <span class="italic">w</span>
  <sub>e</sub> is m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span> but here it has been standardized by the standard deviation computed over the whole period of available data.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SOTs were estimated from both the GLORYS reanalysis and EN4 objective reanalysis, each covering a different time interval. GLORYS produces monthly global ocean reanalysis at eddy-permitting resolution from 1993 to 2010
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, while EN4 generates monthly data that covers the period between 1979 and 2010
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. GLORYS reanalysis is based on the ocean and sea-ice general circulation model NEMO in the ORCA025 configuration forced by surface boundary conditions derived from atmospheric ECMWF reanalysis, and on the assimilation of in situ temperature and salinity profiles observations as well as sea surface temperature from satellite measurements and sea-level anomalies obtained from satellite altimetry
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. EN4 data set is an incremental development of the previous version EN3 and consists of an objective analysis based on the temperature and salinity profiles derived from WOD09, GTSPP, Argo, and the ASBO project
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. SOT were estimated at a 50–400 m water depth range on the continental shelf, where the warm deep waters mix with the continental shelf waters before altering the grounded ice shelf stability (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
