<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref> presents descriptive statistics for climate change variables. The results indicate that university students have low knowledge and understanding of climate change (mean = 3.56; s.d. = 0.94). In support of this finding, Mower (
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) asserts that there is less literature on young people’s knowledge and perceptions of climate change. This implies that most of the literature available on climate change knowledge and perceptions is based on general public opinions. Mower (
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) further asserts that many students have a poor understanding of the details of global warming and the causes thereof. This is because in a study by Mower some students were unaware that CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is a greenhouse gas and a majority of students did not identify water vapour as a natural greenhouse gas. Numerous studies have established that young people often link the ozone hole and general pollution with anthropogenic climate change (Andersson &amp; Wallin 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Pekel &amp; Ozay 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). As a result, it can be established that students’ understanding of climate change is not convincing. Based on the comparison per faculty, it was discovered that students from the Faculty of Science and Agriculture have a better understanding of climate change (mean = 3.28; s.d. = 0.99) compared with students from the Faculty of Health Sciences (mean = 2.12; s.d. = 0.91) and the Faculty of Humanities (mean = 1.12; s.d. = 0.87). The findings are consistent with a similar study by Hargreaves et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>), who posited that people with a formal science qualification have a higher understanding of the process of climate change.
</p>
