<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Academic Life in Emergency Medicine (ALiEM) Faculty Incubator is an international professional development community of practice which involves 32 junior faculty members and 20 mentors to share an understanding of medical education and scholarship. During August and September 2018, the junior faculty educators and mentors of the program discussed the topic of feedback using an online discussion forum. Participation in the discussion was required for all of the junior faculty members. Mentors helped to facilitate discussion although participation was not strictly monitored. The titles of articles addressing feedback which were cited, shared, or recommended were compiled into a list. The authors also utilized social media (Twitter) by ‘tweeting’ requests to have participants of the free open access medical education (#FOAMed and #MedEd) online communities of practice provide suggestions for important papers on the topic of feedback [
  <a rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr" href="#REF9">9</a>]. Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="FIG1" href="#FIG1">1</a> demonstrates an example tweet from the call for articles that was placed via Twitter. Several papers were suggested by more than one modality. 
 </p>
 <div fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Twitter Call for Feedback Article</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="cureus-0011-00000004164-i01" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To ensure the selected papers would be of use to a wide variety of educators throughout their spectrum of their careers, we intentionally involved junior educators in addition to experts [
  <a rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr" href="#REF10">10</a>]. Our consensus group consisted of seven members, including four junior clinician educators (i.e. junior faculty members participating in the Faculty Incubator) as well as three experienced clinician educators (i.e. medical educators, all of whom have published &gt; 10 peer-reviewed publications, or serve as mentors in the ALiEM Faculty Incubator).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A three-round voting method akin to the Delphi methodology was utilized to determine consensus on the top eight papers [
  <a rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr" href="#REF11">11</a>]. All of the articles were read in full by all of this manuscript authors. The first round asked the raters to indicate the importance of each article on a seven-point Likert scale. The Likert scale was anchored at one by the statement "unimportant for junior faculty" and at seven by the statement "essential for junior faculty." In the second round, the participants were provided with the results of the first round including the percent of raters and frequency histogram displaying how each article had been rated. They were then asked to indicate if each article "must be included in the top papers" or "should not be included in the top papers." Participants in this second round could choose as many articles as they deemed appropriate to be included as the “must be included” papers. The third round consisted of the participants being given the results of the second round as a percentage of raters who indicated that each article must be included. They were then asked to select only their top eight papers which should be included in the article because they are the most important. Similar methods were used by the ALiEM Faculty Incubator in prior series [
  <a rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr" href="#REF12">12</a>-
  <a rid="REF23" ref-type="bibr" href="#REF23">23</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
