<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Not all invasive species respond to climate change in a similar way. For example, some invasive species are likely to be reduced in range due to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. The studies have suggested that American bullfrog and Burmese python will have reduced invasion potential under climate change scenarios [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. A recent study on Argentine ant invasions at global level have predicted reduced invasive potential, but there is potential for some regional expansions [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. On the contrary, increase in temperature expands range for some other invasive species like 
 <italic class="italic">Chromolaena odorata</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana camara</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. In the Indian scenario, studies speculate that change in climate will increase wetness and precipitation [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref078" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>], especially in the southern Western Ghats and some species will undergo shifts in their range in future [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref079" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. The MaxEnt model results suggests that the climate change (under RCP 6.0) is likely to increase land area at risk of invasion by up to 1.04%. Currently less suitable regions might become more suitable and vice-versa under changed climate, especially in peninsular India, and eastern India.
</p>
