<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To quantify the fluctuations in the ice cover from days to decades we have analysed satellite passive microwave data using a multifractal methodology [
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. We studied the Arctic equivalent sea-ice extent (EIE), where the EIE is defined as the total surface area, including land, north of the zonal-mean ice edge latitude and thus is proportional to the sine of the ice edge latitude [
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. (By studying the EIE one minimizes coastal effects.) We find that the EIE is a multifractal in time [
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] and thus cannot be explained as an auto-regressive process with a single time scale (a so-called AR-1 process), as is commonly used to characterize Arctic sea ice in GCMs [
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. An AR-1 process is inappropriate because (i) the existence of multiple time scales in the data cannot be treated in a quantitatively consistent manner with a single decay autocorrelation. (ii) The strength of the seasonal cycle is such that, if not appropriately removed, retrievals will always produce a single characteristic time of about a year; a time scale at which all moments converge. Hence, the upper bound on the persistence time in any study that assumes an AR-1 process will inevitably be approximately 1 year, as is indeed found for ice area [
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Separate studies with GCMs [
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTA20170332C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] also show that an upper bound exists on the predictability for the Arctic sea-ice cover and that predictability is 
 <italic class="italic">skilful</italic> only on the seasonal time scales. Therefore, our approach highlights the dangers of not carefully detrending the seasonality.
</p>
