<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We measured δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> values of 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> extending from present-day to Pre-Industrial historical records using both newly collected and herbarium material. This included collecting leaf material of 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> specimens (
 <italic>n</italic> = 142 collected between 1804 and 2017 with four unknown dates of collection) from across the Great Lakes region from herbaria (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Figs. 1A</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">1B</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-6">Table S1</xref>) and in natural present-day occurrences across a range of climate conditions (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-7">Table S2</xref>). 
 <italic>Thuja</italic> has small, 1–10 mm long scale-leaves adpressed along a small branch. Three cm portions of branches representing a single growth year with multiple scale-leaves were cleaned in an ultrasonic bath of deionized water to remove surface debris, oven dried at 50 °C for 48 h and homogenized; this removes any within-leaf isotopic variation. Aliquots of each 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> specimen (0.6–0.8 mg) were placed into tin capsules and placed in a Costech elemental analyzer to measure %C and %N (as well as C:N ratio). Second aliquots of each 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> specimen (0.6–0.8 mg) were placed into tin capsules and placed in a combustion module inlet coupled to a Picarro G2201-i cavity ring-down spectrometer (CRDS) to measure δ
 <sup>13</sup>C values of each specimen. Duplicates were run on both machines to insure homogeneity. Results of each CRDS run were internally calibrated using nine acetanilide standards (δ
 <sup>13</sup>C = −28.17 ± 0.16‰), two IAEA-600 caffeine standards (δ
 <sup>13</sup>C = −27.77 ± 0.04‰) and two IAEA-CH-6 sucrose standards (δ
 <sup>13</sup>C = −10.45 ± 0.03‰) in each run, as seen in 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Cotton, Sheldon &amp; Strömberg (2012)</xref> study. Reproducibility of replicate analyses was better than 0.3‰.
</p>
