<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Production variability in cereal crops in Queensland, Australia has been related to availability of precipitation and temperatures during the growing season (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yu et al., 2014</xref>). They found precipitation during the vegetative stage was the positive factor and most beneficial in determining grain yield, while exposure to high maximum temperatures depressed grain yields. Assessments of the future impacts of climate on agricultural productivity have been the subject of several recent summaries (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hatfield et al., 2011</xref>). These summaries have fostered extensive efforts to model the effects of future climate and have revealed that the continual increase in temperatures will depress wheat yields by 6% per °C increase (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Asseng et al., 2015</xref>). Increasing carbon dioxide levels will increase growth; however, the positive effects are often offset by exposure to high temperatures and reduced precipitation (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hatfield et al., 2011</xref>). The Great Plains of the United States represent one of the most extensive areas of wheat (
 <italic class="italic">Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) production. Historical yields across the Great Plains provide an opportunity to evaluate the change in production relative to climate trends and to determine the effect of a changing climate on grain yields. One potential avenue to evaluate yield response is to examine the change in the yield gap, defined as the difference between the potential and actual yield. 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Licker et al. (2010)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">van Brussel et al. (2015)</xref> have shown the value of yield gaps in being able to assess productivity in crops across the globe. 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hatfield et al. (2017)</xref> utilized yield gap analysis across the Midwest for corn (
 <italic class="italic">Zea mays</italic> L.) and soybean [
 <italic class="italic">Glycine max</italic> (L.) Merr.] to determine the relationship between yield gaps and the meteorological conditions during the growing season. They found that July maximum, August minimum, and July–August precipitation totals were the dominant factors explaining yield gaps in these two crops across the Midwest. They utilized these relationships to estimate the potential impact of a changing climate across the Midwest and found with increasing temperatures and more variable summer precipitation there would be significant decreases in corn and soybean production.
</p>
