<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32" class="p">In contrast, high population densities are related to urban expansion, in the present study and elsewhere (Svirejeva-Hopkins and Schellnhuber 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2008</xref>; Seto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">2012</xref>). This rapid increase in urban population is mainly due to large-scale migration of people from rural areas and smaller towns to bigger cities in search of better employment opportunities and better quality of life. Urban sprawl has resulted in loss of productive agricultural lands, open green spaces and surface water bodies (Castells et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" class="xref">2012</xref>). Growing populations are likely to exert pressure to clear forests, primarily because urbanization raises consumption levels and increases the demand for agricultural products (Satterthwaite et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2010</xref>). Urban consumers generally eat more processed foods and animal products than do rural consumers, thereby causing an increase in the commercial production of crops and livestock supported by the national or international supply chain. This relationship is expected to increase in the near future, considering the current population growth and the changes in food consumption in Mexico (Ibarrola-Rivas and Granados-Ramírez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2017</xref>). Across Latin America, the urban population is expected to grow (Inostroza et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2013</xref>), and this will increase pressure on tropical forests as has already occurred in Africa and Asia (Seto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">2012</xref>). As a result, if there are no improvements in the yields from Mexican agriculture, agricultural expansion would try to fulfil the demand for resources associated with urban population growth. Because much of the agriculture is of subsistence, Mexico should implement sustainable techniques of production to increase the yields. Otherwise, Mexico would depend on higher imports, impacting on food security. For instance, the OECD–FAO (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2017</xref>) suggests that Mexico will keep being dependent on maize, dairy products and oilseed imports.
</p>
