<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, the effects of climate variables on cholera disease in Qom, were evaluated. Since Qom is one of the main religious tourist cities, control of cholera is a strategic and important health issue. From July 1998 and after a huge outbreak in cholera in Qom with 836 cases, the surveillance system began to identify and document all positive cases officially. The health center of Qom province assumed responsibility for finding out the source of infection, monitoring, surveillance and controlling the disease. In the 19-year time period, five waves with a 3–4 year life cycle were happened, as has been recognized in India and Bangladesh with 3-year cycles and 3–6 year cycles, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Cholera infection can be transmitted by direct person-to-person contacts, using contaminated containers of water, unhealthy process of food preparation, or contact with contaminated environmental reservoir with persistence bacteria. However, pathways of transmission can be affected by climate conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. For example, high temperature can accelerate the growth and proliferation of pathogens in their habitats (e.g., raw food, water or environment). Rainfall can have a direct influence on transmission of cholera in two ways: first, high rainfall can increase the risk of contamination of either raw or treated water with wastewater (transmission of person-to-environment) and second, low rainfall can also increase the concentration of pathogens in water media (transmission of environment-to-person) [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. According to the results of correlation between monthly average of climate variables and the number of cholera cases, it is obvious that high temperature with low precipitation in dry season was the ideal climatic conditions for cholera infection. In the current study, a seasonal trend was apperceived, so that the highest number of cholera cases were observed during the summer to early fall (June to October). We hypothesized that an increase in air temperatures during summer created proper environmental conditions for bacterial growth and their survival through increasing salinity. On the other hand, considerable decreasing in precipitation and increasing evaporation during dry months could lead to reducing the amount of water in surface and groundwater sources. In overall, these changes in climatic conditions could lead to increasing salinity, organic matter and aqueous temperatures and subsequent growth and proliferation of pathogens, decreasing raw water quality and increasing bacterial concentration in open water wells and the other water resources. In this regard, using contaminated and untreated water for residential consuming or irrigating vegetation could lead to increasing the risk of cholera disease incidence in high risk people. In different recent studies, environmental variables were known as most important factors in incidence of cholera. Indeed, seasonality was introduced as a stronger parameter which leads to increasing in cholera outbreaks generally during warm months [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The positive correlation between monthly average of temperature and cholera infection was observed in this study, which well proved by findings from East Africa, Zambia and South China [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In the case of precipitation, other studies found that heavy rainfall as an important parameter on cholera incidence can lead to flooding and affect water quality and sanitation systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Although, the effect of low precipitation in increasing the risk of cholera disease described in this study, was supported by recent findings in Bangladesh and Iran [
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224813.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
