<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">By including landscape inertia, our results suggest the maritime forests of the Pacific Northwest may remain relatively stable with climate change over the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century in the absence of stand-replacing disturbances such as wildfire. Examining vegetation potential, as in MC2, provides a useful initial perspective, in part because such projections can help land managers evaluate the likelihood of success in attaining current and future social, economic, and ecological goals (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209490.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>). Furthermore, recent MC2 work has illustrated the importance of simulating wildfire, climate, and vegetation dynamically (rather than keeping any of those variables static) to better capture how wildfire and vegetation can influence each other through time [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. However, a consequence of this modeling approach is that MC2 generally projects more rapid changes in vegetation than is likely realistic (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209490.g005" class="xref">5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209490.g006" class="xref">6</xref>). In contrast, including landscape inertia in the cSTSMs prevented widespread vegetation shifts until a major disturbance event occurred. This difference in vegetation shifts by either including or ignoring inertia was also found by [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>] using a spatially explicit wildfire model. We believe that including landscape inertia is more consistent with the biophysical processes in the study area, since broad-scale changes in vegetation communities are most likely after the infrequent stand-replacing disturbances that characterize some systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>].
</p>
