<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6601870</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31173074</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evz118</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evz118</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Population Genomic Signatures of Genetic Structure and Environmental Selection in the Catadromous Roughskin Sculpin <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yu-Long</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evz118-FM1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Dong-Xiu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evz118-FM1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Bai-Dong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Jin-Xian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz118-aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evz118-cor1"/><!--<email>jinxianliu@gmail.com</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Piontkivska</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="evz118-aff1"><label>1</label>CAS Key Laboratory of Marine Ecology and Environmental Sciences, Institute of Oceanology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Qingdao, China</aff><aff id="evz118-aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory for Marine Ecology and Environmental Science, Qingdao National Laboratory for Marine Science and Technology, Qingdao, China</aff><aff id="evz118-aff3"><label>3</label>Center for Ocean Mega-Science, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Qingdao, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="evz118-cor1">Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>jinxianliu@gmail.com</email>.</corresp><fn id="evz118-FM1"><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-06-07"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>11</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1751</fpage><lpage>1764</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="evz118.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Understanding the patterns of genetic diversity and adaptation across species&#x02019; range is crucial to assess its long-term persistence and determine appropriate conservation measures. The impacts of human activities on the genetic diversity and genetic adaptation to heterogeneous environments remain poorly understood in the marine realm. The roughskin sculpin (<italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic>) is a small catadromous fish, and has been listed as a second-class state protected aquatic animal since 1988 in China. To elucidate the underlying mechanism of population genetic structuring and genetic adaptations to local environments, RAD tags were sequenced for 202 individuals in nine populations across the range of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> in China. The pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values over 9,271 filtered SNPs were significant except that between Dongying and Weifang. All the genetic clustering analysis revealed significant population structure with high support for eight distinct genetic clusters. Both the minor allele frequency spectra and <italic>N</italic>e estimations suggested extremely small <italic>N</italic>e in some populations (e.g., Qinhuangdao, Rongcheng, Wendeng, and Qingdao), which might result from recent population bottleneck. The strong genetic structure can be partly attributed to genetic drift and habitat fragmentation, likely due to the anthropogenic activities. Annotations of candidate adaptive loci suggested that genes involved in metabolism, development, and osmoregulation were critical for adaptation to spatially heterogenous environment of local populations. In the context of anthropogenic activities and environmental change, results of the present population genomic work provided important contributions to the understanding of genetic differentiation and adaptation to changing environments.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>population structure</kwd><kwd>local adaptation</kwd><kwd><italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic></kwd><kwd>habitat fragmentation</kwd><kwd>RAD-seq</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Natural Science Foundation of China</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id>31502169</award-id><award-id>41776171</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">NSFC-Shandong Joint Fund for Marine Ecology and Environmental Sciences</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id>U1606404</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">AoShan Talents Program</named-content></funding-source><award-id>2015ASTP-ES05</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>When different populations experience heterogeneous environments, local selection regimes can drive phenotypic divergence and modulate the underlying genomic architecture, thereby promoting local adaptation and ultimately initiating evolutionary diversification and speciation (<xref rid="evz118-B87" ref-type="bibr">Schluter 2000</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B32" ref-type="bibr">Ferchaud and Hansen 2016</xref>). Detecting selection is an important step toward understanding the genetic basis of adaptive traits and the potential vulnerability or resilience of biodiversity to environment change (<xref rid="evz118-B17" ref-type="bibr">Brauer et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B7" ref-type="bibr">Attard et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B84" ref-type="bibr">Sandoval-Castillo et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Reduction in genetic diversity can compromise the potential of a population to evolutionarily adapt to changing environments (<xref rid="evz118-B3" ref-type="bibr">Allendorf and Luikart 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B76" ref-type="bibr">Ouborg et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B5" ref-type="bibr">Angeloni et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). Small and isolated populations are potentially faced with high extinction risks, due to the strong impact of genetic drift and inbreeding with low level of genetic variation (<xref rid="evz118-B37" ref-type="bibr">Frankham et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B76" ref-type="bibr">Ouborg et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>). Climate change and habitat loss are among the most important factors resulting in biodiversity decline (<xref rid="evz118-B10" ref-type="bibr">Barbosa et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Evolutionary adaptations from standing genetic variation over generations are crucial for species to respond to the new or altered environments, leading to the expression of environment-dependent phenotypes (<xref rid="evz118-B11" ref-type="bibr">Barrett and Schluter 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B42" ref-type="bibr">Harrisson et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B10" ref-type="bibr">Barbosa et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Population with low level of genetic diversity is potentially faced with low effective population size (<italic>N</italic>e). <italic>N</italic>e is a key parameter to understand evolutionary processes and the viability of the overexploited and endangered populations as it determines the rate of genetic drift and inbreeding (<xref rid="evz118-B8" ref-type="bibr">Baalsrud et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). For population with low <italic>N</italic>e, the most important evolutionary forces are genetic drift and inbreeding, both leading to rapid loss of genetic diversity, which will result in a low-fitness risk of the population (<xref rid="evz118-B71" ref-type="bibr">McMahon et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Estimates of <italic>N</italic>e can be theoretically useful to predict the impact of management practices on the loss of genetic variability due to the anthropogenic induced effects of random drift of the overexploited and endangered fishery species (<xref rid="evz118-B79" ref-type="bibr">Pita et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). For species long&#x02010;term persistence, there is a need to maximize genetic variability of species in order to maximize evolutionary potential. In addition, the long-term viability is also dependent on local adaptation, and genetic variability may be expected to decrease but would not limit long term evolutionary potential. Considering the importance of genetic diversity, it is essential and is the first step to appropriately define conservation units (CUs) to help guide management and conservation efforts (<xref rid="evz118-B3" ref-type="bibr">Allendorf and Luikart 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B38" ref-type="bibr">Funk et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). With the rapid development of high-throughput next-generation sequencing (NGS), genome-wide data make it easier to integrate information from neutral and adaptive loci to characterize CUs within a population genetics framework (<xref rid="evz118-B38" ref-type="bibr">Funk et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). <xref rid="evz118-B38" ref-type="bibr">Funk et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> proposed the delineation of three categories of CUs using genomic data: Evolutionarily significant units (ESUs) are defined using all the loci, maintenance of different ESUs will maximize evolutionary potential, management units (MUs) are defined using the neutral loci and are the basis for the short&#x02010;term management of populations, and adaptive units (AUs) are defined using the adaptive loci and are intended to help with protection of adaptive processes (<xref rid="evz118-B72" ref-type="bibr">Moritz 2004</xref>; Funk et al. <xref rid="evz118-B38" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Maintenance of different CUs will help maximize genetic variability of species in the face of environmental change.</p><p>The roughskin sculpin (<italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel 1837), belonging to the family Cottidae, is a small carnivorous catadromous fish dwelling on the bottom of water (<xref rid="evz118-B93" ref-type="bibr">Wang 1999</xref>). <italic>Trachidermus</italic><italic>fasciatus</italic> migrates from freshwater toward estuary and spawns in empty bivalve shells in winter, then the juveniles move upstream in spring to freshwater for growth (<xref rid="evz118-B89" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al. 1980</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B75" ref-type="bibr">Onikura et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). When <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> migrates from freshwater toward estuary, it stops exogenous nutrition ingestion and its digestive organs show an involution in various degrees (<xref rid="evz118-B60" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 1984</xref>). The thyroid gland of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> changes seasonally in close relation to the seaward migration (<xref rid="evz118-B88" ref-type="bibr">Shao 1978</xref>). According to historical records, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> was widely distributed along the coastlines of the Bohai Sea, the Yellow Sea, and the East China Sea as well as in rivers connected to seas (<xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>). However, it has experienced severe population declines, habitat fragmentation and local extinctions in the past decades, probably due to human-mediated environmental change such as water pollution, dam construction, and blockage of migration channel (<xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>). Besides, under the background of global climate change and human activities, runoff volume of some rivers (e.g., Dagu River-Qingdao, Luan River-Qinhuangdao, Wei River-Weifang) has been sharply reduced since recent decades, and drying-up of the river course has occurred frequently (<xref rid="evz118-B48" ref-type="bibr">Jiang and Wang 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B65" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). This condition has seriously threatened the migration of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, and probably resulted in changes of life history of some <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> populations (e.g., Qingdao, Weifang, and Rongcheng population) from catadromous to noncatadromous. Considering its great biological, ecological, and economic importance in China, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> had been included in the List of the Wildlife under Special State Protection as a second-class state protected aquatic animal by Chinese government in 1988.</p><p>In previous studies, researchers had studied population structure and estimated demographic parameters of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, mainly based on presumably neutral DNA-based markers (<xref rid="evz118-B99" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B102" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B39" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B62" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). In our previous study, we found significant population structure and five genetic clusters among seven populations in China based on 16 microsatellite loci (<xref rid="evz118-B62" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). The five genetic clusters have presumably evolved from standing genetic variation of the same genetic lineage following deglaciation around 120,000&#x02009;years ago (<xref rid="evz118-B39" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). To date, few studies were conducted to estimate the genetic effective population size (<italic>N</italic>e) of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, likely due to the lack of power of genome-wide genotyping methods. Moreover, previous studies restricted to neutral markers can provide only limited insight to the mechanisms of local adaptation. Across its widely distributed range for <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, the temperature, salinity, the levels of pollution, and pathogen conditions are largely different (<xref rid="evz118-B9" ref-type="bibr">Bao et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>). Heterogeneous environment can result in patterns of localized adaptive divergence of populations (<xref rid="evz118-B86" ref-type="bibr">Savolainen et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B84" ref-type="bibr">Sandoval-Castillo et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). In these circumstances, to improve the precision and accuracy of estimating a variety of important population genetic parameters and elucidating the mechanisms of local adaption of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, genomic tools as one promising approach may assist by increasing the number of variable genetic markers including both neutral and nonneutral loci. Restriction site-associated DNA tags sequencing (RAD-seq) is one of the rapid and cost-effective methods for genome-wide single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) discovery and genotyping of nonmodel species without reference genomes (<xref rid="evz118-B20" ref-type="bibr">Catchen et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B56" ref-type="bibr">Larson et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B70" ref-type="bibr">McKinney et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>).</p><p>In the present study, nine <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> populations were collected from its entire natural habitats in China. A comprehensive and high-resolution genome-wide assessment of population genetic status of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> was conducted at both neutral loci and putative adaptive loci generated from RAD sequencing. We specifically aimed to address two questions that should have broad implications to conservation and management of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>. First, do <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> exhibit fine genetic structure and what is the status of <italic>N</italic>e for different populations? Second, how the populations genetically adapted to local heterogeneous environments? The results of the present population genomic study can contribute to the understanding of genetic differentiation of aquatic species under anthropogenic activities and their adaptation to changing environments.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Sampling and RAD Sequencing</title><p>A total of 202 individuals of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> were collected from nine sites across its range-distribution in China during 2013&#x02013;2017 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Tissues (including fin clips and muscles) were kept individually in 95% ethanol and stored at &#x02013;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Genomic DNA samples were extracted following the standard phenol-chloroform extraction method. DNA extracts were visualized on 1% agarose gels to assess quality and were subsequently quantified using Qubit Fluorometer. Paired-end RAD (RPE) libraries were prepared followed the protocol as described by <xref rid="evz118-B29" ref-type="bibr">Etter et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref>. Briefly, genomic DNA was digested with the restriction enzyme <italic>Eco</italic>RI, and fragments were then ligated to Illumina P1 adapter with individual-specific index. Adapter-ligated fragments were subsequently pooled and randomly sheared, end repaired, dA added and ligated to Illumina P2 adapter. The fragments with both P1 and P2 adapter were enriched using high-fidelity PCR amplification. The RPE libraries were then sequenced on Illumina HiSeq machine at Novogene (Beijing, China).
</p><fig id="evz118-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 1.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Map of the sampling location for nine populations of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic>. Figure was generated by Ocean Data View 5.0.0 (Schlitzer, R., Ocean Data View, odv.awi.de, 2018).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz118f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>RAD Data Processing, Genotyping, and SNP Filtering</title><p>Raw reads from Illumina runs were demultiplexed into separated files according to individuals&#x02019; indexes. Reads with adaptors were removed using Cutadapt (<xref rid="evz118-B69" ref-type="bibr">Martin 2011</xref>), and further cleaned using &#x0201c;process_radtags&#x0201d; of Stacks 1.48 (<xref rid="evz118-B21" ref-type="bibr">Catchen et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>) with a score limit of 13 and windows size of 0.1. Only those reads with sufficiently high sequencing quality, and that had an unambiguous RAD site, were retained. Finally, reads were processed using &#x0201c;clone_filter&#x0201d; of Stacks to remove potential PCR duplications.</p><p>RAD contigs were assembled using an optimized method as implemented in RADassembler (<xref rid="evz118-B63" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). This pipeline software uses Stacks to cluster reads from multiple individuals, and uses CAP3 (<xref rid="evz118-B46" ref-type="bibr">Huang and Madan 1999</xref>) to do local de novo assembly, which makes full use of the advantages of RPE reads. The optimal similarity thresholds for clustering within and across individuals were chosen using &#x0201c;chooseM&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;chooseN&#x0201d; functions of RADassembler. Reads were then aligned to the assembled contigs using BWA-MEM 0.7.15 (<xref rid="evz118-B58" ref-type="bibr">Li 2013</xref>) with default parameters, and were subsequently processed by SAMtools 1.7 (<xref rid="evz118-B59" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>). SNP calling were performed using BCFtools in SAMtools. The generated SNPs were stored in a Variant Call Format (VCF) file.</p><p>In order to remove SNPs of low qualities, which might be resulted from false calling or paralogs, the following cut-offs were applied using in house Perl script (accessed at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/lyl8086/VCF_filter">https://github.com/lyl8086/VCF_filter</ext-link>; Last accessed June 5, 2019): 1) only biallelic SNPs were retained; 2) SNP quality&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;30; 3) minimum coverage depth for an individual&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;6; 4) minimum genotype quality (GQ) for an individual&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;15; 5) minimum individual coverage for a population&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;12, that is at least 12 individuals were required to be genotyped for a SNP in each population; 6) total missing rate for all individuals of each SNP&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.1; 7) maximum observed heterozygosity (<italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>) for each population&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.5; 8) minor allele frequency (MAF)&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.05, but SNPs with MAF&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.2 in at least one population were retained. The final VCF file was converted into other formats necessary for subsequent analyses using PGDSpider 2.0.1.0 (<xref rid="evz118-B64" ref-type="bibr">Lischer and Excoffier 2012</xref>) and Plink 1.90b5.3 (<xref rid="evz118-B82" ref-type="bibr">Purcell et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>). To minimize the effect of linkage disequilibrium (LD) for structure analysis, only one SNP with the lowest missing rate was retained for each RAD locus using in house Shell script and VCFtools 0.1.17 (<xref rid="evz118-B25" ref-type="bibr">Danecek et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genetic Diversity and Differentiation</title><p>Genetic diversity statistics within populations, including nucleotide diversity (<italic>P</italic>i), observed (<italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>) and expected heterozygosity (<italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>) and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub>, were estimated using &#x0201c;populations&#x0201d; in Stacks. Pairwise genetic differentiation (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) between populations and their significance were evaluated using Arlequin 3.5.2.2 (<xref rid="evz118-B31" ref-type="bibr">Excoffier and Lischer 2010</xref>) with 10,000 permutations. To further evaluate population subdivision, we performed an analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) as implemented in Arlequin. To estimate differentiation among groups (<italic>F</italic><sub>CT</sub>) and differentiation among populations within groups (<italic>F</italic><sub>SC</sub>), three groups were defined considering both the geographic origin of populations (the Bohai sea, the Yellow sea and the East China sea) and geographic distance among them (see <xref rid="evz118-T3" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;3</xref> for grouping details).</p><table-wrap id="evz118-T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Analysis of Molecular Variance (AMOVA) Performed for Three Groups (&#x0201c;Dandong, Dalian, Qinhuangdao, Dongying and Weifang,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Rongcheng and Wendeng, Qingdao,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;Fuyang&#x0201d;), and among All Populations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source of Variation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum of Squares</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variance Components</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage Variation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fixation Index</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Among three groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,032.974</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.146</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>CT</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<bold>0.0615</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Among populations within three groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,613.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.707</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>SC</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<bold>0.0560</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Among nine populations</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,645.992</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.976</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>ST</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<bold>0.0936</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>
<sc>Note</sc>.&#x02014;Significant <italic>F</italic>-statistic values were in bold (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.001).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Inference of population structure and individual assignment were carried out using three methods. Firstly, a model-based maximum likelihood method implemented in Admixture (<xref rid="evz118-B2" ref-type="bibr">Alexander et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>) was used to estimate individual ancestries, which calculates estimates much more rapidly using a fast numerical optimization algorithm. The number of genetic clusters (<italic>K</italic>) was tested for values ranging from 1 to 10 with ten replications for each tested <italic>K</italic> value. In order to accurately estimate the true number of subpopulations, four supervised estimators (MedMedK, MedMeaK, MaxMedK, MaxMeaK) of <xref rid="evz118-B81" ref-type="bibr">Puechmaille (2016)</xref> were used to assess the most likely number of <italic>K</italic> implemented in StructureSelector (<xref rid="evz118-B61" ref-type="bibr">Li and Liu 2018</xref>). StructureSelector also used Clumpak (<xref rid="evz118-B54" ref-type="bibr">Kopelman et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) to generate plots for the selected <italic>K</italic>. Secondly, discriminant analysis of principal components (DAPC) method implemented in the R package Adegenet 2.1.0 (<xref rid="evz118-B49" ref-type="bibr">Jombart 2008</xref>) was used to visualize relationships among groups of samples and assign individuals to these groups. The alpha-score procedure was applied to select an appropriate number of principal components (PCs) as suggested by the manual. Thirdly, to visualize large and fine-scale patterns of population structure, NetView P 0.7.1 (<xref rid="evz118-B90" ref-type="bibr">Steinig et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) was used to visualize network relationships among all individuals with kNN step from 5 to 30. All the above structure analyses were performed on both all loci and neutral loci.</p></sec><sec><title>
<italic>N</italic>e Estimation and MAF Spectrum</title><p>Contemporary effective population size (<italic>N</italic>e) for each population was calculated with NeEstimator v2 (<xref rid="evz118-B26" ref-type="bibr">Do et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). This program implements three single-sample methods that based on LD, heterozygote excess, and molecular coancestry. Data sets with one SNP per locus were used to estimate <italic>N</italic>e, and three MAF limits (0.05, 0.01, and 0) were applied. Furthermore, in order to provide an illustration of the extent to which populations exhibit an L-shaped distribution, MAF spectrum for each population were plotted in R 3.5.0 (<xref rid="evz118-B83" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team 2018</xref>). MAF spectrum is expected to be L-shaped distribution due to the mutation&#x02013;drift equilibrium (<xref rid="evz118-B74" ref-type="bibr">Nei et&#x000a0;al. 1976</xref>). Deviations from an L-shaped distribution would indicate a population bottleneck (<xref rid="evz118-B67" ref-type="bibr">Luikart et&#x000a0;al. 1998</xref>). In order not to bias allele frequency spectra, we did not set a lower minor allele threshold for the SNPs used in MAF calculation, the generated results were visualized in R.</p></sec><sec><title>Outlier Detection, Annotation, and Delimitation of CUs</title><p>To identify putative loci under selection, two genome scan methods were applied. Firstly, the <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>-based method implemented in BayeScan 2.1 (<xref rid="evz118-B35" ref-type="bibr">Foll and Gaggiotti 2008</xref>) was used to identify high-<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> outliers. BayeScan identifies outlier loci with a Bayesian model that decomposing <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> coefficients into a population-specific component (beta) shared by all loci, and a locus-specific component (alpha) shared by all the populations using a logistic regression. BayeScan was performed using default parameters, and outlier loci were identified using a posterior odds of 10 with a 5% FDR. Secondly, a genotype&#x02013;environment association method as implemented in Bayenv 2.0 (<xref rid="evz118-B24" ref-type="bibr">Coop et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>) was used to identify putative loci correlated with environmental variations. Bayenv implements a Bayesian method that estimates the empirical pattern of covariance in allele frequencies between populations, and then uses this pattern as a null model for a test at individual SNPs. Four environmental variables were used for the tests of genotype&#x02013;environment associations, including latitude, longitude, annual mean sea surface temperature (ASST) and mean sea surface temperature during catadromous period (CSST, from November to April, <xref rid="evz118-B95" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2001</xref>). The high-resolution SST data (long term mean SST from 1971 to 2000) provided by the NOAA/OAR/ESRL PSD, Boulder, Colorado, USA, from their web site at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/">https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/</ext-link> (last accessed June 5, 2019) was used. Because minor alleles may also be useful for identifying selection in naturally occurring organisms (<xref rid="evz118-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahrens 2018</xref>), and alleles associated with environment can be significantly rarer than the common allele (<xref rid="evz118-B36" ref-type="bibr">Fournier-Level et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), we did not set a MAF cut-off on the data used in Bayenv tests (but a minimum of three copies of rare allele were required in at least one population in order to minimize genotyping errors). A Bayes Factor (BF)&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;20 was required for the selection of outliers as evidence for &#x0201c;strong support,&#x0201d; following <xref rid="evz118-B50" ref-type="bibr">Kass and Raftery (1995)</xref>. Three replicates were applied for Bayenv tests, and only those SNPs consistently screened out as outliers were retained.</p><p>Contig sequences containing outlier SNPs were then used for BLAST searches using local BLAST+ (<xref rid="evz118-B18" ref-type="bibr">Camacho et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>) implemented in SequenceServer (<xref rid="evz118-B80" ref-type="bibr">Priyam et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) with an e-value of 1e&#x02013;5. For the sequences with multiple matches, only the best hits were retained. Two reference sequences were used as the query database: Firstly, the complementary DNA (cDNA) sequences of <italic>Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic> from Ensembl (<xref rid="evz118-B103" ref-type="bibr">Zerbino et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), we chose it because the phylogenetic relationship between Cottales and Gasterosteales was close as described in <xref rid="evz118-B15" ref-type="bibr">Betancur-R et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> and the genome of <italic>G. aculeatus</italic> was well annotated; secondly, transcriptome reads of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> from <xref rid="evz118-B68" ref-type="bibr">Ma et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> were de novo assembled into transcripts using Trinity 2.6.6 (<xref rid="evz118-B40" ref-type="bibr">Grabherr et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>), and were then used as the database. Loci not matched to the first database were then searched against the second database (transcripts), and the aligned transcript sequences of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> were then searched against the cDNA of <italic>G. aculeatus</italic>. The sequences with blasted hits were annotated using the UniProtKB database (<xref rid="evz118-B91" ref-type="bibr">The UniProt Consortium 2018</xref>), and were further categorized by a gene ontology (GO) term analysis implemented in Blast2Go (<xref rid="evz118-B23" ref-type="bibr">Conesa et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>) with default parameters.</p><p>Three categories of CUs were defined based on different sets of loci. Firstly, the Delta K method (<xref rid="evz118-B30" ref-type="bibr">Evanno et&#x000a0;al. 2005</xref>) was used to determine the most likely uppermost level of hierarchical population structure using the results of Admixture based on all loci for defining ESUs. A principal components analysis (PCA) was also performed to confirm the high-level genetic distinctiveness using GCTA (<xref rid="evz118-B100" ref-type="bibr">Yang et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>). Secondly, MUs were defined according to the structure analysis results based on the neutral loci. Thirdly, to identify patterns of adaptive differentiation among populations, and to further define AUs, structure analysis was performed based on &#x0201c;adaptive loci.&#x0201d; We used only the high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> outliers as the putative adaptive loci following the method used in <xref rid="evz118-B10" ref-type="bibr">Barbosa et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref>, in which the high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> outliers were used to determine AUs. The high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> outliers were identified by BayeScan as being under directional selection. Inference of genetic clusters was carried using Admixture and the best <italic>K</italic> was accessed and visualized in StructureSelector.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>RAD Sequencing and Genotyping</title><p>RAD sequencing of 202 <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> individuals resulted in 1,448,111,215 read pairs, and 812,744,207 read pairs were retained after quality filtering. A total of 635,367,008 read pairs were discarded due to low quality, PCR duplications or ambiguous RAD tags. Using RADassembler, the optimal numbers of mismatch for clustering within and across individuals were set to 6 and 6, respectively, that is, <italic>M</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 and <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 in Stacks. A total of 172,441 RAD loci were assembled and retained, with a mean contig length of 529&#x02009;bp and N50 of 561&#x02009;bp. After mapping read pairs of each individual to the generated RAD contigs, 2,057,173 SNPs were called. Of these, 13,681 SNPs passed the quality cut-off and were retained. The SNPs were with a mean depth of 57.65 and total genotyping rate of 93.93%. After retaining one SNP from each locus with the lowest missing rate, 9,271 SNPs were kept in a total of 202 individuals across nine sampling locations. These 9,271 SNPs (total genotyping rate&#x02009;=&#x02009;94.13%) were used for downstream structure analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Population Genetic Diversity and Structure</title><p>Estimates of <italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub> and <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub> average over the filtered 13,681 loci varied across the nine sampling locations (<italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1135&#x02013;0.1543, <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1039&#x02013;0.1382, <xref rid="evz118-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Nucleotide diversity (<italic>P</italic>i&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1066&#x02013;0.1418) were similar to <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>, and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> were not high across all the sites. Qingdao showed the lowest <italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>, <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>, and <italic>P</italic>i, indicating the lowest genetic diversity among the nine populations. Rongcheng, Wendeng, Qingdao, and Fuyang displayed generally low level of percentage of polymorphic loci (46.69&#x02013;58.48%), suggesting that lots of SNPs were monomorphic with one allele fixed, likely resulting from small populations after bottlenecks.</p><table-wrap id="evz118-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of Genetic Diversity Statistics for Nine Populations of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pop ID</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variant Sites</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Polymorphic Loci</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Num Indv</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>H</italic>
<sub>O</sub>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>H</italic>
<sub>E</sub>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>i</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>IS</sub>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<italic>e</italic><sub>LD</sub> (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dandong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2361</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1231</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infinite (&#x0221e;)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dalian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4955</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2591.1 (2062.7&#x02013;3481.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qinhuangdao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.9629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1335</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1543</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1382</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1418</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0 (31.8&#x02013;32.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dongying</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.4609</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5243</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1350</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1298</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1329</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">512.8 (485.1&#x02013;543.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weifang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.2973</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1374</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1292</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0186</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">313.9 (301.7&#x02013;327.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rongcheng</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.7356</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8 (23.7&#x02013;23.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wendeng</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.4753</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4057</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1310</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0414</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (6.8&#x02013;6.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qingdao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6852</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5603</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.3 (98.3&#x02013;102.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuyang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,681</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0865</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5565</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0091</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1766.0 (1391.6&#x02013;2414.6)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><p>
<sc>Note</sc>.&#x02014;Variant Sites, number of total SNPs; % Polymorphic Loci, proportion of SNPs in this populations; Num Indv, number of genotyped individuals averaged over all SNPs; <italic>H</italic><sub>O</sub>, observed heterozygosity; <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>, expected heterozygosity; <italic>P</italic>i, nucleotide diversity; <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub>, inbreeding coefficient of individuals relative to the subpopulation; N<italic>e</italic><sub>LD</sub>, effective populations size estimated based on LD method.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Most of the pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values over 9,271 SNPs between populations were significant (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.0014 after B-Y FDR correction), except that between Dongying and Weifang. <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> ranged from &#x02013;0.0038 between the two closest populations (Dongying and Weifang) to 0.1916 between Qingdao and Fuyang (<xref rid="evz118-T2" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;2</xref>). The <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> across all populations was 0.0936 and was statistically significant (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.001). The hierarchical AMOVA (<xref rid="evz118-T3" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;3</xref>) showed strong and significant differentiation among the three groups of populations (<italic>F</italic><sub>CT</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0615, <italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.001).</p><table-wrap id="evz118-T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> Values Over 9,271 SNPs across Nine Populations of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dandong</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dalian</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qinhuangdao</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dongying</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weifang</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rongcheng</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wendeng</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qingdao</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuyang</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dandong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dalian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0405</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qinhuangdao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0592</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0401</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dongying</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0393</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0335</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0502</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weifang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0437</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0259</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0401</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.0038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rongcheng</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1130</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1108</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1270</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0980</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1056</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wendeng</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0988</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1033</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1199</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0832</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0895</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.0702</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qingdao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1358</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1396</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1574</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1336</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1424</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1429</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1077</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fuyang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1045</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1283</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1404</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1213</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1189</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1764</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1676</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.1916</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><p>
<sc>Note</sc>.&#x02014;Values in bold were significant after FDR correction (<italic>P&#x02009;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x02009;</italic>0.0014).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The analysis using Admixture and StructureSelector indicated that there were highest supports for eight genetic groups (MedMedK, MedMeaK, MaxMedK, MaxMeaK&#x02009;=&#x02009;8, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) among individuals. The major mode for <italic>K&#x02009;</italic>=<italic>&#x02009;</italic>8 generated by Clumpak followed the patterns as indicated by the pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values: Dongying and Weifang formed into one group, and the other seven populations came out as distinct groups respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2<italic>b</italic></xref>). DAPC analysis retained 13 PCs based on the alpha-score, which explained 25.45% of the total variance. The patterns of DAPC scatter plots were similar to the results revealed by Admixture, individuals of each population formed into distinct clusters respectively, except those from Dongying and Weifang (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>), and several individuals of Rongcheng and Wendeng were overlapped. NetView P was able to reveal fine-scale clustering with kNN&#x02009;=&#x02009;20 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), individuals were grouped into eight different clusters, with most individuals from Dongying and Weifang clustered together. Both Fuyang and Qingdao displayed little connections with other populations, suggesting that the two populations might be highly isolated, which also showed high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values (&#x0003e; 0.1) in comparison with other populations.
</p><fig id="evz118-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 2.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Plots of the individual ancestry inference for (<italic>a</italic>) <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 based on all loci; (<italic>b</italic>) <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8 based on all loci; and (<italic>c</italic>) <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 based on high-<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> adaptive loci in nine populations of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz118f2"/></fig><fig id="evz118-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 3.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;DAPC scatter plots with prior population information. The plots were generated using 13 principle components with the first three coordinate axes based on all loci (explained 25.45% of the total variance).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz118f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>
<italic>N</italic>e Estimation and MAF Spectrum</title><p>Estimations of <italic>N</italic>e were varying across the sampling sites, and the MAF constraint had little effect on the values of <italic>N</italic>e, thus the results with no MAF cut-off were used. The <italic>N</italic>e ranged from 6.8 (Wendeng, 95% CI 6.8&#x02013;6.9) to infinite (Dandong, 95% CI infinite; <xref rid="evz118-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Rongcheng, Wendeng, and Qingdao displayed generally small <italic>N</italic>e, which might result from small population size and subsample effect (<xref rid="evz118-B53" ref-type="bibr">Kjeldsen et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). The estimations of <italic>N</italic>e were consistent with the pattern of genetic diversity, with Rongcheng, Wendeng, and Qingdao all showed low levels of <italic>H</italic>o, <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>, and <italic>P</italic>i. MAF spectra generally exhibited L-shaped distributions, but varied markedly among populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). A certain number of rare alleles (&#x0003e; 15%) were observed in Qinhuangdao, Rongcheng, Wendeng, Qingdao, and Fuyang, suggesting small effective population size or newly founded populations. Specially, distributions of MAF spectra in Wendeng and Qingdao were much more distorted than the other populations, indicating potential bottlenecks with small <italic>N</italic>e. These results were consistent with the estimates of genome-wide <italic>H</italic><sub>E</sub>, <italic>P</italic>i, and percentage of polymorphic loci within populations (<xref rid="evz118-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>).
</p><fig id="evz118-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 4.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;SNP minor allele frequency (MAF) spectrum for nine populations of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus.</italic> The <italic>x</italic>-axis represents categories of MAF with the corresponding allele counts on the <italic>y</italic>-axis. Color in black represents MAF&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;15%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz118f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Candidate Loci under Selection and Delimitation of CUs</title><p>BayeScan detected a total 56 outlier SNPs, of these 9 SNPs were potentially under balancing selection and 47 SNPs were potentially under divergent selection with posterior odds&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;10 and FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). To minimize false positives, only loci under divergent selection were used. Bayenv consistently identified 282 SNPs correlated with environmental variables after three independent replicates, of these 56 SNPs were associated with latitude, 18 SNPs were longitude related, 164 SNPs were ASST related, and 236 SNPs were CSST related. There were little overlaps between SNPs related with longitude and with other environmental variables (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), whereas most of the ASST and CSST related SNPs were shared with each other (149 SNPs). Thereafter we used the combined results from BayeScan and Bayenv as the candidate adaptive loci, which corresponded to 313 SNPs from 300 RAD loci. Contig sequences of these loci were then used for further annotations.</p><p>Of the 300 candidate RAD loci, 69 were directly mapped to 59 cDNA of stickleback. A total of 136 of the remaining 231 loci were aligned to 135 transcripts of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, and 48 of these loci were further aligned to 48 cDNA of stickleback. In total, 117 of the 300 candidate RAD loci were aligned to 105 cDNAs (genes) of stickleback genome. These genes were found to be involved in diverse functions, and were putatively involved in local adaptive processes of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>. Using Blast2Go, 74 loci were annotated and assigned to 138 GO terms. Most of the candidate loci containing SNPs putatively under selection could be categorized as having functions associated with catalytic activity, binding and hydrolase activity functions; cellular metabolic processes, biological regulation, development and response to simulation; or transport, signal transduction, cell communication and biosynthetic process (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). These biological processes are potentially influenced by environmental variations like temperature and osmotic pressure.</p><p>Structure results based on neutral loci were similar to that on all loci (data not shown). Similarly, there was also high support for eight genetic clusters in nine populations of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, which displayed significant genetic divergence. The eight genetic clusters could be defined as eight MUs, including MU1 (Dandong), MU2 (Dalian), MU3 (Qinhuangdao), MU4 (Dongying &#x00026; Weifang), MU5 (Rongcheng), MU6 (Wendeng), MU7 (Qingdao), and MU8 (Fuyang). The Delta K method could identify high-level genetic structure, which indicated the highest support for three major groups (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2<italic>a</italic></xref>), the similar patterns were also indicated by PCA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). Thereby, the three distinct genetic clusters could be defined as three ESUs: ESU1 (Dandong, Dalian, Qinhuangdao, Dongying, Weifang), ESU2 (Rongcheng, Wendeng, Qingdao), ESU3 (Fuyang), which should reflect the major divergence among populations of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>. Using 47 high <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> outlier SNPs, six genetic clusters were identified among individuals (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz118-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2<italic>c</italic></xref>), corresponding to six AUs. Including AU1: Dandong, AU2: Dalian &#x00026; Qinhuangdao, AU3: Dongying &#x00026; Weifang, AU4: Rongcheng &#x00026; Wendeng, AU5: Qingdao, AU6: Fuyang. The pattern of adaptive variation was similar to that using all loci (9,271 SNPs), except that Dalian &#x00026; Qinhuangdao formed into one group and Rongcheng &#x00026; Wendeng formed into another group. Levels of genetic divergence (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) between six clusters using outlier loci were listed in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online. Among the six clusters, AU6 was the most distinctive one in terms of adaptive variation.
</p><fig id="evz118-F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 5.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;PCA scatter plot using the first two principle components based on all loci.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz118f5"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The present population genomic study delineated fine population genetic characteristics of the nine <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> populations by integrating data of putatively neutral and adaptive genetic variation at the genomic level. This is the first use of genome-wide SNP markers to assess a broad-scale population differentiation and signatures of selection in the <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>. Our study contributes to the growing body of literature identifying significant population structure and local adaptation in marine systems and has important implications for the conservation management of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> and other endangered marine species.</p><sec><title>Causes of Population Structure and Low <italic>N</italic>e in <italic>T. fasciatu</italic><italic>s</italic></title><p>The results provided a higher resolution of population structure compared that identified in our previous study based on microsatellite data (<xref rid="evz118-B62" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). In particular, in contrast to the microsatellite results, Dandong, Dalian, and Qinhuangdao populations were further genetically distinguished by RAD data sets. In addition, pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values were higher than those based on microsatellites. A good understanding of how ecological variants of fishes can impact their population structure will provide more comprehensive implications for conservation management and decision-making.</p><p>Habitat fragmentation is detrimental to species by reducing population size and genetic diversity and by restraining population connectivity (<xref rid="evz118-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lemer and Planes 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B101" ref-type="bibr">Young et&#x000a0;al. 1996</xref>). Therefore, habitat fragmentation may have significant effects on population genetic structure because fragmentation usually leads to limited dispersal and thus lower connectivity levels among populations (<xref rid="evz118-B73" ref-type="bibr">Mossman and Waser 2001</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B52" ref-type="bibr">Keyghobadi 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lemer and Planes 2014</xref>). Because of its complex life history, the breeding and growth of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> depends on different habitats including oceans, estuaries and rivers (<xref rid="evz118-B47" ref-type="bibr">Islam et&#x000a0;al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B19" ref-type="bibr">Cao et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>). In the past decades, the habitats of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> has been markedly degraded and fragmented due to excessive anthropogenic activities (e.g., large-scale reclamation, pollution, dam construction, river flow modification), and the census populations size were sharply reduced (<xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>). On the basis of our results, most populations were with low <italic>N</italic>e, thus are potentially faced with strong effect of genetic drift. Therefore, the divergence among the isolated populations may be caused by low gene flow and the effect of genetic drift among these populations due to habitat fragmentation. However, Dongying and Weifang populations are in close geographical proximity and may share the same spawning ground, which could result in high gene flow between the two populations.</p><p>In the presence of limited gene flow between fragmented populations, random genetic drift is expected to increase genetic differentiation among populations (<xref rid="evz118-B41" ref-type="bibr">Harrison and Hastings 1996</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lemer and Planes 2014</xref>). Currently, the populations of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> have been severely declining due to the combination of overfishing and other anthropogenic activities. The strength of genetic drift is highly related with <italic>N</italic>e, which could be much lower than census abundance in marine species (<xref rid="evz118-B43" ref-type="bibr">Hauser et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B78" ref-type="bibr">Pinsky and Palumbi 2014</xref>). Theoretical simulations suggest that short-term conservation of genetic diversity and inbreeding avoidance requires a <italic>N</italic>e&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;500, and a safety balloon to maintain evolutionary flexibility in natural populations requires a <italic>N</italic>e&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1000 (<xref rid="evz118-B79" ref-type="bibr">Pita et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). The smaller <italic>N</italic>e estimates in Qinhuangdao, Rongcheng, Wendeng, and Qingdao indicated the exceptional status of these small populations. According to the MAF spectrum, the high proportion of rare alleles in Qinhuangdao, Rongcheng, Wendeng, and Qingdao also suggested of bottlenecks and strong genetic drift in these populations. Under the background of global climate change and human activities, runoff volume of some rivers as the migration channel of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> (e.g., Dagu River for Qingdao population, Luan River for Qinhuangdao population, Wei River for Weifang population) has been sharply reduced since recent decades, and the drying-up of the river course has occurred frequently. Specially, the Rongcheng population is mainly distributed in Swan Lake. Swan Lake is a semienclosed coastal lagoon, the major environment perturbations might result in bottlenecks and small <italic>N</italic>e values, which will further strengthen genetic drift effects.</p></sec><sec><title>Genomic Signatures of Environmental Selection in <italic>T. fasciatus</italic></title><p>With the advantages of identification of genome-wide polymorphic markers, RAD sequencing can facilitate insight into studies of the ecological, evolutionary and conservation genomics (<xref rid="evz118-B4" ref-type="bibr">Andrews et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), especially in nonmodel organisms. However, RAD sequencing only covers a fraction of the total genome, and may have missed many loci under selection in local adaptation (<xref rid="evz118-B66" ref-type="bibr">Lowry et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Nonetheless, despite the limited ability to detect adaptive loci, RAD sequencing remains a powerful tool for understanding the genetics of local adaptation in natural populations (<xref rid="evz118-B22" ref-type="bibr">Catchen et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Genome scan methods, especially genotype&#x02013;environment associations are still useful for uncovering candidate loci of relatively important ecological effect. In the present study, we did detect a number of important candidate loci that appear to be affected by spatially divergent selection, although some crucial adaptive loci might have been lost.</p><p>Environmental conditions can be important selective forces that shape the genotypic and phenotypic composition of local populations (<xref rid="evz118-B85" ref-type="bibr">Sanford and Kelly 2011</xref>). Environmental heterogeneity across different geographical locations may lead to phenotypic plasticity or genotypic responses (<xref rid="evz118-B44" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann and Willi 2008</xref>). Aquatic organisms mainly exchange heat with their environment via conduction and convection, thus water temperature is one of the most important abiotic factor that influencing the phenotype and habitat of aquatic organisms (<xref rid="evz118-B6" ref-type="bibr">Angilletta 2009</xref>). The temperature of organism&#x02019;s surrounding environment controls a variety of biological and physiological processes, including heat exchange (<xref rid="evz118-B51" ref-type="bibr">Kearney and Porter 2009</xref>), development (<xref rid="evz118-B55" ref-type="bibr">Kroeker et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>), metabolic rates (<xref rid="evz118-B28" ref-type="bibr">Elliott 1976</xref>), responses (<xref rid="evz118-B12" ref-type="bibr">Batty et&#x000a0;al. 1993</xref>), and aerobic scope (<xref rid="evz118-B77" ref-type="bibr">P&#x000f6;rtner and Knust 2007</xref>), which will further affect the higher functions (such as muscular activity, behavior, growth, and reproduction) and might thereby shape the long-term fate of species. We found evidence that a number of metabolic or developmental processes related genes (34 annotated candidate loci) were involved in the genetic adaptation of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> to the local environment. One locus of interest is located in the <italic>Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GPDH)</italic> gene, which encodes enzyme that catalyzes the reversible redox conversion of dihydroxyacetone phosphate to sn-glycerol 3-phosphate. <italic>GPDH</italic> is a major link between carbohydrate metabolism and lipid metabolism, and is crucial in electron transport chain of the mitochondria. Indeed, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> expends a vast amount of energy during the catadromous and reproduction processes. Previous physiological studies indicated that the digestive system of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> was degenerative since its migration from freshwater to saltwater (<xref rid="evz118-B60" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 1984</xref>), and the main energy sources were from intracorporal glycogen and lipid storage (<xref rid="evz118-B93" ref-type="bibr">Wang 1999</xref>). Thus, lipid and carbohydrate metabolism processes might play a crucial role in adaptation to environmental heterogeneity across different geographical populations, especially for the water temperature. Another candidate locus of interest was found in <italic>the GLI family zinc finger 3 gene</italic>, which could be related to embryonic organ development and dorsal/ventral pattern formation. This gene is also critical for specifying the fate of cortical neurons, and acts as the major negative transducer of the Sonic hedgehog (Shh) signaling pathway (<xref rid="evz118-B92" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>). The Shh pathway is one of the key regulators for animal development, suggesting that changes in body development of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> could be implicated in the environmental temperature. This result is consistent with previous studies of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>, for example studies on <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> suggested that high temperatures would restrict the body development (<xref rid="evz118-B97" ref-type="bibr">Wei et&#x000a0;al. 1997</xref>), affect the growth rate of larvae (<xref rid="evz118-B89" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al. 1980</xref>). Therefore, genes related to metabolism and development were likely crucial candidates for the adaptation of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> to water temperature. Studies in other marine organisms have also identified adaptive loci associated with temperature that were involved in similar diverse functions, examples including the greenlip abalone (<xref rid="evz118-B84" ref-type="bibr">Sandoval-Castillo et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), the Asian seabass (<xref rid="evz118-B96" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), and the lake trout (<xref rid="evz118-B14" ref-type="bibr">Bernatchez et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>).</p><p>Evidences of genetic adaptation in osmoregulatory related genes were also found. Among the annotated candidate loci, 19 loci were categorized as having functions involved in iron binding, including the metal iron binding, cation binding, etc., which might be involved in osmoregulation. As a catadromous fish, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> have to uptake ions from the environment to compensate for salts lost in fresh water, whereas in saltwater they have to diffuse ions to compensate for the passive diffusion of salts into their bodies. Importantly, during spawning migration, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> actively migrate from freshwater to saltwater to uptake sufficient iodine for the development of thyroid and sexual maturity (<xref rid="evz118-B88" ref-type="bibr">Shao 1978</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B89" ref-type="bibr">Shao et&#x000a0;al. 1980</xref>). The osmoregulatory and ion-exchange related genes may play a key role in adaptation to freshwater and saltwater systems. Indeed, some populations of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> might not be able to complete the migration between seawater and freshwater due the lack of connections with rivers or drying-up of the rivers. Thus these populations (e.g., Weifang, Rongcheng, and Qingdao) might have been lived completely in saltwater, which has been confirmed by otolith microchemistry analysis (<xref rid="evz118-B16" ref-type="bibr">Bi 2013</xref>). It is possible that there may be a difference of iron regulation between these populations and other populations with complete catadromous life history. Interestingly, we did find the candidate adaptive loci in the solute carrier family 39 (SLC39) like and Cation/H+ exchanger like gene, which were involved in osmoregulation. SLC family genes are multifunctional and are often involved in acid&#x02013;base balancing via movement of monovalent and divalent anions (<xref rid="evz118-B98" ref-type="bibr">Willoughby et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Previous studies in stickleback and trout also identified similar gene (SLC26) being involved in adaptation to the freshwater&#x02013;saltwater systems (<xref rid="evz118-B45" ref-type="bibr">Hohenlohe et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B98" ref-type="bibr">Willoughby et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). The documentation of genes involved in both metabolic and osmoregulatory pathways provides the first glimpse of how <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> have been adapted to the spatially varying environment of local populations.</p><p>Several candidate loci were annotated as having functions involved in biological regulation, response to stimulus, immune and signaling processes. For instance, one locus was found in the <italic>Transporter 1, ATP-binding cassette, subfamily B gene (TAP1)</italic>, which was involved in MHC protein binding, antigen processing and presentation of exogenous peptide antigen. TAP1 functions as the membrane transporter associated with antigen processing that are involved in transport of peptides that bind to MHC molecules (<xref rid="evz118-B33" ref-type="bibr">Flajnik and Kasahara 2001</xref>), and plays a major role in transportation of foreign peptides through the endoplasmic reticulum for processing before loading onto MHC molecules (<xref rid="evz118-B27" ref-type="bibr">Elgert 2009</xref>). Actually, immune response was also shown to be related to the local adaptation to different water temperature in pipefish (<xref rid="evz118-B34" ref-type="bibr">Flanagan et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) and abalones (<xref rid="evz118-B84" ref-type="bibr">Sandoval-Castillo et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Overall, these findings suggested that the observed adaptive divergence of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> might involve diverse functional changes related to spatially varying environments. This information about the functions of annotated candidate loci could help us to understand the genetic basis of adaptation to important environmental variables like temperature, and provided useful leads for future research in marine species.</p></sec><sec><title>Conservation and Management Implications for <italic>T. fasciatus</italic></title><p>Our study used population genomic techniques to offer high resolution genetic information to improve conservation and management policies and decisions, which previously were not clear with respect to patterns of adaptive genetic variation. The results presented here would provide complementary information for management, especially in defining CUs and setting conservation priorities and management plans for <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>.</p><p>The results demonstrated that the nine populations of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> should be defined as eight MUs (based on neutral loci), six AUs (based on adaptive loci), and three ESUs (based on all loci). CUs with lower genetic diversity and <italic>N</italic>e require high conservation priority, such as MU7 (Qingdao) &#x00026; MU8 (Fuyang) or AU5 (Qingdao) &#x00026; AU6 (Fuyang), which show high level of isolation with other populations. In particular, MU6 (Wendeng) deserves special attention given the lowest <italic>N</italic>e, which is related to low fitness risk. However, the census population size of MU6 might be relative large, which could be much larger than that of MU8 (<xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>), but the <italic>N</italic>e of MU6 were much smaller than that of MU8. A large population census size with an extremely low genetic variation and <italic>N</italic>e could be attributed to overharvest or natural bottlenecks (<xref rid="evz118-B79" ref-type="bibr">Pita et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Overharvest and habitat fragmentation due to anthropogenic activities can lead to the loss of genetic variation and a consequent reduction in evolutionary potential and adaptive ability (<xref rid="evz118-B43" ref-type="bibr">Hauser et&#x000a0;al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B78" ref-type="bibr">Pinsky and Palumbi 2014</xref>). Although there is no known targeted fishery for this species, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> is often caught as bycatch from bottom-trawl fishery and trap net fishery in China (<xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>). As a ferocious carnivorous fish with large food consumption, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> needs to live in area with plenty of food resources. The various type of habitats (inshore sea area, estuaries, and rivers) for the breeding and growth of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> also suggested its sensitive to environmental changes. Currently it is difficult for <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> to survive, migrate, breed, and completed the entire life cycle (<xref rid="evz118-B94" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Cheng 2010</xref>; <xref rid="evz118-B62" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Thus, carrying out prohibited fishing areas and prohibited fishing periods as well as habitat restoration and protection are of great concerns and are probably the most immediate action to take at this time to protect <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>.</p><p>Another government-promoted conservation action on <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> was stock enhancement (<xref rid="evz118-B13" ref-type="bibr">Bell et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>). A large number of evidences indicated that stock enhancement could improve the abundance of target species, but it might also impose some risks on the local populations (e.g., mixing genetic lineages, spreading pathogens). For the management and conservation of this species, the eight distinct clusters detected in the present study should be considered as different MUs. Furthermore, <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> that were recruited within their local adaptive cluster (AUs) might show higher fitness (with regard to variation in the thermal environment and migration routes) than recruited in clusters found elsewhere.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>By analysis of genome-wide data of nine <italic>T. fasciatus</italic> populations, fine population genetic structure and genomic signatures of adaptations across the species&#x02019; range were detected. Genetic clustering analysis revealed significant population structure with high support for eight distinct clusters among nine populations. The strong genetic structure could be attributed to habitat fragmentation and genetic drift due to anthropogenic activities. A substantial number of genetic variants appeared to be under differential selective pressure across the range of <italic>T. fasciatus</italic>. Annotations of candidate adaptive loci suggested that the genes involved in diverse functions like metabolism, development and osmoregulation are critical for the adaptation to environmental heterogeneity across the species&#x02019; range.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary_Material_evz118</label><media xlink:href="supplementary_material_evz118.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="evz118-A1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Zhenzhen Wan, Sudong Xia, Liang Cao, Honglei Wang, Jiqing Li, Huankun Gou, and Zhicai Lin for their help in collecting samples. The study was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 31502169 and 41676137), NSFC-Shandong Joint Fund for Marine Ecology and Environmental Sciences (No. U1606404), and AoShan Talents Program supported by Qingdao National Laboratory of Marine Science and Technology (No. 2015ASTP-ES05).</p><sec><title>Author Contributions</title><p>The study was conceived by L.J.X. and X.D.X. The experiment was performed by L.Y.L. and X.D.X. The analysis was performed by L.Y.L. and Z.B.D. The manuscript was written by L.Y.L., X.D.X., and L.J.X. with contributions from Z.B.D.</p></sec></ack><sec><title/><p>
<bold>Data deposition:</bold> This project has been deposited at the NCBI Nucleotide Short Read Archive (SRA) under the accession No.&#x000a0;PRJNA360511.</p></sec><ref-list id="evz118-R1"><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evz118-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>CW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>The search for loci under selection: trends, biases and progress</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1356</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29524276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Fast model-based estimation of ancestry in unrelated individuals</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>19</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1664</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luikart</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<source>Conservation and the genetics of populations</source>.
<publisher-name>Malden:Blackwell</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luikart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>PA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Harnessing the power of RADseq for ecological and evolutionary genomics</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26729255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Angeloni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagemaker</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vergeer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ouborg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genomic toolboxes for conservation biologists</article-title>. <source>Evol Appl</source>. <volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>143</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25568036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Angilletta</surname><given-names>MJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<source>Thermal adaptation: a theoretical and empirical synthesis</source>.
<publisher-name>Oxford:Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Attard</surname><given-names>CRM</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Ecological disturbance influences adaptive divergence despite high gene flow in golden perch (<italic>Macquaria ambigua</italic>): implications for management and resilience to climate change</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baalsrud</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Effects of population characteristics and structure on estimates of effective population size in a house sparrow metapopulation</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2668</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24766660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The characteristics of the seasonal variability of the seasurface temperature field in the Bohai Sea, the Huanghai Sea and the East China Sea from AVHRR data</article-title>. <source>Acta Oceanol Sin</source>. <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Integrative approaches to guide conservation decisions: using genomics to define conservation units and functional corridors</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>3452</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30030869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>RDH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schluter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Adaptation from standing genetic variation</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol (Amst)</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>38</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18006185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batty</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>JHS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fretwell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Effect of temperature on the escape responses of larval herring, <italic>Clupea harengus</italic></article-title>. <source>Mar Biol</source>. <volume>115</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>528</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loneragan</surname><given-names>NR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Restocking and stock enhancement of coastal fisheries: potential, problems and progress</article-title>. <source>Fish Res</source>. <volume>80</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernatchez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laporte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perrier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sirois</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernatchez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Investigating genomic and phenotypic parallelism between piscivorous and planktivorous lake trout (<italic>Salvelinus namaycush</italic>) ecotypes by means of RADseq and morphometrics analyses</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>4773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4792</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27497114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Betancur-R</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic classification of bony fishes</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>162</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28683774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>XX.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. Studies on the morphology and genetics of Trachidermus fasciatus populations [doctoral thesis]. Qingdao:Ocean University of China.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brauer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beheregaray</surname><given-names>LB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Riverscape genomics of a threatened fish across a hydroclimatically heterogeneous river basin</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>5093</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27575282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><volume>10</volume>:<fpage>421.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Threatened fishes of the world: <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel, 1837 (Cottidae)</article-title>. <source>Environ Biol Fish</source>. <volume>86</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63.</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catchen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The population structure and recent colonization history of Oregon threespine stickleback determined using restriction-site associated DNA-sequencing</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>22</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2883</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23718143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catchen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amores</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cresko</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Postlethwait</surname><given-names>JH.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Stacks: building and genotyping loci de novo from short-read sequences</article-title>. <source>G3: Genes|Genomes|Genetics</source><volume>1</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22384329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Catchen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Unbroken: RADseq remains a powerful tool for understanding the genetics of adaptation in natural populations</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>362</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>365</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28319339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>21</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>3674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coop</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Witonsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rienzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Using environmental correlations to identify loci underlying local adaptation</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>185</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1423</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20516501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>27</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>NeEstimator v2: re-implementation of software for the estimation of contemporary effective population size (Ne) from genetic data</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23992227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elgert</surname><given-names>KD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<source>Immunology: understanding the immune system</source>.
<publisher-name>Hoboken:John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>JM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>The energetics of feeding, metabolism and growth of brown trout (<italic>Salmo trutta</italic> L.) in relation to body weight, water temperature and ration size</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>. <volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>948</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Etter</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cresko</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Local de novo assembly of RAD paired-end contigs using short sequencing reads</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e18561.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21541009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evanno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regnaut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software structure: a simulation study</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>14</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lischer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Arlequin suite ver 3.5: a new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and Windows</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>567</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21565059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferchaud</surname><given-names>A-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>MM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The impact of selection, gene flow and demographic history on heterogeneous genomic divergence: three-spine sticklebacks in divergent environments</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>259</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26412233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flajnik</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Comparative genomics of the MHC: glimpses into the evolution of the adaptive immune system</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source><volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11567626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AG.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Population genomics reveals multiple drivers of population differentiation in a sex-role-reversed pipefish</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>5043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5072</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27485274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaggiotti</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>A genome-scan method to identify selected loci appropriate for both dominant and codominant markers: a Bayesian perspective</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source><volume>180</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>993</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18780740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fournier-Level</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>A map of local adaptation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>334</volume>(<issue>6052</issue>):<fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21980109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frankham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briscoe</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballou</surname><given-names>JD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<source>Introduction to conservation genetics</source>. Cambridge:
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Harnessing genomics for delineating conservation units</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol (Amst)</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22727017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Population genetic structure of roughskin sculpin <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> based on the mitochondrial Cytb sequence</article-title>. <source>Acta Hydrobiol Sin</source>. <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <volume>29</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Genetic and evolutionary consequences of metapopulation structure</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>. <volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrisson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Telonis-Scott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunnucks</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Using genomics to characterize evolutionary potential for conservation of wild populations</article-title>. <source>Evol Appl</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1025</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25553064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adcock</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernal Ramirez</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>GR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Loss of microsatellite diversity and low effective population size in an overexploited population of New Zealand snapper (<italic>Pagrus auratus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>99</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>11742</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11747</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12185245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Detecting genetic responses to environmental change</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>432</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18463665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohenlohe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Population genomics of parallel adaptation in threespine stickleback using sequenced RAD tags</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e1000862.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20195501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Madan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>CAP3: a DNA sequence assembly program</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <volume>9</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>868</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>877</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hibino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Tidal and diurnal variations in larval fish abundance in an estuarine inlet in Ariake Bay, Japan: implication for selective tidal stream transport</article-title>. <source>Ecol Res</source>. <volume>22</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Variation of runoff volume in the Dagu river basin in the Jiaodong peninsula</article-title>. <source>Arid Zone Res</source>. <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>965</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>972</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jombart</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>adegenet: a R package for the multivariate analysis of genetic markers</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>24</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1405</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raftery</surname><given-names>AE.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Bayes factors</article-title>. <source>J Am Stat Assoc</source>. <volume>90</volume>(<issue>430</issue>):<fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>795</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Mechanistic niche modelling: combining physiological and spatial data to predict species&#x02019; ranges</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>350</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19292794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keyghobadi</surname><given-names>NK.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The genetic implications of habitat fragmentation for animals</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>. <volume>85</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1064</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjeldsen</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide SNP loci reveal novel insights into koala (<italic>Phascolarctos cinereus</italic>) population variability across its range</article-title>. <source>Conserv Genet</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kopelman</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayrose</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Clumpak: a program for identifying clustering modes and packaging population structure inferences across K</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1191</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25684545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroeker</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Impacts of ocean acidification on marine organisms: quantifying sensitivities and interaction with warming</article-title>. <source>Glob Change Biol</source>. <volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1884</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1896</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Genotyping by sequencing resolves shallow population structure to inform conservation of Chinook salmon (<italic>Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Evol Appl</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>369</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24665338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Planes</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Effects of habitat fragmentation on the genetic structure and connectivity of the black-lipped pearl oyster Pinctada <italic>margaritifera populations</italic> in French Polynesia</article-title>. <source>Mar Biol</source>. <volume>161</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2049</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-MEM. arXiv: 1303.3997 q-bio. doi: http://arxiv.org/abs/1303.3997.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>2078</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2079</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>BX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>JS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1984</year>
<article-title>A histological study on the digestive organs of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> during seaward migration</article-title>. <source>J Fudan Univ</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JX.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>StructureSelector: a web-based software to select and visualize the optimal number of clusters using multiple methods</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28921901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JX.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genetic diversity and population structure of the roughskin sculpin (<italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel) inferred from microsatellite analyses: implications for its conservation and management</article-title>. <source>Conserv Genet</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>930</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>DX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JX.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>An optimized approach for local de novo assembly of overlapping paired-end RAD reads from multiple individuals</article-title>. <source>R Soc Open Sci</source>. <volume>5</volume>:171589. http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsos.171589.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lischer</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>PGDSpider: an automated data conversion tool for connecting population genetics and genomics programs</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>JQ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Quantitative study of impacts for environmental change on runoff in Luanhe river basin</article-title>. <source>J Nat Resour</source>. <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Breaking RAD: an evaluation of the utility of restriction site-associated DNA sequencing for genome scans of adaptation</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27860289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luikart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornuet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sherwin</surname><given-names>WB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Distortion of allele frequency distributions provides a test for recent population bottlenecks</article-title>. <source>J Hered</source>. <volume>89</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>247</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9656466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>ZM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Analyses of the molecular mechanisms associated with salinity adaption of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> through combined iTRAQ-based proteomics and RNA sequencing-based transcriptomics</article-title>. <source>Prog Biophys Mol Biol</source>. <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29447837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-throughput sequencing reads</article-title>. <source>Embnet J</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seeb</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seeb</surname><given-names>JE.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>RADseq provides unprecedented insights into molecular ecology and evolutionary genetics: comment on Breaking RAD by Lowry et al. (2016)</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>361</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28028934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Teeling</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000f6;glund</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>How and why should we implement genomics into conservation?</article-title><source>Evol Appl</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>999</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1007</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25553063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Conservation units and translocations: strategies for conserving evolutionary processes</article-title>. <source>Hereditas</source><volume>130</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>228</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mossman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waser</surname><given-names>PM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Effects of habitat fragmentation on population genetic structure in the white-footed mouse (<italic>Peromyscus leucopus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>. <volume>79</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuerst</surname><given-names>PA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Infinite allele model with varying mutation rate</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. <volume>73</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1069306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onikura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Spawning grounds and nests of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> (Cottidae) in the Kashima and Shiota estuaries system facing Ariake Bay, Japan</article-title>. <source>Ichthyol Res</source>. <volume>49</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouborg</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pertoldi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loeschcke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bijlsma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedrick</surname><given-names>PW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Conservation genetics in transition to conservation genomics</article-title>. <source>Trends Genet</source>. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>187</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000f6;rtner</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knust</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Climate change affects marine fishes through the oxygen limitation of thermal tolerance</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>315</volume>(<issue>5808</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17204649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinsky</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palumbi</surname><given-names>SR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Meta-analysis reveals lower genetic diversity in overfished populations</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24372754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Presa</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Trends of the genetic effective population size in the Southern stock of the European hake</article-title>. <source>Fish Res</source>. <volume>191</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Priyam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>. Sequenceserver: a modern graphical user interface for custom BLAST databases. bioRxiv 033142, doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/033142</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puechmaille</surname><given-names>SJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The program structure does not reliably recover the correct population structure when sampling is uneven: subsampling and new estimators alleviate the problem</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>627</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26856252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>. <volume>81</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>R Core Team</collab>
<year>2018</year>
<source>R: a Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source>.
<publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>,
<publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>; Last accessed June 5, 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandoval-Castillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>LWS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beheregaray</surname><given-names>LB.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Seascape genomics reveals adaptive divergence in a connected and commercially important mollusc, the greenlip abalone (<italic>Haliotis laevigata</italic>), along a longitudinal environmental gradient</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1620</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29420852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>MW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Local adaptation in marine invertebrates</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Mar Sci</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lascoux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merila</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Ecological genomics of local adaptation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. <volume>14</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>820</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24136507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schluter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Ecological character displacement in adaptive radiation</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>. <volume>156</volume>(<issue>S4</issue>):<fpage>S4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>BX.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>The seasonal change of the thyroid gland of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> in relation to the seaward migration</article-title>. <source>Oceanol Limnol Sin</source>. <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>BX</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>On the breeding habit of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel</article-title>. <source>J Fish China</source>. <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinig</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuditschko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khatkar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Raadsma</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zenger</surname><given-names>KR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>netview p: a network visualization tool to unravel complex population structure using genome-wide SNPs</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26129944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>The UniProt Consortium</collab>. <year>2018</year>
<article-title>UniProt: a worldwide hub of protein knowledge</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>D506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D515</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Uchida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title><italic>Gli3</italic> is required for maintenance and fate specification of cortical progenitors</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <volume>31</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>6440</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6448</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21525285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JQ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Advances in studies on the ecology and reproductive biology of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel</article-title>. <source>Acta Hydrobiol Sin</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>734</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The historical variance and causes of geographical distribution of a roughskin sculpin (<italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel) in Chinese territory</article-title>. <source>Acta Ecol Sin</source>. <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>6845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6853</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The distribution of roughskin sculpin (<italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> Heckel) in Yalu river basin, China</article-title>. <source>J Fudan Univ Nat Sci</source><volume>40</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>476</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>GH.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genetic variability, local selection and demographic history: genomic evidence of evolving towards allopatric speciation in Asian seabass</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>3605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3621</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27262162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Environmental factors controlling the growth of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Fudan Univ</source>. <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>585</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willoughby</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harder</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tennessen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scribner</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>MR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Rapid genetic adaptation to a novel environment despite a genome-wide reduction in genetic diversity</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>. <volume>27</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>4041</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4051</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29802799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Analysis of genetic diversity in roughskin sculpin <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> by AFLP markers</article-title>. <source>J Dalian Fish Univ</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>PM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>GCTA: a tool for genome-wide complex trait analysis</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>. <volume>88</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21167468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The population genetic consequences of habitat fragmentation for plants</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>. <volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Analysis of genetic diversity in wild populations of <italic>Trachidermus fasciatus</italic> by RAPD and the transformation of two SCAR markers</article-title>. <source>Zool Res</source>. <volume>33</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22467397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz118-B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zerbino</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Ensembl 2018</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>46</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D754</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D761</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29155950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>