<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We obtained detailed climate data for the area of the Buenaventura reserve (box coordinates: 3,616°S–3,675°S; 79,738°W–79,782°W) from KNMI Climate Explorer [
 <xref rid="pone.0191773.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. For our study, we focused on the anomalies of annual mean temperature and annual precipitation sum for the years 2000–2100 (reference period 1986–2005). We obtained historical climate data (years 2000–2015) from the ERA-interim reanalysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0191773.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. The ERA-interim reanalysis reconstructs a high-resolution model of the state of the atmosphere from 1979 to the present. Future climate (years 2016–2100) was expressed by a subset of CMIP5 models used in the Atlas of Global and Regional Climate Projections (hereafter Atlas subset) of the IPCC’s Fifth Assessment Report [
 <xref rid="pone.0191773.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. We used the output of multiple models to account for key uncertainties due to factors such as different model structures, model parameters, and model initial conditions (for a discussion, see for example [
 <xref rid="pone.0191773.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]). Future climate forcings were sampled using results for four Representative Concentration Pathways: RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5. The RCPs describe different trajectories for greenhouse gas emissions, leading to specific values of radiative forcing by the year 2100 (2.6, 4.5, 6.0, and 8.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>). While RCP2.6 represents a scenario of strong greenhouse gas mitigation in the future with a likely increase of global mean temperature by ~1.5°C above pre-industrial level by the year 2100, RCP8.5 represents a scenario of drastically increasing climate forcing, with a projected temperature increase of ~4.9°C by 2100 (sometimes referred to as “business as usual”). RCP4.5 (temperature increase of ~2.4°C by 2100) and RCP6.0 (temperature increase of ~3.0°C by 2100) describe intermediate scenarios [
 <xref rid="pone.0191773.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. The models used for each RCP scenario are listed in the Supporting Information (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191773.s001" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>; see also [
 <xref rid="pone.0191773.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]).
</p>
