<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ece34944-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">Genetic structure and major climate factors may contribute to the distribution of genetic diversity of a highly valued oil tree species 
  <italic class="italic">Xanthoceras sorbifolium</italic> (yellowhorn). Long‐term over utilization along with climate change is affecting the viability of yellowhorn wild populations. To preserve the species known and unknown valuable gene pools, the identification of genetic diversity “hotspots” is a prerequisite for their consideration as in situ conservation high priority. Chloroplast DNA (cpDNA) diversity was high among 38 natural populations (
  <italic class="italic">H</italic>
  <sub class="sub">d</sub> = 0.717, 
  <italic class="italic">K</italic> = 4.616, Tajmas’ 
  <italic class="italic">D</italic> = −0.22) and characterized by high genetic divergence (
  <italic class="italic">F</italic>
  <sub class="sub">ST</sub> = 0.765) and relatively low gene flow (
  <italic class="italic">N</italic>
  <sub class="sub">m</sub> = 0.03), indicating populations isolation reflecting the species’ habitat fragmentation and inbreeding depression. Six out of the studied 38 populations are defined as genetic diversity “hotspots.” The number and geographic direction of cpDNA mutation steps supported the species southwest to northeast migration history. Climatic factors such as extreme minimum temperature over 30 years indicated that the identified genetic “hotspots” are expected to experience 5°C temperature increase in next following 50 years. The results identified vulnerable genetic diversity “hotspots” and provided fundamental information for the species’ future conservation and breeding activities under the anticipated climate change. More specifically, the role of breeding as a component of a gene resource management strategy aimed at fulfilling both utilization and conservation goals.
 </p>
</abstract>
