<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1dot2-ijerph-13-00438" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.2. Climate Change Impacts on Health in Mediterranean Cities</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent climatic changes and future projections have resulted in growing attention to the health effects on all human populations, both urban and rural [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-13-00438">19</a>]. These overall negative health effects impact in direct ways (e.g., heatwaves, flooding, and drought) and in indirect ways (e.g., food availability). The risks and the number of people exposed to them are influenced by social and economic development, technology, and health service provision. Consequently, urban areas where people, resources and infrastructure are concentrated are especially vulnerable to the health impacts of the changing climate [
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-13-00438">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-13-00438">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Urban populations are increasing in absolute numbers and are also relative to rural populations in every part of the world. According to the UN [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-13-00438">22</a>], 54% of the world population lives in urban areas. Because cities concentrate populations, extreme weather events (such as severe heatwaves or flooding) affect a much larger number of people. Cities also concentrate poor populations who are especially vulnerable to the effects of climate change because of the conditions in which they live and the fact that they often lack adequate shelter or access to health services [
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-13-00438">23</a>]. Another crucial factor is relating to the increasing proportion of the older population. This worldwide growing group is highly vulnerable (more than others) to health risks associated with extreme temperatures, infectious diseases and air pollution [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-13-00438">19</a>,
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-13-00438">21</a>,
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-13-00438">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-13-00438">25</a>]. The population density in cities tends to lengthen the supply lines for essentials such as water, food, and energy sources. Extreme temperatures, storms or droughts that disrupt these urban lifelines can have serious consequences for the health of city residents [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-13-00438">26</a>]. In addition, the ways in which cities are constructed—reducing vegetation, covering large areas with impermeable surfaces, and obstructing natural drainage channels—make many city inhabitants more vulnerable to heatwaves, heavy precipitation, and other extreme weather events whose occurrence is found to be increasing [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-13-00438">9</a>,
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-13-00438">20</a>]. The ways in which the changing climate affects the health of city inhabitants are detailed below:
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Extreme high air temperatures contribute directly to deaths from cardiovascular and respiratory disease, particularly among elderly people and those with chronic diseases. The impacts are worsened by the “urban heat island” effect, which results from greater heat retention of buildings and paved surfaces in urban areas.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Direct physical injuries and deaths from extreme weather events such as intense rainfall, winds and floods. Extreme events may also damage homes, create dangerous transport conditions and disrupt the supply of medical and health services.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Increasingly variable rainfall patterns (drought, floods) affect the supply of fresh water. A lack of safe water can compromise hygiene and increase the risk of water-borne diseases.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Worsening air quality related to changes in temperature and precipitation resulting in the formation of smog may cause respiratory illnesses. High temperatures also raise the levels of ozone and other pollutants in the air that exacerbate cardiovascular and respiratory diseases. Pollen and other aeroallergen levels are also higher in extreme heat conditions.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Illnesses and deaths occur from the spreading and expanded range of vector-borne infectious diseases.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Food-borne diseases resulting from bacterial growth in foods exposed to higher temperatures.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Unstable nutritional security among the urban poor who have reduced access to food (
     <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, shortages and rising prices) as a result of extreme events (extreme temperatures, drought, floods) [
     <a rid="B19-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-13-00438">19</a>,
     <a rid="B20-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-13-00438">20</a>,
     <a rid="B21-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-13-00438">21</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In cities with a Mediterranean climate (Med-cities), people have to deal with cold in winter, which can be either dry or wet, and heat in summer, with high or low humidity. In the transitional seasons, over short periods of time, the climatic conditions can change from one extreme to another. Therefore, dealing with bioclimatic comfort and weather conditions in a Mediterranean climate may be more complicated than in more extreme environments [
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-13-00438">27</a>]. These challenges are increasing since the Mediterranean climate-type regions are among the most vulnerable to the impacts of the changing climate [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-13-00438">8</a>]. In the Mediterranean basin itself, since many cities are old, they are compact and densely populated [
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-13-00438">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-13-00438">29</a>]. Furthermore, Med-cities often lack shading in public places, and when shading elements exist they are often designed in ways that do not provide sufficient shade during the hot hours, nor is their potential to reduce heat stress fulfilled [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-13-00438">30</a>]. Although air conditioning is essential in the long hot season, it is mainly used in areas with higher socio-economic standing while poor populations have less access to air conditioning [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-13-00438">31</a>]. In Med-cities, as a part of the local mentality, windows remain open for most of the hot months. Many activities, particularly social gatherings, occur in outdoor locations such as shaded balconies, courtyards, and outdoor restaurants [
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-13-00438">29</a>]. These cultural behaviors increase the potential for contact with mosquitoes that may be vectors for infectious diseases. All the characteristics above make the residents of the Med-cities susceptible to the impacts of climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
