<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying the underlying drivers of different coral reef ecosystem regimes has great value for managers seeking viable strategies to avoid, or reverse, regime shifts. Drawing on an unprecedented compilation of data, this study presents, to our knowledge, the first attempt at quantifying the relative importance of anthropogenic and biophysical drivers in predicting reef ecosystems defined by both fish and benthic communities. As such, it offers novel insights into coral reef dynamics that can inform management strategies, as well as a promising analytical approach that might be applied in other ecosystems. Our findings provide empirical evidence that dealing with alternative regimes is inherently a social–ecological issue and that designing effective management interventions requires both focusing on prominent human drivers while accounting for the natural bounds set by the local biophysical environment.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The overwhelming influence of biophysical predictors in explaining the occurrence of three out of four regimes is striking. Only the most degraded regime, characterized by low fish biomass, few corals and high turf cover, was primarily predicted by anthropogenic variables (i.e. fishing and effluent). This confirms a large body of literature highlighting the detrimental effects of high fishing pressure and effluent discharge on reef ecosystems [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C31">31</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C32">32</a>]. Studies have shown that fishing can disrupt coral reef trophic structures [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C33">33</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C34">34</a>] and pave the way for algae to overgrow corals by removing key herbivores that would otherwise provide top-down algal control [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C10">10</a>]. Similarly, excess nutrient delivery associated with local human populations has repeatedly been attributed to promoting the competitive abilities of algae [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C32">32</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C35">35</a>], in particular turf algae [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C36">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings also highlight the critical role of wave power and suggest that it drives the occurrence of a specific regime (i.e. regime 2), characterized by exposed sites with high fish biomass but limited coral cover. By contrast, regime 3, which displays substantial coral cover, occurs most commonly in sheltered environments with small pulses of chlorophyll-
  <span class="italic">a</span> in an otherwise rather oligotrophic background. This could illustrate how a pulsed delivery of oceanic-derived nutrients from physical processes such as internal waves or current-driven upwelling [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C37">37</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C38">38</a>] may benefit corals on oligotrophic reefs by increasing ecosystem primary production and the energy available for coral growth [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C39">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Depth and complexity appeared almost systematically among the five most influential predictors, regardless of regime type. Both variables have been identified as key features influencing the structure of reef communities and offering potential for recovery from disturbances (electronic supplementary material, table S3). Areas with complex reef structure, for instance, provide refuge from predation and often harbour higher fish abundance and diversity [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C40">40</a>]. While the most degraded regime (i.e. regime 1) was associated with very low complexity, the occurrence of regime 5, which supports diverse fish assemblages and high coral cover, peaked at mid-depth and increased with higher complexity. Depth and complexity also emerged as prominent interacting predictors, either weakening the effect of waves and favouring recreational boat fishing at deeper depths, or magnifying the impact of commercial fishing at low complexity. Our findings emphasize the value of these simple yet critical features in the management evaluation of a reef's resilience and clarify the mechanisms by which they can synergistically interact.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Defining ecological regimes allows capture of a considerable level of complexity of reef ecosystems [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C8">8</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C12">12</a>]. The approach is also particularly appealing to managers who are often interested in the status of the reef as a whole, rather than its individual components. Yet, the descriptive advantage gained when merging multiple response variables may be counteracted by a reduction in the power to predict their occurrence, especially considering that species often exhibit individual and distinct responses to their surroundings. For instance, Gove 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C16">16</a>] improved model performance fivefold when moving from predicting the spatial variation in overall hard coral cover (11% deviance explained), to modelling the distribution of individual hard coral morphologies that show differential susceptibility to wave stress (55% deviance explained). While the regimes allow us to account for reciprocity between fish and benthic functional groups, they form a complex response variable made of organisms characterized by a wide range of attributes (e.g. slow versus fast growing, mobile versus sessile). Despite such heterogeneity, our models were able to consistently explain around 40% of the cross-validated deviance with high AUC values, thereby providing robust explanatory predictions of the mechanistic dynamics underlying ecological regimes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although different reef regimes were explained by a broad range of anthropogenic and biophysical variables, the particularly strong influence of the latter warrants further consideration. First, it may be specific to Hawaiian reefs. The archipelago is one of the most isolated in the world, is located at subtropical latitudes and experiences large oceanic forcings [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C18">18</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C19">19</a>]. Some regimes might therefore be shaped by powerful biophysical drivers that supersede any human influence. Second, our findings could relate to the spatial scale of the analysis. Understanding the influence of scale requires analysing two major components: grain and extent. Grain refers to the finest spatial resolution within a given dataset, while extent relates to the overall area encompassed by the study [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C41">41</a>]. While we were able to control for different grain sizes, we could not satisfyingly subset the data and run the BRTs for finer geographical areas than the Hawaiian Islands (e.g. a stretch of coastline) owing to sample size. This can obscure the relative importance of anthropogenic predictors that are likely to operate at the local level rather than at the regional-level, such as high sedimentation in an embayment [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C42">42</a>]. Whether a stronger anthropogenic signature would emerge at finer scales of analysis, therefore, represents an important next step for future work that could better inform local community management. Finally, disentangling what represents anthropogenic and biophysical predictors can be difficult in an epoch where humans have become a dominant force in nature [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C43">43</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C44">44</a>]. Rising seawater temperature, for instance, is profoundly influenced by human emissions of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C45">45</a>]. Similarly, nearshore chlorophyll-
  <span class="italic">a</span>, used here as a proxy for oceanic primary production [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C18">18</a>], can also capture local aspects of water quality influenced by humans [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C38">38</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C46">46</a>]. In addition, some biophysical conditions greatly influence anthropogenic impacts, such as large seasonal swell events preventing fishing activities, or flushing out sediment and effluent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coral reef managers are often faced with the challenge of where to allocate their limited resources and what management options to prioritize. Recent studies have shown the potential of fisheries regulations to facilitate reef recovery [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C47">47</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C48">48</a>] and balance conservation objectives with stakeholders' interests [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C49">49</a>]. Yet, less than one per cent of the coastline in the Hawaiian Islands is currently under no-take marine protected areas [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C50">50</a>] and no licence is required for marine recreational fishing across the archipelago, although non-commercial catch has been estimated to be five times larger than commercial catch [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C51">51</a>]. A growing tourism-based economy and planned development of new homes also have the potential to exacerbate pollution and runoff [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C52">52</a>]. While our results provide additional evidence that addressing fishing pressure and water quality is critical to avoid degraded reef regimes, they also highlight which biophysical drivers need to be accounted for in a given location. There is little managers can do about broad-scale biophysical drivers, but understanding how environmental conditions shape coral reef regimes can help inform management strategies and identify priority areas. Importantly, our study provides the first step towards predicting the outcome of alternative management actions. By taking our results and turning them around for use in a forward-thinking model, future work should explore where change in a particular variable (or combination of variables) gives the quickest transition into a more desirable state. Such analysis would help identify where undesirable regimes may be naturally occurring and, otherwise, determine the most cost-effective management actions given a reef's natural setting.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the wake of the 2014–2016 coral bleaching event, the State of Hawai‘i pledged to effectively manage 30 per cent of its nearshore waters by 2030. Our analyses, together with our publicly available database, represent valuable resources to assist managers and policy-makers in this process. Ultimately, however, addressing the challenges coral reefs are facing globally will also require identifying distal drivers of change (e.g. trade, climate change) and recognizing that leverage may lie far away from the reef [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C43">43</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C53">53</a>]. Only through a combination of local and global management interventions, can we ensure coral reefs continue to provide the ecosystem services upon which so many people rely.
 </p>
</sec>
