<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coral reef ecosystems worldwide are shifting to alternative regimes, driven by a combination of human impacts, biotic processes and abiotic conditions [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C1">1</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C2">2</a>]. Beyond abrupt changes in ecosystem structure and function [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C2">2</a>], long-lasting regime shifts may bear heavy costs to society through the loss of ecosystem services associated with a particular regime [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C3">3</a>]. They also pose serious challenges for coral reef managers [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C4">4</a>], since reversing undesirable regimes can be difficult and costly owing to strong reinforcing feedback mechanisms [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C6">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, descriptions of alternative reef regimes have predominantly addressed benthic community structure, with an emphasis on shifts from coral to algal dominance [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C7">7</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C9">9</a>]. Changes in fish assemblages have also been highlighted, either as a driver of benthic regime shifts [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C10">10</a>] or as their direct consequence [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C11">11</a>]. Given the strong interdependence between benthic and fish communities on coral reefs however, disentangling ‘what drives what’ becomes problematic. Recent work by Donovan 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C12">12</a>] addresses this issue by proposing a broader approach that combines both fish and benthic functional groups as the defining elements of reef regimes. Such an integrated description of the reef community provides a more nuanced view of reef regimes which better captures the complexity of coral reef dynamics. Yet, what drives the occurrence of these integrated regimes and how to subsequently prioritize management actions remain unknown.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the face of escalating human impacts, such as overfishing, reduced water quality and effects from climate change, there is growing awareness surrounding the multi-causality of reef regimes [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C8">8</a>] and potential effects of interacting stressors [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C14">14</a>]. Effectively managing coral reefs therefore requires an accurate, and often context-specific, understanding of how multiple drivers combine to support or undermine different regimes. In particular, discerning the relative influence of anthropogenic versus biophysical drivers is critical to appreciate how environmental conditions might limit or favour different management options. Although humans can become the dominant force determining coral reef ecosystem state [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C15">15</a>], variations in biophysical drivers, such as waves and primary productivity, set natural bounds on ecosystem condition even in the absence of local human influence [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C16">16</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C17">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main Hawaiian Islands—the populated portion of the Hawaiian archipelago, hereafter referred to as the Hawaiian Islands for brevity—span gradients in both environmental conditions [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C18">18</a>] and human pressures [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C19">19</a>], allowing for an exploration of their relative importance in determining the spatial distribution of reef regimes. The Hawaiian Islands are also the focus of one of the most extensive spatial databases of biophysical and anthropogenic predictors available for a coastal ecosystem [
  <a rid="RSPB20182544C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182544C20">20</a>]. Here, we use this database to predict the occurrence of multiple reef regimes defined by both fish and benthic communities. We apply boosted regression trees to quantify the relative influence of each biophysical and anthropogenic predictor, identify relationships between predictors and regimes, and characterize interaction patterns. Identifying what predicts different reef ecosystem regimes and how the natural environment can influence management opportunities is essential to help practitioners effectively anticipate, avoid and respond to coral reef change.
 </p>
</sec>
