<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic effects on calving date</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calving season of the semi-domesticated reindeer population of the Kutuharju field reindeer research station in Kaamanen, North Finland has advanced significantly over the last 45 years by almost one week. Eloranta and Nieminen [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref016">16</a>] already reported that most of the calving of this same herd occurred on average 19 days between May 10 and 29 and that the peak of calving varied yearly between May the 15
  <span class="sup">th</span> and 25
  <span class="sup">th</span>. Similarly, 90% of the caribou calves in North America are born in a brief 2-week period [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref028">28</a>]. Therefore, our peak calving date (19-May) matched the previous findings on the same herd [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref016">16</a>] but an overall advancement of 6.8 days of the whole calving season represents a consequent change for the calving period in this area. So far, very few studies have highlighted such temporal trends in the reproduction phenology of mammal populations (squirrel [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref069">69</a>], red deer [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref070">70</a>]). This temporal trend corroborated the overall warming of the spring period from April to May, as well as the reduced snow cover just prior to the births in May observed in the study area the last 45 years. Indeed, earlier calving dates were found following warmer temperatures in April-May, a decreasing amount of precipitation in April (mainly snowfalls at that time of the year) and a reduced snow cover in April the same calendar year. The spring period appears to be critical for ungulate species in northern latitudes, given its influence on the plant growth season pattern [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref071">71</a>] and consequently on the food availability during summer. Moreover, late winter/early spring is the most demanding period for reindeer in Arctic since individuals’ body condition and fat reserves to draw upon (reindeer being a capital breeder) are at their lowest point and availability of food is difficult due to hard and thick snow cover [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref072">72</a>]. When temperatures rise earlier in spring, the snow starts to melt, and snow free patches will also emerge much earlier, allowing reindeer to easily have access to lichens and dwarf shrubs. Altogether, (1) a better availability of late winter food and a decreasing amount of energy spent in thermoregulation [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref073">73</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref074">74</a>] and locomotion on snow [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref075">75</a>] due to a decreasing amount of snowfalls and a reduced snow cover in April, and (2) an earlier onset of the vegetative growing season [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref076">76</a>] and an increased plant biomass observed in the Arctic tundra [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref077">77</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref078">78</a>] due to warmer temperatures in April-May certainly contributed to increase females’ body condition in late pregnancy. Indeed, further analyses revealed that females’ body weight (a correlate of females’ BCI) had significantly increased over the last 45 years in this population. Such improvement in females’ physical condition will result in mothers having more resources during pregnancy, hence likely advancing the date at which the foetus is mature and resulting in an earlier birth, as compared to years with severe late winter conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref042">42</a>]. The significant advancement in calving date could thus be explained by females in better condition giving birth earlier [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref042">42</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref079">79</a>]. The large influence of female body condition on calving date has already been highlighted in numerous studies (bighorn sheep [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref050">50</a>], caribou [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref042">42</a>], elk [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref045">45</a>], reindeer [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An optimal timing of calving will ensure that females have access to a high-quality vegetation (i.e. higher protein content), allowing their calves to be nourished with a high-quality milk [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref080">80</a>] and accelerating the rate of fat accumulation for calves. Moreover, earlier birth dates will (1) provide calves with a longer period of time to sufficiently accumulate fat reserves to survive winter and therefore promoting both their survival and growth, and (2) allow mothers to recover faster from their pregnancy and lactation period and to be in good enough shape to reproduce the next breeding season, promoting both their survival and reproductive success as a result [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref081">81</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref082">82</a>]. Therefore, such plastic response is essential for deer species to adapt to climate change by adjusting the period of high energetic requirements (i.e. lactation) with the period of high-quality forage and thereby ensuring offspring survival. Identifying the environmental variables that trigger a plastic response in the reproductive phenology of animal species is thus of primary concern in order to better predict their long term viability. Many species of birds and mammals have already been shown to rely on temperature to match the birth timing with the peak of resource availability [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref083">83</a>]. In ungulate species, females may adjust their gestation length as a strategy to give birth at the period of the year best suited for offspring survival. Such adjustment of gestation length as part of the reproductive tactic has previously been reported in reindeer [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref084">84</a>]. On the Isle of Rum, Scotland, warm March temperatures were associated with shorter average gestation lengths in red deer and Clements et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref085">85</a>] proposed that high March temperatures could act as a cue to indicate that the optimum birth date is likely to be earlier. The females of the Kutuharju field reindeer research station also seemed to rely on temperature in April-May but also on snow conditions (amount of snowfalls and snow depth index) in April to adjust their gestation length in late pregnancy and consequently calving time within the same year accordingly. Nevertheless, the significant relation between calving dates and mean temperature in April-May do not necessarily mean that females use temperature as a predictive cue for future environmental conditions. This correlation could just be the result of an increased female’s physical condition following improved climatic conditions in late winter/early spring. To demonstrate a cause-effect relationship and whether temperature has a direct signaling effect on seasonal timing, experimental approaches would be necessary but as Caro et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0195603.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref083">83</a>] mentioned, “given the scarcity of experimental approaches investigating this causal effect of temperature, especially in mammals, generalizations are not possible and additional studies are desperately needed”.
 </p>
</sec>
