<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic effects on calving date</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calving season of the semi-domesticated reindeer population of the Kutuharju field reindeer research station in Kaamanen, North Finland has advanced significantly over the last 45 years by almost one week. Eloranta and Nieminen [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref016">16</a>] already reported that most of the calving of this same herd occurred on average 19 days between May 10 and 29 and that the peak of calving varied yearly between May the 15
   <span class="sup">th</span> and 25
   <span class="sup">th</span>. Similarly, 90% of the caribou calves in North America are born in a brief 2-week period [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref028">28</a>]. Therefore, our peak calving date (19-May) matched the previous findings on the same herd [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref016">16</a>] but an overall advancement of 6.8 days of the whole calving season represents a consequent change for the calving period in this area. So far, very few studies have highlighted such temporal trends in the reproduction phenology of mammal populations (squirrel [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref069">69</a>], red deer [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref070">70</a>]). This temporal trend corroborated the overall warming of the spring period from April to May, as well as the reduced snow cover just prior to the births in May observed in the study area the last 45 years. Indeed, earlier calving dates were found following warmer temperatures in April-May, a decreasing amount of precipitation in April (mainly snowfalls at that time of the year) and a reduced snow cover in April the same calendar year. The spring period appears to be critical for ungulate species in northern latitudes, given its influence on the plant growth season pattern [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref071">71</a>] and consequently on the food availability during summer. Moreover, late winter/early spring is the most demanding period for reindeer in Arctic since individuals’ body condition and fat reserves to draw upon (reindeer being a capital breeder) are at their lowest point and availability of food is difficult due to hard and thick snow cover [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref072">72</a>]. When temperatures rise earlier in spring, the snow starts to melt, and snow free patches will also emerge much earlier, allowing reindeer to easily have access to lichens and dwarf shrubs. Altogether, (1) a better availability of late winter food and a decreasing amount of energy spent in thermoregulation [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref073">73</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref074">74</a>] and locomotion on snow [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref075">75</a>] due to a decreasing amount of snowfalls and a reduced snow cover in April, and (2) an earlier onset of the vegetative growing season [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref076">76</a>] and an increased plant biomass observed in the Arctic tundra [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref077">77</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref078">78</a>] due to warmer temperatures in April-May certainly contributed to increase females’ body condition in late pregnancy. Indeed, further analyses revealed that females’ body weight (a correlate of females’ BCI) had significantly increased over the last 45 years in this population. Such improvement in females’ physical condition will result in mothers having more resources during pregnancy, hence likely advancing the date at which the foetus is mature and resulting in an earlier birth, as compared to years with severe late winter conditions [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref042">42</a>]. The significant advancement in calving date could thus be explained by females in better condition giving birth earlier [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref042">42</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref044">44</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref079">79</a>]. The large influence of female body condition on calving date has already been highlighted in numerous studies (bighorn sheep [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref050">50</a>], caribou [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref028">28</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref042">42</a>], elk [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref045">45</a>], reindeer [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref043">43</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref044">44</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>]).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An optimal timing of calving will ensure that females have access to a high-quality vegetation (i.e. higher protein content), allowing their calves to be nourished with a high-quality milk [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref009">9</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref014">14</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref080">80</a>] and accelerating the rate of fat accumulation for calves. Moreover, earlier birth dates will (1) provide calves with a longer period of time to sufficiently accumulate fat reserves to survive winter and therefore promoting both their survival and growth, and (2) allow mothers to recover faster from their pregnancy and lactation period and to be in good enough shape to reproduce the next breeding season, promoting both their survival and reproductive success as a result [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref004">4</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref009">9</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref081">81</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref082">82</a>]. Therefore, such plastic response is essential for deer species to adapt to climate change by adjusting the period of high energetic requirements (i.e. lactation) with the period of high-quality forage and thereby ensuring offspring survival. Identifying the environmental variables that trigger a plastic response in the reproductive phenology of animal species is thus of primary concern in order to better predict their long term viability. Many species of birds and mammals have already been shown to rely on temperature to match the birth timing with the peak of resource availability [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref022">22</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref083">83</a>]. In ungulate species, females may adjust their gestation length as a strategy to give birth at the period of the year best suited for offspring survival. Such adjustment of gestation length as part of the reproductive tactic has previously been reported in reindeer [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref084">84</a>]. On the Isle of Rum, Scotland, warm March temperatures were associated with shorter average gestation lengths in red deer and Clements et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref085">85</a>] proposed that high March temperatures could act as a cue to indicate that the optimum birth date is likely to be earlier. The females of the Kutuharju field reindeer research station also seemed to rely on temperature in April-May but also on snow conditions (amount of snowfalls and snow depth index) in April to adjust their gestation length in late pregnancy and consequently calving time within the same year accordingly. Nevertheless, the significant relation between calving dates and mean temperature in April-May do not necessarily mean that females use temperature as a predictive cue for future environmental conditions. This correlation could just be the result of an increased female’s physical condition following improved climatic conditions in late winter/early spring. To demonstrate a cause-effect relationship and whether temperature has a direct signaling effect on seasonal timing, experimental approaches would be necessary but as Caro et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref083">83</a>] mentioned, “given the scarcity of experimental approaches investigating this causal effect of temperature, especially in mammals, generalizations are not possible and additional studies are desperately needed”.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec018" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic effects on calving synchrony</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calving synchrony was also affected by an overall warming of the period from August to December as well as a reduced snow cover in winter from December to February reported in the study area since a lengthening of the calving season was observed following an overall warming weather in January and an increasing number of days when mean temperature exceeds 0°C in October-November. The calving synchrony was also weakened by a decreasing snow cover in the period from October to November. Moreover, females with an overall better physical condition (i.e. above the third quantile of the population distribution) delayed their calving dates following a higher number of days when mean temperature exceeds 0°C in October-November (LMM; 
   <span class="italic">b</span> = 1.31 ± 0.56 SE; 95% CI (0.22, 2.39)) and warmer temperatures in January (LMM; 
   <span class="italic">b</span> = 1.36 ± 0.60 SE; 95% CI (0.18, 2.53)) whereas females in poor physical condition (i.e. below the first quantile of the population distribution) showed no phenotypic plasticity in their calving dates when facing better climatic conditions in October-November [95% CI = (-1.62, 0.68)] and in January [95% CI = (-0.05, 2.05)]. The lengthening of the calving season following better climatic conditions in October-November and warmer temperatures in January may thus reflect a reduced plasticity among low-quality mothers (young and light females), so that they are not able to respond as quickly as high-quality mothers (older and heavier females) do, to favourable climatic conditions in fall and winter.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The onset of the rut period in deer species has been shown to be mainly triggered by a sudden drop in temperature around the breeding season (around late September/October) which trigger males’ rutting behaviours to start [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref086">86</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref088">88</a>]. Therefore, a higher number of days when mean temperature exceeds 0°C in October-November, highly correlated with a decreasing snow cover during the same period, would delay the time when males begin to display mating behaviours; resulting in a delay in females’ estrus [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref089">89</a>]. Further analyses on a dataset of validated copulation dates (which led to the birth of a calf within the 211–229 days’ time window for gestation lengths reported in this herd [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>]) also revealed a delay in copulation dates only for females in poor physical condition in September following a higher number of days when mean temperature exceeds 0°C in October-November (LMM; 
   <span class="italic">b</span> = 3.06 ± 0.74 SE; 95% CI (1.46, 4.69)). Therefore, the delay in estrus dates following better climatic conditions around the mating time would be more pronounced for females in poor physical condition while females in good condition (old and heavy females) would still be mated earlier [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref089">89</a>]. As shown in many ungulate species, late copulation dates are also correlated with shorter gestation lengths [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref084">84</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref085">85</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref090">90</a>] such as females in poor physical condition not having enough reserves to buffer climatic effects and cope with gestation costs. On the contrary, females in good physical condition would be able to afford the risks of delayed calving dates (as reported above) when climatic conditions in fall are better [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref091">91</a>], and afford such the corresponding gestation costs and thus lengthen their gestation lengths [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref064">64</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref085">85</a>] to improve their calves’ condition at birth, increasing their own reproductive success the following summer as shown in caribou and reindeer [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref092">92</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref094">94</a>]. The lengthening of the calving season after years with better climatic conditions in October-November (warmer temperatures and a decreased snow cover) would thus be explained by delayed calving dates from females in good physical condition.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The positive relationship between mean temperature in January and calving synchrony was enhanced by females BCI. Indeed, longer calving seasons were observed following warmer temperatures in January contributing to increase females’ physical condition, which in turn delayed their calving dates (as described above). From the mother and offspring’s points of view, delaying calving when climatic conditions in winter are favorable provide selective advantages. A longer gestation length provides (1) the foetus a longer period for growth and development [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref095">95</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref096">96</a>], (2) a higher offspring’s birthweight [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref091">91</a>], ensuring a higher survival probability [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref035">35</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref045">45</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref085">85</a>] and (3) an enhanced fitness for the offspring [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref093">93</a>]. A higher offspring’s fitness will certainly mean improved fitness for the mother [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref093">93</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref094">94</a>]. However, the ability for a female to be plastic requires a higher physical condition to be physiologically able to do so [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref049">49</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref097">97</a>]. A warming temperature in January would allow pregnant females to spend less energy for thermoregulation [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref073">73</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref074">74</a>] and reduce the costs of locomotion on snow [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref075">75</a>], thus improving their overall physical condition. However, females with an overall higher physical condition would be more able to buffer climatic effects in warmer winters and allocate more resources to growth and development of their foetus [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref095">95</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref096">96</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref098">98</a>], whereas females in poor physical condition would probably prioritize the maintenance of their own body reserves over their foetus’s growth and development [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref095">95</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref096">96</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref099">99</a>]. In warmer winters, only females in good physical condition would be able to delay their calving dates, thereby contributing to a lengthening of the calving season in those years. Such asymmetric response to improved vs. reduced winter conditions has been demonstrated in reindeer as a ‘risk-averse adjustment in reproductive allocation’ [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref097">97</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inter-individual heterogeneity in the response to improved climatic conditions in October-November and January would thus be responsible for the variability in calving synchrony observed in this herd. Understanding what shapes inter-individual heterogeneity in the plasticity of calving date in response to climatic variation would be a natural continuation to this study. We noted that the shift in birth synchrony has occurred in the quasi-absence of predation (20 cases of calves killed by predation out of 2,137 birth dates) so that climatic variability seemed to be one of the main driver shaping calving synchrony in this population. As the competing models explained at best 23% of the variation in calving synchrony, it suggests that other parameters could also be important in explaining variation in the length of calving season (e.g. social, physiological or behavioural cues). Whether phenological changes in calving date and/or calving synchrony have consequences for populations’ recruitment rate and/or females’ reproductive success is a question with contrasted answers among ungulate species. In red deer, Moyes et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref070">70</a>] did not find a significant temporal change in either offspring birth weight or offspring first-winter survival whereas parturition date has advanced. On the contrary, Post and Forchhammer [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref023">23</a>] found a reduced production and survival of caribou calves following warmer spring temperatures due to a trophic mismatch between the caribou’s timing of calving and onset of the plant growing season in the Low Arctic Greenland. In this semi-domesticated reindeer population, assessing the offspring first-winter survival was not feasible because approximately one third of the calves are slaughtered every fall for meat production. However, calves who survived the summer had earlier birth dates than calves who died either at birth, after one day, one week or later in the summer (LMM; 
   <span class="italic">b</span> = -1.23 ± 0.37 SE; 95% CI (-1.96, -0.50)). Moreover, Holand et al. (unpublished) have found that both the calving dates and calves’ birth weight of this population are under stabilizing selection with advanced birth dates and increased calves’ birth weights. Whether such selection has consequences in terms of population dynamics and life history traits in this population is yet to be demonstrated but as Gaillard et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref100">100</a>] mentioned: “the immature stage, despite a low relative impact on population growth rate compared with the adult stage, may be the critical component of population dynamics of large herbivores”. Furthermore, conditions early in life has been reported to shape lifetime reproductive success [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref061">61</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref101">101</a>]. Therefore, changes in birth dates and birth weights could have major consequences on population dynamics of ungulate species like reindeer. More studies on this matter are needed with the need to disentangle behavioral/phenotypic plastic responses from microevolutionary responses and the consequences for ungulate populations [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref102">102</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec019" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calving season of the semi-domesticated reindeer population in Kaamanen, northern Finland has occurred earlier following warmer temperatures in April-May, a decreased amount of snowfalls in April and a reduced snow cover in April and has lengthened with a warming weather in January, a higher number of days when mean temperature exceeds 0°C in October-November and a decreasing snow cover in the period from October to November. Such phenological trends have allowed this reindeer population to track at least partially the climatic changes observed in this area. The phenology of many species have changed in response to climate change, particularly at higher latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere but most evidences came from long-term studies of many taxonomic groups other than ungulate species [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref021">21</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref103">103</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref104" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref104">104</a>]. As such, this study enhances our understanding of how reproductive phenology of ungulate species would be affected by climate change. That such results on a semi-domesticated reindeer population were observed, where supplemental feeding in harsh winter years could have helped to buffer against climatic conditions, suggests that influence of climatic variation on the reproductive phenology of wild populations might be even stronger. Therefore, more ecological studies linking reproductive phenology of wild populations to climatic variation are needed. While the calving date has already been found to be influenced by temperature and snow conditions [
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref033">33</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref035">35</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0195603.ref105" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0195603.ref105">105</a>], this study is so far the first to highlight an influence of weather variables on calving synchrony in ungulates. In summary, the variability of climatic conditions in the period from October to November and in January seemed important for the variability in females’ plastic response of calving dates to better climatic conditions and as a consequence in shaping calving synchrony at the population level whereas climatic conditions in early spring, just before the calving season, seemed more important in defining the calving dates at the individual level, likely because of its influence on the adjustment of each female’s gestation length.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
