<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6511225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6878</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecosystem Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Marine Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Coupled Natural and Human Systems</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Climate Change Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ecosystem effects of fishing &#x00026; El Ni&#x000f1;o at the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2833-9407</contrib-id><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>Tyler D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-4">4</xref><email>tyler.eddy@sc.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4858-006X</contrib-id><name><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>Alan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-6">6</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9155-8373</contrib-id><name><surname>Salinas de Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Pelayo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label><institution>Changing Ocean Research Unit, Institute for the Oceans &#x00026; Fisheries, University of British Columbia</institution>, <addr-line>Vancouver, BC</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label><institution>Department of Biology, Dalhousie University</institution>, <addr-line>Halifax, NS</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label><institution>Department of Marine Sciences, Charles Darwin Research Station</institution>, <addr-line>Puerto Ayora, Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands</addr-line>, <country>Ecuador</country></aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label><institution>Nereus Program, Baruch Institute for Marine &#x00026; Coastal Sciences, University of South Carolina</institution>, <addr-line>Columbia, SC</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff-5">
<label>5</label><institution>Pristine Seas, National Geographic Society</institution>, <addr-line>Washington, DC</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff-6">
<label>6</label><institution>Fisheries Ecology Research Lab, University of Hawai&#x02019;i</institution>, <addr-line>Honolulu, HI</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gabric</surname><given-names>Albert</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2019-05-08"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e6878</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-11-08"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-03-31"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 Eddy et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Eddy et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/6878"/><abstract><p>The Gal&#x000e1;pagos Archipelago is home to a diverse range of marine bioregions due to the confluence of several cold and warm water currents, resulting in some of the most productive tropical marine ecosystems in the world. These ecosystems are strongly influenced by El Ni&#x000f1;o events which can reduce primary production by an order of magnitude, dramatically reducing energy available throughout the food web. Fisheries are an important component of the local economy, although artisanal and illegal overfishing have dramatically reduced the productivity of invertebrate and finfish resources in recent decades, resulting in reductions in catches for local fishers. The regionally-endemic sailfin grouper (<italic>Myctereoperca olfax</italic>), locally known as <italic>bacalao</italic>, was once the most important fished species in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos, but is now listed as vulnerable by the IUCN due to its limited range and dramatic declines in catch over time. It is unknown how reduction of this predatory species has affected ecosystem structure and function. In the absence of stock assessments, we used an estimate of unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass from fishers&#x02019; ecological knowledge along with unfished biomass estimates of other heavily exploited stocks&#x02014;lobster (<italic>Panulirus penicillatus</italic> and <italic>P. gracilis</italic>) and sea cucumber (<italic>Isostichopus fuscus</italic>)&#x02014;to create historical, unfished versions of existing modern day ecosystem models. We used the unfished and modern versions of the ecosystem models to test the ecosystem effects of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation at the Bolivar Channel, located in the cold, west upwelling bioregion of the archipelago during both El Ni&#x000f1;o and non El Ni&#x000f1;o years, and at Floreana Island, in the warmer, central bioregion. Fishers&#x02019; ecological knowledge indicates that at present, the biomass of <italic>bacalao</italic> is at least seven times lower than when unfished. This reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass is linked with a greatly reduced ecosystem role compared to when unfished, and ecosystem role is further reduced in El Ni&#x000f1;o years. Allowing <italic>bacalao</italic> populations to rebuild to at least half of unfished biomass would partially restore their role within these ecosystems, while also resulting in greater fisheries catches. Comparing ecosystem impacts caused by fishing and El Ni&#x000f1;o, fishing has had a greater negative impact on <italic>bacalao</italic> ecosystem role than regular El Ni&#x000f1;o events.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Ecopath with Ecosim</kwd><kwd>Ecosystem-based fisheries management</kwd><kwd><italic>Myctereoperca olfax</italic></kwd><kwd>Fishers&#x02019; ecological knowledge</kwd><kwd>Keystone species</kwd><kwd>Grouper</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Robin Rigby Trust Collaborative Coastal Research Grant, Lindblad-National Geographic Conservation Fund</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Mohammed Bin Zayed Species Conservation Fund</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-3"><funding-source>Helmsley Charitable Trust</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from the Robin Rigby Trust Collaborative Coastal Research Grant, Lindblad-National Geographic Conservation Fund, the Mohammed Bin Zayed Species Conservation Fund, and the Helmsley Charitable Trust. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Understanding how environmental factors interact with exploitation of resources is a common concern among natural resource managers, biological conservationists, and scientists (<xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bender, Case &#x00026; Gilpin, 1984</xref>). In the marine environment, it has been suggested that fishing magnifies fluctuations in natural populations due to removing older individuals of the population which changes demographic parameters such as intrinsic growth rates (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Anderson et al., 2008</xref>). Removing top predators and keystone species from ecosystems can also cause trophic cascades and reshuffling of ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Worm et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Collie et al., 2016</xref>). We are now in the Anthropocene and changes in environmental conditions are the greatest that they have ever been (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Bopp et al., 2013</xref>), therefore, it is important to understand how populations are affected by the interaction between resource use and a changing world (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cheung, Reygondeau &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;licher, 2016</xref>).</p><p>The Galap&#x000e1;gos Archipelago hosts ecologically important, diverse, and fragile ecosystems with high levels of endemism (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2010</xref>). The strong upweling of the eastward-flowing Cromwell Current on the western portion of the archipelago produces some of the world&#x02019;s most productive tropical waters (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>). This region is strongly affected by El Ni&#x000f1;o events when upweling slows causing water temperatures to increase and substantially reducing primary production flow through ecosystems resulting in dramatic declines in abundance of many species (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>).</p><p>For local people living in the Galap&#x000e1;gos, fisheries are an important source of income. Landed fish are sold within the Archipelago to supply the rapidly growing tourism industry, as well as exported. The handline fishery for the regionally-endemic sailfin grouper (<italic>Mycteroperca olfax</italic>; locally referred to as <italic>bacalao</italic>) has operated since the 1920s and was once the most valuable fishery in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos, comprising over 40% of the mixed whitefish catch (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Reck, 1983</xref>). More recently, <italic>bacalao</italic> has accounted for &#x0003c;10% of the finfish catch, with fishers indicating that catch rates and average individual size have declined significantly over time (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Bustamante, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Burbano et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Schiller et al., 2015</xref>). Recent data indicate that 96% of <italic>bacalao</italic> caught are below reproductive size, with few large spawning individuals, and an extremely skewed sex ratio, suggesting eminent reproductive failure (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2016</xref>). Historical photographs from 1925 to 1938 indicate that average size of caught <italic>bacalao</italic> has declined from 77 to 47 cm in 2012 (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2016</xref>). The economic value of the fishery for <italic>bacalao</italic> has decreased tremendously over time and is not as economically important today as the fisheries for lobster (locally referred to as <italic>langosta</italic>; <italic>Panulirus penicillatus</italic> and <italic>P. gracilis</italic>), sea cucumber (locally referred to as <italic>pepino</italic>; <italic>Isostichopus fuscus</italic>) or pelagic fishes&#x02014;mainly wahoo, yellowfin tuna, and swordfish (<italic>Acanthocybium solandri</italic>, <italic>Thunnus albacares</italic>, and <italic>Xiphias gladius</italic>, respectively).</p><p>In 1998, the Special Law of Gal&#x000e1;pagos established the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve, which excluded industrial fishing fleets within 40 nautical miles of the islands. The coastal zoning scheme for the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve implemented in 2000, closed some areas to fishing (approximately 20% of the coastline, however &#x0003c;1% of the entire Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve), however compliance among fishers is poor&#x02014;with many fishers claiming to not know the locations of protected areas&#x02014;and there is little to no enforcement of closed areas (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Castrej&#x000f3;n &#x00026; Charles, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio, Schuhbauer &#x00026; Friedlander, 2014</xref>). Socio-economic inputs dominated the selection process of no-take zones in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve, with ecological considerations having a lower priority (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gonz&#x000e1;lez et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Castrej&#x000f3;n &#x00026; Charles, 2013</xref>). Other than no-take zones, there are no specific regulations for managing <italic>bacalao</italic> or any other finfish species within the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve.</p><p>The IUCN Red List currently categorizes <italic>bacalao</italic> as vulnerable due to its limited range and declining fishery catches (<xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Erisman &#x00026; Craig, 2018</xref>). The distribution of <italic>bacalao</italic> is limited to the offshore islands of Cocos, Costa Rica; Malpelo, Colombia; and Gal&#x000e1;pagos, Ecuador in the Tropical Eastern Pacific, however, it is rare at both Cocos and Malpelo (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Marconi, Beck &#x00026; Majluf, 2001</xref>). <italic>Bacalao</italic> is a top predator in the coastal ecosystems of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos and is a sequential hermaphrodite, as all individuals are born as females, and transition to males at approximately 12 years of age and 80 cm total length (<xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2015</xref>). The life history characteristics that make <italic>bacalao</italic> susceptible to overfishing, its ecological role within the Gal&#x000e1;pagos ecosystem, and its current threatened conservation status have prompted recent efforts to inform sustainable management of <italic>bacalao</italic> (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n, Rastoin &#x00026; Acu&#x000f1;a-Marrero, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>Understanding the impacts of fisheries and environment on marine ecosystems is a central tenant of ecosystem-based fisheries management (<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Pikitch et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Browman et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Link, 2010</xref>). Ecosystem models are one tool that have been used extensively to understand ecosystem effects of fishing (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Christensen &#x00026; Walters, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Worm et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Collie et al., 2016</xref>), as well as to understand climate change impacts on marine ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Cornwall &#x00026; Eddy, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Payne et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cheung, Reygondeau &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;licher, 2016</xref>). It is also important to understand how fisheries and environmental effects on ecosystems have changed through time, as exploited populations can have reduced roles within ecosystems&#x02014;especially for keystone groups (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Coll, Palomera &#x00026; Tudela, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Eddy et al., 2014</xref>). In the absence of detailed historical fisheries data, historical ecology, catch reconstructions, and fishers&#x02019; ecological knowledge are tools that can be used to estimate the biomass of unfished populations (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Jackson et al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Johannes, Freeman &#x00026; Hamilton, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Rosenberg et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Lotze et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Pauly &#x00026; Zeller, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Here, we use estimates of unfished <italic>bacalao</italic>, <italic>langosta</italic>, and <italic>pepino</italic> biomass to understand the magnitude of depletion throughout history. We employ existing ecosystem models for the Bolivar Channel (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>), in the cold western bioregion, and Floreana Island, in the warmer central bioregion (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>), to run simulations of varying levels of <italic>bacalao</italic> fishing for unfished and modern periods. We then examine the impacts of <italic>bacalao</italic> fishing on its biomass and ecosystem role, as well as its impacts on other groups in the ecosystem and how these impacts change during El Ni&#x000f1;o years at the Bolivar Channel.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Ecosystem models</title><p>We used published Ecopath with Ecosim (EwE; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Christensen &#x00026; Walters, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Christensen et al., 2008</xref>) models for Floreana Island (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>) located in the warm, central bioregion and two models for Bolivar Channel, located in the cold, west bioregion, representing normal, and El Ni&#x000f1;o years (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). All three of these models include fisheries for <italic>bacalao</italic>. The Floreana Island model is available online from Ecobase (<uri xlink:href="http://sirs.agrocampus-ouest.fr/EcoBase/">http://sirs.agrocampus-ouest.fr/EcoBase/</uri>), while the Bolivar Channel models are available by contacting the model developers.</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Map of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve (GMR) indicating ecosystem model locations at the Bolivar Channel and Floreana Island.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-g001"/></fig><sec><title>Floreana Island</title><p>Floreana Island is located in the warm, central bioregion, characterized by a high regional mix of cold and warm-water biota (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>). The Floreana Island ecosystem model was parameterized for the rocky reefs surrounding the island between 0 and 20 m depth (partial depth range inhabited by <italic>bacalao</italic>), covering 6.44 km<sup>2</sup> or 36% of the rocky reef habitat of the island. The model was parameterized for the time period 2000&#x02013;2001, and is characterized by 42 functional groups including <italic>bacalao&#x02014;</italic>estimated to have a trophic level of 4.2 (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>)&#x02014;with prey groups that consisted of planktivorous reef fishes accounting for 60% of diet, small benthic invertebrate eating fishes accounting for 20% of diet, and 20% of diet represented by imports and informed by the literature (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Floreana Island ecosystem model characteristics and fishing simulation results.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-g004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prey groups</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unfished</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sharks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;12, 14, 17&#x02013;19, 21, 22, 27, 29, 32&#x02013;36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toothed cetaceans</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 3, 5&#x02013;11, 21, 27, 32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacalao</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;&#x02010;&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;&#x02010;&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Birds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 6, 7, 9&#x02013;12, 14, 15, 18, 21, 27, 32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea lions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 6, 8&#x02013;10, 12, 14, 21, 27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelagic predators</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, 11, 18, 21, 32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-commercial reef predators</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 14, 15, 18, 19, 21, 37, 39, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octopods</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7, 10&#x02013;12, 14, 16&#x02013;19, 21, 38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pelagic planktivores</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 19, 37, 39, 40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other commercial reef predators</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11, 12, 15, 18, 19, 22, 24, 37, 39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large benthic invertebrate eaters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13, 16&#x02013;19, 21, 24, 28, 31, 35, 36, 38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Planktivorous reef fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 39, 40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexaplex gastropod</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small benthic invertebrate eaters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 19, 22, 24, 25, 28, 31, 37&#x02013;39, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carnivorous zooplankton</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39, 40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiny lobsters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19, 20, 22&#x02013;24, 26, 28, 35, 36, 38, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slipper lobster</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 14, 18, 19, 21, 22, 24, 28, 35, 36, 38, 42, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Omnivorous reef fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 19, 23&#x02013;25, 28, 37&#x02013;39, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shrimps and small crabs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12, 14, 15, 21, 23&#x02013;25, 28, 37&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteroids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19, 23&#x02013;25, 28, 30, 38, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other herbivorous fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 28, 37, 39, 42, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eucidaris urchin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25, 42, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anemones</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13, 15, 19, 20, 22, 24&#x02013;26, 28, 30&#x02013;31, 34&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worms and ophioroids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 25, 28, 37&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stony corals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 39&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chitons</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detritivorous fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small gastropods</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24, 25, 37, 38, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea turtles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15, 42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea cucumbers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23, 24, 41, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other urchins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parrotfishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25, 41&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marine iguana</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other sea cucumbers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40, 42, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tripneustes urchin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lytechinus urchin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small crustaceans</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#x02013;43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filter + suspension feeders</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herbivorous zooplankton</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40, 43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytoplankton</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microphytobenthos</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benthic algae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detritus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02010;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p><bold>Note:</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Floreana Island ecosystem model characteristics and results indicating direction and magnitude of change in biomass of functional groups at modern levels of <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion (85%) compared to unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass (1 &#x02212; (<italic>B<sub>i</sub></italic>/<italic>B<sub>0</sub></italic>)) for unfished and modern versions of the model (TL = trophic level; &#x02010; = &#x02010; &#x0003c;20% change, &#x02010;&#x02010; = &#x02010; &#x0003e;20% and &#x02010; &#x0003c;40% change, &#x02010;&#x02010;&#x02010; = &#x0003e;40% change; + = &#x0003c;20% change, ++ = &#x0003e;20% and &#x0003c;40% change, +++ = &#x0003e;40% change).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Floreana Island production, consumption, and diet data were mostly derived from the literature; biomass estimates of benthic, demersal, and pelagic fish groups, large invertebrates, birds, turtles, sharks, and marine mammals were based on site-specific observations; and primary production was estimated from ocean color satellite data (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Bolivar channel</title><p>The Bolivar Channel is located in the cold west bioregion, characterized by cool, nutrient rich, upwelled waters, and associated biota including dense macroalgae beds, the world&#x02019;s only tropical penguin, and the flightless cormorant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>). The Bolivar Channel ecosystem model was parameterized for rocky habitat between 0 and 30 m depth surrounding Isabela and Fernandina islands, covering 44 km<sup>2</sup> or 14% of the total Bolivar Channel area (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). This model represents the average ecosystem state for the years 2004&#x02013;2008, and includes 30 different functional groups, including <italic>bacalao</italic>, with a predicted trophic level of 3.39 (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), and a diet of 26% sea stars and sea urchins, 20% benthic omnivorous fishes, 9% small planktivorous reef fishes, 8% surgeonfish, chubs, and giant damselfishes, 7% mullets, 6% benthic predatory fish, 5% gorgonians, and six other groups each accounting for &#x0003c;5% of total diet (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>). There was also a Bolivar Channel model that was forced using a 16-year time series of satellite-derived phytoplankton biomass from 1994 to 2009, which included the strong El Ni&#x000f1;o of 1997&#x02013;1998 (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The El Ni&#x000f1;o version of the model has a primary productivity reduction of 76% relative to the non El Ni&#x000f1;o model (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Bolivar Channel ecosystem model characteristics and fishing simulation results.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prey groups</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Direction and magnitude of biomass change</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unfished non El Ni&#x000f1;o</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern non El Ni&#x000f1;o</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unfished El Ni&#x000f1;o</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modern El Ni&#x000f1;o</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytoplankton</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macroalgae + others</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgeonfishes, chubs and giant damiselfishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea cucumbers and other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herbivorous zooplankton</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 2, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea turtles and marine iguanas</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 5, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small herbivorous gastropods</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 5, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sponges and polychaetes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 18, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gorgonians</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 18, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parrotfishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 9, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mullets</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benthic omnivorous fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 2, 5, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anemones and zooanthids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 18, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sea stars and sea urchins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 8, 9, 13, 19, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Planktivorous reef fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 18, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small planktivorous reef fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 18, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lobsters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 14, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predatory zooplankton</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1, 5, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large gastropods and other sea stars</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2, 7, 9, 13, 14, 20, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small predatory gastropods</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 7&#x02013;9, 13, 18, 30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small benthic predatory fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 11, 12, 14, 16, 18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benthic predatory fishes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 7, 11, 12, 14, 16, 17, 20, 21, 23, 24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barracudas</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 11, 12, 15, 16, 21, 22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groupers</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 7, 11, 12, 14, 15&#x02013;17, 20&#x02013;23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-&#x0200a;-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jacks and mackerels</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 11, 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-&#x0200a;-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rays</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4, 14, 17, 19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predatory marine mammals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10, 11, 12, 15&#x02013;17, 19, 21&#x02013;25, 29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seabirds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3, 11, 16, 23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sharks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6, 11, 12, 16, 21&#x02013;23, 25&#x02013;27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+++</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detritus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Note:</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Bolivar Channel ecosystem model characteristics and results indicating direction and magnitude of change in biomass of functional groups at modern <italic>bacalao</italic> level of depletion (85%) compared to unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass (1 &#x02212; (<italic>B<sub>i</sub></italic>/<italic>B<sub>0</sub></italic>)) for unfished and modern versions of the El Ni&#x000f1;o and non El Nino models (TL = trophic level; (TL = trophic level; - = - &#x0003c;20% change, -&#x0200a;- = - &#x0003e;20% and - &#x0003c;40% change, -&#x0200a;-&#x0200a;- = &#x0003e;40% change; + = &#x0003c;20% change, ++ = &#x0003e;20% and &#x0003c;40% change, +++ = &#x0003e;40% change).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Bolivar Channel production, consumption, and diet parameters were estimated from the literature, while biomass estimates of fish, invertebrate, sea bird, marine mammal, and reptile were based on observations from within the model area (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>). Primary production estimates were derived from satellite observations of ocean color, while zooplankton biomass was estimated from observational data (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Unfished biomass estimates</title><p>To understand the ecosystem impact of <italic>bacalao</italic> fishing through time in the absence of stock assessments, we estimated unfished biomass of the most heavily exploited species (<italic>bacalao, langosta</italic>, and <italic>pepino</italic>), using a variety of sources. <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Burbano et al. (2014)</xref> interviewed fishers of different ages, asking them to recall their best catches of <italic>bacalao</italic>. Older fishers indicated a 6.82-fold decline in their best catches from the 1940&#x02013;1950s compared to 2010. <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Ruttenberg (2001)</xref> surveyed reef fishes using underwater visual surveys in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve at both lightly and heavily fished areas in 1998, and found 22-fold less biomass in heavily fished areas. <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Schiller et al. (2015)</xref> performed catch reconstructions at the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands, however did not provide specific values of catches or biomass of <italic>bacalao</italic>. <italic>Pepino</italic> were estimated at six- to eightfold greater biomass when unfished (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>) and there has been a 10-fold decrease in catch per unit effort (CPUE; <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Defeo, Castilla &#x00026; Castrej&#x000f3;n, 2009</xref>). <italic>Langosta</italic> are reported to be 10-fold greater in the more remote northern Darwin and Wolf Islands (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2010</xref>). We applied the <italic>bacalao</italic> multiplier of 6.82 from <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Burbano et al. (2014)</xref> to the modern biomass values to estimate unfished biomasses in each of the three ecosystem models. We applied unfished biomass multipliers of seven for <italic>pepino</italic> (mean value from <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>) and 10 for <italic>langosta</italic> (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Modeling strategy</title><p>We simulated a range of <italic>bacalao</italic> fisheries mortality rates (<italic>F</italic>)&#x02014;from no exploitation (<italic>F</italic> = 0) to local extinction&#x02014;using the Floreana Island and Bolivar Channel models to understand the ecosystem effects of fishing (<italic>sensu</italic>
<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Eddy et al., 2015</xref>). For the modern models, we held fishing mortality (<italic>F</italic>) of all other exploited groups constant at their most recent levels. For the unfished models, we removed all fishing morality aside from that for <italic>bacalao.</italic> Simulations were run until the end of their historical time series when available, and then run for 100 years to allow models to reach equilibrium following the change in <italic>bacalao</italic> fishing mortality. Additionally, in order to understand the ecosystem effects of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation during El Ni&#x000f1;o years, we ran a similar range of exploitation rates of <italic>bacalao</italic> using the Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o model. Only the Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o model was fit to time series data to tune vulnerability values. In the absence of model fits to time series for the other two models, we used the default vulnerabilities.</p><p>In order to standardize exploitation levels across all models, we calculated the level of <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion as the proportion of biomass compared to unfished biomass <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-i001.jpg"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\left( {1 - \left( {{B_i}/{B_0}} \right)} \right)$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-2"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. We report ecosystem effects for 60% depletion as this is a common target used in fisheries management (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Worm et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2011</xref>). We calculated maximum sustainable yield (MSY) as the maximum <italic>bacalao</italic> catch produced by any simulation.</p></sec><sec><title>Ecosystem impacts</title><p>We calculated the ecosystem impacts of varying levels of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation on the biomasses of all other functional groups in the ecosystem. We represent the biomasses of the other functional groups as the proportion of their biomass when <italic>bacalao</italic> was fished at the level of depletion <italic>i</italic> (<italic>B<sub>i</sub></italic>) compared to the biomass when <italic>bacalao</italic> was unfished (<italic>B</italic><sub>0</sub>). This impact is analgous to the interaction strength index developed by <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Okey (2004)</xref> presented in the original Floreana Island EwE model description (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Keystone species are those that display disproportionately large impacts on the biomasses of other groups in an ecosystem compared to their biomass (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Power et al., 1996</xref>). Keystone values of <italic>bacalao</italic> in each of three models for each time period were calculated by EwE using the mixed trophic analysis which quantifies how much other functional groups are impacted in their biomass (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Christensen &#x00026; Walters, 2004</xref>) and the keystone index developed by <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Libralato, Christensen &#x00026; Pauly (2006)</xref> which quantifies how the ecosystem impacts relate to the biomass of the impacting group. The <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Okey (2004)</xref> dynamic keystoneness index more explicitly accounts for the relative biomass of the impacting group, whereas the <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Libralato, Christensen &#x00026; Pauly (2006)</xref> keystone index tends to emphasize interaction strength. We compare the results from both approaches in the discussion.</p></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p>To assess how sensitive model results were to parameter estimates, we performed a sensitivity analysis on <italic>bacalao</italic> unfished biomass estimates and <italic>bacalao</italic> diet. For the three unfished models, instead of using the 6.82 <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass multiplier, we used a conservative estimate of half of the biomass multiplier of 3.41. Using this conservative estimate, we ran the same fishing simulations as above. We compared the results of these simulations to the results from the original unfished models and calculated sensitivity as the difference in ecosystem impacts that resulted from 100% <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion (local extinction), as these simulations produced the greatest ecosystem impacts&#x02014;measured as biomass changes in other functional groups. As indicated above, using the multiplier of 22 times more <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass in unfished versions of the model did not produce simulations that reached equilibrium. We also examined the effect of switching <italic>bacalao</italic> diets from the Floreana model to the Bolivar Channel models and vice versa. The only stomach content analysis of <italic>bacalao</italic> indicates that it is piscivorous (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez, 1984</xref>). The Floreana <italic>bacalao</italic> diet is piscivorous, therefore the Bolivar Channel model was run with the Floreana diet to represent a piscivorous <italic>bacalao</italic> diet. We examined model sensitivity in the same way as for biomass, and also by comparing the estimated trophic levels of <italic>bacalao</italic> with each diet. The Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o model parameterized with the Floreana diet did not reach equilibrium during simulations and therefore results are not presented.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Ecosystem role of <italic>bacalao</italic></title><p>Unfished biomass versions of the Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o and non El Ni&#x000f1;o ecosystem models indicated much greater ecosystem impacts of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation compared to the modern day models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). In the unfished non El Ni&#x000f1;o model, at the modern level of <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion (85%), 38% of functional groups were impacted by at least a 20% change in biomass, while 21% of functional groups were impacted by at least a 40% change in biomass (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2A</xref>). In the modern day model, at the current level of <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion (85%), 21% and 7% of functional groups were impacted by at least 20% and 40% biomass, respectively (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2B</xref>). There was an even greater impact of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation in the unfished El Ni&#x000f1;o version of the Bolivar Channel model, where at 85% <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion, 62% and 34% of functional groups were impacted by at least 20% and 40% of their biomass, respectively, compared to when <italic>bacalao</italic> was unfished (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2D</xref>). The modern day version of the model also showed much smaller ecosystem impacts, similar to the modern day non El Ni&#x000f1;o model at modern level of depletion (85%), with 7% and 3% of functional groups impacted by 20% and 40% of biomass compared to when <italic>bacalao</italic> was unexploited (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2D</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Trade-offs between ecosystem impacts and catches of <italic>bacalao</italic> as a function of fishing exploitation for different EwE models during historical and modern times.</title><p>Ecosystem impact is represented as the proportion of trophic groups other than <italic>bacalao</italic> with a biomass change of by at least 20% (blue line) or 40% (red line) of their unfished biomass. Modern level of <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion (LOD) is represented by the yellow line. Catch is plotted on the secondary axis as a proportion of maximum sustainable yield (MSY). (A) Unfished Bolivar Channel; (B) Bolivar Channel; (C) Unfished Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o; (D) Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o; (E) Unfished Floreana Island; (F) Floreana Island.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-g002"/></fig><p>The functional groups that differed in biomass the most at modern <italic>bacalao</italic> level of depletion (85%) in the unfished non El Ni&#x000f1;o Bolivar Channel model compared to the modern day version with increased biomasses were: phytoplankton, gorgonians, mullets, benthic omnivorous fishes, small benthic predatory fishes, benthic predatory fishes, predatory marine mammals, and sharks (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Groups that showed decreased biomasses in their unfished non El Ni&#x000f1;o model compared to the modern day version were: small herbivorous gastropods, sponges and polychaetes, parrotfishes, anemones and zooanthids, jacks and mackerels, and detritus (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Comparing the two El Ni&#x000f1;o Bolivar Channel models at modern <italic>bacalao</italic> levels of depletion, functional groups that were at greater biomass in the unfished model compared to the modern day version were: surgeonfishes, chubs and giant damiselfishes, gorgonians, mullets, benthic omnivorous fishes, sea stars and sea urchins, planktivorous reef fishes, small planktivorous reef fishes, small predatory gastropods, small benthic predatory fishes, barracudas, jacks and mackerels, predatory marine mammals, seabirds, and sharks (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Functional groups that showed the greatest biomass decreases were: anemones and zooanthids and predatory zooplankton (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>The unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass version of the Floreana Island model showed greater influence of <italic>bacalao</italic> compared to the modern version (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2F</xref>). In the unfished biomass model, at 85% <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion, 5% of functional groups were impacted by at least 20% biomass, while 2% were impacted by 40% of their biomass (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2E</xref>). Only 3% and 2% of groups were impacted by both 20% and 40% of their biomass, respectively in the modern day model when <italic>bacalao</italic> was depleted by 85% (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2F</xref>). The functional groups most impacted by 85% <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion in the unfished biomass model were sharks, non-commercial reef predators, and chitons which were all at greater biomasses compared to modern day, while octopods had lower biomass in the unfished model (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Tradeoffs between <italic>bacalao</italic> catch and ecosystem impacts</title><p>The modern level of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation of 85% depletion is higher than that predicted to yield MSY in all six ecosystem models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Unfished biomass MSY was predicted to occur at lower levels of exploitation in the El Ni&#x000f1;o Bolivar Channel and Floreana models (44% and 38% depletion, respectively) compared to the modern day versions (45% and 58% depletion, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2C</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2F</xref>). The non El Ni&#x000f1;o Bolivar Channel models predicted MSY to occur at 45% depletion at unfished biomass and 43% in the modern day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2B</xref>). In all of the unfished models, fishing at levels producing MSY compared to the modern day exploitation rate (vertical yellow lines) reduces ecosystem impacts, and increases fisheries catches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). The reduction of ecosystem impacts by reducing fishing depletion to MSY levels is greatest for the unfished Bolivar Channel models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2C</xref>). In the unfished Floreana model, reducing fishing depletion to MSY levels results in decrease in functional groups impacted by both 40% and 20% of their biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2F</xref>). In the modern versions of all models, the ecosystem role of <italic>bacalao</italic> has been diminished due to greater levels of depletion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2F</xref>). In the Bolivar Channel models, reducing fishing pressure to MSY levels decreases ecosystem impacts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2D</xref>).</p><p>It is clear that the reduction of <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass due to fishing represented in the modern models has resulted in a diminished ecosystem role (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). By comparing the Bolivar Chanel models during El Ni&#x000f1;o and non El Ni&#x000f1;o years and during unfished and modern states, it is possible to weigh the relative effects of fishing through top-down trophic control and environmental conditions that affect bottom-up primary production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Comparatively, the El Ni&#x000f1;o models do show opposite responses in the unfished and modern models, whereby ecosystem effects of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation get amplified during El Ni&#x000f1;o unfished, while in the modern Bolivar Channel models, ecosystem impacts of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation are diminished during El Ni&#x000f1;o (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Figs. 2A</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">2D</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Keystone role of <italic>bacalao</italic></title><p>In the unfished versions of all three models, the keystone role (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Libralato, Christensen &#x00026; Pauly, 2006</xref>) of <italic>bacalao</italic> was greater than in modern versions of the models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). Of the unfished models, <italic>bacalao</italic> showed the greatest keystone value in the Bolivar Channel, followed by the El Ni&#x000f1;o version of the Bolivar Channel, and Floreana Island (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). For the modern day models, this ranking remained the same, however, all of the values were lower, indicating a diminished keystone role (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Keystone values (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Libralato, Christensen &#x00026; Pauly, 2006</xref>) for <italic>bacalao</italic> during unfished and modern time periods for the Gal&#x000e1;pagos EwE models.</title><p>RTI, relative total impact.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-g003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p>Reducing unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass reduced the ecosystem effects of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The greatest reduction in ecosystem impacts was observed for the Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o model, which also showed the greatest ecosystem impacts during simulations with the greater estimate of unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Similarly, for the unfished Bolivar Channel and Floreana models, reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass also reduced ecosystem impacts (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). Swapping the Floreana and Bolivar Channel <italic>bacalao</italic> diets led to increased ecosystem impacts in both cases. Swapping diets reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> trophic level at Floreana decreased from 4.2 to 4.0, while it increased <italic>bacalao</italic> trophic level at Bolivar Channel from 3.4 to 3.5.</p><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Sensitivity analysis results from reducing unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass and from switching <italic>bacalao</italic> diets from the Floreana model to the Bolivar Channel models and vice versa.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity scenario</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per cent change in number of functional groups impacted by &#x0003e;&#x000b1;40% of their biomass</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per cent change in number of functional groups impacted by &#x0003e;&#x000b1;20% of their biomass</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bolivar Channel unfished with reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o unfished with reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floreana unfished with reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bolivar Channel with Floreana diet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+7%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floreana with Bolivar diet</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+4%</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p><bold>Note:</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Results are from simulations that produced the maximum ecosystem impacts (100% <italic>bacalao</italic> depletion).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Impact of <italic>bacalao</italic> fishing</title><p>We have shown how the ecosystem role of <italic>bacalao</italic> has been greatly diminished with overexploitation&#x02014;which has depleted the stock by 85% compared to unfished levels. This reduced biomass has led to decreases in the ecosystem role played by <italic>bacalao</italic> in all models examined, through direct and indirect feeding interactions with other groups. We did not observe any local extinctions of other species when <italic>bacalao</italic> was fished to local extinction, however, there were large changes in biomass of many functional groups, indicating large ecosystem reshuffling. Our results also suggest that <italic>bacalao</italic> catches could be much greater if their populations were allowed to recover to approximately half of their unfished biomass. This recovery would also reduce ecosystem impacts, creating a win-win situation. The cost associated with such a management action would be a short-term reduction in fisheries catches, which would allow stocks to recover to levels that produce MSY. Such trade-offs among ecological, economical, and societal factors are a central tenant of fisheries policy and management, and have been examined in detail in many marine ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Worm et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Eddy et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Ecosystem role of groupers</title><p>Our results indicate that when unfished, <italic>bacalao</italic> has a much greater keystone role in all three models, also reflected by greater ecosystem effects when unfished with dynamic simulations of <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation. A low <italic>bacalao</italic> keystone value was also reported for the modern Floreana Island model using a different keystone index, adding confidence to our findings (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Okey, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Okey et al., 2004</xref>). Recent work indicates that <italic>bacalao</italic> are extremely size over-fished, suggesting that their modern diet could be different than historically (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2016</xref>). These observations are consistent with other studies that have quantified the change in keystone role of species resulting from intensive exploitation, such as dolphins in the northwest Mediterranean (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Coll, Palomera &#x00026; Tudela, 2009</xref>), and lobster (<italic>Jasus edwardsii</italic>) in New Zealand (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Eddy et al., 2014</xref>). For lobster in New Zealand, the increase in keystone role resulted from a density-dependent change in their diet in unfished areas where greater lobster biomass was observed, where they were more generalist and herbivorous, resulting in decreased trophic level (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Freeman, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Jack, Wing &#x00026; McLeod, 2009</xref>). Currently, it is unclear how the diet of <italic>bacalao</italic> at the Gal&#x000e1;pagos may have changed since historical times when they were found in much higher abundance, but previous work has shown <italic>bacalao</italic> to be highly piscivorous (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez, 1984</xref>). Our sensitivity analysis indicates that a change in <italic>bacalao</italic> diet is a source of variation in ecosystem impacts, however not as great as impacts due to reduced biomass due to fishing.</p><p>The aim of using non-traditional, quantitative sources such as fishers&#x02019; ecological knowledge is to extend time series to avoid the &#x0201c;shifting baseline syndrome&#x0201d; (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Pauly, 1995</xref>) in order to provide appropriate targets for fisheries management and conservation (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Rosenberg et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Eddy, Gardner &#x00026; P&#x000e9;rez-Matus, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Burbano et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Eddy, Cheung &#x00026; Bruno, 2018</xref>). It has been found that a greater sample size of interviewed fishers leads to less biased estimates of past fishing activities (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Shepperson et al., 2014</xref>). The study that informed our unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass estimate interviewed 124 fishers, accounting for 24% of the fishing population (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Burbano et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>Groupers are particularly vulnerable to overexploitation due to their life history characteristics (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Sadovy de Mitcheson et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2015</xref>). A massive decline in the IUCN designated &#x0201c;endangered&#x0201d; goliath grouper (<italic>Epinephelus itajara</italic>) was documented in south Florida USA, using old photographs of winning catches from fishing competitions that indicated a 86% decline in grouper populations from 1956 to 1979, and newspaper accounts dating back to 1923 suggested that the population was already impacted by fishing prior to 1950 (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">McClenachan, 2009</xref>). The prey of goliath grouper likely benefited directly by this large reduction in predation by grouper, and we would also expect indirect negative effects on prey of grouper prey through meso-predator release, as well as increased competition among grouper prey with other species (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">McClenachan, 2009</xref>). In our simulations, the groups that benefitted most from <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation in the Bolivar Channel were anenomes and zooanthids for both El Ni&#x000f1;o and non El Ni&#x000f1;o models; parrotfishes and sponges and polychaetes for the non El Ni&#x000f1;o model, and predatory zooplankton in the El Ni&#x000f1;o model. Following the strong 1997&#x02013;1998 El Ni&#x000f1;o, anemone barrens were observed, providing new benthic habitat for colonization (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Okey, Shepherd &#x00026; Mart&#x000ed;nez, 2003</xref>). For Floreana Island, octopods benefitted from <italic>bacalao</italic> exploitation. All of these increases were due to indirect feeding interactions, highlighting ecosystem cascades that result from removing a key species.</p></sec><sec><title>Unfished biomass estimates</title><p>Working with data poor study systems and trying to reconstruct historical ecosystem states often requires using qualitative information sources that have a high amount of uncertainty in parameter estimates (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">McClenachan, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Schiller et al., 2015</xref>). We only presented results for the lower estimate of unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass, because the higher estimate of 22-fold more <italic>bacalao</italic> from surveys (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Ruttenberg, 2001</xref>) caused the model to become highly unbalanced, without an equilibrium being reaching during simulations. Therefore, our simulations should be considered a conservative estimate of unfished <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass. We acknowledge that this is one of many hypotheses of how the unfished ecosystem may have looked. Species other than those that were primarily targeted by the artisanal fishery have also been exploited, through bycatch, bait or subsistence fisheries.</p></sec><sec><title>Bacalao diet estimates</title><p>The results from the food-web modeling approach that we have employed here are dependent on diet preferences specified in the models. As above, <italic>bacalao</italic> diet composition varies substantially between the two models. Therefore, we can think of these two different ecosystem models as alternate hypotheses of ecosystem structure and function at the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands, which can be further tested and refined as future data become available. It should also be noted that these two model areas are located in different bioregions with different community compositions, which likely contribute to differences in diet. Surveys do not indicate higher abundances of <italic>bacalao</italic> in no-take areas, likely due to lack of compliance and enforcement (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2004</xref>), which has also been observed for lobster (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Buglass et al., 2018</xref>). In the future, if these areas do provide <italic>bacalao</italic> populations protection from fishing, they will be an invaluable resource to understand not only how <italic>bacalao</italic> diet composition changes as biomass increases, but also how the biomasses of all other species in the ecosystem change as a result of direct and indirect interactions.</p></sec><sec><title>Fisheries management in a changing world</title><p>Understanding the impact that regular, although not always predictable, environmental events, such as El Ni&#x000f1;o have on ecosystems is extremely important for ecosystem-based fisheries management, as exploitation of marine resources does not occur in isolation&#x02014;these events impact species of conservation interest and species of importance for the tourism sector (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Lynham et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n et al., 2016</xref>). The cold-west upwelling region of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos is particularly sensitive to El Ni&#x000f1;o events, which result in increased water temperatures and large declines in primary production (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor, 2012</xref>) with catastrophic effects on many marine species (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Okey, Shepherd &#x00026; Mart&#x000ed;nez, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Okey, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2010</xref>). Climate change projections for the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands from an ensemble of Earth system models indicate an increase in primary production under the strong mitigation of emissions scenario (RCP 2.6; <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Bopp et al., 2013</xref>). However, the business as usual emissions scenario (RCP 8.5) indicates a decrease in primary production (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Bopp et al., 2013</xref>), which could lead to an ecosystem state observed in Bolivar Channel El Ni&#x000f1;o model. Considering the relative contributions of <italic>bacalao</italic> fishing and environmental factors to changes in simulated ecosystem effects, our results indicate that reduced <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass through overexploitation has produced greater ecosystem effects than El Ni&#x000f1;o. This finding is similar to another study which concluded that the ecosystem effects of fishing greatly outweighed projected impacts of ocean acidification (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Cornwall &#x00026; Eddy, 2015</xref>).</p><p><italic>Bacalao</italic> is not the only species that has been heavily exploited at the Gal&#x000e1;pagos, as there have been collapses of <italic>pepino</italic> (sea cucumber) and <italic>langosta</italic> (lobster) fisheries in recent history (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Bustamante, Okey &#x00026; Banks, 2008</xref>). Additionally, the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Archipelago is home to a number of species of conservation interest, and understanding the trophic relationships that mediate direct and indirect interactions among these species is imperative to understand how the decline or recovery of one species will affect others. This approach is the basis of ecosystem-based fisheries management, which sets the management unit at the scale of ecosystem rather than individual populations. This study, along with other recent studies describing life history (<xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2015</xref>), reproductive behavior (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n, Rastoin &#x00026; Acu&#x000f1;a-Marrero, 2015</xref>), fishery bycatch and discards rates (<xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Zimmerhackel et al., 2015</xref>), and fisheries characteristics (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Usseglio et al., 2016</xref>) of <italic>bacalao</italic> will allow for an evidence-based management plan for this species, to be developed in partnership with the fisheries managing authority, the Gal&#x000e1;pagos National Park Directorate, and stakeholders such as fishers, the tourism industry, and environmental NGOs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Using multiple lines of evidence about how exploited populations have changed through time, we have created hypotheses about how unfished ecosystems at the Gal&#x000e1;pagos may have been structured. The large reduction in <italic>bacalao</italic> biomass due to fishing has reduced its ecosystem role through direct and indirect feeding interactions. Allowing <italic>bacalao</italic> populations to recover to approximately half of their unfished biomass will partially restore their ecosystem roles as well as provide greater fisheries productivity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title>Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Output simulation data.</title><p>Output simulation data used for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref></p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-s001.csv"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6878/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Keystone simulation data.</title><p>Keystone simulation data used to create <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-6878-s002.csv"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to the Charles Darwin Foundation and the Galapagos National Park Directorate for the institutional support. This study was authorized by the Galapagos National Park under permit PC-16-15. We thank Diego Ruiz for providing access to the Bolivar Channel ecosystem models and Stuart Banks for providing access to the Floreana Island ecosystem model. This is contribution number 2259 from the Charles Darwin Research Station for the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conflict-1"><p>There are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-1"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Tyler D. Eddy</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-2"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Alan M. Friedlander</xref> authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-3"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Pelayo Salinas de Le&#x000f3;n</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>We do not have permission to share the third-party models that we used to perform the simulations, however, interested parties can access the Floreana Island model on the Ecobase website &#x02013; <uri xlink:href="http://sirs.agrocampus-ouest.fr/EcoBase/">http://sirs.agrocampus-ouest.fr/EcoBase/</uri>. The Bolivar Channel models can be obtained by contacting Diego Ruiz &#x02013; diego.ruiz@zmt-breman.de.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Anderson et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>CNK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollowed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beddington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why fishing magnifies fluctuations in fish abundance</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><issue>7189</issue><fpage>835</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18421346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Bender, Case &#x00026; Gilpin (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilpin</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perturbation experiments in community ecology: theory and practice</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1984</year><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1939452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Bopp et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bopp</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Resplandy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Doney</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehlen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Halloran</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinze</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilyina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;f&#x000e9;rian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjiputra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple stressors of ocean ecosystems in the 21st century: projections with CMIP5 models</article-title><source>Biogeosciences</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>6225</fpage><lpage>6245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/bg-10-6225-2013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Browman et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browman</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Cury</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilborn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Murawski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sissenwine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stergiou</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on ecosystem-based approaches to the management of marine resources</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><year>2004</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps274269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Brown et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobday</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matear</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Possingham</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehrke</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribble</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano-Montes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of climate-driven primary production change on marine food webs: implications for fisheries and conservation</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2009.02046.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Buglass et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buglass</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the effectiveness of coastal no-take zones of the Galapagos Marine Reserve for the red spiny lobster, <italic>Panulirus penicillatus</italic></article-title><source>Marine Policy</source><year>2018</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2017.11.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Burbano et al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burbano</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mena</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarderas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinueza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Denkinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinueza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shifting baselines in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos white fin fishery, using fisher&#x02019;s anecdotes to reassess fisheries management: the case of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos grouper</article-title><source>The Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve, Social and Ecological Interactions in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>246</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Bustamante (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><collab><institution>World Wildlife Fund&#x02013;Fundaci&#x000f3;n Natura</institution></collab></person-group><article-title>The artisanal fishing sector of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos and the 1997 fishing season</article-title><source>Gal&#x000e1;pagos Report 1997&#x02013;1998</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Quito</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Trama Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Bustamante, Okey &#x00026; Banks (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>McClanahan</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Branch</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity and food-web structure of a Galapagos shallow rocky-reef ecosystem</article-title><source>Food Webs and the Dynamics of Marine Reefs</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Castrej&#x000f3;n &#x00026; Charles (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castrej&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving fisheries co-management through ecosystem-based spatial management: the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve</article-title><source>Marine Policy</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2012.05.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Cheung, Reygondeau &#x00026; Fr&#x000f6;licher (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>WWL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reygondeau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;licher</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large benefits to marine fisheries of meeting the 1.5&#x000b0;C global warming target</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>354</volume><issue>6319</issue><fpage>1591</fpage><lpage>1594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag2331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28008069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Christensen &#x00026; Walters (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecopath with Ecosim: methods, capabilities and limitations</article-title><source>Ecological Modelling</source><year>2004</year><volume>172</volume><issue>2&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2003.09.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Christensen et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecopath with Ecosim user guide v6</article-title><year>2008</year><uri xlink:href="http://ecopath.org">http://ecopath.org</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Coll, Palomera &#x00026; Tudela (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomera</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tudela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decadal changes in a NW Mediterranean Sea food web in relation to fishing exploitation</article-title><source>Ecological Modelling</source><year>2009</year><volume>220</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2088</fpage><lpage>2102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2009.04.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Collie et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collie</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Largier</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Plag&#x000e1;nyi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecosystem models for fisheries management: finding the sweet spot</article-title><source>Fish and Fisheries</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/faf.12093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Cornwall &#x00026; Eddy (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornwall</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of near-future ocean acidification, fishing, and marine protection on a temperate coastal ecosystem</article-title><source>Conservation Biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cobi.12394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25354555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Defeo, Castilla &#x00026; Castrej&#x000f3;n (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Defeo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Castrej&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lodeiros</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Freites</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rey-M&#x000e9;ndez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pesquer&#x000ed;as artesanales de invertebrados en Am&#x000e9;rica Latina: paradigmas emergentes de manejo y gobernanza</article-title><source>Foro Iberoamericano de los Recursos Marinos y la Acuicultura II</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Cuman&#x000e1;, Venezuela</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Fondo Editorial Universidad de Oriente</publisher-name><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Eddy, Cheung &#x00026; Bruno (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>WWL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Historical baselines of coral cover on tropical reefs as estimated by expert opinion</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><issue>6994</issue><elocation-id>e4308</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.4308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29379692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Eddy et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trade-offs between invertebrate fisheries catches and ecosystem impacts in coastal New Zealand</article-title><source>ICES Journal of Marine Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>72</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icesjms/fsv009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Eddy, Gardner &#x00026; P&#x000e9;rez-Matus (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Matus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Applying fishers&#x02019; ecological knowledge to construct past and future lobster stocks in the Juan Fern&#x000e1;ndez Archipelago, Chile</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e13670</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21079761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Eddy et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bundy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribble</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecosystem effects of invertebrate fisheries</article-title><source>Fish and Fisheries</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/faf.12165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Eddy et al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitcher</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDiarmid</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Byfield</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lobsters as keystone: only in unfished ecosystems?</article-title><source>Ecological Modelling</source><year>2014</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2013.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Edgar et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiriboga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garske</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wellington</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>El Ni&#x000f1;o, grazers and fisheries interact to greatly elevate extinction risk for Gal&#x000e1;pagos marine species</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2876</fpage><lpage>2890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2009.02117.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Edgar et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvopi&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tora-Granda</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bias in evaluating the effects of marine protected areas: the importance of baseline data for the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve</article-title><source>Environmental Conservation</source><year>2004</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0376892904001584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-64"><label>Erisman &#x00026; Craig (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erisman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycteroperca olfax</article-title><source>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><elocation-id>e.T14051A100466495</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2305/IUCN.UK.2018-2.RLTS.T14051A100466495.en</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Freeman (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecology of spiny lobsters (<italic>Jasus edwardsii</italic>) on fished and unfished reefs</article-title><year>2007</year><comment>PhD thesis</comment><publisher-name>University of Auckland</publisher-name><fpage>307</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Gonz&#x000e1;lez et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Montes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rethinking the Gal&#x000e1;pagos islands as a complex social-ecological system: implications for conservation and management</article-title><source>Ecology and Society</source><year>2008</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5751/ES-02557-130213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Jack, Wing &#x00026; McLeod (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prey base shifts in red rock lobster <italic>Jasus edwardsii</italic> in response to habitat conversion in Fiordland marine reserves: implications for effective spatial management</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><year>2009</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps07971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Jackson et al. (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>JBC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorndal</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Erlandson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenihan</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Steneck</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tegner</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Historical overfishing and the recent collapse of coastal ecosystems</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>293</volume><issue>5530</issue><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1059199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11474098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Johannes, Freeman &#x00026; Hamilton (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johannes</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ignore fishers&#x02019; knowledge and miss the boat</article-title><source>Fish and Fisheries</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1467-2979.2000.00019.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Libralato, Christensen &#x00026; Pauly (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libralato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for identifying keystone species in food web models</article-title><source>Ecological Modelling</source><year>2006</year><volume>195</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2005.11.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Link (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Ecosystem-based fisheries management: confronting tradeoffs</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>207</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Lotze et al. (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenihan</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depletion, degradation, and recovery potential of estuaries and coastal seas</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><issue>5781</issue><fpage>1806</fpage><lpage>1809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1128035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16794081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Lynham et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaines</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic valuation of marine- and shark-based tourism in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos islands: report to the Gal&#x000e1;pagos National Park</article-title><uri xlink:href="https://media.nationalgeographic.org/assets/file/GalapagosEconReport_Nov15.pdf">https://media.nationalgeographic.org/assets/file/GalapagosEconReport_Nov15.pdf</uri><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Marconi, Beck &#x00026; Majluf (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marconi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Majluf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservaci&#x000f3;n De Ecosistemas Transfronterizos Y Especies Amenazadas</article-title><year>2001</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.rds.org.co/aa/img_upload/cd3189bd6b9a1ea1575134c54f92a42c/Conservaci_n_de_ecosistemas_transfronterizos_y_especies_ame.pdf">https://www.rds.org.co/aa/img_upload/cd3189bd6b9a1ea1575134c54f92a42c/Conservaci_n_de_ecosistemas_transfronterizos_y_especies_ame.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>McClenachan (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClenachan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Historical declines of goliath grouper populations in South Florida, USA</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>181</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Okey (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A search for keystones in Prince William Sound, Alaska using a mass-continuity trophic model</article-title><source>Shifted Community States in Four Marine Ecosystems: Some Potential Mechanisms</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Vancouver</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of British Columbia</publisher-name><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Okey et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Born</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvopi&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eduardo Espinoza</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garske</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Reck</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Toral-Granda</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallem</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A trophic model of a Gal&#x000e1;pagos subtidal rocky reef for evaluating fisheries and conservation strategies</article-title><source>Ecological Modelling</source><year>2004</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>401</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Okey, Shepherd &#x00026; Mart&#x000ed;nez (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okey</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new record of anemone barrens in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos</article-title><source>Noticias de Galapagos</source><year>2003</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Pauly (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anecdotes and the shifting baseline syndrome of fisheries</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source><year>1995</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>430</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(00)89171-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Pauly &#x00026; Zeller (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catch reconstructions reveal that global marine fisheries catches are higher than reported and declining</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10244</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms10244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Payne et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Barange</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>WWL</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Batchelder</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cormon</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollowed</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Neubauer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Queir&#x000f3;s</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uncertainties in projecting climate-change impacts in marine ecosystems</article-title><source>ICES Journal of Marine Science: Journal du Conseil</source><year>2016</year><volume>73</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1272</fpage><lpage>1282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icesjms/fsv231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Pikitch et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pikitch</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Santora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Babcock</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baku</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Conover</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Doukakis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluharty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heneman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Houde</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Livingston</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sainsbury</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecosystem-based fishery management</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>305</volume><issue>5682</issue><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1098222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15256658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Power et al. (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Power</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Tilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Menge</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Daily</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubchenco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Paine</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challenges in the quest for keystones</article-title><source>BioScience</source><year>1996</year><volume>46</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1312990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Reck (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The coastal fisheries in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands, Equador</article-title><year>1983</year><comment>MSc Thesis</comment><publisher-loc>Germany</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Kiel</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Rodriguez (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estudio preliminar para evaluar las caracteristicas biologicas pesquerias de la <italic>Mycteroperca ofax</italic> en las Islas Gal&#x000e1;pagos (Equador)</article-title><source>Instituto Nacional de Pesca Boletin Cientifico y Tecnico</source><year>1984</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Rosenberg et al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolster</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Leavenworth</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The history of ocean resources: modeling cod biomass using historical records</article-title><source>Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1540-9295(2005)003[0078:thoorm]2.0.co;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Ruiz &#x00026; Wolff (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bolivar channel ecosystem of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos marine reserve: energy flow structure and role of keystone groups</article-title><source>Journal of Sea Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seares.2011.05.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Ruttenberg (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruttenberg</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Artisanal fishing on marine communities in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands</article-title><source>Conservation Biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1691</fpage><lpage>1699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1523-1739.2001.99556.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Sadovy de Mitcheson et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadovy de Mitcheson</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertoncini</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>WWL</given-names></name><name><surname>Choat</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennessy</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Heemstra</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Samoilys</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanciangco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fishing groupers towards extinction: a global assessment of threats and extinction risks in a billion dollar fishery</article-title><source>Fish and Fisheries</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-2979.2011.00455.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a-Marrero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastoin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Largest global shark biomass found in the northern Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands of Darwin and Wolf</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e1911</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27190701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n, Rastoin &#x00026; Acu&#x000f1;a-Marrero (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rastoin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a-Marrero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First record of a spawning aggregation for the tropical eastern Pacific endemic grouper <italic>Mycteroperca olfax</italic> in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve</article-title><source>Journal of Fish Biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfb.12703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25997940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Schiller et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alava</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The demise of Darwin&#x02019;s fishes: evidence of fishing down and illegal shark finning in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Islands</article-title><source>Aquatic Conservation: Marine and Freshwater Ecosystems</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/aqc.2458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Shepperson et al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shepperson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methodological considerations when using local knowledge to infer spatial patterns of resource exploitation in an Irish Sea fishery</article-title><source>Biological Conservation</source><year>2014</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocon.2014.10.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Smith et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>ADM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of fishing low-trophic level species on marine ecosystems</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2011</year><volume>333</volume><issue>6046</issue><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1209395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21778363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Usseglio et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usseglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMartini</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuhbauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schemmel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved estimates of age, growth and reproduction for the regionally endemic Gal&#x000e1;pagos sailfin grouper <italic>Mycteroperca olfax</italic> (Jenys, 1840)</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e1270</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26401463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>Usseglio et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usseglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerhackel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuhbauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas de Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>So long and thanks for all the fish: overexploitation of the regionally endemic Galapagos grouper <italic>Mycteroperca olfax</italic> (Jenyns, 1840)</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e0165167</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0165167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27780213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>Usseglio, Schuhbauer &#x00026; Friedlander (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usseglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuhbauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedlander</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vinueza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Denkinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collaborative approach to fisheries management as a way to increase the effectiveness of future regulations in the Gal&#x000e1;pagos archipelago</article-title><source>The Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine Reserve: A Dynamic Socio-Ecological System</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>202</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-61"><label>Wolff, Ruiz &#x00026; Taylor (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>El Ni&#x000f1;o induced changes to the Bolivar Channel ecosystem (Gal&#x000e1;pagos): comparing model simulations with historical biomass time series</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><year>2012</year><volume>448</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps09542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-62"><label>Worm et al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilborn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Branch</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Collie</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchings</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>McClanahan</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Minto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Palumbi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Parma</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rebuilding global fisheries</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>325</volume><issue>5940</issue><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1173146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19644114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-63"><label>Zimmerhackel et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerhackel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuhbauer</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Usseglio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heel</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas-de-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catch, bycatch and discards of the Gal&#x000e1;pagos Marine reserve small-scale handline fishery</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e995</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26082874</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>