<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P23" class="p">Based on the metrics selected, the results in 
 <xref rid="S35" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 4</xref> provide a knowledge base from which it is possible to place into perspective the trend results described in 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Health</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Vegetation</italic>, and 
 <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gaudel et al. (2017)</xref> (hereinafter referred to as 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Climate</italic>). 
 <xref rid="S35" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 4</xref> provides insight into the implications of using specific exposure metrics for assessing potential changes in ozone relevant for human health and vegetation resulting from, or potentially achievable from the implementation of emission control strategies. Distributions and trends are an important aspect of understanding the behavior of exposure metrics as changes occur in emissions, as well as other drivers. It was anticipated that the development of the software and methodology used for quantifying the relationship between changes in distributions of hourly average levels and changes in the magnitude and trend patterns for the various TOAR metrics would be a lengthy process. To maximize the effort, prior to the completion of the TOAR database, a case study was undertaken in which the relationship between changes in the hourly ozone level distributions and a subset (14) of human health and vegetation metrics included in the TOAR database were explored at sites in Europe, the US, and China. The results from the case study (
 <xref rid="R113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lefohn et al., 2017</xref>) are succinctly summarized in 
 <xref rid="S36" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 4.1</xref> to introduce the reader to the concepts used throughout 
 <xref rid="S35" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 4</xref>. In 
 <xref rid="S39" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 4.2</xref>, a comparison between trend patterns described in the case study and patterns observed in the metrics using the TOAR database provides evidence that the conclusions from 
 <xref rid="R113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lefohn et al. (2017)</xref> are relevant to the larger set of TOAR metrics. Hence in 
 <xref rid="S35" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 4</xref>, the aim in integrating the results from 
 <xref rid="R113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lefohn et al. (2017)</xref> with expanded analyses using the TOAR database, is to further explore why metrics developed to quantify the same impact (e.g., human health acute effects) provide different estimates of spatial and temporal variation in ozone for a particular impact.
</p>
