<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P11" class="p">For each forest, four model simulations were carried out: one under baseline climate (B) and one including the effects of climate change on forest productivity (CC) to calculate CPC. Subsequently, these two simulations were repeated also accounting for the effects of disturbances (abbreviated BD and CCD respectively) to calculate CDPC. According to the framework developed in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S3" class="xref">section 3</xref>, the simulations required to calculate CPC include the pathways P1 and/or P2 while the simulations for CDPC potentially include all pathways (P1–P8) if included in the model used in each case study (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" class="xref">table 2</xref>). The climate change simulations all used forcing from the A1B emission scenario from the ENSEMBLES project (
 <xref rid="R101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">van der Linden and Mitchell 2009</xref>), and were bias-corrected and downscaled to the respective case study at a 100 m spatial resolution (
 <xref rid="R102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zimmermann 2010</xref>). All simulations assumed business-as-usual management (two different ones in the Prades region) typical for the region, and expressed changes in productivity using slightly different indicators such as net primary production or mean annual growth, depending on the model applied. More details about the forests, modeling approaches and data sources can be found in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" class="xref">table 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" class="xref">SOM1-2</xref>. In the following, we briefly describe how, in each forest, productivity and disturbances are affected by climate change, following the conceptual framework outlined above (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2" class="xref">table 2</xref>). We then synthesize results from the case studies across the different indicators of forest productivity and disturbances used in each study by comparing CPC and CDPC.
</p>
