<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results prone to flood mapping with Geographical Information Systems</div>
 <sec id="s30009" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flood</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high intensity of rainfall in the Sonorejo Village causes the rice fields in the area vulnerable to flooding. Based on the mapping of flood-prone rice fields in the Sonorejo Village, the areas most prone to flooding in lowland rice fields are Langsur and Ngiser. Meanwhile, the region that has the same characteristic with the Sonorejo Village is the Jiwo Wetan Village in Klaten Regency. The Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages have an annual flood risk; the frequency of flooding is 4 to 6 times each year. In 2017, farmers in the Jiwo Wetan Village have accepted agricultural insurance claims because their agricultural land was damaged by floods (i.e. 75%).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s30010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The curvature of the river</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The curvature of the river is the ratio between the valleys and the length of the river. The river in the eastern of Sonorejo Village is a meandering river that flows over gently sloping ground that begins to curve back and forth across the landscape. Meandering river has asymmetric channels. The deepest part of the channel is found outside of each bend. The water flows faster in these deeper fragments and grinds down material from the riverbank. The water flows more gently in the shallow areas near the inside of each bend. The slower flow of water cannot carry much residue and deposits its load on a series of point bars. Meandering rivers erode residue from the outer curve of each meander bend and deposit it on an inner curve further downstream.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The characteristics in the Jiwo Wetan Village area have similarity with the Sonorejo Village. Although the meandering is not like in Sonorejo, yet Jiwo Wetan is potentially flooding because the south of the village is the terrain of the Pegunungan Seribu, Yogyakarta. When rainfall is high, rainwater flows into the Dengkeng River and has the potential to increase the vulnerability of the area in Jiwo Wetan Klaten.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s30011" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Slope</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Slope in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo sub-district, shows that most areas in the Sonorejo Village are flat with slope level ranging between 2% and 6%, which leads to the conclusion theoretically that the Sonorejo Village is highly susceptible to flooding. Slope in the Jiwo Wetan Village, Klaten Regency, is approximately 2% – 7%.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s30012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Land use</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Land use index is determined by a map of land use and land use information on RBI topographic maps. The data collected are then contributed to the mapping of land use. The result shows that the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages are classified into three categories of land use, that is housing, irrigated fields and farming.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s30013" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential flooding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flood is a condition of overflowing of a large amount of water. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0001" href="#F0001">Figure 1</a> shows the mapping of flood-prone area in the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages.
  </p>
  <div id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">FIGURE 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Mapping of flood-prone area in the Sonorejo Village.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0001" href="#F0001">Figure 1</a>, the areas marked with dark red are the area mostly prone to flooding in the Sonorejo Village. Based on the results of the mapping using GIS with the consideration of a variable number of flood events, local curvature of the river, slope and land use, it can be seen that Langsur and Ngiser in the Sonorejo Village are two areas prone to catastrophic flooding in lowland rice fields compared with other areas.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figure 2</a>, the results of the mapping using GIS with the consideration of a variable number of flood events, local curvature of the river, slope and land use, it can be seen that most areas in Jiwo Wetan are marked dark red. The Jiwo Wetan Village is passed by a river which can overflow at any time if the intensity of the rain increases. Based on reports from the Local Disaster Board (Badan Penanggulangan Bencana Daerah [BPBD]), standing water can reach 1 m.
  </p>
  <div id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">FIGURE 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Mapping of flood-prone area in the Jiwo Wetan Village.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
