<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increase in emissions of greenhouse gases (GHG) leads to an increase in temperature of the earth and causes global climate change. This is one of the key elements in the system of metabolism and physiology of plants; the global climate change has a major impact on the agricultural sector. According to the Agricultural Research and Development Agency (BBSDLP 
  <a rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0001">2011</a>), the agricultural sector is one of the most threatened sectors that is suffering and vulnerable to climate change. Salinger (
  <a rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0011">2005</a>) and Karim, Jahan and Islam (
  <a rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0006">2014</a>) stated three main factors in the agricultural sector based on global climate change, that is, (1) changes in the patterns of rainfall, (2) the rise of extreme climate events (floods and droughts) and (3) an increase in air temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An extreme climate change causes a great impact on the agricultural sector. The climate change severely leads to changes in pattern, and the level of precipitation affects the initial time of planting and growing period. The alteration in level of precipitation affects the time and seasons, cropping patterns, land degradation, destruction of crops and productivity, planted and harvested acreage, and the damage to biodiversity, especially crops that is relatively sensitive to water availability (Runtunuwu &amp; Syahbuddin 
  <a rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0010">2007</a>). Flooding on rice fields causes a reduction in harvest area and a decline in rice production significantly. High rainfall causes losses to farmers in the United States. The US EPA (
  <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">2015</a>) reported losses in 2010–2011, which reached $220 million. Mall, Gupta and Sungkar (
  <a rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0007">2017</a>) said that farmers must be given guidance to adapt because climate change has a negative effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Central Java Province is the second largest province of East Java with total area of wetland that is prone to flood or inundation (
  <a rid="T0001" ref-type="table" href="#T0001">Table 1</a>). Even so, Central Java Province remains one of Indonesia’s largest rice suppliers. Sukoharjo sub-district is one of the regions that largest suppliers of rice and food buffer in Central Java. Rice is the main agricultural product in Sukoharjo sub-district. According to report from the Minister of Agriculture and the Central Bureau of Statistics in Sukoharjo 2015, rice production in the Sukoharjo sub-district ranks third after the Polokarto sub-district and Mojolaban sub-district. Sukoharjo sub-district consists of 14 villages, where most of the land is used as a wetland. The use of paddy fields in the sub-district of Sukoharjo in 2013 amounted to 2.363 hectares (ha) or 53% of the total area of its territory. Sonorejo is the largest area with land use for rice fields; proportion is reached to 68% (302 ha) of the total area (444 ha). However, at some point the fields contained in the Sonorejo Village is prone to floods. However, Klaten is also a producer of rice in Central Java. Rice production in Klaten reaches 350 000 tons per year, while local demand is only 207 500 tons per year. Unfortunately, some areas become prone to flood because of overflow of the Dengkeng River. One of the worst impacted areas is the Jiwo Wetan Village in Klaten Regency, where, in 2017, there was a crop failure of 35.2 ha which was suffered by 123 farmers.
 </p>
 <div id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">TABLE 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Summary of research methods.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research purposes</th>
     <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis tools</th>
     <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data</th>
     <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody valign="top">
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mapping of flood-prone wetland in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo Sub-district</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIS</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary data
      <span class="break"/>Secondary data
     </td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Map of flood vulnerability</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Livelihood vulnerability index of farmers in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo sub-district</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Descriptive statistics</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary data</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vulnerability index (livelihood vulnerability index)</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <fn class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GIS, Geographic Information System.</p>
   </fn>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the results of the mapping with Geographic Information System (GIS) and interview conducted with the Head of Village and the Head of Sonorejo’s Farmers Group Association (Gapoktan), wetland that is mostly prone to flood is located in the eastern part of the Sonorejo Village, namely, Langsur and Ngiser, that is directly adjacent to the Bulakrejo and Sukoharjo Village. The land altitude in those areas is lower than the surrounding areas, and the water drains (drainage) are not functioning properly, resulting to the flooding in the field.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The research area in Klaten Regency also has characteristics similar to the sample area in Sukoharjo Regency. The altitude of the Jiwo Wetan Region is lower than other areas around it. When the Dengkeng River overflows, the overflow leads in the terrain in the south of the village. If the inundation does not pass, then the water goes to the rice fields and settlements of the Jiwo Wetan Village.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of the population in the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages rely on agriculture, especially crops and paddy rice. This condition causes the vulnerability on the livelihoods of farmers and their households. This study aims to deepen the understanding of the vulnerability of people’s livelihoods in flood-prone areas in paddy field in the Sonorejo Village and Jiwo Wetan Village, which are based on the results of the mapping with GIS and livelihood vulnerability index (LVI). The benefit of this research is to find out whether areas that have the same level of hazard and the same dependence on agriculture will have the same level of vulnerability.</p>
</sec>
