<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We hypothesize that two bioclimatic variables, annual precipitation and temperature, may significantly challenge the geographical distribution of brown bears in Central Asia by potential direct and indirect effects. These effects are not only anticipated to cause shifts in brown bear distributions, as species often pursue an optimal habitat, but threatening their viability due to range reductions or fragmentations and partially altering their biological systems (Parmesan, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Our results highlighted the influence of future meteorological conditions on behavioral plasticity, the ability to respond to environmental changes, which will dictate how well brown bears can adjust or resist to changes occurring in their environment (Williams, Shoo, Isaac, Hoffmann, &amp; Langham,). For example, brown bears tend to modify their ambulatory activities and movement speed during periods of increased precipitation with an increase of 0.1 km/hr for each increase of 5 mm of rainfall (Martin 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) which might predict the relatively greater energetic costs of future high‐speed locomotion of brown bears to meet their basic requirements (Gormezano, McWilliams, Iles, &amp; Rockwell, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) by the probable increase in precipitation from 406 to 459 mm by 2,050. Similarly, the predicated high precipitation should accelerate the melting of snow, increase the run‐off, and cause streams to overflow. On one hand, this could reduce the period during which snow still offers a protective shelter for optimal denning structure and environment. On the other hand, due to poor winter precipitation, the snow depth and snow cover in alpine scrub and meadow habitats would be very less leading to changes in plant community structure, composition, and biomass in the following spring and summer. This could force individuals to move more in search of better quality habitats increasing energy costs. Furthermore, disturbances resulting in displacement at this stage of the life cycle could have deleterious effects, especially in the presence of altricial bear cubs developing locomotory skills, as a new den site must be found, and the offspring need to be relocated (John, Swenson, Andersen, &amp; Barnes, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>).
</p>
