<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20869-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental Design</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For this study we use four simulations, one using fully coupled chemistry and three further simulations using different methods of prescribing stratospheric ozone concentrations. All four simulations use the HadGEM3‐A r2.0 model (Hewitt et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0018">2011</a>), while one simulation is also coupled with the United Kingdom Chemistry and Aerosol scheme (hereafter referred to as UKCA; Figure 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0001">1</a>). This model configuration uses N48L60 resolution, which corresponds to a horizontal resolution of 2.5° latitude by 3.75° longitude, with 60 vertical levels following a hybrid height vertical coordinate and a model top at ∼84 km. The chemistry in the UKCA configuration used for this is a combination of the tropospheric (O'Connor et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0122">2014</a>) and stratospheric (Morgenstern et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0027">2009</a>) chemical schemes, which updates relevant chemical fields every model hour. This scheme includes the chemical cycles of O
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub>, HO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub>, NO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">y</span>
  </sub>, Cl
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">y</span>
  </sub>, and Br
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">y</span>
  </sub> and the oxidation of CO, ethane, propane and isoprene. A detailed treatment of polar processes is included, with chlorine activation through heterogeneous reactions occurring on both polar stratospheric cloud particles and sulfuric acid aerosols (Morgenstern et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0027">2009</a>). The model is run with an atmospheric time step of 20 min, and chemistry is called every hour. Advection in the model is semi‐Lagrangian, after Priestley (
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0032">1993</a>). The radiation scheme, following Edwards and Slingo (
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0009">1996</a>), includes nine longwave bands and six shortwave and is updated every six model hours; ozone and its asymmetries feed back on the dynamics through their effects on radiative heating at this frequency. This model configuration has been used in the studies of Banerjee et al. (
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0003">2014</a>) and Keeble et al. (
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0022">2017</a>), in which further information can be found.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20869-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Annual vertical profiles (top row) and seasonal evolution at 17.5 km (bottom row) of diagnostics from the UKCA simulation. (a and d) Zonal‐mean ozone 
    <div id="nlm-math-3" class="math">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
       <span class="mn">3</span>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
     </div>
    </div>, measured in parts per million by volume. (b and e) ZAO (monthly standard deviation of 
    <div id="nlm-math-4" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
      <span class="mn">3</span>
      <span class="mo">′</span>
     </div>
    </div>), measured as a percentage of (a) and (d), respectively. (c and f) Interannual standard deviation of monthly 
    <div id="nlm-math-5" class="math">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
       <span class="mn">3</span>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
     </div>
    </div>, measured as a percentage of (a) and (d), respectively. We expect that shading in (b) and (e) identifies regions where the ZAO feedback is influential in UKCA (processes which alter 
    <div id="nlm-math-6" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
      <span class="mn">3</span>
      <span class="mo">′</span>
     </div>
    </div>), and we expect that shading in (c) and (f) identifies regions where chemistry and eddy transport of ozone are most influential in UKCA (processes which alter the value of 
    <div id="nlm-math-7" class="math">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
       <span class="mn">3</span>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
     </div>
    </div>). UKCA = United Kingdom Chemistry and Aerosol scheme; ZAO = zonally asymmetric ozone.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="JAME-11-918-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A time slice integration using the UKCA model was run under perpetual year 2000 boundary conditions for 50 years. These boundary conditions include long‐lived greenhouse gas, ozone‐depleting substances, aerosol loadings, sea surface temperatures, and sea ice extent. The ozone field from this integration was then averaged over the 50 years to create both the zonal‐mean and 3‐D ozone climatologies, which were in turn used to prescribe ozone concentrations in a set of nonchemical GCM simulations. All integrations have the same annually repeating year 2000 boundary conditions and forcings, including sea surface temperatures, sea ice extent, greenhouse gas concentrations, and aerosol loadings. Furthermore, the multidecadal zonal‐mean ozone climatology is identical between the simulations, although it may differ at any given chemical time step from the fully coupled UKCA simulation. In this way, we have defined a series of simulations which differ only in the representation of stratospheric ozone. These experiments are listed below: 
  <div list-type="order" id="jame20869-list-0002" class="list">
   <div id="jame20869-li-0004" class="list-item">
    <p>UKCA: Perpetual‐year coupled CCM forced with year 2000 boundary conditions, integrated for 50 years (identical to the TS2000 integration from Banerjee et al., 
     <a rid="jame20869-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0003">2014</a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="jame20869-li-0005" class="list-item">
    <p>SPEC‐ZM: Specified‐composition (no chemistry) configuration of 1 with climatological monthly mean zonal‐mean ozone from 1.</p>
   </div>
   <div id="jame20869-li-0006" class="list-item">
    <p>SPEC‐AZ: Specified‐composition (no chemistry) configuration of 1 with climatological monthly mean 3‐D ozone field from 1.</p>
   </div>
   <div id="jame20869-li-0007" class="list-item">
    <p>CALC‐AZ: Specified‐composition (no chemistry) configuration of 1. The zonally averaged monthly mean ozone is identical to 1 from which a dynamically consistent ZAO field is calculated online in the stratosphere (details below).</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ozone in the simulations using prescribed climatologies (experiments 2–4) is specified as a climatological field of monthly mean values, which are subsequently interpolated and updated daily. In the 3‐D specification (SPEC‐AZ), the tropospheric ozone values are reset to zonal mean, and prescribed asymmetries increase linearly from 0 at ~8 km and below, to full 3‐D climatological values at ~11 km and above. This is to ensure all differences between specified ozone are confined to the stratosphere. Computational costs of specifying fixed ozone are the same for the zonal‐mean and full 3‐D climatologies (SPEC‐ZM, SPEC‐AZ, and CALC‐AZ), which are roughly 3–4 times faster than the full CCM. We prescribe ZAO in our simulations SPEC‐AZ and CALC‐AZ independent of zonal‐mean ozone; covariance between prescribed ZAO and meridional/vertical winds does not produce a net transport in ozone (as it would in a CCM or Earth's atmosphere) because the zonal‐mean distribution is fixed from the UKCA climatology. The following section discusses the treatment of ozone in the CALC‐AZ integration, where zonal asymmetries for stratospheric ozone are actively calculated.</p>
</sec>
