<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20869-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stratospheric ozone plays an important role in the Earth system, both chemically and radiatively. The optical properties of ozone allow it to heat surrounding air through absorption of shortwave or longwave radiation but also cool through emission of longwave radiation. As a result, the net contribution of ozone to total radiative heating depends strongly on altitude, latitude, and time, which substantially affects the climate and circulation (e.g., Fels et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0012">1980</a>; Forster &amp; Shine, 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0013">1997</a>; Hansen et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0016">1997</a>; Ramaswamy et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0033">1996</a>; Shine, 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0037">1986</a>). Furthermore, high‐latitude ozone changes, especially in the Southern Hemisphere (SH), have been shown in both observations and modeling studies to have far‐reaching effects on stratospheric chemistry, circulation, as well as on surface climate (e.g., Braesicke et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0004">2013</a>; Iglesias‐Suarez et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0019">2016</a>; Keeble et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0023">2014</a>; McLandress et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0026">2011</a>; Perlwitz et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0029">2008</a>; Polvani et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0031">2011</a>; Roscoe et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0034">2003</a>; Son et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0040">2010</a>; Thompson &amp; Solomon, 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0042">2002</a>). As a result, there have been significant advances in the representation of stratospheric ozone in climate models over the last decade. For example, while half of the models used in Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 3 (CMIP3) prescribed an invariant ozone concentration field, models in CMIP5 used either prescribed or interactive time‐varying ozone fields (Eyring et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0010">2013</a>; Taylor et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0041">2012</a>). A range of models using both interactive and prescribed stratospheric ozone will be used for CMIP6 (Eyring et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0011">2016</a>). Zonally asymmetric ozone (ZAO) is automatically generated in state‐of‐the‐art coupled chemistry‐climate models (CCMs), which use an interactive chemistry model coupled to a global circulation model (GCM). These models can resolve a range of chemistry‐climate interactions, with the distribution of stratospheric ozone consistent with the model's dynamics and other chemical fields. However, due to the high computational cost of running interactive chemistry, many models continue to prescribe stratospheric ozone as a time‐varying field. This is typically done either as a zonal‐mean (2‐D) field or a climatological 3‐D field: when prescribed as a zonally symmetric field the effects of ZAO on stratospheric circulation are not represented at all within the GCM, and prescribing a climatological 3‐D ozone field results in the chemical ozone field being inconsistent with the model's dynamics for any given time step. Both configurations prevent dynamical zonal asymmetries from feeding back onto the zonal distribution of ozone (by the transport of ozone through advection), and hence also on radiative heating, as occurs in fully interactive systems. As a result, chemical‐radiation‐dynamical feedback processes are not addressed in GCMs with zonal‐mean ozone specifications, and this may be a significant limiting factor in the model's ability to accurately represent the atmosphere and relevant processes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the lower stratosphere, where the chemical lifetime for ozone is long, distributions of ozone are largely controlled by transport. In the polar lower stratosphere during wintertime, zonal asymmetries in dynamics arising from waves and eddies may produce substantial zonally asymmetric features in the distribution of ozone (e.g., Hartmann, 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0017">1981</a>). Recently, zonal asymmetries in ozone have been shown to play a substantial role in driving atmospheric circulation, independent of the zonal‐mean structure of ozone in the atmosphere (e.g., Albers &amp; Nathan, 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0001">2012</a>; McCormack et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0025">2011</a>; Silverman et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0038">2017</a>). Additionally, a number of studies have explored the extent to which stratospheric ZAO has contributed to observed dynamical trends both in the stratosphere and at the surface, over recent decades (e.g., Crook et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0007">2008</a>; Gabriel et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0014">2007</a>; Gillett et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0015">2009</a>; Peters et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0030">2015</a>; Sassi et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0035">2005</a>; Waugh et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0043">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gabriel et al. (
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0014">2007</a>) showed that prescribing the observed ZAO field from the 1990–2000 December through February decadal average (using the ERA‐40 reanalysis data set) resulted in dynamical trends more representative of that decade in the Arctic stratosphere compared to a simulation with zonally symmetric ozone. In terms of ozone depletion in the Arctic, there have been contrasting results on whether severe depletion events (such as the boreal winter of 2010/2011; see Manney et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0024">2011</a>) can influence tropospheric and surface conditions. Studies which have prescribed zonally symmetric ozone depletion (e.g., Karpechko et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0021">2014</a>; Smith &amp; Polvani, 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0039">2014</a>) have struggled to show significant surface impacts when imposing ozone depletion of observed magnitude in the Arctic stratosphere. However, studies which use interannual variability in interactive 3‐D ozone fields have seen significantly different patterns in Northern Hemisphere (NH) sea level pressure between composites of the years with lowest ozone and those with highest ozone (e.g., Calvo et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0005">2015</a>; Ivy et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0020">2017</a>). While the focus of this paper is not ozone depletion, we note that from a dynamical perspective, CCMs only differ from prescribed‐ozone GCMs in that their ozone field is always three‐dimensional and interacts with both dynamics and composition. The fact that CCM and prescribed‐ozone studies see such contrasting tropospheric responses to similar magnitudes of ozone depletion may suggest some degree of importance for ZAO in accurately representing stratosphere‐troposphere coupling in the NH.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Albers and Nathan (
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0001">2012</a>) propose two pathways by which ZAO affect stratospheric temperatures, dynamics, and zonal‐mean ozone: a direct radiation/dynamic impact of ZAO on local wave properties through zonally asymmetric heating (pathway P1) and an indirect effect through residual eddy transport (e.g., 
  <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
   <div accent="true" class="mover">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">v</span>
     <span class="mo">′</span>
     <div class="msubsup">
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
      <span class="mn">3</span>
      <span class="mo">′</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
   </div>
  </div>) producing zonal‐mean changes in ozone (pathway P2). Changes in zonal‐mean ozone can also occur through changes in chemistry. When we mention P2 below, we implicitly also include any changes in chemistry which alter zonal‐mean ozone. Throughout this paper, we use these properties to identify where our prescribed ZAO has a direct influence on dynamics (e.g., through the P1 pathway associated with dynamical asymmetries) and where our prescribed ZAO is unable to represent chemistry and eddy transport of ozone (e.g., through the P2 pathway associated with sharp temporal changes in the value of 
  <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
   <div accent="true" class="mover">
    <div class="msub">
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
     <span class="mn">3</span>
    </div>
    <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
   </div>
  </div>). A schematic describing these pathways within the ZAO feedback, and how they relate to our experimental design, may be found in 
  <a rid="jame20869-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20869-supinf-0001">supporting information</a> Figure 
  <a rid="jame20869-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20869-supitem-0002">S1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies that have looked at the dynamical effects of ZAO in the atmosphere have compared 3‐D ozone fields calculated interactively by CCMs (e.g., Gillett et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0015">2009</a>; McCormack et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0025">2011</a>; Peters et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0030">2015</a>; Sassi et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0035">2005</a>; Silverman et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0038">2017</a>; Waugh et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0043">2009</a>) or prescribed from observations or CCM climatologies within simulations using the zonally averaged ozone field (e.g., Crook et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0007">2008</a>; Gabriel et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0014">2007</a>). Whether ozone asymmetries are calculated interactively or prescribed as a climatology, both approaches require either a relatively expensive fully coupled 3‐D chemistry model to generate interactive ZAO or must prescribe an ozone field which is inconsistent with the modeled dynamics. When prescribing ozone as a climatological field (particularly one which is derived from monthly mean values) the model is unable to accurately resolve the typical daily magnitudes of ozone, as well as temporal changes in ozone on shorter submonthly time scales which are normally present in a coupled CCM, and this may lead to significant differences in modeled stratospheric temperatures in the Antarctic (Neely et al., 
  <a rid="jame20869-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0028">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We present a novel, computationally inexpensive method for prescribing dynamically consistent ZAO from a prescribed zonal‐mean climatology. The simulations used for this study target different methods of prescribing ZAO and are described in section 
  <a rid="jame20869-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20869-sec-0002">2</a>, while the parametrization for calculating dynamically consistent ZAO is described in detail in section 
  <a rid="jame20869-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20869-sec-0003">3</a>. We then compare the performance of three stratospheric ozone prescriptions (zonal‐mean ozone, prescribed 3‐D field, and the developed calculated asymmetry scheme) to a fully coupled CCM in section 
  <a rid="jame20869-sec-0004" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20869-sec-0004">4</a>, identifying the influences of the ZAO feedback. The results are followed by a general discussion on the importance of this feedback and the appropriate use/limitations of each specified‐ozone representation.
 </p>
</sec>
