<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20869-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ozone</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examples of the different ozone representations are shown for the NH in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>, where the spatial distribution of ozone (color shading) at 17.5 km and PV (black contours) at 70 hPa in March are given for two example years from each simulation. One year from each simulation shows the lowest spatial correlation between 
  <div class="inline-formula">O
   <sub>3</sub>
  </div> and PV poleward of 40
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span class="sup">°</span>
  </div> (top row), with the highest spatial correlation shown in the bottom row. The figure highlights the interannual variability in the very good spatial correlation between ZAO and large‐scale dynamical features in the fully coupled UKCA and CALC‐AZ simulations, as well as the inconsistencies introduced between dynamical features and ozone distributions when fixed ozone is prescribed in both SPEC‐ZM and SPEC‐AZ. It also shows that the year with the lowest spatial correlation in UKCA (top left) occurs when there is substantial ozone depletion in the Arctic lower stratosphere, which reinforces the idea that the regression coefficient 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </div> should be small (if not negative) in regions where P2 processes such as heterogenous ozone chemistry regularly occur. Since the dynamics in SPEC‐AZ are close to that of UKCA in general, there will be instances where the instantaneous PV is aligned with the prescribed climatological 3‐D ozone field (Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>e–
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>h); however, this is not always the case (Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>a–
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>d).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20869-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Arctic stereographs of stratospheric ozone at 17.5 km (color shading, ppmv) and distributions of potential vorticity at 70 hPa (black contours, pvu) during March for years with the lowest PV/
    <div class="inline-formula">O
     <sub>3</sub>
    </div> spatial correlation (a–d) and for years with the highest PV/
    <div class="inline-formula">O
     <sub>3</sub>
    </div> spatial correlation (e–h), shown for each of the different representations of stratospheric ozone (columns). Ozone in both UKCA (a, e) and CALC‐AZ (d, h) may be altered by model dynamics at any given time step, while the distribution of ozone in SPEC‐ZM (b, f) and SPEC‐AZ (c, g) is the same every year for any given month. PV = potential vorticity.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="JAME-11-918-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analogous to Figure 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>, Figure 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a> depicts examples of September in the SH during the years of lowest (top row) and highest (bottom row) spatial correlation between PV and ozone. Much like the NH, the year with the lowest PV/ozone spatial correlation also has reduced polar cap ozone compared to the year of highest ozone (Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>a and 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>e). Heterogeneous ozone losses occur on an annual basis in UKCA's Antarctic stratosphere, and this can be seen in the climatological ozone prescribed in both SPEC‐ZM (Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>b and 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>f) and SPEC‐AZ (Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>c and 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>g), as well as in CALC‐AZ (Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>d and 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a>h). Since ZAO here is dominated by heterogeneous chemistry, the value of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </div> in the SH during September is small (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0002">2</a>b), and so CALC‐AZ consistently underestimates the total magnitude of ZAO in the Antarctic.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20869-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Same as Figure 
    <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a> but showing Antarctic stereographs during September during the years of lowest (a–d) and highest (e–h) spatial correlation between potential vorticity and ozone. The dynamical behavior in the Southern Hemisphere is more similar across simulations than the Northern Hemisphere in Figure 
    <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a>. This is because the dynamical asymmetry of the Antarctic stratosphere is generally smaller than that of the Arctic, but it may also be influenced by our choice of the UKCA model for our interactive simulation, which has been shown to underrepresent the degree of zonal asymmetry seen in observational analyses (Dennison et al., 
    <a rid="jame20869-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20869-bib-0008">2017</a>). PV = potential vorticity.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="JAME-11-918-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0003">3</a> and 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0004">4</a> show that ozone (color shading) generally adapts to the dynamical PV patterns (black contours) in UKCA and CALC‐AZ (leftmost and rightmost panels respectively), while the monthly averaged ozone in SPEC‐ZM and SPEC‐AZ is the same every year (compare color shading in top and bottom rows). An important observation is that the zonal‐asymmetry of CALC‐AZ decreases toward the equator (more annual color shading toward the outside edges of rightmost panels), demonstrating how the magnitude of ZAO is small despite the large fluctuations of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </div> toward the equator seen in Figures 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0002">2</a>a and 
  <a rid="jame20869-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20869-fig-0002">2</a>b (i.e., the sensitivity of ZAO to the value of 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span class="italic">α</span>
  </div> diminishes toward the equator).
 </p>
</sec>
