<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Though physiological mechanisms are responsible for the capacity of animals to adjust to new environments,
 <xref rid="R129" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">129</sup>
 </xref> there are limits to the capacity of physiological systems to respond to changing environmental conditions, both because of limited environmental resources and because of biochemical and physical constraints. The physiological response of an organism therefore acts as a “filter” between a change in environmental conditions and fitness, which ultimately determines species persistence and ecosystem biodiversity.
 <xref rid="R130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">130</sup>
 </xref> To predict accurately the direct physiological effects of climate change on a species, we need, first, an understanding of the thermal physiological sensitivity of the species, including how close to its thermal limits, or “prescriptive zone”
 <xref rid="R131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">131</sup>
 </xref>, the species is living. Second, we need an understanding of the relationship between climate and the thermoregulation of the species, including the degree to which the species can adjust, or acclimatize.
 <xref rid="R126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">126</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R132" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">132</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">133</sup>
 </xref> Because of the clearly-defined thermal niches which occur in the marine environment, most studies that have investigated the physiological principles underlying thermal limits and thermal sensitivity have focused on marine ectotherms (for review see refs. 
 <xref rid="R133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="R134" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">134</xref>). These studies have contributed substantially to our understanding of the key mechanisms of thermal adjustments and limitations, including finding that in those ectotherms thermal tolerance is limited by the capacity of circulatory and ventilatory tissues.
 <xref rid="R135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">135</sup>
 </xref> We are yet to establish how thermal sensitivity applies to acclimatization in endotherms, especially the large mammals, and how it applies might be substantially different to its application in ectotherms. In theory, endotherms may be more sensitive than ectotherms to rising ambient temperatures, because endothermy evolved during cold climatic conditions
 <xref rid="R135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">135</sup>
 </xref> and because enhanced organismic complexity often is accompanied by increased thermal sensitivity.
 <xref rid="R136" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">136</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
