<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As is the case with the white lemuroid possum, species that currently live in hot environments may be the most vulnerable to climate change, because they are already living close to their upper limits of thermal tolerance and have limited scope for further acclimatization.
 <xref rid="R133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">133</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">145</sup>
 </xref> The Arabian oryx inhabiting the extreme environment of the Arabian Desert may be living at the edge of its physiological limits.
 <xref rid="R146" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">146</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R147" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">147</sup>
 </xref> In arid environments, the threat of increased ambient temperature is compounded, or even exceeded, by the threat of reduced water availability resulting from climate change.
 <xref rid="R148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">148</sup>
 </xref> Although many factors consequent upon the increase in temperatures and aridity with climate change may threaten survival at community and individual levels, other factors are irrelevant if individual animals cannot maintain homeostasis of body temperature and body fluids, as their habitats become hotter and drier. Desert-adapted artiodactyls have to trade off thermoregulation, osmoregulation, and energy acquisition.
 <xref rid="R149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">149</sup>
 </xref> In the Arabian oryx when conflict between regulatory systems occurs, priority is given to osmoregulation.
 <xref rid="R147" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">147</sup>
 </xref> When water is scarce evaporative cooling is reduced (presumably to conserve body water) at the expense of homeothermy, resulting in higher core body temperature in hot conditions. Similarly, when energy supply is limited endotherms reduce metabolic heat production, resulting in lower core body temperature.
 <xref rid="R150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">150</sup>
 </xref> Though it may save water and/or energy, the resulting heterothermy increases the risk of mortality and morbidity if tissue temperatures depart from the tolerable range. Whether the heterothermy that has been observed in conditions of food and water shortage is a controlled thermoregulatory event that might serve as an adjustment to climate change, or whether it results from failure of homeothermy, remains debatable.
 <xref rid="R147" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">147</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R151" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">151</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
