<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate variables</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The EPICA ‘Dome C' record provides an index of glacial/interglacial temperature fluctuations in Antarctica and has been used previously to explore potential drivers of megafauna extinctions in Sahul
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>. The EPICA initiative has provided the longest ice-core climate record yet, by drilling through 3,270-m-thick ice at a site known as ‘Dome C' in central East Antarctica
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a>. As the time resolution of the core increases towards the present fluctuations on short time scales are more visible in recent parts of the record and can lead to misinterpretation of climate variability if the sampling bias is not corrected, we therefore resampled at an interval of 3 kyrs (to ensure at least 5 temperature values were available to calculate mean deviation per window) over 1,000 iterations and we calculated the mean temperature deviation for each interval and iteration.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate of a large part of eastern and northern Sahul is sensitive to changes in ENSO activity
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" href="#b46">46</a>; thus, metrics describing variation in the strength of ENSO events (such as ENSOp) are a good proxy for shifts in precipitation and temperature, and for changes in aridity. We extracted modelled ENSOp variation directly from Tudhope 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>, who estimated ENSOp variability from application of the Zebiak–Cane coupled ocean–atmosphere model forced only by changing orbital parameters. ENSOp is an extracted sea surface temperature signal from the Nino 3 region, for which the higher power inference means more important effects of El Niño events (that is, increase in rainfall across the east-central and eastern Pacific and drier-than-normal conditions over northern Australia, Indonesia and the Philippines).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also included temperature and precipitation proxies based on a hindcast of the HadCM3 global circulation model focussed specifically on Sahul. This model consists of linked atmospheric, ocean and sea ice models at a spatial resolution of 2.5° latitude × 3.75° longitude resampled at a 1 × 1° resolution
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">47</a>. The temporal resolution of the raw data is 1 kyr slices back to 22 kyr, 2 kyr from 22 to 80 kyr and 4 kyr to 120 kyr; thus, we ran our analyses using a 4-kyr running mean (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1e, f</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</a>). We tested whether both the EPICA record and ENSOp data are representative of Sahul's palaeoclimate by calculating the spatial correlation of HadCM3 model outputs (temperature and precipitation) over the last 120 kyr for each gridcell to both EPICA and ENSOp. The strong correlation between these variables justifies the use of both EPICA and ENSOp as appropriate measures of climate variation in Sahul (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Figs 5 and 6</a>). We also used the HadCM3 palaeoclimate simulation data to calculate vectors of climate velocity (km per year) for mean annual temperature (°C) and mean annual precipitation (mm per day) following established methods
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. Climate velocity describes the rate (and direction) that an organism would need to migrate to maintain an isocline of a temperature and precipitation variable
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. This proxy is often considered synonymous with the rate of climate displacement for a species, such that the higher the velocity, the less probable a species will keep pace with its shifting climatic niche and thus survive. Climate velocity is considered to be more biologically relevant than the use of climate anomalies, because it accounts for regional changes in climate and the ability of topographic heterogeneity to buffer biota against these changes
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. We divided the rate of climate change through time (°C per year) by the spatial gradient in climate at that location (°C km
  <span class="sup">−1</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
