<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both the timing of megafauna extinction and first human arrival in Sahul have long been controversial given the lack of reliable data and bias introduced by the Signor–Lipps effect. Having now accounted for these deficiencies, our results support the general conclusions of previous studies
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>, but they are much better constrained by more diverse and expanded data sets that have been rigorously scrutinized using the best-available analytical tools. It is generally accepted that humans were present in Australia by 48 kyr
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>. Our modelled age estimate of 55.6 kyr reflects the early human colonization of northern Australia
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">38</a>, but geographic gaps in high-quality data (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</a>) prevent a reliable interpretation of the pattern of human dispersal across Sahul. It is clear, however, that humans were present in Tasmania by 39 kyr
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a> and in the arid centre of Australia by 35 kyr
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 13.5-kyr window of human–megafauna coexistence estimated is sufficiently long for groups of hunter–gatherers to disperse and become established across Sahul
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">40</a> and to extirpate many megafauna species without a wave of rapid, continent-wide overkill. These results do not dismiss the possibility of rapid human overkill at more local/regional scales, nor that the longer the period of coexistence, the more time megafauna would have had to adapt to human presence and become more immune to their impacts. However, we currently lack direct evidence for human–megafauna interactions, possibly because of taphonomic loss and sampling bias
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a>. Nonetheless, quantitative models have demonstrated that even small groups of hunter–gatherers living across a vast continent and using stone-based technologies could feasibly exterminate species with low population growth rates, such as large-bodied mammals
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a>. This conclusion could not be supported by results based only on a direct reading of the fossil record, because it would be biased by the uncorrected Signor–Lipps effect
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1c</a>). By including only reliably dated megafauna and archaeological records in our models, and explicitly correcting for the Signor–Lipps effect, the duration of human–megafauna coexistence can be estimated with much higher statistical confidence. Our approach allows us to discriminate between the various proposed extinction mechanisms
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a> for the late Quaternary megafauna of Sahul and has revealed that climate change was not a continental driver of extinction of these genera. The same approach could similarly provide new insights into the causes of late Quaternary megafauna extinction events in other regions of the world.
 </p>
</sec>
