<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information-theoretic ER</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We fitted two regression models to the estimated number of extinct genera as a function of climate variables (described by our six proxies; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1d–h</a>) at the same date. The first model includes a slope parameter that assumes a linear relationship between the number of genera going extinct and the climate conditions at a time step of 1,000 years. The second model is a simpler, mean-field approach, with only an intercept that assumes no climate–extinction relationship (the ‘null' model). The ER provides a way of explicitly evaluating the parameter bias-corrected likelihood of the null hypothesis (that is, no correlation between the number of extinct genera and climate variation) against the alternative (i.e., correlation between climate variation and the number of extinct genera). The ER is calculated as the sample size-adjusted AIC
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">c</span>
  </sub> weight of the slope model divided by AIC
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">c</span>
  </sub> weight of the competing model (in our case, the intercept-only model). Higher ERs (&gt;3, see the ER interpretation scale in ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>) provide stronger support for the alternative hypothesis (model with slope) versus the null hypothesis, meaning that more genera went extinct as climate variation increased; for example, a strongly correlated climate variable might yield an ER&gt;150. We also accounted for a possible temporal lag between climate conditions and megafauna extinctions, and for uncertainties in climate variables. We calculated the temporal lag by regressing against climate from 0 to 20,000 years (at a 2 kyr time step=11 temporal lag scenarios) for the period earlier than 35 kyr ago, which has the maximum number of extinct genera (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1a</a>). For each of these scenarios, we generated 1,000 new sets of climate values resulting in 1,000 random resamples of the climate data within their confidence intervals (11 scenarios of ‘temporal lag' × 1,000 random resamples of each climate-lag data set within their confidence intervals=11,000 sets of climate values for each climate proxy). We refitted both linear models to the estimated number of genera going extinct as a function of these new sets of climate values and recalculated their ERs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Data availability:</span> Models and data used in analyses are available on request to F.S. (
  <span class="email">frederik.saltre@adelaide.edu.au</span>) from the Global Ecology Laboratory, School of Biological Sciences at the University of Adelaide. Sahul's megafauna data set is also available online in the AEKOS data repository (DOI:10.4227/05/564E6209C4FE8).
 </p>
</sec>
