<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Monthly values of bottom temperature, bottom nitrate and maximum 
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> were calculated for each of the nine kelp forest sites and were averaged to produce a regional mean value for each day of the time series. Regional daily means were averaged to produce regional monthly means. Regional monthly anomalies for bottom temperature and bottom nitrate were calculated as the difference between the regional mean value for a given month in a given year and the 15-year average for that month. Monthly anomalies for maximum 
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> used to compare the wave climate during the recent warming in 2014–2015 with that during the 1982–1983 and 1997–1998 El Niños were calculated as the difference between the mean obtained using modelled hindcast and buoy data from Harvest Platform for a given month in a given year and the 36-year average (1980–2015) for that month. To further characterize the oceanographic conditions at our study sites we applied Hobday 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.'s hierarchical approach for defining marine heatwaves
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref> to the bottom temperature data and calculated the occurrence and duration of heatwaves in each year of the time series. We estimated low nitrate events as periods when a mean daily nitrate concentration of 1 μmol l
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> persisted for at least 21 days. The rationale for this definition is based on previous studies that concluded concentrations of nitrate&lt;1 μmol l
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> are not sufficient to support normal growth in 
 <italic class="italic">Macrocystis</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref> and its internal nitrogen reserves become exhausted within 21 days without any external supplies
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>.
</p>
