<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Colonization and establishment: adaptive loci</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying risk factors associated with establishment would be assisted by more information on the genetic basis of adaptive changes in colonizing species. If these changes were known and repeatable, it might help predict when colonizations occur. One of the best examples is the evolutionary changes involved in the repeated independent colonization of freshwater environments by sticklebacks (summary in Bell and Aguirre 
  <a rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25">2013</a>). These colonization events have been associated with repeatable changes in lateral plate morphology across populations involving the ectodysplasin (EDA) locus. Many loci in different genomic regions also appear to be involved, but nevertheless there appear to be changes across the same set of genomic regions in different, isolated freshwater populations of sticklebacks following invasion (Jones et al. 
  <a rid="b152" ref-type="bibr" href="#b152">2012</a>). The stickleback situation may be unusual because there has been a repeated process of invasions that have been occurring over 10 million years (Bell and Aguirre 
  <a rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25">2013</a>), but more cases need to be examined. Because invasive species often occupy similar habitats in the introduced range to those in the native range (see Guisan et al. 
  <a rid="b127" ref-type="bibr" href="#b127">2014</a> for a recent overview and perspective), there is an opportunity to determine whether the same genomic regions contribute to adaptations in the native and introduced ranges across many invasive species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While there is abundant evidence for changes in neutral markers following invasion, characterization of adaptive molecular differences, such as those established in stickleback populations, remains relatively scarce. Transcriptome comparisons of plants in common garden experiments suggest that invasive populations of ragweed show altered patterns of gene expression that are distinct from most populations from the native range, and genes showing altered patterns of expression appear to be linked to stress and biotic responses (Hodgins et al. 
  <a rid="b139" ref-type="bibr" href="#b139">2013</a>). A similar pattern has since been identified in Canada thistle (Guggisberg et al. 
  <a rid="b126" ref-type="bibr" href="#b126">2013</a>), but whether changes to expression during invasion primarily involve certain functional groups, as indicated by these studies, will require more examples across a broader array of organisms.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the challenges in finding the genetic basis of adaptive change is that causal connections between genetic changes and traits can be difficult to identify. Often researchers are faced with the problem of locating small but crucial changes within a mass of genomic data. However, the implementation of population genomic analysis of SNP variation across the genome has enabled the identification of putatively selected loci (or those linked to the causal loci). This approach has already proven useful in several cases. Pyrenean rocket (
  <span class="italic">Sisymbrium austriacum</span> subsp. 
  <span class="italic">chrysanthum</span>) is a small colonizing herb of rocky soils that has recently invaded Belgium and the Netherlands, and Vandepitte et al. (
  <a rid="b304" ref-type="bibr" href="#b304">2014</a>) used a RAD-Seq approach to identify outlier loci in comparisons between invaded and native populations. Multiple native and invaded populations were investigated including those represented by herbarium specimens covering 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 100 years in the invasive range. Several outlier loci that could underlie adaptive differences were discovered, and the sampling enabled a comparison of outliers across space as well as time. Some of the SNPs were located in genes known to affect flowering time in the closely related 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</span>. These findings point to likely adaptive shifts rather than changes associated with demographic processes. This study demonstrates the utility of phenotype–genotype approaches for identifying candidate adaptive loci in invasive species coupled with functional information from model species. As the genomes of invasive species become better defined and genetic tools are developed, it should be increasingly possible to also pursue bottom-up approaches in a range of invasive species particularly because these can often be relatively easily grown under controlled conditions.
 </p>
</sec>
