<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying source populations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although genetic markers have been used for some time and are now used almost routinely for identifying source populations of species, genomic markers promise a much higher level of resolution and they are being increasingly applied. A recent example is provided by the dengue vector mosquito, 
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span>, whose source populations have traditionally been identified using mtDNA markers coupled with microsatellites (Endersby et al. 
  <a rid="b99" ref-type="bibr" href="#b99">2011</a>; Brown et al. 
  <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">2014</a>). These provide some indication of population sources and are currently used in countries such as Australia to locate source populations. However, a much higher level of resolution for identifying source populations can be obtained from SNP nuclear markers that can now be scored in the thousands; this was demonstrated in the extent to which geographic samples of 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> could be completely resolved based on 18 000 SNP markers compared to 10–15 other markers (Rasic et al. 
  <a rid="b233" ref-type="bibr" href="#b233">2014</a>) (Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig02" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Comparison of population structure of 
    <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span> mosquitoes as determined from microsatellite markers versus SNP markers. Based on a discriminant analysis, the SNP markers provide a far higher level of resolution of populations including the invaded (non-Asian) range of this species (from Rasic et al. 
    <a rid="b233" ref-type="bibr" href="#b233">2014</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0008-0023-f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SNP markers are now being developed for other invasive species including invasive plants (De Kort et al. 
  <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2014</a>) and mammals (White et al. 
  <a rid="b315" ref-type="bibr" href="#b315">2013</a>) as well as insects. These markers promise to revolutionize risk assessment and quarantine control because they can reveal both contemporary and historical population processes. The potential of this approach in detecting and understanding past patterns based on whole-genome sequencing is evident from recent human studies on invasions and contractions of different cultural groups that provide new insights into patterns of relatedness and the spread of cultural practices (Sikora et al. 
  <a rid="b265" ref-type="bibr" href="#b265">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding source populations and spread dynamics may benefit from using nuclear and extranuclear genomes. For instance, in the Russian wheat aphid, Zhang et al. (
  <a rid="b333" ref-type="bibr" href="#b333">2014</a>) tested patterns of invasion by characterizing more than 500 clones for genetic markers in nuclear DNA, mtDNA and endosymbionts. They were able to show that Turkey and Syria were the most likely sources of invasion to Kenya and South Africa respectively, as well as establishing patterns of invasion into the New World. Having the different sources of genomic information was essential to this study as the recent introduction limited the genetic resolution of the aphid markers used. Combining nuclear DNA and organellar markers has traditionally improved the understanding of invasive processes, and it is becoming clear that including vertically transmitted endosymbiont or parasitic organisms can provide new insight into the origins of invasive species as well as the diseases they carry (Gupta et al. 
  <a rid="b129" ref-type="bibr" href="#b129">2014</a>; Mobegi et al. 
  <a rid="b197" ref-type="bibr" href="#b197">2014</a>). The addition of mtDNA provides information on introgression patterns between diverged populations or subspecies because mtDNA genomes track maternal lineages (McCormick et al. 
  <a rid="b188" ref-type="bibr" href="#b188">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the future, genomic information will likely prove useful in identifying source risk and predicted outcomes of invasions when they are detected. For instance, in ragweed, it appears, based on microsatellite and chloroplast markers, that invasive populations have developed in the native range of this species associated with human habitation, and these populations are then likely to form the basis of invasive populations into other areas (Martin et al. 
  <a rid="b185" ref-type="bibr" href="#b185">2014</a>). Predictions are that invasions will grow in number and be increasingly difficult to distinguish from range shifts (Walther et al. 
  <a rid="b308" ref-type="bibr" href="#b308">2009</a>). Genomic techniques that can facilitate rapid identification of source populations will prove especially useful for addressing this problem (for an application in identifying the basis of range expansion, see Krehenwinkel and Tautz 
  <a rid="b160" ref-type="bibr" href="#b160">2013</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
