<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" id="embr201948706-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The age of disinformation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This vacuum of knowledge is all too easy for vested interests to hijack, engineering a platform for unsubstantiated views. Moreover, since Mooney's observations 15 years ago, our new channels have drastically changed. The Internet has become our primary source for information, frequently filtered through the distorting prism of social media. The impact has been stark: the media has become far more fragmented, and messages which promote outrage or emotional reaction tend to be much more widely shared, regardless of their veracity 
  <a rid="embr201948706-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#embr201948706-bib-0008">8</a>. The traditional triumvirate of newspapers, television and radio has been supplanted largely by Internet‐based publications. This has positive aspects and has certainly diversified sources of information. But recent investigations into Russian disinformation campaigns have illustrated how this greater ecosystem of information channels allows one to conjure misinformation wholesale, readily disseminating it without the typical machinery of the press. Consequently, one can bypass traditional media channels completely, perpetuating any falsehood desired.
 </p>
 <div content-type="pull-quote" id="embr201948706-blk-0005" class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>The media has become far more fragmented, and messages which promote outrage or emotional reaction tend to be much more widely shared, regardless of their veracity.</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dubious sources are alarmingly common, often outnumbering reputable accounts 
  <a rid="embr201948706-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#embr201948706-bib-0009">9</a>. Nor are we especially adept at identifying questionable sources; one Stanford study investigating this labelled their findings “bleak” and “a threat to democracy” 
  <a rid="embr201948706-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#embr201948706-bib-0010">10</a>. With fringe sources that deliberately blur the line between information and propaganda, false balance is no longer the issue, as these sources eschew any pretence of impartiality. But the damage done can be further compounded by reputable outlets engaging in false balance; this often occurs when journalists deem a claim worthy of coverage due solely to a volume of claims about it, rather than the quality of those claims. In doing so, they can lend legitimacy to positions that do not warrant any oxygen, cementing skewed perceptions in the public mind. This “feedback loop” form of false balance has certainly been at the root of a number of vaccine panics in recent years and has equally driven fears over genetically modified food and 5G technology.
 </p>
</sec>
