<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Finally, the hypothesis that growing several wheat genotypes may contribute to increase resilience of GY in environments with erratic weather patterns was tested. To do so, calculation of grain production of five wheat genotypes was compared to production of one single genotype or “mega-variety.” For this exercise, three sets of data were used: 250 modern winter wheat varieties and breeding lines described above and data generated from international nurseries distributed worldwide by CIMMYT, the 23rd ESWYT (Elite Selection Wheat Yield Trials), and the 21st SAWYT (Semi-Arid Wheat Yield Trial). The data can be found at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cimmyt.org/international-wheat-improvement-network-iwin/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cimmyt.org/international-wheat-improvement-network-iwin/</ext-link>. First, environments were named “training environments” if used for selection of genotypes based on mean GY and “testing environments” if used to test performance of genotypes previously selected in the “training environments.” Then, one or five genotypes with the highest mean yield over six “training environments” were tested for their performance in two other random environments or “testing environments.” In total, 28 combinations of environments were developed using six random “training environments” and two “testing environments.” For each combination, total production of different selections was calculated: (i) total grain production of one genotype grown in two “testing environments” (total of 20 ha), and previously showing the highest mean yield, in six “training environments” (or “mega-variety”); (ii) total grain production of five genotypes grown in two “testing environments” (total of 20 ha) previously showing the top five highest mean yields in six “training environments”; and (iii) total grain production of the genotype showing the highest mean yield in all eight environments in a total of 20 ha.
</p>
