<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">At sub-regional scales, biological and mechanistic models are often used to separate out and investigate the impacts of global warming on malaria risk. Most of these models have incorporated the relationships between temperature and malaria transmission that are relatively well understood. For instance, air temperature is used to estimate the developmental rates of 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes in aquatic stages [
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium</italic> parasites within the mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Few malaria models have attempted to incorporate the causal relationship among rainfall, humidity, soil moisture, and mosquito larval habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. The processes by which rainfall is partitioned into infiltration and stagnant water pools suitable for 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> breeding are strongly dependent on rainfall patterns, micro-topographic features, soil characteristics and vegetation cover. Nevertheless, existing models that have been used are limited in their ability to capture the changes in ecohydrological responses induced by vegetation acclimation under elevated [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] and temperature change [
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. These acclimatory responses have been shown to affect soil moisture and the persistence of ponding through changes in evapotranspiration (ET) [
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0211258.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], and thus habitat structure and distribution for 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes.
</p>
