<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Narrowly distributed species are found across all taxonomic groups, but they are more common among plants. Indeed, the smallest ranges of vascular plants are much smaller than the smallest ranges of birds and mammals (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown, Stevens &amp; Kaufman, 1996</xref>), possibly because plants are limited by edaphic factors (i.e., chemical, physical, and biological properties of soils), microclimate, and dispersal modes (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kruckeberg &amp; Rabinowitz, 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Major, 1988</xref>). Plants are the basis upon which all other life depends. Yet, the number of plant species that have a high extinction risk is unknown. To date, from the estimated 386,000 species of plants (not including algae; The Plant List: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.theplantlist.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.theplantlist.org/</ext-link>), only 28,114 (7.3%) have been evaluated by IUCN Red List (
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IUCN, 2019</xref>). Among these species, 47.7% are threatened (i.e., they have been classified as vulnerable, endangered, or critically endangered) and 0.5% are extinct or extinct in wild (
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IUCN, 2019</xref>), but these numbers have been questioned. For instance, an assessment of a randomly selected sample of species indicated that the proportion of threatened plant species is around 20% (
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brummitt et al., 2015</xref>) while other study estimated that the number of extinct species is more than four times the one estimated by IUCN Red List (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Humphries et al., 2019</xref>). In general, IUCN’s analyses show that habitat loss is the most critical factor endangering plant species everywhere, but the impact of climate change has possibly been underestimated (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loarie et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wiens, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fadrique et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
