<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Yellowhorn is an ancient woody perennial species belonging to Xanthoceroideae family that evolved during the Late Cretaceous (110 My) with other species in Sapindaceae (including four lineages: Xanthoceroideae, Hippocastanoideae, Dodonaeoideae, and Sapindoideae; Buerki et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Yellowhorn original distribution is the tropics (like other species in Sapindaceae, eg. Longan (Nakasone &amp; Paull, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>)), then migrated north to temperate region. In our study, H1 is the most widely distributed haplotypes (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34944-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>) and may be dispersed in the relatively flat landscape by animals. In fact, the Siberian chipmunk (
 <italic class="italic">Eutamias sibiricus</italic>) that was frequently observed in the studied populations could have acted as a vector aiding the spreading of this haplotype. The presence of the Ziwuling Mountain that occurred in 1.67–1.45 Ma BP (Zhaoyu, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1992</xref>) may have contributed to separating clades E (western part of Ziwuling Mountain) and A; Taiyuan Basin formed around 7.2–5.3 Ma (Ke, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), surrounded by Luliang and Taihang Mountains and Fenhe River (in Shanxi Province), could have contributed to the isolation of clade B from other clades; clade D representing the western part of Luliang Mountain which is surrounded by the Fenhe River could be responsible for the species’ observed contemporary distribution. Finally, the isolated evolution of clade C which is distributed in northeastern Qinling Mountain may have separated it from other clades by the occurrence of the Yellow River in 0.15 Ma (Zheng et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Population's genetic diversity showed substantial reduction from northeast to southwest regions (Figures 
 <xref rid="ece34944-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ece34944-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>) and may be due to the isolation by mountains and rivers forcing yellowhorn to evolve to adapt to the new environments during its northeastward migration. According to the tropical origin hypothesis, H1 is the most ancient haplotype, the pattern of mutation steps highly support the northeastward migration route (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34944-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>).
</p>
