<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The study reveals that projected increases in annual precipitation and annual mean temperature may limit the distribution of Sal, as identified by our models (the optimum annual mean temperature was 28°C, and annual precipitation ranges from 1,000 to 2,000 mm; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32846-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> for details; Das &amp; Alam, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Gautam &amp; Devoe, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The variation of temperature seasonality may also regulate the distribution of Sal as it grows in areas where the dry period does not exceed 4 months (Gautam &amp; Devoe, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The predicted shift in the distribution of Sal toward northeast in India is consistent with the findings of a similar study on Sal in India (Chitale &amp; Behera, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Chitale and Behera (
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) predicted the distribution of Sal for the year 2020 under HadClim Emission scenario SRES‐A1B and included all 19 bioclimatic variables without considering their relative contributions. They also found that moisture (annual precipitation) was a key driver of Sal distribution: Our consideration of the relative contribution of the bioclimatic variables revealed that annual mean temperature was also important. Increased rainfall variability and extreme drought conditions in the central and northern parts of Bangladesh may result in unsuitable climate conditions for Sal forests (Shahid, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). The projected increase in annual rainfall and variation in temperature seasonality may restrict the distribution of Garjan in the region, with increasing local‐level extinction risk in the Chittagong hill tract regions of Bangladesh (Das &amp; Alam, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Sarker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
