<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have noted that when compared with familiar foods, a consumer’s willingness to choose new foods, or those that have not been previously eaten, may be affected by neophobia [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Pliner and Hobden [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] referred to food neophobia as the fear of food that has either not been eaten or seen in an eating situation, and describe an unwillingness to approach and eat unfamiliar food. People generate a mixture of conflicting curiosity and fear toward foods they have not previously seen [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Pliner and Hobden [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] developed the food neophobia scale (FNS) to measure aversion to new foods, and previous studies have utilized the FNS to evaluate consumer willingness to eat or choose new foods [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], familiarity and experience with foreign foods [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], willingness to explore food flavors [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and expectations from new foods [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Some scholars have applied a food technology neophobia scale to measure consumer attitudes toward new and traditional food technologies [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], university students’ satisfaction regarding food-related life [
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and consumer neophobia to red wine [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In addition, the degree of an individual’s food neophobia influences their purchase of food products and frequency of purchase [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], as well as their eating habits [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Along the same lines, La Barbera et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] noted that consumer food neophobia and aversions affect the willingness to eat insect foods. The present study postulates that due to varying levels of food neophobia among Taiwanese consumers, consumers will have varying reactions, which may influence their willingness to purchase insect food products. For these reasons, the present study includes food neophobia as a research variable.
</p>
