<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subglacial discharge and Greenland’s marine margins</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most work investigating the direct impacts of surface meltwater has targeted land-terminating outlet glaciers. Marine-terminating glaciers are fundamentally different however, in that ice–ocean interactions permit highly non-linear and unstable behaviour with profound impacts on glacier retreat and the attendant export of ice to the ocean. Sediment-laden freshwater plumes can be seen rising from subglacial conduits to the fjord surface, implicating glacier melt in fjord circulation dynamics. These meltwater inputs draw warm ocean water at depth toward the ice front, where sub-marine meltrates can reach metres per day
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Complexities arise, however, from the particulars of fjord configuration, ice depth, subglacial discharge rates, the geometry of subglacial conduits and externally forced ocean currents and fjord stratification
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Though it is too early to generalize on the importance of ice-sheet hydrology for processes at Greenland’s marine margins, current indications are that surface melt does have an important role in driving dynamics at the ice–ocean interface where marine-terminating glaciers are most sensitive. Although the contributions to Greenland’s dynamic mass loss since 2000 are concentrated in relatively few outlet glaciers, there may be other glaciers with geometries and fjords primed for retreat. In contrast to Antarctica, most of Greenland’s marine-terminating glaciers are ultimately destined to retreat onto dry land, spelling a less dynamic future ice sheet. In the meantime, even a decade of perturbation at the ice front can lead to a century of ice-sheet drawdown and committed sea-level rise
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, so the effects of dynamic thinning will be with us well into the future.
 </p>
</sec>
