<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, the majority of global multi-species studies assessing animal responses to climate change have focused on changes in distribution ranges
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, whereas phenotypic responses and the extent to which they may be adaptive remain little studied
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Moreover, models commonly used to predict species distributions and population viability under climate change usually do not incorporate the potential for species to adapt, often because appropriate data are unavailable to parameterize process-based models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. Our study thus makes an important contribution by focusing on the temporal dimension of species responses to changing environments. We demonstrate that some bird species analysed here seem to respond to warming temperatures by adaptive advancement of their phenology, emphasizing the possibility of species tracking their thermal niches in situ, which can occur with or without shifts in geographic ranges
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. However, we did not find evidence for adaptive change in all species, and even populations undergoing adaptive change may do so at a pace that does not guarantee their persistence. We further document variation among fitness components in the strength of selection, with the strongest negative selection stemming from individual variation in recruitment, followed by selection from variation in reproduction and survival. Such strongest selection acting via recruitment and reproduction may point to a mechanism underlying adaptive phenological responses in birds, which is the synchrony of breeding with the availability of resources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings of adaptive phenological responses to global warming in some bird species, reported here, should not be interpreted over-optimistically. Indeed, perfect adaptation would imply no selection and the significant directional selection observed across studies thus indicates that adaptive responses are imperfect, assuming selection estimates are not consistently biased, for example, see ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, the lack of a temporal trend in the strength of selection means that, although populations are not perfectly adapted in their phenology, they are not getting more adapted or less maladapted over time as temperatures continue to rise. This result suggests that they are phenotypically tracking a shifting optimum, lagging behind at a constant rate, as predicted by Bürger and Lynch
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Our comparisons of the actual vs. critical lags suggest that there is low but non-negligible probability that the degree of maladaptation is large enough for the majority of our study populations to be at risk. The actual risk of population extinction may in fact be larger because our estimations do not account for several sources of stochasticity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Moreover, our dataset predominantly includes common and abundant species (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pica pica</span>) for which collection of selection data is relatively easy. The generality of adaptive phenological responses among rare or endangered species, or those with different life histories, remains to be established
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. We fear that the forecasts of population persistence for such species will be more pessimistic.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the extent to what animals are able to track climate change, we here used an approach based on selection differentials by testing whether selection over time is significant across studies, and whether it is aligned with the direction of the phenotypic change over time. Alternative approaches exist, for example, the velocity of climate change can be used to assess the expected phenological change that is required to track climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>. This approach allowed the authors to demonstrate that, in general, faster phenological shifts occur in regions of faster climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Although it would be insightful to compare the results obtained with the approach adopted here and the one based on the velocity of climate, this would only be possible for phenological, and not morphological traits.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection and trait change in our analyses were measured at the phenotypic and not the genetic level. Therefore, we cannot determine whether the adaptive phenological responses were due to microevolution or adaptive phenotypic plasticity, nor their relative contributions. Further insights would require differentiating between genetic and environmental components of the phenotype and how each relates to the fitness of individuals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. This could be done by using animal models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>, employing common-garden and reciprocal transplant experiments (approaches more suitable for plants, invertebrates and fish) or by combining genetic or genomic and phenotypic information
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. Further, our analyses are correlative and we cannot rule out the possibility that the presumed effects of temperature are in fact due to other or additional environmental variables that correlate with climate, or that selection estimates are biased by environmental correlations between trait and fitness
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>, or do not accurately reflect total selection as a result of being based on incomplete fitness measures.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar to the recent global assessments of the climate effects on phenology
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span> and selection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, our datasets are heavily biased towards studies from the Northern Hemisphere. Additionally, the majority of the phenological traits in our datasets focus on early season (spring) events. Previous research has shown that early season phenological responses, especially at northern latitudes, are advancing with warming temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>, and therefore an advancement of phenological events was our main working assumption. Although the majority of phenological events is reported to advance, delays with warming temperatures have also been recorded
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. For example, delay in emergence from hibernation of Columbian ground squirrels was associated with lower fitness, and thus was maladaptive
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>. Similarly, in our study, the majority of maladaptive responses occurred when selection acted in the direction of earlier phenological events, but observed phenological events were delayed over the study period (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>). However, whether such delays are generally maladaptive across hemispheres and seasons is unknown. We believe that our proposed framework (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) will facilitate answering such questions in the future.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Decrease in body size was suggested to be the third general response of species to global warming, together with changes in phenology and distributions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. However, evidence for this response is equivocal
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. Our results suggest that inconsistency in findings to date may be explained by different studies focusing on different taxa (e.g. birds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>, mammals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>). Indeed, we found that the association between morphological traits and temperature tends to differ among taxa, with only mammals showing a clear negative association. This finding contrasts with a lack of relationship between temperature and morphology reported for mammals by Meiri et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>, potentially because their study periods were longer than ours, and they used a different morphological measure (condyle-basal length). Although our PRC dataset is not exhaustive, our findings of variation among taxa in both phenological and morphological responses highlight the importance of collecting observations on a wide range of taxa.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The assembled PRCS dataset suggests several avenues for further research. For example, currently underappreciated effects of climatic variation on traits and, in turn, on fitness and population viability may be pronounced
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span> and our datasets could be used to investigate them. Further, extending this dataset to incorporate vital rates and, ideally, population growth rate would allow for the mapping of environmental changes onto demography via phenotypic traits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>, and ultimately a better assessment of how trait responses impact population persistence.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results are an important first demonstration that, at least in a range of bird species, adaptive phenological responses may partially alleviate negative fitness effects of changing climate. Further work is needed to quantify the extent of such buffering and to broaden the taxonomic scope to determine if this conclusion also applies to species already encountering higher extinction risk for reasons unrelated to climate. The PRC(S) datasets that we assembled should stimulate research on the resilience of animal populations in the face of global change and contribute to a better predictive framework to assist future conservation management actions.</p>
</sec>
