<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity analyses</div>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One study in the meta-analytical models testing conditions 2 and 3 for phenology in the PRCS dataset appeared to be an outlier (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Therefore, we also re-ran the models without this study (Supplementary Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). Additionally, the PRCS dataset contained mainly studies on bird species, and only one for a mammal species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>. To test how sensitive the results were to inclusion of this taxon, we re-ran the analyses after excluding the study for mammal species. The main findings were qualitatively unaffected by excluding either the only mammal study or an apparent outlier from the PRCS dataset, or both (Supplementary Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measures of phenological responses are known to be sensitive to methodological biases
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, in particular to temporal trends in abundance of the sampled species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Indeed, if species abundance increases over time, the probability of recording earlier events increases (especially if phenology is measured as the first occurrence date), meaning that species abundance can affect mean of the distribution of a phenological trait. For the same reason, the variance around the mean phenological response may be sensitive to population size, with higher variance at lower population sizes. To assess the sensitivity of our results to potential changes in population sizes over time, we fitted a heteroskedastic model in which population abundance was included both as a fixed-effect explanatory variable and as an explanatory variable for the model of the residual variance. This model is an extension of the models specified in Eq. (
  <a rid="Equ2" ref-type="" href="#Equ2">2</a>) that were used to assess condition 2. This model was fit to each study for which abundance data were available and where the duration of the study was at least 11 years (28 out of 42 studies). The fitted model was:
  <div id="Equ5" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">5</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M9" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\mathrm{Trait}}_t = \alpha + \beta _{{\mathrm{Trait}}} \times {\mathrm{Clim}}_t + \gamma \times {\mathrm{Year}}_t + \delta \times {\mathrm{Abund}}_t + \varepsilon _t + \varepsilon ,$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M10" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Trait</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mi">α</span>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">β</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Trait</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">×</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Clim</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span class="mi">γ</span>
     <span class="mo">×</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Year</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span class="mi">δ</span>
     <span class="mo">×</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Abund</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">ε</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span class="mi">ε</span>
     <span class="mo">,</span>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10924_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>where Trait is the mean phenotypic trait (z-scaled across the years within each study), Clim the quantitative climate covariate, Year the quantitative year covariate, Abund the quantitative covariate for species abundance, 
  <span class="italic">t</span> the time, 
  <span class="italic">ε</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>
  </sub> is a Gaussian random variable with mean zero and following an AR1 model over years, and 
  <span class="italic">ε</span> is an independent Gaussian random variable with mean zero and variance proportional to the estimated variance of the mean phenotypic trait (which depends on 
  <span class="italic">t</span>). 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>Trait</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">γ</span> and 
  <span class="italic">δ</span> are regression coefficients that correspond to the slopes of the trait on the climatic variable, the trait on year and the trait on the abundance for the study, respectively. To avoid overfitting, we refitted the same model without the AR1 structure and retained, for each study, the model structure leading to the lowest marginal AIC, analogously to how it was done for the models fitted to assess conditions 1, 2 and 3.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results were qualitatively unaffected by the inclusion of abundance in the models: the rate of advancement in phenology estimated across the studies was −0.346 ± 0.102 SD per °C (LRT between the model with and without change in phenology: 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 8.4, df = 1, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.004) when including abundance and −0.335 ± 0.088 SD per °C without abundance (LRT: 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 9.19, df = 1, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.002; for comparison’s sake both models were fitted to a subset of studies for which abundance data were available). We also found that although abundance affects phenology, its effects were on average smaller compared to the effects of temperature (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
