<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Systematic literature search</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our literature search focused on studies that investigated how change in temperature, precipitation or both affects morphological or phenological traits in arachnids, insects, amphibians, reptiles, birds or mammals. To assess all three conditions necessary for inferring adaptive responses to climate change (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), we selected publications reporting the following data from natural populations during at least 6 years: (1) annual values of a climatic variable, (2) annual mean values (+SE) of a phenotypic trait at the population level and (3) annual linear selection differentials measured on the trait(s). Annual linear selection differentials were measured as the slope of relative fitness on standardized trait values
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> (Methods, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>) and reported for at least one of the three fitness components: adult survival, reproduction (measured as number of offspring) or recruitment (measured as number of offspring contributing to the population size the following year).
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A search on Web of Knowledge (Methods) returned 10,090 publications, of which 58 were retained. These publications reported data on 4835 studies (representing 1413 non-aquatic species in 23 countries) that contained information on phenotypic responses to climate change. Out of these 4835 studies, a subset of 71 studies (representing 17 species in 13 countries) contained all the information required to assess whether responses were adaptive (including selection differentials, Methods). We stored information on the 4835 studies in the ‘PRC’ dataset, and information on the subset of the 71 studies in the ‘PRC with Selection data’ (PRCS) dataset. We used the PRC dataset to assess how representative the PRCS subset was with regard to (1) the observed change in climatic factors over time, and (2) the change in phenotypic traits in response to climatic factors. We define a ‘study’ as a dataset satisfying our selection criteria for a unique combination of a species, location, climatic factor, phenotypic trait and fitness component. We had more studies than publications because some publications reported data for several species, several climatic factors and/or several phenotypic traits.</p>
</sec>
