<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Systematic literature review</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We aimed at assessing adaptive phenotypic responses to climate change across six broad taxa of animals: arachnids, insects, amphibians, reptiles, birds and mammals. We distinguished between two climatic variables: temperature and precipitation. We relied on the authors of the original studies for their expertise and knowledge of the biology of the species and system in the: (1) choice of the appropriate time window over which the annual means of the climatic values were calculated, rather than using a single time window for all species. For instance, if in a bird study the mean temperature over the 2 months preceding nesting was used as an explanatory variable for the timing of egg laying, we used this specific climatic variable; (2) choice of the specific climatic variables, be it air, sea surface or soil temperature, rather than using a single climatic variable across all species; and (3) choice of the spatial scale of the study, so that the measured variables were considered local at that scale. We focused on studies that recorded both changes of at least one climatic variable over time and changes in either morphological or phenological traits for at least one studied species. Phenological traits reflect shifts in timing of biological events, for example, egg-laying date, antler cast date or mean flight date in insects. Morphological traits reflect the size or mass of the whole body or its parts (e.g., bill length, wing length, body mass).</p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess whether trait changes were adaptive, we only used studies that measured selection on the trait(s) of interest by means of linear selection differentials
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> using one of the following fitness components: recruitment, reproduction, and adult survival. Linear selection differentials for all studies were calculated following Lande and Arnold
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, as the slope of the linear model, with relative fitness (individual fitness divided by mean fitness) as response and the z-transformed trait value as predictor. Only studies that reported SE estimates along with annual linear selection differentials were retained. For the majority of studies, we extracted selection differentials directly from the published studies, and for 12 studies, we calculated them ourselves using the respective individual-level data shared by the authors.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To identify the studies satisfying the above-mentioned criteria, we searched the Web of Knowledge (search conducted on 23 May 2016, Berlin) combining the following keywords for climate change (‘climate change’ OR ‘temperat*’ OR ‘global change’ OR ‘precipit’), adaptation (‘plastic*’ OR ‘adapt*’ OR ‘selection’ OR ‘reaction norm’) and trait category (‘body size’ OR ‘body mass’ OR ‘body length’ OR ‘emerg* date’ OR ‘arriv* date’ OR ‘breed* date’). For taxa, we used broad taxon names in the first search (‘bird*’ OR ‘mammal*’ OR ‘arachnid*’ OR ‘insect*’ OR ‘reptil*’ OR ‘amphibia*’ OR ‘spider*’). Next, to increase the probability of finding the relevant papers, we run the search by using instead of taxa names detailed names below the level of the Class, as follows: (‘rodent*’ OR ‘primat*’ OR ‘rabbit*’ OR ‘hare’ OR ‘mole’ OR ‘shrew*’ OR ‘viverrid*’ OR ‘hyaena’ OR ‘bear*’ OR ‘seal*’ OR ‘mustelid*’ OR ‘skunk*’ OR ‘Ailurid*’ OR ‘walrus*’ OR ‘pinniped*’ OR ‘canid*’ OR ‘mongoos*’ OR ‘felid*’ OR ‘pangolin*’ OR ‘mammal*’ OR ‘bird*’ OR ‘flamingo*’ OR ‘pigeon*’ OR ‘grouse*’ OR ‘cuckoo*’ OR ‘turaco*’ OR ‘rail*’ OR ‘wader*’ OR ‘shorebird*’ OR ‘penguin*’ OR ‘stork*’ OR ‘pelican*’ OR ‘condor*’ OR ‘owl*’ OR ‘hornbill*’ OR “hoopoe*’ OR ‘kingfisher*’ OR ‘woodpecker*’ OR ‘falcon*’ OR ‘parrot*’ OR ‘songbird*’ OR ‘turtle*’ OR ‘tortoise*’ OR ‘lizard*’ OR ‘snake*’ OR ‘crocodil*’ OR ‘caiman*’ OR ‘alligator*’ OR ‘reptil*’ OR ‘frog*’ OR ‘salamander*’ OR ‘toad*’ OR ‘amphibia*’ OR ‘insect*’ OR ‘beetle*’ OR ‘butterfl*’ OR ‘moth*’ OR ‘mosquito*’ OR ‘midge*’ OR ‘dragonfly*’ OR ‘wasp*’ OR ‘bee*’ OR ‘ant*’ NOT (‘fish*’ OR ‘water*’ OR ‘aquatic*’)). These detailed taxon names were combined with the same keywords for climate change, adaptation and trait as before. Finally, we joined the unique records from each of these two searches in a single database.</p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature search returned 10,090 publications, 56 of which were retained after skimming the abstracts. Of these 56 publications, 23 contained the data necessary to assess the three conditions required to infer adaptive responses and were used for assembling the final dataset (PRCS dataset). In cases where several publications reported on the same study system (same species in the same location, measuring the same traits and selection via exactly same fitness components), we retained the publication that reported data for the longest time period. We assembled the PRCS dataset by directly extracting the data from the identified 23 publications wherever possible, or by contacting the authors to ask for the original data. Data were extracted either from tables directly or from plots by digitizing them with the help of WebPlotDigitiser or the metagear package in R
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. In the process of contacting the authors, one research group offered to share relevant unpublished data on two more species, adding two more studies to the dataset, totalling 25 publications. The PRCS dataset consisted of 71 studies containing data on annual values of climatic factors, annual phenotypic trait values and annual linear selection differentials for 17 species in 13 countries (Supplementary Data 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The remaining 33 publications from the originally selected 56 (58 with the shared unpublished data considered as two publications) did not report data on selection, but presented data on the annual values of climatic factors and mean population phenotypic traits, totalling 4764 studies that covered 1401 species. We retained these studies and combined them together with the 71 studies in the PRCS dataset to assemble the ‘PRC’ dataset (Supplementary Data 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">3</a>). With the PRC dataset, we did not aim for comprehensive coverage of the literature published on the topic. Instead, we used this larger PRC dataset to verify whether the smaller PRCS dataset was representative in terms of climate change over time and trait change in response to a climatic factor. A flowchart showing the numbers of studies included at each stage of the systematic literature review is given in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
