<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Rural people are engaging in a plethora of activities as resilience mechanisms to withstand the effects posed by climate change. However, some of their income-generating activities are reliant on agricultural and forest products, which are susceptible to climate change and variability. This is perpetuating the poverty levels in Zimbabwe’s rural communities because rural people are executing mechanisms that are not responsive to the changing climate (Madzwamuse 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Adaptive capacity among rural people is typically limited by poverty, poor public and environmental health, weak institutions, lack of infrastructure and services, marginalisation from decision-making processes and planning procedures, gender inequality, lack of education and information, natural disasters, environmental degradation, reliance on rain-fed agriculture and climate-sensitive resources, and insecure tenure (UNFCCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). According to the International Fund for Agricultural Development (
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), poor rural households are highly exposed to shocks because their livelihoods depend on an increasingly deteriorating natural resource base and on often-volatile climatic conditions. They are also particularly vulnerable to shocks because they have few assets to fall back on and limited risk management strategies. Yohe and Tol (
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>) noted that adaptive capacity has its own determinants, and in any system it can be prudent to assert that individuals, communities and institutions have such determinants: (1) the availability of technological advancements that enable adaptation, (2) the equal distribution of resources, (3) availability of human and social capital including literacy levels, social and personal security and (4) how the public perceives the cause of disturbances (climate change) and its manifestations. The researchers affirmed that the envisaged determinants of adaptive capacity are still far from being a lived reality in Zimbabwe’s rural communities, where poverty is at the centre stage of people’s livelihoods, aggravated by climate change.
</p>
