<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Most of the 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> species studied in this research showed a decrease in habitat suitability in the future considering a climatic niche conservatism scenario (Díaz de la Vega‐Pérez et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Rocha &amp; Vrcibradic, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>). Thus, it would be expected that the species of lizards of this genus should be vulnerable to climate change because this will modify the environmental parameters of the climatic niche where the species occur (Gabriel, Robock, Xia, Zambri, &amp; Kravitz, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). For example, the results of the niche models for species 
 <italic class="italic">X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">grandis</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">mendozai</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">phalaroanthereon</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">rectocollaris</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tzacualtipantecus</italic>, which inhabit temperate and cold ecosystems, showed a dramatic decrease in their habitat suitability by 2070. Similar patterns have been reported by Espinosa and Ocegueda (
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) and Villers‐Ruiz and Trejo‐Vázquez (
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>), who mentioned that the distribution range of vegetation of ecosystems with Nearctic affinities (associated with cold climates) will decrease due to climatic change. Therefore, on the basis of the aforementioned evidence, it is reasonable to infer that the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> will be exposed to a high vulnerability risk due to climatic change. In this sense, Lemos‐Espinal et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003a</xref>) pointed out that 
 <italic class="italic">X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">grandis</italic> might persist in croplands that provide the minimum requirements of microhabitat and native vegetation cover. However, the areas predicted by its habitat suitability model in the future, include croplands and urban settlements, which reduce the possibility of occupying these sites due to the particular ecological characteristics of this species, such as high microhabitat specificity and low dispersion capacity, and therefore, the future survival of its populations will be at high risk (King &amp; Thompson, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1968</xref>).
</p>
