<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many models exist to address this pressing topic, each with different approaches to control for data limitations, confounding processes, climate and disease model uncertainty, different concepts of population at risk, and different preferences towards experimental, mechanistic, or phenomenological approaches e.g. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. While climate change poses perhaps the most serious threat to global health security, the relationship between climate change and burdens of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic>-borne diseases is unlikely to be straightforward, and no single model will accurately predict the complex process of a global regime shift in 
 <italic>Aedes-</italic>borne viral transmission. Our models only set an outer spatiotemporal bound on where transmission is thermally plausible, given climate projections. Climate change is likely to change the relationship between transmission risk and disease burden at fine scales within those zones of transmission nonlinearly, such that areas with shorter seasons of transmission could still experience increased overall disease burdens, or vice versa. Combining broad spatial models with finer-scale models of attack rates or outbreak size is a critical step towards bridging scales [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>], but more broadly, building consensus and revealing similarities and differences between all available models via transparency, is of paramount importance [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. This task is not limited to research on dengue and chikungunya; with several emerging flaviviruses on the horizon [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], and countless other emerging arboviruses likely to test the limits of public health infrastructure in coming years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], approaches that bridge the gap between experimental biology and global forecasting can be one of the foundational methods of anticipating and preparing for the next emerging global health threat.
</p>
