<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Paris Agreement is intended to keep increases in the global mean surface air temperature to below 2 °C relative to preindustrial levels and to make efforts toward limiting that increase to 1.5 °C. Although reducing greenhouse gas emissions is the predominant mitigating measure in achieving that goal, the effect of this measure on global mean surface air temperatures will not be observed over the course of the next few decades, because after being emitted carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) has an atmospheric lifetime over a time scale of a century. It has been suggested that reducing other greenhouse species with shorter atmospheric lifetimes than CO
  <sub>2</sub> might be a way to mitigate global warming before the effect of CO
  <sub>2</sub> reduction becomes apparent. Most short-lived greenhouse species are harmful to human health, so reducing them is also crucial in the context of air quality and would result in a co-beneficial effect. Such pollutants are referred to by the Climate and Clean Air Coalition (CCAC)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> as short-lived climate pollutants (SLCPs) and consist of black carbon (BC), methane (CH
  <sub>4</sub>), tropospheric ozone (O
  <sub>3</sub>), and hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two significant issues emerge when attempting to achieve co-beneficial effects on climate change and air quality via reducing pollutant emissions. One is that some air pollutants, such as sulphate and nitrate aerosols, cool the atmosphere; simply reducing them would accelerate global warming. This implies that the overall impact of air pollutants in both warming and cooling the climate need to be assessed when seeking a co-beneficial effect. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) considers them as short-lived climate forcers (SLCFs), regardless of whether the radiative forcing, an imbalance of the energy budget affected by a change in their concentration, is positive or negative. An IPCC Assessment Report
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> indicated that global mean radiative forcing due to total anthropogenic aerosols is negative, meaning that a reduction in their emissions will accelerate global warming. To mitigate air pollution and acid rain, developed countries have primarily reduced emissions of sulphur dioxide (SO
  <sub>2</sub>), a primary precursor of sulphate aerosols.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The other issue is that although BC is associated with a strong positive radiative forcing effect, recent studies have found that the sensitivity of surface air temperatures to BC tends to be weaker than expected
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Past and future climate simulations used in the IPCC Assessment Reports
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> all included the effects of all major climate forcing agents, however their individual effects on meteorological parameters (e.g. temperature and precipitation) were not assessed. In an attempt to fill this gap, the Precipitation Driver Response Model Intercomparison Project (PDRMIP) recently analysed responses of precipitation and temperature to individual perturbation of some climate forcing agents using both atmosphere-only and ocean-coupled general circulation models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. The PDRMIP protocol included simulations of climate change with extreme perturbations of sulphate and BC aerosol concentrations or emissions. It predicted that increasing present-day concentrations or emissions of BC by even a factor of 10 would result in only small changes in surface air temperatures due to the dominant rapid adjustment of the climate system, including an increase in low-level clouds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. However, assessment of perturbation of each climate forcing agent individually, particularly with such an unrealistic magnitude, is not sufficient to assess the climate response fully over a range of perturbations, including realistic perturbations. This is essential when making scientifically based decisions about potential measures to mitigate SLCPs/SLCFs, as well as about well-mixed greenhouse gases, such as CO
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigate the quantitative trend in surface air temperatures with multiple perturbed emissions of BC and SO
  <sub>2</sub> in the realistic range (zero to twice) relative to the present conditions using a general circulation model coupled with aerosol processes, known as MIROC-SPRINTARS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Contrary to the previous studies that took multi-model ensembles for each experiment with only one perturbation per species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, an advantage of this single-model approach is that the results are not contaminated with differences in physical representations that vary across models, enabling consistent investigation of the relationship between the energy budget perturbation and the climate response. The MIROC-SPRINTARS calculates changes in meteorological parameters by aerosol-radiation interactions in which aerosols scatter and absorb solar and thermal radiation, and aerosol-cloud interactions in which aerosols alter cloud microphysical properties and affect the radiation budget by acting as cloud condensation and ice nuclei. Here, two simulations are executed to distinguish climate changes due to rapid adjustment and slow response: one with prescribed sea surface temperatures and sea ice and the other coupled with an ocean general circulation model (OGCM) (see Methods).
 </p>
</sec>
