<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A global ocean-atmosphere general circulation model, MIROC
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, and an aerosol processes model, SPRINTARS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, were used in this study. The coupled MIROC-SPRINTARS models predicted wind, temperature, surface pressure, specific humidity, mass mixing ratios of cloud water/ice and major aerosol components (sulphate, BC, organic matter (OM), soil dust, and sea salt and precursor gases of sulphate including SO
  <sub>2</sub> and dimethyl sulphide) and precipitation flux, etc. These meteorological parameters in MIROC-SPRINTARS change via aerosol-radiation and aerosol-cloud interactions. The simulated transport processes of aerosols and their precursors include emission, advection, diffusion, chemical reactions of sulphur, wet deposition, and dry deposition. Emission fluxes from fuel and biomass burning sources of SO
  <sub>2</sub>, BC, and OM were acquired from the Emissions Database for Global Atmospheric Research and Task Force on Hemispheric Transport of Air Pollution (EDGAR-HTAP)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> and Global Fire Emissions Database (GFED)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Emissions from natural sources, such as soil dust and sea salt, were calculated from the internal parameters of the model. A change in the snow albedo due to deposition of BC and soil dust was parameterised. A detailed model description of MIROC-SPRINTARS is provided in a previous study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity tests were performed with various scaling factors (i.e. 0, 0.1, 0.3, 0.5, 0.8, 1.5, 2, 5, and 10), which are globally homogeneous relative to the standard emission amount of SO
  <sub>2</sub> and BC from fuel sources, i.e. the EDGAR-HTAP database. The emission scaling factors were only 5 and 10 times for SO
  <sub>2</sub> and BC, respectively, in the PDRMIP model intercomparison experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. To understand the climate effects of sulphate and BC aerosols due to the total response to rapid adjustment, both the simulations with prescribed sea surface temperatures (SSTs) and sea ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> and with an ocean general circulation model (OGCM)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, were executed for each of the perturbed emissions. The results of the simulations with prescribed SSTs and sea ice were defined to represent the rapid adjustment only, and those with the OGCM included both rapid adjustment and slow responses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. The slow response was estimated as the difference between the results from the two simulations. The instantaneous radiative forcing was calculated by a ‘double call’ in which the atmospheric radiation process in the climate model is called twice with and without the aerosol-radiation interaction in a time step using the simulations with prescribed SSTs and sea ice. The simulations are integrated for 15 and 100 years in the prescribed SSTs and sea ice and ocean-coupled experiments, respectively, and the simulated results were analysed for the last 10 and 50 years, respectively. The horizontal resolution of all simulations was T85 (approximately 1.4° by 1.4° in longitude and latitude) and the vertical resolution was 40 layers with the hybrid sigma-pressure coordinate.
 </p>
</sec>
