<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Attractors and basins of attraction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Up to this point we have presented behavioural states as categorical (such as calm and agitated), but behaviours can actually be more fluid. For example, a spider may be slightly irritated, but not fully agitated. As time progresses, the spider may become calm or agitated, depending on environmental parameters. In this example, the categorical states of calm and agitated are referred to as 
  <span class="italic">attractors</span> and the set of fluid states that tend towards these categorical states are these attractors' 
  <span class="italic">basins of attraction</span>. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20181282F1" href="#RSPB20181282F1">figure 1</a>, the solid red and blue lines depict the agitated and calm attractors for a range of environmental parameters (here, temperature). The lighter shaded areas in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20181282F1" href="#RSPB20181282F1">figure 1</a> are the basins of attraction for these two attractors. For intermediate environmental parameters, two attractors exist. At very low temperatures, there is only one attractor, the calm state, while at very high temperatures, only the agitated attractor exists. It is important to emphasize that attractors can appear and disappear, depending on environmental parameters.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In some cases, environmentally driven tipping points may be irreversible. For example, events such as the onset of sex change in sequential hermaphrodites [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C19">19</a>], the onset of epidemic spawning in marine invertebrates [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C20">20</a>], or the emergence of sexual alates in social insects [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C21">21</a>] can be one-way transitions in behavioural state driven by minor perturbations to environmental parameters. In these cases, the former attractors have vanished as a consequence of the system undergoing a tipping point.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the presence and number of attractors, the landscape of attraction can vary. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20181282F1" href="#RSPB20181282F1">figure 1</a>, this is depicted with the landscape slices above the main figure which show how the geometry of the basins of attraction are modified as environmental parameters change. In each case, the blue or red balls indicate the attractors at the bottom of wells symbolizing the basins of attraction. The steepness of the walls of these basins of attraction determine the strength of the feedback mechanisms keeping the system in a given state—the steeper the walls of the wells, the quicker the system returns to the attractor state and the more resistant the state is to noise. When the wells are shallow, the system returns to the attractor more slowly and drifts more widely in response to noise [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C9">9</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C22">22</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C23">23</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
