<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many animals are social, and behaviours that occur within social groups can affect individuals, their immediate neighbours, and the overall performance of the society. In some cases, even small changes in external environmental conditions can cause large and abrupt changes to individuals' behaviours, interactions among group members, and therefore how the group functions as a whole. Examples of changing environmental conditions include food deprivation, heat/cold stress, predation risk, or various anthropogenic stressors. Uncovering how and why small perturbations can cause marked and abrupt shifts in group dynamics is important for understanding group functioning, cohesion, and responsiveness to the environment. Here, we introduce the idea of tipping points, which have been used to better understand the dynamics of complex systems in many fields.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The term 
  <span class="italic">tipping point</span> was first used in the academic literature by Morton Grodzins to describe racial segregation in US cities [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C1">1</a>]. Ecologists and climate scientists have since used tipping points to better understand shifts in lake eutrophication [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C2">2</a>], forest-grass transitions [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C3">3</a>], and coral reef states [
  <a rid="RSPB20181282C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C4">4</a>]. Although the idea of tipping points has been used as a popular analogy for sudden changes in social systems, the conceptual framework underlying tipping points has not been widely applied to questions in behavioural ecology. In this article we explain what tipping points are, how they have been studied in other contexts, and how the tipping point framework could provide new insights and predictive power into the study of animal behaviour.
 </p>
 <sec id="s1a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What are tipping points?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tipping points are drastic shifts in the behaviour of systems as a result of small changes to the environment. In ecology, tipping points are often referred to as 
   <span class="italic">ecological thresholds</span> [
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C5">5</a>–
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C7">7</a>]. For example, a small change in the temperature of a lake can lead to large shifts in the composition of the lake's community. Other commonly cited examples of ecological tipping points include sudden shifts in species dominance or population collapse [
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C8">8</a>,
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C9">9</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, in a social context, 
   <span class="italic">social tipping points</span> occur when small changes to the physical or social environment result in qualitative changes to group behaviour or dynamics [
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C10">10</a>]. In animal societies, tipping points could be used to explain social transitions such as the onset of collective movements, shifts in group behaviour from calm to agitated states, the emergence and disappearance of wars between neighbouring societies, the formation or disbandment of cooperation, or the diffusion of new innovations. For instance, African desert locusts rapidly shift between their little-observed solitary state to a swarming plague phenotype. The transition between these states is density-mediated and catalysed by positive feedback loops between population density, individual activity level, and serotonin-mediated gregariousness [
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C11">11</a>–
   <a rid="RSPB20181282C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20181282C13">13</a>]. Thus, small changes in population density can cause large and abrupt changes in both individual state and group dynamics in these locusts.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
