<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-ijerph-16-02970" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. The Study Area</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study focused on southern African countries, namely Angola, Botswana, Comoros, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC), Lesotho, Madagascar, Mauritius, Malawi, Mozambique, Namibia, Seychelles, South Africa, Swaziland, Tanzania, Zambia and Zimbabwe (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f001" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f001">Figure 1</a>). The same 16 countries form an economic regional bloc known as the Southern African Development Community (SADC). Agriculture is the main source of livelihoods for the generally rural population, contributing about 17% to regional GDP (increasing to above 28% when middle income countries are excluded [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02970">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-02970">31</a>]. The SADC treaty, the overarching regional policy framework that aims to achieve economic development, peace and security, alleviate poverty and improve the livelihoods of the people, through regional integration [
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-02970">32</a>]. To strengthen its agrarian economy, the region intends to increase agricultural production by increasing the irrigated area. Increasing agricultural production is envisaged to result in surplus yields that households of comparative advantage are able to supply regions of less potential, thereby ensuring food security and improving livelihoods. In this regard the region intends to double the irrigated area from 3.5% to 7% by 2025 [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-02970">31</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although irrigation potential in southern Africa is very high, agriculture remains rainfed (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f001" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f001">Figure 1</a>). Land with irrigation potential is about 20 million ha, yet only 3.9 million ha is equipped for irrigation, accounting for approximately 6.6% of the total cultivated area [
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-02970">18</a>,
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02970">33</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f001" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f001">Figure 1</a> also shows the distribution of agricultural systems in the region. The vision to increase the irrigated area targets the smallholder farming sector because of its importance in food security, but at the same time its high vulnerability to climate variability and change. Despite the huge agriculture potential and a big domestic market for agricultural products, poverty levels remain high, particularly rural areas [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02970">5</a>]. Regional population stands at 342 million, of which 70% live in rural areas [
  <a rid="B34-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-16-02970">34</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
