<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-16-02970" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. The Methodological Framework</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Managing water, energy, and food resources as an interconnected system, and eliminating the traditional silo-based planning, improves sustainable development through research-based evidence [
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-02970">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-02970">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-02970">37</a>]. The basis of the WEF nexus approach to resource management lies in identifying and justifying the interactions at the multiple interfaces of resource systems, while holistically assessing the impact of specific contexts or interventions from the environmental, financial, and socio-cultural perspectives [
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-02970">38</a>]. It is from this systems perspective that 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a> is presented as a methodological framework, focusing on the improvement of rural livelihoods and health in the advent of climate variability and change. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a> represents the components of the WEF nexus analytical livelihoods framework (ALF), as viewed from a systems thinking perspective. The WEF nexus ALF is adapted from the work done by McMichael et al., (2006), which depicts the pathways by which climate change can affect population health. Several climatic-environmental manifestations of climate change are shown, which altogether portray an increase in complexity of causal processes having environmental consequences and, therefore, the likelihood that health effects will be exacerbated or protracted. In order to elicit the linkages among the causes and the effects of climate, we converted the McMichael’s schematic summary (see 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-16-02970" href="#app1-ijerph-16-02970">Supplementary Material, Figure S1</a>) of the main pathways by which climate change affects population health in to a causal loop diagram (CLD) shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a>. The systems approach integrates water, food, and energy aspects by mapping key elements of the subsystems and visualising their interdependencies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim is to build livelihoods resilience through the WEF nexus by considering the linkages between WEF resources and causal mechanisms [
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-02970">39</a>]. Improving livelihoods and social equality requires inclusive participation by all in decision making through consultation [
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-02970">40</a>]. Faced with the realities of climate change, and how they are impacting mainly the rural poor, there have been loud calls to reduce greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions, which is the major cause of accelerated climate change [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-16-02970">41</a>,
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-16-02970">42</a>]. For example, the Paris Climate Agreement brings the globe into a common cause of undertaking ambitious efforts to combat climate change and adapt to its effects, by keeping a global temperature rise this century well below 2 °C above pre-industrial levels, and to assist developing countries to achieve climate change adaptation [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-02970">43</a>,
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-16-02970">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first part of the study relates to the impacts of climate change on WEF resources and proposes mitigation strategies through the WEF nexus ALF. We identify that, as people in rural areas generally depend on natural systems for their livelihoods, availability and accessibility to land and other natural resources are crucial for their survival. Then, secondly, the study demonstrates how the WEF nexus can be used as a decision support tool in addressing the pertinent issues, mainly transforming livelihoods and sustaining the environment. The premise is that resilience and adaptation must be decoupled from extensive use and depletion of natural resources and environmental damage, and promote sustainable means of production, investment, and consumption, along with enhanced resource efficiency and the reduction of waste, food losses, and pollution [
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-16-02970">45</a>]. Adaptation through the WEF nexus ensures that vulnerable and marginalised populations are empowered through the removal of barriers that hinder balanced resource sharing and inclusive economic development [
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02970">6</a>]. Specific challenges brought about by climate variability and change, such as extreme weather events, resource depletion, among others (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a>) are addressed by strengthening resilience at the local and community level. Thus, the first and second parts of the methodological framework (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a>) emphasise both mitigation and adaptation. Mitigation is tackling the root cause of climate change to alleviate further damage to the atmosphere, and adaptation is dealing with the impact of climate change, such as extreme weather events and depletion of resources [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-02970">46</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third part addresses health effects of climate changes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a>), and applies the WEF nexus analytical livelihoods framework to understand the causes and effects on human well-being, and to develop guidelines to alleviate health effects brought about by climate change. Environmental sustainability and human well-being are linked to the conservation of nature and natural resources and the preservation of biodiversity and ecosystems services and the WEF nexus plays an important role of guiding decision making [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-16-02970">47</a>,
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-02970">48</a>]. Sustainable use and management of natural resources through the WEF nexus ensures water, energy and food security, equitable supply of public goods and services and inclusive development [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02970">5</a>]. Thus, sustainable livelihoods transformation cannot be separated from climate change adaptation and the WEF nexus based research, as the approach is a “fitting tool” in transforming livelihoods, providing evidence to policy and decision-making in adaptation strategies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CLD shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f002">Figure 2</a> explains the WEF nexus analytical livelihoods framework and provides an understanding of the complex interrelationships among resources for livelihoods transformation, human health and well-being. The CLD provides a visual representation of multiple, interdependent effects of climate change and human actions on WEF resources. The Vensim PLE x32 software (
  <span xlink:href="www.ventanasystems.com" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ventanasystems.com</span>) was used to develop the CLD for the WEF analytical livelihoods framework. The CLD is a qualitative representation of the interlinkages between resources utilisation and management and their effects on livelihoods in the advent of climate variability and change. The arrows show the influence of one variable on another (a change in the cause leads to a change in the effect). The polarity of the arrows indicates the factual relationship between any two nodes, which illustrate the causal link. The interplay between balancing and reinforcing loops gives rise to a realistic multi-loop system that explains the behaviour of the WEF model and the nexus impact over time. The reinforcing loop, R1, indicates the pathway through which mitigation measures lead to adaptation, with reduced anthropogenic GHG emissions in an amplified manner between resource insecurities and climate change. R1 is the ultimate loop that the WEF nexus research has to achieve. One of the means to achieve this aim is through the ability to assess the nexus interactions (evidence-based interventions) with amplifying effects for adaptation as in R2, which is the aim of this study. Other vicious bottlenecks in the system include R3 (the vicious reinforcing interrelationship between water, energy, and food insecurities), R4 (environmental behavioural patterns that contribute to climate change) and R5 (heightened disease transmissibility pathways).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CLD justifies the context of complexity of causal mechanisms within which climate change occurs and the resulting causal effects it generates on the WEF resources, livelihoods, and health. It sets the context for considering the indicators listed in 
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02970-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02970-t001">Table 1</a> for the pairwise comparison.
 </p>
</sec>
