<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-16-02970" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. WEF Nexus Analytical Livelihoods Framework</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation strategies are wide-ranging in nature, and can be conceptualised broadly along a continuum, varying from interventions that are exclusively designed to mitigate the impacts associated with a changing climate, to initiatives aimed at addressing the wider underlying drivers of vulnerability and adaptive capacity [
  <a rid="B73-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-ijerph-16-02970">73</a>]. Adaptation depends on the adaptive capacity of a household or community, which is generally lacking in most rural communities of southern Africa [
  <a rid="B62-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijerph-16-02970">62</a>,
  <a rid="B74-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-16-02970">74</a>]. Adaptive capacity is the ability of a system to adjust to climate change and be able to accommodate shock or stress, or to expand the scope of variability with which it can cope [
  <a rid="B73-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-ijerph-16-02970">73</a>]. The adjustments include controlling potential damage, taking advantage of opportunities, coping with consequences, as well as expanding coping range, and reducing vulnerability [
  <a rid="B73-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-ijerph-16-02970">73</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change adaptation refers to changes in processes, practices, or structures to offset potential damages, or to take advantage of opportunities associated with changes in the climate [
  <a rid="B75-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-16-02970">75</a>]. It encompasses actions that minimise the vulnerability of households, communities, and regions to climate change. Although adaptation can either be spontaneous or planned action, its success is determined by institutional and analytical frameworks that oversee and assess the level of vulnerability and the adaptive capacity [
  <a rid="B73-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-ijerph-16-02970">73</a>]. The WEF nexus analytical livelihoods framework ensures an integrated management of resources, public services, and, at the same time considering synergies and trade-offs at all scales [
  <a rid="B76-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76-ijerph-16-02970">76</a>]. The transformation of rural livelihoods and the sustainability of adaptation strategies is underpinned by the understanding of the role of the WEF nexus in framing effective policies and institutions. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f004" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f004">Figure 4</a> represents a WEF nexus adaptation framework for assessing, monitoring and improving resource utilisation and management to ensure sustainable livelihoods transformation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first component of the framework (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f004" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f004">Figure 4</a>) depicts the WEF nexus as a tool to enhance climate change adaptation and resilience for sustainable livelihoods and the environment [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-16-02970">47</a>]. It illustrates the intricacies in the interlinkages among the WEF nexus sectors. These envisaged outcomes are achieved through the key adaptation strategies of governance (policies and plans), social equity (accelerating access for all), environmental sustainability (investing to sustain ecosystem services), and economic efficiency (increasing resource efficiency), as shown in the second component [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02970">1</a>]. These four key adaptation components form the basis to meet sustainable targets of reducing poverty and building resilience, which result in the security of resources, and sustainable development. The targets define sustainability indicators (last component of the framework) that assess and monitor resource planning and management, and to ensure equitable resource distribution and inclusive development. WEF nexus sustainability indicators are measurable parameters that indicate the performance of resource development, and monitor how the development is impacting on livelihoods or vice-versa [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-02970">14</a>]. The essence of the indicators is to connect statements of intent (objectives) and measurable aspects of natural and human systems. The four components of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02970-f004" href="#ijerph-16-02970-f004">Figure 4</a> are supported and underpinned by an enabling environment that oversees the WEF nexus implementation [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02970" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02970">1</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
