<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predictive models</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mechanistic model, AFLA-maize
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>, was applied to predict aflatoxin contamination in maize during the growing season, at the European level. Briefly, the mechanistic model is based on the infection cycle of 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> in maize, it is weather-driven and predictions are given on a daily basis from silk emergence to harvest. Hourly data of air temperature, relative humidity and rain were used as model data input, and they served as input to estimate crop phenology (in the crop phenology module) and fungal activity (in AFLA-maize). The crop phenology module used regression equations to estimate the shift in crop development in the future climate. Besides the climate data, it used databases with information on the cultivation of maize as well as the related temperature requirements, per grid, in Europe. Temperature requirements (JRC data) related to Degree Day (DD, the summation of daily temperature) needed to reach the cropping stages of silk emergence, the time of crop susceptibility to 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> infection, and harvest time were defined. Model output is the aflatoxin index (AFI), which results from the summation of daily outputs. The index has been associated to a probability of overcoming the threshold of 5 μg of toxin per kg of kernels at harvest applying a logistic equation between AFI and six years of field data of aflatoxin content in maize collected in Italy.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change data are generated on a daily scale; therefore, the model AFLA-maize was adapted accordingly. A new logistic regression was developed to associate AFI, based on daily climate data, to aflatoxin contamination in the field, using the same six-year data as previously mentioned, and AFI &gt; 95 was the resulting threshold value associated to the 50% probability of contamination above 5 μg of aflatoxin per kg of kernels.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity analysis was applied. Input data for AFLA-maize were manipulated; Temperature was changed from −6 °C to +6 °C, Relative Humidity and Number of rainy days from −30% to +30% and following AFI changes determined (See 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">supplementary material</a> for details).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Accuracy of model prediction changing data input was estimated based on the correlation coefficient (R
  <span class="sup">2</span>) using bootstrap samples (10000 iterations
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>). Air temperature, relative humidity and rainy days were used as as regressors in a Linear Regression Model to reconstruct the variability of AFI simulated for the present climate scenario and to estimate uncertainty associated with AFLA-maize model when extrapolated to climate change scenarios. Eight years were selected, characterized by the largest variations compared to year representing the mean values (See 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">supplementary material</a> for details).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A modified version of AFLA-maize, called AFLA-wheat, was used for predictions in wheat. Starting point of simulation in the crop phenology module was 1 January, and temperature requirements related to DD needed to reach the cropping stages, like flowering and harvest time were defined. In this case, with very limited field data on aflatoxin contamination in wheat, no probability of overcoming the threshold could be associated to the AFI value obtained. Therefore, comparing the legal limit for aflatoxin B
  <sub>1</sub> in maize and wheat (5 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> 2 μg of aflatoxin per kg of kernels), AFI &gt; 38 was arbitrary associated to the 50% probability of contamination above the threshold.
 </p>
</sec>
