<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predictive models and climate change data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AFLA-maize, a mechanistic model, was applied to predict 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> growth and aflatoxin production in maize, using weather data as input
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. AFLA-maize was also linked to a crop phenology prediction module, based on temperature sums, with a focus on the crucial stages of flowering and ripening, or date of harvest. Two climate change scenarios, +2 °C and +5 °C above pre-industrial levels, which take into account whether or not mitigation strategies for climate change are applied, in addition to the present (baseline) scenario, were considered.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each scenario, 100 years of simulated daily weather data (minimum and maximum temperatures, rainfall and solar radiation) were obtained for each of the 2254 georeferenced (central) grid points, with grids spaced 50 × 50 km, over the European domain. These data were used as input for running both the crop phenology model and the AFLA-maize model. Output of the crop phenology model, i.e. predicted flowering and harvest dates, was also used as input for AFLA-maize. The final output included aflatoxin hazard indexes (AFI) for each of the mentioned grid point (2254 points) throughout Europe, per simulation run (100 years) and scenario (present, + 2 °C and +5 °C climate change scenarios ; see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">supplementary material for details</a>). AFI = 0 when the host crop: i) cannot be grown in the grid point due to unsuitable meteorological conditions, or ii) its susceptibility to 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> never occur or never match. When AFI &gt; 0, fungus-host interactions are possible as well as the production of aflatoxins. Referring to the current legal limits in Europe (Commission Regulations 574/2011 and 1881/2006 with amendments), the threshold of 5 μg of aflatoxin per kg of raw maize kernels was considered consistent with AFI ≥ 95.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data on 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span>-wheat interactions and predictive models were not available from the literature. Therefore, AFLA-wheat, a modified version of the AFLA-maize model, was developed and run using the same meteorological input data as with the AFLA-maize model (See 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">supplementary material</a> for details). An AFI threshold for high probability of wheat contamination was not available, due to the lack of data on grain contamination. Therefore, an AFI ≥ 38 was considered to coincide with the legal limit for aflatoxin B
  <sub>1</sub> in wheat of 2 μg of aflatoxin per kg of raw grains (Commission Regulation 1881/ 2006 and amendments).
 </p>
</sec>
