<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extended periods of anomalously warm ocean temperatures can have major impacts on marine biodiversity and ecosystems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> and the economics of regional fisheries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Despite a growing appreciation of their importance, scientific understanding of marine heatwaves (MHWs) is in its infancy compared to that of atmospheric heatwaves. In particular, there is limited understanding of the physical processes that give rise to MHWs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, and how large-scale climate variability modulates the likelihood and severity of these events.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent years, a number of prominent MHWs have been reported with devastating changes to marine ecosystems around the globe. These include MHW events in the northwest Atlantic in 2012
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, northeast Pacific Ocean from 2013–2016
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, Tasman Sea in 2015/16
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, and waters around tropical Australia in 2015/16
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. On a global scale, these extreme temperature events have increased in frequency
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, a trend projected to continue throughout the twenty-first century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, and hence there is a pressing need to understand their physical drivers.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The focus of this study was to develop and apply a consistent framework for understanding how regional MHW events relate to different modes of climate variability and the physical conditions causing waters to warm above a threshold. This framework aimed to inform the predictability of MHW events and, on a global scale, our capability to detect and understand how MHWs emerge. A useful lens for understanding the formation, maintenance, and decay of MHWs is the upper ocean mixed layer heat budget, which includes the local processes responsible for changes in surface ocean temperatures. For MHW events, the dominant contributions to the temperature tendency within the mixed layer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> are given by
  <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">1</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\frac{{\partial T}}{{\partial t}} = - \frac{1}{H}\mathop {\smallint }\limits_{ - H}^0 \left( {{\mathbf{u}} \cdot \nabla _hT} \right)dz + \frac{Q}{{\rho C_pH}} + {\mathrm{residual}}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M2" class="math">
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">∂</span>
       <span class="mi">T</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">∂</span>
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mo">-</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">1</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">H</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div accent="false" accentunder="false" class="munderover">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">∫</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">-</span>
       <span class="mi">H</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">0</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="bold" class="mi">u</span>
       <span class="mo">⋅</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">∇</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">h</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mi">T</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mi">d</span>
     <span class="mi">z</span>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">Q</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">ρ</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">C</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">p</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mi">H</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">residual</span>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10206_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>where the first term on the right hand side (RHS) is the horizontal advection (ocean advective fluxes) owing to the vertical integral of the product between the depth-dependent horizontal velocity vector 
  <span class="bold">u</span> and the horizontal gradient of the mixed layer temperature 
  <span class="italic">T</span>, the second term is the contribution from the net air-sea heat flux 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>, where 
  <span class="italic">ρ</span> is the average seawater density, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">p</span>
  </sub> is the specific heat capacity of seawater (4000 J kg
  <span class="sup">−1</span> °C
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), 
  <span class="italic">H</span> is the mixed layer depth, and the residual third term includes horizontal eddy heat fluxes and the heat flux at the bottom of the mixed layer owing to radiative heat loss, vertical diffusion, entrainment, and vertical advection. To generate MHWs, the physical processes on the RHS of Equation (
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>) have to contribute a sufficiently large net positive temperature tendency to increase the surface ocean temperature over a threshold
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Oceanic advective fluxes include unusually intense poleward flow associated with the transport of warmer waters, enhanced heat advection by boundary currents, or reduced turbulent mixing. Favourable air-sea heat fluxes for MHWs include contributions from anomalous net downward surface radiation characteristics of reduced cloud cover, and from convective air-sea heat flux and suppressed latent heat loss from anomalously weak surface winds. While Equation (
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>) explicitly describes temperature variations that extend throughout the mixed layer, MHWs may extend deeper. The expression of surface intensified MHWs may also depend on the state of the subsurface ocean, such as shoaling of the mixed layer base
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the majority of research conducted to date, and in our global analysis here, MHWs have been identified and characterized based on sea surface temperature (SST). This focus reflects the relative scarcity of subsurface ocean data, and the reported ecological impacts that are prevalent in the upper ocean where biological productivity is greatest. Key mechanisms that drive temperature changes in the mixed layer include local internal variability (e.g. eddy instabilities) or large-scale modes of climate variability that act to modulate the local conditions—either from local sources, for example, extreme ocean-atmosphere coupled feedbacks in the eastern equatorial Pacific during extreme El Niño-Southern Oscillation (ENSO) events, or remote sources via teleconnection mechanisms, for example, the propagation of planetary waves in the atmosphere (that give rise to distant changes in the surface winds, cloud cover, etc.) or ocean (that can change the depth of the thermocline and drive remote circulation changes).</p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We established an analytical framework to examine the influence of these drivers on MHWs regionally. Our first goal was to identify regions where robust statistically significant relationships exist between surface signatures of MHW occurrence and large-scale climate modes. We recognize and caution that significant statistical relationships do not necessarily indicate causal links. However, these analyses are indicative of potentially important connections that can provide clear pointers to potential predictability. Importantly, the relationships we have found and will highlight in the results between large-scale climate modes and MHW occurrences do not simply mirror those between climate modes and SST anomalies (SSTA) more generally.</p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our second goal was to perform a comprehensive and systematic global synthesis of the existing peer-reviewed literature on historical MHWs (from 1950 to February 2016) that have occurred in oceanographically and/or climatically distinct regions. We conducted a confidence assessment of their characteristic drivers and processes to determine: the processes in the mixed layer temperature budget (RHS of Equation 
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>) important for MHW formation; climatological systems and their configurations (e.g. high/low pressure systems, jet stream location), and teleconnection processes (e.g. atmospheric or oceanic Kelvin and Rossby waves), that either force or modulate the temperature budget terms; and large-scale modes of climate variability that have played a role in modulating individual identified MHWs, either locally or via teleconnections.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our third goal was to revisit and analyze these reported events since 1982 by producing consistent measurements of the key MHW characteristics based on daily satellite SST data. These characteristics were estimated based on a consistent MHW definition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, which allows for comparability since the MHWs identified in our literature search have been reported using a diverse set of criteria.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study concludes that the consideration of extremes in an ocean mixed layer temperature tendency budget framework provides a useful lens for understanding the formation, maintenance, and decay of surface MHWs locally. Furthermore, remote influences (e.g. climate modes), and ocean/atmosphere teleconnection processes, appear to be important modulators for the enhancement or suppression of MHW occurrences and thus their likelihoods. We expect these findings to be beneficial to studies on the potential predictability of MHWs and provide future direction for prediction studies.</p>
</sec>
