<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Middle and high latitudes</div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Middle and high latitude ocean regions are considered poleward of 30 degrees latitude where the seasonal variability is much higher compared to the tropics. MHWs here have been associated with shifts in warm ocean currents
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, mesoscale eddy activity, and atmosphere-ocean interactions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. MHWs have also been attributed to anomalous reductions in wind speed and wintertime surface cooling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, shifts in the jet stream position
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> and the weakening of cold water currents and Ekman pumping
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, ENSO teleconnections favour the seasonal persistence of large-scale weather patterns, such as high-pressure ridge systems that persist for multiple weeks, conducive to anomalous ocean warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine heatwaves in the Mediterranean Sea have been associated with large-scale atmospheric anomalies through increased heat flux and reduced wind speed that passively elevate SST well above their normal range
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Anomalous atmospheric circulation played a key role in the development of the 2012 northwest Atlantic marine heatwave
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. The northward displacement of the jet stream can stabilize atmospheric blocking patterns of high pressure that reduce surface wind speeds and thereby inhibit ocean mixing, as well as increase surface air temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Large-scale atmospheric forcing can simultaneously warm large regions of surface water and cause large-scale MHWs. Blocking high pressure weather systems that develop over the Gulf of Alaska, in combination with remote tropical Pacific teleconnections, can cause sudden changes in oceanographic conditions leading to MHWs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. In the Bering Sea, large-scale atmospheric anomalies shift wind-driven oceanic frontal zones, increase the upper ocean stratification, and enhance heat flux into the ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. Reduced surface heat loss and sluggish circulation from weakened winds drive MHWs in the northeast Pacific
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. Similarly, the South Pacific experiences MHWs from atmospheric pressure anomalies associated with ENSO that divert warm air poleward, weaken wind speeds, and slow the normal northward advection of cold water
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MHWs at the six middle and high latitude regions identified here all have a common driver. Large-scale atmospheric pressure anomalies precede anomalous ocean warming and are often triggered by remote changes in SST. Stalled ridges of atmospheric high-pressure systems cause clear skies, warm air, and reduced wind speeds. These conditions make rapid warming in the upper ocean possible, coupled with increase thermal stratification due to reduced vertical mixing. In the North Pacific, we identify multiple drivers that can enhance the occurrence of MHWs, including El Niño and the positive PDO and IPO phases (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). El Niño mainly influences MHWs in the South Pacific case-study region (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>). The northwest Atlantic MHWs are associated with the negative NAO phase (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>), while the Mediterranean Sea is dominated by the positive DMI (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
