<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results suggest that the tropics play a prominent role in the recent rise of global N pollution despite receiving much lower amounts of anthropogenic Nr inputs than the extratropics. This result arises due to the prevalence of tropical basins undergoing intensive LULCC since the 20th century, combined with enhanced land N sequestration in many extratropical basins recovering from past LULCC, which has slowed increases in N pollution from these regions. These results are found to be robust to the different BNF settings, fertilizer inputs, LULCC scenarios, partitioning of land N outputs into pollution, and to the exclusion of CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As mentioned previously, the global transition of land from a net N source to sink in the late 1940s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>) is consistent with a similar transition in terrestrial C storage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Our results are also consistent with published estimates of C balance in various tropical systems (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). Tropical land as a whole being nearly N neutral over the late 20th century (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) aligns with filtered inverse models against an additional observational constraint, suggesting nearly neutral net C fluxes from tropical land
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. Many plot measurements in Amazonian intact forests demonstrated long-term increases in the aboveground biomass density since 1983 (e.g., Brienen and colleagues
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>), and a similar pattern during 1983–2005 was captured in our simulation (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). For the same period (1983–2005), however, our simulation suggests a net C source from the whole tropical forests (including both intact and disturbed forests), in a manner consistent with a recent satellite-data-based study of Baccini and colleagues
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> for 2004–2014 (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). These patterns have been attributed to a decline in forest area and forest disturbance across the tropics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Parana River Basin, large increases in land N outputs (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7c</a>) are only partially explained by increases in land Nr inputs, including agricultural BNF and fertilizer applications (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a</a>), leading to a Baccini-like decline in land N storage (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7e</a>). It is the prevalence of the Parana-type basins across the tropics (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>) that underlies the idea that increasing tropical N outputs derive from release of legacy land N storage and recent accelerating agricultural land use, relative to the largest contribution of fertilizer inputs to increasing extratropical N outputs (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b, d</a>). In contrast, agricultural development is not nearly as widespread in the Amazon River Basin (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b, d</a>), leading to a more Brienen-like response at the basin scale, with accumulation of land N storage (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7f</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results, those of Brienen and colleagues
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>, and other bottom-up estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> are indicative of enhanced growth and C demand in intact forests, hypothesized to result from CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. In LM3-TAN, BNF responds dynamically to enhanced C demand
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>, and thus increases particularly in Amazonian non-agricultural lands including large intact forests (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b</a>). Although this result is plausible, it should be noted that large uncertainty remains in these simulations with little empirical evidence for BNF in intact forests increasing with CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization. While our conclusions concerning the contribution of tropical systems to global N pollution is insensitive to this response, further observational work and investigation with multi-model ensembles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span> could help resolve this uncertainty.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important factor that is not resolved in our model is the potential role of phosphorous (P) in limiting tropical production. We would expect that BNF in response to CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization is particularly restricted in P-limited tropical intact forests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. We would not expect, however, that the BNF response is restricted in mostly N-limited tropical regrowing and temperate forests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span> or agricultural lands. Like the no-CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization case, overall N outputs would be ultimately most strongly shaped by accelerating LULCC. That is, despite the restricted BNF in tropical intact forests, overall tropical N outputs would be only modestly reduced, as the output fluxes would be supplied through release of legacy land N storage. Indeed, the P-limited tropics combined with enhanced land N sequestration in the N-limited and CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilized extratropics would likely accentuate the prominence of the tropics as a source of global N pollution.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lower tropical land capacity to sequester Nr inputs will challenge efforts to control atmospheric and oceanic pollution in tropical regions, and control tropical contributions to global N pollution. Tropical pollutant loadings to the ocean and atmosphere are expected to further grow with dramatic increases in Nr inputs and LULCC in tropical regions over the next few decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. The resulting high N fluxes will exacerbate hypoxia and phytoplankton blooms in tropical coastal waters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span> and amplify nitrous oxide emissions from tropical land
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. It is thus critical that tropical Nr inputs, LULCC, and legacy N are thoroughly considered in future coastal eutrophication and greenhouse gas emission policies and mitigation strategies.
 </p>
</sec>
