<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Today's scientists are faced with the task of forecasting how climate change will affect species distributions and species assemblages. A pressing challenge is to develop integrated modelling frameworks that account for all aspects of vulnerability: exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Directly accounting for climate-driven changes in survival, persistence, and fitness (sensitivity) can provide improved forecasts of extinction risk [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], yet model predictions rarely account for the demographic and physiological sensitivities of species to prevailing climates. Biological processes underlying adaptation of a species to its environment remain poorly understood. Rare attempts to include evolutionary responses directly in climate-biodiversity models have shown that predictions of vulnerability can be affected by adaptive capacity [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Mesocosm experiments are key to meeting this shortfall, providing valuable information on aspects of climate change ecology (e.g., the impact of extreme events on species survival, climate as a driver of phenotypic changes) that cannot be readily assembled from other approaches [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Establishing multigenerational mesocosm experiments systematically, using taxa representing a diversity of ecological and evolutionary milieu, and integrating observed demographic and physiological responses into simulation models is likely to strengthen confidence in climate-impact science and improve vulnerability assessments (
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.g001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. This will be particularly so for short-lived taxa that are passively dispersed or with short active dispersal requirements. Developing mesocosm experiments for long-lived, wide-ranging species will be much less feasible.
</p>
