<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With this background, we propose the hypothesis that 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Candida auris</named-content> is the first example of a new pathogenic fungus emerging from human-induced global warming. We posit that prior to its recognition as a human pathogen, 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> was an environmental fungus. The fact that 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> fails to grow anaerobically, along with the fact that it is typically detected on cooler skin sites but not in the gut, supports the notion that 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> was an environmental fungus, until recently. Several factors, not necessarily mutually exclusive, may have been operative as to why 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> emerged in the last decade. For example, as 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> constitutively overexpresses HSP 90, this may account for its multidrug resistance, virulence, thermal tolerance, and osmotic-stress tolerance (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Thus, 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> might have previously existed as a plant saprophyte in specialized ecosystems, such as wetlands. As a first step, its emergence might have been linked to global warming (including climatic oscillations) effects on wetlands (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), and its enrichment in that ecological niche was the result of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content>’s combined thermal tolerance and salinity tolerance. Interestingly, areas where 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> was first recognized overlap, at least in part, the impacted wetland ecosystems (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Of interest, 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. albicans</named-content> can be a part of a wetland ecosystem (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), and although many of the virulence determinants in the 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> genome have not been characterized, it is theoretically possible that human-pathogenic 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. have passed some virulence traits to previously nonpathogenic 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> strains through plasmid DNA transfer (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), in the backdrop of changing ecological niches. Alternatively, the effect of higher UV radiation in combination with global warming (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) might have contributed to mutagenic events that resulted in the suddenly increased fitness of a saprobe for survival in a host, via melanin- or non-melanin-dependent processes (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content>’s jump from an environmental fungus to a fungus capable of transmission to, and pathogenic for, humans might have had an intermediate host, specifically an avian host, as fungi that can grow at 40 or 42°C can infect avian fauna. Of note, sea birds may serve as reservoirs for indirect transmission of drug-resistant 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species, such as 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. glabrata</named-content>, to humans (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The uncanny ability of 
 <italic>C auris</italic> to adapt to specific niches, first in the environment and then in an avian host, might have led as a third step to its ultimate establishment as a human pathogen through genetic and epigenetic switches (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).
</p>
