<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bifurcation Diagram of the Frozen-in System and Parameter Drift Scenarios</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When investigating systems with a parameter drift, it is worth looking at first the long-term dynamics depending on the parameter without the intrinsic drift. This results in a classical bifurcation diagram for the frozen-in system. Here we are particularly interested in systems which are periodically forced. This forcing with a certain period 
  <span class="italic">T</span> would correspond to the seasonal variability of the climate or of certain environmental drivers over the period of one year, like e.g. temperature for a natural or societal system, or periodic energy input into a mechanical system. The strength of the forcing would be the main control parameter 
  <span class="italic">C</span> to be varied. A typical bifurcation diagram for such a system is presented in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>. It shows various stable long-term dynamics, usually called attractors (
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <span class="sup">*</span> represents one of the state space variables on them), which in general could be regular or chaotic, depending on the fixed control parameter 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. When the system possesses a periodic or seasonal forcing it is convenient to plot the state of the system as a stroboscopic map, or Poincaré section, i.e. always at the same time instant in each period of the forcing. This corresponds to measuring the time in units of the period 
  <span class="italic">T</span> of the forcing. For the paradigmatic system of a periodically forced pendulum studied here as an example (cf. Supplemental Discussion 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">I</a> for a detailed description) only periodic and chaotic attractors exist. While chaotic dynamics corresponds to the black areas filled irregularly with points in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>., the different periodic motions appear as curves. Out of these, swinging motion about the equilibrium of a resting pendulum (cyan) as well as clockwise and counter clockwise rotations (red and blue) are discerned. The latter are born (along with their unstable counterparts) in a saddle-node bifurcation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">b</span>
  </sub> = 0.2, and exist throughout the 
  <span class="italic">C</span>-range shown except for chaotic regimes. Small, multi-piece attractors are also visible in short parameter intervals.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Bifurcation diagram of a typical nonlinear system with frozen-in control parameter 
     <span class="italic">C</span>: the 
     <span class="italic">x</span>-coordinates of the long-term attractors are shown on a stroboscopic map. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Schematic diagram of the parameter drift scenario used in the paper. The scenario covers a control parameter interval 
     <span class="italic">I</span> = [
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>−</sub>, 
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>+</sub>] corresponding to a control parameter change Δ
     <span class="italic">C</span> = 
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>+</sub> − 
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>−</sub>. The limiting 
     <span class="italic">C</span> values of the scenarios are marked by vertical dashed-dotted lines in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>). The continuous-time attractors belonging to these values are given in the insets. The control parameter intervals 
     <span class="italic">I</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">n</span>
     </sub>, 
     <span class="italic">n</span> = 1, …, 4 investigated in the main text are marked by line segments along the frame of the bifurcation diagram.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44863_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e495" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insets show the continuous-time attractors in state space (
  <span class="italic">x</span>, 
  <span class="italic">y</span>) associated with a few selected values of the control parameter 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. These will serve as limiting values of the parameter drift scenarios. The stroboscopic view of these attractors presented in the bifurcation diagram is obtained by cutting through these curves with a line. The strikingly different geometrical appearance of these attractors implies qualitatively different long-term dynamics in the frozen-in system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bifurcation diagram suggests a rather limited presence of chaos in the dynamics. However, we should emphasize that bifurcation diagrams are known to not represent an important aspect of the dynamics, namely transients. In typical nonlinear systems, transients can be chaotic, and their existence due to an underlying unstable chaotic set, called a chaotic saddle
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, might extend over a considerable range of the control parameter.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let us now consider the scenario of a parameter drift, i.e. a case when the control parameter becomes time-dependent following a known function 
  <span class="italic">C</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>). One possibility would be that the control parameter starts at some initial value 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub>, changes initially rather weakly, then undergoes a rapid change in some time interval before ending at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> &gt; 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. We consider here a simpler case, a piece-wise linear parameter drift involving a ramp, i.e., a linear increase of size Δ
  <span class="italic">C</span> = 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub>, starting always at time 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 0 and ending at the ramping time 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub>. The rate 
  <span class="italic">r</span> of the parameter drift in the time interval 0 &lt; 
  <span class="italic">t</span> &lt; 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub> is thus given by
  <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">1</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$r=\frac{{\rm{\Delta }}C}{{t}_{r}}.$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
     <span class="mi">r</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
       <span class="mi">C</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">r</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">.</span>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44863_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Such ramping scenarios are rather common in the climate literature (see e.g.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>), and have been used to study critical transitions and regime shifts
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, also describing parameter detuning in physical and dynamical systems (see e.g.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Typically, our investigations start at some initial time 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>−</sub> ≤ 0, with the initial 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> value on a plateau and end at time 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>+</sub> &gt; 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub> on a higher plateau of value 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> (cf. Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a> for a schematic diagram). The parameter intervals 
  <span class="italic">I</span> used in the paper are marked by line segments below and above the frame of Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The full scenario is determined by 5 parameters: 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>−</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>+</sub>. The infinite past and infinite future is approximated by the conditions |
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>−</sub>|, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>+</sub> ≫ 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub>. Thanks to the plateaus, where the dynamics takes place with frozen-in parameters, the asymptotic attractors at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> can be determined as usual. In order to ensure a time scale that is comparable to those of the frozen-in dynamics (which are in the range[1, 10]), we will focus on the range 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub> &lt; 40.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main effect of the parameter drift is that states initially close to the attractor at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> (which would indeed converge to this attractor without ramping (Δ
  <span class="italic">C</span> = 0)) might in fact converge to a completely different attractor (exemplified by the insets in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). We refer to this qualitative change in the asymptotic behavior as a tipping transition.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to find a quantitative measure for the probability of possible tipping transitions, we are interested in the 
  <span class="italic">scenario-dependent</span> changes of the basins of different attractors. The basin of attraction of a particular attractor is the set of initial conditions, distributed uniformly over the state space, which converges to it. Here, we will determine the basins of the attractors at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>+</sub> for initial conditions taken at an initial time 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>−</sub> and control parameter value 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub>. The result will depend not only on the interval 
  <span class="italic">I</span> of the parameter drift, but also on the other, temporal parameters of the scenario. It is worth noting that the special case of ramping time 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub> = 0, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>−</sub> = 0, corresponds, for large 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>+</sub>, to the basin of attraction for the frozen-in system with 
  <span class="italic">C</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) = 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub>.
 </p>
</sec>
