<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tippings when Extended Chaotic Attractors are Involved</div>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the scenario ends at a 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> belonging to a single extended chaotic attractor (interval 
  <span class="italic">I</span>
  <sub>3</sub> in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>), a global type of tipping occurs. Here the end state is not a limit cycle represented by a few points in the stroboscopic map, but rather an extended chaotic attractor of fractal structure, possible on 
  <span class="italic">intervals</span> in the bifurcation diagram of Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>, or a coil as in the 4th inset there. We call this transition 
  <span class="italic">tipping into a chaotic attractor</span>. In this case, all initial conditions lead to an unpredictable motion. It is worth emphasizing that these features hold for 
  <span class="italic">all scenarios</span> starting at any 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> &gt; 0 with any 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>−</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub>, provided 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>+</sub> is sufficiently large. Since the chaotic attractor at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> is a single globally stable attractor for our system, the tipping probability into this attractor is 
  <span class="italic">unity</span> starting from 
  <span class="italic">any</span> attractor that may exist at 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, let us consider a final parameter value 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub> lying beyond the extended chaotic attractor where again only the two rotating motions are attracting. Choosing for simplicity a low value of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> = 0.1 where a single attractor exists (see interval 
  <span class="italic">I</span>
  <sub>4</sub> in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>), one finds the basin structure shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8a,b</a>. We see that in the near vicinity of any colour there is a neighbouring point of the other colour: the basins are riddled-like
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig8" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 8</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Scenario-dependent basins of attraction for a parameter drift scenario ending at 
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>+</sub> = 1.8 (after an extended chaotic regime, interval 
     <span class="italic">I</span>
     <sub>4</sub> in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>) with 
     <span class="italic">t</span>
     <sub>−</sub> = 0, 
     <span class="italic">t</span>
     <sub>+</sub> = 100. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) 
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>−</sub> = 0.1, 
     <span class="italic">t</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">r</span>
     </sub> = 7, and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) 
     <span class="italic">C</span>
     <sub>−</sub> = 0.1, 
     <span class="italic">t</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">r</span>
     </sub> = 27.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44863_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e2560" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dynamics on the extended chaotic attractor is so strongly mixing that in 
  <span class="italic">any</span> scenario passing through such an attractor the tipping probabilities from the initial attractor to both of the rotating periodic ones are found to be practically 1/2. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8a,b</a> illustrates that the pattern hardly depends on 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">r</span>
  </sub>. Predictability of individual trajectories is completely lost and one can speak of 
  <span class="italic">random tippings</span> in such cases. The fact that the tipping probabilities are independent of the choice of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> imply an important special case. When 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>−</sub> (&lt;
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub>) belongs to an extended chaotic attractor, the probabilities remain 1/2 and the process is fully unpredictable and random. We call such random tipping transitions 
  <span class="italic">tipping from or through a chaotic attractor</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scenarios ending or starting on small-size chaotic attractors and a comparison of different 
  <span class="italic">I</span> intervals of the same length are investigated in Supplementary Discussions 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">IIC</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">IID</a>. In Supplementary Discussion 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">IV</a> we study the role of snapshot attractors (see Methods) in the tipping transitions. We show that after arriving at the plateau of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>+</sub>, the snapshot attractor starts to develop peaks about the usual periodic attractors. The weight of these peaks determines the tipping probabilities, and they, just like the time evolution of the snapshot attractor, depend on the entire scenario.
 </p>
</sec>
