<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in ambient temperature affects various life stages of organisms (Stearns 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">1992</a>; Mainwaring and Hartley 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2016</a>; Rodríguez et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2016</a>; Bleu et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2017</a>; Vaugoyeau et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2017</a>). It has a large influence on the optimal laying-incubation-hatching dates of insectivorous passerines, because it affects the timing of food abundance (Perrins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">1991</a>; Hinks et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2015</a>). A combination of warm weather and mild rainfall in spring provides good conditions which enable the development of plants and rich arthropod communities, while low temperature slows down these processes. Clutch initiation date in tits is characterized by wide phenotypic plasticity and it largely depends on the temperatures directly before the laying of the first egg. The moment of initiating a clutch by a single tit female may differ more than 3 weeks between breeding seasons depending on the temperatures (Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2014</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2016a</a>; Wesołowski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2016</a>) but also on the habitat type (Blondel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">1993</a>; Massa et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2011</a>). When the temperatures are appropriate, females start producing eggs (in tits one per day) and then, if there is a sudden temperature drop, they may delay the moment of laying the next eggs or delay the moment of starting incubation. It is rather difficult to pause the incubation for more than a few hours without losing the clutch (Lee and Lima 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2017</a>). Therefore, delays in hatching usually occur when females are faced with a sudden cold spell (García-Navas and Sanz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2011</a>; Kluen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2011</a>; Tomás 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2015</a>) and may be considered as beneficial, when they allow for better synchronization between food demands of nestlings and the peak of caterpillar availability (Monrós et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">1998</a>; Cresswell and McCleery 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2003</a>). Females may also accelerate hatching, by starting incubation before producing their last eggs, when conditions are improving. Additionally, laying gaps and hatching delay may be interpreted as a consequence of food shortage or increased costs of thermoregulation during egg laying period (Nilsson and Svensson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1993a</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">b</a>; Cucco et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2017</a>). Little is known about the flexibility of the hatching delay (Naef-Daenzer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2004</a>; Kluen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2011</a>) and since phenotypic plasticity and flexibility of behavior play a major role in adjusting to unpredictable weather conditions in spring, examining their limits may be an important goal for research (Tomás 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a need to study variation in weather characteristics before and during the breeding period in birds in order to understand the ecological implications of climate change and more frequent extreme weather events (Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2008</a>; Goodenough et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2011</a>; Pipoly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2013</a>; Donnelly and Yu 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2017</a>; Marrot et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2017</a>). Extreme weather events are seen as weather conditions that cause the biological response to be in the 5% of most extreme values of the response variable (Altwegg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>; van de Pol et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2017</a>). As a result, the number of studies on various phenology traits has recently increased (Gaughan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2017</a>; Sheridan and Allen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2017</a>). It was also suggested that climate change not only implies higher temperatures and global changes in precipitation, but also more frequent extreme weather events, like cold spells in spring, or warm spells during winter (Otto 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2015</a>; Buckley and Huey 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2016</a>; Bailey and van de Pol 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2016</a>; Ummenhofer and Meehl 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2017</a>). Some authors even suggest that extreme weather events may have stronger effects on wildlife populations and habitats than changes in averages (Bateman et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2015</a>; Martinuzzi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2016</a>). In addition to variation in local weather conditions, the occurrence of extreme weather events also affects breeding birds (Jenouvrier 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2013</a>; Mainwaring et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2017</a>). A cold snap during the breeding season may have large consequences for breeding birds (Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2014</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2016a</a>; Indykiewicz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2015</a>; Tobolka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2015</a>). On the other hand, it was suggested that the recent extreme weather events can be treated as natural experiments that may elucidate the mechanisms by which birds adjust their phenology to fluctuating environments (Both and Visser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2005</a>; Jentsch et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2007</a>; Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2016a</a>; Altwegg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>). Fletcher et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2013</a>) and Whitehouse et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2013</a>) conclude that there is a need to collect long-term phenology monitoring data in order to fully understand the impacts of climate change on different species. Bauer et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2010</a>) note in addition that most papers analyzing these trends do not use data from central Europe, and there is a need to fill this gap.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2017, a large temperature drop during breeding was noticed in many parts of Europe and caused hatching delays in many tit populations in Belgium, England, France, Germany, Hungary, the Netherlands, Sweden, and others (Massemin S. personal information, Matthysen E. personal information, Nilsson J.-Å. personal information, Santema P. personal information, Seress G. personal information, Szulkin M. personal information, Visser M. personal information—information gathered during 8th International Hole-Nesting Birds Conference, Trondheim, Norway, October 30–November 2, 2017). In 2017, great temperature drop occurred shortly after the moment of the initiation of tit breeding at our study areas. Such temperature drops may indeed be seen as natural experiments. The aim of this paper is to show effects of extreme temperature drops during breeding on hatching delays in the great tit 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> and the blue tit 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span> at an urban parkland and a deciduous forest in central Poland. We suggest that during colder weather, ecological interactions, including predator-prey interactions, change (smaller amounts of prey available), and it may lead to changes in breeding strategies—eggs of small songbirds are built from the current income of resources. Additionally, female parents may require more food for body maintenance than for eggs, and this may lead to days with no produced eggs. Therefore, we predict that hatching delay should depend on ambient temperatures during breeding and very low temperatures should increase hatching delay.
 </p>
</sec>
