<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was carried out in 2002–2017 as part of long-term research project concerning the breeding biology of secondary hole-nesting birds occupying nestboxes near Łódź, central Poland (51° 47′ N, 19° 28′ E) (Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2015</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2017</a>; Wawrzyniak et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2015</a>). Both study sites are located in two, 10-km-distant, structurally and floristically contrasting habitats, an urban parkland (51° 45′ N, 19° 24′ E) and a deciduous forest (51° 50′ N, 19° 29′ E). The urban parkland area (80 ha) consists of the zoological garden (16 ha) and the botanical garden (64 ha). This area is one of the biggest recreation and entertainment areas in Łódź (Glądalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2016b</a>). The vegetation of the parkland area consists of a diverse mix of tree species including exotic tree species (Marciniak et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2007</a>). The forest site is about 130 ha area in the center of mature mixed deciduous forest (Łagiewniki forest, 1250 ha in total), bordering on the NE suburbia of Łódź. Large parts of the forest come directly from the ancient woodland typical for this region of central Europe. Oaks (
  <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Q. petraea</span>) are predominating tree species in the forest.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both study areas were supplied with standard wooden nestboxes (Lambrechts et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2010</a>). About 200 nestboxes were set in the parkland and about 300 nestboxes were set in the forest. All the nestboxes were placed on trees (usually on oaks) at a height of about 3 m. In both study areas, distances between neighboring nestboxes were about 50 m. At the start of the breeding season, the nestbox study areas were visited every day to record nestbox occupancy, laying date, clutch size, and hatching day. In normal conditions, the female lays one egg per day in tits (Perrins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">1996</a>). In situations when we found older hatchlings, we estimated hatching day using our photographic key for age determination of nestling tits. In the case of great tits, only first clutches were analyzed—clutches that started no more than 30 days from the first clutch in a studied population during the breeding season (van Noordwijk et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1995</a>). A total of 1517 (890 in the parkland and 627 in the forest) first clutches of the great tit and a total of 835 (348 in the parkland and 487 in the forest) first clutches of the blue tit were studied.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main period of the temperature drop during the mid-laying-early-incubating time of tits in Łódź in April 2017 lasted for about 5 days and was characterized by the mean ambient temperature ca. 2–3 °C, with no snow cover (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). We define a cold spell as a sudden drop in ambient temperature for a relatively short period of time and extreme weather events as weather conditions that cause the biological response to be in the 5% of most extreme values of the biological response variable (Altwegg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>; van de Pol et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2017</a>). The biological response variable was hatching delay, which occurred in most extreme form in 2017 in both study areas and for both tit species (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, and 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). The local temperatures (average annual temperature) for Łódź were obtained from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tutiempo.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">TuTiempo.net</span> climate database for Łódź (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tutiempo.net/en/Climate/LODZ/124650.htm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.tutiempo.net/en/Climate/LODZ/124650.htm</span> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.tutiempo.net/climate/ws-121055.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://en.tutiempo.net/climate/ws-121055.html</span>). Following García-Navas and Sanz (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2011</a>), we calculated the expected hatching date as follows: first egg date + clutch size + 12 (incubation in these species normally lasts 13 days and female usually starts to incubate 1 day before completing the clutch (García-Navas and Sanz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2011</a>). The difference between this date and observed hatching date was taken as hatching delay (negative values equals hatching occurred before expected and positive values equals a delay). In all calculations, the mean laying dates were expressed as days from 1 March. Following Perrins and McCleery (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">1989</a>) and Glądalski et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2014</a>), we calculated mid-laying-early-incubating warmth sums (mid-laying temperatures are crucial for hatching delays; García-Navas and Sanz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2011</a>; Cresswell and McCleery 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2003</a>), as the sum of the mean daily temperatures for the 7 days starting on the 4th day since the first egg date (first egg date + 4), to characterize thermal conditions during egg laying.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Mean temperatures for the mid-laying-early-incubating time in April 2017</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="484_2018_1541_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Mid-laying-early-incubating warmth sums, as the sum of the mean daily temperatures for the 7 days starting in the 4th day since the first egg date, in great tits and blue tits and in the forest study area and in the urban parkland study area (2002–2017)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="484_2018_1541_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Relationship between hatching delay (days) and the sum of the mean daily temperatures for the 7 days starting on the 4th day since the first egg date (warmth sum, °C) for great tits in the urban parkland area (cubic, filled circles) and in the forest area (cubic, open circles) (seasons 2002–2017)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="484_2018_1541_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Relationship between hatching delay (days) and the sum of the mean daily temperatures for the 7 days starting on the 4th day since the first egg date (warmth sum, °C) for blue tits in the urban parkland area (quadratic, filled circles) and in the forest area (cubic, open circles) (seasons 2002–2017)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="484_2018_1541_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We computed general linear models to examine effects of year and site factors (factorial design ANOVA) on hatching delays, assuming a Gaussian error structure. Separate models for blue tits and great tits were fit. Because interactions of the main factors were significant, the full models were presented. To check if the relationship between hatching delays and thermal conditions (mid-laying-early-incubating warmth sums) was linear or non-linear, we calculated polynomial regressions with cubic and quadratic terms. We used 
  <span class="italic">t</span> tests for the cubic and quadratic terms to delete non-significant terms. We also present adjusted values of 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> to evaluate the fit of the regressions. STATISTICA 12 (StatSoft Inc 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2014</a>) was applied to perform all computing and to produce charts.
 </p>
</sec>
