<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34" class="p">Future land conversion to (or from) cropland or developed land impacts TN flux via the land use term in Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>) (LU
 <sub class="sub">D,C</sub>), but land conversion to (or from) cropland also indirectly impacts TN flux via the NANI term in Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>) (
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>
 <sub class="sub">NANI</sub>) because it affect three of the NANI components, namely fertilizer usage, agricultural nitrogen fixation, and net food and feed import. Future changes to fertilizer application rate for a given crop type, on the other hand, impact TN flux only via their impact on the NANI term in Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>) and this only via two of the NANI components, namely fertilizer usage and net food and feed import. To assess the contribution of changes in future cropland (together with its embedded change in anthropogenic nitrogen inputs), developed land, or future fertilizer application rate individually, we developed three additional sets of future TN flux estimates based on: first, future cropland change (and concomitant changes to NANI) but historical developed land and fertilizer application rates; second, future changes to developed land area, maintaining cropland and fertilizer application rates at historical levels; and third, historical cropland and developed land but with future fertilizer application rates. Because the observation-based NANI estimates (see Section “Historical and future NANI datasets”) do not make it possible to assess fertilizer application rates for the five crop types in the LUH2 database, for these additional runs the historical fertilizer application rate was based on LUH2 data, and for consistency all other components of NANI were based on LUH2 data (as described in Section “Future changes in TN flux due to change in land use and land management”) rather than observation-based NANI. Also, due to the nonlinear form of the model and the impact of interactions among changes in land use and NANI, the impacts of the three individual components are not simply additive.
</p>
