<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">i) Data from quantitative intertidal samples of 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tuberculata</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">braziliensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hirsuticauda</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">analoga</italic> collected during spring low tides of December 1998—January 1999 at the Chilean beaches of El Aguila, Hornitos, Apolillado, Las Cruces, Matanzas, Cobquecura, Calfuco and Mar Brava (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0177116.g001" class="xref">Fig 1B</xref>). We focused on these crustaceans, since they are the most common taxa along Chilean sandy beaches and account for most of the abundance and biomass [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Sediments were collected with plastic cylinders (25 cm in diameter) at ten equally spaced levels (stations) along four replicated transects (1 m apart) extending from above the drift line to the swash zone; 
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>. the uppermost station of each transect was located above the drift line, the second on that line and the last at the lowest limit of the swash zone indicated by wave-bore collapse. The sediment was sieved through a 1-mm mesh sieve and the specimens collected were stored in 5% formalin until sorted and measured in the laboratory. Body size (length) and sex was determined for all specimens of all species. For 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tuberculata</italic>, body length was defined as the distance from rostrum tip to telson base, whereas for 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">braziliensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hirsuticauda</italic>, body length was defined as the distance from rostrum tip to telson tip. Body size of 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">analoga</italic> was defined as carapace length (CL), and was measured with calipers from the tip of the rostrum to the distal scoop of the carapace.
</p>
