<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The use of mineral fertilizers has strongly increased the flow of nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) in agricultural systems worldwide and altered global biogeochemical cycles. A significant part of the N and P contained in the fertilizers is lost from agro‐ecosystems via leaching, causing serious groundwater pollution and eutrophication (Galloway et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). The amount of nutrients applied in agricultural systems is not expected to decline in the coming decades and models predict a global increase of N and P excess of 23% and 54%, respectively, with a major intensification in developing countries (Bouwman et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; McIntyre, Herren, Wakhungu, &amp; Watson, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Concurrently, climate change models predict changes in rainfall patterns with increased annual precipitation in some regions, and more intense rainfall events (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Higher precipitation is often linked to increased nutrient leaching (Austin &amp; Vitousek, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>), which aggravates the risk of associated human and environmental health problems as highlighted by the Millennium Ecosystem Assessment (MEA, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). It is therefore crucial to reduce nutrient losses via leaching to preserve the environment and protect human health. A number of recent studies suggest that soil biota, including arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi, enhance nutrient cycling in agro‐ecosystems and reduce leaching losses (Bender &amp; Van der Heijden, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Cavagnaro, Bender, Asghari, &amp; van der Heijden, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>); however, it is not known if AM fungal ability to decrease nutrient losses is maintained across different precipitation scenarios.
</p>
