<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Variation in germination between species in a community can determine community structure. Plants have evolved strategies involving both predictive germination and optimization of their fitness such that some seeds germinate in the current environment, while others remain dormant and thus hedge their bet against unpredictable conditions that are not favorable for seedling establishment (Cohen, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1966</xref>; Gremer, Kimball, &amp; Venable, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). In the desert, germination in different environments with distinct water and temperature conditions is a risk‐spreading strategy (Gremer &amp; Venable, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Snyder, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Venable, Flores‐Martinez, Muller‐Landau, Barron‐Gafford, &amp; Becerra, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Volis &amp; Bohrer, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Furthermore, variation in germination requirements of desert plants at the community level may allow species coexistence, since it can contribute to temporal differences in use of resources such as water and nutrients between species and provide a buffer against extinction in the unpredictable desert environment (Ellner, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>; Gremer &amp; Venable, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). In addition, the differences between species in conditions required for germination can result in different combinations of annual species at the same site in different years (Chesson &amp; Huntly, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1988</xref>; Venable, 
 <xref rid="ece34909-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>).
</p>
