<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earth structure and rheology beneath Antarctica</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pattern and magnitude of the solid Earth response to ice-sheet growth and decay is strongly dependent on the rheology of the interior of the solid Earth, and the choice of rheological model has a large effect on the modelled GIA response (see Box 
  <a rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec4">1</a>). For example, ice history is often tuned in tandem with Earth rheology, so adoption of a different rheological model can lead to large differences in the assumed ice history. Earth rheology beneath Antarctica is spatially variable and, as detailed in the next section, this has implications for the behaviour of the ice sheet.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of rheological models have been adopted to explain the solid Earth response to surface load change across Antarctica, including linear Maxwell viscoelastic rheology, power law rheology, and Burgers rheology (see Box 
  <a rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec4">1</a>). Regardless of the choice of rheological model, the need for future modelling efforts to consider spatial variations in Earth structure beneath Antarctica is now clear. Seismic studies of the upper mantle beneath Antarctica suggest large lateral variations in material properties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>, with greater heterogeneity than observed in areas of Northern Hemisphere continental glaciation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. East Antarctica shows high upper mantle seismic velocities characteristic of cold cratonic regions worldwide, whereas West Antarctica shows upper mantle structure consistent with much warmer tectonically active zones (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a-c</a>). The range of seismic velocities observed beneath Antarctica provides strong evidence for lateral variations in mantle viscosity, but absolute values are currently poorly known. Preliminary GIA studies that explore the effect of including lateral variations in mantle viscosity reveal significant differences in predicted patterns and rates of deformation across Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>, motivating the need for better constraints on absolute mantle viscosity in this region.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatial variations in Earth properties in the upper mantle beneath Antarctica. Seismic shear wave velocity perturbations at depths of (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) 100, (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) 200 and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) 300 km beneath Antarctica derived from an adjoint inversion of teleseismic waveforms recorded by seismic stations south of 45°S (ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
     </span>). Colours indicate observed Voigt average velocity anomalies relative to global reference model STW105 (ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147" href="#CR147">147</a>
     </span>). Regions of negative anomalies (slower than global average velocities) suggest higher temperatures and hence likely lower viscosities
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8068_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e817" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Upper mantle viscosity variations of several orders of magnitude beneath West Antarctica have been quantified by modelling observed GPS uplift in specific settings. Nield et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> identified rapid viscoelastic deformation occurring in the northern Antarctic Peninsula due to a well-observed change in glacial loading resulting from the 2002 breakup of the Larsen B Ice Shelf. Comparison of GPS time series and modelled uplift in the region suggests upper mantle viscosities of between 6 × 10
  <span class="sup">17</span> and 2 × 10
  <span class="sup">18</span> Pa s in the northern Antarctic Peninsula. Similarly, Zhao et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span> used the changes in ice load resulting from thinning of Fleming Glacier over recent decades to estimate upper mantle viscosity, 500 km further south along the southern Antarctic Peninsula, to be at least 2 × 10
  <span class="sup">19</span> Pa s. Other estimates of upper mantle viscosity in West Antarctica include 1–3 × 10
  <span class="sup">20</span> Pa s beneath the southwestern Weddell Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span> and 4 × 10
  <span class="sup">18</span> Pa s for the Amundsen Sea Coast
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>. These represent variations of two orders of magnitude. In contrast, estimates of spatially-averaged upper mantle viscosity beneath the whole of Antarctica range from 2 × 10
  <span class="sup">20</span> to 1 × 10
  <span class="sup">21</span> Pa s (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>), which are similar to estimates of upper mantle viscosity in Fennoscandia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. The emerging picture suggests cratonic East Antarctica is characterised by higher upper mantle viscosity than West Antarctica, with exceptionally low upper mantle viscosity, on the order of 10
  <span class="sup">18</span> to 10
  <span class="sup">19</span> Pa s, beneath some regions of West Antarctica.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Existing constraints on mantle viscosity across Antarctica draw on our ability to measure the solid Earth response to known surface-load change. In regions where this is not possible, the three-dimensional shear velocity structure of the upper mantle beneath Antarctica can be used to estimate the lateral and depth variation of viscosity. Although there is no direct physical correspondence between shear velocity and viscosity, their variation in the upper mantle is largely controlled by temperature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. Ivins and Sammis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span> formulated an approach for converting shear velocity anomalies to viscosity anomalies relative to a global reference 1-D viscosity model, using the observed scaling of shear velocity and density anomalies to infer the temperature scaling, and then using olivine diffusion creep (linear) flow laws to constrain the viscosity perturbation. Wu et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span> proposed a similar method that uses experimentally determined temperature derivatives of shear velocity, including the effect of anelasticity. An alternative method is to estimate the temperature structure of the mantle from the shear velocity structure, and then use a composite rheology that computes the strain associated with both diffusion and dislocation creep mechanisms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. Since the dislocation creep rheology is non-linear, the calculated effective viscosity of the mantle will depend on the stress field. One key assumption in any of these methods is that the observed seismic velocity anomalies result entirely from temperature anomalies, whereas it is well known that a portion of the velocity perturbations result from (spatially variable) compositional anomalies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. Wu et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span> adjust their viscosity structure by the percentage of the velocity anomalies thought to be caused by thermal variations, which in their study was estimated to be between 65% and 100%. An alternative approach would involve correcting for (poorly known) spatial variations in mantle composition.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the approach outlined in Wu et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>, the estimated mantle viscosity beneath Antarctica, at depths of 100 and 250 km, varies by 2–3 orders of magnitude across the continent (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), with extremely low viscosity predicted beneath the Antarctic Peninsula, the Amundsen Sea coast, Marie Byrd Land, and the Transantarctic Mountain Front. The implications of these viscosity variations, and in particular the anomalously low viscosities beneath parts of West Antarctica, are explored in the next section.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatial variations in estimated upper mantle viscosity beneath Antarctica at depths of (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) 100 km and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) 250 km. Viscosity is estimated using the seismic shear velocity model presented in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and the method outlined in Wu et al.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
     </span>, as discussed in the text. These results are derived using a dry diffusion creep rheology
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
     </span> and the IJ05-R2 (ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
     </span>) reference viscosity model, assuming that the seismic velocity variations are entirely due to temperature, except that a correction for depleted cratonic mantle is applied to the East Antarctic lithosphere
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8068_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e945" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="boxed-text" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Box 1 Rheological models of the solid Earth</span>
   <p id="Par19">The response of the Earth to changing loads has generally been described using a linear Maxwell viscoelastic rheology, with an instantaneous elastic response superposed on a longer-term Newtonian viscous relaxation
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149" href="#CR149">149</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150" href="#CR150">150</a>
    </span>. The majority of GIA models, including most coupled ice sheet–sea level models, adopt this simple rheology and consider a spherical Earth, with an elastic lithosphere, a layered viscoelastic mantle, and an inviscid core. Crucially, such models typically include no lateral variation in rheological structure. However, differences in the response of the Earth to surface loading around the world suggest regional variations in rheological properties. Laboratory experiments on mantle materials, primarily olivine, show that the mantle can respond to long-term loading with either diffusion creep, corresponding to linear viscosity, or dislocation creep, corresponding to a power-law viscosity
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151" href="#CR151">151</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152" href="#CR152">152</a>
    </span>. Although both mechanisms operate simultaneously in the mantle, deformation will be controlled by the weaker mechanism at any given location, with higher stress and larger grain size favouring dislocation creep, i.e., a non-linear response
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153" href="#CR153">153</a>
    </span>. It is commonly thought that dislocation creep dominates at shallow depth in the upper mantle, as indicated by xenoliths
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154" href="#CR154">154</a>
    </span> and significant seismic anisotropy
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155" href="#CR155">155</a>
    </span>, transitioning to diffusion creep at depths greater than 200–300 km (ref. 
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152" href="#CR152">152</a>
    </span>). It is difficult to clearly delineate the regions of the mantle dominated by linear and power-law viscosities because the rheologies depend on stress and the poorly constrained parameters of water content, grain size and activation volume
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153" href="#CR153">153</a>
    </span>. Power-law rheologies can be introduced into GIA models using a composite rheology, where low stress portions of the model adopt a linear Maxwell rheology and high stress portions adopt a power law rheology assuming some transition stress
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156" href="#CR156">156</a>
    </span>. Alternatively, strain is assumed to be the sum of diffusion and dislocation creep, as calculated using laboratory-based flow laws assuming parameters such as grain size and temperature
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153" href="#CR153">153</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157" href="#CR157">157</a>
    </span>.
   </p>
   <p id="Par20">Recent studies show that the transient relaxation following major earthquakes is generally best fit by a Burgers (biviscous) rheology with two characteristic relaxation times or effective viscosities
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158" href="#CR158">158</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159" href="#CR159">159</a>
    </span>. These observations have resulted in increased interest in the use of Burgers rheology in GIA studies
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
    </span>. However, similar to the power-law case, there are few data to constrain these more complex models and most recent GIA models continue to use a Maxwell rheology
    <span class="sup">
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
