<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent modelling advances have highlighted the importance of understanding the role of the solid Earth in moderating the response of the global ice sheets to past and future climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. It has long been understood that the growth and decay of an ice sheet will alter the shape of the solid Earth and result in spatially variable sea-level change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. We are beginning to understand how those changes affect the dynamics of ice sheets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>, but further work is needed to quantify feedbacks between ice sheet evolution and landscape evolution before we can fully explain the long-term evolution of the Antarctic Ice Sheet.
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coupled models that consider interactions between ice sheets and the solid Earth via dynamic modelling of both systems represent a new type of model that can provide insight into the extent, timing, and mechanisms of past ice sheet evolution and sea-level change. Such models also provide a new tool for understanding the link between past climate and global sea-level change. Coupled models have been used to demonstrate that the solid Earth response to ice loss, and the accompanying fall in sea level, will have a stabilising effect on grounding line dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>. This mechanism has the potential to slow or even halt grounding line retreat along a reverse bed slope, depending on the rate of solid Earth rebound. Such negative feedbacks have been modelled in association with ice loss across West Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, but crucially the rheology of the underlying mantle is poorly constrained, and so the strength of the feedback cannot currently be quantified.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interdisciplinary approaches to determining mantle rheology reveal large differences between East and West Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>, with low viscosity mantle inferred to lie beneath West Antarctica. The short mantle relaxation time associated with such regions means that estimates of the contemporary GIA signal derived by forward modelling will be biased if they do not account for ice-sheet change over the last few millennia, with implications for estimates of current ice mass balance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. Improved quantification of late Holocene ice history, as well as tighter constraints on mantle rheology, are needed to reduce uncertainty on the contemporary GIA signal across Antarctica. Low viscosity mantle will also enhance the strength of the stabilising effect of GIA on grounding line dynamics, highlighting the importance of considering such feedbacks when modelling the future evolution of the Antarctic Ice Sheet. A number of studies have successfully incorporated 3-D Earth structure into GIA models beneath modern ice sheets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143" href="#CR143">143</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144" href="#CR144">144</a>
  </span>, and it is now apparent that coupled modelling and inclusion of 3-D Earth structure should both be considered when modelling solid Earth-cryosphere feedbacks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Such models are being developed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>
  </span> but further interdisciplinary work, combining modelling and observational approaches, is needed to calibrate such models and better understand controls on the evolution of the Antarctic Ice Sheet.
 </p>
</sec>
