<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ptarmigan banding work was approved by the UBC Animal Care Committee Protocol A01-0097. Birds were captured under the Canadian Federal Banding Sub Permit—10365BO and BC Provincial banding permit (Water, Lands and Parks)—C068541. Research was conducted in Strathcona Provincial Park under Park Use Permit—#3081065.</p>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and species occurrence data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study area encompassed all of Vancouver Island, located on the southwest coast of British Columbia, Canada (between 47° and 52° N latitude and 123° and 128° W longitude). At 460 km long (north to south) and 80 km wide (east to west; 32,134 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>), Vancouver Island is the largest island on the west coast of North America. Elevation varies from 0 to 2,195 m a.s.l. A central spine of mountains spans the length of the island, with highest elevations located in the center of the island within Strathcona Provincial Park (with four mountain summits between 1,830 m and 2,195 m). These mountains create a rain shadow on the eastern side, resulting in a strong east-west precipitation gradient across the island. The biogeography of the island has been classified into biogeoclimatic (BEC) zones by the provincial government that represent vegetation, soil, and climate conditions. Four BEC zones exist on Vancouver Island, including Coastal Douglas Fir, Coastal Western Hemlock, Mountain Hemlock and Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine. The largest areas of continuous alpine habitats are found in the central region of the island, while alpine patches in the northern and southern regions are generally lower in elevation and more fragmented.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used two sources of distributional data for Vancouver Island White-tailed Ptarmigan. The first consisted of ptarmigan presence locations from field surveys conducted by K. Martin from 1995–1999. These surveys targeted the entire range of VIWTP and representative alpine habitat deemed suitable for ptarmigan was searched in the north, central, and south island. Birds were located using playbacks of male territorial calls and chick distress calls, then captured with a snare attached to an extendable pole [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref038">38</a>] and outfitted with a necklace collar radio transmitter (RI-2D/2B, 18 mo battery life, weight 6–9 gm, Holohil Systems Ltd., Carp, Ontario). K. Martin and field crews tracked the radio-collared birds over the 4-year period by foot during summer and recorded encounters with other uncollared birds using playbacks and incidental encounters. GPS coordinates were recorded at each bird location.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From this field survey dataset, we extracted summer (June–October) observations and eliminated sightings of juveniles, since they were usually found at or near the same GPS coordinate as their parent during the summer period. We then eliminated duplicates at the same GPS point (i.e., if a flock of several birds was recorded at one point, only one observation was included in the final dataset). To minimize bias due to certain individuals being observed more than others, we first eliminated records from the same individual that were &lt; 1 day apart, and then randomly selected two records per individual. Lastly, we randomly selected one observation within each 100-m grid cell of the environmental predictor GIS layers. All filtering of the original ptarmigan data was carried out using R 3.1.2.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to supplement the field survey records, an opportunistic citizen science program was initiated in partnership between the Strathcona Wilderness Institute and K. Martin at the Centre for Alpine Studies, University of British Columbia. Notices were posted at trailheads within Strathcona Provincial Park describing distinguishing features of White-tailed Ptarmigan. The notices requested that hikers report their ptarmigan sightings by mailing a card or sending an e-mail with GPS or map coordinates and photos (if possible) to K. Martin at UBC. The citizen science initiative began in 1995 and continues to the present, currently resulting in 404 confirmed White-tailed Ptarmigan sightings (see [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>] for details). Although trailhead cards were posted within Strathcona Provincial Park, many hikers frequently submitted records from their other alpine hikes on the island after finding out about the program. This resulted in a public dataset spanning the entire range of alpine habitat on Vancouver Island (
   <a rid="pone.0142110.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0142110.g001">Fig 1</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0142110.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0142110.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">White-tailed Ptarmigan presence locations on Vancouver Island from the field survey (circles; N = 207) and public submissions (triangles; N = 137).</div>
    <p>Strathcona Provincial Park is outlined in black. This map is similar but not identical to that shown in [
     <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0142110.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We extracted summer (June–October) observations from the public dataset and then filtered the observations by location accuracy, keeping only those that contained precise GPS or map coordinates (accurate to within 100 m). As with the field survey observations, we eliminated duplicates at the same location and randomly selected one observation within each 100-m grid cell. Because the field survey and public datasets result in models with similar accuracy and distributional predictions when using machine learning modeling techniques [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>], we combined ptarmigan presence locations from each dataset in order to maximize sample size and model accuracy for the purpose of this study. If two sightings fell within the same 100-m grid cell in the combined dataset, we randomly eliminated one sighting from the cell. The resulting combined dataset contained 344 sightings (207 from the field survey and 137 from the public dataset; 
   <a rid="pone.0142110.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0142110.g001">Fig 1</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because we lack information on ptarmigan absences (areas traversed by observers where ptarmigan were not encountered) in either dataset, we generated a baseline random sample of pseudo-absences for the combined dataset to represent the landscape potentially available to VIWTP. First, we constrained the pseudo-absence background within a 200-m buffer surrounding the minimum convex polygon around the entire set of ptarmigan observation points. Within this area, we restricted the background to areas within the Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine and Mountain Hemlock Biogeoclimatic (BEC) zones. The majority (92%) of ptarmigan presence locations fell within the Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine BEC zone, while the remainder fell within the Mountain Hemlock zone (except for one sighting in the Coastal Western Hemlock zone).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some methods for generating pseudo-absences first predict low suitability areas using presence-only models and select pseudo-absences from those areas [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref039">39</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref041">41</a>]. Senay et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref042">42</a>] apply a novel three-step approach to select pseudo-absences using environmental constraints which can outperform models where pseudo-absences are randomly generated. We used distribution maps of BEC zones, which incorporate environmental variables known to be correlated with ptarmigan presence, to define environmental constraints for pseudo-absence selection. In contrast to methods that generate pseudo-absences outside of suitable habitat, we differentiated ‘‘suitable” from ‘‘highly suitable” habitat by generating pseudo-absences within potentially suitable habitat (which included both Mountain Hemlock and Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine zones). Such a distinction is important for rare and threatened species [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref043">43</a>]. Including Mountain Hemlock zones in our pseudo-absence background also allowed for better discrimination between presence and absence locations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within this background, we excluded all areas within a 200-m buffer around known ptarmigan presence locations (the median distance moved by ptarmigan within a day during summer was 170 m based on the radio-telemetry study; N = 37 movements). Finally, we randomly selected twice as many pseudo-absence locations as the number of ptarmigan presence locations (688 total pseudo-absences). This choice was based on an initial exploration of different ratios of presences to pseudo-absences (1:2, 1:4, and 1:10) to check for changes in model accuracy measures (sensitivity, specificity, Kappa, AUC, and the True Skill Statistic). Using a ratio of 1:2 resulted in the highest Kappa value, whereas all other accuracy measures were not affected by presence-to-pseudo absence ratio.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Abiotic predictor variables</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To model ptarmigan occurrence, we used eight abiotic variables believed to influence ptarmigan distribution (
   <a rid="pone.0142110.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0142110.t001">Table 1</a>). Five topographic variables included elevation, aspect, slope, compound topographic index (CTI, commonly referred to as a wetness index), and a vector ruggedness measure (VRM). All topographic variables were derived from a 100-m resolution digital elevation model (DEM). Aspect and slope were calculated using ArcGIS Spatial Analyst. We transformed aspect as x = -1*cos[Ø(π/180)], where Ø is the aspect measured in degrees. Values ranged from -1 where the angle of solar incidence was lower (north-facing slopes) to 1 where it was higher (south-facing slopes). The importance of aspect depends on slope, so we assigned aspects with slopes of &lt;5° a neutral value of 0 [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref044">44</a>]. CTI was calculated based on the slope and upstream contributing area orthogonal to the flow direction [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref045">45</a>], so that low values represent small catchments such as steep slopes or ridges and high values represent large catchments such as gentle slopes or depressions. VRM is an integrative measure of terrain heterogeneity based on slope and aspect, and was calculated using neighbourhoods of nine pixel cells. Ruggedness values can range from 0 (no terrain variation, or a smooth surface) to 1 (extremely rugged terrain with high variability in slope and aspect; [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref046">46</a>]).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0142110.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0142110.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Abiotic variables used in the Random Forest model for predicting the distribution of Vancouver Island White-tailed Ptarmigan habitat.</div>
    <p>The mean and standard deviation (SD) along with the range (in brackets) of each variable are shown for ptarmigan presences and pseudo-absences.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0142110.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0142110.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Variable</th>
       <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">Description</th>
       <th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Mean (± SD) and range of ptarmigan locations</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field survey presences</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public presences</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pseudo-absences</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevation (m)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elevation a.s.l.</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,557 (±178) [1,088–1,989]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,590 (±189) [968–2,29]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,173 (± 197) [675–1,800]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspect</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aspect transformed for solar incidence
        <a rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn" href="#t001fn001">
         <span class="sup">1</span>
        </a>
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.50 (± 0.52) [-1–0.99]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.28 (± 0.60) [–1–1]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.08 (± 0.68) [–1–1]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope (°)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope of the landscape</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3 (± 9.8) [2.1–48.4]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 (± 9.8) [1.3–53.4]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1 (± 11.6) [0–57.2]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTI</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound Topographic Index
        <a rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn" href="#t001fn002">
         <span class="sup">2</span>
        </a>, a function of the slope and the upstream contributing area [
        <a rid="pone.0142110.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref045">45</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.0 (± 0.9) [9.2–14.5]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (± 0.9) [8.9–14.3]</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 (±1.4) [8.9–19.4]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VRM</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vector Ruggedness Measure, a measurement of terrain ruggedness as the variation in three-dimensional orientation of grid cells within a 9-cell neighborhood [
        <a rid="pone.0142110.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref046">46</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063 (± 0.031) [0.006–0.162]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079 (± 0.035) [0.006–0.212]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049 (± 0.031) [0.001–0.218]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean summer precipitation (mm)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean annual summer (May–Sept.) precipitation</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">619 (± 390) [284–1,867]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">594 (± 263) [152–1,591]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">563 (± 300) [171–2,536]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean summer temperature (°C)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean summer temperature</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 (± 1.0) [7.7–12.8]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 (± 1.1) [7.3–13.3]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 (± 1.0) [8.8–14.5]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precipitation as snow (mm)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precipitation as snow from August in previous year to July of current year</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,793 (± 721) [586–4,592]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,436 (± 522) [676–3,718]</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,101 (± 507) [330–4,129]</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="t001fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">1</span> x = -1*cos[Ø(π/180)], where Ø is the aspect measured in degrees. Since the importance of aspect depends on slope, we assigned aspects with slopes of &lt;5° a neutral value of 0 [
      <a rid="pone.0142110.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref044">44</a>].
     </p>
    </fn>
    <fn id="t001fn002" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">2</span> CTI = ln(As / tan(β)) where As = Area Value calculated as (flow accumulation + 1) * (pixel area m
      <span class="sup">2</span>) and β is the slope expressed in radians.
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We extracted three climate variables for each ptarmigan location from the year the observation was collected using the program ClimateBC v5.03 [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref047">47</a>] (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cfcg.forestry.ubc.ca/projects/climate-data/climatebcwna/#ClimateBC" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cfcg.forestry.ubc.ca/projects/climate-data/climatebcwna/#ClimateBC</span>; 
   <a rid="pone.0142110.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0142110.t001">Table 1</a>). ClimateBC extracts PRISM [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref048">48</a>] monthly climate normal data at a coarse scale (800 x 800 m) and then downscales it using bilinear interpolation and adjustments based on latitude, longitude, and elevation. We used mean summer temperature, mean summer precipitation, and precipitation as snow to model ptarmigan distribution. These climate variables reflected prior knowledge about White-tailed Ptarmigan energy and water constraints [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref030">30</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref032">32</a>]. To predict suitable ptarmigan habitat across Vancouver Island, we also extracted the climate variables for the baseline time period 1980–2010 for each cell in our 100-m DEM.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To model the distribution of VIWTP in the future, we extracted the above climate predictors from ClimateBC for the 2020s (2010–2039), 2050s (2040–2069), and 2080s (2070–2099) across three general circulation models (GCMs): CanESM2 from the Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis, CCSM4 from the National Center for Atmospheric Research, and GFDL-CM3 from the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory, and two Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) from the International Panel on Climate Change AR5 report: RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5. We chose these three GCMs to represent a range of possible climate futures on Vancouver Island based on scatter plots of future temperature and precipitation using all 16 GCMs made available through ClimateBC. The GFDL model predicts a hot, moderately wet future, the CanESM2 model predicts a hot, very wet future, and the CCSM model predicts the least change in both temperature and precipitation (
   <a rid="pone.0142110.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0142110.g002">Fig 2</a>). The RCP 4.5 scenario represents lower future greenhouse gas concentrations and more conservative predictions of climate change, whereas the RCP 8.5 scenario represents higher future greenhouse gas concentrations and a more extreme climate change scenario. In order to predict future ptarmigan distribution, we extracted the three climate predictors for every cell in the 100-m DEM covering all of Vancouver Island for each GCM and greenhouse gas scenario combination.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0142110.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0142110.g002</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Predicted changes in mean summer temperature (a), mean summer precipitation (b) and precipitation as snow (c) according to three general circulation models (GCMs): CanESM2 (Can), CCSM4 (CCSM), and GFDL-CM3 (GFDL), and two IPCC emissions scenarios (RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5) for Vancouver Island.</div>
    <p>The RCP 4.5 scenario is displayed using dotted lines while the RCP 8.5 scenario is displayed using solid lines. Line weights correspond to the three GCMs (thick = Can, medium = GFDL, thin = CCSM).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0142110.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distribution model construction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We predicted probability of White-tailed Ptarmigan occurrence over all of Vancouver Island at 100-m resolution using a Random Forest model [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref049">49</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref050">50</a>] with the ‘randomForest’ package in R. Random Forest models had high accuracy and were most consistent when modeling the field survey and public data separately [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>]. Furthermore, Random Forest is robust to the inclusion of correlated variables (e.g., temperature and elevation; [
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref049">49</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0142110.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref051">51</a>]). Random Forest models produce many classification trees, each constructed using a bootstrap sample of the input data. The number of predictor variables randomly selected at each tree node was set to the default (the square root of the total number of predictors), and 1500 classification trees were constructed.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used ptarmigan presence and pseudo-absence locations from the pooled datasets as the response variable and all abiotic predictor variables in the model. In order to convert probability of presence into binary presence-absence predictions, we used the threshold probability that maximized sensitivity (percent of presences correctly classified) at 90% using the ‘PresenceAbsence’ package in R. Map pixels with probabilities above the threshold were considered ‘suitable’ habitat and those below the threshold were considered ‘unsuitable.’ We felt that from a conservation perspective, errors of omission (misclassifying presences as absences) were more “dangerous” than errors of commission (misclassifying absences as presences). Furthermore, since we knew the presences to be true presences but absences were pseudo-absences and may have been false (located in areas where ptarmigan are present) we chose to maximize the number of presences correctly predicted at 90%, recognizing that this may result in slight over-prediction of suitable habitat compared to other threshold-setting measures (e.g., maximizing kappa). We evaluated the RF model by calculating out-of-bag (OOB) errors based on bootstrapped samples of the input data according to the pre-chosen threshold using the R package ‘PresenceAbsence’. We constructed all models using R 3.1.2.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We predicted the RF model onto the entire landscape of Vancouver Island at 100-m resolution using baseline (1980–2010) and future (2020s, 2050s, and 2080s) climates, resulting in one baseline distribution model and 18 future distributions (= 3 GCMs × 2 emission scenarios × 3 time periods).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial analysis of baseline and future distributions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We calculated baseline and future habitat area by multiplying the number of raster grid cells considered “suitable” in each predicted distribution by the area of each grid cell (0.01 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>). We assessed the potential effects of climate change on predicted distributions by evaluating potential net range change. Range change (RC) was calculated using the formula 
   <div id="pone.0142110.e001" class="disp-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0142110.e001.jpg" id="pone.0142110.e001g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M1" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mtext">RC </span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <span class="mtext"> </span>
       <span class="mn">100</span>
       <span class="mtext"> </span>
       <span class="mo">×</span>
       <span class="mtext"> </span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mtext">RG </span>
         <span class="mo">–</span>
         <span class="mtext"> RL</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mtext"> </span>
       <span class="mo">/</span>
       <span class="mtext"> BR</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where RG = range gain, RL = range loss, and BR = baseline range area. RG and RL were both summed at the level of individual grid cells. We also calculated the number of suitable habitat patches and mean patch size based on the configuration of baseline and future suitable habitat.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
