<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The geological record of past climatic and biological change provides important insights into the responses of the Earth system to large-scale environmental perturbations, and hence the likely responses of the Earth to anthropogenic climate change
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>. Consequently, extreme events such as the Palaeocene–Eocene thermal maximum (PETM, ∼56 million years ago, Myr ago) and Permian–Triassic boundary (∼252 Myr ago) have been contextualized through comparisons of calculated rates of temperature change to observed and projected modern rates
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>. The Permian–Triassic boundary represents the most significant global warming of the Phanerozoic, when Earth's largest mass extinction was accompanied by an increase in tropical sea surface temperature (SST) of ∼15 °C over an interval of nearly 1 Myr (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>). Recent high precision U–Pb dating suggests that ∼10 °C of surface ocean warming occurred over a timespan of ∼60 kyr (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>), that is, a rate of ∼1.7 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−4</sup> °C per year. In a modern day context, this local rate is ∼42 times lower than the global surface ocean warming of 0.35 °C over the past 50 years
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>. Similarly, through the PETM, a global surface ocean warming of ∼6 °C over 5–20 kyr (refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>) has been linked to a pronounced perturbation of the global carbon cycle, and suggests a warming rate at least six times slower than modern.
</p>
