<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies predicted the distribution of BTV and its vectors; most of these studies were limited to Europe after BTV emergence in Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], and assessed transmission risk based mostly on vector distribution and abundance [
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. However, a single study took the advantage of a mechanistic models to quantify 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <italic class="italic" xmlns="">0</italic>
 </sub> values of BTV across Europe based on different temporal scales of climate data. This latter study demonstrated BTV risk areas across most of Europe that coincide with our results. However, our prediction covers a much broader portion of Europe, extending across much of the continent, east to western Russia. A recent study of BTV potential in the United States predicted that further northwards expansion of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sonorensis</italic> can be expected in the future [
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Our current study anticipated both the northern United States, southwestern Canada, and Ontario as at risk, as long as both BTV and vector expand distributionally in tandem; however, it marked unsuitability of conditions to virus spread along the US Gulf Coast and in the eastern Rocky Mountains, where livestock and wild animals have been diagnosed as positive to BTV [
 <xref rid="pone.0150489.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. This discord may reflect limitations of our model; however, these same regions were identified as suitable in our future models, which may indicate that our present-day models cannot anticipate risk in these regions given ongoing climate reorganization.
</p>
