<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Temperature and water availability are fundamental constraints on crop growth. Since growing seasons can be adapted to changing climate, we consider annual (rather than seasonal) sum of GDD (base temperatures, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">b</sub>, of 0, 8 and 5 °C for wheat, maize and rice, respectively
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>) and mean precipitation as climatic variables 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>(1) and 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>(2). This maintains consistency with the methods used to derive the attainable yield data set
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>. Precipitation is included because areas with very low rainfall may not have the option of irrigation (that is, the attainable yield is a rainfed yield). Seasonal timing of precipitation is not considered critical, as water may be stored for irrigation later in the year. More discussion of the effect of analogue variable choice is provided in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Note 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 18</xref>. 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> is calculated individually for every crop type. For every 0.5° × 0.5° grid-cell, 
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> is calculated between the future climate in that grid-cell, and reference climates in all grid-cells, 
 <italic class="italic">j</italic>, including at least 1,000 ha of that crop
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>. We note that harvested area has expanded substantially for some crops since Monfreda 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref> was published
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>, but this data set remains the 
 <italic class="italic">de facto</italic> standard and maintains consistency with Mueller 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>, from whom we have taken the present-day attainable yield data. As changes in cropped area are much smaller than for harvested area, this should have minimal influence on our results.
</p>
