<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are serval uncertainty sources in statistical crop models. For example, uncertainty is inherent in that empirical models are based on finite historical observations (referred to as sampling uncertainty). Here, this sampling uncertainty is estimated using bootstrap resampling technique. Specifically, 1000 bootstrap replicates of 30-year data points are generated for each crop–region combination and the statistical model is fitted for each replicate, based on which the sampling uncertainty is quantified by the standard deviation. Comparing Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref> shows that climate model uncertainty as indicated by the error bar is much larger than sampling uncertainty. Other aspects of crop model uncertainty mainly involve the variables and temporal scales selected for analysis. Indeed, to develop statistical models for describing climate-crop yield relations, we must struggle with the fundamental problem of variable selection. In this study, the models are developed from monthly averages of selected climate variables, and therefore does not explicitly consider other influencing factors such as extreme weathers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>. Further, climate anomalies occurring at different stages of crop development have varied impacts on agricultural production. However, including all possible months and variables will result in an over-parameterized model that tends to over-fit the training sample and give poor predictive performance
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Besides climate change, crop yields would be influenced by agricultural managements such as conservation tillage
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>, multiple cropping
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>, soil Mulching
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>, irrigation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup> and fertilization
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>, which are ignored in this study.
</p>
