<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">Blue carbon ecosystems are among the most threatened ecosystems on Earth. The global area occupied by VCE is being globally reduced at rates ranging from 0.03 to &gt;1% per year, twice as high as those reported for tropical forests
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. These losses led to the development of blue carbon strategies to prevent and mitigate greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions through the conservation and restoration of VCE. The development of programs like REDD+, the payments for ecosystem services
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup> and the inclusion of VCE within Nationally Appropriate Mitigation Actions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup> aim to maintain the benefits these ecosystems provide to climate change mitigation and adaptation, fisheries, and other ecosystem services that support coastal communities and their livelihoods
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Blue carbon strategies are now being included within Nationally 
 <italic>Determined</italic> Contribution to mitigate and adapt to climate change. However, this requires strong scientific evidence, and whereas reports of C stocks and sequestration rates in VCE have recently increased exponentially
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>, comprehensive estimates of blue carbon storage at national and continental scales are lacking, particularly for tidal marshes and seagrass. Uncertainties on the extent of these ecosystems, their C stocks and sequestration rates, as well as limited available data on the loss and fate of C after disturbance, hinder adoption of VCE into carbon trading and national inventories
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
