<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Scott Moreau (
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1986</xref>) uses the following analogy to better illustrate Mbiti’s concept of African TO. An individual is standing in a river, facing the downstream flow of the water. The water current represents the flow of time (
 <italic class="italic">actual time</italic>) and the individual’s temporal view is represented by his or her peripheral perspective, hereby including all the water that has moved downstream past him or her. The individual’s ‘future’ view is represented by what can be visually perceived upstream (near-sighted future view) and unseen water (representing 
 <italic class="italic">no-time</italic>) is insignificant for the individual because the unseen water (unknown future events – 
 <italic class="italic">no-time</italic>) will ‘pass when and how it passes, and then it will become of consequence’ (Moreau 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1986</xref>:39). Only the water (time flow) in peripheral view that is currently flowing past the individual and the water that has previously passed the individual (past and present timeframes constituting 
 <italic class="italic">actual time</italic>) carry significance. Natural debris (like sticks and leaves) floating in the water is representative of inevitable natural phenomena (
 <italic class="italic">potential time</italic>), and the debris will unavoidably float past him or her. The individual has no logical motivation to move upstream and therefore remains stationary. Awareness is attributed to the fact that the upstream current will eventually reach him or her and moving against the current will not accelerate the waters’ natural flow. Therefore, it is considered unnecessary to focus on the uncontrollable flow of the upstream water (unknown future events: 
 <italic class="italic">no-time</italic>). Moreau (
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1986</xref>) concludes this analogy by stating that an individual with a contemporary monochronic TO will see no use in remaining stationary, but will rather swim upstream, thus chasing the future.
</p>
