<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chronology of loess sections is commonly established based on the correlation of MS/MGS with marine benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O (ice volume) or orbital parameters (“Methods”), and constrained with paleomagnetic data when the studied section is sufficiently long. Consequently, MS/MGS variations, proxies for East Asian summer and winter monsoon, respectively, from various sections on the CLP are essentially synchronous on glacial–interglacial timescales (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>), a fundamental tenet in loess studies. Sediment hiatus, if presented, could affect the correlation-based chronology. A 4–5-kyr hiatus in the typical loess deposits has been reported in several studies based on independent quartz optically stimulated luminescence (OSL) dating technology, indicating that the loess record is not continuous over millennial timescales, and this hiatus may be forced by a period of strengthened East Asian winter monsoon and less vegetation cover at the investigated sites
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. However, at other sites sediment hiatus is not detectable, suggesting that dust accumulation for the last glacial loess is generally continuous at millennial timescales on the CLP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. The inferred hiatus typically occurred at the paleosol–loess boundary, where processes of pedogenesis and carbonate leaching could both affect the estimates of OSL ages
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Some of the inferred hiatuses are actually an artifact of inaccurate determination of OSL ages
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Therefore, sediment hiatus over the major part of the CLP including the classical Xifeng and Luochuan sections (except desert margins
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>) might be minimal over millennial timescales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to further evaluate chronological uncertainty, we compare age discrepancies between correlation-based and high-resolution OSL-derived chronologies from Weinan
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>, Xifeng
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, Luochuan
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> and Jingyuan
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> sections. Over the past 60/130 kyr, the age difference is within 5 kyr for most periods and &lt;10 kyr in extreme cases (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). Consequently, the MS/MGS changes still took place between ~10 and 20 ka, with either of the two chronologies (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>). Therefore, the high-resolution OSL ages from the last glacial period strongly support the fidelity of the correlation approach that spans the last seven glacial–interglacial cycles in the present study.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also examined the early signals in our temperature records, relative to the onsite MS variations from Xifeng, Weinan, Lantian, and Mangshan loess profiles, in depth domain without transforming into ages. The offset in depth between LSTs and MS, supporting the early warming, becomes larger from the southeast to northwest of the CLP (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>). Considering loess deposition rate at Xifeng (~3.9–22.5 cm/kyr, average 11.5 cm/kyr
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>) is lower than that at Mangshan, ~26 cm/kyr
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>, the spatial pattern of early warming would be more apparent in time domain. Therefore, the early warming relative to MS/MGS changes and the spatial pattern of early warming on the CLP reported in this study are largely unaffected by chronological uncertainty, based on our assessment of sediment hiatus, comparison of the two chronologies, and examination of the signal offset in depth domain.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global and local studies of modern processes have shown that the distribution of brGDGTs corresponds well with temperature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, which can be used to reconstruct paleotemperature changes on land
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, although the specific biological source of brGDGTs has not been identified. Currently brGDGT-based temperature reconstructions are generally calibrated against mean annual air temperature at both global and regional scales due to the lack of soil temperature data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. However, we argue that brGDGT-based temperature reconstructions from these loess sections should best be interpreted as near-ground LSTs during bacterial growth seasons since bacterial production of brGDGTs on the CLP occurs during warm, wet seasons
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. A recent investigation using an independent set of 20 soil samples collected from temperate area of northern China has also demonstrated that brGDGT indices correlate strongly with growing season (March to November) soil temperatures but respond weakly to winter soil temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although responding to air temperatures, LST variability registered in brGDGTs produced by bacteria living within soil layers is more directly influenced by the near-ground climate. The near-ground climate may substantially differ from the air layer (defined as a height of ~1.5 m above the level of the ground), since when ground surface is approached, many atmospheric elements change rapidly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> and can be further modified by soil physical parameters (such as albedo, texture, and moisture)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. This distinction is important as land surface barriers impact near surface radiation and alter surface energy balance as well as boundary development in the way of influencing soil and near surface temperatures. We therefore interpret brGDGT-based temperatures to indicate LSTs during bacterial growing seasons on the CLP.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although brGDGT-producing bacteria may survive in deeper soils, brGDGTs produced in surface soil should predominate. The lifestyle of brGDGT-synthesizing bacteria is heterotrophic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, and thus surface soil is more suitable for bacterial growth due to available organic matter and oxygen. A stable isotope probing experiment has also demonstrated that brGDGT-producing bacteria in peat are more active in the aerobic acrotelm than the anoxic catotelm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. Further, brGDGTs concentrations in surface soil (0–5 cm) are generally much higher than those in deeper soil (5–30 cm) at Xifeng, Lantian, and Mangshan (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>), supporting that brGDGTs are mainly produced in the surface soil layer, at least on the CLP.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also examined downcore variations of LST, brGDGT concentration, brGDGT concentration normalized by TOC content, TOC content, and MS in the Xifeng profile. Changes in all these contents correspond well with MS, while LST changes are obviously ahead of them (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). Generally, higher LSTs correspond with lower brGDGT concentrations. Therefore, the higher LSTs unlikely result from downward migration of brGDGTs produced at a later time or in situ modern production in deeper soils. Bioturbation and diagenesis, although affecting GDGT concentrations, have neglected effects on GDGT temperature proxies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. Therefore, the early warming observed in our temperature records is unlikely due to the alteration of brGDGT distributions after burial in loess–paleosol sequences or chronological uncertainty as assessed above and requires a climatic interpretation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modern investigations show that vegetation coverage on the CLP gradually decreases from southeast to northwest (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). For instance, remote sensing data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span> indicate that vegetation coverage decreases from 50–60% at Mangshan to 20–30% at Xifeng in 1999. Modern TOC content also decreases toward the northwest CLP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>. However, past vegetation coverage reconstruction remains difficult. Pollen records suggest that during the LGM, temperate grassland, xerophytic shrubland and desert dominated northern China, including the CLP (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>). Several sections on the CLP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> reveal the presence of desert/steppe vegetation on the plateau during the LGM, with more abundant Poaceae at the southwest. However, as pollen records largely represent large-scale regional vegetation changes, not at a particular locality, we thus here use TOC content as an indicator of vegetation cover at those study sites, previously proposed to reflect vegetation history and biomass variations on the CLP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TOC contents at Xifeng, Luochuan, Weinan, and Mangshan over the past 60 kyr show generally synchronous changes with the MS, as well as pollen-inferred vegetation changes in northern China and global climate but clearly decouple from the onsite LST changes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>). That is, the TOC-inferred vegetation cover gradually decreased and reached the lowest value during the LGM and then increased gradually in parallel with the monsoon intensity indicators such as MS/MGS (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>). The TOC-inferred vegetation variations on the CLP also indicate a decrease in vegetation coverage from southeast to northwest, in parallel with the reduction of EAM influence. As such, TOC contents at Luochuan and Xifeng sections remained &lt;0.3% throughout the last glacial period until the early Holocene, while being higher toward the southeastern CLP (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Previous published δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C-based precipitation reconstructions on the CLP are in high level of congruence with variations of TOC contents
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>, providing additional support for the EAM-controlled vegetation gradient on the CLP. It can thus be inferred that, during the past glacial period, particularly LGM, desert/steppe vegetation dominated the center CLP, such as Xifeng and Luochuan, whereas substantial vegetation cover still existed at Mangshan, the southeast CLP. The spatial trajectory of vegetation coverage change is also consistent with the pattern of early warming times recorded in our reconstructed LSTs (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These distinctive features captured in our LST reconstructions (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) can be explained by a combination of better understanding of the nature of the brGDGT proxy and considering the vegetation feedback on the CLP under the EAM influence, offering an opportunity to tease out the complicity of continental temperature reconstructions in Asian semi-humid and semi-arid regions. Because of the nature of the brGDGT proxy mentioned above, the influence of local vegetation variations on LSTs during bacterial growing seasons may be more pronounced on the relatively dry CLP, causing a large deviation from air temperatures. These factors become even more apparent when we closely examine our LST records in the context of overall features on the CLP.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies on loess–paleosol sections have demonstrated the importance of solar insolation on temperature variations on the south CLP, in addition to other potential drivers (e.g., atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> and Southern Hemisphere cooling)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. However, the obvious mismatch observed in our LST records indicates the existence of other factor(s) at working in modulating LSTs on the CLP. These five loess–paleosol sections are quite close geographically (~600 km between Mangshan and Xifeng) and have minor latitudinal differences, only ~1.5° from the southernmost Lantian to the northernmost Luochuan. Therefore, it is unlikely that the time difference in temperature rise was due to local insolation affected by orbital parameters or variations in greenhouse gas concentrations. The fact that the spatial distribution of these sections and the advancement of warming times correspond well with the reduction of EAM influence suggests a connection between these LST changes and a powerful covariant factor that is controlled by the EAM on the CLP.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We suggest that the EAM-controlled vegetation variations on the CLP have exerted an important influence on LST variations, and have thus tested this hypothesis in both spatial and temporal perspectives. Vegetation feedback on climate has been previously noticed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. Vegetation’s influence on air temperatures is believed to be relatively weak (probably &lt;2 °C), although modeling experiments have demonstrated that vegetation change is an important mechanism contributing to climate configurations during the mid-Holocene and the last interglacial period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. Such vegetation feedbacks can be intensified in soil layers in semi-humid and semi-arid regions, causing larger and amplified LST variations registered in brGDGT proxies, primarily due to heat transfer and influx balanced by the interaction between soil and vegetation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. The critical role that local vegetation variations have played in altering LSTs has also been illustrated in the following cases. A 12-month document recording daily soil temperatures from forest, woodland, and grassland sites in the Meru National Park in Kenya has well demonstrated an obvious influence of vegetation types on soil surface temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. While air temperatures remain similar in the park, open areas have daily high surface ground temperatures up to 25 °C higher than those at the nearby well-shaded areas, due to higher light intensity and lower soil moisture without woody canopy coverage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. The measured in situ surface soil temperatures obtained by temperature loggers placed at 11 soil study sites (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), as well as the 4 selected meteorological stations representing different vegetation zones in China (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>), also show that the difference between LSTs and air temperatures increases with reducing vegetation coverage, especially during soil bacterial growing seasons.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the way solar radiation is absorbed in soils varies, different underlying surfaces may affect the distribution of energy between the atmosphere and surface soil
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Vegetation changes can directly or indirectly influence spatial and temporal variations of soil temperatures in a number of ways through physiological activities underground and changing heat fluxes on and above ground through changing shading (measured by means such as leaf area index, projected leaf area per unit of ground area), ground litter stores, and soil and air moisture
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. Generally, two opposing vegetation feedback effects may occur on heat fluxes: warming through increased energy absorption (i.e., relatively low albedo) and cooling through increased evaporation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. The net impact of vegetation feedback (warming or cooling) that can be registered in the brGDGT-based proxy depends on which influence is predominant. Normally, loess stages developed during the cold-dry glacial periods with relatively low vegetation coverage. Cold air temperatures may have prevailed on the whole CLP as suggested by pollen records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. During these periods, however, the poor vegetation and low soil moisture facilitate more efficient heat absorption to warm up soil layers. This may explain why our brGDGT-derived LSTs are insensitive to the extremely cold air temperatures during the LGM, when the minimal vegetation cover resulted in a maximal difference between air temperatures and LSTs. All of our observed early LST warmings occurred within loess stages at regions with low TOC contents and soil δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C-based precipitation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>, corresponding to poor vegetation coverage toward the northwestern CLP. The longer warming duration and lower rates of temperature transitioning from glacials into interglacials recorded in our LST reconstructions at the center CLP appear to reflect a different land surface energy balance modulated by a significant vegetation feedback, resulting in the insensitivity of LST to air temperature changes. The large deviations (mean 6.0 °C) between modern land surface and air temperatures observed in regions with little vegetation cover (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>), similar to the temperature variations between glacials and interglacials (4–10 °C) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), further support that, in semi-humid and semi-arid regions, the brGDGT-based LSTs could have increased to a higher level, while air temperatures remained low during glacial periods, corresponding to the global signal.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of our LST records spanning the past 800 kyr in loess–paleosol sequences at the center CLP leads us to conclude that surface vegetation variations may have played a substantial role in regulating near-surface land temperatures. The complicity of interpreting terrestrial temperature records is manifested at our CLP case, while not fundamentally challenging the orbital (“Milankovitch”) theory of the Ice Ages. Well-constrained regional LST signals, such as the ones from our brGDGT-based reconstructions, can enrich our understanding of seemingly nonsynchronous climatic variations on land due to surface dynamics. This long neglected mechanism of terrestrial paleotemperature changes opens new windows for studies of terrestrial climate change, as well as improving projections of terrestrial climate. Our results confirm that LST changes in semi-humid and semi-arid regions with little vegetation cover are more sensitive to global warming and also reinforce one of the obvious, but less appreciated, beliefs that improving vegetation coverage on the CLP would help mitigate ecological impacts under the projected warming trend by reducing near-surface temperatures.</p>
</sec>
