<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The marine realm</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A meta-analysis of 144 studies showed that, on average, 37% of the ocean should be strongly protected (preferably in fully protected marine reserves) to achieve a number of goals: protect biodiversity, ensure connectivity, avoid species collapse and adverse evolution, ensure sustainable fisheries, and benefit multiple stakeholders (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>). More than 80% of these objectives can be met with 50% marine reserve protection (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>). With only 2% of the world’s ocean currently in fully to highly protected marine reserves (
  <a rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" href="#R59">
   <span class="italic">59</span>
  </a>), these estimates highlight enormous gaps in marine conservation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to biodiversity, marine ecosystems are also important carbon sinks. Coastal ecosystem such as mangroves, salt marshes, and seagrass beds sequester astonishing amounts of carbon per hectare and thus play a disproportionately large role in the global capture and storage of carbon (
  <a rid="R60" ref-type="bibr" href="#R60">
   <span class="italic">60</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R61" ref-type="bibr" href="#R61">
   <span class="italic">61</span>
  </a>). Although the spatial extent of the world’s 20 mangrove ecoregion complexes is minute compared to other biomes (300,294 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> or 0.23%), conservation and restoration of mangroves are vital to climate and marine conservation scenarios, and buffer storm surges and hurricanes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ocean also harbors old-growth ecosystems equivalent to primary forests, such as unfished seamounts with deep corals thousands of years old (
  <a rid="R62" ref-type="bibr" href="#R62">
   <span class="italic">62</span>
  </a>). In the coastal zone, some seagrass species such as the Mediterranean 
  <span class="italic">Posidonia oceanica</span> have complex belowground organs that help accrete sediment and bury carbon over millennia (
  <a rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" href="#R63">
   <span class="italic">63</span>
  </a>). Preserving the vegetative cover of these coastal habitats is important, but preserving their megafauna is essential, as studies suggest that intact predator populations are critical to maintaining or growing reserves of carbon stored in marine ecosystems (
  <a rid="R64" ref-type="bibr" href="#R64">
   <span class="italic">64</span>
  </a>). For example, tiger sharks in seagrass beds in Australia create a “landscape of fear,” where sea turtles and dugongs preferentially forage in seagrass microhabitats that are low in predation risk. The majority of the habitat, with high predation risk, has greater carbon stocks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ongoing efforts are identifying priority areas that will help protect biodiversity at multiple levels (from species to ecosystems), help produce food through fish spillover from fully protected reserves, and help mitigate climate change through the protection and restoration of important carbon sinks. Here, we present general targets and categories that should be prioritized as part of the GDN (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>). The current shortfalls in ocean protection are presented in a revised map of the coastal ecoregions and pelagic provinces of the world, alongside the global system of MPAs (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3, A and B</a>) (
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Coastal ecoregions, pelagic provinces, and marine protected areas of the world oceans.</div>
   <p> (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Coastal ecoregions and pelagic provinces. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Map of marine protected areas.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aaw2869-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
