<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Old-growth habitats</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before the industrial revolution, primary or old-growth habitats covered most of Earth’s 846 terrestrial ecoregions. Today, these primary habitats, as represented by unlogged forests, ungrazed deserts, ancient grasslands, and savannas—and in the marine realm, the untrawled seafloor and unfished seamounts—are now remnants. These ancient repositories of rich and vulnerable biodiversity are optimal arenas for life-sustaining processes (
  <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">
   <span class="italic">53</span>
  </a>). Clear, time-bound milestones and targets for the above biodiversity features, including targets for old-growth forests and ever-wet forests, are included in the GDN and are drawn from the scientific literature supporting each target (
  <a rid="T2" ref-type="table" href="#T2">Table 2</a>). Protecting habitats that have low anthropogenic disturbance offers the most cost-effective approach to conserve the largest number of species and also for their climate resilience and should become obvious targets under the GDN (
  <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">
   <span class="italic">54</span>
  </a>). As a prime example, tropical forests occur on only 7% of the land area, yet they harbor more than half of the world’s known species and most of these are dependent on primary forest (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R55" ref-type="bibr" href="#R55">
   <span class="italic">55</span>
  </a>). The buffering conditions of many complex “old-growth” habitats also enable local adaptation to climate change for many vulnerable species. These biologically important areas also serve as carbon repositories. For example, ancient grasslands are extremely species rich, including endemics (
  <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">
   <span class="italic">53</span>
  </a>), and they store approximately as much carbon globally as forests. Because most grassland carbon is stored belowground, it is a highly secure and reliable carbon sink, especially in the face of fire and other climate-sensitive disturbance factors (
  <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">
   <span class="italic">56</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
