<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study enhances our understanding of the gender gap previously identified in the climate change knowledge perceptions literature [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref032">32</a>], [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref033">33</a>]. Our results illustrate that the negative perceptions of climate change knowledge in women are correlated with higher educational attainment, and at lower levels of education, women actually self-report more knowledge than men. Although further research is required, previous studies find minorities have lower levels of assessed climate change knowledge [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref032">32</a>], and a lack of psycho-social support—which can lead to less engagement with scientific topics [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref067">67</a>], [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref071">71</a>]. Together with our findings, these studies may indicate the need for educational and psychological intervention on behalf of minorities in order to increase climate change literacy and perceptions of intelligence. A lack of confidence in one’s own knowledge can make educational efforts more effective by encouraging further knowledge seeking [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref018">18</a>], but a downside may emerge if highly educated women and minorities avoid starting conversations with others about climate change because they do not believe they understand the issue well enough. Encouraging knowledge-seeking behavior among women and minorities–who are less skeptical about climate change than white men [
  <a rid="pone.0210149.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210149.ref029">29</a>]–could help to increase concern and policy action in the politically polarized United States.
 </p>
</sec>
