<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant Material, Genome Sequencing, and Assembly.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seedlings of 
  <span class="italic">C. himalaica</span> were sampled from Batang County (altitude 4,010 m, N 30.313°, E 99.358°) of QTP. Seedlings from the same individual were cultivated in the greenhouse at Kunming Institute of Botany. High-quality genomic DNA was extracted using the Qiagen DNeasy Plant Mini Kit. The 
  <span class="italic">C. himalaica</span> genome assembly was performed using sequence data obtained from a combination of sequencing technologies: Illumina PE reads, Illumina MP reads, and PacBio RS II reads (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1817580116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
  </span>). The whole step of library construction and sequencing was performed at Novogene Bioinformatics Technology Co., Ltd. First, six PE libraries were prepared to sequence the 
  <span class="italic">C. himalaica</span> genome. These included two PE libraries with insert sizes of 250 and 450 bp and four MP libraries with insert sizes of 2, 5, 10 and 15 kb. Whole genomic sequence (44.49 Gb) data were generated solely using Illumina platforms (HiSEq. 2500) and assembled using ALLPATHS -LG (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>). Next, the PacBio reads (6.19 Gb) were used to fill gaps using the PBJelly2 tool (
  <a rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" href="#r16">16</a>), followed by scaffold assembly with SSPACE (
  <a rid="r82" ref-type="bibr" href="#r82">82</a>) using long-insert-size PE reads. The accuracy and completeness of the assemblies were assessed by aligning the reads from short-insert-size libraries back to the scaffolds using BWA-mem (v. 0.7.17) (
  <a rid="r83" ref-type="bibr" href="#r83">83</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
