<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par59">The stochastic modelling algorithm has nine steps. The first step is to determine 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>repeat</sub>, the time elapsed since intrusion of the previous sill: either specify 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>repeat</sub> a priori or allow 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>repeat</sub> to vary as a function of mantle plume flux, sill intrusion density data and sill province area data. Secondly, define a new sill–vent system by drawing eight random numbers for use in steps 3–5; physical properties thus specified remain fixed for subsequent time steps. Thirdly, determine new sill dimensions: define sill surface area 
 <italic>A</italic>, depth of intrusion 
 <italic>Z</italic>, maximum thickness 
 <italic>S</italic> and thickness profile exponent 
 <italic>β</italic> using the cumulative probability distributions in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Step 4 is to determine host-rock characteristics for the new sill: define the weight fraction that converts to methane 
 <italic>w</italic>
 <sub>CH4</sub> and the kerogen composition parameter 
 <italic>K</italic> using the cumulative probability distributions in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Step 5 is to determine thermogenic carbon generation parameters for the new sill: use the new thermogenic carbon emissions parameterisation to estimate the final mass of generated carbon 
 <italic>M</italic>
 <sub>therm</sub>(
 <italic>A, K</italic>, 
 <italic>S, Z, w</italic>
 <sub>CH4</sub>, 
 <italic>β</italic>), the emissions decay time 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>decay</sub>(
 <italic>S</italic>, 
 <italic>K</italic>, 
 <italic>Z</italic>) and the emissions decay exponent 
 <italic>p</italic>(
 <italic>S</italic>, 
 <italic>K</italic>, 
 <italic>Z</italic>) from the sill dimensions and host-rock characteristics obtained in steps 3 and 4. Step 6 is to determine new sill location, if required: determine polar coordinates based on the plume head model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup> and known sill province geography, determine aureole overlaps, and correct 
 <italic>M</italic>
 <sub>therm</sub> to avoid double-counting. Step 7 is to determine direct magma degassing carbon emissions parameters for the new sill: the final mass of degassed carbon 
 <italic>M</italic>
 <sub>magma</sub>(
 <italic>A, S</italic>) and the emissions decay time 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>solid</sub>(
 <italic>S</italic>, 
 <italic>Z</italic>) are estimated from the sill dimensions obtained in step 3. Step 8 is to determine carbon emissions flux and cumulative emitted carbon from the entire sill province by summing thermogenic emissions (
 <italic>q</italic>, 
 <italic>m</italic>)(
 <italic>M</italic>
 <sub>therm</sub>, 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>decay</sub>, 
 <italic>p</italic>, 
 <italic>t</italic>) and magma degassing emissions (
 <italic>q</italic>, 
 <italic>m</italic>)(
 <italic>M</italic>
 <sub>magma</sub>, 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>solid</sub>, 
 <italic>t</italic>) from all sill–vent systems that exist at this time step. Finally, repeat steps 1–8 as required: for fixed 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>repeat</sub>, the total number of sills is specified a priori; for variable 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>repeat</sub>, the calculation is continued until 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>repeat</sub> goes to infinity, thereby determining the total number of sills.
</p>
