<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both HOSUT effects and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment decreased the concentrations of free amino acids, storage proteins, and grain N in a similar way, although the effect was stronger for CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" class="xref">Fig. 6B</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="T4" class="xref">Table 4</xref>). Thus, yield increases, due to either HOSUT effects or CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment, were strongly associated with loss of grain quality, expressed as a percentage of grain N (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). It has been shown that CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment frequently reduces N concentrations in plants (
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taub 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>). The mechanisms responsible are dilution effects by increased production of non-structural carbohydrates, decreased root N uptake, reduced transpiration and N uptake with water mass flow from the soil, as well as improved photosynthetic N use efficiency by less N investment in Rubisco. Our results show that CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and HOSUT effects exert analogous C:N imbalances. However, line responses to N fertilization for ear biomass, grain yield, grains per pot, and harvest index indicate N stimulation preferentially for HOSUT. This could be due to the fact that HOSUT is optimized for assimilate transfer/mass flow especially towards grains and may profit from the additional N with respect to ears and grains (
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taub and Wang, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chapman 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>). This could finally improve grain yield, ear biomass, and grain number per plant. On the other hand, vegetative growth was preferentially stimulated in Certo by high N fertilization relative to HOSUT. The optimized N use is also underpinned by the fact that high N fertilization decreased the harvest index in Certo relative to HOSUT. High N fertilization in Certo stimulated vegetative growth and decreased the harvest index, whereas in HOSUT N could be used more efficiently due to improved transport to sinks, not only for sucrose but also for N.
</p>
