<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We purchased two groups of 10, eight-week old male veiled chameleon siblings through a private breeder (FL Chams, Florida, USA) in July 2011. Chameleons were initially housed in groups of five brothers in four identical cages (89 × 56 × 53 cm) with screen roofs and doors, feeding cups, and automated misters (which misted for three minutes, four times per day). All chameleons experienced a 12:12 light:dark cycle, and we provided each cage with a heat lamp (Zoo Med Repti-Basking Spot Lamp, 50 watt, Zoo Med laboratories Inc., San Luis Obispo, CA, USA) and a UV light source (Zoo Med Reptisun 5.0 UVB Fluorescent Bulbs, Zoo Med laboratories Inc., San Luis Obispo, CA, USA). Individual cage lamps were set to turn on 15 min after the room lights to simulate dawn and turn off 15 min before room lights to simulate dusk. We housed the chameleons in an indoor, climate-controlled room with the daily temperature range set to 25.0-27.2°C and an average humidity of 25-35%.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All cages were furnished with grape vines (
   <span class="italic">Vitis</span> spp.), yellow palo verde (
   <span class="italic">Parkinsonia microphylla</span>) branches, and faux vines to provide perches at various heights for thermoregulation under the heat lamps [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>]. Space limitations necessitated that we place chameleon cages in two tiers, with one group of 10 brothers (hereafter, family A) occupying the upper cages of our stacked racks and the remaining group of brothers (family B) occupying the lower cages. All members of each family were kept at the same relative height throughout the duration of the study to minimize within-family differences in housing conditions and maximize our ability to detect any effects of carotenoid supplementation. After an eight week acclimation period, we moved all chameleons into individual cages to prevent excessive aggression [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>]. During both the acclimation and experimental periods, we fed the chameleons crickets dusted with calcium (
   <span class="italic">Rep-Cal</span> Phosphorus-free Calcium, 0% D3, Rep-Cal Research Labs, Los Gatos, CA, USA) and vitamins (Zoo Med Reptivite Reptile Vitamins, Zoo Med Laboratories Inc., San Luis Obispo, CA, USA) throughout the study. Wild chameleons have access to a broader array of dietary items, so the limited diversity of commercially available food items necessitates dietary supplements such as these [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>]. Reptivite vitamins contained no measurable quantities of any carotenoid.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four weeks into the eight-week acclimation period, we acquired pre-supplementation baseline values for wound healing, agglutination and lysis, and plasma carotenoid levels (see below) and randomly assigned half of each group of brothers to the carotenoid-supplemented (C) group and the remaining animals to the control group (non-supplemented = N). This arrangement resulted in four distinct groups, two supplemented family groups (AC and BC) and two control family groups (AN and BN). During weeks 8-21 of the study, supplemental carotenoids were given twice weekly in the form of an oral administration of powdered 10% lutein (FloraGLO Lutein 10% CWS/S-TG, Kemin Industries, Inc., Des Moines, IA) dissolved in 1 mL of warm (~ 46°C) distilled water. Warm water was required to break down the starch-based transport molecules containing the carotenoids and create a homogenous solution for oral supplementation. To control for potential effects of handling stress and hydration state, the control group received oral supplementations of 1 mL of warm distilled water. We weighed each chameleon to the nearest 0.01 g with an electronic balance each time we administered the carotenoid and water solutions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determination of carotenoid supplementation levels</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the dearth of literature regarding the carotenoid content in circulation or in the diet of wild veiled chameleons, we identified and quantified the carotenoids present in a selection of arthropods collected from LaBelle, FL, USA, in a habitat known to contain a feral population of veiled chameleons, as a means of determining an appropriate dietary carotenoid dose to administer in our experiment (Additional file 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>: Table S1). We desiccated the dead arthropods in a 40°C drying oven overnight before pulverizing them (first with a mortar and pestle, then a micronizer) in ethanol until homogenized; from this homogenate, we then extracted carotenoids as described below [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B47" href="#B47">47</a>]. We found that lutein made up the largest portion (28%) of total carotenoids in the wild arthropods and on average made up 48.20 (± s.e. 21.10) μg/g of a food item. Additionally, lutein was the predominant carotenoid circulating in the plasma of unmanipulated chameleons, representing 88.6% of the total circulating carotenoids. Therefore, to elevate carotenoid levels above those in a typical chameleon diet, we administered a concentration of lutein that corresponded to one standard deviation (63.30 μg/g) above this average (48.20 + 63.30 = 111.50 μg/g), calculated using the average mass of crickets eaten per day per individual in our captive colony. Initially, we provided all chameleons 10 half-inch crickets per day (average cricket mass = 76.68 mg, average total mass consumed = 766.79 mg), but as the chameleons grew and regularly consumed all food items provided we increased this to 15 adult crickets per day (average mass = 288.61 mg, average total mass consumed = 4.33 g) in Week 10. Therefore, for the first two weeks of treatment (Weeks 8-10), the chameleons received a dose of 854.93 μg of 10% lutein in 1 mL of water (an effective dose of 85.49 μg of lutein), and thereafter were given 4826.70 μg of 10% lutein in 1 mL (an effective dose of 482.67 μg of lutein). For reference, previous studies examining the effects of carotenoid supplementation on lizards have typically administered lower levels of carotenoids (e.g. 0.084 ug/supplementation for brown anoles 
   <span class="italic">Norops sagrei</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B48" href="#B48">48</a>] and 20 ug/supplementation for Australian painted dragon lizards 
   <span class="italic">Ctenophorous pictus</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B49" href="#B49">49</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blood collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess circulating carotenoid levels and some aspects of immunity, we drew blood five times during the study – once prior to carotenoid supplementation (Week 4) and at four other times during the supplementation period (Weeks 11, 14, 17, and 20; Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>). At each collection point, we collected up to 0.1% of each chameleon’s body mass of blood from the caudal vein with a 0.3 cc heparinized syringe and kept this blood on ice until centrifugation (5 min at 10,000 rpm). After centrifugation, we drew off plasma and stored it at -80°C for subsequent analyses (see below).
  </p>
  <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Timeline of carotenoid supplementation, blood collection, and dermal biopsies during our study.</span> During Week 4 of the study, blood was collected from all individuals to establish initial values for circulating carotenoid, agglutination, and lysis titers prior to supplementation (
     <span class="italic">Blood Collection 1</span>). Additionally, biopsy X
     <sub>0</sub> was performed during Week 4 of the study to determine the post-wounding time points with the greatest variation in wound area (to focus subsequent wound healing analyses). In Week 8 of the study, carotenoid supplementation commenced. Every three weeks during the supplementation period, blood was collected to measure circulating carotenoid levels and agglutination and lysis titers (
     <span class="italic">Blood Collections 2-5</span>). At weeks 14 and 20 of the study, we biopsied (X
     <sub>1</sub>, X
     <sub>2</sub>) the chameleons to evaluate wound healing. Wound healing rates were determined by measuring wound area from photographs taken immediately after biopsies, and on days 6 and 10 after wounding. Furthermore, we evaluated circulating nitric oxide levels by collecting blood samples immediately before, and again two days, after each biopsy.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1742-9994-11-26-2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carotenoid extraction and analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-performance liquid chromatographic analyses of carotenoids followed previously published methods [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B47" href="#B47">47</a>], with the following modifications. We sequentially extracted carotenoids from 20 μL of thawed plasma with 200 μL of both ethanol and 1:1 hexane:tert-butyl methyl ether, then vortexed the extract briefly before centrifugation for 3 min at 10,000 rpm. We transferred the supernatant to a fresh, labeled tube and then evaporated it to dryness under nitrogen and stored it at -80°C. We resuspended samples in 200 μL of HPLC mobile phase (42:42:16, v/v/v, methanol:acetonitrile:dicholoromethane) and vortexed them until all pigment was visibly suspended. By comparing their retention times and absorbance maxima to external standards and published specifications [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>], we identified the following carotenoid pigments in chameleon plasma: lutein, cis lutein isomers, zeaxanthin and three canary xanthophylls (A-C). We determined pigment concentrations by integrating the peaks and by comparing these areas to a standard curve. Concentrations of all carotenoid types were significantly and positively correlated with each other (all r &gt; 0.76, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.0001, Additional file 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2" href="#S2">2</a>: Table S2), indicating that our supplementation of lutein also influenced circulating levels of all measured carotenoid types. Therefore, we used total circulating carotenoid concentration in all subsequent analyses to better understand the general importance of carotenoids, as opposed to just lutein, on immunity in growing chameleons.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agglutination and lysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the effect of carotenoid supplementation on immune system performance in juvenile chameleons, we used a modified version of the agglutination and lysis assay described by Matson et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>], which is a highly repeatable and informative way to measure the strength of the humoral components of the constitutive innate immune system (specifically, antibodies and complement enzymes; [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>]). We made two modifications to the procedure described by Matson et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>] based on pilot work to maximize our ability to detect inter-individual variation: 1) we reduced the concentration of the SRBC suspensions in this assay from 1% to 0.5% and 2) the incubation temperature was decreased from 37°C to 26.5°C. This temperature change allowed the assay incubation to more accurately reflect the ambient temperature in which study animals were housed (range 25.0 - 27.2°C), as has been done previously with ectotherms [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B51" href="#B51">51</a>] and which is important because incubation temperature plays a significant role in agglutination and lysis [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B52" href="#B52">52</a>]. After incubation for 90 min, the plates were tilted for 20 min at 45° to permit visualization of the agglutination response, then digitally scanned at a resolution of 600 dpi. After scanning, the plates were laid out on a flat surface for 70 min before scanning a second time to record the lysis response. This assay thus identifies the plasma dilution at which agglutination (clumping of sRBC) and lysis (destruction of sRBC) occur due to innate immune mechanisms. The assessments of two independent investigators, blind to treatment, family, and individual, were significantly repeatable [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>] for both agglutination (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.990
   <span class="italic">, P</span> &lt; 0.0001) and lysis (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.989
   <span class="italic">, P</span> &lt; 0.0001), so we used the average of these scores for all subsequent statistical analyses. Because agglutination and lysis were highly positively correlated and are at least partially mechanistically linked [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>], we performed principal components analyses (PCA) to collapse agglutination and lysis scores into a single metric (with two metrics, this is the covariation between the two). The agglutination and lysis scores for chameleons during development reduced to a single principal component that explained 98% of the variation among these variables (agglutination loading, 0.71, lysis loading, 0.71). Therefore, individuals with high positive PC1 scores exhibited strong agglutination and lysis responses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wound healing</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We took dermal biopsies from each chameleon at three time points during the study and recorded changes in wound area using digital photography [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] and image processing and analysis freeware (ImageJ64, NIH [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">54</a>]). We collected dermal biopsies using a standardized procedure based on a previous wound healing study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>], though we modified biopsy placement to better suit chameleon morphology. Immediately after blood collection, we anesthetized each chameleon using isoflurane, then disinfected the biopsy site with isopropyl alcohol and removed a circular section of the epidermis and dermis near the hip using a 3.5 mm biopsy punch. After wounding, pressure was applied for three minutes or until bleeding was stopped before the wound was photographed. We conducted the first biopsy (X
   <sub>0</sub>) and all associated wound photography (Weeks 4-7) before carotenoid supplementation began. We performed two other biopsies adjacent to, but not at, the location of previous biopsies during the supplementation period at predetermined time points corresponding to the middle (Biopsy 1 = X
   <sub>1</sub>; Week 14) and end (Biopsy 2 = X
   <sub>2</sub>; Week 20) of the study. The second biopsy (X
   <sub>1</sub>) was conducted on the opposite side of the body as the first biopsy (X
   <sub>0</sub>), and the third biopsy (X
   <sub>2</sub>) was on the same side as biopsy X
   <sub>0</sub>, separated by approximately 8 mm.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All wounds were photographed in a standardized fashion to control for angle and distance, as well as to improve repeatability. Chameleons were manually restrained during photography sessions and all photographs were taken with a digital camera (Panasonic HDC-TM700P/PC, Panasonic Corporation, Kadoma, Osaka, Japan) on a small tripod. We positioned light sources to best illuminate the wound area and elevated a ruler to be level with the wound for setting scale in later image analysis. A minimum of four photographs were taken of each wound, ensuring at least two were zoomed in as close as possible without compromising focus.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After X
   <sub>0</sub>, we monitored and photographed all wounds every other day, beginning on the day of biopsy (D
   <sub>0</sub>), until at least one chameleon’s wound was fully healed (i.e., biopsy site was completely covered in smooth, gray scar tissue or new colorful epidermis). From a subset of these photographs, we determined two time-points (Day 6 = D
   <sub>6</sub> and Day 10 = D
   <sub>10</sub>) during the healing process that yielded the greatest variation in wound size, suggesting that wound measurements taken on these days during future biopsies would be most likely to capture inter-individual variation in wound healing rate.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All wound photographs were viewed in ImageJ64 to assess the size of the wound (mm
   <span class="sup">2</span>), with the investigator blind to sampling date, treatment, and chameleon identity (ImageJ64, NIH [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">54</a>]). Based on French et al.’s [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] study in tree lizards (
   <span class="italic">Urosaurus ornatus</span>), we used the area of the wound as a measure of wound healing (where area was the most reliable metric because wounds healed in a non-uniform manner and irregular closure of wounds was common). Specifically, the area of any portion of the biopsy site that was considered unhealed “wound” (i.e., textured or deep red) was measured (Additional file 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3" href="#S3">3</a>: Figure S1). On every occasion of wound measurement, at least two photos with both a well-focused ruler and wound were analyzed and the wound areas averaged. We calculated the repeatability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>] of wound sizes during one round of wound healing and found that wound size (mm
   <span class="sup">2</span>) was significantly repeatable for all chameleons (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.97, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nitric oxide assays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed the change in NO during the course of each wounding to measure the magnitude of the chameleon innate immune response [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. We collected blood immediately before wounding (and anesthetization) and two days after wounding, in an attempt to sample animals near the peak of the NO burst (as determined by [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>] in mammals), and stored 50 μL of the plasma fraction at -80°C until NO assays could be performed. The NO assay was conducted as described by Butler and McGraw [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B56" href="#B56">56</a>], adapted from [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. We first deproteinized 15 μL of plasma in 40 μL of zinc sulfate (75 mM) and 50 μL of sodium hydroxide (55 mM), then centrifuged the samples for 10 min at 16,000 RPM. We combined 80 μL of the supernatant with 80 μL of glycine buffer (pH 9.7) before adding two activated cadmium granules and vortexing the samples for 15 min. Next, we combined 120 μL of supernatant with 120 μL of Greiss reagent (Sigma G4410-10G) before vortexing for another 15 min. Finally, we transferred 200 μL of each sample into a 96-well plate and used an iMark Microplate Reader (Bio-Rad Laboratories, UK) to measure the absorbance of each well at λ = 540 nm. Using the standard curves run with each assay, we converted absorbance values to concentrations of plasma NO.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test if circulating carotenoid levels, body mass, NO levels, agglutination and lysis titers, and wound-healing rate differed as a function of carotenoid treatment, family, age, and all interactions, we ran repeated-measures analysis of variance (rmANOVA) models. Because we were interested in the relationship between circulating carotenoid levels and NO levels, agglutination performance, and lysis performance within individuals regardless of dietary access to carotenoids, we also ran 
   <span class="italic">post hoc</span> analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) models within each treatment group and sampling period, with circulating carotenoid levels as the covariate, family as a fixed effect, and NO levels and agglutination and lysis PC1 values as dependent variables. Because of potential dilution effects of circulating carotenoids as body size increases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B57" href="#B57">57</a>], we tested whether body mass affected circulating carotenoid concentration by performing simple linear regressions within each treatment group. We were also interested in the relationship between body mass and circulating carotenoid levels, and agglutination and lysis titers; however, body mass of individuals was significantly different between families (see below). Therefore, to ensure that both mass and family terms were not explaining the same variance, we ran 
   <span class="italic">post hoc</span> ANCOVAs within each sampling period and family, with mass as the covariate, treatment as the independent variable, and wound size and agglutination and lysis titers as dependent variables. We used SAS 9.2 (Cary, NC) for all analyses and, when the assumption of sphericity was violated (Greenhouse-Geisser Epsilon &lt; 0.7), we interpreted the G-G adjusted p-value (
   <span class="italic">P</span>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For most of the study, every chameleon was measured at every sampling period. However, an unanticipated infection forced us to eliminate one individual (group AC) from the Week 17 blood collection and biopsy 2. Additionally, problems with photo clarity and wound scabbing prohibited accurate wound area measurement in some photographs, resulting in the elimination of two individuals from biopsy X
   <sub>0</sub> (one each from groups BC and BN) and four individuals from biopsy X
   <sub>1</sub> (one from AC and three from BC); hence we had to eliminate each of these six animals from our full repeated-measures analysis. Thus, we ran a mixed-models analysis for comparison; unlike rm-ANOVA, mixed-models allow for the incorporation of all data points from a subject, even if observations are missing for that subject.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
