<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Information obtained from each model was projected in order to identify potential areas under current climatic conditions and the scenario of the climate change RCP85‐2070. We used projections to the year 2070 employing the environmental variables records available on the WorldClim database, which are calculated from future climate projections of General Circulation Models (Hijmans et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). The RCP 85 assumes that global greenhouse gas concentration trajectories will continue to rise throughout the XXI century and will stabilize in the year 2100 (Meinshausen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). We evaluated MaxEnt model performance using a fifteen‐fold cross‐validation of the area under the curve (AUC) of the receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC). Models with an AUC score of 0.5 indicated a model performing randomly, while models with an AUC score of 1 indicated a perfect model (Lobo, Jiménez‐Valverde, &amp; Real, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Phillips, Dudik, &amp; Schapire, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). The best model among the 15 cross‐validations for each species (the model with the highest AUC) was converted into a binary map (presence‐absence), using the logistic threshold considering maximum training sensitivity plus specificity, which had the best characteristics for each model. These conversions were performed in ArcMap version 10.3. Finally, to assess the impact of climate change in 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic>, the percentage of change between current and future conditions was obtained using the formula: % of change = [(S1–S0)/S0]*100%, where S0 is the suitable area for each species according to the baseline scenario and S1 is the suitable area for each species under future climatic conditions (Gutiérrez &amp; Trejo, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
