<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured barn swallows on 12–16 February 2012 at a nocturnal roosting site in the remote village of Boje, eastern Nigeria (6°17’26” N, 8°55’51”E) (see also 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-57" href="#ref-57">Saino et al., 2013</a>). This site is a traditional roosting place of hundreds of thousands of barn swallows wintering in the area at least since 1996 (P Micheloni, unpublished data), but likely much earlier times. Ring recoveries have shown that this wintering area receives swallows originating from or breeding in at least twelve, mostly western or central European countries. Sampling at a roost to study molt of barn swallows and its temporal change has also been adopted in previous studies (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-45" href="#ref-45">Møller et al., 1995</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-46" href="#ref-46">Møller et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-64" href="#ref-64">van den Brink, Bijlsma &amp; van der Have, 2000</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To get a picture of the association between molt and 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotype around completion of molt of the primary wing feathers (hereafter “primaries”) shortly before spring migration, we decided to conduct the study in mid-February, when 40%–50% of the birds have normally completed molt (P Micheloni, unpublished data). However, we also aimed at retaining variation in molt stages in the sample and we therefore a priori decided to collect a sample composed for 3/4 by birds that were still actively molting their wing feathers and for 1/4 by birds that had completed molt. Individuals within these categories were then sampled randomly. For the purposes of this study, each primary (excluding the vestigial P10; P1–P9 were counted outwards, so that P1 was the innermost of the 10 primaries) was scored for molt stage using a standard 6 levels (0–5) discrete scale (0: presence of the old feather; 5: fully grown new feather; 1–4: progressively increasing development of the growing feather) (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21" href="#ref-21">Ginn &amp; Melville, 1983</a>). Molt scoring was performed by very well-trained bird ringers (C S, R L &amp; P M) and was done blind of 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotype. A total molt score (TMS) was then calculated as the sum of the molt scores of P1-P9 of the right wing, as very high symmetry in the progress of molt between the wings was observed among the first 60 birds that were sampled. Because TMS is computed on nine primaries on a 0–5 scale, its values range between 0 (no growing new feather) and 45 ( = 9 × 5) when all 9 primaries have been molted.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Age (yearling vs. older) was not considered because several yearlings could have completed molt and were therefore indistinguishable from older individuals. However, we can see no reason to speculate that our sampling protocol resulted in different odds of sampling individuals with a different 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotype according to their age. Before releasing the swallows, we collected a small (ca. 40 µl) blood sample for molecular sexing and 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotyping purposes. Molecular sexing based on the 
  <span class="italic">CHD</span> gene and 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotyping were done according to protocols that we published and were replicated here (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-55" href="#ref-55">Saino, Martinelli &amp; Romano, 2008</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11" href="#ref-11">Caprioli et al., 2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We carefully scrutinized our sampling approach in search of potential sources of bias and, in particular, we considered the possibility that pre-migratory movements, whereby particular classes of individuals (e.g. those that had completed molt) left the roost before we did our sampling, could bias the results. Obviously, because the roost included hundreds of thousands of swallows, we could not monitor all the individuals and how the composition of the roost changed, if it did. However, until February, the roost has constant size (P Micheloni, unpublished data), which then increases in March when barn swallows wintering farther south stop in the area before resuming migration and cross the Sahara. Importantly, the roost is very close (ca. 2° in latitude corresponding to ca. 200 km) to the northern limit of the wintering range of barn swallows, as identified based on all the information on ring recoveries of wintering barn swallows in Africa available to date in the EURING database and encompassing several decades (see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-3" href="#ref-3">Ambrosini et al., 2011</a>). Moreover, recently acquired information from geolocators suggests that during wintering, including February when the present study was conducted, adult (i.e. more than 1-year old) barn swallows, which are the first to complete molt (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-46" href="#ref-46">Møller et al., 2011</a>), are sedentary. Hence, in February barn swallows do not occur north of the region where the study was conducted and do not show pre-migratory movements. Moreover, during February the roost is known to retain constant size (see also Methods), suggesting no “leakage” of individuals or that individuals that leave the roost are replaced by newcomers (but see above) that have also completed molt and should therefore not bias the sample. Other arguments (including e.g. similarity of the proportions of male and females that had or, respectively, had not completed molt) that corroborate the idea that sampling did not bias the results are presented in 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-57" href="#ref-57">Saino et al. (2013)</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
