<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study organism</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The barn swallow is a small (ca. 18 g), long-distance migratory, aerially insectivorous passerine bird. Individuals breeding in Europe winter in sub-Saharan Africa, exhibiting significant migratory connectivity (i.e. individuals breeding in the same geographical area tend also to winter in the same area) (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-44" href="#ref-44">Møller, 1994</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-13" href="#ref-13">Cramp, 1998</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-2" href="#ref-2">Ambrosini, Møller &amp; Saino, 2009</a>). A single annual molt of remiges (wing feathers) and rectrices (tail feathers) occurs, mostly in the African winter quarters (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-21" href="#ref-21">Ginn &amp; Melville, 1983</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-13" href="#ref-13">Cramp, 1998</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-64" href="#ref-64">van den Brink, Bijlsma &amp; van der Have, 2000</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-62" href="#ref-62">Turner, 2006</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-33" href="#ref-33">Jenni &amp; Winkler, 1994</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-1" href="#ref-1">Altwegg et al., 2012</a>). Primary wing feathers, which are at the focus of the present study because they are the most aerodynamically important, are molted sequentially starting from the innermost one (P1). Barn swallows start arriving in Europe by mid-March but late individuals can arrive as late as May–June. Females tend to arrive later than males but the difference in arrival date is small (ca. 5 days) (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-44" href="#ref-44">Møller, 1994</a>). Autumn migration in Europe mostly occurs in September–October.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Low polymorphism has been recorded at 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> in seven breeding barn swallow populations (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-19" href="#ref-19">Dor et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11" href="#ref-11">Caprioli et al., 2012</a>; N Saino, M Caprioli &amp; AP Møller, unpublished data). Yet, in an Italian population where the association between 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> and breeding phenology has been investigated, females with a rare (
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>7</sub>/
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>8</sub>) genotype have been observed to delay breeding, with negative consequence on seasonal reproductive success. In addition, frequency of 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>7</sub>/
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>8</sub> is higher among yearlings than among two or more years old individuals, suggesting that 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> affects breeding phenology in this species and selection occurs against a rare, phenologically deviant genotype (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="ref-11" href="#ref-11">Caprioli et al., 2012</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
