<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is a truism, but unfortunately not true: policy-relevant climate information should be communicated such that non-scientists can understand. Through their assessment reports, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) periodically assesses global climate research, and creates “Summaries for Policymakers” (SPM) which constitute a synopsis of the most policy-relevant findings. The SPMs' main principles include being “audience-appropriate” and “policy-relevant but not policy-prescriptive” (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1998</xref>). To do justice to these principles, the communicated climate science must deliver an optimal basis for decision-making by non-scientists. However, SPMs are written in a highly scientific style. In a recent linguistic analysis, SPMs' readability proved to be extremely low, scoring even below scientific publications (Barkemeyer et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). There is, however, reason to believe that more effective climate communication is possible. Recent research has shown that despite a long-held skepticism (e.g., Sterman, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>), accessible presentation formats can increase understanding of the dynamically complex determinants of climate change (Fischer et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Importantly, the communication of highly scientific topics such as climate change or health is generally either intended to promote predefined behavior change in the recipient (e.g., anti- smoking-campaigns; messages that aim at the reduction of red meat consumption), or may induce premature closure around specific strategies by unintentionally shaping public discourse and opinion (Amelung and Funke, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Because SPMs should not be policy-prescriptive, however, they should enable informed decision-making without promoting specific response strategies or unintentionally and prematurely narrowing down public debates.
</p>
