<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Epigenetic studies in isogenic populations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an attempt to link epigenetic variation with phenotypic discordance in MZ twins, gene expression at the genomic scale has also been studied using a large group of MZ twins (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">Fraga et al. 2005</a>). Global and locus-specific 5mC DNA methylation, and acetylation of histones 3 and 4 were analyzed in lymphocytes of 15 male and 25 female MZ twin sets. The results showed that 65% of twins had almost identical epigenetic characteristics but that 35% had divergent characteristics and that the widest divergence was seen in older twins and those with divergent lifestyles. Microarray analysis of gene expression appeared to confirm these findings. The essential point of this article is that it shows that epigenetic differences between individuals correlate with gene expression differences in the presence of the same genetic background. Discordance between MZ twins with respect to occurrence of schizophrenia led to attempts to attribute this to epigenetic variation. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">Petronis et al. (2003)</a>, using evidence from two pairs of twins, one pair being discordant for schizophrenia, claimed proof of principle that multiple epigenetic differences exist between MZ twins (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">Petronis et al. 2003</a>). The study analyzed the promoter region of a single gene with methods rarely used by others; thus, the conclusions await independent confirmation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is likely that further twin studies, as well as studies in isogenic mice, will expand our understanding of the association between epigenetics and phenotype in mammals. For example, studies of gene expression in large sets of MZ twins, ideally discordant for some phenotypic character such as a genetically determined incompletely penetrant disease, could provide the groundwork for further studies to link epigenotype to gene expression and/or biological phenotype.</p>
</sec>
