<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Underlying genetic instability could be a confounding effect</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the preceding sections it is evident that the scientific community is still at the very edge of understanding the impact of epigenetics on phenotypic variation. In outbred populations, recombination and the existence of innumerable SNPs could theoretically alter epigenetic regulation of genes by altering the potential for DNA methylation and chromatin-associated protein attachment to loci. Further complicating this is the recent realization of extensive large-scale and fine-scale structural variation in mouse and human genomes (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">Crawford et al. 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">Iafrate et al. 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">McVean et al. 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">Myers et al. 2005</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">Sebat et al. 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">Tuzun et al. 2005</a>). This variation includes deletions, inversions, insertions, copy-number variation, and duplication of large genome segments. Over 25,000 recombination hotspots were recently identified in the human genome, occurring preferentially within 50 kb of genes and not within transcribed domains (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">Myers et al. 2005</a>). Structural variation has been identified as the source of phenotypic variation mediating human response to the environment, proof of principle that structural variation is important in human biology (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">Gonzalez et al. 2005</a>). It is not known what effect this might have on regulatory sequences subject to epigenetic control, and it could be argued that structural changes leading to altered epigenetic regulation of genes are at heart a genetic cause of variation. However, this problem remains theoretical in the absence of a deeper understanding of the epigenome and its behavior. It is interesting to note that naturally occurring transgenerational epigenetic inheritance in plants occurs at repeat sequences or at repeat arrays of transgenes (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">Zilberman and Henikoff 2005</a>). Perhaps, in mammalian genomes, other repeat types, in addition to the known retrotransposon examples, might also be reasonable candidates for epigenetic modification and transgenerational inheritance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important question stemming from the investigation of epigenetic heritability is can epigenotype be selected in an evolutionary sense? Data from the plant world suggest that epigenetically determined phenotypic variability allows plants to respond rapidly to environmental change, potentially allowing survival and reproduction until genetic change can provide more stable adaptation or until the environment reverts to the previous state (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">Finnegan 2002</a>). The mouse and human data presented here are not really able to address this idea. What sort of data might be compatible with the notion of evolutionary selection of an epigenetically determined variation? An intriguing observation of heritable phenotypic plasticity in birds provides clues as to the sort of study that might provide insight into epigenetic inheritance and selection (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">Nussey et al. 2005</a>). Nussey and colleagues analyzed the variability in reproductive timing in a population of great tits, 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>, across 30 generations in the wild. Reproductive timing in these birds is highly plastic in response to spring temperatures, with signficant variation between birds in the plasticity of the response. Coincident with changes in climate and food availability over the observation period, selection as measured by lifetime reproductive success has favored more plastic birds who are better able to synchronize egg laying with climate and hence food availability.
 </p>
</sec>
