<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Considering the increasing incidence of a multitude of childhood diseases, awareness of diseases that alter thermoregulatory responses, recent illness, specific medications, and mental retardation (for example, a compromised ability to recognize dangers of heat, not rehydrating) are also important. Education surrounding behavioral thermoregulation is vital, including seeking shade, requesting help when needed, and using cool water and damp towels to help to reduce body temperature during hyperthermia. Sunscreen should be applied to reduce acute effects of UV radiation on cutaneous vascular responses in the heat and avoid sunburn. Clothing insulation and requirements in children in varying environmental conditions are beyond the scope of this review but are an important consideration. Readers are directed to other excellent reviews [
 <xref rid="B211-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>]. Emerging evidence highlights the complex interplay between multiple stressors, modulating physiological responses, and, therefore, morbidity and mortality risk. Exposure to increasing global temperatures necessitates consideration of heat stress in cumulative risk assessment [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], due to potential temperature-related modulation of toxicity of air pollution and other abundant chemicals, for example, pesticides [
 <xref rid="B174-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>], exacerbating health effects. Children are exposed to many physical and chemical stressors, including heat, UV radiation, sunlight, noise, infection, psychosocial stressors, and pollution. Long-term exposure may facilitate earlier progression to clinical disease, altered physiological responses versus those observed in healthy children, and ultimately premature mortality. The long-term impact of multiple environmental–physiological factors on physiological function are currently not fully understood. Combined efforts between thermal physiologists, epidemiologists, climate physiologists, and regulatory bodies/policymakers are necessary to produce more comprehensive heat protection policies, incorporating technology, clothing, and behavioral adaptations as global climate change advances and limits of human tolerance are reached [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].
</p>
