<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2dot3-ijerph-12-12941" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3. Data Collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Delphi process consisted of two rounds and was completed in 2012. In 
  <span class="bold">Round 1</span>: the Communiqué comprising the workshop delegates’ priorities, a participant information sheet and a semi-structured questionnaire were emailed to an international sample of experts who had not attended the workshop. The questionnaire asked participants to: (i) state what, if any, broad research priority areas they believed were missing from the Communiqué; and (ii) suggest at least one but no more than three priority research questions that would address one or more knowledge deficits in the overlap between climate change and NCD prevention and which would be feasible to conduct (see questionnaire at 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="bold">Round 2</span> questionnaire consisted of the responses to Round 1 after removal of duplicates and arranged in categories. It was emailed with an explanatory letter and instructions to respondents from Round 1 who were asked to either: (i) exclude or include the priority research areas identified in Round 1; and (ii) to rank each included question as either high, medium or low priority (see questionnaire at 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ijerph-12-12941-s001" href="#ijerph-12-12941-s001">Figure S4</a>). Specifically, participants were requested to identify those areas and questions that: 
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">-</span>
    <p>were of central importance to the global response to NCD prevention and climate change;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">-</span>
    <p>addressed a knowledge or evidence deficit that is preventing progress in an area of high importance to the overlap between mitigating or adapting to climate change and preventing or significantly reducing the impact of NCDs and/or which focused on social and health justice issues;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">-</span>
    <p>addressed problems at the interface between NCDs and climate change which may be amenable to modification through legal interventions;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">-</span>
    <p>had a degree of urgency or immediacy.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
