<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results also go beyond previous studies in revealing the outsized role of more intense climate extremes in future climate-driven air pollution mortality in China. In total, increases in future atmospheric stagnation events contribute 68% to the climate-driven increase in PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> concentration and 39% to the increase in air pollution-related mortality (incorporating a much smaller effect on ozone concentrations) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S6
 </ext-link>). These estimates bear out the suggestions of previous studies that increasingly frequent stagnation events could negatively impact human health (
 <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). Although less important than stagnation due to fewer event days, increases in future heat waves have a large effect on ozone concentrations, totaling 14% of the climate-driven ozone increase we project and 6% of the increase in air pollution-related mortality (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S6
 </ext-link>). In contrast, increases in future heavy precipitation events reduce 6% of the climate-driven air pollution-related mortality (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S6
 </ext-link>). Our results reveal the large effect of these climate extremes on PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> and the less pronounced effect on ozone (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S6
 </ext-link>), indicating that PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> increases dramatically under extreme conditions, while the ozone increases might be prevalent under both extreme and mean conditions due to climate warming. Given the substantial contribution from extreme weather events to the modeled increase in air pollution (especially PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>) and mortality, as well as the dominant role that extreme weather events play in the increase in extreme haze events, we suggest that extreme weather events may be an important mechanism by which climate change will affect air quality, and especially PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>.
</p>
