<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our findings here are subject to several important limitations and sources of uncertainty. First, given the high-resolution and computationally intensive methodology, our simulations are limited to a single climate-chemistry model. However, our finding that future climate change is likely to exacerbate China’s air pollution is broadly consistent with numerous previous studies (
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>) that used independent models and methods. In particular, several studies have indicated that weather conditions conducive to extreme haze will likely occur at a higher frequency in China under climate change as a result of large-scale circulation changes caused by the Arctic sea ice decline and the weakening of the East Asian winter monsoon (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>). Yet, the original air stagnation index adopted by Cai et al. (
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>) and Horton et al. (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>) does not capture the wintertime frequent haze events in China (
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>). By adopting a new air stagnation index (
 <italic class="italic">Methods</italic>), we find that stagnation can identify a large fraction of severe haze events in China (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S5
 </ext-link>). The increased frequency of stagnation events is consistent with the more frequent weather conditions conducive to extreme haze as reported by previous studies (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>). Previous studies reveal 3 potential pathways linking midlatitude weather extremes to Arctic amplification, including changes in storm tracks, the jet stream, and planetary waves (
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>), although there is not yet consensus regarding the Arctic linkages (
 <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>). Several studies have suggested that amplified planetary waves favor weather extremes in midlatitudes (
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>).
</p>
