<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-vetsci-06-00040" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The epidemiology of infectious diseases is constantly fluctuating in response to environmental changes and changing interactions among hosts, reservoirs, vectors, and pathogens. This is particularly true for zoonotic diseases that infect humans, animals of veterinary importance, and wildlife. Within the subset of zoonotic diseases, vector-borne pathogens are changing more rapidly with climate change and potentially have a more complex epidemiology. In the past 80 years, the majority of global emerging infectious diseases have been zoonotic [
  <a rid="B1-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-vetsci-06-00040">1</a>]. While most of the zoonoses arise from wildlife (72%), vector-borne emerging diseases are increasing at a more rapid rate [
  <a rid="B1-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-vetsci-06-00040">1</a>]. Along with an increase in emerging zoonotic diseases, there have been range expansions of reservoir hosts, vectors, and the pathogens they harbor.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vector-borne diseases account for more than 17% of all infectious diseases, causing more than 700,000 deaths annually [
  <a rid="B2-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-vetsci-06-00040">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-vetsci-06-00040">3</a>]. For example, almost 4 billion people in over 128 countries are at risk of contracting dengue, with 96 million cases estimated per year [
  <a rid="B2-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-vetsci-06-00040">2</a>,
  <a rid="B4-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-vetsci-06-00040">4</a>]. Dengue virus has both animal hosts and reservoirs that are both impacted and help maintain virus circulating in populations [
  <a rid="B5-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-vetsci-06-00040">5</a>]. Many of the vectors that transmit important zoonotic infectious diseases are bloodsucking insects that ingest disease-producing microorganisms during a blood meal from an infected host and then later inject it into a new host during their subsequent blood meal. Mosquitoes are the best-known disease vector. However, other vectors, such as ticks, black flies, sandflies, midges, fleas, and triatomine bugs are also important vectors of human pathogens. 
  <a rid="vetsci-06-00040-t001" ref-type="table" href="#vetsci-06-00040-t001">Table 1</a> lists the primary zoonotic arboviruses and other pathogens vectored by Dipterans, and 
  <a rid="vetsci-06-00040-t002" ref-type="table" href="#vetsci-06-00040-t002">Table 2</a> lists the primary animal (non-zoonotic) pathogens vectored by Dipterans. For a recent review on tick-borne pathogens, see [
  <a rid="B6-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-vetsci-06-00040">6</a>]. The rest of this review focuses on modeling mosquito vectors and mosquito-borne infectious diseases in response to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mosquitoes are heavily dependent and closely tied to the environment [
  <a rid="B7-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-vetsci-06-00040">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-vetsci-06-00040">8</a>]. A mosquito’s life is a microcosm of water, available habitats, temperature, predators, and competitors. Each aspect of a mosquito’s life history is greatly influenced by even the slightest changes in the environment in unpredictable ways. For example, droughts can increase mosquito habitat by increasing stagnant water in streams, thereby increasing mosquito populations [
  <a rid="B9-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-vetsci-06-00040">9</a>]. In other cases, range expansion is simply due to warmer winters in the northern latitudes [
  <a rid="B10-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-vetsci-06-00040">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-vetsci-06-00040">11</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
