<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-vetsci-06-00040" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Earth System Modeling: The State of Climate Forecasting</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The modeling of global climate systems dates back to 1960, and were based on weather prediction models (e.g., [
  <a rid="B167-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B167-vetsci-06-00040">167</a>]). Most of these early models only include atmosphere without detailed representation of land (e.g., no explicit representation of vegetation) and ocean process (e.g., motionless ocean). However, there are also pioneering models that coupled atmosphere and ocean currents [
  <a rid="B168-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B168-vetsci-06-00040">168</a>,
  <a rid="B169-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B169-vetsci-06-00040">169</a>]. Because these models capture the circulation of both atmospheric and ocean currents, they are referred to as general circulation models (GCMs). With the advancement in computing powers and our improved understanding of coupled physical systems, GCMs have made great progress in simulating the coupled physical climate processes (e.g., winds, clouds, land surface, oceans, and ice) and atmospheric chemistry, aerosol, and static vegetation in our Earth system from the 1960s to 2000s [
  <a rid="B170-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B170-vetsci-06-00040">170</a>]. Since the late 2000s, Earth system models (ESMs) began to evolve from GCMs to simulate the interaction between climate and biogeochemical components (e.g., dynamic terrestrial vegetation and ocean biogeochemistry) to better simulate the feedback of biological systems to our climate [
  <a rid="B171-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B171-vetsci-06-00040">171</a>]. Meanwhile, great progress has been made to integrate the human component into ESMs (i.e., the integrated ESM or IESM) [
  <a rid="B172-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B172-vetsci-06-00040">172</a>]. The modern ESMs and IESMs provide the potential to simulate zoonotic relevant components including biological components (e.g., vegetation dynamics), abiotic components (e.g., inundation and water temperature), and human components (e.g., urban environment and population changes). All these progresses provide great potential for seamless coupling with disease modeling for a better prediction of disease risks under population growth, warming, and climate extremes.
 </p>
</sec>
