<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5-vetsci-06-00040" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Bridging the Gap Between Epidemiological and Earth System Modeling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although great strides have been made in simulating and predicting global climate with large-scale ESMs, coupling these forecasts with human and living-natural (HLN) systems is critical for planning and mitigating long-term impacts of changes in the environment. HLN systems interact nonlinearly with climates, and data that account for relevant parameters and states of system dynamics in a single source are limited, posing a significant challenge in understanding and predicting the response of these systems. Mosquito-borne diseases are considered a HLN system with rich traditional (e.g., number of cases) and non-traditional (e.g., remote sensing imagery) data streams. Mosquito abundance and virus development rates show both inter- and intra-seasonal variation, and are affected by long-term changes in climate regimes leading to potential range expansion of both mosquitoes and associated diseases. Changes in temperature, climate variability, and extreme weather events are already impacting mosquito-borne diseases around the world [
  <a rid="B173-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B173-vetsci-06-00040">173</a>,
  <a rid="B174-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B174-vetsci-06-00040">174</a>,
  <a rid="B175-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B175-vetsci-06-00040">175</a>]. A recent example is the emergence of Zika virus throughout Latin America, which was likely fueled by the hot drought during the 2015–2016 El Niño [
  <a rid="B175-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B175-vetsci-06-00040">175</a>]. The mosquito-borne disease HLN system not only affects human health in the US and troops abroad, but is also linked to poverty and regional stability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We face three key challenges to be able to make reliable large-scale predictions of disease risks at both short-term (seasonal/sub-seasonal) and long-term (decadal) temporal scales, which is critical for planning and improving disease mitigation strategies. First, there is currently no capability to integrate key processes at large scales including (1) hydrology and vegetation that affect mosquito habitats; (2) temperature and humidity that affect mosquito population dynamics and pathogen replication; and (3) human population density and movement that affect vector human contact and facilitates the dispersal of mosquitoes and the development of additional mosquito habitats. There are numerous baseline data requirements for both the epidemiological and climate models for zoonotic infectious diseases (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="vetsci-06-00040-f001" href="#vetsci-06-00040-f001">Figure 1</a>). Statistical models built on the relationship between local meteorological and environmental factors and reported disease cases have been developed for understanding the ecological niches of mosquito-borne diseases [
  <a rid="B116-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116-vetsci-06-00040">116</a>,
  <a rid="B155-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B155-vetsci-06-00040">155</a>,
  <a rid="B156-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B156-vetsci-06-00040">156</a>]. However, they do not directly incorporate the coupled nonlinear processes (e.g., human behavior or mosquito population dynamics) [
  <a rid="B112-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112-vetsci-06-00040">112</a>], a weakness under novel future climate conditions. Meanwhile, most current process-based models have only incorporated the impact of temperature [
  <a rid="B141-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B141-vetsci-06-00040">141</a>,
  <a rid="B142-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-vetsci-06-00040">142</a>,
  <a rid="B143-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B143-vetsci-06-00040">143</a>,
  <a rid="B144-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144-vetsci-06-00040">144</a>,
  <a rid="B145-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145-vetsci-06-00040">145</a>] and rainfall [
  <a rid="B149-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B149-vetsci-06-00040">149</a>,
  <a rid="B150-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B150-vetsci-06-00040">150</a>,
  <a rid="B151-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B151-vetsci-06-00040">151</a>] on mosquito population dynamics without explicitly considering the formation and persistence of water on the landscape, which is critical for accurately predicting the nonlinear response of mosquito habitats to precipitation. One exception is the HYDREMATS model [
  <a rid="B153-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B153-vetsci-06-00040">153</a>], but it is limited to local watersheds. Thus, it cannot account for key processes of disease transmission such as human movement or nearby pathogen reservoirs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, although recent models have started to incorporate human population and movement data [
  <a rid="B141-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B141-vetsci-06-00040">141</a>,
  <a rid="B176-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-vetsci-06-00040">176</a>,
  <a rid="B177-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B177-vetsci-06-00040">177</a>], they have not yet considered future human populations and movement that are relevant to predicting disease risk in the future. While animal movement data is also required, it can be either easy or impossible to obtain, based on the region. Third, although field and lab studies and analysis of diverse and often non-traditional data streams critical to developing and validating coupled HLN-climate systems are increasingly available, the research community lacks an advanced data fusion and mining system to extract critical information from different data sources for parameterization, development, and evaluation of such large-scale, complex models. The climate system, resulting environmental change, vectors, animal and human hosts, and infectious pathogens are each in its own a complex system. Data requirements, existing models, a foundational understanding of infectious diseases, statistical and data fusion, and computer science are all required for predicting how climate change may impact vector-borne diseases (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="vetsci-06-00040-f002" href="#vetsci-06-00040-f002">Figure 2</a>). The main hurdle to the above three challenges can be attributed to the lack of large investments that enable seamless collaboration between diverse and highly skilled subject-matter experts, availability of computational resources to scale up and integrate key processes within the complex systems, and data fusion/integration approaches needed to validate models while capturing uncertainty in model parameters, inputs, and predictions.
 </p>
</sec>
