<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec7-vetsci-06-00040" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">7. Assumptions or Challenges of Disease Forecasting and Modeling in Animals and Humans</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are three major challenges in achieving the scientific and technological advances made in weather forecasting and transferring them into disease forecasting; these are: (1) data availability, (2) human behavior, and (3) funding [
  <a rid="B123-vetsci-06-00040" ref-type="bibr" href="#B123-vetsci-06-00040">123</a>]. In terms of data availability, unlike weather forecasting, there is the lack of real-time ground truth data to inform disease forecasting models. In order to accurately predict the future, mathematical models must account for the complex and interacting dynamics of the changing environment, the vectors (e.g., mosquitoes), and the host (e.g., the humans) based on past and current data. Specifically, real-time data on mosquito prevalence and diversity at various spatial resolutions is limited and often non-existent. Without these data streams, modelers use proxy information such as vegetation and hydrology to infer mosquito prevalence, however, these limitations increase the uncertainty in the predictions. Similarly, clinical surveillance data is often biased, due to limited and costly access, and delayed, due to the bureaucratic reporting process, taking weeks or even months to be published. In order to advance our ability to forecast diseases, we need billions of sensors around the world collecting and uploading real-time information to inform forecasting models.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second major challenge to accurately forecasting infectious diseases is human behavior. Unlike weather, which is governed by the laws of physics, humans can be unpredictable and, as a host, they play a key role in the spread of infectious diseases. Human behavior, such as vaccination, can reduce or increase the probability of infection. Thus, understanding what people do during an epidemic is crucial for modeling disease dynamics. However, there are no databases monitoring human behavior and although Internet data streams, such as social media, have been used to capture population sentiment, there are biases and uncertainty in using this information. In addition, because of the role that humans are playing in changing the climate, it will be crucial to understand how their behavior will change model predictions. Finally, infectious disease forecasting needs significant investment in building the infrastructure necessary to collect data about the environment, the vectors, and the hosts at all spatial and temporal resolutions. These investments can also contribute to building a modeling community around the globe to support public health officials and ultimately reduce disease burden through forecasts with quantified uncertainty.</p>
</sec>
