<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimental work has demonstrated the effectiveness of using artificial projectiles to assess the prey capture abilities of different webs (
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Sensenig 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2012
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and similar approaches have been used in previous simulation studies (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Harmer 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2015
 </xref>). We therefore adopted this approach using a projectile with a mass of 500 mg and a horizontal impact velocity of 2.0 m s
 <sup>-1</sup>, therefore an impact kinetic energy of 1.0 mJ. The impact was tested at 23 different points on the web, as illustrated in 
 <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. To account for web property changes across temperatures and humidities, we altered the stiffness and breaking strains in line with the values obtained experimentally for another species of 
 <italic>Argiope</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Plaza 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2006
 </xref>). These values are only indicative of possible property changes that might be perceived, since it is very likely that the different silk formulations within the web react differently and there is likely to be considerable differences across spider species (as indeed there are for all material and geometric properties of spider webs). The typical ranges that might be predicted are based on varying the humidity from 15% to 100% at a constant temperature (i.e. 55°C), which are shown in 
 <xref rid="TB3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Similar data can be used to estimate the range of effects for temperature at a constant humidity (i.e. 50%) (
 <xref rid="TB4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). It is noted that the temperature and humidity ranges used herein are outside the range that spider webs are likely to encounter, even under worst-case scenario climate change projections (
 <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Schneider, 2009</xref>). Nevertheless, the ranges used are illustratively very useful. The percentage changes in 
 <xref rid="TB3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="TB4" ref-type="table">4</xref> were then applied to the material properties in 
 <xref rid="TB1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> to provide the following test scenarios: low (−78% max strain, +94% mean stiffness), medium and high (+78% max strain, −94% mean stiffness) humidity; and low (+1% max strain, +18% mean stiffness), medium and high (−1% max strain, −18% mean stiffness) temperature.
</p>
