<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the challenges in finding the genetic basis of adaptive change is that causal connections between genetic changes and traits can be difficult to identify. Often researchers are faced with the problem of locating small but crucial changes within a mass of genomic data. However, the implementation of population genomic analysis of SNP variation across the genome has enabled the identification of putatively selected loci (or those linked to the causal loci). This approach has already proven useful in several cases. Pyrenean rocket (
 <italic class="italic">Sisymbrium austriacum</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">chrysanthum</italic>) is a small colonizing herb of rocky soils that has recently invaded Belgium and the Netherlands, and Vandepitte et al. (
 <xref rid="b304" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) used a RAD-Seq approach to identify outlier loci in comparisons between invaded and native populations. Multiple native and invaded populations were investigated including those represented by herbarium specimens covering 
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 100 years in the invasive range. Several outlier loci that could underlie adaptive differences were discovered, and the sampling enabled a comparison of outliers across space as well as time. Some of the SNPs were located in genes known to affect flowering time in the closely related 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. These findings point to likely adaptive shifts rather than changes associated with demographic processes. This study demonstrates the utility of phenotype–genotype approaches for identifying candidate adaptive loci in invasive species coupled with functional information from model species. As the genomes of invasive species become better defined and genetic tools are developed, it should be increasingly possible to also pursue bottom-up approaches in a range of invasive species particularly because these can often be relatively easily grown under controlled conditions.
</p>
