<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6639258</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">11103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-11103-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Controls of soil organic matter on soil thermal dynamics in the northern high latitudes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5857-1899</contrib-id><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><address><email>dan.zhu@lsce.ipsl.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8560-4943</contrib-id><name><surname>Ciais</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2959-5920</contrib-id><name><surname>Krinner</surname><given-names>Gerhard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5024-5928</contrib-id><name><surname>Maignan</surname><given-names>Fabienne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jornet Puig</surname><given-names>Albert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hugelius</surname><given-names>Gustaf</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Laboratoire des Sciences du Climat et de l&#x02019;Environnement, LSCE/IPSL, CEA-CNRS-UVSQ, Gif Sur Yvette, 91191 France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.503237.0</institution-id><institution>CNRS, Univ. Grenoble Alpes, </institution><institution>Institut de G&#x000e9;osciences de l&#x02019;Environnement (IGE), </institution></institution-wrap>Grenoble, 38000 France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9377</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10548.38</institution-id><institution>Department of Physical Geography, </institution><institution>Stockholm University, </institution></institution-wrap>Stockholm, 10691 Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9377</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10548.38</institution-id><institution>Bolin Centre for Climate Research, </institution><institution>Stockholm University, </institution></institution-wrap>Stockholm, 10691 Sweden </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>3172</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Permafrost warming and potential soil carbon (SOC) release after thawing may amplify climate change, yet model estimates of present-day and future permafrost extent vary widely, partly due to uncertainties in simulated soil temperature. Here, we derive thermal diffusivity, a key parameter in the soil thermal regime, from depth-specific measurements of monthly soil temperature at about 200 sites in the high latitude regions. We find that, among the tested soil properties including SOC, soil texture, bulk density, and soil moisture, SOC is the dominant factor controlling the variability of diffusivity among sites. Analysis of the CMIP5 model outputs reveals that the parameterization of thermal diffusivity drives the differences in simulated present-day permafrost extent among these models. The strong SOC-thermics coupling is crucial for projecting future permafrost dynamics, since the response of soil temperature and permafrost area to a rising air temperature would be impacted by potential changes in SOC.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Soils in the northern permafrost region contain large quantities of organic carbon, formed over long time scales under cold climates. Here the authors test a number of soil properties and show that soil organic carbon is the dominant factor controlling thermal diffusivity among 200 sites in high latitude regions.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Carbon cycle</kwd><kwd>Cryospheric science</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100010663</institution-id><institution>EC | EU Framework Programme for Research and Innovation H2020 | H2020 Priority Excellent Science | H2020 European Research Council (H2020 Excellent Science - European Research Council)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>ERC-SyG-2013-610028 IMBALANCE-P</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Soils in the northern permafrost region contain ~1300&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;300 Pg of soil organic carbon (SOC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, more than one-third of the global total SOC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, formed under cold climates with limited decomposition. Carbon release from this large pool due to warming-induced thawing and acceleration of microbial decomposition may act as an important positive feedback to climate change, but the magnitude and timing of this carbon release remains uncertain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Model estimates of changes in permafrost extent and carbon stocks vary widely for the recent decades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> as well as for future scenarios<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, partly because different representations of soil thermodynamics lead to different soil temperature responses to air temperature changes. For the ground surface, the energy budget is composed of net radiation, sensible heat, latent heat from evapotranspiration, and heat flux into and out of the ground. On the other hand, below the surface, thermal dynamics is dominated by heat conduction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> driven by surface soil temperature variations, and also affected by latent heat released or absorbed during soil water phase changes which can be important for wet soils in permafrost regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">The heat conduction in the soil, assuming a uniform and constant medium, can be described by the one-dimensional Fourier&#x02019;s Law (Eqs. [<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>] and (<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>) in &#x0201c;Methods&#x0201d; section)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, in which thermal diffusivity, <italic>D</italic>, is the key parameter that describes the rate at which soil temperature changes given a temperature gradient. The value of <italic>D</italic> is determined by soil composition (minerals, air, water/ice, organic matter) and soil structure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Among the different soil constituents, thermal diffusivity of soil organic matter (SOM) is an order of magnitude smaller than that of typical soil minerals, and slightly smaller than water<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Structurally, a higher organic matter content in the soil increases soil porosity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, which also decreases soil thermal conductivity and <italic>D</italic> especially when the soil pores are filled with air. As a result, SOM acts as an insulator and the presence of SOM cools the soil during summer, while its warming effect during winter is less important due to the insulating snow cover<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The summer-time cooling effect of SOM in turn restrains microbial decomposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and favours the accumulation of SOC. Given the high SOC storage in permafrost soils and the high vulnerability and sensitivity of these carbon stocks to projected warming<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, it is important to assess the quantitative impact of SOC on <italic>D</italic> and the potential acceleration of soil warming due to the loss of SOC and its insulating effect.</p><p id="Par5">Considering a harmonic forcing as the upper boundary condition (e.g., the seasonal cycle of surface soil temperature), the solution of the heat conduction equation (Eq. [<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>]) gives an exponential dampening of the temperature amplitude with increasing depth, with its e-folding depth reflecting the <italic>D</italic> value<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> (Eq. [<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>]). Accordingly, <italic>D</italic> can be derived from temperature amplitudes concurrently observed at two soil depths. This equation has been used to calculate <italic>D</italic> and its influence factors in in situ studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, but these studies were limited to a few sites. A large-scale application of this equation has been applied by ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> to study the snow insulation effect between air and soil temperature at 20&#x02009;cm depth, but did not touch the research problem of heat conduction in sub-surface soils below 20&#x02009;cm.</p><p id="Par6">Here we infer <italic>D</italic> from two large data sets of depth-specific soil temperature measurements, the Russian Historical Soil Temperature Data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> (hereafter RHST) and the International Polar Year Thermal State of Permafrost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> (hereafter IPY), at 274 locations that spread throughout Russia and North America including permafrost and non-permafrost regions (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). A key requirement for Eqs. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) and (<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>) to be valid for inferring <italic>D</italic> using real-world soil temperature profiles is that non-conductive processes, like the latent heat associated with soil freezing, have minor impacts on the heat budget of soils at seasonal-cycle time-scale. Therefore, we examined the shape of temperature profiles at each site and selected only the sites where monthly temperature oscillations conform to sinusoidal functions, that is, to the solution (Eq. [<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>]) of heat conduction (see detailed data processing and discussion in Methods). After this data-filtering, 184 sites were retained. The calculated <italic>D</italic> value using Eq. [<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>] can approximately represent the thermal diffusivity for the bulk soil in the corresponding depth interval at those selected sites. Then, we searched for emerging relationships between the observation-derived <italic>D</italic> values and a suite of soil properties extracted from broad-scale soil maps, in order to identify the dominant factors that control <italic>D</italic> and subsequently the propagation of temperature waves from ground surface to deeper soils. We find that SOC is the strongest predictor to explain the variability of <italic>D</italic> among sites. Using the same method to calculate <italic>D</italic> from CMIP5 model outputs, we find that the different parameterization of <italic>D</italic> in these models dominates their large-scale performance in simulating today&#x02019;s permafrost extent. Further with a land surface model, we show that the thermal insulation of SOC increases modelled present-day permafrost carbon stock (0&#x02013;3&#x02009;m depth) by 39% (&#x02009;+&#x02009;230 Pg C) and permafrost area by 33% (+3.4 million km<sup>2</sup>), increasing agreement with broad-scale observational data. These findings demonstrate the need to explicitly represent the coupling between SOC and soil thermal dynamics in models that are utilized to project future permafrost changes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Organic matter content controls soil thermal diffusivity</title><p id="Par7">We find a significant negative correlation between soil thermal diffusivity (log-transformed) and soil organic carbon density (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This empirical result confirms that soils with more organic materials have a lower thermal diffusivity. Among all the tested soil characteristics including soil texture (fractions of sand, silt and clay)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, bulk density<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, organic carbon content per unit dry weight<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> (g kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), and soil volumetric moisture content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), the SOC density shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> has the strongest explanatory power for <italic>D</italic> variations among the different site-depths. Considering the interrelation between these soil properties, e.g., SOC density is negatively correlated with bulk density (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), we conducted partial correlation analysis to test if the <italic>D-</italic>SOC relationship persists after removing the effect of other variables. The partial correlation between <italic>D</italic> and SOC density remains significant after controlling the other properties separately or combined (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). This suggests that the impact of SOC on <italic>D</italic> is a composite result of soil composition and structure alterations such that its correlation with <italic>D</italic> cannot be fully accounted for by the variability in the texture- and porosity-related properties.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Relationship between soil thermal diffusivity and soil organic carbon (SOC). Thermal diffusivities (<italic>D</italic>) are derived from depth-specific measurements of monthly soil temperature from two data sets, RHST<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> (circles) and IPY<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> (crosses), at 184 sites (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), grouped into four depth intervals above 3 m (see Methods). The vertical error bars indicate 25th&#x02013;75th percentiles among the available years for each site-depth. SOC densities (kg&#x02009;C&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) are derived from two databases, WISE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> (blue) and NCSCD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> (red), integrated into the same four depth intervals. The blue and red solid lines indicate the linear regression lines of log<sub>10</sub> (<italic>D</italic>) vs. SOC from WISE (<italic>y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.012&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;&#x02212;0.35) and from NCSCD (<italic>y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.016&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;&#x02212;0.30), respectively, with 95% confidence intervals shown in the dashed lines</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e574"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Uncertainties in the results shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> include a spatial-scale mismatch: the local soil temperature observations are not accompanied by collocated records of soil texture, moisture and organic carbon; we therefore resort to the global (WISE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>) and regional (NCSCD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>) databases for these soil properties, which are not fully representative for site-level observations. In addition, even at broad-scale, soil inventories bear substantial uncertainties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The two databases used here differ in total carbon stock by about 20% for their overlapping areas (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5ab</xref>, 690 Pg C in WISE vs. 825 Pg C in NCSCD for 0&#x02013;2&#x02009;m depth). Both databases derive their spatial distributions by linking field data of soil profiles to global/regional soil classification maps, their accuracy depending on both the accuracy of the up-scaling maps and the representativeness of samples within each soil class. Thus, the high landscape complexity in the northern permafrost zone and limited soil profiles available from Siberia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> add to uncertainties in this region. To partly reduce this uncertainty, we excluded the site-depth data whose relative difference in SOC density between the two databases is higher than 25% (see Methods and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5c</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">Apart from the predominant role of SOC, soil moisture also affects <italic>D</italic>, especially in dry soils where an increased soil water act as bridges to improve thermal contacts between soil particles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. A laboratory experiment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> showed that for sandy soils, <italic>D</italic> increases rapidly with moisture content when the water content is less than 0.1&#x02013;0.2&#x02009;m<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>, and then remains stable or slightly decreases; while for cohesive soils of silty and clayey texture, the variation of <italic>D</italic> with moisture is smaller. To investigate if soil moisture can explain the spatial variability of <italic>D</italic>, we used two data sets, the satellite-based surface soil moisture product (ESA-CCI-SM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>) and the depth-specific soil moisture simulated by a land surface model (ERA-Interim/Land<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>). Neither of them shows significant correlation with <italic>D</italic>, possibly because the annual mean moisture contents at the sites are mostly higher than 0.2 m<sup>3</sup> m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>, a saturation level sufficient to bridge air gaps between soil grains (see Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref> and Supplementary Discussion). Apart from total moisture content, its phase composition also affects <italic>D</italic>, since ice has a much higher <italic>D</italic> than water (1.1 vs. 0.14&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>&#x02009;m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Soils in the northern permafrost region often contain abundant ground ice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> that can exceed soil porosity, including segregated ice and ice wedges<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. These occurrences of excess ice beyond soil pores modify soil thermal properties and add to the heterogeneity of permafrost soils<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, contributing to the scatter in observations shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>. Considering a potential confounding effect of ground ice on the correlation between SOC and <italic>D</italic> shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> (as a deeper depth could feature both lower SOC density and higher ice content, as well as a higher <italic>D</italic>), we calculated the regression for the top depth interval only (&#x0003c;0.4&#x02009;m) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>), which is generally above the permanently frozen layer and less affected by large ice volumes. The similar results as Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> indicate that the observed strong correlation between SOC and <italic>D</italic> is unlikely confounded by ice content.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><italic>D</italic> is a strong predictor for simulated permafrost extent</title><p id="Par10">Thermal diffusivity (<italic>D</italic>) is a key feature in the soil thermal regime. Its parameterization in land surface models may fundamentally impact their broad-scale patterns of soil temperature and permafrost distribution. Yet, this process has been given little attention. To test this, we analyzed the outputs of the historical experiment from a set of Earth System Models (ESMs) that participated in the fifth phase of the Climate Model Inter-comparison Project (CMIP5)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. As the simulated climate differs among the models, the total area of grid cells with mean annual air temperature (MAAT) less than 0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (A<sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub>) ranges from 22 to 32 million km<sup>2</sup>, with a standard deviation of 2.7 million km<sup>2</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). As expected, simulated near-surface permafrost area (A<sub>p</sub>, defined as modelled active layer thickness less than 3&#x02009;m (ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>), see Methods) is significantly correlated with <italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub>, with a slope slightly larger than 1, which might be related to the continuity of permafrost (namely, in models with a warm bias, permafrost area is underestimated more strongly, as they miss the sub-grid discontinuous permafrost in the southern grid cells). However, the difference in MAAT among the models can only partly explain the much wider variation in <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub> across the models, with a standard variation of 7.5 million km<sup>2</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). The ratio between the two areas (<italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub>) is determined by both air-soil interface energy exchanges affected by vegetation and snow covers, and sub-surface heat transfer in the soil column affected by soil thermal properties. Here it appears to be the latter that dominates <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> in the CMIP5 models, since 69% of the variation in <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> can be explained simply by differences in simulated <italic>D</italic> between models (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Note that the <italic>D</italic> values for each model are diagnosed from their outputted monthly soil temperatures after excluding the pixels where non-conductive processes are not negligible (the same treatment as the observations, see Methods).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Relationship between permafrost area and thermal diffusivity in the CMIP5 models. <bold>a</bold> Modelled area of regions with surface mean annual air temperature (MAAT) less than 0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (A<sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub>) and area of near-surface permafrost (<italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>, see &#x0201c;Methods&#x0201d; section) during the period 1961&#x02013;1990, from the historical runs of CMIP5 models. Models from the same institute are shown in the same color. The error bars indicate 25th&#x02013;75th percentiles among the 30 years. The black star indicates observations derived from CRU TS v3.24 climate dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> and the IPA (International Permafrost Association) continuous and discontinuous permafrost extent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. <bold>b</bold> Area ratio between near-surface permafrost and regions with MAAT&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (<italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub>) during the period 1961&#x02013;1990, against median thermal diffusivity from each CMIP5 model at the same site-years as the observations, with the horizontal error bars indicating 25th&#x02013;75th percentiles. The solid grey line in (<bold>b</bold>) represents the linear regression line between <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> and log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>D</italic>) for CMIP5 models (<italic>y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.55&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.33)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e879"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">To further analyze whether simulated snow depth also controls <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub>, we calculated the effective snow depth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> (the mean snow depth for each month weighted by its duration, see &#x0201c;Methods&#x0201d; section) for each model. In contrast to the strong correlation between <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> and <italic>D</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7a</xref>), effective snow depth is not significantly correlated with <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> among the CMIP5 models (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7b</xref>). This is probably because of the following: (1) the insulation of snow occurs during winter, thus its effect on the maximum thaw depth is much smaller compared to the summer-time insulation by SOM, although the winter soil warming can be carried over to summer in regions with thick snow cover<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>; and (2) the CMIP5 models did not represent snow thermodynamics well (among these models, only CCSM4, MIROC and NorESM families used an explicit multilayer snow scheme<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>).</p><p id="Par12">Interestingly, in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, the observation lies near the linear regression line of <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> against <italic>D</italic> from the CMIP5 models, implying that the models generally have a reasonable structure for the soil thermal regime (most of the models adopt multilayer finite difference heat conduction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>), but individual models have large biases of <italic>A</italic><sub>p</sub>/<italic>A</italic><sub>MAAT&#x0003c;0</sub> related to their biases of <italic>D</italic>. This means that improving the parameterization of soil thermal properties should be a priority in order to capture permafrost distribution in these models. Note that most of the land models of CMIP5 ESMs did not consider the impact of SOM on soil physical properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>; nonetheless, modelled <italic>D</italic> differs greatly among the models (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>), possibly due to varied parameters for soil properties, different soil texture maps, and effects of different hydrological regimes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Thermal effect of SOC enhances soil carbon accumulation</title><p id="Par13">The reduction of soil thermal diffusivity by the presence of organic matter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) leads to a stronger dampening of the seasonal-cycle amplitude along the soil depth, and thus cools the deeper soils during summer, thins the active layer thickness (ALT), and reduces microbial respiration of SOC during the thawing season. To investigate the magnitude of this SOM effect on soil temperature and SOC accumulation, we conducted two simulations of the ORCHIDEE-MICT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> land surface model, with (hereafter yesSOM) and without (hereafter noSOM) the impacts of SOM on soil thermo- and hydrodynamics. The SOM insulation effect in the model was implemented via SOM-dependent soil physical parameters including thermal conductivity, heat capacity, porosity and available water capacity, with detailed descriptions in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The inclusion of SOM effect allows the model to reproduce the relationship between SOC density and <italic>D</italic>, and to lower <italic>D</italic> values which are more consistent with observations than the results of noSOM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). Peak summer-time monthly mean soil temperature decreases by about 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C on average at 0.8 and 1.6&#x02009;m depths for the sites in permafrost region in yesSOM compared to noSOM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>). Consequently, ALT decreases by 0.6&#x02009;m averagely across the region due to the presence of SOM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, b</xref>), and the permafrost area (ALT&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;3&#x02009;m) increases from 10.4 in noSOM to 13.8 million km<sup>2</sup> in yesSOM, closer to the empirical estimate of 15.3 million km<sup>2</sup> for the continuous and discontinuous categories<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Impact of organic matter on modelled active layer thickness (ALT) and soil organic carbon (SOC). <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> Modelled mean ALT during 1990&#x02013;2010 from yesSOM (<bold>a</bold>) and the difference between yesSOM and noSOM (<bold>b</bold>). The color-filled circles on (<bold>a</bold>) indicate observations from the CALM network. <bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Modelled mean SOC during 1990&#x02013;2010 from yesSOM (<bold>c</bold>), and its relative difference against noSOM (<bold>d</bold>). The red and magenta lines indicate boundaries of northern permafrost according to the IPA map<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1067"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">For SOC, modelled total carbon stock for 0&#x02013;3&#x02009;m depth in the northern permafrost zones (22 million km<sup>2</sup>, according to IPA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> including all permafrost categories) increases by 39%, from 590 Pg C in noSOM to 820 Pg C in yesSOM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e, f</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11</xref>), which is still less than the estimate of 1030 Pg C in NCSCD database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> over the same region. This discrepancy may in part be attributed to peat formation not being included in the current model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The accumulation of SOC depends on both carbon input rate controlled by vegetation productivity, and carbon decomposition rate regulated by many abiotic (e.g., temperature, moisture, oxygen) and biotic factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Modelled gross and net primary productivity (GPP and NPP) is generally higher in yesSOM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>), since a higher water holding capacity due to the existence of SOM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> can alleviate plant water stress during growing season. The relative increase of total primary productivities for the permafrost region is 8% (9.5 vs. 8.8&#x02009;Pg&#x02009;C per year for GPP; 5.3 vs. 4.9 Pg&#x02009;C per year for NPP); thus, the 39% increase of SOC in yesSOM is mainly driven by the cooler summer-time soil temperature that slows down soil respiration in the model (Supplementary Discussion).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par15">The key finding of this study is the dominant (spatial) impact of soil organic matter on soil thermal diffusivity (<italic>D</italic>) supported by empirical evidence, which is shown in model simulations to affect the broad-scale soil thermodynamics and in turn affects the soil organic carbon (SOC) accumulation. Thermal mediation of soil organic layer is known to stabilize the underlying permafrost in relatively warm regions where the climate alone cannot sustain the persistence of permafrost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Here we provide a quantitative empirical estimate for the insulation effect of SOC through its impact on <italic>D</italic>. We recognize that, apart from heat conduction controlled by <italic>D</italic>, the latent heat associated with soil water/ice phase changes could be substantial in the soil energy budget, especially on the border of permafrost zones (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), which complicates the permafrost stability. This latent heat could partly explain the slower warming rate of the mean annual permafrost temperature in discontinuous zones during the past decades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. However, this latent heat effect delays but does not prevent the eventual permafrost thawing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Under the long-term climate warming, as permafrost might greatly retreat poleward<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, heat conduction would finally dominate, inferred from the cold sites outside the permafrost regions today (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>); and the SOC-<italic>D</italic> relationship suggests a significant impact of changes in SOC on soil temperature in the former permafrost regions.</p><p id="Par16">The implication of such SOC-<italic>D</italic> feedback for future permafrost dynamics, therefore, depends on the direction and magnitude of soil carbon changes in the future. Although enzyme kinetics theory and short-term observations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup> suggest an initially increasing SOC decomposition rate with warming, large uncertainties still remain in the long-term response of soil carbon to climate change, due to uncertainties in the rate of SOC formation (including changes of plant productivity, soil-aggregate formation, etc.)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> and in microbial physiological changes/adaptation to warming<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. A recent compilation of field warming studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> showed diverging changes in SOC stock of top 10&#x02009;cm depth after warming, with statistically neutral change across all studies. These studies are, however, limited by a generally shallow depths of warming treatment, which missed the response of subsoils<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>; as well as a paucity of measurements for SOC stock changes at deeper soil horizons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, especially for the formerly frozen soils. Laboratory incubation experiments, though, have demonstrated a high lability of permafrost soils under unfrozen conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. On the other hand, modeling studies mostly projected carbon losses in permafrost soils in the long run, albeit varying rates and magnitudes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The protection of permafrost by SOC is also manifested in fire disturbances, where the combustion of surface organic layer led to increased soil temperature and deeper thaw depth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Thus, the projected increase in fire activities in the northern high latitudes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> might also be an important driver of permafrost thaw through the impact of SOC on soil thermal properties.</p><p id="Par17">Apart from the dominant role of SOC in <italic>D</italic>, which controls the temperature propagation below ground (in the case of minor latent heat induced by freezing/thawing), the aboveground features including vegetation and snow cover also impact the vulnerability of permafrost to a rising air temperature by controlling heat exchanges between air and land surface<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Besides, degradation of ice wedges may lead to land subsidence and thus thermokarst formation, which is estimated to affect 20% of the northern permafrost region<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Such abrupt changes in the landscape strongly alter micro-topography and thus local hydrological and thermal regimes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Meanwhile, the decadal trajectories after initial thaw are closely linked to accumulation of organic matter (itself related to vegetation succession) on the thermokarst troughs, which helps to stabilize ice wedges and prevent further thaw<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. This mechanism, however, might be perturbed under future warming and intensified fire activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Such complex interactions call for models that quantitatively integrates thermo-hydrological processes, their heterogeneity at small spatial scales, vegetation dynamics and soil carbon cycle, thermal impacts of organic matter, and fires, in order to improve our understanding and prediction of the overall vulnerability of permafrost.</p><p id="Par18">The emergent slope of permafrost area versus <italic>D</italic> from CMIP5 models (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>) and the empirical relationship of <italic>D</italic> versus SOC (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) suggest a non-negligible sensitivity of permafrost area to potential SOC changes (a loss of ca. 0.2 million km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> per 1&#x02009;kg&#x02009;C&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> reduction of SOC on average). Without the SOC-<italic>D</italic> coupling, CMIP5 models have projected a linear relationship between air temperature change and permafrost area change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The recent estimate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> for the sensitivity of permafrost area to warming was also based on the assumption of an unchanged present-day MAAT-permafrost relationship for future scenarios. In contrast, the results shown here implies a non-linear trajectory of permafrost area changes in response to warming, highlighting a critical need to explicitly represent the coupling between SOC and soil thermal dynamics in models that are utilized to project the future of permafrost.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Calculation of <italic>D</italic> from soil temperature measurements</title><p id="Par19">On the basis of Fourier&#x02019;s law, the one-dimensional heat conduction can be described by:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c\frac{{\partial T}}{{\partial t}} - \frac{\partial }{{\partial z}}\left( {\lambda \frac{{\partial T}}{{\partial z}}} \right) = 0,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>T</italic> is temperature at time <italic>t</italic> and depth <italic>z</italic>; <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> is thermal conductivity (J m<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>); <italic>c</italic> is volumetric heat capacity (J m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> K<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><p id="Par20">If <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> and <italic>c</italic> are constants, Eq. [<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>] can be re-written as:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{{\partial T}}{{\partial t}} - D\frac{{\partial ^2T}}{{\partial z^2}} = 0,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>D</italic> is soil thermal diffusivity (m<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), equalling to the quotient of <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> and <italic>c</italic>.</p><p id="Par21">To solve Eq. [<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>], we consider the case that the upper boundary condition is given by a sine-wave temperature oscillation, which represents the diurnal or seasonal cycle of surface soil temperature driven by air temperature fluctuations:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$T\left( {0,t} \right) = \overline {T_0} + A_0{\mathrm{sin}}(\omega t + \varphi ),$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">sin</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>A</italic><sub>0</sub> is amplitude of the temperature oscillation at the surface, equaling to half of the difference between warmest and coldest values; <italic>&#x003c9;</italic> is its angular frequency, equalling to <inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{{2\pi }}{{86400 \times 365}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>86400</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>365</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> if we consider the seasonal cycle in a year; <italic>&#x003c6;</italic> is its phase; <inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\overline {T_0}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the mean surface temperature in a wave period.</p><p id="Par22">In the solution of Eq. [<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>], after a sufficient long time, the term that describes the transient disturbance since <italic>t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0 becomes negligible (i.e., the effect of the initial temperature function is lost)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Thus, the solution of Eq. [<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>] for the periodic steady-state is as follows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$T\left( {z,t} \right) = \overline {T_0} + A_0e^{ - \sqrt {\frac{\omega }{{2D}}} z}\sin \left( {\omega t + \varphi - \sqrt {\frac{\omega }{{2D}}} z} \right).$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> sin</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par23">Equation (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) infers an exponential dampening of the temperature amplitude with increasing depth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\frac{{A_{z1}}}{{A_{z2}}} = e^{(z2 - z1)\sqrt {\frac{\omega }{{2D}}} }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>A</italic> is amplitude of the temperature wave at depth <italic>z1</italic> or <italic>z2</italic>.</p><p id="Par24">Therefore, <italic>D</italic> can be calculated from observed temperature amplitudes at two soil depths during the same period.</p><p id="Par25">Equation (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) is an idealized mathematical model to describe the real-world soil thermal regime, its applicability requiring several necessary conditions: first, the heat transfer in the soil is dominated by conduction, so that convection, radiation, and particularly the latent heat release/absorption associated with phase transitions are of minor importance at the seasonal-cycle time-scale; second, the soil thermal properties are relatively constant over time and uniform along the considered depth interval; and third, soil temperature at the upper boundary follows a sinusoidal function. If the real soil thermodynamics at a site significantly violates any of the above conditions, it is unlikely that the soil temperature function <italic>T</italic>(z,t) would take the simple sinusoidal form as Eq. [<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>]. We therefore assume that, if the measured soil monthly temperatures at two adjacent depths both conform to sine-waves (with a small error), the soil thermodynamics in this interval can be approximated by Eq. [<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>], and the calculated <italic>D</italic> using Eq. [<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>] is a valid value that describes the thermal diffusivity for the bulk soil in this depth interval at the site.</p><p id="Par26">In this study, we used two data sets of in-situ soil temperature measurements to calculate <italic>D</italic>: the Russian Historical Soil Temperature Data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> (RHST), and the International Polar Year Thermal State of Permafrost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> (IPY). RHST provides monthly soil temperature records at 263 sites since the 1880s until 1990, but the majority of data exist after 1960. Here we used the last ten years&#x02019; data, from 1981 to 1990. RHST contains measurements at multiple depths for near surface (0.02&#x02013;0.2&#x02009;m) and deeper (mostly at 0.2, 0.4, 0.8, 1.2, 1.6, 2.4, and 3.2&#x02009;m) soils, but the near surface measurements were taken in bare areas whereas the deeper soil measurements were taken under natural cover of grasses and snow<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>; so we only used the data below 0.2&#x02009;m in our analysis. The IPY soil temperatures were measured at various depths dependent on the site, mostly for the years 2007&#x02013;2013. The daily observations in IPY dataset were aggregated to monthly means.</p><p id="Par27">For both data sets, we conducted the following data processing:</p><p id="Par28">First, only the sites with available monthly temperature records for at least two nearby depths (depth difference less than 1&#x02009;m) and for at least 12 consecutive months were used (in total 274 sites, 219 from RHST and 55 from IPY, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par29">Second, to determine whether the monthly soil temperatures evolve as a sinusoidal cycle, we first fitted the 12 months to a sine curve as Eq. [<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="">3</xref>] using non-linear least squares regression, and then calculated the sum of square error (SSE) after normalizing by amplitude such that the SSE for different depths are comparable:<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{SSE}} = \mathop {\sum }\limits_{i = 1}^{12} (\frac{{T_i - \hat T_i}}{{\hat A}})^2,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SSE</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover accent="false" accentunder="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo> &#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0005e;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x000c2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the temperature for month <italic>i</italic>; <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hat T_i$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0005e;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the predicted temperature with the fitted sine curve; <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hat A$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mi>&#x000c2;</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the amplitude of the fitted curve.</p><p id="Par30">To derive an SSE threshold, we assume that the fluctuations of monthly air temperature, according to the CRU dataset<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>, generally approximate sine-waves, and calculated their SSE values for the northern hemisphere (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref>). The 75th percentile of the SSE values for air temperatures, 0.34, was chosen to filter the soil temperature data: the observation for a site-depth-year is removed if its SSE is higher than 0.34. After this filtering, 170 sites from RHST and 15 sites from IPY remained. Note that the retained sites do not necessarily fulfil the SSE threshold for all years or depths; those depth-years that exceed the threshold were also removed before the calculation of <italic>D</italic>.</p><p id="Par31">Most of the high SSE situations are associated with the so-called zero curtain effect, namely, the soil temperature stays near 0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C during extended periods of freezing/thawing, maintained by the release/absorption of latent heat and by other non-conductive processes including vapor transport and evaporation/condensation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref> presents four examples from the IPY dataset to illustrate the disparity or similarity between soil temperature observations and the theoretical sine-waves. Whenever prominent zero curtain occurs, the SSE value will be much higher than 0.34 (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14ab</xref>). Note that the presence of zero curtain effects, although of smaller impact on the season cycle after the data screening by SSE threshold, may lead to an underestimation in the derived <italic>D</italic> values.</p><p id="Par32">In terms of the spatial distribution of removed sites, the sites located in warmer permafrost regions (discontinuous, sporadic and isolated permafrost zones) have a higher removal percentage (52%, 41 sites out of 79) than those in the continuous permafrost zone (35%, 28 out of 80) and in non-permafrost regions (17%, 20 out of 115) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). This could be plausibly explained by the near-0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C of the mean annual permafrost temperature in the relatively warmer permafrost regions, where a partial freezing/thawing at upper permafrost and inter-annual climate variability could induce significant amounts of latent heat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. A comparison of MAAT of retained vs. removed sites also shows significant differences in both permafrost regions (including continuous and discontinuous categories) and non-permafrost region, with the removed sites having a closer-to-zero MAAT than retained sites (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">15</xref>). We also compared the ground ice abundance (extracted from the IPA map<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, which gives three levels of abundance) to test whether the filtering would preferentially remove the sites with high ground ice contents. As shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16</xref>, no such difference was found between removed and retained sites. No significant difference in the surface soil moisture (extracted from ESA-CCI-SM v02.2 product<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>) was found between the removed and retained sites (not shown).</p><p id="Par33">To further test if applying the SSE threshold can effectively filter out the cases where the phase change-induced latent heat cannot be neglected at monthly time-scales, we conducted analyses based on simulations of the ORCHIDEE-MICT land surface model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> (see the last part of Methods).</p><p id="Par34">Third, for the retained site-depth-year data after step ii), we calculated the <italic>D</italic> value for each depth according to Eq. [<xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>], using the observed temperature amplitude of this layer and of the adjacent upper layer, only if the two depths are nearby (&#x0003c;1&#x02009;m). Since we try to correlate <italic>D</italic> with soil properties extracted from the global/regional soil databases which have fixed/limited layers (see below), the derived <italic>D</italic> values for different depths were integrated into four depth intervals: 0&#x02013;0.4, 0.4&#x02013;0.8, 0.8&#x02013;2, and 2&#x02013;3&#x02009;m, taking the median <italic>D</italic> if multiple depths are available within each interval. Finally, if multiple years of <italic>D</italic> are available for a site-depth, their median value is used for the regression analysis against soil properties, while their 25th&#x02013;75th percentiles are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Soil databases</title><p id="Par35">In order to identify the dominant influential factors on <italic>D</italic>, and considering that the soil temperature data sets do not report collocated measurements of soil properties at the Russian meteorological stations in the RHST dataset or the boreholes in the IPY dataset, we seek to extract soil information for these sites from the spatially explicit global/regional soil databases. To our knowledge, there are four such soil databases that are recent and/or widely used: HWSD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>; WISE30sec<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> (hereafter WISE); SoilGrids250m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup> (hereafter SoilGrids); and NCSCD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Among them, WISE is developed based on HWSD, but includes updates on the mapping unit composition, adopts a consistent taxotransfer procedure, and provides information down to 2 m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. We therefore used WISE instead of HWSD in this study. The SoilGrids product, unlike the other three databases that rely on soil classification maps to derive spatially explicit information, predicts soil properties using statistical methods from a list of covariates (climate, vegetation, topography, lithological units, etc), and thus can generate high-resolution maps (250&#x02009;m) dependent on the resolution of input covariates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. However, in a pre-processing, we found that SoilGrids gives a much higher SOC stock (in kg&#x02009;C&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) than other databases in most grid cells in the northern hemisphere, and gives a global total SOC storage of 2757 Pg C for 0&#x02013;1&#x02009;m and 4570 Pg&#x02009;C for 0&#x02013;2&#x02009;m (calculated using their 250&#x02009;m resolution map). This total SOC storage is almost twice the estimate by the majority of previous studies (see a short review in ref<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>.). Therefore, we did not use SoilGrids in this study.</p><p id="Par36">Compared to WISE, NCSCD provides SOC stock down to 3&#x02009;m, and is based on more soil samples in permafrost region than WISE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. However, NCSCD is a regional database for the northern permafrost zones only, and does not provide other properties like soil texture and bulk density. We therefore used both databases for SOC and used WISE for other soil properties. At their highest resolution (0.012&#x000b0; for NCSCD and 30 arc second for WISE), we took the grid cells whose center is nearest to the coordinates of each observation site. The two databases provide different depth intervals (4 intervals down to 3&#x02009;m in NCSCD, and 7 intervals down to 2&#x02009;m in WISE), and we integrated their original layers into the same four depth intervals as <italic>D</italic> values mentioned above (0&#x02013;0.4, 0.4&#x02013;0.8, 0.8&#x02013;2, and 2&#x02013;3&#x02009;m), using depth-weighted averages. WISE does not provide information below 2&#x02009;m, so its variables for the 4<sup>th</sup> depth interval are non-valid value in all the regression analyses.</p><p id="Par37">Using the large-scale soil databases to indicate local-scale observations introduces uncertainties. To reduce this uncertainty, we compared the SOC density for the available site-depths from the two databases (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5c</xref>), and excluded those with a relative difference (calculated as <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\left| {\frac{{{\rm{SOC}}_{{\rm{NCSCD}}} - {\rm{SOC}}_{{\rm{WISE}}}}}{{{\rm{SOC}}_{{\rm{NCSCD}}} + {\rm{SOC}}_{{\rm{WISE}}}}}} \right|$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mfenced close="&#x02223;" open="&#x02223;" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SOC</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NCSCD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SOC</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">WISE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SOC</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NCSCD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">SOC</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">WISE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) larger than 25%. This filtering process removes 105 site-depth SOC values, leaving 100 pairs of <italic>D</italic>-SOC<sub>NCSCD</sub> and 278 pairs of <italic>D</italic>-SOC<sub>WISE</sub> as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, spanning 184 sites (170 sites from RHST and 14 sites from IPY, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> red). For consistency, the excluded site-depths were also removed from the analysis of the other soil properties as shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par38">A linear relationship was found between log-transformed <italic>D</italic> and SOC density (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>); we therefore used log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>D</italic>) in all the correlation analyses. A log-transformation of <italic>D</italic> also improves its normality. To explore the potential multivariate relationships, we conducted a stepwise regression analysis using SOC density (from WISE and NCSCD respectively) and all the other soil properties as predictive variables. In the case of SOC from NCSCD, none of the other variables are significant in the stepwise regression to explain <italic>D</italic> variations, namely, the addition of other properties does not increase the explanatory power compared to the log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>D</italic>)-SOC<sub>NCSCD</sub> regression model. In the case of SOC from WISE, only silt fraction is significant, but R<sup>2</sup> only marginally increases from 0.35 to 0.37, and the slope of SOC<sub>WISE</sub> in the stepwise regression equation (&#x02212;0.010) is only slightly different from that in the single-variable regression (&#x02212;0.012).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Treatment of CMIP5 models</title><p id="Par39">We used all CMIP5 ESMs that provide access to their historical simulation (r1i1p1) on the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://esgf-node.ipsl.upmc.fr/search/cmip5-ipsl/">https://esgf-node.ipsl.upmc.fr/search/cmip5-ipsl/</ext-link> (accessed in July 2017) and that provide surface air temperature and vertically-resolved soil temperatures (in total 27 models). To calculate active layer thickness (ALT) of each grid cell, we firstly calculated the maximum monthly soil temperature (<italic>T</italic><sub>s,max</sub>) for each soil level, then took the deepest depth where <italic>T</italic><sub>s,max</sub> was at or above 0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. If the depth of 0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C was between two soil levels, a linear interpolation was used to locate the depth. Permafrost is defined to be present in a grid cell if ALT is less than 3&#x02009;m or the deepest model soil level, following ref<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>. which gives an approximation of near-surface permafrost.</p><p id="Par40">For the simulated thermal diffusivity, the same procedure as the calculation of <italic>D</italic> for the sites was carried out using the outputted monthly soil temperatures by each model for all land grid cells and soil layers. Specifically, the same SSE threshold of 0.34 was adopted to exclude the pixel-depth-years whose monthly soil temperature oscillations do not conform to sine-waves. Since the CMIP5 models have different (or a lack of) parameterizations for the soil freezing process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, their SSE values differ (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17</xref>). In general, the models that do not consider the latent heat associated with water phase change (CMCC, IPSL, and MPI families) produce sine wave-shaped monthly soil temperatures and thus have smaller SSE values (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17</xref>). Applying the SSE threshold before calculating <italic>D</italic> values for each model could reduce the confounding effect of their different parameterizations for the freezing-induces latent heat.</p><p id="Par41">The CMIP5 models have different vertical soil layers (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>), and here we only calculated the <italic>D</italic> values for the upper 3&#x02009;m, and integrated them into the same four depth intervals as the observations. Then, to compare with the observation-derived <italic>D</italic> values at the RHST and IPY sites, the same locations (nearest grid cell center to the site coordinates) were selected for each model, thus deriving the results shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>.</p><p id="Par42">For the simulated snow depth, in order to better describe its insulation effect, we calculated the effective snow depth (<italic>S</italic><sub>eff</sub>) defined as the mean snow depth weighted by its duration, following ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_{{\rm{eff}}} = \frac{{\mathop {\sum }\nolimits_{i = 1}^6 S_iw_i}}{{\mathop {\sum }\nolimits_{i = 1}^6 w_i}},$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">eff</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>i</italic> (1&#x02013;6) represents the winter months from October to March; <italic>w</italic><sub>i</sub> is a weighting factor that equals to 6 for October and decreases to 1 for March; <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the mean snow depth for the month <italic>i</italic>. In this way, an earlier accumulation of snow, with its longer time period to insulate the soil during the whole snow season, has a larger weighting and yields a higher <italic>S</italic><sub>eff</sub> than the case of a linearly accumulating snowpack. Note that this calculation did not account for the compaction/densification-induced increase in snow thermal conductivity that weakens its insulating effect during the late snow season, as demonstrated by the observed smaller temperature gradient (soil temperature at 20&#x02009;cm depth minus air temperature) under a certain snow depth during the late snow season than that during the early season under the same snow depth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par43">Only 21 models out of the 27 models provided outputs for snow depth (or snow mass) at the time we accessed the CMIP5 repository. For the models that only provided snow mass but not depth (the MPI and HadGEM families), a snow density of 250&#x02009;kg&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> was used for conversion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Simulations of the ORCHIDEE-MICT land surface model</title><p id="Par44">We incorporated the impacts of organic carbon on soil thermal and hydrological properties in the ORCHIDEE-MICT land surface model, assuming that soil physical properties are weighted averages of mineral soil and pure organic soil. Detailed descriptions can be found in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. One modification compared to ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. is that the soil thermal conductivity is calculated as geometric average of mineral and organic soils (instead of arithmetic average in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>), which is more consistent with the empirical linear relationship between log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>D</italic>) and SOC density (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We conducted two simulations for the northern hemisphere (&#x0003e;30&#x000b0;N) at 2&#x000b0; spatial resolution forced by CRUNCEP v8 climate: yesSOM, in which an observation-based SOC map was used in the thermal and hydrological modules to derive soil properties; and noSOM, in which the thermal and hydrological modules see zero SOC, i.e., no impacts of SOC on soil properties. For yesSOM, the observational SOC map was constructed from NCSCD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> for permafrost regions and from WISE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> for non-permafrost regions, using linear vertical interpolation to convert their original soil horizons into ORCHIDEE-MICT vertical layers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Here we did not use the prognostically modelled SOC by the carbon module of ORCHIDEE-MICT, in order to exclude bias of the carbon cycle module for the analysis of SOM effect. For both simulations, spin-ups were first conducted forced by looped 1901&#x02013;1920 climate and pre-industrial CO<sub>2</sub> level of 286 ppm, covering 200 years of the full model and 20,000 years of the soil carbon sub-model to reach equilibrium for the pre-industrial period. Afterwards, transient runs for 1861&#x02013;2010 were conducted forced by historical climate and rising CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations.</p><p id="Par45">We also made use of the simulations to test the validity of the SSE threshold, and to compare the temperature amplitude-derived diffusivity (<italic>D</italic>) against the real diffusivity as used in the one-dimensional Fourier&#x02019;s equation to solve for soil temperatures in the model. ORCHIDEE-MICT includes a soil-freezing parameterization, in which the latent heat of fusion is incorporated into an apparent heat capacity, so that Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) writes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_{{\rm{app}}}\frac{{\partial T}}{{\partial t}} - \frac{\partial }{{\partial z}}\left( {\lambda \frac{{\partial T}}{{\partial z}}} \right) = 0,$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">app</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced close=")" open="(" separators=""><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x02202;</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\mathrm{in}}\;{\mathrm{which}}\;c_{app} = c - \rho L\frac{{\Delta \theta }}{{\Delta T}},$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">in</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">which</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ8.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003c1;</italic> is ice density (kg m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>); <italic>L</italic> is latent heat of fusion (J kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>); <italic>&#x02206;T</italic> equals to 2&#x02009;K, corresponding to the freezing window between &#x02212;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the model; <italic>&#x02206;&#x003b8;</italic> equals to the total water content (m<sup>3</sup>&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) for the layer, providing the available amount to freeze/thaw in the freezing window.</p><p id="Par46">Then, thermal diffusivities:<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$D_{{\rm{with}} - {\rm{fusion}}} = \frac{\lambda }{{c_{{\rm{app}}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">with</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">fusion</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">app</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ9"><label>9</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$D_{{\rm{no}} - {\rm{fusion}}} = \frac{\lambda }{c}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">no</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">fusion</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_Equ9.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>can be calculated for each time-step and averaged over the year to compare with the amplitude-derived diffusivity (<italic>D</italic>). Detailed parameterizations of <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> and <italic>c</italic> in ORCHIDEE-MICT are given in ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, which generally follows the empirical equations of ref. <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup> to account for the impact of soil moisture on thermal conductivity <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>.</p><p id="Par47">As shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19a</xref>, the relative difference of annual mean <italic>D</italic><sub>with-fusion</sub> and <italic>D</italic><sub>no-fusion</sub> (<inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$1 - \frac{{D_{{\rm{with}} - {\rm{fusion}}}}}{{D_{{\rm{no}} - {\rm{fusion}}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">with</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">fusion</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">no</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">fusion</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, which ranges from 0 to 1) are generally small (less than 30%) for those locations where modelled monthly soil temperatures conform to sine-waves (SSE&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.34). This suggests that applying the SSE threshold can effectively exclude the cases in which the latent heat significantly changes the apparent thermal diffusivity. Note that some site-depths have high SSE values (and thus were excluded) even though they are less affected by soil freezing/thawing (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19a</xref>), probably because the other conditions for the validity of Eq. (<xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) are not met, e.g., the diffusivity varies too much over the year or along the considered depth interval, or the surface soil temperature itself does not conform to a sine-wave (due to, e.g., a non-sine shaped air temperature, or a strong winter insulation of snow causing asymmetric effects on the seasonal-cycle).</p><p id="Par48">Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19b</xref> compares the amplitude-derived diffusivity (<italic>D</italic>) with <italic>D</italic><sub>with-fusion</sub>, which shows a good correlation between them (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.85), although <italic>D</italic> is generally smaller than <italic>D</italic><sub>with-fusion</sub> when their values are low. This suggests that the amplitude-derived diffusivities (after excluding high SSE values) are reasonable indicators for the internal parameterization of soil thermal properties in land surface models.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_MOESM3_ESM.rar"><caption><p>Source Data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Peer review information:</bold>
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks the anonymous reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Peer reviewer reports are available.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41467-019-11103-1.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the financial support from the European Research Council Synergy grant ERC-SyG-2013&#x02013;610028 IMBALANCE-P, and from the GAP project in the framework of French-Swedish research cooperation program.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>D.Z. performed the analysis and produced the first version of the manuscript. P.C and G.K. provided advice and discussion throughout the process. F.M. and A.J. helped with the development for the SOC-thermic coupling in the ORCHIDEE-MICT model. G.H. contributed to analyses of soil C data sets and the discussion. All authors contributed to the writing of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data sets analysed in this study are available online: Russian Historical Soil Temperature Data: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.eol.ucar.edu/dataset/106.ARCSS078">https://data.eol.ucar.edu/dataset/106.ARCSS078</ext-link>; borehole temperature measurements during the International Polar Year (IPY): <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gtnpdatabase.org/boreholes">http://gtnpdatabase.org/boreholes</ext-link>; WISE30sec v1.0 soil database: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isric.org/explore/wise-databases">http://www.isric.org/explore/wise-databases</ext-link>; NCSCD soil database: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bolin.su.se/data/ncscd/tiff.php">https://bolin.su.se/data/ncscd/tiff.php</ext-link>; ESA CCI SM v02.2 product: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://esa-soilmoisture-cci.org/node/202">http://esa-soilmoisture-cci.org/node/202</ext-link>; soil moisture from the ERA-Interim/Land product: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ecmwf.int/en/forecasts/datasets/archive-datasets/reanalysis-datasets/era-interim-land">https://www.ecmwf.int/en/forecasts//archive-datasets/reanalysis-datasets/era-interim-land</ext-link>; CMIP5 model outputs: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://esgf-node.ipsl.upmc.fr/search/cmip5-ipsl/">https://esgf-node.ipsl.upmc.fr/search/cmip5-ipsl/</ext-link>. Other data that support the findings of this study, such as the ORCHIDEE-MICT model outputs, are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p>The python script to calculate thermal diffusivity from soil temperature measurements, as well as the input data to run the script, are provided in a Supplementary zipped file. This file contains the source data underlying Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> and Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par49">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hugelius</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimated stocks of circumpolar permafrost carbon with quantified uncertainty ranges and identified data gaps</article-title><source>Biogeosciences</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>6573</fpage><lpage>6593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/bg-11-6573-2014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarnocai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Soil organic carbon pools in the northern circumpolar permafrost region</article-title><source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>GB2023</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2008GB003327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuur</surname><given-names>EAG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change and the permafrost carbon feedback</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>520</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25855454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ecology of soil carbon: pools, vulnerabilities, and biotic and abiotic controls</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Ecol. Evol. Syst.</source><year>2017</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-112414-054234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature sensitivity of soil carbon decomposition and feedbacks to climate change</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>440</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16525463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowther</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantifying global soil carbon losses in response to warming</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>540</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27905442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Permafrost carbon-climate feedbacks accelerate global warming</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci.</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>14769</fpage><lpage>14774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1103910108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21852573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McGuire, A. D. <italic>et</italic><italic>al</italic>. Variability in the sensitivity among model simulations of permafrost and carbon dynamics in the permafrost region between 1960 and 2009. <italic>Global</italic><italic>Biogeochem</italic>. <italic>Cycles</italic><bold>30</bold>, 1015&#x02013;1037 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A simplified, data-constrained approach to estimate the permafrost carbon&#x02013;climate feedback</article-title><source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>20140423</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2014.0423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the permafrost-carbon climate response in the CMIP5 climate models using a simplified approach</article-title><source>J. Clim.</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>4897</fpage><lpage>4909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/JCLI-D-12-00550.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Farouki, O. T. <italic>Thermal Properties of Soils</italic> (Cold Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory, Hanover, NH, UK, 1981).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zona</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cold season emissions dominate the Arctic tundra methane budget</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1516017113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26699476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carslaw, H. S. &#x00026; Jaeger, J. C. <italic>Conduction of Heat in Solids</italic> (Oxford University Press, Amen House, London E.C.4, 1959).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yershov, E. D. <italic>General Geocryology</italic> (Cambridge University Press, 1998). 10.1017/CBO9780511564505</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of organic matter on the bulk and true densities of some uncultivated podzolic soils</article-title><source>J. Soil Sci.</source><year>1973</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2389.1973.tb00737.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporating organic soil into a global climate model</article-title><source>Clim. Dyn.</source><year>2008</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00382-007-0278-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decharme</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of snow and organic soils parameterization on northern Eurasian soil temperature profiles simulated by the ISBA land surface model</article-title><source>Cryosphere</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/tc-10-853-2016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hugelius</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieder</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Higher climatological temperature sensitivity of soil carbon in cold than warm climates</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Chang</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate3421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Jong van Lier</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Durigon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil thermal diffusivity estimated from data of soil temperature and single soil component properties</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Ci&#x000ea;ncia do Solo</source><year>2013</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0100-06832013000100011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Passerat De Silans</surname><given-names>AMB</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteny</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lhomme</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apparent soil thermal diffusivity, a case study: HAPEX-Sahel experiment</article-title><source>Agric. Meteorol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-1923(95)02323-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wierenga</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of methods for determining the apparent thermal diffusivity of soil near the surface1</article-title><source>Soil Sci. Soc. Am. J.</source><year>1983</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2136/sssaj1983.03615995004700010005x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Process-level model evaluation: a snow and heat transfer metric</article-title><source>Cryosph</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/tc-11-989-2017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang, T., Barry, R., Gilichinsky, D., University of Colorado, Russian Academy of Sciences. <italic>Russian Historical Soil Temperature Data. Version 1.0. UCAR/NCAR - Earth Observing Laboratory</italic>10.5065/D66971QC (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romanovsky</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Permafrost thermal state in the polar northern hemisphere during the international polar year 2007-2009: A synthesis. Permafr</article-title><source>Periglac. Process.</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppp.689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batjes</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Harmonized soil property values for broad-scale modelling (WISE30sec) with estimates of global soil carbon stocks</article-title><source>Geoderma</source><year>2016</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2016.01.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developing an improved soil moisture dataset by blending passive and active microwave satellite-based retrievals</article-title><source>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci.</source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/hess-15-425-2011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balsamo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ERA-Interim/Land: a global land surface reanalysis data set</article-title><source>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/hess-19-389-2015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hugelius</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A new data set for estimating organic carbon storage to 3 m depth in soils of the northern circumpolar permafrost region</article-title><source>Earth Syst. Sci. Data</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/essd-5-393-2013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scharlemann</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiederer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global soil carbon: understanding and managing the largest terrestrial carbon pool</article-title><source>Carbon Manag</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4155/cmt.13.77</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;chy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiederer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Freibauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global distribution of soil organic carbon &#x02013; Part 1: Masses and frequency distributions of SOC stocks for the tropics, permafrost regions</article-title><source>Wetl., world SOIL</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>365</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hugelius</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Northern Circumpolar Soil Carbon Database: spatially distributed datasets of soil coverage and soil carbon storage in the northern permafrost regions</article-title><source>Earth Syst. Sci. Data</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/essd-5-3-2013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arkhangelskaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukyashchenko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating soil thermal diffusivity at different water contents from easily available data on soil texture, bulk density, and organic carbon content</article-title><source>Biosyst. Eng.</source><year>2017</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biosystemseng.2017.06.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brown, J., Ferrians Jr., O. J., Heginbottom, J. A., and Melnikov, E, S. <italic>Circum-Arctic Map of Permafrost and Ground-Ice Conditions (Version 2)</italic> (National Snow and Ice Data Center, Boulder, CO, USA) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nsidc.org/data/ggd318.html">http://nsidc.org/data/ggd318.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schirrmeister</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sedimentary characteristics and origin of the Late Pleistocene Ice Complex on north-east Siberian Arctic coastal lowlands and islands &#x02013; A review</article-title><source>Quat. Int.</source><year>2011</year><volume>241</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.quaint.2010.04.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Swenson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of excess ground ice on projections of permafrost in a warming climate</article-title><source>Environ. Res. Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>124006</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/9/12/124006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Stouffer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meehl</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of CMIP5 and the experiment design</article-title><source>Bull. Am. Meteorol. Soc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/BAMS-D-11-00094.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of permafrost thermal dynamics and response to climate change in the CMIP5 earth system models</article-title><source>J. Clim.</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1877</fpage><lpage>1900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/JCLI-D-12-00228.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouttevin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How the insulating properties of snow affect soil carbon distribution in the continental pan-Arctic area</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res. Biogeosciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>n/a</fpage><lpage>n/a</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2011JG001916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosing present and future permafrost from climate models</article-title><source>J. Clim.</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5608</fpage><lpage>5623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/JCLI-D-12-00341.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimberteau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ORCHIDEE-MICT (v8.4.1), a land surface model for the high latitudes: model description and validation</article-title><source>Geosci. Model Dev.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/gmd-11-121-2018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toward more realistic projections of soil carbon dynamics by Earth system models</article-title><source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/2015GB005239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huntington</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil organic matter and available water capacity</article-title><source>J. Soil Water Conserv.</source><year>1994</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>194</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shur</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgenson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of permafrost formation and degradation in relation to climate and ecosystems. Permafr</article-title><source>Periglac. Process.</source><year>2007</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppp.582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riseborough</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil latent heat as a filter of the climate signal in permafrost</article-title><source>Proc. Fifth Can. Permafr. Conf. Univ. Laval, Que., Collect. Nord</source><year>1990</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biskaborn</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Permafrost is warming at a global scale</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-08240-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30651568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conant</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temperature and soil organic matter decomposition rates - synthesis of current knowledge and a way forward. Glob</article-title><source>Chang. Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3392</fpage><lpage>3404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2011.02496.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bradford, M. A. <italic>et</italic><italic>al</italic>. Managing uncertainty in soil carbon feedbacks to climate change. <italic>Nat</italic>. <italic>Clim</italic>. <italic>Chang</italic>. <bold>6</bold>, 751&#x02013;758 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallenstein</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil-carbon response to warming dependent on microbial physiology</article-title><source>Nat. Geosci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Gestel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting soil carbon loss with warming</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>554</volume><fpage>E4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature25745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29469098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hicks Pries</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Castanha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Porras</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Torn</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The whole-soil carbon flux in response to warming</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>1420</fpage><lpage>1423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aal1319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28280251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuur</surname><given-names>EAG</given-names></name><name><surname>Inglett</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rate of permafrost carbon release under aerobic and anaerobic conditions and its potential effects on climate. Glob</article-title><source>Chang. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2011.02519.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elberling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term CO2 production following permafrost thaw</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Chang</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate1955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>A. David</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>David M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koven</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name><name><surname>Clein</surname><given-names>Joy S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>Eleanor</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Guangsheng</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafarov</surname><given-names>Elchin</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDougall</surname><given-names>Andrew H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchenko</surname><given-names>Sergey</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolsky</surname><given-names>Dmitry</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Shushi</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinke</surname><given-names>Annette</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciais</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouttevin</surname><given-names>Isabelle</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>Daniel J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Duoying</given-names></name><name><surname>Krinner</surname><given-names>Gerhard</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>John C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanovsky</surname><given-names>Vladimir</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;del</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuur</surname><given-names>Edward A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Qianlai</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dependence of the evolution of carbon dynamics in the northern permafrost region on the trajectory of climate change</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>3882</fpage><lpage>3887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1719903115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nossov</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Torre Jorgenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kielland</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanevskiy</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Edaphic and microclimatic controls over permafrost response to fire in interior Alaska</article-title><source>Environ. Res. Lett.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>035013</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/8/3/035013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DRN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interactive effects of wildfire and climate on permafrost degradation in Alaskan lowland forests</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res. Biogeosciences</source><year>2015</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1619</fpage><lpage>1637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/2015JG003033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flannigan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global wildland fire season severity in the 21st century</article-title><source>Ecol. Manag.</source><year>2013</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foreco.2012.10.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vulnerability of high-latitude soil organic carbon in North America to disturbance</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>G00K06</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2010JG001507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olefeldt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circumpolar distribution and carbon storage of thermokarst landscapes</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13043</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms13043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27725633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liljedahl</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pan-Arctic ice-wedge degradation in warming permafrost and its influence on tundra hydrology</article-title><source>Nat. Geosci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo2674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanevskiy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Degradation and stabilization of ice wedges: Implications for assessing risk of thermokarst in northern Alaska</article-title><source>Geomorphology</source><year>2017</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geomorph.2017.09.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Wildfire as a major driver of recent permafrost thaw in boreal peatlands</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3041</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-05457-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30072751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chadburn</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An observation-based constraint on permafrost loss as a function of global warming</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Chang</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate3262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiltshire</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computing thermal diffusivity from soil temperature measurements</article-title><source>Comput. Geosci.</source><year>1993</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0098-3004(93)90096-N</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gilichinsky, D. A. <italic>et</italic><italic>al</italic>. A century of temperature observations of soil climate: methods of analysis and long-term trends. In. <italic>Proc 7th International Conference</italic> 313&#x02013;317 (Yellowknife (Canada), Collection Nordicana No 55, 1998).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Representing twentieth-century space&#x02013;time climate variability. part ii: development of 1901&#x02013;96 monthly grids of terrestrial surface Climate</article-title><source>J. Clim.</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2217</fpage><lpage>2238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/1520-0442(2000)013&#x0003c;2217:RTCSTC&#x0003e;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Outcalt</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinkel</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The zero-curtain effect: Heat and mass transfer across an isothermal region in freezing soil</article-title><source>Water Resour. Res.</source><year>1990</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1509</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>FAO/IIASA/ISRIC/ISSCAS/JRC.</collab></person-group><source>Harmonized World Soil Database (version 1.2)</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy and IIASA, Laxenburg, Austria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hengl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SoilGrids250m: Global gridded soil information based on machine learning</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0169748</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0169748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28207752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouttevin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Krinner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciais</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Polcher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Legout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-scale validation of a new soil freezing scheme for a land-surface model with physically-based hydrology</article-title><source>Cryosph</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/tc-6-407-2012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Johansen, O. <italic>Thermal Conductivity Of Soils</italic> (Univ. of Trondheim, Norway. English Translation, No. 637, (Cold Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory, Hanover, NH, UK, 1977).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>