<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-animals-08-00224" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In evaluating the effects of global climate change on biodiversity, the species was most commonly considered to be the basic unit, and the influences of climate change on genetic variation at the population level were often ignored [
  <a rid="B1-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-animals-08-00224">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-animals-08-00224">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-animals-08-00224">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-animals-08-00224">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-animals-08-00224">5</a>]. Pauls et al. highlighted genetic diversity as an important aspect of biodiversity in global climate change studies [
  <a rid="B1-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-animals-08-00224">1</a>]. Intraspecific genetic variation provides the basis for evolutionary change and is thus the most fundamental level of biodiversity [
  <a rid="B6-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-animals-08-00224">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-animals-08-00224">7</a>]. The exploration of the effects of climatic alterations on intraspecific genetic diversity will facilitate the full understanding of the evolutionary consequences of global climate change and its long-term effects on biodiversity [
  <a rid="B1-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-animals-08-00224">1</a>]. The use of molecular techniques in biodiversity research increasingly results in the recognition of multiple divergent mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) lineages below the morphospecies level [
  <a rid="B8-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-animals-08-00224">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-animals-08-00224">9</a>]. However, the overlapping distribution of multiple divergent lineages is a striking phylogeographic pattern that is common to most of the organisms, and it raises the question of whether some of these lineages are in fact cryptic species. In the light of present global climate change, on a population level, it is necessary to assess the status of these divergent lineages and delimit evolutionarily significant units (ESUs) [
  <a rid="B9-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-animals-08-00224">9</a>], which is the foundation of forecasting the influence of climate change on intraspecific genetic variation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the marine environment, ocean currents are believed to have a major influence on the population connectivity of marine species. The coastal water of Japan is characterized by a series of ocean currents. In the Pacific Ocean of the Japanese islands, two western boundary currents, the subtropical warm and saline Kuroshio Current and the subarctic cold and less saline Oyashio Current, meet each other off the east coasts of the islands. These two currents produce the mixed water mass region between the Kuroshio and Oyashio Fronts, where the most pronounced latitudinal gradients of the surface temperature and sea surface salinity are observed in the Northwestern Pacific [
  <a rid="B10-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-08-00224">10</a>]. Thus, these warm and cold ocean currents produce stable and distinct thermal environments along the latitude throughout the year. In the Sea of Japan, a branch of the warm Kuroshio Current, the Tsushima Current, is the only warm current that flows along the Sea of Japan coast off of the Japanese islands. The Tsushima Current supplies a large quantity of heat from low to high latitudes and produces weakening thermal stress along the coasts of the Japanese islands [
  <a rid="B11-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-animals-08-00224">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Japanese sand lance 
  <span class="italic">Ammodytes personatus</span>, is a cold water species in the Northwestern Pacific. Populations of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> are distributed along both sides of the coast around Japan and the Yellow Sea throughout subtropical and cold-temperate coastal areas, facing contrasting sea surface temperatures (i.e., the Kuroshio, Oyashio and Tsushima Currents), which implies an impressive tolerance to a broad range of temperatures. The species is sensitive to warm temperatures [
  <a rid="B12-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-animals-08-00224">12</a>]; they bury themselves in sand when the water temperature increases to 17–20 °C during the summer in southern and central Japan populations [
  <a rid="B12-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-animals-08-00224">12</a>]. Rather than a long migration, adults of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> perform a microgeographic migration [
  <a rid="B13-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-animals-08-00224">13</a>]. Clear genetic differences were found between populations north of the Iwate Prefecture and those south of the Miyagi Prefecture by isozyme and morphological analyses [
  <a rid="B13-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-animals-08-00224">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-animals-08-00224">14</a>]. The boundary of the two groups was consistent with the transition zone between the Kuroshio and Oyashio Currents. However, different conclusions were inferred from the mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA results) [
  <a rid="B15-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-08-00224">15</a>]. Two highly divergent mitochondrial lineages (lineages A and B) were detected in 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span>. The mtDNA lineage A was distributed in all populations from Hokkaido to the Yellow Sea, whereas the mtDNA lineage B was mainly found in the northern group. The distribution of haplotype lineage B was highly limited by the annual sea temperature [
  <a rid="B13-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-animals-08-00224">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The overlapping distribution of two divergent lineages in the northern and southern groups raises the question of whether these two lineages or the two geographic groups represent cryptic species. For any species, the success of conservation programs and the creation of effective management policies depend on determining the levels of genetic divergence within and between populations and on developing strategies to maintain genetic diversity. Evidence of whether a single species is present in the Northwestern Pacific Ocean or whether different significant evolutionary units appear in its distribution would be important in estimating the effect of global climate change on biodiversity. Bálint et al. showed that without correctly recognized intraspecific evolutionary significant units, the effects of global climate change are likely to be drastically underestimated [
  <a rid="B7-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-animals-08-00224">7</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MtDNA phylogeny represents only the genealogy of a single gene that is almost only maternally inherited. Therefore, the above questions could not be answered by employing mtDNA markers. Amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) was introduced by Vos and colleagues in 1995 [
  <a rid="B16-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-08-00224">16</a>]. This technique can provide a very large number of polymorphic markers with a very fast and relatively simple laboratory procedure and is widely used for the identification of cryptic evolutionary units [
  <a rid="B17-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-animals-08-00224">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we evaluated a multilocus approach employing AFLP to investigate the genetic structures of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> and compare the genetic variation of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> in different ocean currents characterized by thermal environments. The status of independence of the different 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> mtDNA lineages was also estimated.
 </p>
</sec>
