<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-animals-08-00224" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genetic variation of the population of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">personatus</span> around the Japanese islands has been studied by morphology, isozymes, and mtDNA sequences [
  <a rid="B14-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-animals-08-00224">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-08-00224">15</a>,
  <a rid="B18-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-animals-08-00224">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-08-00224">19</a>]. Morphological population studies of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">personatus</span> in the context of the vertebral count revealed that two groups with a vertebral count mode of approximately 65 or 63 inhabit the seas around Japan, and they intermingle in Sendai Bay off Aomori and Miyagi [
  <a rid="B18-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-animals-08-00224">18</a>]. In a previous isozyme study, 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> distributed around Japan consisted of two populations: the northern and southern populations [
  <a rid="B19-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-08-00224">19</a>]. However, no fixed locus was found between the two populations by isozyme analysis, and it was difficult to identify two populations at the individual level according to isozyme data. MtDNA control region sequence analysis of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> revealed two distinct mtDNA lineages in the Northwestern Pacific, reflecting population isolation during low Pleistocene sea level stands [
  <a rid="B13-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-animals-08-00224">13</a>]. Because mtDNA is maternally inherited, it is not possible to determine whether the presence of divergent mitochondrial lineages in the same population is a result of secondary contact after an extended period of isolation and/or the presence of two sibling species. In the present study, two completely isolated clades of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> were revealed by AFLP markers, which were consistent with previous morphological and isozyme studies [
  <a rid="B14-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-animals-08-00224">14</a>,
  <a rid="B18-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-animals-08-00224">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-08-00224">19</a>]. Several fixed loci were detected between the northern and southern clades. Considering the sympatry of the two clades in Sendai Bay, complete reproductive isolation may exist between these two clades. Although the incongruence between nuclear clades and mitochondrial lineages suggests that the two distinct mtDNA lineages do not represent cryptic species, the present study demonstrates that 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> is indeed composed of at least two genetically divergent new species in the Northwestern Pacific. The same lineage in the southern and northern clades belongs to different cryptic species, which revealed a historical mtDNA introgression from southern populations to northern populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sharp phylogeographical breaks in all species indicate limits to dispersal over both contemporary and historical time scales [
  <a rid="B29-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-animals-08-00224">29</a>]. Many authors suggest that Pleistocene glaciations were the most significant historical factors to shape the phylogeographic patterns and population structure in marine fish species [
  <a rid="B30-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-animals-08-00224">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-animals-08-00224">31</a>]. Toews and Brelsford examined 126 cases in animal systems including 24 cases in fish where there was strong evidence of discordance between the biogeographic patterns identified in mitochondrial DNA and those observed in the nuclear genome [
  <a rid="B32-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-animals-08-00224">32</a>]. The majority of cases (97%) were those where discordance likely arose following geographic isolation and secondary contact. Regions of mito-nuclear discordance are most apparent in northern groups of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus.</span> According to the general interpretation from Toews and Brelsford, the significant discordance between mtDNA and nuclear markers suggested 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> experienced at least two isolation events during Pleistocene glaciations. Lineage A and B dominated the south group and north group, respectively, indicating Pacific Ocean and Sea of Japan origin. The first isolation event created the two mtDNA lineages, which happened about 453,000 years ago during the separation of Pacific Ocean and Sea of Japan [
  <a rid="B15-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-08-00224">15</a>]. The two lineages began secondary contact in northern groups during the following postglacial period. Once again, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">personatus</span> suffered long time isolation after secondary contact during another glacial period. During the second period of isolation, it is assumed that divergent northern and southern groups accumulated mutations in their nuclear genomes and developed reproductive isolation. Besides historical factors, intra- and interspecific genetic variation patterns are also greatly influenced by established barriers to marine animal movement created by circulation patterns, temperature regimens, and coastal topography [
  <a rid="B33-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-animals-08-00224">33</a>]. In the present study, marked geographic structuring in 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> diverged into two genetically distinct new species (northern and southern). The distributional range of the two species appears mainly to be shaped by the major oceanographic current systems. A candidate for a barrier to gene flow between the northern and southern clades of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> is the temperature difference of the sea water derived by the Kuroshio and Oyashio Currents.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the Pacific side of the Japanese islands, the boundary of the two clades was consistent with the transition zone of the Kuroshio and Oyashio Currents. The Kuroshio Current flows along the southern coast of the Japanese Islands and towards the east off central Japan as a part of the wind-driven subtropical gyre circulation cell. The Oyashio Current is the western component of the Kamchatka–Alaskan Current and carries cold and high-nutrient surface water to the Northwestern Pacific. The great sea surface temperature gradient between the Kuroshio and Oyashio Currents may function as an effective physical barrier between the northern and southern clades.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the mantel test, pairwise temperature was considered a major factor significantly associated with genetic differentiation for the entire study area and southern clade. Such close relationships between sea surface temperature and clade distributions presumably reflect possible temperature adaptions. The annual temperature ranged from 13.16 to 19.99 °C in the southern clade samples, with a relatively high temperature; the northern clade sampling waters were characterized by lower temperature, which ranged from 11.26 to 14.17 °C (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="animals-08-00224-f001" href="#animals-08-00224-f001">Figure 1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="animals-08-00224-f004" href="#animals-08-00224-f004">Figure 4</a>). Different performances of mantel tests in both clades were revealed, indicating significant isolation by surface temperature in the southern clade and non-significant isolation by surface temperature in the northern clade. This suggested that environmental divergence had a larger impact on genetic divergence in the southern clade than in the northern clade. Isolation by surface temperature in the southern clade indicated that populations of the southern clade were adapted to local surface temperature. Absence of isolation by surface temperature in the northern clade indicated these populations were in the optimum range of temperature. An interesting result was found in the Qingdao population from the southern group with a relatively low annual sea surface temperature (13.16 °C), which was a lower temperature than the northern margin population of Sendai in the southern group. Competitive release may be a possible explanation for the distribution of the southern clade in the Yellow Sea. Without the competition of the northern clade in the Yellow Sea, the southern clade with wide temperature tolerance expanded its range and entered the Yellow Sea. Thus, the northern and southern clades might have different temperature adaptations. The northern clade belonged to the stenothermal type, which was restricted by high sea temperature (the annual sea temperature of 14.21 °C might be the threshold temperature). Although local adaption was revealed, the southern clade might fit a wide range of temperatures; the low threshold temperature may even be below 13.16 °C. The eurythermal character of the southern clade and the cold bias character of the northern clade was evidenced by our previous mtDNA results [
  <a rid="B15-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-08-00224">15</a>]. The mtDNA lineages A and B represent the eurythermal and cold stenothermal types, respectively. The southern clade contained lineage A in all populations and a very low percentage of lineage B in the transition zone (only 11.3 %). However, the northern clade contained a low frequency of lineage A (17.1% to 43.5% among different populations) and a high frequency of lineage B (56.5% to 82.9% among different populations) [
  <a rid="B15-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-08-00224">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local temperature adaption was reported in some marine fishes. The distributional range of the three cryptic species of 
  <span class="italic">M. cephalus</span> in the Northwestern Pacific was associated with different surface temperatures, indicating local thermal adaptation [
  <a rid="B34-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-animals-08-00224">34</a>]. The simple sequence repeat (SSR) results of Atlantic salmon, 
  <span class="italic">Salmo salar</span>, suggested that the adaptation of the thermal regime mainly explained the hierarchical genetic structure observed among salmon populations [
  <a rid="B35-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-animals-08-00224">35</a>]. Santos et al. also suggested that differences in seawater temperature in the tropical and subtropical regions represented the main factor that isolated the 
  <span class="italic">Macrodon</span> groups [
  <a rid="B36-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-animals-08-00224">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides temperature, isolation by distance was also the important mechanism that promoted genetic differentiation in 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span>, especially within the northern clade. The plot of Log 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub> and geographic distance (Log KM) revealed a strong pattern of isolation by distance in the northern clade, explaining about 76% of the variation in gene flow. Isolation by distance in the northern clade indicates that this clade is at genetic equilibrium under dispersal and genetic drift [
  <a rid="B37-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-animals-08-00224">37</a>]. In contrast, the southern clade did not exhibit a pattern of isolation by distance. Absence of isolation by distance may be caused by insufficient time following a recent range expansion in the southern clade. Considering the Holarctic origin for 
  <span class="italic">Ammodytes</span> species, it is reasonable that the southern clade colonized its current habitat recently.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlation between the sea temperature and genetic structure of marine organisms identified temperature-linked spatial distributions in some evolutionary units, which helped us to predict the species distribution shift under different scenarios of global climate change. Environmental niche models have been widely used to predict the distributions of plants and animals [
  <a rid="B38-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-animals-08-00224">38</a>], which are based on nominal morphospecies and ignore intraspecific genetic diversity, biotic interactions, and species dispersal [
  <a rid="B1-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-animals-08-00224">1</a>]. A bioclimate envelope can be defined as a set of physical and biological conditions that are suitable for a given species. Thus, shifts in species distributions can be predicted by evaluating changes in bioclimate envelopes under climate change scenarios [
  <a rid="B38-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-animals-08-00224">38</a>]. However, there are some fundamental shortcomings. It is clear that the cryptic diversity affects global climate change projections [
  <a rid="B1-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-animals-08-00224">1</a>]. In a recent study, Bálint et al. showed that without discerning intraspecific genetic variation and cryptic diversity, the effects of global climate change were likely to be drastically underestimated [
  <a rid="B7-animals-08-00224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-animals-08-00224">7</a>]. From our findings, the southern and northern clades of 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> may represent two cryptic species in 
  <span class="italic">A. personatus</span> with different and independent significant evolutionary units and different thermal adaptations. Furthermore, competitive release and competitive exclusion among cryptic species may cause error in estimating the preferred temperature for species. If the present study was only conducted in the coastal waters of the Japanese islands, uncovering the Yellow Sea, 14.21 °C was the lower boundary of annual temperature for the southern group. Based on this temperature value, the absence of the southern group in the northern coast of the Japanese islands was likely because the cold temperature limited the distribution of the southern group to the north. Competitive release and competitive exclusion were revealed, which may explain the distributions of the two groups. Thus, our results demonstrate that cryptic diversity should be considered when estimating the effects of climate change on biodiversity.
 </p>
</sec>
