<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nocturnal vigilance levels of peahens were not significantly impacted by noise pollution within trials. Individual peahens exhibited similar rates of head movements (a proxy of vigilance; 
  <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">Jones, Krebs &amp; Whittingham, 2007</a>) at night regardless of whether noise pollution was present or absent. Furthermore, they showed no preference for roosting away from artificial noise pollution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results suggest that peahens’ perception of risk is not drastically impacted by noise pollution. They did not increase their vigilance behavior to compensate for a potentially reduced ability to detect threats nor did they decrease their vigilance levels to take advantage of a potentially safer environment within trials. In most of the studies examining vigilance behavior and noise pollution, individuals elevate their vigilance levels in response to noise pollution (however, these studies were conducted on diurnal species during the day while this study was conducted at night; reviewed in 
  <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Beauchamp, 2015</a>): California ground squirrels (
  <span class="italic">Otospermophilus beecheyi</span>) are more vigilant in areas with turbine noise (
  <a rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-33">Rabin, Coss &amp; Owings, 2006</a>), great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) are more vigilant when exposed to aircraft noise (
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Klett-Mindo, Pavón &amp; Gil, 2016</a>), prairie dogs (
  <span class="italic">Cynomys ludovicianus</span>) and white-crowned sparrows (
  <span class="italic">Zonotrichia leucophrys</span>) are more vigilant in response to traffic noise (
  <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Shannon et al., 2014a</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-44">Ware et al., 2015</a>), chaffinches are more vigilant in response to white noise (
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Quinn et al., 2006</a>), and koalas (
  <span class="italic">Phascolarctos cinereus</span>) are more vigilant when hearing zoo visitors (
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Larsen, Sherwen &amp; Rault, 2014</a>). This increased level of vigilance may allow animals to detect threats faster (
  <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">Meillère, Brischoux &amp; Angelier, 2015</a>). However, some species may decrease their vigilance levels in response to noise pollution because their risk perception is lower. Elk are less vigilant in response to traffic noise (though human activity may have also contributed to this effect; 
  <a rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-38">Shannon et al., 2014b</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, noise pollution did not influence the peahens’ selection of nocturnal roosting locations. The peahens selected roosts irrespective of noise pollution levels, indicating that they did not perceive noise pollution as impacting their risk. Because both roosts were exposed to some level of noise pollution, it is possible that the peahens did not distinguish between them since they were both noisy. Additional experiments in which one of the roosts is completely free of noise would be important. Previous studies have found that some species avoid areas with noise pollution (
  <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">Blickley, Blackwood &amp; Patricelli, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-44">Ware et al., 2015</a>) while other species do not (
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Neo et al., 2015</a>); an understanding of ecological differences between species could elucidate why they respond differentially.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though we did not find that vigilance levels differed within trials, we did find that peahens were more vigilant overall during control compared to noise trials. And, peahens descended from the roost later in the morning overall during control trials compared to noise trials. These overall effects could be related to predators being more frequent during control trials (see below) and peahens adjusting to this increase in predator presence throughout the trial (i.e., carry-over effects). In fact, head movement rates across all nights during control trials in this study (171 ± 9.9 head movements/h) were higher than control trials from a previous study conducted under similar experimental conditions (99 ± 6.5 head movements/h; 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>); this suggests that changes in the external environment, such as increased predators, may have resulted in the higher vigilance rates during our control trials in this study. Because predator presence can impact vigilance behavior, future experiments could be conducted in which predator presence is controlled. Additional experiments will also be necessary to determine whether long-term effects of noise pollution impact vigilance behavior.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Peahens may not rely strongly on acoustic cues when detecting nocturnal predators, potentially explaining why they do not alter their perception of risk based on noise pollution within trials. Nocturnal vigilance levels in peahens dramatically increases with exposure to artificial light pollution (
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>), suggesting that the birds heavily rely on vision to detect predators. Given that peahens in the wild roost atop tall trees, they also likely rely on vibrations to detect the approach of large predators. Noise pollution may mask acoustic cues from predators but be less important than visual or vibrational cues to the peahens. Given that their antipredator vocalizations are loud and cover a wide frequency range (
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Yorzinski, 2014</a>), peahens may also be able to hear conspecific warning calls despite noise pollution (
  <a rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-13">Francis, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-29">Pettinga, Kennedy &amp; Proppe, 2016</a>). Additional studies that examine whether peahens use acoustic cues during predator detection in the daytime would be useful. A comparative study examining variation in species’ response to noise pollution would help elucidate the factors impacting the perception of risk in response to noise pollution across species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is possible that the peahens in this study had previously habituated to noise pollution. The peahens were captured from feral populations located in country areas or suburban neighborhoods at least two years prior to the onset of this study. They may therefore have habituated to noise pollution while they were feral. However, the loudness and duration of the noise pollution they experienced while they were feral were likely less than the loud noise treatment in this study. It is also possible that the birds habituated to the noise during the trials because the noise was broadcast for four consecutive days. However, their nocturnal vigilance levels were similar on the first and last day when the noise was broadcast, suggesting that habituation within trials was not influencing vigilance rates.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because nocturnal vigilance is inversely correlated with sleep in peahens (
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>), noise pollution did not likely impact the amount of time the birds spent sleeping within trials. In addition, they ascended the roost in the evening and descended from the roost in the morning at similar times regardless of whether noise pollution was present or not within trials. However, noise pollution could have affected their sleep patterns in subtler ways. In humans, noise pollution can alter the amount of time spent in different stages of sleep (
  <a rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-30">Pirrera, Valck &amp; Cluydts, 2010</a>). Further research investigating the impact of noise pollution on sleep in birds would be useful. One study found that European robins (
  <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span>) sing at night when they are exposed to noise pollution but how this behavioral change impacted their sleep behavior was not explored (
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Fuller, Warren &amp; Gaston, 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our study, predators often avoided the experimental area during nights with noise pollution. Similarly, 
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Francis, Ortega &amp; Cruz (2009)</a> found that avian predators avoided depredating nests in areas exposed to noise pollution. In addition, three-spined sticklebacks (
  <span class="italic">Gasterosteus aculeatus</span>) and greater mouse-eared bats (
  <span class="italic">Myotis myotis</span>) are less efficient hunters when subjected to noise pollution (
  <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Purser &amp; Radford, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-40">Siemers &amp; Schaub, 2011</a>). Because some predators may be sensitive to noise pollution, prey may be safer and have higher reproductive success in noisy environments (
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Francis, Ortega &amp; Cruz, 2009</a>). However, in other species, prey are more easily captured by predators when exposed to noise (
  <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">Simpson, Purser &amp; Radford, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-42">Simpson et al., 2015</a>). The mechanisms underlying differences in hunting behavior across species in response to noise are not well understood.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other types of anthropogenic disturbances, such as light and chemical pollution, often accompany sources of noise pollution (
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Halfwerk &amp; Slabbekoorn, 2015</a>). Understanding how different types of disturbances singly and jointly influence antipredator behavior would be informative. While we found that noise pollution had limited effects on nocturnal vigilance rates in peahens in this study, we previously found that light pollution significantly increases their nocturnal vigilance rates (similar sample size as used in this study; 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>). Across nights with exposure to pollution, nocturnal vigilance rates in response to noise pollution in this study (medium noise: 118 ± 3.5 head movements/h; loud noise: 112 ± 6.0 head movements/h) were two times lower compared to vigilance rates in response to light pollution in a similar study (246 ± 38.6 head movements/h; 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>). Based on the evidence thus far, management practices aimed at minimizing artificial disturbances to peafowl might therefore invest more in reducing light pollution compared to noise pollution.
 </p>
</sec>
