<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vigilance levels</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested whether artificial noise pollution impacts vigilance levels in peahens (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 30). For each trial, a peahen was put inside of the experimental cage for seven consecutive nights (the experimental design was similar to 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>). The experimental cage had one wooden roost (0.85 m tall and 1.3 m long) that was 1.5 m from a rock-shaped speaker (150 W Outdoor Rock Speaker, model tfs6sl; TIC Corporation, City of Industry, California, USA). The speaker was connected to an audio amplifier (Audioengine N22; Austin, Texas) and an iPod touch (model A1509; Apple Corporation, Cupertino, California, USA). During noise trials, the speaker continuously broadcast white noise (white Gaussian noise generated with Matlab; 16 bit; 44.1 Hz) during nights (and days) 2–5; no noise was broadcast on nights 1, 6, or 7. The white noise automatically turned on at noon on the second day and turned off at noon on the sixth day (Woods outlet timer, model 50002, Mississauga, Canada). During medium noise trials (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 10), the white noise had a sound pressure level (SPL) of 75 dB (A weighting; slow setting) at the middle of the roost; during loud noise trials (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 10), the white noise measured 90 dB SPL at the middle of the roost (model 407730; Extech Instruments, Waltham, MA, USA). During control trials (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 10), white noise was not broadcast on any of the seven nights. The medium and loud noise trials broadcast noise at the same decibel levels as used in a previous study on noise pollution and birds (
  <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">Swaddle &amp; Page, 2007</a>); noise pollution in urban environments can exceed the decibel level that we broadcast in our loud noise trials (
  <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">Chepesiuk, 2005</a>). Furthermore, the peahens were not necessarily exposed to the same level of noise pollution for the entire trial. During the day, they could move to the opposite side of the experimental cage and therefore reduce the loudness of the noise that they experienced. Also, even though the peahens could have slept on the ground at the opposite side of the speaker at night, they always slept on the roost near the speaker.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The head movements of the peahens were continuously monitored with a 3-axis accelerometer (TechnoSmart, Rome, Italy; 3 mm × 1.1 mm; 0.5 g; sample resolution: 19.6 m s
  <span class="sup">−2</span>; sample rate: 50 Hz). The accelerometer was attached to a velcro strip (3.5 mm × 1.8 mm) that was glued (Artiglio Super 620) to the feathers atop the birds’ head (see 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a> for further details on accelerometer and attachment). The accelerometer was replaced every day because the battery would not last for the duration of an entire trial. The accelerometer does not impact head movement rates (
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a>). We used a custom algorithm to extract the number of head movements the peahens exhibited during each night of the trial (starting 1 h after sunset and ending 1 h before sunrise; “nighttime period”); the accuracy of this algorithm is high (over 90% of head movements are correctly classified as head movements; see 
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Yorzinski et al., 2015</a> for more details).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The peahens were weighed at the start and end of the trial (ZIEIS Veterinary Pet Scale; Apple Valley, Minnesota; 5 g accuracy). The length of the peahens’ tarsus + metatarsus was measured at the start of the entire experiment (Neiko digital caliper; Neiko Tools, Wenzhou, Zhejiang, China; model number: 01409 A; ± 0.03 mm accuracy). Three video cameras (Swann Pro-500; Swann Communications, Santa Fe Springs, California, USA) connected to a DVR (Swann DVR4-2600) recorded the experimental cage and the area immediately outside the experimental cage (2 m from the cage perimeter). Using these video recordings, we determined the amount of time that predators (raccoons and domestic cats) and non-predators (mice, frogs, flying squirrels, deer, and rabbits) were visible during the nighttime period. We also assessed the time at which the peahens ascended to and descended from the roost each night. The time at which a bird ascended to the roost for the night was assessed by moving backwards in the videos from the nighttime period (1 h after sunset) and finding the time when the bird jumped on the roost. If the bird was not already on the roost 1 h after sunset, then we moved forward in the videos until the bird jumped on the roost. The time at which a bird descended from the roost for the night was assessed in a similar way except that we moved forward in the videos from the nighttime period (1 h before sunrise) until finding the time when the bird jumped off the roost. If the bird was already off the roost 1 h before sunrise, we moved backward in the videos until the bird jumped off the roost. We excluded times when the experimenters interfered with when the bird ascended to the roost or descended from the roost.</p>
</sec>
