<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Deressa et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) undertook a study on climate change impact on sugarcane by means of the Ricardian Model for both rain-fed and irrigated production. The results indicated that sugarcane production is highly vulnerable to changes in climate conditions. Another study conducted on climate change impact on sugarcane by the Southern African Sugar Industry (SASA) revealed that the total revenue per hectare of sugarcane is likely to decrease with projected temperature intensification (SASA 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The report further stated that changes in precipitation would also impact sugarcane production, but not as severely as temperature changes would. The studies show that less land would be used for the cultivation of sugarcane because of the changes in climate that renders land and soil no longer suitable for sugarcane cultivation (SASA 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). In an earlier study, the SASA reveals that there would be an increase in flash floods and a tendency towards a warmer climate (SASA 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). With such trends, insects, pests and diseases were expected to thrive as the ecological balance gets disrupted. This viewpoint is confirmed by Nayamuth and Nayamuth (
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) who maintain that insects may colonise new areas and new species could move into sugarcane growing areas. Land suitability may change, resulting in a shift in sugarcane growing areas, thus competing with other crops for appropriate arable land and growing areas. Land-use changes will have to be analysed in relation to mills and infrastructure as well as the surrounding communities (Dale 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). A deterioration of sugarcane quality will potentially reduce milling efficiencies, and the cost of production and increase in sugar prices in the world market could reduce the adaptive capacity of farmers such as SSFAs (Parry et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>).
</p>
