<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological rhythms are ubiquitous in nature and occur on several temporal scales. Daily rhythms are important for the coordination of physiological, immunological and behavioural processes within organisms as well as for biotic interactions. The proper functioning of these rhythms is disrupted by modern human lifestyles—including sleep deprivation, light at night, jet lag and shift work [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C1">1</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C2">2</a>], which induce temporal mismatches between the environment and circadian biology, and have detrimental effects on health and well-being. Problems of mismatch extend beyond daily rhythmicity. New research by Dopico 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C3">3</a>] has elegantly demonstrated massive seasonal changes in human immunity and physiology, adding to evidence for marked annual rhythms in the vast majority of organisms [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C4">4</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C5">5</a>]. The disruption of annual rhythms under global climate change has potentially dramatic consequences for the health of animals, humans and ecosystems. Whether or not organisms can adapt to changing seasonality depends on the regulation of their annual rhythms. Principally, annual rhythms could be: (i) 
  <span class="italic">genetically programmed</span>, i.e. genotype-dependent responses to the environment resulting from evolutionary adaptation to predictable annual change; (ii) 
  <span class="italic">direct environmental</span> effects, e.g. accelerated growth owing to longer light hours in the day; or (iii) 
  <span class="italic">coincidental</span>, e.g. human rhythms arising as a consequence from holidays.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This review will focus on genetically programmed, internal cell- and tissue-based mechanisms, which are predicted to track changes in environmental seasonality. In many species, tissue function is reprogrammed between subjective winter and summer states, generating endogenous rhythms that approximate a year (i.e. circannual rhythms) [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C3">3</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C6">6</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C9">9</a>]. The existence of innate circannual rhythmicity has been demonstrated when organisms, from unicells to vertebrates, are maintained in constant environmental conditions for many years [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C6">6</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C11">11</a>]. Species with genetically programmed annual rhythmicity occur globally, from high latitudes to the equator, and even in apparently ‘constant’ environments such as the deep sea [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C6">6</a>]. Genetic programming is seen to be adaptive because it is 
  <span class="italic">pre-emptive</span> and serves to predict and prepare organisms for alternations in seasonal environmental conditions [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C12">12</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C14">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In humans, the evidence in support of seasonal effects on disease risk, physiology and immune function is pervasive ([
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C3">3</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C15">15</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C17">17</a>]; electronic supplementary material, tables S1 and S2) and suggests present-day implications of evolutionarily inherited and refined mechanisms [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C5">5</a>]. During the twentieth century, our species has developed technologies that allow precise photic and climate control over our living environments, and humans in developed societies now spend the vast majority of their lives in conditions that mimic ‘summer-like’ environments [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C15">15</a>]. These so-called 
  <span class="italic">eternal summers</span> are characterized by light and temperature conditions that lack seasonal rhythmicity. Presently, many of us no longer live in accordance with the naturally occurring variation in geophysical rhythms. The consequences of such modified environmental seasonality on human health are still being elucidated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, human activities are also affecting seasonality in a wider ecological context, with implications for disease risk, ecosystem health and food security. In agricultural and natural ecosystems, there is growing evidence that seasonal patterns and ecological interactions are disrupted by global climate change [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C18">18</a>]. Disruptions in annual rhythms are expected to become progressively more prevalent and detrimental consequences have already been documented [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C19">19</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C20">20</a>]. Nevertheless, there is a surprising lack of data to determine if, and how seasonally generated and regulated functions can adapt [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C21">21</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C22">22</a>] to altered environmental conditions. Thus, an overarching, integrated scientific understanding is needed of the mechanisms that underlie seasonality, including cyclical biology of humans and of the consequences for all organisms as they adapt to disrupted seasonality and a fast changing climate. Addressing the arising practical challenges requires an integrated, cross-disciplinary approach, as exemplified by the ‘one health’ initiative for advancing healthcare for humans, animals and the environment [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C23">23</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C24">24</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we review current examples of disruption between seasonal environmental conditions and internal timing mechanisms. From this basis, we further emphasize the pervasiveness of seasonality (with a focus on humans). Finally, we outline potential threats of disruption for humans, industry, and managed and natural ecosystems, with a call for the development of a synergistic research agenda for seasonal biology.</p>
</sec>
