<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular, cellular and physiological basis of seasonal time-keeping</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A better understanding of how species respond to seasonal changes in their environment and how they can adapt to their disrupted seasonality requires knowledge of the mechanisms of seasonal time-keeping. Endogenous annual rhythmicity is evident in a wide range of species (e.g. protists [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C6">6</a>], insects [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C27">27</a>], plants [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C28">28</a>], fishes [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C29">29</a>], birds [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C30">30</a>] and mammals [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C4">4</a>]), but is especially strong and widespread among vertebrates, making it highly likely that seasonal genes and/or intracellular pathways are also involved in long-term changes in human physiology and behaviour. Broadly, in multicellular organisms, the mechanisms for regulating annual rhythms involve cellular and molecular timers that interact closely with refined input pathways for transmitting day length (photoperiod) and other environmental cues (electronic supplementary material, figure S3). Highly photoperiodic species have been extremely valuable for the identification of key genetic, cellular and neuronal circuits that regulate annual rhythms [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C31">31</a>]. Direct evidence for endogenous seasonal rhythms in humans is scarce owing to the challenges of collecting data over multiple annual oscillations and the near impossibility of isolating subjects from exogenous influences for extensive time periods. Historical and contemporary studies have demonstrated that humans exhibit seasonal reproduction, hypothesized to be driven by internal mechanisms [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C32">32</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C33">33</a>]. Over the past few centuries, there has been a decrease in seasonal patterns in humans [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C32">32</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C33">33</a>] that could have resulted from a reduction in the seasonal amplitude or desynchronization from environmental cues. Nevertheless, these data suggest that exogenous cues (i.e. photoperiod) can entrain seasonal human responses [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C33">33</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C34">34</a>]. In most mammals, annual changes in day length affect seasonal rhythmicity via the suprachiasmatic nucleus in the hypothalamus, and consequently, altering the nocturnal secretion of the hormone melatonin from the pineal gland ([
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C35">35</a>]; electronic supplementary material, figure S3
  <span class="italic">a</span>). Melatonin receptors are localized in many of the brain regions implicated in cognitive, affective and homeostatic processes, and thus seasonal changes in melatonin secretion regulate key genes required for the neuroendocrine control of physiology, immune function and behaviour [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C36">36</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C40">40</a>]. Although exact photoperiodic input pathways vary among vertebrate groups, similar day length-induced changes in neuroendocrine brain regions (electronic supplementary material, figure S3
  <span class="italic">b</span>) occur in fishes [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C41">41</a>] and birds [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C42">42</a>], which would suggest that seasonal changes in day length act to regulate a common, evolutionarily ancient internal timing system [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C43">43</a>]. Recent work suggests that the fundamental nature of this timer may depend on cyclical histogenesis [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C44">44</a>] and/or epigenetic mechanisms [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C45">45</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C46">46</a>], potentially operating in multiple tissues to form a circannual clock-network.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this framework, the hypothalamus of the brain acts as an important interface for many processes that are relevant for health and physiology, coordinating seasonal changes in autonomic and endocrine function. Of note, seasonal timing in immune function is vital for the survival of many small seasonal animals such as rodents and birds [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C39">39</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C41">41</a>]. Seasonal- or light-induced changes in a range of innate humoral and cell-mediated systems are present in a wide range of species (electronic supplementary material, table S2). A general finding is that short days which mimic a winter environment enhance some immune functions [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C39">39</a>]; for species where winter is a time of increased pathological risk, immune function is increased presumably in anticipation of increased need. It is important to note that different aspects of immunity may be differently regulated across the seasons. For example, rodent and bird models have shown that short days enhance many aspects of cell-mediated immunity while suppressing other specific immune defences ([
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C39">39</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C41">41</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C47">47</a>]; electronic supplementary material, table S2). The precise molecular and cellular mechanisms involved in the seasonal restructuring of immune function are not well described, but recent evidence suggests that a common molecular switch occurs in hypothalamic regions and immune tissues (e.g. leucocytes; [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C3">3</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C48">48</a>]). Recent developments in next-generation sequencing platforms, transcriptomics and proteomic analyses, provide a powerful means to identify the precise molecular and cellular pathways that underlie annual rhythms [
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C3">3</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C44">44</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20151453C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20151453C46">46</a>]. Once the mechanisms that govern such rhythms are identified, experiments can be devised for field-based or clinical settings to examine the relationship between external environment and internal timing.
 </p>
</sec>
