<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent literature on feedback in medical education strongly emphasizes bidirectional dialogue and exchange of information [
  <a rid="CIT0001" href="#CIT0001">1</a>], described as an ‘educational alliance’ between the learner and the teacher, and recommends coaching for professional growth rather than ‘giving’ feedback [
  <a rid="CIT0002" href="#CIT0002">2</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0004" href="#CIT0004">4</a>]. While the newer conceptual models of this complex, interpersonal interaction [
  <a rid="CIT0005" href="#CIT0005">5</a>] sound promising, discussion on promoting feedback seeking and acceptance by learners cannot be devoid of the context (i.e., learning environment) within which the feedback occurs [
  <a rid="CIT0006" href="#CIT0006">6</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0007" href="#CIT0007">7</a>]. As suggested by the popularized phrase ‘culture eats strategy for breakfast,’ [
  <a rid="CIT0008" href="#CIT0008">8</a>] efforts to enhance the exchange of feedback within an educational alliance could be drastically undermined if the culture of an educational program does not support the newer approaches to feedback. In order to enhance the quality and impact of feedback, understanding the residency program culture (i.e., defined as the underlying assumptions and values that drive the behaviors of an organization) and addressing sociocultural barriers are paramount.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two perspectives of culture might impact the feedback process between faculty and medical students and residents: the learning culture and the residency program culture. Learning culture is described as the attitudes, values and practices that impact how a profession designs education for its learners [
  <a rid="CIT0009" href="#CIT0009">9</a>]. It can affect the feedback-giving behavior of medical teachers [
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>] the feedback seeking behavior of learners, the credibility of feedback, and the process and outcome of feedback [
  <a rid="CIT0011" href="#CIT0011">11</a>]. Watling et al. [
  <a rid="CIT0012" href="#CIT0012">12</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0013" href="#CIT0013">13</a>] explored the impact of the learning culture on feedback in three different professional contexts (e.g., medicine, music, professional sports) and found significant differences in feedback seeking, acceptance of constructive feedback and direct observation of performance. This research suggests professions may have a unique and dominant learning culture influencing the feedback process.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The organizational culture (or what we have called ‘residency program culture’) drives the behaviors of an organization that can either facilitate or inhibit educational efforts [
  <a rid="CIT0014" href="#CIT0014">14</a>]. For example, it has been reported that medical schools with a culture that promotes flexible policies and interdisciplinary teamwork implement curricular reform more successfully than medical schools with authoritative cultures [
  <a rid="CIT0015" href="#CIT0015">15</a>]. We believe that a residency program exists within a departmental structure that could have a specific or dominant culture. In a qualitative study, Ramani et al. [
  <a rid="CIT0016" href="#CIT0016">16</a>] reported that cultural factors dominated internal medicine residents’ perceptions of the quality and impact of feedback; interestingly, a departmental ‘culture of niceness’ was viewed by residents as a barrier rather than as a promoter of meaningful feedback. Sargeant et al. [
  <a rid="CIT0004" href="#CIT0004">4</a>] examined the implementation of the R2C2 model (
  <span class="underline">r</span>elationship building; exploring 
  <span class="underline">r</span>eactions to feedback; exploring understanding of feedback 
  <span class="underline">c</span>ontent; and 
  <span class="underline">c</span>oaching for performance change) in internal medicine and pediatrics programs as a potential strategy to shift towards a culture with more positive feedback.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Organizational Culture Assessment Instrument (OCAI) is a well-known framework for assessing the culture of a work environment [
  <a rid="CIT0017" href="#CIT0017">17</a>], although the use of the OCAI in graduate medical education is novel. The OCAI differentiates culture along two dimensions: one concentrated on external versus internal orientation, and the other concentrated on discretion and flexibility versus stability and control. These two dimensions identify how individuals view the culture of their work environments within one of four distinct frames: Clan, Hierarchy, Adhocracy, and Market. A Clan culture reflects a more sociable working environment, and individuals view it as a ‘family.’ Hierarchy cultures focus on structure and formality, with an emphasis on organizations functioning efficiently. The Adhocracy culture reflects a climate where risk is accepted in an innovative, energetic, and creative environment. Market cultures are results-oriented, and individuals complete goals in a competitive manner. Efforts to measure culture have mainly occurred in other professional fields rather than in medical education [
  <a rid="CIT0018" href="#CIT0018">18</a>]. However, Rougas et al. [
  <a rid="CIT0019" href="#CIT0019">19</a>] developed a modified OCAI tool, and collected validity evidence of the tool implementation within an emergency medicine residency program.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We define feedback as information given to learners for the purpose of improving their performance, and we concur with the theoretical constructs of the feedback exchange as an educational alliance [
  <a rid="CIT0002" href="#CIT0002">2</a>]. That said, due to the lack of validated instruments to assess learner’s perception of the feedback they receive, we developed such instruments and collected preliminary validity evidence in a previous study [
  <a rid="CIT0020" href="#CIT0020">20</a>]. Our previous work determined that learners differentiate between the feedback received from the milieu or environment of a rotation (i.e., what we have termed ‘culture’) versus the feedback received from an individual provider.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a lack of studies that examine the culture in residency programs, especially as it pertains to the influence of this residency program culture on the exchange of feedback, the perception of its credibility, and the impact of feedback on behavior change. Since a greater understanding of the residency program and feedback cultures is necessary to enhance the quality and impact of the feedback process, our research questions were: 1) What is the relationship between residents’ perceptions of their residency program’s culture and feedback culture?; and 2) Are there differences in residents’ perceptions of their programs’ and feedback cultures amongst residents from different disciplines and different institutions? We hypothesized that residents preferred certain program culture types and that certain aspects of a residency program’s culture were related to the feedback that occurred in a learning culture.</p>
</sec>
