<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002-S2003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Survey instruments</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the Qualtrics (Provo, UT) program to administer the surveys. This program allows participants to access the survey link on any desktop or mobile device. We sent emails to residents with a single anonymous electronic link. Residents were offered an option to complete the surveys at one sitting or to save and return to the surveys later. Residents completed the OCAI survey first and the FEEDME-Culture instrument afterwards.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The OCAI [
  <a rid="CIT0017" href="#CIT0017">17</a>] was slightly modified by replacing the word ‘organization’ with the words ‘residency program’ (electronic supplementary material). The OCAI consists of two sets of six questions to measure six domains – Dominant Characteristics, Organizational Leadership, Management of Employees, Organization Glue, Strategic Emphases and Criteria for Success. Each question has four alternatives (A = Clan, B = Adhocracy, C = Market, and D = Hierarchy). The first set of questions is labeled as ‘Now’ that refers to the existing culture. We asked the residents to divide 100 points among the four alternatives and give higher points to the options that were similar to their residency program culture. The same set of questions was repeated and labeled as ‘Preferred.’ With the second set, we asked the residents to allot points based on how they would like their residency program to look five years from now. The scores were calculated by taking the average of all alternative responses in the Now and Preferred sets. The Cronbach’s alpha value for the OCAI is 0.86 [
  <a rid="CIT0021" href="#CIT0021">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FEEDME-Culture instrument (electronic supplementary material) comprises 16 items each with a 1–5 Likert-type rating scale. This tool assesses learners’ perceptions of the feedback culture in their learning environment [
  <a rid="CIT0020" href="#CIT0020">20</a>]. A FEEDME-Culture mean score is calculated from the average of all 16 items. Since the mean score is an aggregate score of 5-point Likert scale items, now it takes on the property of a continuous scale. Higher scores indicate a more positive feedback culture, where learners perceive that they are receiving effective, beneficial, and quality feedback about their performance. The Cronbach value of the FEEDME-Culture instrument is 0.94.
 </p>
</sec>
