<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Authors’ contributions</div>
 <p>GS co-developed the strategy for reporting evidence-based practices, wrote substantial sections of the paper and provided editing. LB co-developed the strategy for reporting evidence-based practices and provided feedback and editing on the paper. FR assisted in developing the strategy for reporting practices and provided feedback and edits on the paper. PD oversaw policy actions to facilitate the developing of the reporting practices and provided feedback and edits on the paper. SJ synthesizes evidence use in the reporting practices and assisted in manuscript preparation. JL co-developed the strategy for reporting evidence-based practices and provided feedback and editing on the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acknowledgements</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper was prepared through the support of the Division of Behavioral Health and Recovery, Washington State Department of Social and Health Services. The views in the paper represent the view of the authors only. We are grateful for the many clinicians, providers and administrators who provided feedback on the tools presented in this paper. We thank Ellie Qian for her assistance in preparing the manuscript. The paper was presented in part at the 2018 NIMH Mental Health Services Meeting.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" sec-type="COI-statement" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Competing interests</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" sec-type="data-availability" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Availability of data and materials</div>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consent for publication</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All authors read and approved this manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics approval and consent to participate</div>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Funding</div>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Funding for this paper came from the Division of Behavioral Health and Recovery, Washington State Department of Social and Health Services.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Publisher’s Note</div>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
