<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results of the potential CAS distribution modelling by MaxEnt showed that the Mean Temperature of Driest Quarter is the most important climatic variable defining the current global distribution of this pest. Previous results have demonstrated that CAS eggs hatch to nymphs in 8–12 days when the temperature is 24.5 °C (
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Howard et al., 1999</xref>) and adult female would be not laid eggs when temperature at 18 °C and 35 °C (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cave, Sciacchetano &amp; Diaz, 2009</xref>). Moreover, 25 °C–28 °C has been confirmed to be the most suitable temperature range for the development and reproduction of CAS (
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ravuiwasa et al., 2012</xref>). However, temperatures below 15 °C have been shown to be unsuitable for this insect, as indicated by the high mortality observed in laboratory research (
 <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Teaaro, 2009</xref>). Moreover, some research has suggested there were significant correlations between population growth and temperature variations. Our results confirmed that the mean temperature of driest quarter is the most important factor affecting the model, accounting for 48.1% of the contribution of all climatic variables. Our model suggested that the population of this pest would increase under an mean temperature of 15–20 °C in the driest quarter and a mean temperature of 25–28 °C in the wettest quarter. Therefore, these temperature values represent the most suitable climatic conditions for the population growth of this pest and some currently unsuitable habitats, such as southern China, may be come suitable in the future as currently suitable areas become too hot for CAS development. In contrast, some currently highly suitable habitats, such as North America, may become unsuitable due to global warming. This decrease in habitat suitability in these regions may constraint the spread of CAS outside its current suitable range or limit its development.
</p>
