<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Supplementing the feed with more lipids and fatty acids was reported to reduce the dietary energy loss in goats [
 <xref rid="B51-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. However, the effectiveness of lipid supplementation relies on the source, inclusion rate, fatty acid profile and the composition of the rest of the diet [
 <xref rid="B48-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Reduction in enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission to the tune of around 40% is possible using high quality lipid feed supplements [
 <xref rid="B46-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. By differing the mode of action, lipid feed additives may reduce the methanogen and ciliated protozoan population in the rumen. Further, lipid supplementation reduces fibre and organic matter degradability and decreases the fermentable substrate availability and thereby minimising CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production [
 <xref rid="B53-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Abubakr et al. [
 <xref rid="B54-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] conducted an experiment in Boer X Catcang crossbred goats where they found that adding decanter cake and palm kernel cake at up to 80% inclusion decreases methanogenesis by reducing rumen protozoa in goats. Further, Zhou et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] reported the ability of lauric acid to reduce CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production by reducing the viability of 
 <italic class="italic">Methanobrevibacter ruminantium</italic>. Likewise, Kong et al. [
 <xref rid="B56-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>] reported a significant reduction in the methanogenesis without affecting the quantity of rumen methanogenic archaea after flaxseed supplementation.
</p>
