<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Phenolic monomers, condensed tannins and other plant secondary metabolites in dose-dependent manner can reduce enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission from the ruminants because of their ability to reduce methanogenesis. Puchala et al. [
 <xref rid="B72-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] reported 57% reduction in CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> in terms of g/kg DMI in condensed tannin containing 
 <italic class="italic">Lespedeza cuneata</italic> fed Angora goats compared to Angora goats fed a combination of 
 <italic class="italic">Festucaarundinacea</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Digitariaischaemum</italic>. Dietary tannins can directly hinder CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production as well as indirectly limit methanogenesis through reducing the availability of hydrogen atoms. In a meta-analysis using 30 experiments comprising 171 treatments to evaluate the extent of dietary tannins to reduce the CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission, Jayanegara et al. [
 <xref rid="B73-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>] found a negative correlation between enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production and tannin supplementation. Furthermore, Wina et al. [
 <xref rid="B74-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] reported a reduction in methanogens in methanol extract saponin containing 
 <italic class="italic">Sapindus rarak</italic> fed animals. Similarly, Mao et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>] reported a 27% reduction in enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production with tea saponin supplementation. Further, in an experiment conducted in goats fed with natural tannin containing 
 <italic class="italic">Mimosa</italic> spp., Bhatta et al. [
 <xref rid="B46-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] reported a CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> reduction after 
 <italic class="italic">Mimosa</italic> spp. supplementation even at low concentrations (2–8 g/kg DM of the diet). In a study conducted in Nanjiang Yellow goats, Dong et al. [
 <xref rid="B76-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>] reported a reduction in enteric methane production on 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisiae annuae</italic> extract and herbal medicines mixture supplementation to different diets. Further, under in vitro condition, Denman et al. [
 <xref rid="B77-animals-08-00235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>] reported 91% reduction in methane production using bromochloromethane at 5 g/100 kg LW in Japanese native goats. 
</p>
