<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-nutrients-10-01455" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acknowledging food insecurity as a public health concern is a huge advancement in the chronological development of this issue. Several populations, namely children, the elderly, minorities, and low-income households have been known to possess a higher risk of facing food insecurity [
  <a rid="B1-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-nutrients-10-01455">1</a>]. Furthermore, being the minority, Indigenous People are not excluded from this dilemma as the prevalence rate of food insecurity among this population has been reported to be high in some countries. Willows et al. [
  <a rid="B2-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-nutrients-10-01455">2</a>] showed that 33% of Indigenous households in Canada were categorized as food-insecure. Within that total percentage, 14% of the cases were found to be severe. On the other hand, according to the Australian Institute of Health and Welfare [
  <a rid="B3-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-nutrients-10-01455">3</a>], 24% of the Indigenous People in Australia, aged 15 or older, had faced food shortage in the previous 12 months from 2004 to 2005. Moreover, about 8% of the people affected by this issue claimed that they could not afford to buy food during a food shortage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This issue was not widely explored by previous studies in Malaysia. The first research related to food security among the Orang Asli (OA) was conducted by Zalilah and Tham [
  <a rid="B4-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-nutrients-10-01455">4</a>] who found that 82% of the OA households at Hulu Langat, Selangor were food-insecure. Meanwhile, Nurfahilin and Norhasmah [
  <a rid="B5-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-nutrients-10-01455">5</a>] reported that 88% of OA households at Gombak, Selangor State had been food insecure until 2015. In addition, the most recent study on this matter revealed that 82.9% of the OA households (Mah Meri) at Carey Island and Tanjung Sepat (both are located in the Kuala Langat district) faced food insecurity; 29.3% household food insecurity, 23.4% individual food insecurity, and 30.2% experiencing child hunger [
  <a rid="B6-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-nutrients-10-01455">6</a>]. Besides, Haemamalar et al. [
  <a rid="B7-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-nutrients-10-01455">7</a>] and Chua et al. [
  <a rid="B8-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-nutrients-10-01455">8</a>] found evidence related to food insecurity among the OA, which referred to the issue of the low dietary diversity (one of food insecurity indirect measures) among the OA in Pahang State, Malaysia.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indigenous People, including the OA, are well-equipped with traditional knowledge inherited from generation to generation. This line of knowledge should have developed further with all the available natural resources offered by Mother Nature [
  <a rid="B9-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-nutrients-10-01455">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-nutrients-10-01455">10</a>]. Therefore, the high prevalence rate of food insecurity among the Indigenous People is rather unexpected. This could be due to several challenges they encounter in practicing traditional food systems, which include the declining amount of plant and animal species, lack of transfer of cultural knowledge to youth, reduced time and energy invested for harvesting due to employment, decreased densities of species, and decreased land use. Moreover, the raising concern about environmental contamination and the increasing availability and acceptance towards new food are linked with the abandonment of traditional food systems in this community [
  <a rid="B11-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nutrients-10-01455">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, food security is closely linked with food systems. Food systems play a role in the food management process that consists of four stages including the production, processing and packaging, distribution and retail, and consumption of food. To put this simply, food systems regulate the overall process of food management [
  <a rid="B12-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nutrients-10-01455">12</a>]. Furthermore, the management of food loss and waste, which is another component under the food system, is a foundation of food security. Recently, significant food loss and waste has been reported during the harvesting, transportation, storage, packaging, wholesaling, retailing, and consumption of food [
  <a rid="B12-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nutrients-10-01455">12</a>]. Food loss and waste was estimated to be approximately one third of total food production globally (1.3 billion tons) [
  <a rid="B13-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-nutrients-10-01455">13</a>]. The food loss and waste is not acceptable as millions of people are suffering food insecurity globally, yet tons and tons of food that were aimed to feed the targeted groups were wasted due to mismanagement [
  <a rid="B12-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-nutrients-10-01455">12</a>]. This also implies that presence of food availability alone does not guarantee food security. The food should be made (physically, economically, and socially) accessible to the public [
  <a rid="B14-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-nutrients-10-01455">14</a>]. Therefore, the primary focus of this study is the traditional food system. The traditional food system for Indigenous People is described as “being composed of items from the local, natural environment that are culturally acceptable” [
  <a rid="B11-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-nutrients-10-01455">11</a>] (p. 417). An in-depth exploration of the traditional food system is necessary, provided that most of the Indigenous People worldwide depend on the food systems to obtain food and generate income [
  <a rid="B9-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-nutrients-10-01455">9</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the data obtained from the Department of Orang Asli Development (JAKOA), the population of OA in Peninsular Malaysia was 178,197 in 2013, and this number was divided into three main ethnic groups, which were Senoi, Malay-Proto, and Negrito [
  <a rid="B15-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-nutrients-10-01455">15</a>]. Orang Asli were expected to flourish under the traditional food systems attributed to their rich knowledge of their surrounding environment (forests/lakes/rivers) and food-seeking activities (farming/hunting/gathering). However, contradictive findings from other studies showed a high prevalence of food insecurity and low dietary diversity among the OA in Peninsular Malaysia. This information proves that the OA are facing hardships to obtain sufficient food through traditional food-seeking methods, namely farming, hunting, fishing, and gathering. Therefore, drastic measures are needed to curb food insecurity issues among the OA. Before any recommendations and resolutions can be planned or proposed, a thorough understanding of this issue is important. For this reason, this study was conducted to identify the factors connected with food insecurity among the OA. This study aims to find out the factors for the absence of traditional food practices as a safeguard for OA to obtain enough food.
 </p>
</sec>
