<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-nutrients-10-01455" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Data Collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This process was conducted through several sessions of semi-structured in-depth interviews with the help from an interview protocol. The interview protocol referred to a list of questions and issues of interest that were covered during the in-depth interview. The interviews were audio-recorded with permissions from the informants. The Malay language, a national language among Malaysians regardless of their ethnic background, was used during this session. However, for informants who were not able to express themselves in this language, the services of translators were used to smooth the interview sessions, and they consisted of the local OA who were able to speak both the native OA language and the Malay language. Another instrument used in this study was a sociodemographic questionnaire that was used to assess the sociodemographic characteristics of the informants.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each of the informants was required to go through two sessions of the in-depth interview. The primary aim of these sessions was to establish a sense of rapport between the researcher and the informants [
  <a rid="B20-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-nutrients-10-01455">20</a>]. To reemphasize, this study particularly looked into the contributing factors of household food insecurity under traditional food systems. The questions which were directed to the informants were:
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Are you facing any problems in obtaining sufficient food?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>(Based on Question 1) If yes, can you elaborate the problem(s) you are facing by providing a suitable example(s)?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>(Based on Question 2) How frequent is/are the problem(s)?</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
