<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2dot4-nutrients-10-01455" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.4. Weather</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This issue fell under the fourth theme which explained the failure of the OA to achieve household food security. To be specific, Malaysia experiences two monsoon seasons, namely the southwest monsoon (June to September) and northeast monsoon (November to March) as well as two inter-monsoon seasons (October and April to May). The southwest monsoon brings rain to the east coast while the northeast monsoon increases rainfall to the west coast of Peninsular Malaysia [
  <a rid="B24-nutrients-10-01455" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-nutrients-10-01455">24</a>]. The extreme rainy season was found to interrupt economic activities, such as rubber tapping, mining, and searching for natural commodities in the forests. Furthermore, heavy rain also led to the occurrence of floods which destroyed the farms cultivated by the OA. This problem was found to occur among all ethnic groups in the present study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Informant 46: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“Due to the raining season, we become jobless. It is hard to find a job. Some of the available jobs are related to farm works, such as rubber tapping. These jobs are usually pursued through contracts and recruits are unneeded due to rain. Workers are recruited only during dry seasons. This is why sometimes earning money is not an easy task for us.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Informant 52: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“A bit tough when the rainy season arrives. Cannot earn money. For example, we want to search vegetables or want to harvest the banana for sale are also restricted, people (traders) do not want the products. In addition, people (traders) do not travel here to pick up the products.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, the extreme dry season reduced the chance of successful harvesting as crops or vegetables might die before the plants got to be full grown. This factor was also reported by all ethnic groups in the present study.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Informant 4: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“Dry season. The leaves wither instead of flourishing. The land is dry, but many still carry out agricultural works. Harvesting can be done, but the plants will not fully grow.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Informant 45: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“Water, sometimes do not have water. The water flow is slow. The tuber roots are also dying. Because of the heat.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
