<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Arctic biotas are facing rapid environmental modifications. The Arctic is warming twice as fast as any other place on earth, with visible negative impacts on sea-ice distribution, significantly changing wind regimes and precipitation levels
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. The concurrent emergence of competitors
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>, parasites
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup> or pollutants
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup> poses additional new threats for Arctic wildlife
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. In this context, there is an urgent need for long-term monitoring programs to investigate Arctic species and ecosystem reactions to multiple environmental modifications
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. This is especially true in the North as arctic biomes are poorly studied compared to the rest of the world
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. In this region, coastal ecosystems deserve particular attention
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>; they host endemic seabirds which have been identified as powerful ecological indicators, and are emblematic for Arctic peoples
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Seabirds are subjected to a fair number of long-term monitoring programs in polar regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. Yet most of these studies focus on the sub-Antarctic and the Antarctic, and integrative, long-term studies of the impacts of environmental changes on the foraging ecology and fitness proxies of arctic seabirds are rare (e.g.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>). Those are however needed to fully apprehend the incidence of ecosystem modifications on these vulnerable species.
</p>
