<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The daily meteorological data sets generated by LARS, described above, were used to drive DyMSiM to simulate current and projected future mosquito populations and human dengue cases. DyMSiM also requires the parameterization of additional environmental variables and the site latitude to determine the duration of sunlight hours (which influences the evaporation of standing water). To account for spatiotemporal variability in parameter values and climate conditions, 96 simulations were performed at each site using different combinations of model parameter values. The parameter values were selected to represent ranges of values reported in the literature (
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morin et al. 2015</xref>). Six of the seven parameters included in our suite of simulations were represented by only 2 or 3 possible values because their values are well established (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). In contrast, we included 12 possible values for habitat area (determined by the number and surface area of containers available for egg laying) because of greater uncertainty and potential for variation in this parameter (
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morin et al. 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Parameter values for the simulation were chosen from the best-fit 1% of simulations for San Juan, Puerto Rico for the period 2010–2013 because of their superior ability to replicate patterns of dengue (
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morin et al. 2015</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t2" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). We simulated a total of 21 years of daily total mosquito populations and dengue case data for each site driven by baseline climate, and we repeated this process with the future climate scenarios. After discarding the first year of DyMSiM results to allow for model spin-up time, each of the 23 mainland U.S. sites had four associated 20-year daily time series: 
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>) total mosquitoes, present climate; 
 <italic class="italic">b</italic>) total dengue cases, present climate; 
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>) total mosquitoes, future climate; and 
 <italic class="italic">d</italic>) total dengue cases, future climate.
</p>
