<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although temperature is thought to be a critical factor in limiting species’ distributions in North America (Merriam, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1984</xref>; Root, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1988</xref>; Whitton, Purvis, Orme, &amp; Olalla‐Tárraga, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), our analysis did not consider other variables known to influence geographic ranges in this group. For instance, other habitat requirements (e.g., precipitation), and biotic factors including competition could also limit species’ ranges and thereby contribute to variation in range size. However, for salamanders, precipitation alone was not found to be a significant predictor of distributions in other studies looking at salamanders (see Quintero &amp; Wiens, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>
 <italic class="italic">)</italic>, and interspecific interactions have only been found to limit portions of distributions (Deitloff, Church, Adams, &amp; Jaeger, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Gifford &amp; Kozak, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Jaeger, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1971</xref>). As many of the species in this study are found to coexist regionally and locally (Adams, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Highton, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>), it suggests that biotic interactions do not underlie variation in geographic range size in the clades we examined. While temperature and physiology alone are not likely to explain all of the aspects of a species’ range, there is empirical support for the strong influence of these factors in determining geographic distributions (Addo‐Bediako et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>; Calosi et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Gaston, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Hillman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). In addition, we also did not investigate seasonal and developmental plasticity of these traits, which could potentially influence the extent of the response (see Hoffmann, Tomiuk, Schmuths, Koch, &amp; Bachmann, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Terblanche &amp; Chown, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>).
</p>
