<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change greatly impacts spatial configuration of VIWTP habitat</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While many studies project future range shifts for wildlife, the spatial configuration and connectivity of future habitats has been less well addressed. Our work predicts that VIWTP habitat will become increasingly fragmented and confined to mountaintops. Climate change will likely cause fragmentation of VIWTP habitat by facilitating infilling of trees and shrubs into previously open alpine tundra [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref008">8</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref058">58</a>], a process already documented at high elevations on Vancouver Island [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref025">25</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref026">26</a>]. The effects of habitat fragmentation on VIWTP persistence will depend on their home range size and dispersal ability. Substantial movement of VIWTP genes occurs across the landscape and high allelic richness is found even among the most isolated populations [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref059">59</a>]. Female White-tailed Ptarmigan in Colorado can move long distances to other breeding areas without incurring reproductive or survival costs during the breeding season [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref034">34</a>]. These studies suggest that ptarmigan may be able to persist on Vancouver Island despite increasing habitat fragmentation due to their apparent ability to move between patches, at least for the initial periods of change. Still, our results predict the disappearance of nearly all of the ptarmigan habitat south of Strathcona Provincial Park by the 2080s. Large areas of unsuitable low elevation habitat act as a barrier to VIWTP gene flow, as the southern populations appeared to be smaller and more temporally variable [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref059">59</a>]. Thus, these southern populations may well be extirpated by climate-induced habitat loss within 70 years. The ability of ptarmigan to disperse between smaller and more spatially fragmented habitat patches will be an important predictor of VIWTP long-term viability, and future research should examine VIWTP dispersal distance as a function of future climates in order to inform management and conservation of the subspecies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under all climate change scenarios, our results predict substantial decline in the average suitable patch size for VIWTP by the 2080s, including loss of most large patches and an increasing number of very small patches. Although average patch size is predicted to decline gradually from the 2020s–2080s, total number of patches is predicted to decline by the 2020s but then increase in the 2050s and 2080s. The predicted reduction in number of patches by the 2020s primarily reflects the disappearance of most very small patches of currently suitable habitat. By the 2080s, however, most current larger patches are predicted to become fragmented into several smaller patches, increasing the total number of patches but lowering average patch size. As shown by [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref033">33</a>], there is likely a demographic cost for VIWTP persisting in smaller patches. Alpine habitat already exists as small, fragmented “sky islands” on Vancouver Island compared to interior alpine, which is more continuous. Further fragmentation and reduction in patch size of VIWTP habitat will likely be detrimental to ptarmigan breeding success [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref033">33</a>] and may also hinder dispersal and increase the ecological cost of movement, as birds will increasingly be forced to cross unsuitable habitat in order to reach suitable breeding patches. Finally, the average elevation of suitable habitat patches is expected to increase by the 2080s, reflecting a loss of patches at lower elevations. Thus ptarmigan are in danger of being “squeezed off the mountain”, as their remaining suitable habitat will be increasingly confined to mountaintops.
 </p>
</sec>
