<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and species occurrence data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study area encompassed all of Vancouver Island, located on the southwest coast of British Columbia, Canada (between 47° and 52° N latitude and 123° and 128° W longitude). At 460 km long (north to south) and 80 km wide (east to west; 32,134 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>), Vancouver Island is the largest island on the west coast of North America. Elevation varies from 0 to 2,195 m a.s.l. A central spine of mountains spans the length of the island, with highest elevations located in the center of the island within Strathcona Provincial Park (with four mountain summits between 1,830 m and 2,195 m). These mountains create a rain shadow on the eastern side, resulting in a strong east-west precipitation gradient across the island. The biogeography of the island has been classified into biogeoclimatic (BEC) zones by the provincial government that represent vegetation, soil, and climate conditions. Four BEC zones exist on Vancouver Island, including Coastal Douglas Fir, Coastal Western Hemlock, Mountain Hemlock and Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine. The largest areas of continuous alpine habitats are found in the central region of the island, while alpine patches in the northern and southern regions are generally lower in elevation and more fragmented.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used two sources of distributional data for Vancouver Island White-tailed Ptarmigan. The first consisted of ptarmigan presence locations from field surveys conducted by K. Martin from 1995–1999. These surveys targeted the entire range of VIWTP and representative alpine habitat deemed suitable for ptarmigan was searched in the north, central, and south island. Birds were located using playbacks of male territorial calls and chick distress calls, then captured with a snare attached to an extendable pole [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref038">38</a>] and outfitted with a necklace collar radio transmitter (RI-2D/2B, 18 mo battery life, weight 6–9 gm, Holohil Systems Ltd., Carp, Ontario). K. Martin and field crews tracked the radio-collared birds over the 4-year period by foot during summer and recorded encounters with other uncollared birds using playbacks and incidental encounters. GPS coordinates were recorded at each bird location.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From this field survey dataset, we extracted summer (June–October) observations and eliminated sightings of juveniles, since they were usually found at or near the same GPS coordinate as their parent during the summer period. We then eliminated duplicates at the same GPS point (i.e., if a flock of several birds was recorded at one point, only one observation was included in the final dataset). To minimize bias due to certain individuals being observed more than others, we first eliminated records from the same individual that were &lt; 1 day apart, and then randomly selected two records per individual. Lastly, we randomly selected one observation within each 100-m grid cell of the environmental predictor GIS layers. All filtering of the original ptarmigan data was carried out using R 3.1.2.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to supplement the field survey records, an opportunistic citizen science program was initiated in partnership between the Strathcona Wilderness Institute and K. Martin at the Centre for Alpine Studies, University of British Columbia. Notices were posted at trailheads within Strathcona Provincial Park describing distinguishing features of White-tailed Ptarmigan. The notices requested that hikers report their ptarmigan sightings by mailing a card or sending an e-mail with GPS or map coordinates and photos (if possible) to K. Martin at UBC. The citizen science initiative began in 1995 and continues to the present, currently resulting in 404 confirmed White-tailed Ptarmigan sightings (see [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>] for details). Although trailhead cards were posted within Strathcona Provincial Park, many hikers frequently submitted records from their other alpine hikes on the island after finding out about the program. This resulted in a public dataset spanning the entire range of alpine habitat on Vancouver Island (
  <a rid="pone.0142110.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0142110.g001">Fig 1</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0142110.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0142110.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">White-tailed Ptarmigan presence locations on Vancouver Island from the field survey (circles; N = 207) and public submissions (triangles; N = 137).</div>
   <p>Strathcona Provincial Park is outlined in black. This map is similar but not identical to that shown in [
    <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>].
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0142110.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We extracted summer (June–October) observations from the public dataset and then filtered the observations by location accuracy, keeping only those that contained precise GPS or map coordinates (accurate to within 100 m). As with the field survey observations, we eliminated duplicates at the same location and randomly selected one observation within each 100-m grid cell. Because the field survey and public datasets result in models with similar accuracy and distributional predictions when using machine learning modeling techniques [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref036">36</a>], we combined ptarmigan presence locations from each dataset in order to maximize sample size and model accuracy for the purpose of this study. If two sightings fell within the same 100-m grid cell in the combined dataset, we randomly eliminated one sighting from the cell. The resulting combined dataset contained 344 sightings (207 from the field survey and 137 from the public dataset; 
  <a rid="pone.0142110.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0142110.g001">Fig 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because we lack information on ptarmigan absences (areas traversed by observers where ptarmigan were not encountered) in either dataset, we generated a baseline random sample of pseudo-absences for the combined dataset to represent the landscape potentially available to VIWTP. First, we constrained the pseudo-absence background within a 200-m buffer surrounding the minimum convex polygon around the entire set of ptarmigan observation points. Within this area, we restricted the background to areas within the Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine and Mountain Hemlock Biogeoclimatic (BEC) zones. The majority (92%) of ptarmigan presence locations fell within the Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine BEC zone, while the remainder fell within the Mountain Hemlock zone (except for one sighting in the Coastal Western Hemlock zone).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some methods for generating pseudo-absences first predict low suitability areas using presence-only models and select pseudo-absences from those areas [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref039">39</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref041">41</a>]. Senay et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref042">42</a>] apply a novel three-step approach to select pseudo-absences using environmental constraints which can outperform models where pseudo-absences are randomly generated. We used distribution maps of BEC zones, which incorporate environmental variables known to be correlated with ptarmigan presence, to define environmental constraints for pseudo-absence selection. In contrast to methods that generate pseudo-absences outside of suitable habitat, we differentiated ‘‘suitable” from ‘‘highly suitable” habitat by generating pseudo-absences within potentially suitable habitat (which included both Mountain Hemlock and Coastal Mountain-heather Alpine zones). Such a distinction is important for rare and threatened species [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref043">43</a>]. Including Mountain Hemlock zones in our pseudo-absence background also allowed for better discrimination between presence and absence locations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within this background, we excluded all areas within a 200-m buffer around known ptarmigan presence locations (the median distance moved by ptarmigan within a day during summer was 170 m based on the radio-telemetry study; N = 37 movements). Finally, we randomly selected twice as many pseudo-absence locations as the number of ptarmigan presence locations (688 total pseudo-absences). This choice was based on an initial exploration of different ratios of presences to pseudo-absences (1:2, 1:4, and 1:10) to check for changes in model accuracy measures (sensitivity, specificity, Kappa, AUC, and the True Skill Statistic). Using a ratio of 1:2 resulted in the highest Kappa value, whereas all other accuracy measures were not affected by presence-to-pseudo absence ratio.</p>
</sec>
