<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strengths and limitations of climate envelope models</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The choice of a threshold for determining habitat suitability with species distribution models can be subjective, especially when reliable absence data are not available [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref075">75</a>]. We used a threshold that maximized sensitivity (set at 0.90) to correctly predict the largest number of ptarmigan presence locations while attempting to avoid overpredicting habitat suitability across the landscape by setting sensitivity too high. However, as in most studies of this kind, we cannot be sure that areas without ptarmigan sightings represent unsuitable summer habitat. A series of initial trials revealed that our choice of threshold and resulting estimates of habitat loss were conservative; other methodological choices for setting a threshold, such as maximizing model accuracy according to kappa or setting a lower sensitivity, resulted in smaller estimates of suitable habitat area and greater predictions for climate-induced habitat loss. By utilizing a threshold that slightly over-predicts baseline suitable habitat for VIWTP, we minimized the chances of “missing” areas of suitable habitat and overestimating habitat loss as often occurs in climate envelope studies [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref076">76</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although their shortcomings have been described elsewhere [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref077">77</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref078">78</a>], predictions from climate envelope models have corresponded well with observed population trends for breeding birds [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref079">79</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref080">80</a>] and range shifts for montane birds [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref081">81</a>]. Climate envelope models can also be useful for identifying conservation opportunities within climatic macro-refugia or newly available habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref076">76</a>]. Our predictions for VIWTP appear realistic based on predictions for loss of alpine tundra in British Columbia [
  <a rid="pone.0142110.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0142110.ref037">37</a>], and allow for informed decisions for prioritizing management of areas where ptarmigan are likely to persist.
 </p>
</sec>
