<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We investigate climate extremes in future climate conditions and further evaluate their impacts on air quality. The climate extremes investigated in this study include heat waves, heavy precipitation, and atmospheric stagnation. Following previous studies (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), we applied the criteria based on meteorological variables to define the occurrence of climate extreme events. Similar to Guo et al. (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), we define the occurrence of a heat wave when the daily maximum temperature exceeds the critical temperature threshold for at least 3 consecutive days during May to September. The temperature threshold is defined as the 95th percentile of the baseline period (2006 to 2010 in this study) and, regardless, not less than 30 °C. The original air stagnation index adopted by Cai et al. (
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and Horton et al. (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) is found to have failed to capture the wintertime frequent haze events in China due to a weak linkage between surface air pollution and upper air wind speed (
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Following recent studies (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), which include the boundary layer height to represent the strength of vertical mixing instead of the upper air wind speed, a new metric is proposed. We define the occurrence of an atmospheric stagnation event when the ventilation coefficient (the product of surface wind speed and boundary layer height in this study) within 1 d is less than 800 m
 <sup>2</sup>⋅s
 <sup>−1</sup> and the precipitation accumulation is less than 1 mm⋅d
 <sup>−1</sup> (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The new air stagnation index is able to capture 72% of winter severe haze days with PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> &gt; 150 μg/m
 <sup>3</sup> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S5
 </ext-link>); thus, it is effective in representing air stagnation. A heavy precipitation event is defined as when the daily precipitation exceeds 20 mm⋅d
 <sup>−1</sup> (
 <xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). The intensification of future heat wave and precipitation extremes projected by this study is consistent with previous climate extreme studies over China based on the CMIP5 multimodel ensembles (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). The projected increased frequency of stagnation events in this study is similar to that of a previous study using an ensemble of regional climate model simulations (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).
</p>
