<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic amplification and mid-latitude winter circulation</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to declining sea-ice, the Arctic Ocean absorbs more incoming solar radiation from spring to autumn. By early winter, when near-surface air temperatures drop below sea-surface temperatures, this excessive heat is released into the atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. The additional heat inflates the lower troposphere over the Arctic Ocean and nearby continents, and increase geopotential heights, which could affect circulation patterns further south.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed increase in Arctic geopotential heights
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> might reduce the poleward pressure gradient in the troposphere and therefore weaken the storm tracks and westerly jet. However, this notion based on thermal-wind balance and baroclinicity provides little explanation for the recent changes in winter circulation. In winter, the near-surface warming in the Arctic has been pronounced but confined to high latitudes only, i.e., north of 70° N
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Within the mid-latitudes (i.e., 30° N–60° N), neither the poleward temperature gradient nor the zonal-mean jet or storm track have seen any significant changes in winter
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Future climate model projections under high-emission scenarios show that both changes in the tropics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> and in the Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> can influence the strength and position of the mid-latitude winter circulation. Enhanced warming projected in the tropical tropopause region (due to enhanced deep convection and latent heating) acts to increase the upper-level poleward temperature gradient, which strengthens the mid-latitude westerlies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This has become known as the tug-of-war (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), whereby tropical changes tend to strengthen mid-latitude circulation and lead to a poleward migration, whereas AA has the opposite effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic figure illustrating the main seasonal differences in upper tropospheric circulation between winter (January) and summer (July). Panels 
     <span class="bold">a</span> and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> show 250-hPa wind speed (green-to-blue shading) illustrating the jet streams with black arrow lines that follow the zone of maximum wind speed. The wintertime stratospheric polar vortex is outlined with the thick green line following the 30-hPa maximum wind speed. Panels 
     <span class="bold">c</span> and 
     <span class="bold">d</span> show the 250 hPa meridional wind speed (dark gray-to-dark red shading) depicting the stationary wave features associated with the jet streams. White arrows are added to illustrate wind direction. Basic differences in the summer circulation features, as compared to winter, include shorter stationary waves, more northerly subtropical jet, absence of stratospheric polar vortex and an Arctic front jet forming double jets. Data are 1970–2000 climatology of NCEP Reanalysis
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" href="#CR134">134</a>
     </span> (downloadable: 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/data.ncep.reanalysis.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/data.ncep.reanalysis.html</span>). (Figure created using Panoply and Apple’s Keynote software)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5256_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e590" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many recent winters were characterized by extremely warm temperatures in the Arctic and anomalously cold conditions further south, especially over Eurasia. In fact, large areas over central Eurasia have been cooling since 1990
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Possible dynamical mechanisms behind this warm-Arctic cold-continent pattern involving sea-ice loss consist of a direct tropospheric pathway
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> and pathways involving the stratospheric polar vortex (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. In the latter hypothesis, increased geopotential heights over high-latitude regions can cause a pronounced upward wave propagation into the stratosphere which can weaken the stratospheric polar vortex and, in extreme cases, trigger sudden stratospheric warming events. A weak polar vortex can propagate downwards into the troposphere causing a negative Arctic oscillation (AO) that is conducive to cold spells in Eurasia and Siberia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is relatively high confidence that this stratospheric pathway is a real phenomenon and has a role in the warm-Arctic cold-continent pattern, as it is supported by multiple lines of evidence: From empirical analyses, to causal discovery algorithms, and climate model simulations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. Still, its relative importance compared to other pathways, tropical influences and atmosphere internal variability remains unclear
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
