<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" sec-type="box" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BOX 2 Atmospheric teleconnections in summer</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Remote climate effects, known as atmospheric teleconnections, consist of three main types: (i) regional long-wave pattern confined in a longitudinal sector of the globe, like the Pacific-North America pattern and the North Atlantic Oscillation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" href="#CR135">135</a>
  </span>; (ii) a hemisphere-wide pattern with a prominent zonal-mean component like the Arctic Oscillation or the Annular Modes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" href="#CR136">136</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>
  </span>; and (iii) the trapping and focusing effects of the seasonal jet streams on low-frequency tropospheric waves
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, known as the waveguide effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. The figure below shows schematic representations of these three types of teleconnection patterns.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The summer North Atlantic Oscillation (SNAO) can be regarded as the counterpart of the more robust winter NAO. The centers of action of the SNAO exhibit a more northerly location, have a smaller geographical extent and a weaker dipole pattern compared to the winter NAO. Panel a schematically shows the surface pressure patterns of the positive SNAO phase, i.e., when pressure differences are strong, together with the position of the warmer/drier and colder/wetter regions. Generally, the negative phase shows a reverse pattern. Like the winter NAO, the impact of the SNAO on climate extremes such as heavy rainfall and flooding is profound, especially for Europe. Post-2007 summers have seen increasingly robust negative SNAO associated with a persistent anticyclonic anomaly over Greenland and a cyclonic anomaly over Northwest Europe. This pattern caused rapid melting of the Greenland ice sheet and brought unusually wet summers to Northwest Europe, including the massive flooding of U.K. in summer 2012. Future projections of climate models suggest an increasingly positive SNAO in warmer climates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138" href="#CR138">138</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Northern Hemisphere Annular Mode (NAM) is an internally driven atmospheric mode maintained by both stationary and transient waves. The NAM is defined as the first EOF of monthly 500 hPa geopotential height fields and coincides with the definition of the Arctic Oscillation during the winter months
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>
  </span>. Winter and summer NAM patterns present both a diverse geopotential height field, mean meridional circulation and eddy structure. The summer NAM has a smaller latitudinal extent and has a stronger link to surface air temperature over Eurasia. The positive phase of the summer NAM is associated with negative geopotential height anomalies over Greenland and the Arctic Ocean and an annual band of positive anomalies comprised between 40° and 60° N and particularly extended over Eurasia, as schematically shown in panel b. When the summer NAM is strongly positive, the storm tracks follow the Arctic front
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>
  </span>. Anomalously positive summer NAM phases are associated with double jets favoring blocking between the polar and the subtropical jets. During a positive summer NAM phase, surface temperatures over Eurasia show a dipole pattern with warmer conditions over Europe and colder conditions over East Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The energy of waves trapped in a waveguide is not dispersed as broadly as in teleconnections of type (i) and therefore it can propagate farther before being dissipated. In summer, when an efficiently trapping waveguide becomes (almost) circumglobal, then resonant interactions between free and forced waves (typically of synoptic scale, wavenumbers 6–8) might lead to wave-amplification and persistent, high-amplitude waves. Waveguide formation is favored during double-jet regimes and thus linked to strongly positive NAM phases. Panel c shows a schematic representation of a wave-resonance event with an amplified wave 7. The orange and green areas represent regions of positive and negative upper-level meridional winds. Such events are associated with alternating hot-dry and cold-wet conditions, following the ridges and troughs. Such a situation is prone to blocking weather systems and deepened troughs, and their relative longevity is key to making severe weather extremes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Wave-resonance periods have therefore been linked to both persistent heatwaves and severe flooding events
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, blocking itself is also distinctly different in summer compared to winter. Upstream latent heat release has been identified as an important contributor to persistent blocking and this mechanism is especially important in summer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139" href="#CR139">139</a>
  </span>.
  <span xlink:href="41467_2018_5256_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e1184" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Figure Box 2:</span> Panel 
  <span class="bold">a</span> shows a schematic of the positive SNAO indicating the anomalously low (blue) and high (red) sea level pressure regions together with cold/wet and dry/warm regions. Panel 
  <span class="bold">b</span> shows a schematic of the 500 hPa geopotential height configuration during the positive phase of the NAM. Rainy clouds mark the position of the storm tracks during a strongly positive NAM phase. Panel 
  <span class="bold">c</span> shows a schematic of an amplified wave 7. Green and orange regions show the position of pronounced northward and southward wind anomalies. (Figure created using Python, GIMP, Powerpoint and Inkscape software)
 </p>
</sec>
