<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Due to climate change, food will be produced in altered climatic conditions in modified surrounding ecosystems. The interactions between these changes and the food system are complex, and hence, there are major uncertainties over the resulting effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Possibly the most important consequence is the potential for emergence or re-emergence of novel pathogenic bacteria, viruses and parasites. These phenomena are highly non-linear, difficult to predict and may occur through many mechanisms. For example, an increased use of indoor animal husbandry to counteract heat stress may elevate the potential for animal-to-animal transmission of zoonotic pathogens. Alternatively, an increased growing season may lead to greater use of outdoor pasture increasing the probability of pathogen transmission from the environment. The development of (or preference for) new livestock breeds less susceptible to heat stress may have impacts upon their pathogen susceptibility [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>], and changes in livestock patterns may provide possibilities for pathogens to cross between species. For many pathogens, the environment plays an important role in transmission [e.g. Campylobacter jejuni; [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]] and hence changing environmental conditions (e.g. temperature) may alter the geographical distribution, diversity, levels and seasonality of the pathogen in the natural and farm environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>] with consequences for pathogen levels in food. A changing environment has been linked to the emergence of new pathogens in South America [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. Marine systems may also be affected, and levels of 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio vulnificus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> in shellfish are influenced by sea surface temperature and by rainfall affecting salinity levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. It is difficult to predict these changes so increased preparedness is a natural strategy.
</p>
