<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.3. Spatial Distribution for RS of the Climate Change-Sensitive Disease</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides finding out which diseases’ transmission would be affected by climate change, we also investigated where infectious diseases were more sensitive to climate change, in support of the prevention of these infectious diseases in local areas. Here, the top two infectious disease, 
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, HFMs and dysenteries were employed to explain the spatial distribution of the relative sensitivity indicator in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-00767-f004" href="#ijerph-12-00767-f004">Figure 4</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-00767-f005" href="#ijerph-12-00767-f005">Figure 5</a>. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Anhui Province, a total of 169,287 HFM cases and 92,047 dysentery cases were reported from 2004 to 2010. In spatial distribution, the prevalence of HFM was sensitive to temperature change in 63% of the effective counties, which are scattered around the northeast, midwest and south parts of Anhui Province (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-00767-f004" href="#ijerph-12-00767-f004">Figure 4</a>a). 
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-00767-f004" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The spatial distribution of 
    <span class="italic">RS</span> for HFM in Anhui Province: (
    <span class="bold">a</span>) RS to temperature; (
    <span class="bold">b</span>) RS to precipitation; (
    <span class="bold">c</span>) RS to absolute humidity.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-00767-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is worthwhile to note that the relative sensitivity of HFM in eight cities among the twelve effective cities was smaller compared to that in the surrounding rural counties. There was also a similar phenomenon in the effect of absolute humidity change on HFM. The incidence of HFM in eleven cities of the sixteen effective cities were less sensitive than that in the nearby rural counties to the change of absolute humidity. It is evident that better medical conditions in cities 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> rural counties can reduce sensitivity of climate change to some extent. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As for dysentery, the thirty five counties where disease outbreak was sensitive to the temperature change were mainly located along a band distribution from the northwest to southeast. The counties with significantly different association between dysentery incidence and precipitation in the exposure and non-exposure groups were mainly located along the Huai River and Yangtze River. For most parts of Anhui Province, except some southwestern counties, dysentery incidence was sensitive to the change of absolute humidity. Moreover, the relative sensitivity to absolute humidity in thirteen urban cities was smaller than that in the surrounding rural counties. That is to say, rural areas may be the key areas that need more inputs in response to climate change due to the relatively underdeveloped medical conditions. </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-00767-f005" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The spatial distribution of RS for dysentery in Anhui Province: (
    <span class="bold">a</span>) RS to temperature; (
    <span class="bold">b</span>) RS to precipitation; (
    <span class="bold">c</span>) RS to absolute humidity.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-00767-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
