<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Our study species is Austrian yellow-cress, 
 <italic class="italic">Rorippa austriaca</italic> (Crantz) Besser (Brassicaceae). Like many species that have expanded their range poleward due to climate change (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2011</xref>), this perennial plant has expanded its range northward from its original distribution in southeastern Europe to the current northern range limit in southern Scandinavia (Bleeker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2003</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Rorippa austriaca</italic> was first recorded in the Netherlands between 1900 and 1925 and has increased in abundance there in the last decades (Tamis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2004</xref>). In addition to climate change, the increasing connection of waterways in Europe may have contributed to its range expansion. The spread of the species occurs mostly naturally along rivers. Human-aided spread can happen through redistributions of soils (Keil 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">1999</xref>). Habitats where 
 <italic class="italic">R. austriaca</italic> occurs in its novel range are riversides, ruderal areas and agricultural fields (Bleeker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2003</xref>, Table S1). It has been considered invasive in parts of its new range, e.g., Germany and the Netherlands, where it also hybridizes with native 
 <italic class="italic">Rorippa</italic> species (Bleeker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2003</xref>; Engelkes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2012</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Rorippa austriaca</italic>, like most Brassicaceae, contains glucosinolates as defense compounds (Huberty et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2014</xref>). The species has also been introduced from Europe to North America. Plants of invasive populations in North American grew bigger than native Austrian plants but showed no difference in resistance to generalist slug herbivory (Buschmann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2005</xref>). We used plants from three European regions, two regions that are recently colonized, the Netherlands (five populations) and southern Germany (two populations) and one region at the core distribution, the Czech Republic (five populations), and had an experimental site in each of the regions. The plants from the Czech Republic were from the western edge of the core distribution. We planted the same ten individuals of each population, propagated via root cuttings, in each site. To test the effect of insect communities and gastropods on the plants in the experimental sites, all plants were caged individually with open or closed cages to either include or exclude insects and gastropods. Plant performance, herbivore damage/presence, and chemical defenses were measured for one growing season. Our aim was to investigate (a) whether plants would perform better in their home region (regional adaptation) with and without herbivory, (b) whether herbivory was less in the novel range compared to the core edge region due to potential enemy release in the recently colonized range, and (c) whether plant origins differed in herbivory and chemical defenses.
</p>
