<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concluding remarks and future directions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recombination is a fundamental component of meiosis and a near universal mechanism in multicellular organisms, with far-reaching effects on an individual's fitness and on evolutionary processes. Whole-genome sequencing, dense marker panels and the development of new approaches to estimate population-scaled recombination rates have provided new opportunities to estimate recombination at much greater resolution and across natural populations, with great impact. Genome-wide averages of recombination rate are useful for broad-scale comparisons; however, averaging the number of recombination events across the genome can mask the dynamic nature of changes in distribution at a finer genomic scale. Studies in the future should consider the fine genomic landscape and not only the frequency. Across eukaryotes, there is large variation between taxa, populations and individuals in the frequency and distribution of recombination. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F1" href="#RSTB20160455F1">figure 1</a>, we illustrate how variation collected and compared across different taxonomic scales provides complementary information to address many important and outstanding questions about how and why recombination varies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significant progress has been made recently in identifying the genetic and epigenetic mechanisms governing the recombination landscape; for example, the presence or absence of one locus in particular (
  <span class="italic">PRDM9</span>) can explain variation across species and how conserved or dynamic their recombination landscape is. However, it is unclear how widespread recombination hotspots are, and if all hotspots fall broadly into two categories—conserved versus rapidly evolving, although comparative studies are moving some way to elucidate this issue [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C88" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C88">88</a>]. Other features of the recombination landscape, such as sex differences and plasticity, are also lacking empirical support across a wide range of taxa. We urge researchers to collect recombination data at the fine genomic scale in a greater range of species, in particular neglected taxa (marine microorganisms, basal animals and plants) and to estimate (and report) both sex-specific and sex-averaged recombination rates. LD-based estimates are likely to be especially powerful in this respect as they provide opportunities to estimate recombination rate from polymorphism data of sampled populations without the need to create crosses or use pedigrees. Data from a greater range of species can further our understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying recombination and enable us to address a range of long-standing questions regarding the evolution of recombination.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding the fitness consequences and evolutionary processes driving variation in recombination rate is still in its infancy. Investigation of how changes in recombination can directly influence phenotypic traits and fitness is needed and, although established theory on the evolution of sex considers the conditions under which changes in the GwRR may be favoured, there are almost no empirical data testing these predictions in sexual organisms. More comparisons across related taxa, populations and individuals in the field are needed to characterize natural variation in recombination rate. Comparisons across populations and taxa could ask if, for example, drift, fluctuating selection and modes of reproduction covary with variation in recombination. Studying the recombination landscape across an environmental or ecological gradient while controlling for possible confounding effects of drift and changes in 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>e</sub> are likely to be most informative. Experimental evolution studies could manipulate population parameters and see if recombination rate evolves in response to changes in density, inbreeding, fluctuating selection and parasites, and could investigate how changes in recombination rate influence fitness-related traits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More effort should be devoted to modelling recombination rate as a quantitative trait and consider how it will respond to different selection regimes in sexually reproducing organisms (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C60" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C60">60</a>]). Models of the evolution of GwRRs may have limited power to explain variation in the landscape at fine genomic scales. Mathematical models could explore how selection influences patterns of recombination near loci under strong selection or loci involved in coevolutionary arms races, for example. Regional suppression of recombination on specific genomic features (inversions, supergenes) is receiving increased attention in the literature, spurred on by the recognition that the association of these features with suppressed recombination is key to adaptation and speciation in the presence of gene flow. Current empirical challenges reside in determining the sequence of events that have permitted favourable genomic features or recombination modifiers to establish and be maintained in the presence of gene flow, from the selection of pre-existing favourable genomic features to the selection of mechanisms generating them during the course of the processes of adaptation and speciation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To summarize, there is enormous variation in recombination frequency and landscape across species and genomes. Great progress has been made in determining the genetic and epigenetic factors controlling recombination, but more theoretical and empirical data are needed to further our understanding of why recombination varies and to determine if this variation is the result of selection.</p>
</sec>
