<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Patterns of variation in recombination</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recombination can be compared at different taxonomic scales and at different genomic resolutions, and information at these different scales provides opportunities to address different questions about how and why recombination rate varies (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F1" href="#RSTB20160455F1">figure 1</a>). Recent advances in DNA sequencing technologies and in methods to estimate recombination rate from genetic variation data (polymorphisms) sampled from a population have facilitated estimates of the genome-wide recombination rate (GwRR) across species and provided new opportunities to determine the distribution of recombination at a finer genomic scale (see 
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX1" href="#RSTB20160455BX1">box 1</a>). A pervasive pattern to emerge from these studies is that recombination events are distinctly non-random, and two important patterns are recognized. First, the exchange of DNA during a CO event at a location on the chromosome (known as a chiasma) tends to suppress the creation of nearby chiasma, in a process known as CO interference [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C40">40</a>], and, second, recombination events are often localized into narrow regions, termed hotspots, where recombination is an order of magnitude (2–10×) higher than the average. Hotspots have been observed in a range of organisms, e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Saccharomyces</span> yeast [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C41">41</a>], fungal pathogens [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C42">42</a>], plants (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C43">43</a>]), mammals [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C44">44</a>] and birds [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C45">45</a>], but are absent from others, e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</span> [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C46">46</a>], honeybees [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C47">47</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila</span> (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C48">48</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C49">49</a>]). Studies across different taxonomic scales have shown that recombination frequency and landscape may be controlled by different mechanisms in different taxa. Consequently, describing how recombination frequency and landscape vary at different taxonomic scales, from distantly related taxa to individuals, is a key step towards understanding their rate of evolution as well as their proximal and ultimate correlates. 
  <div id="RSTB20160455F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparing recombination landscape and frequency (REC) across different taxonomic and spatial scales (boxes on the left) provides complementary data to address outstanding questions about how and why recombination varies (boxes on right).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20160455-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <div id="RSTB20160455BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="boxed-text" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Box 1.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Estimating recombination rate.</div>
  </div>
  <p>Two parameters can describe how patterns of recombination vary between any two individuals or groups of individuals: the GwRR (how often COs occur e.g. in a given meiosis) and the recombination landscape (where COs occur in the genome). These estimates of recombination rate are commonly expressed as the recombination frequency per mega- or kilobase per generation [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C11">11</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C23">23</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>] and can be estimated at different genomic resolutions. Historically, recombination rates were estimated by directly counting the number of chiasmata during meiosis using cytogenetic methods, and from early linkage maps, where phenotypes and/or genetic markers were ordered along chromosomes based on the frequency at which they were co-inherited (i.e. not separated by a CO). A spacing of one centimorgan (cM) indicates a one per cent chance that two genes will be separated by crossing over. Both approaches provided coarse-scale estimates of the recombination frequency, but lacked accuracy. In particular, linkage map estimates of recombination require pedigree information and are limited by the number of independent meioses characterized (i.e as a function of sample size, pedigree size and depth), and if marker densities are low, they fail to capture all COs and underestimate map length [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C28">28</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C29">29</a>]. Low-resolution estimates of recombination provide limited information about the recombination landscape, but can provide useful data for looking at large-scale differences between chromosomes, chromosome arms or chromosome segments. These estimates also provide common measures that are comparable across larger taxonomic scales.
  </p>
  <p>Today, the resolution to determine recombination rates and landscapes has dramatically improved with developments in high-throughput sequencing and genotyping technologies. It is now feasible to obtain estimates of recombination rate on a finer genomic scale, with dense linkage maps and population-scaled estimates of recombination rate. While linkage maps provide an estimate of COs observed over a few generations, population-scaled approaches provide estimates of historical recombination [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C30">30</a>]. This approach uses high-density marker and/or genome sequence data to estimate population-scaled recombination rates (
   <span class="italic">ρ</span>) using coalescent methods that model patterns of linkage disequilibrium (LD), the non-random association of alleles across loci, within narrow genomic regions. These approaches have been used to identify recombination ‘hotspots’. A limitation of coalescent estimates is that LD is also affected by the effective population size of a population, which is influenced by the population's demographic history (e.g. bottlenecks, gene flow, selection (e.g. [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C31">31</a>])). However, new developments in population-based approaches are implementing ways to account for demographic history during recombination rate inference (e.g. [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C32">32</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C33">33</a>]).
  </p>
  <p>Despite their differences, results from linkage map and population-based estimates are highly correlated [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C31">31</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C34">34</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C37">37</a>]. It is also important to note that all marker-based estimates (linkage map and population-based estimates) can only detect a recombination event that results in a change in the allelic combination in the next generation (effective recombination)—for example, if parents are homozygote across many markers, the action of recombination is not detectable and recombination is typically only measured from gametes that successfully produced offspring (realized recombination). One method to quantify recombination events in all gametes, not just those that produce offspring, is to genotype or whole-genome sequence single sperm. For example, in humans this approach has been used to fine-map the recombination landscape and investigate transmission distortion and allelic drive [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C38">38</a>], and in 
   <span class="italic">Daphnia</span> it was used to build a genetic linkage that helped to improve the genome assembly [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C39">39</a>].
  </p>
 </div>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation across distantly related eukaryote taxa</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There have been several comparisons of the GwRR per base, kilobase (Kb) or megabase (Mb) across distantly related taxa [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C23">23</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C24">24</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C50">50</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C51">51</a>]. The most striking pattern to emerge was that microorganisms and fungi have much higher recombination rates compared to animals and plants [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C23">23</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C24">24</a>]. However, these studies were carried out in a relatively small number of species, often relying on chiasma count data in a single sex. Therefore, we compiled data on linkage map length, haploid chromosome number (HCN) and genome size from all the major groups of eukaryotes, to provide a more comprehensive and up-to-date picture of recombination rate variation. Details of the methods and data are provided in the electronic supplementary material, and a summary of the species included in our dataset is in 
   <a rid="RSTB20160455TB1" ref-type="table" href="#RSTB20160455TB1">table 1</a> (see the electronic supplementary material for full list). Briefly, we obtained sex-averaged linkage map lengths, genome size and HCN from the published literature and public databases. In cases where a species had multiple maps, we chose the map with the most markers or the most individuals in cases where two maps had a similar number of markers. We omitted linkage maps with fewer than 50 markers and where the number of linkage groups (LG) and the HCN differed markedly (absolute(LG–HCN)/HCN &gt; 0.7). In our analyses, we controlled for phylogeny by fitting a Phylogenetic Generalized Linear Model with the R Package ‘Caper’ [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C52">52</a>]. The phylogeny was obtained using the Phylotastic Web Service (
   <span xlink:href="https://github.com/phylotastic/phylo_services_docs/blob/master/ServiceDescription/PhyloServicesDescription.md" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/phylotastic/phylo_services_docs/blob/master/ServiceDescription/PhyloServicesDescription.md</span>), which extracts a Supertree from openTree [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C53">53</a>]. All branch lengths were set to 1 in the Supertree. In total, we obtained data for 353 species, across animals, plants, fungi and the SAR (Stramenopiles-Alveolates-Rhizaria Eukaryote) supergroup. Not surprisingly, there is a bias towards model species, domestic and crop species, and parasitic or disease-causing species, for which quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping studies have been the focus of much research. 
   <div id="RSTB20160455TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Summary of the linkage map data compiled from the literature; linkage map length (centimorgans, cM), genome size (megabases, Mb), haploid chromosome number and recombination rate (cM/Mb). SAR, Stramenopiles-Alveolates-Rhizaria Eukaryote.</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead valign="bottom">
      <tr>
       <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">group</th>
       <th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">n</span>
       </th>
       <th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">linkage map length (cM)
        <span class="hr"/>
       </th>
       <th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">genome size (Mb)
        <span class="hr"/>
       </th>
       <th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">haploid chromosome number
        <span class="hr"/>
       </th>
       <th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">recombination rate (cM/Mb)
        <span class="hr"/>
       </th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAR</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1782</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">653</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2884</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.87</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">560</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.78</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.67</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108.00</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fungi</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2068</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5860</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.26</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.05</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170.2</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.27</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.68</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.90</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">animals</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1813</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5961</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1538</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.15</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 880</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.27</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.10</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">plants</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">189</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1567</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8184</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2956</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.40</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 280</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.91</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.22</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">total or mean</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">353</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1807.5</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1183.0</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.05</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.93</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the GwRR from linkage map data, we divided the linkage map length (the sum of the length of all sex-averaged LGs) by the haploid genome size (in Mb) (
   <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX2" href="#RSTB20160455BX2">box 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F2" href="#RSTB20160455F2">figure 2</a>). This is a commonly reported measure of recombination rate [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C11">11</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C23">23</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>] and provides a useful metric to compare across taxa with vastly different genome sizes. This measure averages recombination across both the open and transcriptionally active euchromatic region and the closed and inactive heterochromatic regions of the genome. Recombination is often suppressed in heterochromatic regions, and the strength of suppression and the proportion of the genome that is heterochromatic vary greatly between organisms (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C69">69</a>]). Thus, the GwRR represents a genome average that reveals differences in recombination rate, but will be related to differences in the amount of heterochromatin in the genome and how strongly recombination is suppressed in these regions. Taking account of the proportion of the genome that is heterochromatic may provide more informative estimates of recombination with respect to evolutionary processes [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C69">69</a>]; however, these data are only available for relatively few organisms, so we have not included them in this analysis. Overall, our analysis confirms the previously reported pattern of a higher GwRR in fungi and SAR compared to plants and animals, but also provides estimates for new taxonomic groups (electronic supplementary material, figures S1–S3) and opportunities to begin to address enduring questions about the evolution of recombination rate (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F1" href="#RSTB20160455F1">figure 1</a>). 
   <div id="RSTB20160455F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Variation in the log of recombination rate, estimated by dividing linkage map length in centimorgans (cM) by genome size (Mb) across eukaryotic taxa. Other plants: Pteridophyta, Chlorophyta, Bryophyta. Other animals: Anthzoa, Holothuriodea, Ascidacae. unseg, unsegmented.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rstb20160455-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <div id="RSTB20160455BX2" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="boxed-text" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Box 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">How does recombination rate vary with genome architecture?</div>
   </div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Genome size</span>
   </p>
   <p>Following the observation that linkage map length was similar across eukaryotes despite large variation in genome size, it was proposed that larger genomes have several orders of magnitude lower recombination rates [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C51">51</a>]. This is consistent with the observed relationships between recombination rate and sequence features; recombination rate is positively correlated with gene density and negatively with the density of repetitive elements, which could drive lower recombination rates in large, repeat-rich genomes [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C54">54</a>]. Higher recombination rates can also lead to reductions in genome size—if recombination rate increases the mutation rate and small deletions are more common than small insertions (mutational bias), purifying selection on these mutations can drive genome contraction [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C55">55</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C56">56</a>]. Both positive and negative relationships between genome size and recombination rate have been found (positive [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C57">57</a>], negative [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C24">24</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C50">50</a>]). The disparity in results may be attributed to differences in the methods used and taxonomic breadths considered, but may also be due to statistical problems. When the recombination rate is calculated as the linkage map length (cM) divided by genome size (Kb or Mb), then genome size and recombination are mathematically coupled; it is not appropriate to test for relationship between mathematically coupled variables [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C58">58</a>]. To investigate the relationship between genome size and recombination rate, we examined the fit of linear and quadratic relationships between linkage map length and genome size, while controlling for phylogeny. In animals and fungi, a linear model best fit the data, but in plants, a quadratic model was a better fit (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
    <span class="italic">a</span>; electronic supplementary material). This suggests that recombination rate is lower in larger plant genomes, but in animals and fungi there is no evidence to suggest recombination rate declines with genome size. 
    <div id="RSTB20160455F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Observed (points) and fitted (lines) relationships between: (
       <span class="italic">a</span>) log genome size (megabases, Mb) and log linkage map length (centimorgans, cM), (
       <span class="italic">b</span>) log haploid chromosome number (HCN) and log linkage map length (cM) and (
       <span class="italic">c</span>) log HCN and log recombination rate measured as linkage map (cM) divided by genome size (Mb). Fitted linear and quadratic relationships were obtained by fitting a phylogenetic generalized linear model separately for plants, animals and fungi.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="rstb20160455-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Haploid chromosome number</span>
   </p>
   <p>The number and size of chromosomes can explain variation in the GwRR because a minimum of one CO per chromosome (or chromosome arm) is often required to ensure proper segregation of chromosomes during meiosis [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C13">13</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C59">59</a>–
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C62">62</a>]. There are several exceptions: some chromosomes do not recombine in one sex (e.g. achiasmate species; see §2c) and often more than one CO per chromosome is observed on larger chromosomes (see [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C62">62</a>]). Under the obligate CO requirement, a higher recombination rate could be achieved by increasing the number of chromosomes or by having smaller chromosomes; bird genomes, containing many microchromosomes, provide support for this hypothesis [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C37">37</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C63">63</a>]. Whether karyotypic variation is driven by selection on recombination rate is unclear (e.g. [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C64">64</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C65">65</a>]), but Burt [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C66">66</a>] demonstrated that an increase in the efficacy of selection was better achieved by increasing the number of COs per chromosome rather than increasing the number of chromosomes. Whole-genome duplication and polyploidy are dramatic ways to increase chromosome number, and under an obligate CO requirement, this should result in at least a doubling of chiasma frequency. Polyploids' ability to achieve stable meiosis may be partly due to a reduction in the GwRR (and increase in interference distance) to ensure only one CO per pair of homologous chromosomes, as a mechanism to avoid the pairing of three or more homologous chromosomes [
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C67">67</a>,
    <a rid="RSTB20160455C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C68">68</a>]. The data we compiled provide an opportunity to test whether HCN explains variation in linkage map length and the GwRR (cM/Mb) across eukaryotes. A positive linear relationship between linkage map length and HCN was found for plants and fungi, while in animals a quadratic relationship was slightly better at explaining this relationship (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
    <span class="italic">b</span>; electronic supplementary material). We found that the HCN was not related to GwRR (per Mb) in fungi and animals, and although a relationship was found in plants, the amount of variation explained was low (
    <span class="italic">r</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.02) (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
    <span class="italic">c</span>; electronic supplementary material). Despite explaining little variation, we do suggest that scaling the GwRR by HCN provides a useful comparative measure of recombination rate and removes variation attributable to the obligate CO requirement.
   </p>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast with comparing recombination rate across distantly related taxa, comparisons within specific taxonomic groups are more common (i.e. mammals [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C59">59</a>], plants [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C25">25</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C57">57</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C70">70</a>], homopterous insects [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C71">71</a>] and hymenoptera [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C64">64</a>]), and several notable patterns have been identified. For example, among insects, social hymenoptera have much higher recombination rates [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C23">23</a>]; among mammals, marsupials have lower recombination rates [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C72" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C72">72</a>]; and among plants, conifers have very low recombination rates [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C25">25</a>]. Comparing within taxonomic groups in our data, we also observed these patterns and make several new observations: among Crustaceans, the Cladocerans (represented by two species of Daphnia) have much higher recombination rates (electronic supplementary material, figure S1), Dipterans have the lowest rates of recombination rate across insects (electronic supplementary material, figure S1) and fishes have the highest recombination rate among vertebrates (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F2" href="#RSTB20160455F2">figure 2</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation among closely related taxa and between populations within species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linking variation in recombination rates between closely related species and between populations with variation in selection and demography may elucidate long-term mechanisms driving recombination rate evolution. Differences in chiasma count between sister species, populations, accessions and inbred lines of cultivated and model species have been studied since the 1930s (e.g. [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C73" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C73">73</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C76" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C76">76</a>]). Within a more ecological context (i.e. natural populations, non-model species), early empirical work identified relationships between chiasma frequency and ecological and environmental variables. For example, chiasma frequency per bivalent (Cf/B) in orthopterans is associated with latitude (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C15">15</a>]) and was higher in low-density populations of grasshoppers [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C77" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C77">77</a>] and snails [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C78" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C78">78</a>], and in plants Cf/B was higher in selfers compared to outcrosses [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C79" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C79">79</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C80" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C80">80</a>]. In many cases where clinal variation in recombination has been detected, karyotypic differences, which are known to modify recombination, are also present (e.g. accessory or B chromosomes (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C15">15</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C78" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C78">78</a>]), chromosomal inversions [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C78" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C78">78</a>]). These karyotypic differences can suppress the GwRR and may explain the variation observed. At a finer genomic scale, comparisons between closely related taxa find, in general, greater variation in the recombination landscape compared to the GwRR. For example, similar linkage map lengths are evident across species (e.g. 
   <span class="italic">Eucalyptus</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C81" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C81">81</a>], flycatchers (
   <span class="italic">Ficedula)</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C34">34</a>]), strains (e.g. 
   <span class="italic">C. briggsae</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C82" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C82">82</a>]), cultivars (e.g. maize (
   <span class="italic">Zea mays</span>) [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C83" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C83">83</a>]) and populations (e.g. great tit (
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C84" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C84">84</a>], honeybee (
   <span class="italic">Apis mellifera</span>) [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C85" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C85">85</a>]). In most mammals, the position of hotspots appears to be dynamic, differing between subspecies of mice [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C86" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C86">86</a>] and between humans and chimps [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C32">32</a>], while hotspot location is more conserved in other groups, for example birds [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C34">34</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C45">45</a>], dogs [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C35">35</a>] and in 
   <span class="italic">Saccharomyces</span> yeast [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C87" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C87">87</a>]. Recent work in determining the molecular mechanisms governing hotspot activity has shed light on this pattern: most notably, in species with rapidly evolving hotspots, hotspot position is determined by a common gene (
   <span class="italic">PRDM9</span>), whereas this gene is missing or non-functional in species with more conserved hotspots ([
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C88" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C88">88</a>] and discussed in §3b).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in recombination between the sexes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most widely reported within-species variation in recombination rate is that seen between the sexes. Differences between sexes can be as extreme as one sex lacking recombination completely (achiasmy), or where recombination is present but different in both sexes, in terms of the rate and landscape (heterochiasmy), [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C89" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C89">89</a>]. Achiasmy has evolved independently at least 26 times [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C15">15</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C90" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C90">90</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C91" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C91">91</a>] and nearly always occurs in the heterogametic sex (e.g. in XY 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila</span> males and ZW 
   <span class="italic">Bombyx</span> females) [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C92" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C92">92</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C94" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C94">94</a>]. By contrast, heterochiasmy is phylogenetically dispersed across plants and animals, and reduced recombination is not always observed in the heterogametic sex [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C89" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C89">89</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C90" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C90">90</a>]. In animals and plants, females tend to have higher overall rates of recombination, although exceptions exist, such as in corals, marsupials, macaques and sheep [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C89" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C89">89</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C95" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C95">95</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C96" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C96">96</a>]. There appears to be no link between sex chromosomes or sex-determining mechanism (genetic, environmental) and the direction of heterochiasmy. However, only one species that has environmental sex determination (ESD) has been studied to date, and more studies are needed in clades that have evolved ESD multiple times (e.g. lizards and turtles) to test this more explicitly.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(d)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in recombination between individuals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examination of recombination at the individual level, using cytogenetic and pedigree-based approaches, has shown that GwRRs can vary substantially between individuals within a population. Studies in humans, cattle, sheep, mice and 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila</span> have shown that variation in regional or GwRRs (cM/Mb) often have an underlying heritable component, explaining 8–40% of the phenotypic variance in rate [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C16">16</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C18">18</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C97" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C97">97</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C98" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C98">98</a>]. Mammalian studies have identified meiotic genes that consistently underlie rate variation, notably ring finger protein 212 (
   <span class="italic">RNF212</span>); studies at finer genomic scale, e.g. in humans and cattle, have also exposed heritable differences in recombination landscape and hotspot usage mediated by variation in 
   <span class="italic">PRDM9</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C18">18</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C36">36</a>]. We explain these genetic mechanisms driving heritable variation in more detail in §3b.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2e" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(e)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation within individuals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in recombination rate has been observed within individuals, i.e. between subsequent measurements or between clones experiencing different environments, demonstrating plasticity in recombination rate. Intrinsic factors, such as age and stress, as well as a diverse range of extrinsic factors, such as parasites, have been found to influence CO frequency [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C99" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C99">99</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C101" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C101">101</a>]. Of all studies to date, there are three commonly reported factors affecting recombination rate within individuals.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first, age, has been considered in several model species, but there is little consensus in broad trends. In humans, the recombination rate (cM/Mb) tends to increase with maternal age, while there appears to be little effect of paternal age (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C102" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C102">102</a>] and references therein; for an exception see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C103" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C103">103</a>]); in mice, patterns in females and males are varied [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C104" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C104">104</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C107" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C107">107</a>]. In 
   <span class="italic">Arabadopsis thaliana</span>, paternal recombination rate (cM/Mb) measured at nine genomic intervals was stable in five of these regions, but increased with age in the other four [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C99" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C99">99</a>]. In cattle and humans, CO interference, which can set a minimum distance between neighbouring COs, decreases with maternal age, which may explain observed increases in recombination frequency [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C106" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C106">106</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C108" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C108">108</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, temperature is one of the most commonly reported extrinsic correlates of recombination rate variation. In exothermic organisms, successful completion of meiosis is sensitive to changes in temperature, which are frequently associated with failures in synapsis and subsequent declines in fertility (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C109" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C109">109</a>]). The relationship between increasing temperature and CO number and positioning varies across species; for example, in plants it is associated with increased paternal recombination in 
   <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span> and barley (
   <span class="italic">Hordeum vulgare</span> L.), but decreases in other species (e.g. 
   <span class="italic">Allium ursinum</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Locusta migratoria</span>) (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C99" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C99">99</a>]). Relationships can also vary nonlinearly with temperature, such as in 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila</span>, where the highest recombination rates occur at both high and low temperature extremes (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C109" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C109">109</a>]). Interestingly, temperature can also influence the degree of heterochiasmy; in barley, at 10°C, sex-specific rates of recombination (cM/Mb) estimated from linkage maps were similar with a male/female map length ratio of 1.02, but at 30°C this ratio increased to 1.58 [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C110" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C110">110</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third factor frequently associated with variation in recombination rate is pathogen infection. In line with predictions of the Red Queen hypothesis—enhanced recombination rates will increase the genetic diversity of offspring, so that more rapidly evolving parasites cannot exploit a static host genotype [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C111" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C111">111</a>]—studies have observed longer linkage maps, and increased recombination frequency and rate (cM/Mb) with parasite infection; e.g. 
   <span class="italic">Tribolium castenatum</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C112" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C112">112</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C113" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C113">113</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C114" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C114">114</a>] and tomato and barley [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C115" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C115">115</a>], but see other studies in e.g. mice [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C116" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C116">116</a>] and 
   <span class="italic">T. castenatum</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C117" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C117">117</a>]). A study in 
   <span class="italic">D. melanogaster</span> showed increased production of recombinant offspring in response to two bacteria and to a parasitic wasp, and this increase was driven by transmission distortion of recombinant chromatids—either during meiosis or due to asymmetric viability of gametes [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C97" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C97">97</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
