<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular mechanisms governing variation in recombination rate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meiosis evolved in the early history of eukaryotes, and many of the core mechanisms governing meiosis are highly conserved across the group [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C70">70</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C119" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C119">119</a>]. Recombination is initiated by a DSB generated by SPO11 endonuclease, which is a DNA-binding domain (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C120" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C120">120</a>]). Most DSBs are repaired via a non-crossover (NCO) pathway, which results in gene conversion rather than the exchange of DNA between chromosomes (e.g. only 5% of DSBs are repaired by CO in 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span> [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C43">43</a>], 
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 10% in mice [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C121" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C121">121</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 60% in yeast [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C122" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C122">122</a>]). Recombination is, therefore, a function of DSB formation and also a function of processes that govern CO versus NCO. Multiple factors govern the position of the DSB at multiple genomic scales; from the chromosome/sub-chromosomal regions to variation in the DNA sequence. DSBs occur predominantly within the euchromatic regions of the chromosome, preferentially in the chromatin loops, and are associated with several sequence features, with these mechanisms working hierarchically (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C119" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C119">119</a>]). For example, two identical DNA sequences can experience markedly different recombination frequencies if they occur within different chromatic regions [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C119" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C119">119</a>]; likewise, an active initiation site can lose its activity if it is inserted into a region with low DSB activity [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C123" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C123">123</a>]. In this section, we review the genetic and epigenetic factors that are associated with variation in recombination, reflecting this hierarchy; we start at the broad genomic scale, and move to DNA sequence and epigenetic levels.
 </p>
 <sec id="s3a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How does genomic architecture relate to recombination?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GwRR has often been attributed to variation in the underlying genomic architecture, namely genome size, HCN, changes in ploidy, chromosome size and chromosomal rearrangements. Although a negative relationship between genome size and recombination rate is often assumed, there are limited robust data in support of this (see 
   <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX2" href="#RSTB20160455BX2">box 2</a>). Our analysis of linkage map data across eukaryotes suggests little evidence that recombination rate decreases with genome size in fungi and animals, but that larger plant genomes have reduced recombination rates (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span> and 
   <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX2" href="#RSTB20160455BX2">box 2</a>). It should be noted that our data average across genomes with different chromosome numbers and across hetero- and euchromatic regions. In addition, we did not include data on the proportion of the genome that is heterochromatic; however, we did explore the relationship between HCN and recombination rate. Although the HCN explains variation in the total number of recombination events across a genome, i.e. the linkage map length (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>), it explains little variation in recombination rate per megabase (cM/Mb) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
   <span class="italic">c</span>). Our analysis suggests that genome architecture may play a limited role in driving variation in recombination rate at a broad scale (after controlling for phylogeny), which is consistent with the prediction that changing the number of COs per chromosomes is more effective at changing the efficacy of selection compared to changing the number of chromosomes [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C66">66</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering variation between chromosomes, recombination can be absent or greatly reduced on entire chromosomes (i.e. absent in one sex (achiasmate)) or on certain autosomes (e.g. 
   <span class="italic">D. melanogaster</span> Chr 4 and 
   <span class="italic">Toxoplasmodia gondii</span> Ch1a [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C124" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C124">124</a>]), but also influenced by the presence of chromosomal rearrangements, such as inversions, fissions, fusions and translocations. Inversions represent a well-known case of rearrangement that can modify recombination: recombination is suppressed in individuals that are heterozygous for the inversion (heterokaryotype), because the inversion causes problems with pairing and segregation during meiosis [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C125" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C125">125</a>]. This local suppression of recombination can also modify the recombination landscape in the longer term, so that suppression can extend to individuals homozygous for the inversion and to other, non-rearranged chromosomes (e.g. [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C20">20</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C126" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C126">126</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C129" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C129">129</a>]). Such a long-term suppression of recombination due to strong selection may be achieved through a reduction in hotspot loci in the inverted and rearranged regions, which persists beyond the heterozygous state of such rearrangements [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C126" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C126">126</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One broad-scale and general pattern observed within chromosomes is a lower recombination rate around centromeres. While this could be attributed to selection against recombination in highly repetitive regions, repetitive sequence is not necessary for suppression; organisms that have no or few centromeric repeats also show suppressed recombination at the centromere [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C130" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C130">130</a>]. Suppression is probably driven by chromatin structure; DSBs are less common in condensed heterochromatin, and the chromatin environment can influence the probability that a DSB is repaired with an NCO rather than a CO [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>]. Recently, Talbert &amp; Henikoff [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C130" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C130">130</a>] argued that a DSB and repair via an NCO may be common in centromeres, and this could explain the accumulation of repetitive elements and diversification of centromeres, despite apparently few COs. Differences in the chromatin structure between males and females may also explain sex differences in the GwRR in mammals; for example in mice, females have longer bivalents (less compact chromatin) and have greater CO number [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C131" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C131">131</a>]. Although heterochromatic regions are often difficult to sequence and study, it is likely they can provide important insights into factors influencing CO and NCO repair mechanisms and recombination.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fine-scale molecular genetic mechanisms related to determining recombination</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genome architecture and chromatin structure clearly influence large-scale patterns in recombination, but what do we know about the patterns at smaller genomic scales? Recombination frequency and position covary consistently with several DNA sequence features; it is positively correlated with GC content and gene density and negatively correlated with transposable element (TE) density, and it is also consistently related to a number of gene regulatory elements and to histone modification (i.e. methylation) (for review, see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C27">27</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C54">54</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C132" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C132">132</a>]). Determining cause and effect from these correlations is problematic (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C54">54</a>] for discussion about TEs). For example, recombination may drive increases in GC content via biased gene conversion in DSB repair in, for example, mammals [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C133" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C133">133</a>], insects [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C134" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C134">134</a>], birds [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C135" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C135">135</a>] and rice [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C136" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C136">136</a>]. However, in yeast, AT to GC substitutions are not directly correlated with recombination [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C137" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C137">137</a>] and GC content may be a modifier of recombination [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C138" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C138">138</a>]. Within genic regions, DSBs and subsequent recombination are more common in gene promoters or in regions with promoter-like features (see [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C43">43</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C70">70</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C120" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C120">120</a>]).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In mammals and plants, several specific genetic mechanisms underlying variation in recombination rate have been identified. For example, 
   <span class="italic">RNF212</span> (and its paralogue 
   <span class="italic">RNF212B</span>), meiotic recombination protein REC8, and E3 ubiquitin–protein ligase 
   <span class="italic">CCNB1IP1</span> homologue 
   <span class="italic">HEI10</span>, have been consistently associated with rate in maize, yeast, 
   <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span>, cattle, humans, mice and sheep [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C16">16</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C18">18</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C83" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C83">83</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C98" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C98">98</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C139" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C139">139</a>–
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C141" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C141">141</a>]. Research in mice has shown that 
   <span class="italic">RNF212</span> is essential for crossing-over, with a key role in synapsis and the formation of recombination complexes specific to COs [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C142" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C142">142</a>], whereas 
   <span class="italic">HEI10</span> plays an antagonistic role that is essential for regulating NCO/CO processes [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C139" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C139">139</a>]; studies suggest that these proteins have a dosage-dependent effect on CO rates.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As most recombination occurs in hotspots, understanding what governs hotspot position is highly relevant to revealing the genetic mechanisms governing recombination. The post-translational modification of histones, in particular trimethylation of lysine 4 on histone 3 (H3K4me3), is associated with DSB in many species [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C43">43</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C88" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C88">88</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C120" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C120">120</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C143" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C143">143</a>]. The regulatory element positive-regulatory (PR) domain zinc finger protein 9 (
   <span class="italic">PRDM9</span>), which can modify H3K4, has been shown to drive DSB formation in mice and humans [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C17">17</a>]. Not all H3K4me3 sites are recombination hotspots and many species lack functional copies or orthologues of 
   <span class="italic">PRDM9</span> (e.g. 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila</span>, yeast, dogs, birds and most plants), demonstrating that other mechanisms most certainly exist. In 
   <span class="italic">Arabidopsis,</span> DNA methylation of H3K9me2 can suppress euchromatic CO hotspots [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C144" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C144">144</a>]. There are likely to be at least two classes of hotspots: ancestral—occur in a wide range of organisms, are temporally stable and associated with gene promoter regions, and derived—location determined by e.g. the 
   <span class="italic">PRDM9</span> DNA-binding motif and rapidly evolving [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C145" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C145">145</a>]. Not all species studied have obvious recombination hotspots and considerable progress has also been made in determining the mechanisms governing recombination in these cases and outside hotspots. In 
   <span class="italic">C. elegans,</span> histone modifications do not strongly associate with recombination [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C146" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C146">146</a>]; however, other post-translational modifications have been identified; phosphorylation of 
   <span class="italic">REC-1</span> has been shown to govern CO distribution in 
   <span class="italic">C. elegans</span> [
   <a rid="RSTB20160455C147" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C147">147</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
