<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4d" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(d)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolutionary explanations for sex differences in recombination</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prevailing hypothesis for the complete absence of recombination in the heterogametic sex is that achiasmy is a pleiotropic effect of selection for tight linkage on the Y or W chromosomes and/or suppression of recombination between the heterogametic sex chromosomes [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C94" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C94">94</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C96" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C96">96</a>]. However, reduced recombination is not always observed in the heterogametic sex (i.e. birds and moths) and it cannot explain variation between the sexes in hermaphrodites [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C210" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C210">210</a>]. Understanding the conditions under which heterochiasmy evolves has been the subject of extensive theoretical attention and debate (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C96" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C96">96</a>]), but as yet, there is no consensus on its evolutionary drivers. Arguments related to the relative strengths of sexual selection, sperm competition and dispersal remain weakly supported by empirical data [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C211" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C211">211</a>], with some arguing that sex differences are primarily driven by drift [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C94" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C94">94</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C96" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C96">96</a>]. Nevertheless, there are two arguments gaining broader theoretical and empirical support. The first is haploid selection; the sex experiencing the strongest haploid selection should recombine less (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C89" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C89">89</a>]). In plants, both female and male gametes have a haploid phase, but Lenormand &amp; Dutheil [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C89" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C89">89</a>] proposed that selfing could be used as a proxy for the strength of selection on the female haploid phase, and showed that the degree of heterochiasmy (male–female ratio) was higher in species with moderate to high selfing. The second is the role of meiotic drive, for example where asymmetry in female meiosis can be exploited by selfish genetic elements associated with centromere strength [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C90" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C90">90</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C212" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C212">212</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C213" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C213">213</a>]; selection for increased recombination at centromeric regions will counteract meiotic drive by increasing the uncertainty of segregation into the egg [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C212" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C212">212</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
