<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3a" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How does genomic architecture relate to recombination?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GwRR has often been attributed to variation in the underlying genomic architecture, namely genome size, HCN, changes in ploidy, chromosome size and chromosomal rearrangements. Although a negative relationship between genome size and recombination rate is often assumed, there are limited robust data in support of this (see 
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX2" href="#RSTB20160455BX2">box 2</a>). Our analysis of linkage map data across eukaryotes suggests little evidence that recombination rate decreases with genome size in fungi and animals, but that larger plant genomes have reduced recombination rates (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span> and 
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX2" href="#RSTB20160455BX2">box 2</a>). It should be noted that our data average across genomes with different chromosome numbers and across hetero- and euchromatic regions. In addition, we did not include data on the proportion of the genome that is heterochromatic; however, we did explore the relationship between HCN and recombination rate. Although the HCN explains variation in the total number of recombination events across a genome, i.e. the linkage map length (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>), it explains little variation in recombination rate per megabase (cM/Mb) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160455F3" href="#RSTB20160455F3">figure 3</a>
  <span class="italic">c</span>). Our analysis suggests that genome architecture may play a limited role in driving variation in recombination rate at a broad scale (after controlling for phylogeny), which is consistent with the prediction that changing the number of COs per chromosomes is more effective at changing the efficacy of selection compared to changing the number of chromosomes [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C66">66</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering variation between chromosomes, recombination can be absent or greatly reduced on entire chromosomes (i.e. absent in one sex (achiasmate)) or on certain autosomes (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">D. melanogaster</span> Chr 4 and 
  <span class="italic">Toxoplasmodia gondii</span> Ch1a [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C124" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C124">124</a>]), but also influenced by the presence of chromosomal rearrangements, such as inversions, fissions, fusions and translocations. Inversions represent a well-known case of rearrangement that can modify recombination: recombination is suppressed in individuals that are heterozygous for the inversion (heterokaryotype), because the inversion causes problems with pairing and segregation during meiosis [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C125" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C125">125</a>]. This local suppression of recombination can also modify the recombination landscape in the longer term, so that suppression can extend to individuals homozygous for the inversion and to other, non-rearranged chromosomes (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C20">20</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C126" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C126">126</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C129" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C129">129</a>]). Such a long-term suppression of recombination due to strong selection may be achieved through a reduction in hotspot loci in the inverted and rearranged regions, which persists beyond the heterozygous state of such rearrangements [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C126" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C126">126</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One broad-scale and general pattern observed within chromosomes is a lower recombination rate around centromeres. While this could be attributed to selection against recombination in highly repetitive regions, repetitive sequence is not necessary for suppression; organisms that have no or few centromeric repeats also show suppressed recombination at the centromere [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C130" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C130">130</a>]. Suppression is probably driven by chromatin structure; DSBs are less common in condensed heterochromatin, and the chromatin environment can influence the probability that a DSB is repaired with an NCO rather than a CO [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C118" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C118">118</a>]. Recently, Talbert &amp; Henikoff [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C130" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C130">130</a>] argued that a DSB and repair via an NCO may be common in centromeres, and this could explain the accumulation of repetitive elements and diversification of centromeres, despite apparently few COs. Differences in the chromatin structure between males and females may also explain sex differences in the GwRR in mammals; for example in mice, females have longer bivalents (less compact chromatin) and have greater CO number [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C131" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C131">131</a>]. Although heterochromatic regions are often difficult to sequence and study, it is likely they can provide important insights into factors influencing CO and NCO repair mechanisms and recombination.
 </p>
</sec>
