<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4a" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indirect selection on variation in genome-wide recombination rate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indirect selection on recombination rate has received much empirical and theoretical consideration in order to understand the evolution of sex, but there has been less focus on understanding the processes that govern recombination variation in obligate sexuals (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C60" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C60">60</a>]). Models of the evolution of sex suggest that one of the main advantages of recombination is that it can increase the efficacy of selection and facilitate adaptation (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C3">3</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C66">66</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C151" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C151">151</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C152" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C152">152</a>]). It does this by reducing the amount that genetic variants or alleles interfere with each other's response to selection. Alleles can interfere in at least two ways: first, when the presence of one allele alters the fitness effects of another allele (epistasis); and second, when the probability of two alleles at two different loci occurring together in a population is non-random (referred to as linkage disequilibrium (LD)), which can be due to their physical proximity on a chromosome (genetically linked) or because of selection, migration or drift (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C153" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C153">153</a>]). For simplicity, we will use the more general term 
  <span class="italic">allelic non-independence</span> to refer to LD, epistasis and other processes that make alleles behave non-independently. Allelic 
  <span class="italic">non-independence</span> can interfere with how an allele responds to selection. For example, selection at one locus interferes with selection at other selected loci, reducing its probability of fixation (termed Hill–Robertson interference (HRI) [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C152" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C152">152</a>], and the degree of interference increases with genetic linkage between the loci under selection. Another example is when alleles in LD experience conflicting selection pressures—if a beneficial allele is associated with a strongly deleterious allele, it can be lost from the population, whereas a deleterious allele can rise to high frequency if it is associated with a strongly beneficial allele. Finally, selection at one locus can reduce the level of polymorphism at linked loci (an effect called background selection when purifying selection acts on a deleterious allele and selective sweep when positive selection acts on a beneficial allele), and this selection at linked sites was found to be a key factor determining genetic diversity within a species and diversity within the genome across animals and plants [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C154" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C154">154</a>]. The most recognized benefits of recombination in sexual species is that (i) it can increase the efficacy of selection by modifying the degree of independence among alleles: it can break down negative LD generated by selection and drift, thus reducing HRI; and (ii) it can create beneficial combinations of alleles and create greater genetic variation that selection can act on. What makes recombination paradoxical is that it can break apart combinations of beneficial alleles that selection has brought together, resulting in negative fitness effects, both direct [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C2">2</a>] and indirect [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C4">4</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C26">26</a>]. Therefore, the benefits of recombination are dependent on how alleles are associated and how breaking up these associations influences fitness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several demographic and ecological factors can increase the number and strength of allelic non-independence within a population. For example, small effective population size (
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>e</sub>) and high rates of inbreeding or selfing will increase associations between alleles and thus HRI; in these cases, indirect selection should favour an increase in the rate of recombination [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C66">66</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C155" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C155">155</a>]. In line with this expectation, studies have found a negative association between recombination rate and indirect measures of 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>e</sub> across species of animals and plants. In mammals, Cf/B was positively correlated with age at maturity, with greater age a proxy for smaller 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>e</sub> [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C156" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C156">156</a>], and in snails, it was negatively correlated with population density [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C78" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C78">78</a>]. In plants, recombination (cM/Mb) was higher in large, long-lived tree species compared to shrubs and herbs [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C25">25</a>]; Cf/B was higher in selfing plants [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C157" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C157">157</a>] and higher in annual plants that are probably experiencing higher rates of inbreeding and drift [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C74" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C74">74</a>]. Higher rates of asexual reproduction, for example in parthenogenetic animals or fungi, would also increase HRI and should also select for higher rates of recombination. In line with this prediction, we observed elevated recombination in parthenogenic animals compared to animals with gonochorus sexual systems—where all individuals are either male or female and reproduce sexually every generation (electronic supplementary material, figure S4). Taken together, these data suggest that optimal rates of recombination between species have evolved to reduce HRI and increase genetic variation and the efficacy of selection; however, these relationships do not provide definitive proof of causality. For example, in mammals longer-lived species have a longer meiotic arrest in females, which may favour higher recombination to prevent aneuploidy [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C158" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C158">158</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increased recombination can also evolve in populations experiencing strong directional selection and drift [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C152" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C152">152</a>], even when traits unrelated to meiosis or recombination are being selected for (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C159" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C159">159</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C160" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C160">160</a>]). This may explain observations of increased recombination in some domesticated species [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C156" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C156">156</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C161" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C161">161</a>]. However, there is mixed evidence for changes in overall recombination rates between artificially selected populations and their wild progenitors [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C152" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C152">152</a>]: a study comparing chiasma counts in wild and domesticated mammal species pairs saw no differences [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C162" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C162">162</a>], suggesting that an increase in recombination is not a universal feature of domestication.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Populations experiencing heterogeneity in selection are also expected to benefit from higher rates of recombination. In particular, higher rates are predicted when organisms experience rapid oscillations in the fitness of certain allelic combinations, for example in organisms involved in a coevolutionary arms race [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C1">1</a>], or that experience fluctuating environments [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C163" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C163">163</a>] or inter-locus sexual conflict [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C164" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C164">164</a>]. In an arms race scenario, parasite-induced selection on the host can drive an increase in recombination rate. This has been confirmed in several experimental evolution studies (see §2e) and supported by indirect evidence: high recombination in genomic regions harbouring genes related to immunity (e.g. major histocompatibility complex (MHC) [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C165" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C165">165</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span> [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C166" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C166">166</a>]) and high somatic recombination observed in developing lymphocytes in jawed vertebrates [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C167" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C167">167</a>]. Studies testing this model normally consider parasite-induced changes in the host; however, it is possible that host-induced selection on the parasite can also drive a high recombination rate in parasites [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C168" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C168">168</a>]. We tested this hypothesis with our data by comparing the GwRR of parasitic or pathogenic species with free-living species. Using phylogenetic generalized linear models, we found that parasitic or pathogenic species had a higher recombination rate compared to their free-living counterparts in SAR and in animals, but there was no difference between parasitic or pathogenic and free-living species of fungi (electronic supplementary material, figure S5; plants were excluded as data were not available for any parasitic or pathogenic plant species). Interestingly, parasites often have smaller genomes compared to their free-living counterparts, which is consistent with high recombination driving genome contraction (discussed earlier in 
  <a ref-type="boxed-text" rid="RSTB20160455BX2" href="#RSTB20160455BX2">box 2</a>), although genome contraction may also be due to selection on small cell size and fast replication rates [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C55">55</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C169" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C169">169</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial and temporal variation in the abiotic environment can also favour higher recombination [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C153" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C153">153</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C163" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C163">163</a>], although there is little evidence testing this hypothesis in sexual species (studies more often compare between sexual and asexual populations). Temporal variation is often considered less likely to drive increases in recombination because the fluctuations in the abiotic environment are not fast or predictable enough (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C164" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C164">164</a>]). Data collected in the field investigating the effects of spatial variation in an abiotic environment on recombination often cannot rule out other confounding effects such as demography or biotic factors. For example, marginal populations of 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila robusta</span>, which can experience greater environmental fluctuations, have fewer inversion heterozygotes and thus higher recombination rates (see [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C5">5</a>]). In plants, higher Cf/B was found in annuals that are well suited to colonizing new variable habitats [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C74" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C74">74</a>]. However, in both cases higher recombination rate may be favoured because of the small 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>e</sub> of marginal or colonizing populations. More empirical work is needed to test this hypothesis, ideally comparing across natural populations while controlling for potential confounding effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretically, differential selection pressure on males and females can induce fluctuating selection on an allele as it cycles through the male and female genomes [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C164" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C164">164</a>]. Differential selection on male and female traits, such as mating rate or parental investment, creates intra-locus sexual conflict that could favour increased recombination [
  <a rid="RSTB20160455C164" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20160455C164">164</a>]. One prediction that can be drawn from this model is that hermaphrodites, which do not have separate sexes and thus have low levels of intra-locus sexual conflict, should have lower recombination rates compared to species with separate sexes. We tested this in our data looking at how sexual system (gonochorous, hermaphrodite, male-haploid and parthenogenic) was related to recombination rate (GwRR/HCN) across animals. We found that parthenogenic and male-haploid species had a higher recombination rate compared to species with separate sexes, but found no difference between separate sexes and hermaphrodites (see the electronic supplementary material). The dataset used here has a limited number of hermaphrodites (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 7) and it will be interesting to explore this question and other questions relating to the strength of sexual selection with more data.
 </p>
</sec>
