<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Red-backed Shrike Breeding Data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Breeding data were extracted from four sites across the Czech Republic (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s004" href="#pone.0043944.s004">Table S1</a>) from a combination of two datasets: (1) nestling ringing records stored at the Prague Bird Ringing Centre, and (2) field notes from bird ringers specialized at ringing shrikes 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek3">[49]</a>. We used data from those years for which we were able both to calculate estimates of nesting mortality (see below) and obtain hatching dates and brood sizes. Data were available for 15 years from site A (“Praha”) and B (“Masečín”), 42 years from site C (“Vítězná”), and 14 years from site D (“Vsetín”). At each site ringers searched for shrike nests regularly from middle May to early August, visiting the first active (i.e. after the first egg was laid) nest on average (±SD) on 29±11 May and making a final control of the last active nest on average on 23±11 July. The nests found were followed either until nest failure or ringing of the nestlings. Except one, each ringer was only active at one particular site per year. To avoid a possible bias introduced by unequal intra-annual searching effort, we excluded records from the sites from those years when the ringer was simultaneously working at more than one site. In order to obtain unbiased estimates of hatching dates of survived attempts we also only used data from years when the maximum length of the interval between successive nest visits at the respective study sites was less than 11 days (assuming a nestling period of 11 days as a minimum 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Cramp1">[50]</a>). We ended up with data from 48 years, and with a mean annual number of nests with ringed nestlings of 36 (9–127) per site (in total 1728 nests, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s005" href="#pone.0043944.s005">Table S2</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Red-backed Shrike Population Density</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimates of breeding density (number of breeding pairs per km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) for the respective study sites were available only for the period 1994–2006 from reports by red-backed shrike ringers and observers of the Czech Shrike Working Group 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Mikk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Mikk1">[51]</a>. The ln-transformed estimates were however strongly correlated with the respective ln-transformed numbers of ringed broods per km
   <span class="sup">2</span> from our data (r = 0.81, p&lt;0.001, n = 22). Therefore we used the ln-transformed number of ringed broods per km
   <span class="sup">2</span> available for all years as a proxy for annual conspecific density (“ln(density)” hereafter).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spring Progress and Climatic Data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rate of insect development and reproductive maturation during spring is critically determined by ambient temperatures 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Schwartz1">[52]</a>. Daily amount of accumulated heat when the temperature is above a given minimum threshold is often referred to as a “degree-day” (DD). Both insect and plant growth is strongly related to cumulated total of degree days during a period relevant for a given species 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Schwartz1">[52]</a>. We thus employed the cumulated total of DDs at a given date as a measure for general spring progress of the vegetation and of the shrikes’ insect prey 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Saino1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Saino1">[53]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prey composition of adult and nestling red-backed shrikes is similar and consists mainly of insects, with Orthophera (up to ca. 44% of prey biomass), Coleoptera (up to ca. 23%), and Hymenoptera (2.5–4%) being the most important food items 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Cramp1">[50]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Tryjanowski2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Tryjanowski2">[54]</a>. Minimum temperature threshold for development of most insects lies within a range of 4–11°C, with minimal values recorded for Coleoptera (based on 55 species), Orthopthera (4 species) and Hymenoptera (91 species) of 3.7°C, 4.0°C and 2.4°C, respectively 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Schwartz1">[52]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Nietschke1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Nietschke1">[55]</a>. Minimum temperature thresholds triggering bud growth, leaf unfolding and other tree phenophases lie somewhat lower than for insect development, within a range of 0–5°C 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Schwartz1">[52]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Chmielewski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Chmielewski1">[56]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following Schwartz 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Schwartz1">[52]</a>, cumulated total of degree days at hatching day (CDD
   <sub>HD</sub>) for each nest in each year and at each site was calculated as a sum of the differences in mean daily temperatures and minimal developmental threshold temperature of 0°C from the start of the calculation period (1 January) to hatching date. We considered minimum threshold temperatures of 0, 2, 4, 10°C in analysed models but only present the best fitting model with threshold of 0°C. In central Europe, 1 January is relevant as a starting date for tree and even some Hymenoptera prey development and it is also used when there is no clear phenological event to start calculation from 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Schwartz1">[52]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Chmielewski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Chmielewski1">[56]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Sparks1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Sparks1">[57]</a>. Mean daily temperatures at each study site were obtained from the respective closest meteorological stations (Praha-Libuš, ca. 7 km from site A; Neumětely, ca. 24 km from site B; Holovousy, ca. 19 km from site C; and Přerov, ca. 33 km from site D and Vsetín at site D). Mean May temperatures (T
   <sub>MAY</sub> hereafter), i.e. temperatures during the time when the onset of breeding takes place, were also obtained. All climatic data were provided by the Czech Hydrometeorological Institute and the Research and Breeding Institute of Pomology Holovousy Ltd.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We were interested in general biological patterns. Therefore, we analyzed the relationships between explanatory and response variables across all sites, i.e. using all combined data and considering site as a random effect. We employed linear mixed models (LMM hereafter) and generalized additive mixed models (GAMMs). Generalized additive model (GAM) is a generalized linear model where the linear predictor of explanatory variables of the form ∑ β
   <sub>j</sub>(X
   <sub>j</sub>) is replaced by a sum of smooth functions with estimated degrees of freedom (“edf” hereafter) of explanatory variables ∑ s
   <sub>j</sub>(X
   <sub>j</sub>) 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Wood1">[58]</a>. Basis of the smooth functions is represented by thin plate regression splines (or similar) and is estimated as a part of fitting process. GAMM is an extension of GAM including random effects. We preferred to employ GAMM to LMM for two reasons in some cases: 1) it allows flexible modelling of nonlinear relationships between the explanatory and response variable by means of smooth functions, 2) in a graphical representation it directly shows the effect size of a given explanatory variable (i.e. partial residuals of a response) with its 95% confidence interval. We used nlme library 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Pinheiro1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Pinheiro1">[59]</a> and mgcv library 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Wood1">[58]</a> in R 2.13.1 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-R1">[60]</a> to fit LMMs and GAMMs, respectively. We checked for normality of the response and explanatory variables and used ln-transformation when appropriate. Sample size was 48 site-specific annual values. We provide results of all respective analyses for particular sites employing linear regression in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s007" href="#pone.0043944.s007">Results S1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s006" href="#pone.0043944.s006">Table S3</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using data from the Czech nest record scheme, Hušek and Adamík 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek4">[61]</a> showed that shrike nestlings are ringed on average when 7–8 days old, which is just a few days before earliest possible fledging age of 11 days, and that the ringed numbers closely match the numbers of fledglings from survived nests. Hence, we used all available ringing dates corrected for variation in age at ringing as a proxy for hatching dates of survived attempts. The age of 7 days at ringing was assumed if the exact age was unknown (25% of ringed broods). The number of ringed nestlings was used as a proxy for productivity (brood size).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal distribution of reproductive output was characterized by standardized differentials for hatching dates (SD
   <sub>HD</sub>). Standardized differentials were calculated by subtracting annual average hatching dates from the annual average hatching dates weighted for the brood size, and dividing this difference by the standard deviation of the hatching dates (see 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Arnold1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Arnold1">[62]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Lande1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Lande1">[63]</a>). Standardized differentials measure direction and strength of the skewness of the distribution of the reproductive output relative to the distribution of hatching dates. Negative/positive SD
   <sub>HD</sub> indicates larger broods earlier/later in the season, respectively. The productivity of a particular nest presumably well reflects the annual productivity of a female and it does not seem to be seasonally confounded by female age or condition in this species 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Cramp1">[50]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Mller2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Mller2">[64]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate annual site-specific estimates of, and seasonal trends in, nesting mortality, we extracted data on nest inspections from the field notes of bird ringers at the respective sites (see “Nest monitoring data” in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s005" href="#pone.0043944.s005">Table S2</a>). We modelled nesting mortality in terms of daily mortality rate (“DMR” hereafter). A logistic-exposure method (an extension of logistic regression which allows for varying length of nest visit intervals 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Shaffer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Shaffer1">[65]</a>) implemented in the PROC GENMOD of SAS 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-SAS1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-SAS1">[66]</a> was employed for estimation of DMR. The fate of the interval between successive nest visits is a binary response variable. Only nests with at least two visits were therefore considered (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s005" href="#pone.0043944.s005">Table S2</a>). Also, only nest visit intervals ending before the earliest possible fledging date were analyzed to avoid uncertain nest fates. For each year and site, we either modelled seasonally constant (mean) DMR or linear seasonal trends in DMR (“trendDMR” hereafter). Seasonal trend was modelled by including date (i.e. average date of each nest visit interval) as a covariate. To correct for annual variation, dates were expressed as deviations (i.e. relative dates) from the annual median clutch initiation date of all established nests, and standardized to zero mean and unit variance (for details on the data and analysis see 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek3">[49]</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we analyzed inter-annual trends in variables. There was no need for formal time series modelling as there was no temporal autocorrelation in either first or mean hatching date (Durbin Watson test, all DW&gt;1.7, all p&gt;0.16), T
   <sub>MAY</sub> (all DW&gt;2.2, all p&gt;0.16), trendDMR (all DW&gt;1.8, all p&gt;0.23) at either site A, C, or D (site B was not tested because of short time series). There only was indication of autocorrelation in the mean CDD
   <sub>HD</sub> at site C (DW = 1.40, p = 0.027). Trends in DMR were analyzed elsewhere. Hušek et al. 
   <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek3">[49]</a> found general increase in DMR from early 1980ties at three out of four sites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, to test prediction #1, we fitted two LMMs on the relationship between mean hatching dates as response variable and T
   <sub>MAY</sub> and DMR as explanatory variables. Then, in following two LMMs, we included year as a continuous explanatory variable to test whether the effects of T
   <sub>MAY</sub> and DMR were confounded by the effect of inter-annual trend in mean hatching dates. Finally, we included T
   <sub>MAY,</sub> DMR and ln(density) in a single complete LMM, and corroborated the results by fitting GAMM. There were no strong correlations between the explanatory variables (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s008" href="#pone.0043944.s008">Results S2</a>). The results and conclusions were similar for both first and mean hatching date and so we only present results for the latter one.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last, to test prediction #2, we analyzed the relationship between the mean CDD
   <sub>HD</sub>, trendDMR and ln(density) as explanatory variables and standardized differentials for hatching dates (SD
   <sub>HD</sub>) as response variable in a single GAMM. The precision of estimates of DMR and trendDMR varied across years. When, however, the reciprocal variance of nesting mortality estimates was used as a weighting factor, the results did not change qualitatively and are therefore not presented.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
