<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Red-backed Shrike Breeding Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Breeding data were extracted from four sites across the Czech Republic (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s004" href="#pone.0043944.s004">Table S1</a>) from a combination of two datasets: (1) nestling ringing records stored at the Prague Bird Ringing Centre, and (2) field notes from bird ringers specialized at ringing shrikes 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek3">[49]</a>. We used data from those years for which we were able both to calculate estimates of nesting mortality (see below) and obtain hatching dates and brood sizes. Data were available for 15 years from site A (“Praha”) and B (“Masečín”), 42 years from site C (“Vítězná”), and 14 years from site D (“Vsetín”). At each site ringers searched for shrike nests regularly from middle May to early August, visiting the first active (i.e. after the first egg was laid) nest on average (±SD) on 29±11 May and making a final control of the last active nest on average on 23±11 July. The nests found were followed either until nest failure or ringing of the nestlings. Except one, each ringer was only active at one particular site per year. To avoid a possible bias introduced by unequal intra-annual searching effort, we excluded records from the sites from those years when the ringer was simultaneously working at more than one site. In order to obtain unbiased estimates of hatching dates of survived attempts we also only used data from years when the maximum length of the interval between successive nest visits at the respective study sites was less than 11 days (assuming a nestling period of 11 days as a minimum 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Cramp1">[50]</a>). We ended up with data from 48 years, and with a mean annual number of nests with ringed nestlings of 36 (9–127) per site (in total 1728 nests, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s005" href="#pone.0043944.s005">Table S2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
