<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We were interested in general biological patterns. Therefore, we analyzed the relationships between explanatory and response variables across all sites, i.e. using all combined data and considering site as a random effect. We employed linear mixed models (LMM hereafter) and generalized additive mixed models (GAMMs). Generalized additive model (GAM) is a generalized linear model where the linear predictor of explanatory variables of the form ∑ β
  <sub>j</sub>(X
  <sub>j</sub>) is replaced by a sum of smooth functions with estimated degrees of freedom (“edf” hereafter) of explanatory variables ∑ s
  <sub>j</sub>(X
  <sub>j</sub>) 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Wood1">[58]</a>. Basis of the smooth functions is represented by thin plate regression splines (or similar) and is estimated as a part of fitting process. GAMM is an extension of GAM including random effects. We preferred to employ GAMM to LMM for two reasons in some cases: 1) it allows flexible modelling of nonlinear relationships between the explanatory and response variable by means of smooth functions, 2) in a graphical representation it directly shows the effect size of a given explanatory variable (i.e. partial residuals of a response) with its 95% confidence interval. We used nlme library 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Pinheiro1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Pinheiro1">[59]</a> and mgcv library 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Wood1">[58]</a> in R 2.13.1 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-R1">[60]</a> to fit LMMs and GAMMs, respectively. We checked for normality of the response and explanatory variables and used ln-transformation when appropriate. Sample size was 48 site-specific annual values. We provide results of all respective analyses for particular sites employing linear regression in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s007" href="#pone.0043944.s007">Results S1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s006" href="#pone.0043944.s006">Table S3</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using data from the Czech nest record scheme, Hušek and Adamík 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek4">[61]</a> showed that shrike nestlings are ringed on average when 7–8 days old, which is just a few days before earliest possible fledging age of 11 days, and that the ringed numbers closely match the numbers of fledglings from survived nests. Hence, we used all available ringing dates corrected for variation in age at ringing as a proxy for hatching dates of survived attempts. The age of 7 days at ringing was assumed if the exact age was unknown (25% of ringed broods). The number of ringed nestlings was used as a proxy for productivity (brood size).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal distribution of reproductive output was characterized by standardized differentials for hatching dates (SD
  <sub>HD</sub>). Standardized differentials were calculated by subtracting annual average hatching dates from the annual average hatching dates weighted for the brood size, and dividing this difference by the standard deviation of the hatching dates (see 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Arnold1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Arnold1">[62]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Lande1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Lande1">[63]</a>). Standardized differentials measure direction and strength of the skewness of the distribution of the reproductive output relative to the distribution of hatching dates. Negative/positive SD
  <sub>HD</sub> indicates larger broods earlier/later in the season, respectively. The productivity of a particular nest presumably well reflects the annual productivity of a female and it does not seem to be seasonally confounded by female age or condition in this species 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Cramp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Cramp1">[50]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Mller2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Mller2">[64]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate annual site-specific estimates of, and seasonal trends in, nesting mortality, we extracted data on nest inspections from the field notes of bird ringers at the respective sites (see “Nest monitoring data” in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s005" href="#pone.0043944.s005">Table S2</a>). We modelled nesting mortality in terms of daily mortality rate (“DMR” hereafter). A logistic-exposure method (an extension of logistic regression which allows for varying length of nest visit intervals 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Shaffer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Shaffer1">[65]</a>) implemented in the PROC GENMOD of SAS 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-SAS1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-SAS1">[66]</a> was employed for estimation of DMR. The fate of the interval between successive nest visits is a binary response variable. Only nests with at least two visits were therefore considered (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s005" href="#pone.0043944.s005">Table S2</a>). Also, only nest visit intervals ending before the earliest possible fledging date were analyzed to avoid uncertain nest fates. For each year and site, we either modelled seasonally constant (mean) DMR or linear seasonal trends in DMR (“trendDMR” hereafter). Seasonal trend was modelled by including date (i.e. average date of each nest visit interval) as a covariate. To correct for annual variation, dates were expressed as deviations (i.e. relative dates) from the annual median clutch initiation date of all established nests, and standardized to zero mean and unit variance (for details on the data and analysis see 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek3">[49]</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we analyzed inter-annual trends in variables. There was no need for formal time series modelling as there was no temporal autocorrelation in either first or mean hatching date (Durbin Watson test, all DW&gt;1.7, all p&gt;0.16), T
  <sub>MAY</sub> (all DW&gt;2.2, all p&gt;0.16), trendDMR (all DW&gt;1.8, all p&gt;0.23) at either site A, C, or D (site B was not tested because of short time series). There only was indication of autocorrelation in the mean CDD
  <sub>HD</sub> at site C (DW = 1.40, p = 0.027). Trends in DMR were analyzed elsewhere. Hušek et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0043944-Huek3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0043944-Huek3">[49]</a> found general increase in DMR from early 1980ties at three out of four sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, to test prediction #1, we fitted two LMMs on the relationship between mean hatching dates as response variable and T
  <sub>MAY</sub> and DMR as explanatory variables. Then, in following two LMMs, we included year as a continuous explanatory variable to test whether the effects of T
  <sub>MAY</sub> and DMR were confounded by the effect of inter-annual trend in mean hatching dates. Finally, we included T
  <sub>MAY,</sub> DMR and ln(density) in a single complete LMM, and corroborated the results by fitting GAMM. There were no strong correlations between the explanatory variables (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0043944.s008" href="#pone.0043944.s008">Results S2</a>). The results and conclusions were similar for both first and mean hatching date and so we only present results for the latter one.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last, to test prediction #2, we analyzed the relationship between the mean CDD
  <sub>HD</sub>, trendDMR and ln(density) as explanatory variables and standardized differentials for hatching dates (SD
  <sub>HD</sub>) as response variable in a single GAMM. The precision of estimates of DMR and trendDMR varied across years. When, however, the reciprocal variance of nesting mortality estimates was used as a weighting factor, the results did not change qualitatively and are therefore not presented.
 </p>
</sec>
