<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35190-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparative biogeography</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used several quantitative approaches to compare our 
  <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> data to three previously known instances of avian genetic divergence and hybridization along the Florida peninsula/Gulf Coast region of the United States; those were 
  <span class="italic">Strix varia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Melanerpes carolinus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Poecile carolinensis</span>. We sequenced the complete ND2 gene for two specimens each of 
  <span class="italic">S. varia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span> to obtain estimates of genetic divergence along the Gulf Coast in these species. In both cases, we used individual specimens known to possess southeastern and western haplotypes based on prior studies of their phylogeography (e.g., Barrowclough et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0008">2011</a>; Gill, Slikas, &amp; Sheldon, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0026">2005</a>). The ND2 sequences of 
  <span class="italic">Melanerpes carolinus</span> had been reported previously (Barrowclough et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>). We computed the percent sequence divergence between the southeastern and north or western haplotypes for the 1,041 base pairs of the ND2 gene for 
  <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> and the three additional species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modeled the hybrid zones in 
  <span class="italic">S. varia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">M. carolinus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span> in a fashion similar to that described above for 
  <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span>. For 
  <span class="italic">S. varia</span>, we used the mitochondrial control region haplotype frequency data reported in Barrowclough et al. (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0008">2011</a>) to assign individuals sampled in populations along the Gulf Coast and in peninsula Florida to either southeastern or western haplotype clades. The resulting binary assignments were then projected onto the same transect used in the 
  <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> analysis and fit to a cumulative normal distribution. For 
  <span class="italic">M. carolinus</span>, we used complete ND2 sequences fit to that transect as described previously (Barrowclough et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>). For 
  <span class="italic">Poecile carolinensis</span>, we used the assignment of Gill et al. (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0025">1999</a>) of individuals to eastern and western clades of mitochondrial restriction fragments; those assignments were projected onto the Georgia to Texas portion of the 
  <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> transect (there were no 
  <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span> samples from peninsula Florida in the Gill et al. study) and fit to a cumulative normal. Thus, we obtained estimates of the centers and widths of four avian hybrid zones.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We searched the literature for reports of natal dispersal distances in 
  <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">S. varia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">M. carolinus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span>; we used those data to estimate a gene flow distance, the root‐mean‐square dispersal distance, relevant to the population genetics of clines and hybrid zones (e.g., May et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0037">1975</a>). Studies that provided estimates of individual dispersal distances or other statistics sufficient to allow the estimation of gene flow were used. Gene flow was estimated as the root‐mean‐square dispersal distance if the distribution of individual dispersal distances was provided (e.g., Endler, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0023">1977</a>; Rockwell &amp; Barrowclough, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0056">1987</a>). For cases in which mean dispersal distance plus the standard error of the mean were reported, we estimated gene flow as 
  <span class="italic">√N*SE</span>; this estimate follows from the definition of a standard error (
  <span class="italic">SE</span>). We scattered the estimates of gene flow, and of ND2 divergence, against estimates of hybrid zone width in order to determine whether those parameters might be correlated.
 </p>
</sec>
