<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35190-sec-0022" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparative avian phylogeography in the Southeastern United States</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four avian taxa have now been identified showing mtDNA divergence with hybridization on the Florida peninsula or along the Gulf Coast of the southern United States. This is a region identified as a suture zone, on the basis of external morphology of many organisms (Remington, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0054">1968</a>). Three of those four hybrid zones, all except that of the Carolina chickadee, are centered within the geographical limits of Remington's original description of the zone. A survey of molecular studies (Soltis et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0059">2006</a>) showed that a wide variety of organisms are genetically divergent in the same region. The four avian zones differ in degree of morphological and mtDNA divergence, position of the center, and width of the zone (Table 
  <a rid="ece35190-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" href="#ece35190-tbl-0003">3</a>, Figure 
  <a rid="ece35190-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0005">5</a>). However, these may not necessarily represent responses to differing ultimate causes; for example, three Pleistocene refugia in southern Europe have led to multiple patterns of range expansion and subsequent hybridization (Hewitt, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0027">1999</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of interest is whether these four avian zones represent patterns resulting from a single temporal biogeographic event. This would appear to be unlikely; the extent of mtDNA divergence, often thought to be a surrogate for time, differed by more than an order of magnitude among the species pairs. That suggests that some of the taxa, particularly 
  <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span>, may have differentiated through repeated isolation events over multiple glacial cycles; Soltis et al. (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0059">2006</a>) indicated that scenario might be a general phenomenon.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondly, the centers of the zones differ substantially in geographical position. The 
  <span class="italic">Poecile</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Strix</span> cases would appear to correspond to the Tombigbee and Apalachicola discontinuities of Soltis et al. (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0059">2006</a>). Barton (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0009">1979</a>) and Barton and Hewitt (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0010">1985</a>) pointed out that hybrid zones are attracted to physical barriers and density troughs such as those presented by wide rivers. The 
  <span class="italic">Melanerpes</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Buteo</span> zones centered on the Florida peninsula seem to be exemplars of the southern edge of the canonical Northern Florida Suture Zone. Remington (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0054">1968</a>) suggested the zone represented the position of initial contact for many previously allopatric species pairs. In an important synthesis of phylogeographic patterns found in turtles of this same region, Walker and Avise (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0063">1998</a>) discovered exemplars of each of the geographic patterns we observed in the four birds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the widths of the four hybrid zones vary by a factor in excess of six. The widths of neutral hybrid zones are expected to scale with dispersal (gene flow) distance and the square root of time since secondary contact (Endler, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0023">1977</a>). The latter is likely similar for these species. However, dispersal distances vary greatly among the species pairs, and the hybrid zone widths scatter reasonably well with those estimates (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35190-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0006">6</a>). For hybrid zones maintained by a balance between dispersal and selection, the widths should scale with the inverse square root of selection intensity (Barton &amp; Hewitt, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0010">1985</a>). In these four cases, widths scale poorly with phenotypic differences (e.g., sexual selection) and only weakly with genetic divergence (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35190-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0006">6</a>, Table 
  <a rid="ece35190-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" href="#ece35190-tbl-0003">3</a>), possible correlates of general selective divergence. Thus, it appears that these avian zones have been in isolation for varying numbers of glacial cycles and that their current positions and widths reflect their idiosyncratic dispersal propensities. Further insight will require denser geographical sampling, extensive nuclear sequencing, and examination of additional species pairs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, these four avian cases, along with numerous examples from plants and other animals (Soltis et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0059">2006</a>), suggest there may be additional, cryptic divergence waiting to be discovered in the avifauna of the Southeastern United States. Interestingly, Remington (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0054">1968</a>) and later Newton (
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0044">2003</a>), suggested six species of birds as candidates for differentiation in the Northern Florida Suture Zone. Three of those (northern bobwhite, wild turkey, and Bachman's sparrow) have now been surveyed using phylogeographic methods, and none were found to possess significant mitochondrial differentiation. Thus, it appears that predicting which avian taxa might be involved is not transparent. Nevertheless, species that are permanent residents or only partially migratory would seem to be particularly appropriate candidates for further investigation.
 </p>
</sec>
