<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35190-sec-0018" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eastern North America‐Pacific Coast divergence</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found major genetic divergence between the California samples of red‐shouldered hawks and those from the eastern portion of the range, consistent with species‐level taxa in a Bayesian coalescent analysis. At the ND2 locus, there was no sharing of haplotypes (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35190-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0001">1</a>) and our estimate of 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>st</sub>, 0.65, indicates that two‐thirds of the genetic variance was distributed between the regions. For the two introns, the divergence was less, but there were salient differences in allelic frequencies between the regions and this was statistically significant for one of them (Table 
  <a rid="ece35190-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#ece35190-tbl-0002">2</a>; Figure 
  <a rid="ece35190-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0002">2</a>), consistent with differences expected between mitochondrial and nuclear divergence based on differences in their respective coalescent times (e.g., Zink &amp; Barrowclough, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0072">2008</a>). For ND2, there was approximately an order of magnitude less nucleotide diversity in the California populations than in the eastern ones; there was also more variation in the east for both G3PDH and TGFB2. Those results are consistent with the major difference in range sizes of the two populations, presumably reflective of substantial differences in 
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> and, as a consequence, genetic variation. The patterns are also consistent with no recent gene flow between the two portions of the range. At present, they are completely allopatric and the ENM results suggest they may have been so during recent glacial cycles (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35190-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0003">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genetic divergence between these eastern and western North America populations is not surprising; a previous microsatellite investigation had uncovered similar results (Hull et al., 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0031">2008</a>) and the birds show phenotypic differences in plumage (Wheeler, 
  <a rid="ece35190-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0065">2018b</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
