<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="ece35190-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">METHODS</div>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We attempted to obtain tissue samples of 
   <span class="italic">Buteo lineatus</span> from throughout its known breeding range (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35190-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0001">1</a>); all samples came from specimens cataloged in natural history museums, but many originally came from raptor rehabilitation centers (see Acknowledgments). We tried to obtain approximately ten unrelated individuals from within a relatively confined geographical region (up to several adjacent counties) to represent local populations. Along the Gulf Coast of the United States and in peninsula Florida, we used geographically denser sampling to investigate finer‐scale spatial variation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laboratory</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We amplified and sequenced both mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences from the tissue samples. The laboratory work generally employed methods previously described (e.g., Barrowclough, Groth, Odom, &amp; Lai, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0008">2011</a>; Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>). We extracted total DNA from tissue samples using standard protocols; we used taq‐DNA polymerase and PCR methods to amplify the complete mitochondrial ND2 gene plus small fragments of the two flanking tRNAs using standard ND2 primers; the resulting products were isolated on agarose gels and reamplified as two overlapping fragments using internal primers. The fragments were sequenced in both directions using Sanger techniques, end‐labeled with fluorescent dye, and separated on an ABI 3730xl DNA analyzer.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using similar techniques, we also sequenced two introns suggested to be useful for studies of avian phylogeography (Primmer, Borge, Lindell, &amp; Saetre, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0051">2002</a>). These were intron 11 of the G3PDH gene (chromosome 1 in 
   <span class="italic">Gallus</span>) and intron 5 of the TGFB2 gene (chromosome 3 in 
   <span class="italic">Gallus</span>). Both of these loci were amplified and sequenced as single fragments using primers located in the two flanking exons. We designed novel primers for the G3PDH intron: G3P11Fb (5'‐TTCCAGGTTGTCTCTYGTGACTTCA‐3') and G3P12Ra: (5'‐CTTGGATGCCATGTGGACC‐3'). The primers used to amplify TGFB2 were previously described (Primmer et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0051">2002</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The G3PDH and TGFB2 introns are autosomal and therefore diploid in birds; consequently, we encountered many individuals having ambiguous sites due to heterozygous alleles. We phased these alternate alleles in individuals having two or more ambiguities by sequencing the product of allele‐specific PCR amplification. Primers were designed to amplify one of the two alternate alleles in an individual by matching only one of these at the 3' end of the primer for one of the two (i.e., 5'‐most or 3'‐most) most distal ambiguities; in addition, the penultimate 3' base of the phasing primer was purposely mismatched to both alleles so that the sequence of the allele‐specific primer mismatched one allele at two 3' bases, including the final one, whereas the other allele was mismatched only at a single, penultimate base. After one allele was determined by sequencing, the alternate allele was reconstructed by subtracting the sequenced allele from the original, heterozygous sequence.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sequence analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assembled and edited sequences using SEQUENCHER software (Gene Codes). Mitochondrial sequences were trimmed of primer and flanking genes to provide complete ND2 sequences; the sequences were aligned by eye. We checked the sequences for quality by searching for indels, unexpected stop codons, heterogeneous base composition, and ambiguous sites.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the purposes of estimating several population genetic parameters, individuals were assigned to one of 14 population samples (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35190-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35190-fig-0001">1</a>). Standard genetic statistics were estimated for these populations using procedures previously described (e.g., Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0008">2011</a>; Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>); these included Nei's (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0043">1987</a>) nucleotide diversity and Tajima's (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0061">1989a</a>, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0062">1989b</a>) 
   <span class="italic">D</span> statistic. We used Excoffier, Laval, and Schneider's (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0024">2005</a>) ARLEQUIN program to estimate various hierarchical genetic variance (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>st</sub>) components (Wright, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0067">1969</a>). We used two ND2 sequences deposited in GenBank (
   <span class="italic">B. jamaicensis</span>: 
   <span ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AY987156" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AY987156</span>; 
   <span class="italic">B. ridgwayi</span>: 
   <span ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="GQ264886" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GQ264886</span>) as outgroups and used PAUP* version 4.0b10 (Swofford, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0060">2001</a>) to infer gene trees and a minimum length network for the unique haplotypes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The diploid G3PDH and TGFB2 sequences were also trimmed of primer and flanking exon sequence and aligned by eye. Individuals possessing two different alleles were phased, if necessary, as described above. The two alleles for each individual were assigned to the same 14 population samples used for the ND2 sequences and the same statistics computed. Possible recombination events were identified using a four‐gamete test, and sequences were trimmed to the largest sequence fragment consistent with no recombination. PAUP* was used to infer gene trees and minimum length networks for the unique alleles at each locus; in these analyses, we used the 
   <span class="italic">B. jamaicensis</span> sequences as outgroups.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hybrid zone analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modeled the ND2 differentiation of 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> populations in the southeastern portion of its range using a binary hybrid zone analysis. For a geographic axis, we designated a theoretical transect as a straight line from Key Largo, Florida north‐northwest to Lakeland, Georgia and then west along the 31° line of latitude through Texas. Each specimen of 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> from Florida, Louisiana, and Texas was identified as possessing either a “Florida peninsula” or a “common” ND2 haplotype. We then projected each of the assigned haplotypes perpendicularly from its approximate original geographical position onto that transect. In this way, we obtained an ND2 haplotype frequency by distance survey through the southeastern portion of the hawk's range (e.g., Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crank (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0017">1975</a>) showed that transient neutral diffusion is expected to result in a modified cumulative normal distribution that scales with the square root of the product of the diffusion coefficient (gene flow) and time since primary contact (e.g., Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>). In practice, hybrid zones and other clines are generally characterized by their maximum slope (May, Endler, &amp; McMurtrie, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0037">1975</a>) or their 20%‐80% width (Endler, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0023">1977</a>). We fit the distribution of ND2 haplotypes along our designated transect to a cumulative normal distribution using the logistic regression procedure in SAS (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0057">1990</a>). The form of the fit was 
   <span class="italic">F</span>(
   <span class="italic">X</span>)
   <span class="italic"> = </span>Φ(
   <span class="italic">mX + b</span>) where Φ is the cumulative normal distribution, 
   <span class="italic">X</span> is the distance along the transect, and 
   <span class="italic">m</span> and 
   <span class="italic">b</span> are the maximum likelihood estimated parameters (slope and intercept). The center of the hybrid zone was estimated as 
   <span class="italic">b/m</span>, the maximum slope as 
   <span class="italic">m</span>/√(2π), and the 20%‐80% width as 
   <span class="italic">1.68/m</span>; those estimates come directly from the definition of a normal distribution.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coalescent species status analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We attempted to ascertain whether gene trees derived from our mitochondrial and nuclear loci might be consistent with more than a single species of red‐shouldered hawk under a coalescent process accounting for gene tree uncertainty, incomplete lineage sorting due to ancestral polymorphism, but no gene flow among populations (Yang &amp; Rannala, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0069">2010</a>). We used the Bayesian Phylogenetics and Phylogeography Program (BPP version 3.3: Yang, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0068">2015</a>) to obtain joint Bayesian estimates of species delimitation and species trees by treating the ND2 and two nuclear genes as freely recombining among, but with no recombination within, loci. We assigned ND2 one‐quarter the effective population size of the nuclear loci. We treated sequences from California and those from the eastern United States as a priori candidate species, with 
   <span class="italic">B. jamaicensis</span> sequences as a possible basal taxon.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the A01 MCMC algorithm (species delimitation with user‐defined guide tree) with adaptive adjustment during burn‐in of both priors and step length search parameters. Because the ages of the possible divergences (τ) and the ancestral effective population sizes (θ = 4μ
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span>) of these birds are poorly known, we used three sets of initial conditions for the runs. These were the following: large 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span> and old divergence (θ and τ gamma‐distributed priors of 
   <span class="italic">G</span>(1,10) and 
   <span class="italic">G</span>(1,10), respectively), small 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span> and recent divergence (priors of 
   <span class="italic">G</span>(2, 2000) and 
   <span class="italic">G</span>(2, 2000), respectively), and large 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span> and recent divergence (priors of 
   <span class="italic">G</span>(1, 10) and 
   <span class="italic">G</span>(2, 2000), respectively). Runs with each set of priors were repeated twice, with different initial seeds; the MCMC chains included 200,000 steps of burn‐in with adaptive parameter estimation and adjustment, followed by estimation chains 200,000 steps in length sampled every 20 steps (10,000 estimation points).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological niche modeling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We attempted to estimate the approximate Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) distribution of 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> using ecological niche modeling (ENM: Peterson et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0047">2011</a>); an approach that has been shown to be useful for interpreting phylogeographic patterns (Alvarado‐Serrano &amp; Knowles, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0001">2014</a>). We created a file of latitudes and longitudes for 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> using AMNH specimens, geo‐referenced museum specimens compiled in the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF.org) and documented breeding attempts in various state breeding bird atlases. We removed vagrants from the GBIF list by checking for specimens collected in United States and Mexican states and in Canadian provinces in which the hawk has not been documented to breed. Because 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> is largely nonmigratory and its known migration does not extend south of its breeding range (Crocoll, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0018">1994</a>), this file represents a reasonable assessment of the species' breeding distribution.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We constructed ENMs using the WorldClim database for current climate (Hijmans, Cameron, Parra, Jones, &amp; Jarvis, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0029">2005</a>) and the Paleoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project Phase II database for the LGM (Braconnot et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0013">2007</a>). Based on the pattern of correlations among climatic variables, we reduced 19 commonly used bioclimatic factors to seven variables not highly correlated in the North American breeding range of 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span>. Two of these represented temperature extremes (minimum temperature of the coldest month of the year; mean temperature of the warmest quarter); three represented seasonality of precipitation (precipitation seasonality; precipitation of warmest quarter; precipitation of wettest quarter); one represented drought incidence (precipitation of driest quarter); and one representing frost, ice, and snow conditions (precipitation of coldest quarter). These variables had correlations ranging from 0.14 to 0.86 (median 0.49), and the correlation patterns were similar in the current climate and LGM databases. By using only (abiotic) climate variables in our analysis, our ENMs represent projections of areas with suitable climate for 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> rather than its true range, which would also require biotic factors, such as competition with other predators. Nevertheless, our climatic ENMs do allow us to make broad comparisons about changes in suitable regions for 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> between current conditions and those at the LGM.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We built ENMs using MAXENT version 3.3.3e (Phillips, Anderson, &amp; Schapire, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0048">2006</a>); MAXENT estimates the unknown probability density for a species' actual range by minimizing the relative entropy between the species' observed range and environmental conditions across the study area (Elith et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0021">2006</a>). We selected the regularization parameter for the MAXENT model by testing a range of values from one to four and determining which model resulted in the highest area under the curve (AUC) of the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) plot, calculated with one‐fourth of occurrence data set aside as test data (Radosavljevic &amp; Anderson, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0053">2014</a>). We chose a regularization parameter of two. Other model parameterizations followed generic recommendations by the model developers (Phillips et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0048">2006</a>; Phillips &amp; Dudik, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0049">2008</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the predictive capabilities of the model using a fourfold partitioning (Peterson et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0047">2011</a>). For each partitioning, we calculated the AUC. We also calculated the omission rate by generating binary predictions using a maximum training sensitivity plus specificity threshold and used a binomial test to assess whether the observed omission rate was better than expected compared with a random prediction (Anderson, Gómez‐Laverde, &amp; Peterson, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0002">2002</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35190-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparative biogeography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used several quantitative approaches to compare our 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> data to three previously known instances of avian genetic divergence and hybridization along the Florida peninsula/Gulf Coast region of the United States; those were 
   <span class="italic">Strix varia</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Melanerpes carolinus</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">Poecile carolinensis</span>. We sequenced the complete ND2 gene for two specimens each of 
   <span class="italic">S. varia</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span> to obtain estimates of genetic divergence along the Gulf Coast in these species. In both cases, we used individual specimens known to possess southeastern and western haplotypes based on prior studies of their phylogeography (e.g., Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0008">2011</a>; Gill, Slikas, &amp; Sheldon, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0026">2005</a>). The ND2 sequences of 
   <span class="italic">Melanerpes carolinus</span> had been reported previously (Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>). We computed the percent sequence divergence between the southeastern and north or western haplotypes for the 1,041 base pairs of the ND2 gene for 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> and the three additional species.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modeled the hybrid zones in 
   <span class="italic">S. varia</span>, 
   <span class="italic">M. carolinus</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span> in a fashion similar to that described above for 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span>. For 
   <span class="italic">S. varia</span>, we used the mitochondrial control region haplotype frequency data reported in Barrowclough et al. (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0008">2011</a>) to assign individuals sampled in populations along the Gulf Coast and in peninsula Florida to either southeastern or western haplotype clades. The resulting binary assignments were then projected onto the same transect used in the 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> analysis and fit to a cumulative normal distribution. For 
   <span class="italic">M. carolinus</span>, we used complete ND2 sequences fit to that transect as described previously (Barrowclough et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0007">2018</a>). For 
   <span class="italic">Poecile carolinensis</span>, we used the assignment of Gill et al. (
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0025">1999</a>) of individuals to eastern and western clades of mitochondrial restriction fragments; those assignments were projected onto the Georgia to Texas portion of the 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span> transect (there were no 
   <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span> samples from peninsula Florida in the Gill et al. study) and fit to a cumulative normal. Thus, we obtained estimates of the centers and widths of four avian hybrid zones.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We searched the literature for reports of natal dispersal distances in 
   <span class="italic">B. lineatus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. varia</span>, 
   <span class="italic">M. carolinus</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">P. carolinensis</span>; we used those data to estimate a gene flow distance, the root‐mean‐square dispersal distance, relevant to the population genetics of clines and hybrid zones (e.g., May et al., 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0037">1975</a>). Studies that provided estimates of individual dispersal distances or other statistics sufficient to allow the estimation of gene flow were used. Gene flow was estimated as the root‐mean‐square dispersal distance if the distribution of individual dispersal distances was provided (e.g., Endler, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0023">1977</a>; Rockwell &amp; Barrowclough, 
   <a rid="ece35190-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35190-bib-0056">1987</a>). For cases in which mean dispersal distance plus the standard error of the mean were reported, we estimated gene flow as 
   <span class="italic">√N*SE</span>; this estimate follows from the definition of a standard error (
   <span class="italic">SE</span>). We scattered the estimates of gene flow, and of ND2 divergence, against estimates of hybrid zone width in order to determine whether those parameters might be correlated.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
