<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37" class="p">The statistical models showed that occurrences of 
 <italic class="italic">An. atroparvus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">An. labranchiae</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">An. messeae</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">An. sacharovi</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">An. sergentii</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">An. superpictus</italic> are highly related to climate. This confirms the high climate sensitivity of 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> vectors as already identified in previous studies, e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. In this regard, temperature in the transitional seasons as well as rainfall during summer are of particular importance. The results point to the impact of climate on specific parts of the vectors life-cycle - temperature mainly influences the active and hibernation periods of adult mosquitoes, whereas rainfall is particularly important for the aquatic life stages. Precipitation was mostly positively connected with 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> occurrences. However, very high monthly precipitation amounts can also have a reverse impact on occurrences. 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles messeae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">An. sergentii</italic> prefer freshwater sites with very slow flowing or stagnant water [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>], so that a prevention of breeding sites by high rainfall amounts can occur. 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles sacharovi</italic> is described as a highly adaptive species, developing in all kinds of brackish as well as fresh water habitats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. However, the species is sensible to organic pollutants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Thus, it can be speculated that intense rainfall events may import pollutants into its habitat yielding a reduced species occurrence.
</p>
