<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Migration is a complex phenomenon. Black et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2011</xref>) suggest a non-regional framework for understanding how the environment, acting together with economic, political, social, and demographic drivers, affects migration. Direct environmental pressures include impacts on ecosystem services, which in the Alaska case support subsistence food harvesting and inter-community travel, along with settlement infrastructure including homes, schools, water, and power supplies. Moreover, environmental change can raise what Black et al. term “the hazardousness of place,” a description that well suits Alaska communities with growing flood risks to infrastructure and people. Black et al. emphasize the role of human agency in migration decisions, a role that underlies our use of net migration as an indicator. But this indicator shows no visible response to environmental stress to date, which serves to emphasize that human agency can work against migration as well as for it. Pressures to move are countered by reasons people might not want to leave their ancestral homes, or lack appealing alternatives (Adams 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2015</xref>; Marino 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2015</xref>). La Ganga (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">2015</xref>) quotes a longtime Kivalina resident:
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p class="p">When… asked why her people don’t move—somewhere, anywhere to be safe—she is polite but firm. The land and the water make the Inupiat who they are. If they moved to Kotzebue, they would be visitors. Moving to Anchorage or Fairbanks, she said, “would be like asking us not to be a people any more.”</p>
 </disp-quote>Instead of their populations declining through out-migration, many of the threatened places are growing—raising both the potential costs of relocation and the number of people exposed to risks. Meanwhile, the physical threats are not diminished. Permafrost thaws, rivers rise, and shorelines erode; on decadal timescales, sea level could be an increasing factor as well. State or federal action sufficient to relocate these communities does not yet appear imminent.
</p>
