<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">In climate change impact studies, the envelope of multiple GCM × RCP realizations includes the uncertainty accumulated throughout the process of climate generation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. At the end of the process, fine-scale climate data to feed impact models are developed from a variety of coarse scale GCMs and in dependence on alternative emission and socio-economic pathways. Uncertainties in model parameters, and imbalances in model equations, may propagate through the climate modelling chain, and these uncertainties may be enhanced or compensated during downscaling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> and then translated into impact estimates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Studies analysing climate change have mostly emphasized the sources of uncertainty associated with adopting alternative GCM × RCP configurations in an ensemble of climate scenarios, but without fully considering the amount of uncertainty associated with using WG-based downscaling. Our results not only indicate that the impact of stochastic generation on precipitation and air temperature patterns within statistical downscaling methods can be substantial, but that the projected results may even be reversed, that is, the most favourable scenario obtained with a WG may become the worst with an alternative WG (and 
 <italic>vice versa</italic>). This means that generated weather series may differ more due to the chosen stochastic generator rather than to the envelope of assumptions. Projection uncertainties handled by comparing different GCMs and RCPs could therefore be superseded by the uncertainties due to the WGs employed for the downscaling of climate variables. In our study, the array of climate indices and the rice yield analysis performed indicate an effect depending more on the WGs than on other factors (followed by the site dependant effect). While the effect of applying generated weather series in different areas, and for different crops and objectives is still to be assessed, further simulation experiments will verify if some biological resilience attenuate the impacts of stochastic weather generation on (simulated) biophysical processes.
</p>
