<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">With such systemic complexity, modelling can be a valuable inductive and deductive tool for exploring adaptation strategies (Kelly et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2013</xref>). However, models that incorporate poorly grounded or weakly specified representations of adaptation may be more misleading than informative (Schneider et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2000</xref>; Irwin and Geoghegan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2001</xref>; Polhill et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2005</xref>). At the same time, model focus on the adaptive process should not obscure its dependencies on the particular impacts and responses involved. Hence, the representation of climate change adaptation (hereafter referred to as adaptation) within models requires careful consideration. Although adaptation is recognised as important in most climate change impact, adaptation and vulnerability (CCIAV) modelling studies, the climate-centric nature of many of the models used often precludes more integrated perspectives on decision-making and institutional processes (de Bremond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2014</xref>). As a result, recent reviews (Brown et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">2017</xref>; Olmstead 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">2014</xref>; Holman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2012</xref>; Fisher-Vanden et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2011</xref>; Patt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2010</xref>; Füssel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2010</xref>; Dickinson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2007</xref>) have found general weaknesses in the representation of adaptation in both sectoral and integrated assessment models, implying serious shortcomings in our ability to use models to develop robust adaptation strategies.
</p>
