<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1dot5-ijerph-16-01792" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.5. Cross-Links between Processes and Consequences</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The organisational climate can affect employees’ well-being, directly influencing burnout. Under this hypothesis, Winnubst [
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-01792">38</a>] carried out a pioneering study and concluded that organisational climate is an important antecedent of burnout. Recent studies have shown that formal support groups create organisational climates that decrease stressors such as burnout [
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-01792">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also, the study of the relationship between role stress and job satisfaction is of major importance. Recently, several studies have presented evidence of this relationship in different country, industry, and labour contexts [
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-01792">40</a>,
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-16-01792">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The JD-R model also provides a relationship between the consequences of job demands and those of job resources. A recent longitudinal study by Figueiredo-Ferraz et al. [
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-16-01792">42</a>], who focused on analysing the relationship between burnout and job satisfaction, found a significant two-way relationship between these variables.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other findings explained that—relative to private sector employees—public servants became the most engaged by intrinsic factors including work-related resources [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-01792">43</a>]. Work engagement significantly mediated the relationship between job resources and personal resources of public employees. Public sector workers were more strongly motivated by the desire to work in a supportive working environment. Most observed differences were explained by differences in job content such as skill variety, feedback, or task identity, not by the sector itself [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-01792">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study is to analyse the relationship between organisational climate, role stress, burnout, and job satisfaction in public employees. For this purpose, our hypotheses are consistent with previous studies:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Organisational climate will show a significant and negative reciprocal relationship with role stress (hypothesis 1) and a positive reciprocal relationship with job satisfaction (hypothesis 2). Also, role stress will show a significant and positive reciprocal relationship with burnout (hypothesis 3). Furthermore, organisational climate will show a significant and negative reciprocal relationship with burnout (hypothesis 4) and role stress will show a significant and negative reciprocal relationship with job satisfaction (hypothesis 5). Finally, job satisfaction will have a reciprocal relationship, both significant and negative, with burnout (hypothesis 6).</p>
</sec>
