<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot3-ijerph-16-01792" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Statistical Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to verify the reliability of the dimensions, the internal consistency was assessed using Cronbach’s alpha coefficient [
  <a rid="B50-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-16-01792">50</a>] for each variable and dimension. For each of the four variables under study, a structural equation model was fitted to confirm the dimensions. Finally, to check the relations between the different variables, a structural equation model was developed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Structural equation models were fitted using the diagonalised weighted least squares (DWLS) [
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-16-01792">51</a>] or robust maximum likelihood (RML) method [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-16-01792">52</a>], depending on the construct to be analysed, since the multivariate normality of the data was not met for any of the dimensions or variables. The univariate normality was checked for each item and skewness and kurtosis measures were obtained. To test the multivariate normality, the Henze-Zirkler test [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-16-01792">53</a>] was used.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DWLS method requires large data sets; specifically, the sample size should be larger than 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; (
  <span class="italic">p</span> + 1)/2, where p is the number of parameters to be estimated by the structural equation. Therefore, dimensions where the number of items considered in the model was too low could not be fitted using this method. Thus, the method used for those dimensions was RML. Those dimensions were from two variables: Climate and job satisfaction [
  <a rid="B54-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-16-01792">54</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The goodness of fit for the proposed models was measured using the Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI) and the Comparative Fit Index (CFI). For both, values greater than 0.9 indicate a good fit. Another measure used was the Root Mean Square Error of Approximation, (RMSEA) where values lower than 0.08 indicate a good model fit and the upper limit of the 90% confidence interval should be below the 0.1 cut-off value for a good model fit [
  <a rid="B55-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijerph-16-01792">55</a>]. The Standardized Root Mean Square Residual (SRMR) is an absolute measure of fit defined as the normalisation of the difference between the observed and predicted correlations. An SRMR value of less than 0.08 is considered as an adequate cut-off point for the goodness of fit [
  <a rid="B56-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-16-01792">56</a>]. The models were implemented using R software (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) and the Lavaan package [
  <a rid="B57-ijerph-16-01792" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-16-01792">57</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
