<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Citrus belong to the Rutaceae family, Aurantioideae subfamily. Most of the cultivated citrus species are part of the 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> genus (
 <xref rid="B243" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka, 1961</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B240" ref-type="bibr">Swingle and Reece, 1967</xref>). Molecular studies (
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr">Nicolosi et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Barkley et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Lor et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Curk et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and recent genomic studies (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Curk et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B202" ref-type="bibr">Oueslati et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B273" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2018</xref>) provided a clear understanding of the evolution of cultivated 
 <italic>Citrus</italic>, revealing the existence of four ancestral taxa: [
 <italic>Citrus maxima</italic> (Burm.) Merr. – the pummelos, 
 <italic>Citrus medica</italic> L. – the citrons, 
 <italic>Citrus reticulata</italic> Blanco – the mandarins and 
 <italic>Citrus micrantha</italic> Wester a wild papeda species]. The other cultivated species [
 <italic>Citrus aurantium</italic> L. – sour orange, 
 <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> (L.) Osbeck – sweet orange, 
 <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> Macf. – grapefruit, 
 <italic>Citrus limon</italic> (L.) Burm. F. – lemon and 
 <italic>Citrus aurantifolia</italic> (Christm.) Swingle – lime] resulted from recombination among ancestral taxa. Several genera (
 <italic>Poncirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Fortunella</italic>, 
 <italic>Eremocitrus</italic>, 
 <italic>Microcitrus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Clymenia</italic>) are sexually compatible with 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> species and constitute the true citrus group (
 <xref rid="B240" ref-type="bibr">Swingle and Reece, 1967</xref>). They have interest as parentals for rootstock breeding due to their tolerance traits to several abiotic stresses and diseases. Citrus species were domesticated in Southeast Asia several thousand years ago. The first species known in the Mediterranean was Citron, probably introduced by Alexander the Great to Persia and Greece from India. Old mosaics show that the Romans may have known lemon fruits around 100 years BC. Citrus were then spread throughout Europe and North Africa during the expansion of the Arabic empire. Citron, sour orange, lemon, lime, and pummelo are described in tenth and eleventh century books from Spain. Modern types of sweet oranges were introduced in Europe by the Portuguese in the early sixteenth century. The introduction of mandarins is more recent (early nineteenth century). The Mediterranean Basin is considered a secondary area of Citrus diversification, particularly important for sweet oranges and lemons (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Aubert, 2001</xref>).
</p>
