<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6597063</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-18-33538</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical Locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Asia</subject><subj-group><subject>Iran</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Atmospheric Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Climatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Climate Change</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Crop Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Crops</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Soil Science</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and Environmental Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Soil Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Soil Science</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Seasons</subject><subj-group><subject>Winter</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Atmospheric Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Meteorology</subject><subj-group><subject>Humidity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Computer and Information Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geoinformatics</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographic Information Systems</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Geoinformatics</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographic Information Systems</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Applying the AOGCM-AR5 models to the assessments of land suitability for walnut cultivation in response to climate change: A case study of Iran</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Land suitability assessment for walnut cultivation in response to climate change</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8458-8697</contrib-id><name><surname>Vahdati</surname><given-names>Kourosh</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Massah Bavani</surname><given-names>Ali Reza</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Khosh-Khui</surname><given-names>Morteza</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Project administration</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fakour</surname><given-names>Poya</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sarikhani</surname><given-names>Saadat</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001"><sup>&#x02021;</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Horticulture, College of Aburaihan, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Irrigation and Drainage, College of Aburaihan, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Horticultural Science, College of Agriculture, Shiraz University, Shiraz, Iran</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Chemura</surname><given-names>Abel</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research, GERMANY</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001"><p>&#x02021; These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>kvahdati@ut.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0218725</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 Vahdati et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Vahdati et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0218725.pdf"/><abstract><p>Due to higher temperatures and lower water availability, climate change is likely to have a major impact on walnut production in the near future. Climate change will alter the land suitability for walnut cultivation around the world, especially in arid and semi-arid regions like Iran. Here, land suitability for the cultivation of walnut (<italic>Juglans regia</italic> L.) in Iran was determined using the GIS for present and future conditions (2020&#x02013;2049) with an approach to climate change. Accordingly, data from 375 synoptic stations throughout Iran were gathered for climatic factors including average, minimum and maximum temperatures, relative humidity and chilling requirement. Also, ASTER sensors (Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Reflection Radiometer) and their data provided this research with cells that make a precision of 150 m (5 s), and the data were used for gauging geological parameters such as altitude and land slope. The electrical conductivity (EC) of soil and water were informed by the data bank of the Iranian Water Resources Management. The results of temperature simulations for the future (2020&#x02013;2049) were analyzed by 21 AOGCM-AR5 models under the RCP4.5 emission scenario. In the first phase of evaluations, the maps of land suitability were constructed for present conditions by considering a network of the above-mentioned parameters. By combining these layers of information, the final map of land suitability was illustrated for walnut cultivation. In the second phase, the NEX-GDDP was used in order to determine land suitability for the future (2020&#x02013;2049). The results showed that Iran currently has 582844 km<sup>2</sup> of land suitable for walnut cultivation. However, the future will see less suitable lands: the current area will be reduced by 6.19%, from 582844 km<sup>2</sup> to 546710 km<sup>2</sup>. In general, the northern, northwestern and western margins of Iran are currently suitable for walnut cultivation. By approximation, these lands will also be major areas for prospective cultivations of walnut in the future (2020&#x02013;2049), even though their current stretch will be reduced.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data is within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data is within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Iran is a vast country in the Middle East. It has a variety of climates because of its two mountain ranges (Alborz and Zagros). The country is further endowed with long coastlines in its south and north [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Also, several other mountains in Baluchestan, Khorasan and the central parts of Iran provide a variety of microclimates [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Although the main climate of Iran is extremely dry and semi-arid, its north is characterized by a wet climate. The west of Iran is also considered as relatively wet. Apart from the south of the Caspian Sea, where the annual preciption is almost high and evenly distributed throughout the year, most parts of Iran have moderate to low rainfall which occur mostly from October through April [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Agricultural land suitability in Iran is very limited due to multiple limiting factors including high sodium contents in the soil, high EC of the soil and water, low precipitation, low amounts of organic carbon in the soil and steep slopes. In other words, a large part of Iran&#x02019;s land (around 78.2%) is regarded as unsuitable or poorly suitable areas [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Despite these limitations, Iran has experienced the cultivation of many different horticultural crops, especially nut crops, because of the country&#x02019;s diverse climates. In fact, Iran is one of the main centers of origin for many temperate fruit trees, including walnuts [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Nut crops are one of the most important horticultural crops in the world. Their production has increased by more than 24% (equivalent to 2.4 million metric tons of nut kernel) through the past ten years. In particular, almonds and walnuts have had the highest growth rates in the world, among other nut crops [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Persian walnuts (<italic>Juglans regia</italic> L.) are widely cultivated across the temperate regions of the northern hemisphere, especially from 30&#x000b0; to 50&#x000b0; (in Asia, Europe and North America) as well as in the southern hemisphere from 30&#x000b0; to 40&#x000b0; (in Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, Chile and Argentina) [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The Persian walnut originated in ancient Persia and spread to its western neighbors and central Asia [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Iran is the fourth leading nut crop producer and its total production accounts for 7% of the world&#x02019;s total production. The country produces 79% and 13% of the pistachios and walnuts in the world, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. After the pistachio, walnut is the most important nut crop in Iran, and there have been growing demands for its production and consumption in recent years [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Iran is one of the main centers of origin for walnuts and ranks third as a leading producer of Persian walnuts in the world (with around 349192 tons) after China and the United States. Walnut production and its area of harvest in Iran have increased by 63% and 58.9%, respectively, through the last 10 years [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Land suitability evaluation is to estimate the inherent capacity of any unit of land that could support specific practices and uses for a long period without deterioration [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The evaluation of land suitability not only indicates the type of land use but also shows its limitations in the production of a given type of crop [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Geographic information systems (GIS) and remote sensing data are commonly used for land suitability evaluation. GIS has been used as a tool for developing alternative uses of agricultural land, precision farming and land suitability mapping [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>In previous studies, the GIS-based approach has been used in order to evaluate land suitability for various crops in different areas [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Mesgaran et al. [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] evaluated Iran&#x02019;s land for agriculture using GIS information. They reported that only 2.4% of Iran&#x02019;s land is either suitable or highly suitable for agricultural crop production. Also, the majority of highly suitable lands for agriculture are located in the northern and western provinces of Iran [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The GIS approach has assisted the evaluation of land suitability for apple and pear cultivation in the Uttarankhand region, north of India, and it was reported that the south of Uttarankhand is more suitable for pome fruit production. In contrast, its upper hilly region was found to be unsuitable for the cultivation of apples and pears due to the presence of clay soils and chilling injuries [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The evaluation of land suitability for walnut cultivation in Beijing, China, involved the use of GIS data and showed that low mountainous regions situated in the west and north of Beijing are suitable for walnut cultivation [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Over the past recent decades, climate change has significantly affected agricultural activities on a global scale. The consequences of climate change on temperate-zone fruit trees include drought stress, earlier flowering among trees, possible risks of more damage due to late-spring frost, the decline in the number of chill hours in the winter and deprivation of the chilling requirement [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. According to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), most countries will experience an increase in their average temperatures, more frequent heat waves, scarcer water resources, desertification, and irregular periods of heavy precipitation [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The consideration of climate change and its effects on land suitability has become an important issue concerning food security [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In this context, Zhao and Lin [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported that climate change would reduce the area of suitable lands for <italic>Jatropha</italic> cultivation in the world. It was suggested that the predicted scenarios of climate change would reduce the suitability of <italic>Jatropha</italic> cultivation in areas near the equator [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p>After pistachio, walnut is the most important nut crop in Iran. In recent years, the country has experienced a rise in demand for newly established, modern walnut orchards by fruit growers. Due to the effects of climate change on suitable lands for walnut cultivation, this study was conducted to determine land suitability for walnut cultivation using GIS. Two temporal spans were considered in this research: the present-day conditions of walnut cultivation and the future of cultivation (2020&#x02013;2049) as affected by simulations of climate change and the speculations thereof.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Material and methods</title><p>In this study, we evaluated the entirety of Iranian territory for walnut production using GIS information. Iran has a total area of 1,648,195 km<sup>2</sup> and is the world&#x02019;s 17<sup>th</sup> largest country [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This study was performed in two phases. In the first phase, land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran was determined for the present conditions. In the next phase, the effects of climate change were estimated for the next thirty years (2020&#x02013;2049) in the areas of study. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g001">Fig 1</xref> shows the conceptual model used for this study.</p><fig id="pone.0218725.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Conceptual model to prepare the maps of land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran using GIS.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.g001"/></fig><sec id="sec003"><title>Land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran under the current conditions</title><p>In the first phase, the climatic (maximum, average and minimum temperature, relative humidity and chilling requirement), edaphic (water and soil EC) and topographic (altitude and land slope) data of walnut production were used. The climate data obtained from the Iranian Meteorological Organization (375 synopetic stations). The climatic data included ambient temperatures in the growing season, minimum winter temperatures and the maximum temperature during the year, chilling requirement and relative humidity. The calculations were performed using long-term statistics (spanning from 30 to 67 years) among 375 synoptic stations in Iran. The ArcGIS software was used for analyzing the data. The climatic data from synoptic stations were interpolated by applying the Kriging method of prediction maps in the form of layers.</p><p>In order to classify the chilling requirements in all regions of Iran, along with the consideration of daily winter temperatures (December, January, and February), the raw data were converted to hourly data using the Monteith and Unsworth [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] method according to the following formula:
<disp-formula id="pone.0218725.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.e001.jpg" id="pone.0218725.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Hourly</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">temperature</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">sin</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>15</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>210</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>Tmax: Daily maximum temperature</p><p>Tmin: Daily minimum Temperature</p><p>H: Hour of day</p><p>The ASTER (Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Reflection Radiometer) sensors provided information regarding altitude and land slopes. In this study, a digital elevation model (DEM) was used which had a precision of 150 m (5 seconds). Usually, a digital elevation model (DEM) is used in most spatial GIS analysis and can be used for mapping terrestrial slopes and their directions. It can assist various analyses in a three-dimensional fashion.</p><p>The edaphic data in this study were prepared based on a database from the Iran Water Resources Management Company (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wrm.ir/">http://www.wrm.ir/</ext-link>). To analyze the edaphic data, the method of interpolation was used based on Kriging method by using ArcGIS software. The map was predicted with regard to the electrical conductivity (EC) of the soil, and the EC of surface and underground waters.</p><p>Iran&#x02019;s land was classified into four suitability class based on the climate, edaphic and topography variables which is important for walnut production (<xref rid="pone.0218725.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These suitability classes were named as highly suitable, suitable, fairly suitable and unsuitable. This classification was conducted based on the literature review [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and the comments of expert walnut researchers in the world who advise on commercial walnut production. Highly suitable pedoclimate conditions are considered as ideal conditions for planting walnuts. Suitable conditions are lands which share a proximity with the ideal conditions for the planting. Fairly suitable conditions are those in which the cultivation of walnuts is possible but with some restrictions. Unsuitable conditions apply to conditions where the success of planting walnuts is not technically and economically feasible.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0218725.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Classification of pedoclimate condition of walnut for land suitability assessment.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0218725.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0218725.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pedoclimate Condition</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highly Suitable (Best)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suitable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fairly Suitable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unsuitable</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Altitude (m)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;1000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000&#x02013;2000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2000&#x02013;3000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;3000 and &#x0003c;0</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Average Temperature in Growth Season (&#x000b0;C)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;15</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Min. Temperature in Winter (&#x000b0;C)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5&#x0003c;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5&#x0003e;Suitable&#x0003e;-15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-15&#x0003e;Fairly Suitable&#x0003e;-20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; -20</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Max. Temperature (&#x000b0;C)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x0003e;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#x02013;38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;38</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chilling Requirement (0&#x02013;7&#x000b0;C)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1100&#x02013;1800</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900&#x02013;1100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">600&#x02013;900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;600</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Soil EC (ds/m)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x0003e;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x02013;2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5&#x02013;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x0003c;</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Surface Water EC (ds/m)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x0003e;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x02013;2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5&#x02013;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x0003c;</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Groundwater EC (ds/m)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x0003e;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#x02013;2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5&#x02013;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x0003c;</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Relative Humidity in Summer (%)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x02013;65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;45</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x0003e; and 65&#x0003c;</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Land Slope (%)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02013;30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x0003c;</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The base maps provided from free shapefile maps which obtained from Iran Water Resource Management Company. The fuzzy algebraic product model was applied to combine the layers and determine land suitability for walnut cultivation. Here, the membership of an element in a set is defined with a value in the range of one (full membership) to zero (non-full membership). The degree of membership is usually expressed by a membership function whereby the form of the function can be linear, nonlinear, continuous or discontinuous. In a fuzzy model, each pixel in each map is assigned a value between zero and one which indicates the amount. The location of the pixel is inappropriate from the point of view of the relevant criterion for the target [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran for the future (2029&#x02013;2049)</title><p>In the second phase, the NASA Earth Exchange Global Daily Downscaled Projections (NEX-GDDP) dataset was used, and land suitability for walnut cultivation was determined by considering an approach to climate change during the years 2020&#x02013;2049. The NEX-GDDP climatic data were obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cds.nccs.nasa.gov/nex-gddp">https://cds.nccs.nasa.gov/nex-gddp</ext-link> and the ensemble of 21 AOGCM models was used by equally weighting them. For this purpose, the BCSD downscaling method was originally designed to process monthly data. This algorithm assumes that the biases in the current and future simulations follow the same pattern. To perform the BCSD algorithm, three databases are required: observational data, AOGCM model data for the base period and AOGCM model data for future periods. The bias correction is applied to the first and second databases. At first, the observation data and the base period of the AOGCM models are converted to the resolution (e.g. 0.1&#x000b0;&#x000d7;0.1&#x000b0;). Then, in each cell, the cumulative probability distribution function (CDF) of observation data and the base period of the AOGCM models are calculated. The relationship between these two CDFs has been established to draw a correlation. Finally, this relationship will be used for overriding the future data of the AOGCM model [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The parameters in the second phase included the minimum and maximum daily temperatures and the chilling requirement.</p><p>Variations among the maximum and minimum temperatures in the 2020&#x02013;2049 period were determined in comparison with the 1976&#x02013;2005 baseline period. Firstly, the delta ratio values (&#x00394;T) of the maximum and minimum temperatures between the 30-year average monthly values were calculated for the upcoming period (2020&#x02013;2049) and then the simulated baseline period (1976&#x02013;2005) was calculated by the same model for each cell according to the following equation [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. These values estimate a 30-year average of climate change, as considered in relation to the baseline period. The baseline period refers to data belonging to 1976&#x02013;2005 which can also be mentioned in the formula as the 'base.'
<disp-formula id="pone.0218725.e002"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.e002.jpg" id="pone.0218725.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GCM</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">fut</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">GCM</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">base</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p><bold>&#x020b8; GCM, fut, i:</bold> 30-year average temperature simulated by AOGCM in the future period (2020&#x02013;2049) for each month</p><p><bold>&#x020b8; GCM, base, i:</bold> 30-year average temperature simulated by AOGCM during the baseline period (1976&#x02013;2005) with observations for each month</p><p>In this study, the temperature delta values were calculated for all 21 AOGCM models. Then, the median of values for the 21 models pertaining to each month were calculated. These were set as criteria for determining the country&#x02019;s climatic changes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec005"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec006"><title>Phase I: Determination of land suitability for walnut cultivation under the present conditions</title><p>The ultimate structure of mapping suitable lands for walnut cultivation in Iran was established here by combining the layers pertaining to the average air temperature in the growing season, the maximum temperature in summer, the minimum temperature in winter, the chilling requirement, the relative humidity of the air during the growing season, the altitude, land slope, EC of the soil, surface water and groundwater (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218725.s002">S1 Fig</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g002">Fig 2</xref> illustrates the zoning of land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran. It consists of cells, each of which has dimensions of 150 meters (2.2 ha). The results revealed that the total amount of unsuitable lands for walnut cultivation are 1065351 km<sup>2</sup> (106535100 ha) which comprises 64.64% of the total area of Iran (<xref rid="pone.0218725.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The majority of unsuitable lands for walnut cultivation were in the south of Iran. These lands comprise parts of the provinces of Khuzestan (except a part of Andimeshk, Dezful, Masjed Soleiman and Izeh cities), Bushehr, Hormozgan (except a part of Haji Abad city), Sistan and Baluchestan and Fars (including Farashband, Mohr, Qir and Karzin, Khonj, Jahrom, Larestan, Zarin Dasht and Darab cities) and Kerman (including Qaleh Ganj, Rodbar-e-Jonubi, Manujan, Kahnuj, Anbarabad, Jiroft, Bam and Kerman cities). In addition to the south of Iran, the unsuitable lands were also mapped in parts of the central regions of Iran such as the south of Semnan and Yazd provinces (including Ardekan, Meybod, Behabad, Ashkezar and Yazd cities) and South Khorasan (except Nehbandan and Sariyan cities). These lands can be considered as unsuitable for walnut cultivation because of a lack of sufficient winter chill hours which are necessary to meet the chilling requirement. The mentioned lands are also characterized by unfavorably high EC values in the soil and in the water resources, along with high summer temperatures (higher than 38&#x000b0;C) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g002">Fig 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0218725.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>The map of land suitability of walnut cultivation in Iran for current conditions.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0218725.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran in the present and future (2020&#x02013;2049).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0218725.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0218725.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="2">Cultivation ability</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Present</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Future</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area (km<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Share of Iran&#x02019;s area</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area (km<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Share of Iran&#x02019;s area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Highly suitable (best)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150433</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132525</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Suitable</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">275213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">293448</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.80</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fairly suitable</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157198</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120737</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Cultivable</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">582844</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">546710</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.17</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No cultivable (Unsuitable)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1065351</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1101485</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.83</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>*The total walnut cultivable area are the sum of highly suitable, suitable and fairly suitable.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on the results, parts of the Caspian coastline in northern Iran, especially parts of Golestan, Mazandaran and Gilan provinces, have relative humidity levels of more than 65 percent and thus are not recommended for walnut cultivation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g002">Fig 2</xref>).</p><p>The results revealed that parts of the provinces of Khorasan Razavi (including Meh Valat, Bajestan, Gonabad, Rashtkhar and Khalilabad cities), Qom, Isfahan (including Aranbidgol and Ardestan cities), Semnan (including south of Semnan, Garmsar and Shahrud cities), Yazd (Bafgh city), and Kerman (including Bardsir, Baft and Anar cities) were of the &#x0201c;fairly suitable&#x0201d; class of regions for the cultivation of walnut (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g002">Fig 2</xref>). In addition to these areas, parts of the northwestern provinces of Iran were also included in this class. Accordingly, over 9.54% of the total area of Iran (i.e. 157198 km<sup>2</sup>) can be considered to be in the &#x0201c;fairly suitable&#x0201d; class of regions for walnut cultivation. (<xref rid="pone.0218725.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Unlike unsuitable lands, fairly suitable lands can be potentially considered suitable for the cultivation of walnut, but certain pedo-climatic restrictions may probably incur additional production costs and thus make low yields per unit area.</p><p>The results indicated that 150433 km<sup>2</sup> (i.e., 9.13% of Iran's total area) and 275213 km<sup>2</sup> (i.e. 16.70% of Iran&#x02019;s total area) are of the &#x0201c;highly suitable&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;suitable&#x0201d; classes for walnut cultivation, respectively. In other words, minimal limits exist there for walnut production when considering the studied factors (i.e. soil and water EC, relative humidity, temperature, chilling requirement, altitude and land slope). The provinces in the range of Alborz, Zagros and Kopet Dagh mountains are considered as highly suitable and suitable areas for walnut cultivation. Parts of the Fars province, Kerman and Yazd are also among the highly suitable and suitable classes for the cultivation of walnut. In general, the available potential for walnut cultivation comprises about 35.36% of the country&#x02019;s total area. The majority of this percentage is located in the northern, north-western and western margins of Iran (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g002">Fig 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Phase II: Determination of suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran by taking the approach of climate change</title><p>By simulating the variations in the maximum and minimum temperatures for the future period (from 2020 to 2049), an increase in temperature (around 1.5&#x000b0;C) is indicated throughout all months of the year and in all regions of Iran (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g003">Fig 3</xref>). This is consistent with the predicted amounts of increase in the fifth report of IPCC (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change). The most significant increase in temperature will be observed in the summer months, and the lowest increase is anticipated in the winter and spring. The minimum temperature in the northern half of Iran faces an average increase of 1&#x000b0;C during the winter and spring months. However, the increase will be higher in the southern half of the country and be 1.3&#x000b0;C. In the summer, minimum temperatures are expected to rise substantially in all areas of the country. This increase will be about 1.7&#x000b0;C. Maximum temperatures in the north and north-eastern parts of the country will experience an average increase of 1.53&#x000b0;C. Furthermore, this increase in maximum temperatures will be 1.5 to 1.7&#x000b0;C in December and May, but will be 1.8&#x000b0;C in the summer (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218725.s003">S2 Fig</xref>). In general, the temperature for all areas of the country will increase by 1.53&#x000b0;C in maximum temperature and 1.45&#x000b0;C in minimum temperature.</p><fig id="pone.0218725.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><p>Classification of Iran for walnut cultivation regarding maximum (a) and minimum (b) temperature in the future period (2020&#x02013;2049).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.g003"/></fig><p>Climate change and global warming have substantial effects on the number of chill hours in winter. It is estimated that a significant decrease will occur in the number of chill hours in the coming years [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. This decline in the chill hours of winter can cause deprivations of the chilling requirement for many fruit trees in temperate regions and could reduce the vastness of the temperate zone [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The classification of Iranian regions in terms of the chilling requirement for the future period (2020&#x02013;2049) showed that the southern provinces of Iran which are close to the Persian Gulf and the Oman Sea (e.g., Sistan and Baluchistan, Hormozgan, and Bushehr) will continue to be unsuitable regions for the cultivation of walnuts for the coming years. This is mostly because of the inability of those regions in providing the chilling requirement of walnut trees.</p><p>The potential impact of climate change has been adverse, especially on the horticultural demand for chill hours throughout the country, and the vastness of areas that are currently capable of meeting the chilling requirement will be reduced. In other words, some regions in the &#x02018;highly suitable&#x02019; class will be turned into the &#x02018;suitable&#x02019; class, and some regions that are currently &#x02018;suitable&#x02019; will be turned into the &#x02018;fairly suitable&#x02019; class regarding the number of chill hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g004">Fig 4</xref>). On average, there will be 50 hours of decline in the number of chill hours in Iran over the future period. For instance, regions that are currently with a total number of 1600 chill hours will have 1550 chill hours in the future period.</p><fig id="pone.0218725.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><p>Classification of Iran&#x02019;s land for walnut cultivation regarding the chilling requirement in the present (a) and future (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.g004"/></fig><p>Studying land suitability for walnut cultivation in the future of Iran (2020&#x02013;2049) indicates that the overall appearance of the map overview will be almost identical to the current one. In general, as in the current situation, large parts of the southern and central regions of Iran will remain to be unsuitable for the production of walnuts in the future. In contrast, the northern, northwestern and western margins of Iran (across the Alborz, Zagros and Kopet Dagh Mountains) are currently considered and will continue to be in the &#x0201c;highly suitable&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;suitable&#x0201d; class of regions for the cultivation of walnuts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g005">Fig 5</xref>). An exact comparison between the current status (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g002">Fig 2</xref>) and the future status (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g005">Fig 5</xref>) of land suitability in Iran shows that many areas that are currently in the &#x0201c;fairly suitable&#x0201d; class of regions for walnut cultivation will be turned into the &#x0201c;unsuitable&#x0201d; class. These include parts of Semnan province, Qom and Isfahan. Also, some &#x0201c;highly suitable&#x0201d; regions in the northwest of Iran (including Zanjan, Ardebil, and East Azarbaijan provinces) and some central regions of Iran (e.g. Isfahan province) will be downgraded to the &#x0201c;suitable&#x0201d; class of cultivation over the future period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218725.g005">Fig 5</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0218725.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0218725.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>The map of land suitability for walnut cultivation in Iran (2020&#x02013;2049) with an emphasis on climate change.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0218725.g005"/></fig><p>The current conditions suggest that 582844 km<sup>2</sup> out of 1648195 km<sup>2</sup> in Iran are cultivable for walnut and are capable of meeting productive expectations. Based on the results, it is estimated that highly suitable lands for walnut cultivation in Iran will be reduced by 11.39% over the next 30 years (2020&#x02013;2049) due to global warming. This decline in highly suitable lands would be from 150433 km<sup>2</sup> to 132525 km<sup>2</sup>. This also means that the reduced area of highly suitable lands will be approximately added to the &#x0201c;suitable&#x0201d; class of regions which will increase from 275213 km<sup>2</sup> to 293448 km<sup>2</sup>. In other words, some of the &#x0201c;highly suitable&#x0201d; class for walnut cultivation in Iran is becoming &#x0201c;suitable&#x0201d; because of climate change. In general, during the next thirty years (2020&#x02013;2049), climate change will take away 36,136 km<sup>2</sup> of the country from any prospect for walnut cultivation. Accordingly, 546710 km<sup>2</sup> of Iran&#x02019;s land will be suitable for walnut cultivation in the next 30 years. Furthermore, 66.83% of Iran&#x02019;s land (i.e. 1101485 km<sup>2</sup>) will become unsuitable for walnut cultivation, and only 33.17% (i.e. 546710 km<sup>2</sup>) of the country&#x02019;s area will be capable of hosting walnuts. The latter percentage is achieved by adding up the highly suitable, suitable and fairly suitable classes (<xref rid="pone.0218725.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec008"><title>Discussion</title><p>Climate change can adversely affect food security on global and regional scales. It influences the quality and quantity of agricultural products and, generally, the availability of food [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Among the consequences of climate change are the increase in temperatures, the decline of rainfall and available water, the erratic fluctuations in rainfall patterns, the changes in flowering patterns of fruit trees, reductions in the number of chill hours and higher risks of late spring frost [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Climate change and the rise in urbanization have cut back on agricultural lands, and it is necessary to select suitable areas for the cultivation of crops.</p><p>Meanwhile, demands for the establishment of commercial, modern walnut orchards have increased in Iran over the past recent years, and it is a knowledgeable decision to identify suitable areas for walnut cultivation in response to climate change [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The results of this study showed that the northern, northwestern and western regions of Iran are highly suitable for walnut cultivation. Among the most important suitable areas for walnut cultivation, we can mention provinces like Khorasan Razavi and North Khorasan, the north of Semnan, the south of Mazandaran, Tehran, Alborz, Qazvin, Zanjan, Gilan, Ardabil, East Azarbaijan, West Azarbaijan, Hamedan, Lorestan, Kurdistan, Kermanshah, Kohgiluyeh and Boyer Ahmad, Chaharmahal and Bakhtiari, in addition to some parts of Fars (including Farashband, Mohr, Qir and Karzin, Khonj, Jahrom, Larestan, Zarin Dasht and Darab cities), Kerman (including Bardsir, Baft and Anar cities), Isfahan (except Ardestan, Isfahan, Nain, Khur and Biabanak cities) and Yazd (including a part of Khatam, Abakuh, Taft, Mehrz and Bafgh cities). Among these provinces, the highest levels of land suitability and cultivation are expected to be in Hamedan, Lorestan, Kurdistan, Kermanshah, Zanjan and West Azarbaijan.</p><p>In order to evaluate the validation of the map drawn for land suitability in this study, the results were compared with reports and statistics published by the Iranian Ministry of Agriculture, along with other relevant information and field evaluations [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. According to a report by the Ministry of Agriculture [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and Soleimani et al. [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], the production of walnut is mostly centered in the northern and western regions of the country. In the central regions of the country, as reported by the Ministry, only some parts of Isfahan, Kerman, Yazd, and Fars are observed to be under walnut cultivation. Accordingly, the accuracy of the map obtained in this study can be confirmed.</p><p>Furthermore, Soleimani et al. [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] published maps of walnut production in Iran, based on statistics of the year 2005 which were provided by the Iranian Ministry of Agriculture (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218725.s004">S3 Fig</xref>). The researchers reported no instances of walnut cultivation along the Caspian coastline but referred to the populated cultivation of walnuts in the provinces of Kerman, Hamedan, Fars, Lorestan, Kurdistan, and Kermanshah [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The map obtained in this study confirms that the mentioned provinces are the most suitable areas for walnut cultivation.</p><p>The assessment of land suitability for walnut cultivation in the Tehran province [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] showed that about 50% of the province (i.e. 1,904,307 hectares) is unsuitable for walnut cultivation. The northern parts of the Tehran province (including parts of Shemiranat, Firoozkooh and Damavand) and a southern part of the province (including a part of Varamin city) are unsuitable areas for walnut cultivation. The greatest limits to walnut cultivation in the north and south of the Tehran province are high altitude and high values of EC in the water and soil, respectively. In addition, the occurrence of high temperatures during the growing season is another limiting factor for walnut cultivation in Varamin, Tehran province. These results confirm a previous study on land suitability for walnut cultivation in the Tehran province [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>The study of climate change and its effects on the land suitability of walnut cultivation in Iran showed that climate change is capable of increasing the temperature by 1&#x02013;1.7&#x000b0;C during the growing season, and would reduce the number of chill hours in the winter by 50 hours over the next 30 years (2020&#x02013;2049) [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0218725.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This increase in temperature and the deficiency of chill hours will significantly reduce the suitable areas for walnut cultivation from 582844 km<sup>2</sup> to 546710 km<sup>2</sup>, and these results confirm previous research on other crops such as <italic>Jatropha</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, the results of this research suggested that a large part of the north and west of Iran is suitable for the cultivation of walnuts. More than 582844 km<sup>2</sup> (35.36%) of Iran&#x02019;s total area are currently suitable for walnut cultivation. However, this study considered some parameters only, whereas several other restrictions exist which deserve further inquiry. These include the edaphic pH, along with the availability of water and the soil depth which could undermine the suitability of lands for walnut cultivation. It is an imperative to evaluate the micro-climate of each region and conduct observations in the field before establishing new orchards in each region. In general, the land suitability of walnut cultivation will decrease by 6.20% and reach 546710 km<sup>2</sup> during the next 30 years (2020&#x02013;2049). Nonetheless, climate change will affect other environmental parameters including the availability of water, relative humidity, as well as the EC of the water and soil. Since climate change affects these factors too, the unpredictability of an uncertain future for walnuts could be even bleaker than the descriptions made in this research.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec010"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0218725.s001"><label>S1 Dataset</label><caption><title>The meterological data of Iran and delta T<sub>max</sub> and T<sub>min</sub> used to prepare walnut land suitability maps for present and future condition.</title><p>(RAR)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0218725.s001.rar"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0218725.s002"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><p><bold>Classification of Iran&#x02019;s land for walnut cultivation in the present condition</bold> (in aspect of latitude (a), relative humidity (b), average temperature (c), chilling requirement (e), land slope (e) and soil EC (f) (the map (c) just shows the average temperature in growth season in Iran)).</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0218725.s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0218725.s003"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><p><bold>Classification of Iran&#x02019;s land for walnut cultivation in the future (2020&#x02013;2049)</bold> (regarding maximum (a) and minimum (b) temperature in different months of the year).</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0218725.s003.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0218725.s004"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>The areas of walnut cultivation in Iran based on statistics of the year 2005 which were provided by the Iranian Ministry of Agriculture; each black spot spans about 20 hectares [<xref rid="pone.0218725.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</title><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0218725.s004.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank Iran National Science Foundation (INSF), University of Tehran, University of Shiraz, Iran&#x02019;s National Elites Foundation (NEF) and Center of Excellence of Walnut Improvement and Technology of Iran for their technical and hardware supports.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0218725.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alizadeh-Choobari</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Najafi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Extreme weather events in Iran under a changing climate</article-title>. <source>Climate Dynamics</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>): <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00382-017-3602-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Vahdati</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hassani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rezaee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jafari Seyedi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarikhani Khorami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Walnut footprint in Iran</chapter-title>
<source>Following walnut footprints (<italic toggle="yes">Juglans regia</italic> L.) cultivation and culture, folklore and history, traditions and uses</source>. <publisher-name>International Society for Horticultural Science (ISHS)</publisher-name>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mesgaran</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Madani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azadi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Iran&#x02019;s land suitability for agriculture</article-title>. <source>Scientific Reports</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): p. <fpage>7670</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-08066-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28794520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28794520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fallahi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Horticulture in Iran can be an alternative to petroleum and a major source of international business with unique potential and challenges</article-title>. <source>HortScience</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>52</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21273/HORTSCI12080-17</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Talaei</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>. <article-title>A brief outlook on Iran horticulture</article-title>. <source>Acta Horticulturae</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>726</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17660/ActaHortic.2006.726.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>INC</collab>. <chapter-title>Nuts and dried fruits, Statistical yearbook</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>International Nut and Dried Fruits Press</publisher-name>
<year>2018</year>: 76 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Germain E. Le Noyer. Centre Technique Interprofessionnel des Fruits et Legumes (CTIFL) Publication: 1999; 280 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FAO. 2017. FAOSTAT production crops. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://faostat.fao.org/site/567/default.aspx#ancor">http://faostat.fao.org/site/567/default.aspx#ancor</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dhami</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nain</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panwar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Suitability analysis of apple and pear using remote sensing and GIS in Uttarakhand</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agrometeorology</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>474</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vahdati</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Massah Bavani</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khosh-Khui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fakour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarikhani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Land suitability classification of Persian walnut cultivation in Iran using geographic information system (GIS)</article-title>. <source>Iranian Journal of Horticultural Science and Technology</source>
<year>2018</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ziadat</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Bakri</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparing existing and potential land use for sustainable land utilization</article-title>. <source>Jordan Journal of Agricultural Sciences</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>2</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>372</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mansor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shafri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Apicultural site zonation using GIS and Multi-Criteria Decision analysis</article-title>. <source>Pertanika Journal of Tropical Agricultural Science</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>31</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Amiri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohamed Shariff</surname><given-names>ARB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Application of geographic information systems in land-use suitability evaluation for beekeeping: A case study of Vahregan watershed (Iran)</article-title>. <source>African Journal of Agricultural Research</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJAR10.1037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>AbdelRahman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of land suitability and capability by integrating remote sensing and GIS for agriculture in Chamarajanagar district, Karnataka, India</article-title>. <source>The Egyptian Journal of Remote Sensing and Space Science</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejrs.2016.02.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gao Z, Li Z, Chen J. Planning and suggestions for the walnut production areas in Beijing. 10th International Conference on Measuring Technology and Mechatronics Automation (ICMTMA) 2018; 358&#x02013;361.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Teka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haftu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Land suitability characterization for crop and fruit production in Midlands of Tigray, Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>Momona Ethiopian Journal of Science</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Chuong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Land suitability analysis and evaluation for production of fruit trees using GIS technology</article-title>. <source>Journal of Science, Hue University</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>67</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26459/jard.v67i4.3105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fruit tree suitability assessment using GIS and multi-criteria evaluation</article-title>. <source>Transaction of the CSAE</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>690</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hassankhah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vahdati</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rahemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hassani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarikhani Khorami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Persian Walnut phenology: effect of chilling and heat requirements on budbreak and flowering date</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Horticultural Science and Technology</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>271</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22059/IJHST.2018.260944.249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eccel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caffarra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crisci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk of spring frost to apple production under future climate scenarios: the role of phenological acclimation</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Biometeorology</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>53</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00484-009-0213-8</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19263089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19263089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ochieng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirimi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathenge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of climate variability and change on agricultural production: The case of small scale farmers in Kenya</article-title>. <source>NJAS-Wageningen Journal of Life Sciences</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.njas.2016.03.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abd-Elmabod</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anaya Romero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jord&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz Rojas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>DDL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Using MicroLEIS DSS to evaluate climate change impacts on land suitability in Andalusia, Spain</article-title>. <source>Geophysical Research Abstracts</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>15</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of the impacts of climate change on land suitability for <italic>Jatropha</italic> cultivation</article-title>. <source>Advanced Materials Research</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>955</volume>: <fpage>3777</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3782</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4028/www.scientific.net/AMR.955-959.3777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IBP. Iran Company laws and regulations handbook. Volume 1: strategic information and basic laws. International Business Publications, USA 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.com/books?id=vif3CwAAQBAJ">https://books.google.com/books?id=vif3CwAAQBAJ</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Monteith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unsworth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <source>Principles of environmental physics: plants, animals, and the atmosphere</source>. <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
<year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, Editor. <source>Walnut production manual</source>. Vol. <volume>3373</volume>
<publisher-name>UCANR Publications</publisher-name>
<year>1997</year>; 330 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<source>Nut grower&#x02019;s guide: the complete handbook for producers and hobbyists</source>. <publisher-name>Landlinks Press</publisher-name>: <fpage>2005</fpage>; 240 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Fuzzy knowledge based GIS for zonation of landslide susceptibility."</chapter-title>
<source>In Applications of Chaos and Nonlinear Dynamics in Science and Engineering-Vol. 2</source>, <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc>, <year>2012</year>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-642-29329-0_2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Uncertainty in hydrologic impacts of climate change in the Sierra Nevada, California under two emissions scenarios</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>82</volume> (<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>): <fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-006-9180-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, and <name><surname>Hulme</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Calculating regional climatic time series for temperature and precipitation: methods and illustrations</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Climatology</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>377</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0088(199604)16:4&#x0003c;361::AID-JOC53&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-F</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baldocchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Accumulated winter chill is decreasing in the fruit growing regions of California</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>87</volume>: <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-007-9367-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luedeling</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Climate change impacts on winter chill for temperate fruit and nut production: a review</article-title>. <source>Scientia Horticulturae</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2012.07.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wrege</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caramori</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herter</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reisser J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matzenauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Impact of global warming on the accumulated chilling hours in the southern region of Brazil</article-title>. <source>Acta Horticulturae</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>872</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17660/ActaHortic.2010.872.2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rosenzweig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <article-title>Potential impact of climate change on world food supply</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>367</volume> (<issue>6459</issue>): <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/367133a0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brown ME, Antle JM, Backlund P, Carr ER, Easterling WE, Walsh MK, et al. Climate change, global food security and the US food system. US Global Change Research Program 2015; 146 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gholizadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebadzadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hosseinpoor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdshah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kazemian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<chapter-title>Iran agricultural statistics in 2015&#x02013;2016</chapter-title>
<source>Center for Information and Communication Technology</source>. <publisher-name>Ministry of Jihad-Agriculture of Iran</publisher-name>
<year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soleimani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdollahi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zare</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Horticultural research and development in Iran: A review</article-title>. <source>Progressive Horticulture</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Falahati</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alijani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghohrodi Tali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barati</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Site selection of appropriate locations for development of orchards using GIS &#x00026; RS, by emphasizing climatic factors (case study: walnut&#x02014;Tehran province)</article-title>. <source>Geography and Environmental Sustainability</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>2</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kallarackal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Climate change and chilling requirements</article-title>. <source>In Responses of Fruit Trees to Global Climate Change</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>31&#x02013;34</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-14200-5</pub-id>_9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0218725.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luedeling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girvetz</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Semenov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Climate change affects winter chill for temperate fruit and nut trees</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>e20155</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0020155</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21629649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21629649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>