<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Impacts of shrub encroachment on high altitude ecosystems have the potential to disrupt resident plant communities by changing resources including open space and light (Wilson &amp; Nilsson, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>); nutrient and water dynamics (Myers‐Smith et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>); shelter and forage resources for mammalian and insect herbivores (Muñoz et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>); and services of belowground (Becklin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) and aboveground (Lara‐Romero et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) mutualists. Our results suggest that encroachment of willows can also reduce the fitness benefits of a pollination mutualism for the alpine wildflower, 
 <italic class="italic">P. viscosum</italic>. Under a wide range of environmental conditions at low altitudes in alpine krummholz habitat, 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> co‐flowered with 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic>. Convergence on temperature cues for budburst likely plays a role in flowering overlap, suggesting that pollinator sharing will continue as willows move upward onto the tundra with climate change. Because willows are magnet species for early‐season pollinators (Moquet et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), they attract a variety of insect pollinators including queens of the bumble bee species 
 <italic class="italic">Bombus balteatus</italic> whose visits account for 60%–95% of pollination in 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic> (Galen, 
 <xref rid="ece33272-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>). Although these queens are relatively scarce and difficult to survey, 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> pollen was found on all ten individuals sampled during visits to 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic> flowers and comprised up to a fourth of the pollen delivered to the stigmas. Contamination with 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> was associated with declining seed set in 
 <italic class="italic">Polemonium</italic>. Experimental manipulation of pollen loads indicated that costs of 
 <italic class="italic">Salix</italic> pollen precedence arise during postpollination stages of mating.
</p>
