<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean annual temperatures between 1881 and 2011 for the German states of Länder Baden-Wuerttemberg and Bavaria were obtained from the Deutscher Wetterdienst (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dwd.de" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.dwd.de</span>). A GAM revealed that the smooth term year was significantly associated with temperature in the study area (F
  <sub>3.72, 126.28</sub> = 13.58, p&lt;0.001, adjusted R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.323). During the study period, there was a general non-linear trend for increasing temperatures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0101927-g001" href="#pone-0101927-g001">Figure 1</a>). Between 1881 and about 1940, temperatures generally increased. From then until about 1970, temperatures decreasing slightly, followed by a steep increase in temperatures to the present day that is consistent with recent global warming 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-IPCC1">[32]</a>.
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0101927-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0101927.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Mean annual temperature in southern Germany between 1881 and 2011.</div>
   <p>Solid line – regression spline fit from the GAM; dashed lines – 95% confidence intervals.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0101927.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conditions during certain seasons may have a greater influence on survival compared to other seasons 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Robinson1">[60]</a>. Therefore, morphological adaptations to conditions during a crucial period within the annual cycle may not be detected when using temperature means over the entire annual cycle. However, linear regressions revealed that mean temperatures during seasons were significantly correlated with the temperature of the respective years: spring (March-May; n = 132, 
  <sub>F1,128</sub> = 130.4, adjusted R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.50, p = &lt;0.001), summer (June-August; n = 132, 
  <sub>F1,128</sub> = 49.62, adjusted R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.27, p = &lt;0.001), autumn (September-November; n = 132, 
  <sub>F1,128</sub> = 27.15, adjusted R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.17, p = &lt;0.001) and winter (December-February; n = 132, 
  <sub>F1,128</sub> = 59.93, adjusted R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.31, p = &lt;0.001). Therefore, seasonal trends in temperature were not considered further.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature in the year of collection may not be the most biologically-appropriate year to correlate with morphological characters. Many specimens have been collected early in the year and feathers grew in the previous year. Tarsi are fully grown when birds fledge 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Alatalo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Alatalo1">[61]</a> and thus temperature in subsequent years has no direct influence on the tarsus length of older individuals. Further, phenotypic expression of morphological characters may be more influenced by selective pressures acting in previous years. Therefore, we examined correlations between morphology and running means of temperature for the year of collection and the four preceding years. All species considered in this study have a generation length of less than 3.5 years 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Bauer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Bauer1">[62]</a>. Therefore, our approach includes temperatures experienced when the respective traits developed as well as temperatures causing potential selective pressures on one or two previous generations of most individuals considered in this study. Hence, temperatures that may cause phenotypic responses as well as microevolutionary adaptations are included.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test whether temperature explained fluctuations in morphology better than a time trend alone, we fitted similar GAMs to the same data as described above, but with temperature instead of year as the smooth term. We compared pairs of GAMs (temperature, year) for each morphological trait and species with a likelihood ratio test. The accepted significance level was p≤0.05.</p>
</sec>
