<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The morphology of birds shows intraspecific latitudinal variation which is mostly correlated with migratory behaviour 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Fiedler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Fiedler1">[36]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Frschler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Frschler1">[37]</a>. Therefore, we restricted our study to specimens that were collected in southern Germany and adjacent areas in Switzerland and Austria between about 47.0°N and 50.8°N and between about 6.9°E and 14.3°E. The great majority of the specimens used (75%) were collected in the German federal states of Baden-Württemberg and Bavaria between 47.27° and 50.57°N and between 7.5°E and 13.8°E.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection of study species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We selected a range of species that represent different migration strategies because non-migratory bird species follow Bergmann's rule more strongly than migrants 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Meiri1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Meiri1">[38]</a>. The migration categories considered were: long-distance migrants from the study area to sub-Saharan Africa, short-distance or partial migrants in which either the entire or a proportion of the population migrates to the Mediterranean, and residents. Initially, we selected six species out of each migration category according to the catalogue of the Rosenstein Museum in Stuttgart, but after the visits to the first two and largest collections (Stuttgart, Munich), we discovered that we could not expect to get sufficient specimens for many species, especially for long-distance migrants. For this reason we restricted our analyses to eleven of our initial 18 target species. Of the eleven species, we measured 4529 specimens collected between 1889 and 2010 (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0101927.s002" href="#pone.0101927.s002">Table S1</a>). Some sample sizes for specific analyses may be lower than the totals of measured specimens because it was not possible to measure all morphological variables in all specimens, and specimens were excluded when they did not meet our criteria for certain analyses (see below).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements were taken in collections which are listed in the Acknowledgements.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been debated which measurements represent the size of birds most adequately 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Piersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Piersma1">[26]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Gosler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gosler1">[30]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Rising1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Rising1">[39]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Freeman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Freeman1">[40]</a>. Several studies proposed tarsus length as the preferred single proxy for body size 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Rising1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Rising1">[39]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Senar1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Senar1">[41]</a>. Gosler et al. 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Gosler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gosler1">[30]</a> described wing length as the best single linear proxy of body size (but see 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Rising1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Rising1">[39]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Senar1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Senar1">[41]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Moser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Moser1">[42]</a>). However, wing length is also related to migration and habitat use 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Leisler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Leisler1">[43]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Winkler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Winkler1">[44]</a>. Wing pointedness is related to the efficiency of long-distance flight, with migrants having more pointed wings 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Fiedler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Fiedler1">[36]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Frschler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Frschler1">[37]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Kipp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Kipp1">[45]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Baldwin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Baldwin1">[46]</a>.We considered tarsus length, wing length and the Kipp-index of wing pointedness in parallel to appraise whether trends were consistent across all traits and whether alternative explanations suggest some of these traits might not be good surrogates for body size. With respect to the expectation of decreasing body size 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Sheridan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Sheridan1">[2]</a> and reduced migratory activity 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Visser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Visser1">[47]</a> as a response to the current global warming, the three measurements are expected to decrease during the study period and especially during the last four decades.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wing length was measured from the wrist to the tip with a butted ruler (Wmax 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Eck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Eck1">[48]</a>), and the primary projection with a piece of laminated millimetre-gridded paper with a precision of 0.5 mm. The tarsus was measured by taking the distance between the back of the intertarsal joint and the lower front edge of the last undivided scale before the toes diverge (Tar 2 in 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Eck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Eck1">[48]</a>). The length was marked using the tip of dividers (pair of compasses) and the length read from them on millimetre-gridded paper under a magnifying lamp with a precision of 0.1 mm. The Kipp-index 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Kipp2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Kipp2">[49]</a>, hereafter “Kipp”, is calculated as the percentage of the primary projection (distance from the tip of the first secondary feather to the tip of the longest primary feather) of the wing length (Kipp  =  primary projection/wing length*100).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All measurements were taken by K.-H. Siebenrock, thereby avoiding inter-measurer variation 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Gosler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gosler1">[30]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Salewski2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Salewski2">[50]</a>. We analysed within-observer consistency by blindly repeating the measurements of 98 blackbirds 
   <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span> (97 for tarsus) in 2012 that were first measured in 2007. The mean of the repeated values differed by &lt;0.01 mm for tarsus length, 0.02 mm for wing length and 0.04 mm for the primary projection. Analysing the data according to Lessells &amp; Boag 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Lessells1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Lessells1">[51]</a>, repeatabilities were 50%, 97% and 84% for tarsus length, wing length and primary projection respectively. The repeatability for tarsus length was surprisingly low in contrast to other studies 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-vanNoordwijk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-vanNoordwijk1">[52]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Perkta1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Perkta1">[54]</a>, which is probably due to the sometimes problematic assignment of a reference point for measurements of museum specimens 
   <a rid="pone.0101927-Svensson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Svensson1">[55]</a>. Nevertheless, these inconsistencies in tarsus measurements did not vary with year of collection of specimens (hereafter: year); a linear model with the differences between two measurements as dependent and year as the independent variable revealed an equal distribution of differences over time (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0101927.s001" href="#pone.0101927.s001">Figure S1</a>). Therefore, we consider that any trends over time in our data are not influenced by low repeatability although confidence intervals around estimates of temporal trends may be higher for tarsus length.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analyses</div>
  <sec id="s2d1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generalized Additive Models</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used generalized additive models (GAMs), implemented in the package mgcv of the programme R 2.11.1 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-R1">[56]</a>, to associate morphological variables with year and temperature. GAMs allow for arbitrary variation in the target variables through time 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Wood1">[57]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Zuur1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Zuur1">[58]</a> that potentially describe fluctuations of morphological characters better than linear models, while still approximating linear trends if these are biologically real. In order to avoid possible errors in interpretation due to biased availability of specimens by age or sex cohorts, or due to the presence of individuals that only migrated to or through the study area, we performed a two-step analysis for every species and morphological trait. In the first step, we considered only specimens with known sex and age (before the first primary moult or afterwards) according to Svensson 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Svensson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Svensson1">[55]</a>, Jenni &amp; Winkler 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Jenni1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Jenni1">[59]</a> or the label on the specimen, as well as specimens with known month of collection. We then used ANOVA to test for potential associations of sex, age or month of collection with tarsus length, wing length or Kipp. In the second step, we fitted GAMs to the data with either year or temperature as a smoothing term and the variables that were significant in the first step as fixed factors. Specimens for which information was not available for inclusion at the first step were included at the second step if the relevant variable was not significant at the first, thus considerably increasing our sample sizes for the GAMs.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s2d2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean annual temperatures between 1881 and 2011 for the German states of Länder Baden-Wuerttemberg and Bavaria were obtained from the Deutscher Wetterdienst (
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dwd.de" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.dwd.de</span>). A GAM revealed that the smooth term year was significantly associated with temperature in the study area (F
    <sub>3.72, 126.28</sub> = 13.58, p&lt;0.001, adjusted R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.323). During the study period, there was a general non-linear trend for increasing temperatures (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0101927-g001" href="#pone-0101927-g001">Figure 1</a>). Between 1881 and about 1940, temperatures generally increased. From then until about 1970, temperatures decreasing slightly, followed by a steep increase in temperatures to the present day that is consistent with recent global warming 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-IPCC1">[32]</a>.
   </p>
   <div id="pone-0101927-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0101927.g001</span>
    <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <div class="title">Mean annual temperature in southern Germany between 1881 and 2011.</div>
     <p>Solid line – regression spline fit from the GAM; dashed lines – 95% confidence intervals.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="pone.0101927.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conditions during certain seasons may have a greater influence on survival compared to other seasons 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Robinson1">[60]</a>. Therefore, morphological adaptations to conditions during a crucial period within the annual cycle may not be detected when using temperature means over the entire annual cycle. However, linear regressions revealed that mean temperatures during seasons were significantly correlated with the temperature of the respective years: spring (March-May; n = 132, 
    <sub>F1,128</sub> = 130.4, adjusted R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.50, p = &lt;0.001), summer (June-August; n = 132, 
    <sub>F1,128</sub> = 49.62, adjusted R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.27, p = &lt;0.001), autumn (September-November; n = 132, 
    <sub>F1,128</sub> = 27.15, adjusted R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.17, p = &lt;0.001) and winter (December-February; n = 132, 
    <sub>F1,128</sub> = 59.93, adjusted R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.31, p = &lt;0.001). Therefore, seasonal trends in temperature were not considered further.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature in the year of collection may not be the most biologically-appropriate year to correlate with morphological characters. Many specimens have been collected early in the year and feathers grew in the previous year. Tarsi are fully grown when birds fledge 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Alatalo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Alatalo1">[61]</a> and thus temperature in subsequent years has no direct influence on the tarsus length of older individuals. Further, phenotypic expression of morphological characters may be more influenced by selective pressures acting in previous years. Therefore, we examined correlations between morphology and running means of temperature for the year of collection and the four preceding years. All species considered in this study have a generation length of less than 3.5 years 
    <a rid="pone.0101927-Bauer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Bauer1">[62]</a>. Therefore, our approach includes temperatures experienced when the respective traits developed as well as temperatures causing potential selective pressures on one or two previous generations of most individuals considered in this study. Hence, temperatures that may cause phenotypic responses as well as microevolutionary adaptations are included.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test whether temperature explained fluctuations in morphology better than a time trend alone, we fitted similar GAMs to the same data as described above, but with temperature instead of year as the smooth term. We compared pairs of GAMs (temperature, year) for each morphological trait and species with a likelihood ratio test. The accepted significance level was p≤0.05.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
