<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in morphology, and in particular a decline in body size, are expected to be one of many responses of animals to current rapid global warming 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Millien1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Millien1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Sheridan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Sheridan1">[2]</a>. Fluctuations in the body size of mammals during the Holocene, sometimes with shifts of up to 25% within a century, are correlated with climatic change 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Smith1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Smith1">[3]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Hill1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Hill1">[5]</a>. Animals introduced to new environments changed morphology and size within a few decades 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Johnston1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Johnston1">[6]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov1">[8]</a>, and morphology can change rapidly when driven by selection 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Grant1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Grant1">[9]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Pergams1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Pergams1">[10]</a>. Previous authors 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Sheridan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Sheridan1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov2">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gardner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gardner1">[12]</a> have suggested that changes in body size follow Bergmann's prediction 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Bergmann1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Bergmann1">[13]</a> that endotherms should be smaller in warmer climates because of thermoregulatory needs. However, Bergmann 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Bergmann1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Bergmann1">[13]</a> himself discussed species-specific factors (e.g. body insulation, habitat use, behaviour, nutrition) that may mask the predicted size trend (see also 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Scholander1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Scholander1">[14]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-McNab1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-McNab1">[15]</a>). Therefore, the assumption of unidirectional changes in morphology as a response to a single environmental factor (temperature) across a wide range of species with different ecologies may be questioned, and a review of recent studies examining trends in body size produced conflicting results 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gardner2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gardner2">[16]</a>. Birds and mammals have shown trends consistent with 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gardner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gardner1">[12]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-VanBuskirk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-VanBuskirk1">[17]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Rode1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Rode1">[18]</a>, and contrary to 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov3">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Goodman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Goodman1">[20]</a>, the prediction of decreasing body size with warmer temperatures and lower latitudes, or no clear trend 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Koontz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Koontz1">[21]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Salewski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Salewski1">[23]</a>. Some studies of multiple species experiencing the same climate regime have found opposing directions of change among them 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov2">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gardner2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gardner2">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Salewski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Salewski1">[23]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Dayan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Dayan1">[24]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are several potential caveats to the analyses and interpretation of body size trends in animals 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov4">[25]</a>. First, selecting an appropriate measure to represent body size may be problematic. Examples are the use of the size of teeth in studies of quaternary mammals or the use of body mass in studies of body size of birds 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Dayan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Dayan1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Piersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Piersma1">[26]</a>. Ecological factors such as habitat structure, food availability or competition within a community may influence the size of organs such as teeth, bills or limbs independently of body size 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Dayan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Dayan1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Smith3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Smith3">[27]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Vanhooydonck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Vanhooydonck1">[29]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second caveat is related to the structure and interpretation of analyses. In birds, for example, body mass or wing length is frequently used as surrogates for body size 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gosler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gosler1">[30]</a>. However, body mass varies with season, time of the day, temperature and moult status 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Salewski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Salewski1">[23]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Piersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Piersma1">[26]</a>, and wing length may vary with age, sex and the age of the feathers 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Flinks1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Flinks1">[31]</a>. Ignoring such associations may lead to spurious results. Furthermore, the increase in temperature associated with recent climate change has not been linear; during the past hundred years there have been periods of both rising and falling temperature, with the recent steep increase of global temperatures starting in the early 1970s 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-IPCC1">[32]</a>. Therefore, potential adjustments of size to the prevailing temperature regime could lead to fluctuations rather than linear trends. However, many studies using long-term data sets have used linear models or compared values of one time period with another 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov2">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gardner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gardner1">[12]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-VanBuskirk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-VanBuskirk1">[17]</a> even though forcing linear regressions through non-linear trends is problematic.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third caveat is that the time span of the data set needs to be long enough to distinguish between long-term trends and microevolutionary adaptive change such as may be caused by year-to-year variation of local weather 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Meril1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Meril1">[33]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Husby1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Husby1">[35]</a>. Even under the scenario of recent climate change, local fluctuations in weather conditions may trigger phenotypic responses and thus better explain morphological change in short-term data sets 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Husby1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Husby1">[35]</a>. However, analyses of body-size trends using data going back for more than 50 years are scarce 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-YomTov2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-YomTov2">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Gardner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Gardner1">[12]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we present an analysis of morphological change based on museum specimens of eleven bird species collected in southern Germany and adjacent areas between 1889 and 2010. We examine variation over time in three aspects of morphology (tarsus length, wing length and the Kipp-index of wing pointedness), using additive models that allow for non-linear change. We additionally control for the potential effects of month of collection, sex and age of the individuals. Thus, our study was designed to address the caveats noted above. With respect to the assumption of generally decreasing body sizes in times of global warming 
  <a rid="pone.0101927-Sheridan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0101927-Sheridan1">[2]</a>, the goals of our study are: 1) to determine whether there has been significant long-term variation in morphology over time across all species; 2) to identify differences among species in morphological trends that may be associated with ecological drivers other than temperature; and 3) to identify associations between the observed trends in morphology and changes in climate in the study area.
 </p>
</sec>
