<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2 Economy and climate impacts on harvesting costs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishers’ harvesting decisions are affected by climatic conditions, prices for fish, fuel and labor, technological progress, and the stock level. We use a similar economic dataset to previous studies [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref058">58</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref059">59</a>]. We model purse seines targeting 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella aurita</span> in four Senegalese regions, namely, Thiès Sud, Thiès Nord, Fleuve, and the Dakar peninsula called Cap Vert, and we aggregate the results afterwards. Thus, we limit the included catches to those landed in Senegal. Part of the catch landed in Fleuve may stem from Mauritanian waters. These catches are included, as long as they are landed in Senegal, and thus can be assumed to contribute to Senegalese fishers and consumers rents. We use monthly regional data on purse seine catches (tons), prices (FCFA/kg), and effort (days at sea, DAS) for 2001–2013, provided by the Centre of Oceanographic Research of Dakar-Thiaroye (CRODT). Purse seines exhibited an annual catch share of more than 80% for 2001–2013 in all regions except Thiès Sud (57%). Price data after 2013 are not available to us, which is a limiting factor for the time period covered by our estimation dataset. All prices are given in units of 2010-level FCFA, which is the the Senegalese currency Franc de la Communauté Financière d’Afrique, after deflation with yearly World Bank Consumer Price Index data [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref060">60</a>]. We use regional 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella aurita</span> prices, but fill in gaps with prices from the neighboring region or alternatively the price for 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella maderensis</span>, the closest substitute (4% of observations). We prolong the time series of annual biomass data (cf., Section 2.1) by using our own stock predictions for 2010–2013. This allows us to make use of 187 additional data points, which is desirable in particular for a more robust estimation of time trends. It is also important when looking at fuel impacts, as fuel prices typically are more variable over the long term. The estimation results for the time period 2001–2009, including only observed biomass levels, and further alternative specifications are provided in S7 Section. Monthly local fuel price data are obtained from the annual reports of the Directorate of Maritime Fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref061">61</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref070">70</a>]. Prices are given in units of FCFA/liter. Local fuel prices and global prices for the internationally traded Brent crude oil are highly correlated. A strong upward trend can be observed until 2008, after which fuel prices fall to the level of 2005, followed again by a gradual increase. For climate impacts, we again use the ERA Interim Reanalysis product with a monthly time scale. We average over regional coordinate boxes between 13.5–16.5°N and 17.25–18.75°W. The dataset is summarized in Section C of the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0220433.s001" href="#pone.0220433.s001">S1 File</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supply and demand are simultaneously estimated via the reduced form using robust standard errors. We estimate 32 parameters in three equations from 561 observations. These are monthly regional observations during 2009–2013 with few, unsystematic gaps. A Bayesian information criterion of 4056 and an 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> of 32–34% indicate a good model fit. Sections E and F of the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0220433.s001" href="#pone.0220433.s001">S1 File</a> provide technical details on the model and estimation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assume an iso-elastic inverse demand function for fresh 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella aurita</span>. Our estimates show that inverse demand is decreasing and convex in harvest (significant at the 1% level). This means that consumers are willing to pay a higher price if fish supply is scarce, and the marginal effect decreases with the quantity supplied. This is in accordance with the literature finding that fish is sold mainly in local markets [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref013">13</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref071">71</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref072">72</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella aurita</span> is an important consumption good for these local markets, and consumers respond to quantity changes. Furthermore, the price elasticity of demand is found to depend negatively on population density, a result that is significant at the 1% level. This is a sensible finding, as population density can be taken as a proxy for market size. Larger markets, in turn, spur the supply of various products at affordable prices, and reduce consumers’ dependence on this particular fish. We assume that a linear time trend affects prices. Our empirical estimates show that prices are subject to a monthly positive linear time trend of 0.2%, an estimate that is significant at the 10% level.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The harvesting technology is modeled as a constant returns-to-scale Cobb–Douglas function from a capital–labor composite and fuel. This means that fishers can substitute between fuel, capital, and labor: If one of these inputs becomes more expensive, the fisher is able to partly replace it with other inputs. Several estimation studies [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref073">73</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref077">77</a>], concur that substitution possibilities exist in fisheries. We choose a substitution elasticity of one to keep the model simple and tractable. Harvest production is assumed to depend positively on biomass. At larger biomass values, catches become easier, as fish are located more easily. The “catchability” parameter is used for scaling. A linear time trend on catchability reflects unobserved changes over time. Monthly dummies are introduced to represent regular harvest seasonality, for example, owing to biomass growth, northward stock migration in summer, and cultural events that impact fishing [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref029">29</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref034">34</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref051">51</a>]. One dummy variable is used per month; it equals one if the observation has occurred in that month, and zero otherwise. Thus, its coefficient measures the impact on the outcome variable that stems from the time in the year when the observation occurs. For example, if a certain cultural event that keeps fishers from harvesting takes place each December, the use of monthly dummies would show a negative coefficient for the December dummy. Moreover, harvest success depends on climate variables, which we assume are entered as an exponential function, in which the exponent comprises linear and quadratic terms of climate variables.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We infer the following results from the estimation. The output elasticity of the capital–labor composite is 0.815 (significant at 1%). The resulting output elasticity of 0.185 for fuel means that fuel expenses constitute 18.5% of total fishing costs. Harvest production also depends on biomass at an estimated elasticity of 0.222 (significant at the 1%-level): harvest increases biomass, but the elasticity is rather small, as should be expected for a schooling fishery. Fish are located more easily at a larger biomass, but as fish form schools, this effect is comparatively weak; once a school is located, a large catch can be made without searching further. We estimate there is a positive linear time trend on catchability at a monthly rate of 0.9% (significant at the 1%-level), which we interpret to reflect technical progress. Furthermore, we estimate monthly dummies and find that catch productivity is highest in spring and winter, and lowest in late summer. Monthly dummies are all significant at least at the 10% level.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the influence of climate variables on catchability, we test several specifications, including SST, wind speed and direction, as well as precipitation. We refer the reader to Section G of the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0220433.s001" href="#pone.0220433.s001">S1 File</a> for robustness checks. An important determinant of catchability is the SST. We find a non-linear dependence with a peak of 25.4°C at the 1% significance level, a threshold which is usually crossed between May and June. This is in line with the literature, which finds a non-linear dependence and optimal catch temperatures between 21 and 27°C [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref044">44</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref046">46</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref051">51</a>]. The stock shifts inshore in spring towards the nursing areas, when upwelling recedes and the temperature rises. The earlier this occurs, the earlier are fish within easy catching distance [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref032">32</a>]. When the temperature increases further, 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella aurita</span> migrates northward and out of immediate reach [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref034">34</a>]. This is a natural migration pattern. Interestingly, this feature can explain why we find no negative impact of very high temperatures on biomass growth: As long as it is possible for the species to start procreating earlier in the year, the general increase in SST will not threaten larval survival, considering the fast growth rate of larvae of 2.5/cm per month [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref029">29</a>]. No other climate variables were found to have a significant effect on 
  <span class="italic">Sardinella</span> migration.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the model assumptions, fishers minimize costs subject to the prices for capital, labor, and fuel. Capital and labor are supplied on local markets and are not flexibly adaptable following Quaas et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref078">78</a>]. Hence, we assume increasing and convex iso-elastic inverse supply functions: in equilibrium, wages and the cost of capital increase with the amount of capital and labor used by the fishery. In previous climate change adaptation studies on agriculture, access to financing has been found to be a major determinant [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref079">79</a>]. Fuel supply is perfectly elastic, and prices are determined on the world market. We specify the resulting equilibrium cost function as quadratic, following [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref080">80</a>] (see Section G of the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0220433.s001" href="#pone.0220433.s001">S1 File</a> for robustness). Fuel prices already explain a large part of the strong cost trend found in the previous literature [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref071">71</a>]. A linear cost time trend is added to include remaining unobserved trends in factor prices and the size of factor units. The trend parameter is estimated to be positive at the 1% level. Net linear time trends in total, ceteris paribus, lead to a monthly increase in fishing pressure of 0.8–1.0%; however, this result is pitted against rising fuel prices, market development, and changing climate conditions. With continued market development, equilibrium harvest becomes more sensitive to input changes, particularly biomass. As consumers become less dependent on fish supply, prices remain stable across large ranges of biomass. The cost-reduction effect of larger biomass becomes more important in relative terms. For the subsequent simulation, we need to model how population density as well as fuel prices develop in the future. Data on population density as described earlier in this section and data on Brent oil prices, available from the U.S. Energy Information Administration [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref081">81</a>], are used to estimate linear trends into the future. Thereafter, the trend parameters are assumed to decline linearly over a period of 20 years, as is standard for economic models, such as DICE [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref082">82</a>]. For population density, we observe lower growth rates for more dense regions, in line with decreasing UN population projections [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref083">83</a>]. We also observe a lower productivity trend rate for the longer time horizon (see Section G of the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0220433.s001" href="#pone.0220433.s001">S1 File</a>) and a decreasing trend in energy prices worldwide.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The important model dynamics from our empirical results are summarized as follows.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate enters the economic model in two ways: It affects the growth of the stock and changes the amount of fish that can be harvested sustainably. Higher stock levels decrease harvesting costs. Second, SST has a non-linear, convex impact on harvesting costs, as it affects the spatial distribution of the stock. Thus, an increase in SST can increase the propensity to over-fish.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A higher fuel price leads to a steeper equilibrium cost curve and thus, lower fishing pressure. This is in line with the literature findings that fuel subsidies have led to larger vessels, more powerful engines, longer distances traveled and overall a higher fishing effort [
  <a rid="pone.0220433.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0220433.ref024">24</a>]. In contrast to capital interest and wages, fuel prices are independent from the fuel quantity used by the fishery. This leaves the fishery particularly sensitive to fuel price changes. An increasing fuel price pushes downwards the curve that defines harvest as a function of the stock and thus, reduces over-fishing. For a varying stock growth curve, this means that high growth years are allowed to cushion against following low growth years. Under low fuel prices, the fishers would immediately catch more, thereby swiftly lowering the biomass. Varying both climate models and fuel price trend sheds light on the interaction between the two, as adaptation takes place. The system is less susceptible to climate impacts under high fuel prices, as they have a relative dampening impact on biomass and SST-induced changes in the cost function. In summary, we expect the elimination of fuel subsidies to be beneficial to the sector.
 </p>
</sec>
