<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In accordance with the Island biogeography theory of MacArthur and Wilson (
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1963</xref>) and subsequent studies about metapopulation models (Levins, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1969</xref>; Wiens, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1976</xref>), new areas are generally conquered via successive, more and more distant steps from the starting point. There is a hierarchy in the chronology of occupancy from optimal to suboptimal areas, with suboptimal areas being becoming occupied once optimal areas are saturated (Krebs &amp; Davies 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0804" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1978</xref>, Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1984</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1989</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997b</xref>; Rushing et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). The Island theory concerns breeding populations, with new individuals (propagules) produced in the successive conquered zones that in turn participate to progressive geographical expansion. The case of wintering cormorants is different because they usually return to their native area located in northern Europe each following spring. Among birds in general the wintering area is usually quite far from the breeding area for climatic reasons. However, we can admit that a similar pattern to the Island theory could occur with the progressive geographical conquest of potential (more distant) wintering areas by cormorants for obvious energy costs of flight because the breeding and wintering populations successively increased in Europe after protection of cormorants by the EC Bird Directive in 1979 (Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997b</xref>; Van Eerden &amp; Munsterman, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>), as numerous bird species did once legally protected.
</p>
