<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reconstructing community and population baselines for marine animals is one of the most challenging objectives in ecology and conservation. It is difficult because there are few places on Earth that are unaltered by humans (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>), and for most marine locations, scientific data became available long after initial human impacts (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>). Furthermore, the ecosystem consequences of this impact often go beyond the spatial and biological boundaries of this perturbation (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). Therefore, even in remote and uninhabited marine locations, it is unclear whether ecosystems are pristine or are the results of historical or indirect ecological changes triggered elsewhere.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Chagos archipelago, scientific surveys predated industrial exploitation in inshore and offshore waters, and for 40 years, fisheries statistics and scientific monitoring data were available before and after the establishment of one of the largest MPAs in the planet. These data were sparse and heterogeneous but enabled us to estimate the abundance of local reef sharks across temporal and spatial contrasts of fishing exploitation and reconstruct their abundance under pristine conditions. Our models indicated that the recent abundance of these species (in 2012) was a fraction of their estimated baseline abundance, although both displayed complex decadal trajectories of population abundance, likely driven by alternate phases of fishing exploitation and protection in coastal and pelagic environments.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been frequently assumed that the Chagos archipelago was nearly pristine when scuba diving surveys were first carried out in the area in 1975 (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>). The impact of historical settlements in the archipelago was thought to be minimal, and industrial exploitation offshore was deemed to be in a very germinal stage to affect reef shark populations (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>). Here, we estimated that silvertips were, in 1975, 3.68 times more abundant than gray reef sharks and at 79% of their estimated carrying capacity. Gray reef sharks, in turn, were already at 13% of their predicted abundance under baseline conditions. These abundance levels were radically different from expectations from ecological theory (fig. S6) and from what historical fisheries surveys recorded in 1948 (fig. S5) (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local inhabitants have been in the Chagos archipelago at least since 1744, when the area was first explored by French navigators (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). These people were mainly workers of coconut plantations (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>), subsidizing their dietary needs with imported rice and other agricultural products of the islands. However, they also exploited local marine life, causing population depletions and local eradications of large marine animals as early as the mid 19th century (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). Early explorers reported that seals, “walruses” (probably dugongs, 
  <span class="italic">Dugong dugon</span>), and large numbers of green (
  <span class="italic">Chelonia mydas</span>) and hawksbill (
  <span class="italic">Eretmochelys imbricata</span>) turtles occurred in the Chagos archipelago before the second half of the 19th century (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). Seals and dugongs disappeared from the archipelago in the mid 19th century, and although the area remains a globally significant breeding site for both green and hawksbill turtles, these animals were heavily exploited for their shells and meat (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). How much these coconut plantation workers affected local shark populations is unclear. However, independent historical reconstructions predicted that, between 1950 and 1972, about 46 to 93 metric tons of finfish were taken annually by subsistence fishing in the archipelago (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>). Although this fishery may have not targeted sharks specifically, previous studies have shown that sharks can be intentionally killed in similar subsistence coral reef fisheries to increase catch rates of more profitable bony fishes (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the Chagos archipelago was one of the sectors exploited by a Mauritian semi-industrial handline fishery that began exploiting several banks of the WIO at the end of the 18th century (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>). Catch data from this fishery in the Chagos archipelago only became available in 1977 and indicated that, until 1994, annual fish catches ranged from 32 to 305 metric tons. However, this fishery may have operated in the Chagos banks at least since the late 1940s, when Wheeler and Ommanney (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>) published the results of their exploratory fishing survey, giving new impetus for a region-wide exploitation (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>). Again, information on the impact of this fishery on sharks is scant. Bank fishers targeted coral reef–associated fish such as lethrinids, serranids, lutjanids, siganids, and carangids, with light handlines (
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>), but sharks caught on the spot were used as bait, and results from the exploratory handline surveys suggested that a substantial number of sharks could be caught as well (about 16% of the total fish catch in number) (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>). Furthermore, fishers operating on other WIO banks were seeing declines of shark populations, which they attributed to targeted exploitation by foreign fishing vessels. Therefore, although we cannot be sure of the impact of the bank fishery on shark populations around the Chagos archipelago, anecdotal evidence suggest that reef sharks were being depleted across the WIO (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>). Thus, it cannot be excluded that subsistence fishing by local Chagossians and the Mauritian bank fishery had affected the reef shark community around the Chagos archipelago much earlier than when scuba diving surveys began to be carried out in the area (
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The radical differences in population abundance estimates between baseline reference points and the 1970s, and eventually the complementary population trajectories estimated between 1975 and 2012, were possibly driven by alternate phases of fishing exploitation and protection, inshore and offshore within the BIOT, and the species’ susceptibility to these changing exploitation regimes, given by their intrinsic vulnerability and spatial ecology. We saw three overlapping stages of exploitation regimes:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(1) Historical inshore phase. Since the initial settlement, the Chagos archipelago went through an initial phase of subsistence inshore fishing operated by locals and, toward the mid 20th century, even a short period of semi-industrial exploitation operated by the Mauritian bank fishery. This exploitation phase would have more strongly affected the inshore and more reef-associated gray reef sharks (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). In 1972, local Chagossians were relocated because of the transition of the archipelago to UK jurisdiction, and the Mauritian bank fishery ended its operations in 1994.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(2) Offshore phase. In the second half of the 20th century, the Chagos archipelago became exposed to industrial exploitation offshore from high-seas fisheries, over time becoming increasingly more impactful for sharks (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>). These high-seas fisheries would have posed a larger threat to silvertip sharks than to gray reef sharks, because silvertips use offshore waters more extensively (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
   <span class="italic">35</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
   <span class="italic">42</span>
  </a>) and have been demonstrated to be vulnerable to these fisheries around other coral reefs of the Indian Ocean and the Pacific Ocean (
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
   <span class="italic">35</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(3) Protection phase. Since 1991, in the BIOT, there has been a period of increasing fisheries monitoring, restrictions, and protection for sharks, culminating in 2010 with the total closure of the area to fishing (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). In this period, we estimated the largest reef shark removal, mostly driven by poaching. Catches of the two species were predicted to be an order of magnitude higher than in the 1968 to 1987 period (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>), with little difference before and after the MPA creation. Results of our models suggested that such a low exploitation regime before 1996 was likely an artifact of missing catch statistics, mainly during the 1980s and 1990s in the offshore fishing period (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">Table 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). However, although these unobserved catches would explain the steep decline of silvertips, they were not enough to have an impact on the population of gray reef sharks, which are three times more productive than silvertips (in terms of 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>max</sub>, 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">Table 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical accounts of exploitation and protection regimes, such as those we documented here, are still rare in the literature but may have occurred in many other remote archipelagos across the planet. Since the beginning of industrial fishing, access to pelagic environments or unmonitored jurisdictional waters of many remote coral reef ecosystems has been trivial for globally ranging fishing fleets (
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>). High-seas fisheries have been recorded to affect shark communities globally, but most of their shark catches are unreported (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>). In addition, the history of settlement and inshore exploitation for many of these isolated tropical archipelagos has not yet been described or may be much longer than what is available from scientific record. In the Chagos archipelago, this history unfolded for at least 200 years before the first scientific monitoring programs began. These scientific data documented severe depletion of local shark communities (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>), and by comparing and integrating them with more historical observations, we showed that shark populations were far from being pristine even in the initial years of this scientific monitoring stage. A historical perspective is therefore crucial when interpreting patterns of shark abundance and composition in remote coral reefs. In these ecosystems, high abundances of reef sharks are often celebrated as conservation opportunities or victories (
  <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">
   <span class="italic">45</span>
  </a>). However, ensuring that we clearly understand whether these states are truly natural or an effect of ecosystem change is paramount to avoid not only misguiding management, conservation, and recovery plans but also wasting already limited resources for these goals (
  <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
   <span class="italic">46</span>
  </a>). Controlling for historical shifts in fishing exposure for the diverse and variably vulnerable range of shark species occurring in these systems can help correctly identify ecosystem baselines (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>), characterize the functional role of sharks in coral reef ecosystems (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>), and consequently evaluate the ecological and conservation role of large MPAs and shark sanctuaries around the world.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Together with a historical perspective, observations coming from remote coral reefs need to be properly handled statistically and integrated within a population and community dynamics’ framework (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>). Often, this has the effect of substantially reducing initial estimates of shark abundance and verifying whether these indices are plausible ecologically. Our standing stock estimates for the gray reef shark were comparable in magnitude to the shark densities recently estimated in Palmyra, another remote large marine reserve (36.5 gray reef sharks/km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in the Chagos archipelago compared to 21.3 sharks/km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in Palmyra) (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>) and a rare place where shark stock assessment is also available. Here, population indices were obtained from analyses that explicitly addressed the statistical nature and spatial process of the field observations. They downsized previous estimates (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) by orders of magnitude and empirically disproved the occurrence of inverted trophic pyramids (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>). However, because no temporal trends were detected in 5 years of observations, these shark densities were inferred to represent population baselines. In light of our results, we propose that even this conclusion is uncertain. Carrying capacity was not directly assessed and the multiannual shark densities estimated could also be coherent with a longer-term increasing population trajectory. In the Chagos archipelago, we estimated shark populations far from their carrying capacity despite no previously detected trends in shark indices of abundance between 1975 and 1979 (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>). Gray reef sharks were recovering from a strongly altered status, whereas silvertip sharks were rapidly declining from a historical status of dominance. After 37 years (in 2012), gray reefs reached population densities higher than those in Palmyra but still at 79% of the estimated baseline level.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether the history of exploitation in the Chagos archipelago triggered ecological consequences such as meso-predator releases and trophic cascades (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>) could not be tested. We could not test whether the gray reef shark recovery was only attributable to a reduction of fishing mortality and not to an increase in survival or overall fitness caused by the overexploitation of other shark predators (for example, bull, tiger, hammerhead, or oceanic whitetip sharks) or competitors (like the silvertip sharks) from the BIOT marine reserve’s boundaries (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>). In addition, unknown at this time are the impacts on these patterns of environmental variation detected in the Indian Ocean (
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
   <span class="italic">47</span>
  </a>). Detecting these processes is possible only by combining multiple data sets spanning decades or entire oceanic regions (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) and analyzing them in the context of a quasi-experimental framework (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>). Here, we adopted such an integrative approach with all historical data sets we could find in the region by extracting from them as much information as possible and borrowing information from other systems. Moreover, we exploited the Chagos archipelago’s temporal and spatial contrasts in exploitation and protection regimes to interpret the emerging patterns in shark abundance. However, the available data (indices of abundance, catch statistics, and other priors of baseline structure) were too scant, uncertain, and of limited resolution to increase the number of parameters we could reliably estimate in the Bayesian SPM used. Nonetheless, integrative analyses such as these are essential to reconstruct and conserve baselines of animal populations. Iterative in nature, they identify information gaps and lay the ground for future work. In the Chagos archipelago, our analyses provided a different view of baselines previously assumed for the system, shed new light on how they responded to human impact, and confirmed that management strategies involving both site protection and fisheries management in surrounding regions may be the best options to protect these sites (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). More effort is now needed to increase the resolution of the catch data and historical information for reducing uncertainty on the reconstructed population estimates and to explain the multiple drivers affecting them.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Remote coral reefs offer rare opportunities to reconstruct ecosystem baselines (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>). However, shark community dynamics and their stressors unfold over spatial and temporal scales larger than any extant large MPA and conservation program ever established (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). These scales make the term remote inappropriate for many distant coral reef ecosystems. In these locations, selective exploitation and protection can alter shark baselines in ways difficult to characterize unless field observations are properly handled statistically (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>), incorporated within a population and community dynamics’ framework, and interpreted with a historical perspective. This approach promises to reveal important insights into the abundance, structure, and function of shark communities in coral reef ecosystems around the world and thus identify true pristine ecosystems to protect or set as conservation targets.
 </p>
</sec>
