<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The key finding of this study is the dominant (spatial) impact of soil organic matter on soil thermal diffusivity (
  <span class="italic">D</span>) supported by empirical evidence, which is shown in model simulations to affect the broad-scale soil thermodynamics and in turn affects the soil organic carbon (SOC) accumulation. Thermal mediation of soil organic layer is known to stabilize the underlying permafrost in relatively warm regions where the climate alone cannot sustain the persistence of permafrost
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Here we provide a quantitative empirical estimate for the insulation effect of SOC through its impact on 
  <span class="italic">D</span>. We recognize that, apart from heat conduction controlled by 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, the latent heat associated with soil water/ice phase changes could be substantial in the soil energy budget, especially on the border of permafrost zones (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which complicates the permafrost stability. This latent heat could partly explain the slower warming rate of the mean annual permafrost temperature in discontinuous zones during the past decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. However, this latent heat effect delays but does not prevent the eventual permafrost thawing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. Under the long-term climate warming, as permafrost might greatly retreat poleward
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, heat conduction would finally dominate, inferred from the cold sites outside the permafrost regions today (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>); and the SOC-
  <span class="italic">D</span> relationship suggests a significant impact of changes in SOC on soil temperature in the former permafrost regions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The implication of such SOC-
  <span class="italic">D</span> feedback for future permafrost dynamics, therefore, depends on the direction and magnitude of soil carbon changes in the future. Although enzyme kinetics theory and short-term observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> suggest an initially increasing SOC decomposition rate with warming, large uncertainties still remain in the long-term response of soil carbon to climate change, due to uncertainties in the rate of SOC formation (including changes of plant productivity, soil-aggregate formation, etc.)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> and in microbial physiological changes/adaptation to warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. A recent compilation of field warming studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span> showed diverging changes in SOC stock of top 10 cm depth after warming, with statistically neutral change across all studies. These studies are, however, limited by a generally shallow depths of warming treatment, which missed the response of subsoils
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>; as well as a paucity of measurements for SOC stock changes at deeper soil horizons
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, especially for the formerly frozen soils. Laboratory incubation experiments, though, have demonstrated a high lability of permafrost soils under unfrozen conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. On the other hand, modeling studies mostly projected carbon losses in permafrost soils in the long run, albeit varying rates and magnitudes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>. The protection of permafrost by SOC is also manifested in fire disturbances, where the combustion of surface organic layer led to increased soil temperature and deeper thaw depth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. Thus, the projected increase in fire activities in the northern high latitudes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> might also be an important driver of permafrost thaw through the impact of SOC on soil thermal properties.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from the dominant role of SOC in 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, which controls the temperature propagation below ground (in the case of minor latent heat induced by freezing/thawing), the aboveground features including vegetation and snow cover also impact the vulnerability of permafrost to a rising air temperature by controlling heat exchanges between air and land surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Besides, degradation of ice wedges may lead to land subsidence and thus thermokarst formation, which is estimated to affect 20% of the northern permafrost region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. Such abrupt changes in the landscape strongly alter micro-topography and thus local hydrological and thermal regimes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. Meanwhile, the decadal trajectories after initial thaw are closely linked to accumulation of organic matter (itself related to vegetation succession) on the thermokarst troughs, which helps to stabilize ice wedges and prevent further thaw
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. This mechanism, however, might be perturbed under future warming and intensified fire activities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. Such complex interactions call for models that quantitatively integrates thermo-hydrological processes, their heterogeneity at small spatial scales, vegetation dynamics and soil carbon cycle, thermal impacts of organic matter, and fires, in order to improve our understanding and prediction of the overall vulnerability of permafrost.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The emergent slope of permafrost area versus 
  <span class="italic">D</span> from CMIP5 models (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>) and the empirical relationship of 
  <span class="italic">D</span> versus SOC (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) suggest a non-negligible sensitivity of permafrost area to potential SOC changes (a loss of ca. 0.2 million km
  <span class="sup">−2</span> per 1 kg C m
  <span class="sup">−3</span> reduction of SOC on average). Without the SOC-
  <span class="italic">D</span> coupling, CMIP5 models have projected a linear relationship between air temperature change and permafrost area change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. The recent estimate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span> for the sensitivity of permafrost area to warming was also based on the assumption of an unchanged present-day MAAT-permafrost relationship for future scenarios. In contrast, the results shown here implies a non-linear trajectory of permafrost area changes in response to warming, highlighting a critical need to explicitly represent the coupling between SOC and soil thermal dynamics in models that are utilized to project the future of permafrost.
 </p>
</sec>
