<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soils in the northern permafrost region contain ~1300 ± 300 Pg of soil organic carbon (SOC)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, more than one-third of the global total SOC
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, formed under cold climates with limited decomposition. Carbon release from this large pool due to warming-induced thawing and acceleration of microbial decomposition may act as an important positive feedback to climate change, but the magnitude and timing of this carbon release remains uncertain
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Model estimates of changes in permafrost extent and carbon stocks vary widely for the recent decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> as well as for future scenarios
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, partly because different representations of soil thermodynamics lead to different soil temperature responses to air temperature changes. For the ground surface, the energy budget is composed of net radiation, sensible heat, latent heat from evapotranspiration, and heat flux into and out of the ground. On the other hand, below the surface, thermal dynamics is dominated by heat conduction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> driven by surface soil temperature variations, and also affected by latent heat released or absorbed during soil water phase changes which can be important for wet soils in permafrost regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The heat conduction in the soil, assuming a uniform and constant medium, can be described by the one-dimensional Fourier’s Law (Eqs. [
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>] and (
  <a rid="Equ2" ref-type="" href="#Equ2">2</a>) in “Methods” section)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, in which thermal diffusivity, 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, is the key parameter that describes the rate at which soil temperature changes given a temperature gradient. The value of 
  <span class="italic">D</span> is determined by soil composition (minerals, air, water/ice, organic matter) and soil structure
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Among the different soil constituents, thermal diffusivity of soil organic matter (SOM) is an order of magnitude smaller than that of typical soil minerals, and slightly smaller than water
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Structurally, a higher organic matter content in the soil increases soil porosity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, which also decreases soil thermal conductivity and 
  <span class="italic">D</span> especially when the soil pores are filled with air. As a result, SOM acts as an insulator and the presence of SOM cools the soil during summer, while its warming effect during winter is less important due to the insulating snow cover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. The summer-time cooling effect of SOM in turn restrains microbial decomposition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> and favours the accumulation of SOC. Given the high SOC storage in permafrost soils and the high vulnerability and sensitivity of these carbon stocks to projected warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, it is important to assess the quantitative impact of SOC on 
  <span class="italic">D</span> and the potential acceleration of soil warming due to the loss of SOC and its insulating effect.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering a harmonic forcing as the upper boundary condition (e.g., the seasonal cycle of surface soil temperature), the solution of the heat conduction equation (Eq. [
  <a rid="Equ4" ref-type="" href="#Equ4">4</a>]) gives an exponential dampening of the temperature amplitude with increasing depth, with its e-folding depth reflecting the 
  <span class="italic">D</span> value
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> (Eq. [
  <a rid="Equ5" ref-type="" href="#Equ5">5</a>]). Accordingly, 
  <span class="italic">D</span> can be derived from temperature amplitudes concurrently observed at two soil depths. This equation has been used to calculate 
  <span class="italic">D</span> and its influence factors in in situ studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>, but these studies were limited to a few sites. A large-scale application of this equation has been applied by ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> to study the snow insulation effect between air and soil temperature at 20 cm depth, but did not touch the research problem of heat conduction in sub-surface soils below 20 cm.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we infer 
  <span class="italic">D</span> from two large data sets of depth-specific soil temperature measurements, the Russian Historical Soil Temperature Data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> (hereafter RHST) and the International Polar Year Thermal State of Permafrost
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> (hereafter IPY), at 274 locations that spread throughout Russia and North America including permafrost and non-permafrost regions (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). A key requirement for Eqs. (
  <a rid="Equ4" ref-type="" href="#Equ4">4</a>) and (
  <a rid="Equ5" ref-type="" href="#Equ5">5</a>) to be valid for inferring 
  <span class="italic">D</span> using real-world soil temperature profiles is that non-conductive processes, like the latent heat associated with soil freezing, have minor impacts on the heat budget of soils at seasonal-cycle time-scale. Therefore, we examined the shape of temperature profiles at each site and selected only the sites where monthly temperature oscillations conform to sinusoidal functions, that is, to the solution (Eq. [
  <a rid="Equ4" ref-type="" href="#Equ4">4</a>]) of heat conduction (see detailed data processing and discussion in Methods). After this data-filtering, 184 sites were retained. The calculated 
  <span class="italic">D</span> value using Eq. [
  <a rid="Equ5" ref-type="" href="#Equ5">5</a>] can approximately represent the thermal diffusivity for the bulk soil in the corresponding depth interval at those selected sites. Then, we searched for emerging relationships between the observation-derived 
  <span class="italic">D</span> values and a suite of soil properties extracted from broad-scale soil maps, in order to identify the dominant factors that control 
  <span class="italic">D</span> and subsequently the propagation of temperature waves from ground surface to deeper soils. We find that SOC is the strongest predictor to explain the variability of 
  <span class="italic">D</span> among sites. Using the same method to calculate 
  <span class="italic">D</span> from CMIP5 model outputs, we find that the different parameterization of 
  <span class="italic">D</span> in these models dominates their large-scale performance in simulating today’s permafrost extent. Further with a land surface model, we show that the thermal insulation of SOC increases modelled present-day permafrost carbon stock (0–3 m depth) by 39% ( + 230 Pg C) and permafrost area by 33% (+3.4 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span>), increasing agreement with broad-scale observational data. These findings demonstrate the need to explicitly represent the coupling between SOC and soil thermal dynamics in models that are utilized to project future permafrost changes.
 </p>
</sec>
