<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Organic matter content controls soil thermal diffusivity</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We find a significant negative correlation between soil thermal diffusivity (log-transformed) and soil organic carbon density (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). This empirical result confirms that soils with more organic materials have a lower thermal diffusivity. Among all the tested soil characteristics including soil texture (fractions of sand, silt and clay)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, bulk density
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, organic carbon content per unit dry weight
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span> (g kg
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), and soil volumetric moisture content
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> (Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>), the SOC density shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> has the strongest explanatory power for 
  <span class="italic">D</span> variations among the different site-depths. Considering the interrelation between these soil properties, e.g., SOC density is negatively correlated with bulk density (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>), we conducted partial correlation analysis to test if the 
  <span class="italic">D-</span>SOC relationship persists after removing the effect of other variables. The partial correlation between 
  <span class="italic">D</span> and SOC density remains significant after controlling the other properties separately or combined (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This suggests that the impact of SOC on 
  <span class="italic">D</span> is a composite result of soil composition and structure alterations such that its correlation with 
  <span class="italic">D</span> cannot be fully accounted for by the variability in the texture- and porosity-related properties.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Relationship between soil thermal diffusivity and soil organic carbon (SOC). Thermal diffusivities (
     <span class="italic">D</span>) are derived from depth-specific measurements of monthly soil temperature from two data sets, RHST
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
     </span> (circles) and IPY
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span> (crosses), at 184 sites (Supplementary Fig. 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), grouped into four depth intervals above 3 m (see Methods). The vertical error bars indicate 25th–75th percentiles among the available years for each site-depth. SOC densities (kg C m
     <span class="sup">−3</span>) are derived from two databases, WISE
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
     </span> (blue) and NCSCD
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
     </span> (red), integrated into the same four depth intervals. The blue and red solid lines indicate the linear regression lines of log
     <sub>10</sub> (
     <span class="italic">D</span>) vs. SOC from WISE (
     <span class="italic">y</span> = −0.012 × −0.35) and from NCSCD (
     <span class="italic">y</span> = −0.016 × −0.30), respectively, with 95% confidence intervals shown in the dashed lines
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11103_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e574" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainties in the results shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> include a spatial-scale mismatch: the local soil temperature observations are not accompanied by collocated records of soil texture, moisture and organic carbon; we therefore resort to the global (WISE
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>) and regional (NCSCD
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>) databases for these soil properties, which are not fully representative for site-level observations. In addition, even at broad-scale, soil inventories bear substantial uncertainties
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. The two databases used here differ in total carbon stock by about 20% for their overlapping areas (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5ab</a>, 690 Pg C in WISE vs. 825 Pg C in NCSCD for 0–2 m depth). Both databases derive their spatial distributions by linking field data of soil profiles to global/regional soil classification maps, their accuracy depending on both the accuracy of the up-scaling maps and the representativeness of samples within each soil class. Thus, the high landscape complexity in the northern permafrost zone and limited soil profiles available from Siberia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> add to uncertainties in this region. To partly reduce this uncertainty, we excluded the site-depth data whose relative difference in SOC density between the two databases is higher than 25% (see Methods and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5c</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from the predominant role of SOC, soil moisture also affects 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, especially in dry soils where an increased soil water act as bridges to improve thermal contacts between soil particles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. A laboratory experiment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> showed that for sandy soils, 
  <span class="italic">D</span> increases rapidly with moisture content when the water content is less than 0.1–0.2 m
  <span class="sup">3</span> m
  <span class="sup">−3</span>, and then remains stable or slightly decreases; while for cohesive soils of silty and clayey texture, the variation of 
  <span class="italic">D</span> with moisture is smaller. To investigate if soil moisture can explain the spatial variability of 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, we used two data sets, the satellite-based surface soil moisture product (ESA-CCI-SM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>) and the depth-specific soil moisture simulated by a land surface model (ERA-Interim/Land
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>). Neither of them shows significant correlation with 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, possibly because the annual mean moisture contents at the sites are mostly higher than 0.2 m
  <span class="sup">3</span> m
  <span class="sup">−3</span>, a saturation level sufficient to bridge air gaps between soil grains (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a> and Supplementary Discussion). Apart from total moisture content, its phase composition also affects 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, since ice has a much higher 
  <span class="italic">D</span> than water (1.1 vs. 0.14 × 10
  <span class="sup">−6</span> m
  <span class="sup">2</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Soils in the northern permafrost region often contain abundant ground ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> that can exceed soil porosity, including segregated ice and ice wedges
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. These occurrences of excess ice beyond soil pores modify soil thermal properties and add to the heterogeneity of permafrost soils
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>, contributing to the scatter in observations shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> and Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>. Considering a potential confounding effect of ground ice on the correlation between SOC and 
  <span class="italic">D</span> shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> (as a deeper depth could feature both lower SOC density and higher ice content, as well as a higher 
  <span class="italic">D</span>), we calculated the regression for the top depth interval only (&lt;0.4 m) (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>), which is generally above the permanently frozen layer and less affected by large ice volumes. The similar results as Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> indicate that the observed strong correlation between SOC and 
  <span class="italic">D</span> is unlikely confounded by ice content.
 </p>
</sec>
