<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We found significant climatic niche divergence for all eight AIWs between the native range (the American continent) and the invasive range (China), indicating that climatic niche divergence must be considered when using ENMs to project the habitat suitability of AIWs in invasive ranges. As suggested by previous studies, regional climatic niches may differ significantly between native and invasive ranges for invasive plant species (Dellinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Early &amp; Sax, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Gallien et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Furthermore, the values of overlap between the native and invasive niches were extremely low, and the niche expansion of some species was large, for example, for 
 <italic class="italic">A. retroflexus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. Canadensis</italic>. This highlights the partial niche overlap between the native and invasive ranges and the difficulty of pre‐introduction weed risk assessment (Gallien et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Hulme, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Early &amp; Sax, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Shabani &amp; Kumar, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Table 
 <xref rid="ece32684-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). It is not sensible to predict the spread risk of AIWs in the invade regions based on the occurrence records of either native ranges or invasive ranges (Early &amp; Sax, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Furthermore, the low and moderate success of the AIWs in projections based on the native and invasive ranges, respectively, indicated that the AIWs are likely to expand more extensively into China than in their native ranges owing to more favorable habitat suitability in China (Collingham et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>; Hoffmann &amp; Sgrò, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Warren &amp; Seifert, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Beaumont et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Our results, together with those of previous studies (Gallien et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Mainali et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Shabani &amp; Kumar, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), suggest that the occurrence records of both native and invasive ranges should be used in applying ENMs for the assessment of plant invasion.
</p>
