<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of observed and model datasets</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We first examine the suitability of the available models to carry out D&amp;A by comparing the decadal-frequency variability simulated by individual model historical experiment realisations with observations. The individual monthly anomaly time series for 1906–2005 were filtered with a 5–20 year band-pass filter (see details in Supplementary material) and the standard deviation of filtered anomaly for ALLIN and the seven homogeneous regions is plotted against the linear trend of the unfiltered time series (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). The linear trend for each of the observations with its 5–95% uncertainty range shows that the two datasets are in very good agreement for all the regions except ECIND (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>). The CRU time series consistently shows much higher variability than the IITM data in all regions though the standard deviations in the two coastal regions ECIND and WCIND are more in agreement. The discrepancies are mainly due to the larger number of stations included in the IITM dataset and possibly also differences in the homogenization and area averaging/gridding procedures. We note that these differences in variability between the two datasets could have a bearing on the results of D&amp;A analysis. In terms of the variability, most model simulations are clustered around the IITM value in all the regions. The WHIND region (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2h</a>) stands out as the one region where model simulated variability is lower than observed for most models and to a lesser extent the NCIND and NWIND regions where the GISS-E2-R, GISS-E2-H and CSIRO-MK3-6.0 have lower than observed variability. Taylor Diagrams
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> comparing CRU and the different experiments and realizations against the IITM reference dataset are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> (Supplementary Information). Among the five experiments, the historicalNat simulations are least correlated with observations and the historical and historicalGHG simulations have the highest correlation with observations. The standard deviations in this figure reveal that historicalNat simulations have less than observed variability whereas historicalAA, historicalAnt, historical, and historicalGHG simulations have higher standard deviation than observations. Note that this standard deviation includes variations on all time-scales and trends in the data as they were computed using unfiltered annual mean time-series. On the whole given the small areas of the regions, the CMIP5 simulations perform quite well and the realistic simulation of low-frequency variability is encouraging for carrying out the D&amp;A analysis. While carrying out the D&amp;A analysis using individual models may give different results, we include all the models in our analysis by averaging across models (after averaging each across realisations) thereby giving each model equal weightage rather than weighting each realisation equally (see Supplementary Information for details).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison of observed and modelled linear trend of unfiltered TAS anomaly and standard deviation of 5–20 year bandpass filtered detrended TAS anomaly from CMIP5 historical simulations for the 1906–2005 period over (
     <span class="bold">a)</span> ALLIN, (
     <span class="bold">b)</span> WCIND, (
     <span class="bold">c)</span> IPIND, (
     <span class="bold">d)</span> ECIND, (
     <span class="bold">e)</span> NEIND, (
     <span class="bold">f)</span> NCIND, (
     <span class="bold">g)</span> NWIND, and (
     <span class="bold">h)</span> WHIND. The numbers inside the brackets next to the model names indicate the total number of realisations used in this study. The trend uncertainty (5–95%) for observations was calculated as in ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_27185_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e360" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to examine the sensitivity of our results to D&amp;A methodology, we used three variants of regression based optimal fingerprint approaches in our analysis of TAS over the Indian region - Ordinary Least Squares (OLS)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, Total Least Squares (TLS)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, and Regularized Optimal Fingerprinting (ROF)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. In all three methods we regress the observations on to the model simulated signals. We calculate the scaling factors for time-series of individual regions and for a combined “All Region” where we retain the spatial information from the seven homogeneous zones (See Supplementary Information for further details). Note that “All Region” is different from ALLIN we have used previously to denote a spatial average over India. We estimate these regressions separately for three time periods (the 50-year periods 1906–1955 and 1956–2005, and the full 100-year period 1906–2005) and two averaging time-lengths (non-overlapping decadal and pentadal averages).
 </p>
</sec>
