<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the problems of attributing changes at regional scales, numerous studies provide evidence of an anthropogenic influence on surface temperature at continental and subcontinental scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Temperature changes over the Indian subcontinent during the 20th Century have been documented
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> but have not been subject to formal D&amp;A analysis. The Indian subcontinent contains many sub-regions with vastly different climatic conditions and each of these have witnessed changes to different extents. It is critical for the mitigation and adaptation policy responses of a large developing economy with a population of more than a billion to be informed of the extent to which anthropogenic and natural factors have caused the observed climate changes. In this study we attempt to detect statistically significant changes in surface air temperature (TAS) over sub-regions of India and when detected, quantify contributions of natural (NAT) and anthropogenic (ANT) forcings using formal D&amp;A methods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. We also examine whether the anthropogenic forcings due to Greenhouse Gases (GHG) can be isolated from Other Anthropogenic (OA) factors. We use climate model simulations that include individual and combinations of forcings as prescribed in the standard experimental protocols of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase-5 (CMIP5)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. We also use two publicly available long-term datasets of observed temperature over India; i) the CRU-3.22 gridded temperature dataset (0.5° × 0.5° resolution) available from 1901 to 2013
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>, and ii) a monthly mean temperature time-series from 1901 to 2007 for seven “homogeneous temperature zones” obtained from the Indian Institute of Tropical Meteorology (IITM)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The IITM dataset includes observations from many more stations than the CRU dataset over the Indian region. The Indian region (ALLIN) is further divided into seven homogenous temperature zones West Coast (WCIND), East Coast (ECIND), Interior Peninsula(IPIND), North East (NEIND), North Central(NCIND), North West (NWIND), and Western Himalaya (WHIND) based on geographical, topographical and climatological features. The CRU data is regridded to a 1° × 1° grid and masked over each homogeneous temperature zone (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1i</a>) before being spatially averaged to produce a monthly time-series analogous to the IITM data. The monthly mean TAS data from the piControl’, ‘historical’, ‘historicalNat’, ‘historicalAnt’, ‘historicalGHG’, and ‘historicalAA’ experiments were obtained from 7 models in the CMIP5 database and treated in the same way as the CRU data (see Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> and details of data processing in Supplementary Information). Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a–h</a> shows the annual mean anomaly time series for each of the 8 regions from the two observed datasets as well as the historical and historicalNat simulations (5–95% confidence intervals shown in pink and light-blue shading respectively). The historical and historicalNat simulations are similar for most of the record but diverge from each other after about 1990. Clearly seen in both observations and in the model simulations are the sharp decreases in temperature resulting from volcanic eruptions of the 20
  <span class="sup">th</span> Century.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Annual Mean Temperature Anomaly (from 1906–2005 mean) in the observed datasets; IITM (black) and CRU (gray), and in the historical (red) and historicalNat (light-blue) simulations with their 5–95% confidence bounds (calculated as in Jones 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>. ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
     </span>) for (
     <span class="bold">a)</span> All India (ALLIN), and the individual homogeneous zones (
     <span class="bold">b)</span> West Coast (WCIND), (
     <span class="bold">c)</span> Interior Peninsula (IPIND), (
     <span class="bold">d)</span> East Coast (ECIND), (
     <span class="bold">e)</span> North East (NEIND), (
     <span class="bold">f)</span> North Central (NCIND), (
     <span class="bold">g)</span> North West (NWIND), and (
     <span class="bold">h)</span> Western Himalaya (WHIND). The vertical lines in panels a-h indicate timings of major volcanic eruptions during the 1906–2005 period.The demarcation of homogeneous temperature zones (based on ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
     </span>) is shown in (
     <span class="bold">i</span>). The map was generated using UVCDAT 2.12 (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://uvcdat.llnl.gov/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://uvcdat.llnl.gov/</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_27185_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e297" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
