<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crop models</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorghum and millet are the two main staple crops of sub-Saharan West Africa (59% of the total cereal production over the 2000–2009 period, on average; FAOSTAT data). The annual yields of millet and sorghum derived from two different process-based crop models were used. One was SARRA-H
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, a model with a detailed process-based approach for phenology and carbon assimilation, and another was the CYGMA model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, with less details on water and carbon processes but including technological improvements. Using these two models with different modelling concepts under similar climate change conditions allows assessment of the uncertainty of the simulated yield response, as different parameterizations of physical and biological processes in crop models play a critical role in assessing and simulating yield responses to future climate change and adaptations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. Indeed, a similar change in terms of temperature, rainfall and/or radiation is likely to affect crop yields differently in the two models (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>); thus, consensus in the sign or in the amplitude of climate change may strengthen the confidence of the results.
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summary of the main processes affecting crop yields under climate change simulations framework in the two crop models SARRA-H and CYGMA. Details on the processes can be found in Kouressy 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
     </span> and Iizumi and 
     <span class="italic">et al.</span>
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
     </span>, respectively.
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>SARRA-H</th>
      <th>CYGMA</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Temperature acts on plant development rates through the concept of thermal time</td>
      <td>Crop development is modelled using the growing degree days. The crop thermal requirement varies by crop and location.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Temperature has an effect on maintenance respiration</td>
      <td>Temperature affects potential and actual evapotranspiration rates. The daily increment of leaf area and yield are stressed when the actual evapotranspiration is lower than its potential value.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>No cold/heat stress</td>
      <td>Each of heat and cold stresses are modelled as a function of daily mean temperature and used to compute the daily actual increment of leaf area and yield.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Water deficit affects plant transpiration and carbon assimilation</td>
      <td>Water deficit defined as a ratio between actual and potential evapotranspiration rate is used to compute the daily actual increment of leaf area and yield.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Rainfall triggers sowing dates, and water stress can lead to sowing failures</td>
      <td>Sowing date is determined according to 10-yr average temperature and moisture conditions. Sowing date is updated every year in the model. A crop-specific look-up table is used to derive the sowing date under a given climate condition.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>No nitrogen stress</td>
      <td>Stress associated with nitrogen deficit is modelled as a function of annual nitrogen application rate.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Solar radiation impacts potential assimilation rates through the intercepted, photosynthetically active radiation</td>
      <td>Solar radiation affects daily potential increment of crop total biomass. After the modelled heading date, the CYGMA model starts calculating the daily increment of yield based on the intercepted photosynthetically active radiation, CO
       <sub>2</sub> fertilization and fraction of the increment of the total biomass allocated to the harvestable part of a crop.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>No CO
       <sub>2</sub> effect
      </td>
      <td>The CO
       <sub>2</sub> fertilization effect is considered. The radiation-use efficiency changes depending on CO
       <sub>2</sub> concentration.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Cultivar choice</td>
      <td>The total thermal requirement of a crop that represents the cultivar’s characteristics on crop duration changes depending on the 10-yr average temperature condition and is updated every year in the model.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>No technology improvements</td>
      <td>The nitrogen application rate increases with changes in per capita GDP and per capita agricultural area. The crop’s tolerance to suboptimal conditions (nitrogen deficit, heat, cold, water deficit, and water excess) increases with changes in per capita GDP, GDP share of agriculture value added and total R&amp;D expenditure (these are used to calculate agricultural knowledge stock), which represents the use of high-yielding technology and management.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Only rainfed condition is assumed</td>
      <td>Yields in rainfed and irrigated conditions are separately simulated, and their area-weighted average is then computed. Because there is almost no irrigated area in West Africa, the millet and sorghum yields in West Africa simulated by the CYGMA model represent those in the rainfed condition.</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SARRA-H model was originally developed to simulate crops in dry tropics, such as millet and sorghum
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. The inputs to the model are daily weather data, latitude, soil characteristics (depth, soil water capacity) and crop management (sowing density and depth, sowing date). The crop model estimates attainable yield under water-limited conditions by computing the soil water balance, evapotranspiration, phenology, assimilation, and biomass partitioning (see ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> for a detailed review of the model concepts). The water balance simulates runoff using a rain event empirical threshold of 20 mm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, soil evaporation, storage, deep drainage, transpiration and soil surface evaporation. Water stress is evaluated from the fraction of transpirable soil water according to Sinclair and Ludlow
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, which acts as a reducing factor on plant transpiration and carbon assimilation based on FAO guidelines. Carbon assimilation and partitioning is explicitly simulated in the model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> with assimilation rates depending on solar radiation and water stress and with maintenance respiration depending on temperature. Daily temperatures are also involved in the computation of thermal time, which serves, on an additive basis, to calculate the progress of developmental processes. The phenology of the model is based on a simplified concept of successive phenological stages that have constant (genotypic) thermal duration. The photoperiod sensitivity routine is not activated in this study. SARRA-H was calibrated against local agronomic-trial data and on-farm surveys conducted in eight contrasted sites in terms of climate and agricultural practices in West Africa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. These data were used to define the varieties and the parameters representing management practice in the crop model. SARRA-H showed good performance in simulating crop yield variability in West Africa compared to FAO data, even if it tends to overestimate the mean yield
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, the CYGMA model is a global gridded crop model and initially covers four major crops (maize, soybean, rice and spring wheat); it is modified in this study to include millet and sorghum. In the CYGMA model, the development of the crop growth stage is computed as a fraction of the accumulated growing degree days relative to the crop thermal requirements. Leaf area expansion and senescence are computed according to the fraction of the growing season using the prescribed shape of the leaf area index curve. The yields are computed from the photosynthetically active radiation intercepted by the crop canopy, the radiation-use efficiency, the CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization on the efficiency and the fraction of total biomass increments allocated to the harvestable component. The soil water balance submodel and the snow cover submodel are used to calculate the actual evapotranspiration (although no snow cover occurs in the studied area). Five different stress types – nitrogen (N) deficits, heat, cold, water deficits and water excesses – are considered. The most dominant stress type for a day decreases the daily potential increment of the leaf area and yield. All of the stress types except N deficits are functions of daily weather conditions. The stress associated with the N deficit is modelled as a function of the annual N application rate. The crop’s tolerance to these stresses increases as the knowledge stock increases. The knowledge stock is an economic indicator derived as the sum of the governmental annual research and development (R&amp;D) expenditures in the agricultural sector since 1961 with a certain obsolescence rate, and it represents the average agronomic technology and management level among farmers in the country. More details on modelling are available in the Supplementary Note described in the Supplementary Information of Iizumi 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CYGMA model uses socioeconomic variables (such as per capita GDP, per capita agricultural area, agricultural research and development expenditure) as the model inputs in addition to physical variables (e.g., daily weather and plant-extractable water holding capacity of soil), enabling the model to simulate yield trends associated with technological improvements. This is a unique characteristic of the CYGMA model. The daily mean, maximum and minimum temperatures, precipitation, solar radiation, relative humidity and wind speed are used as the weather inputs. For this study, the CYGMA model was calibrated for millet and sorghum using the global dataset of actual and potential yields in 2000
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, as was done for the four crops in earlier work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. In short, the sensitivity of the daily increment of leaf area index and yield to each of five different stress factors (N deficit, heat, cold, water deficit and water excess) was determined using the relationship among the yield gap (the ratio between actual and potential yields) in 2000, knowledge stock in 2000 and simulated average growing season stress factor in 1996–2005. The crop coefficient values for millet and sorghum used in this study are available in Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>. The CYGMA model operates globally for millet and sorghum, similar to the four crops previously modelled; therefore, the simulated yields in West Africa were used for this study.
 </p>
</sec>
