<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical, factual and counterfactual crop simulations</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The crop model simulation experiment has two purposes (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>). First, climate observation data are used to force the crop models to compare simulated crop yields with observed crop yields and check the performance of SARRA-H and CYGMA on the historical period. The two crop models are run using the same historical forcing dataset S14FD in West Africa (20°W to 15°E; 4°N to 18°N) for the period 1961–2012. Second, factual and counterfactual climate simulations are used to force the crop models to reproduce the crop yields under climate with (factual) and without (counterfactual) human influences. The comparison between the factual and counterfactual crop yield simulations enables the quantification of the effect of human influence on historical crop yields as simulated by the two crop models.
  <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The crop simulation design.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Climate forcing dataset</th>
      <th>CO
       <sub>2</sub>
      </th>
      <th>Crop model</th>
      <th>Purpose of simulations</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>S14FD retrospective meteorological forcing dataset
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td rowspan="2">Historical (317 ppm in 1961 to 389 ppm in 2010)</td>
      <td rowspan="3">CYGMA and SARRA-H</td>
      <td>Comparison between simulated crop yield and reported yield data</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Bias-corrected MRI-AGCM3.2 simulations with human influence on climate systems
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>Factual crop yield simulation</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Bias-corrected MRI-AGCM3.2 simulations without human influence on climate systems
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>287 ppm (the level of the year 1850)</td>
      <td>Counterfactual crop yield simulation</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SARRA-H simulations include four sets of parameters to capture the diversity of crop management in West Africa. They aim to reproduce the behaviour of two representative varieties of millet and two varieties of sorghum that differ mainly by the length of the growth cycle– a short duration crop (approximately 90 days) and a long duration crop (approximately 120 days) that are both insensitive to the photoperiod – and two levels of fertilization rate by modifying the biomass conversion ratio to a sub-optimal level and a better level to simulate, respectively, a low and a moderate fertilization rate. Here, we run the model separately using each of these four sets of parameters and average the resulting yield with even weights year by year, as in an earlier study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, since no information is available to determine weights for the individual management conditions. The available water holding capacity of the soil (between wilting point and field capacity) was set to 100 mm m
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, and the upper limit of the rooting depth was fixed at 1800 mm (see more details in ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>). The sowing date was generated by the model and defined as the day when the simulated plant available water in the soil was greater than 10 mm at the end of the day, followed by a 20-day period during which crop establishment was monitored
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. The juvenile stage of the crop was considered to have failed, triggering automatic re-sowing if the simulated daily total biomass decreased during 11 out of 20 days. Simulations were performed without any irrigation since most crop systems are rainfed (93% of all agricultural land in Sub-Saharan Africa; FAOSTAT data), and to our knowledge, irrigation is never used for pearl millet and sorghum in West Africa.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CYGMA model required a 60-yr long soil moisture spin-up (1958–1960 × 20 times) before crop simulation. Annual nitrogen application rates for the individual crops were parameterized as a function of per capita GDP and per capita agricultural area, with the assumption that an increase in average farm income and an increase in land scarcity lead to increased fertilizer use. The use of improved varieties and corresponding management was parameterized using the agricultural knowledge stock, which is an economic indicator to represent technological improvements. These socioeconomic data were obtained from the World Bank and FAOSTAT databases. The sowing dates of the individual crops in 2000 in the CYGMA model follow those reported in the Monthly Irrigated and Rainfed Crop Areas around the year 2000 (MIRCA2000) dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> but change dynamically according to the long-term temperature and moisture conditions calculated in the model. The extent of harvested area and the fractions of irrigated and rainfed areas in 2000 were obtained from the M3-Crops dataset and MIRCA2000 dataset, respectively. We also used the Historical Irrigation Information (HID) dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> to take the annual growth rates of irrigation-equipped area (if any) into account. However, in West Africa, there are almost no irrigated areas. Therefore, the crop yields in West Africa simulated by the CYGMA model represent those in rainfed conditions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Factual and non-warming counterfactual crop simulations were performed using the two crop models with the 100 factual and counterfactual ensemble climate simulations as the inputs to the crop models to estimate the impacts of historical climate change on crop yields. The climatic variables used as the model inputs include daily mean, maximum and minimum 2-m air temperatures, precipitation, downward shortwave radiation flux, relative humidity and 10-m wind speed. The ET
  <sub>0</sub> estimation is calculated by the Penman-Monteith FAO56 equation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> in the SARRA-H model and a variant of this equation in the CYGMA model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
