<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts of historical human activities on the regional climate of West Africa</div>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human influence has strongly modified the annual mean temperature in West Africa, with a regional warming depicted since the 1950s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). We found a difference of approximately 1 °C when comparing the average temperature of the last decade 2000–2009 between the factual and counterfactual climate simulations (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). Although this warming is simulated all over West Africa, it is more pronounced in the north and central Sahel and in the Sahara (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1a</a>). This is certainly the most robust change, with all statistical tests showing significant values (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). In addition, the factual climate simulation, which includes human influence, is able to more accurately reproduce the mean and the variability of the observed annual temperatures derived from the CRU dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> than the counterfactual climate simulation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The correlation between the observed and simulated time series of annual temperature reaches 0.92 with the factual simulation, while it falls to 0.75 with the counterfactual simulation. Moreover, the bias between the simulated and observed annual temperatures is −0.9 °C with the counterfactual simulation, which is colder than CRU data, while the bias is only +0.1 °C with the factual simulation. This comparison provides clear evidence of the reality of anthropogenic climate change in West Africa. The factual and counterfactual climate simulations significantly differ from each other. For instance, an important increase in the number of very hot days in the factual climate simulation was found (the number of hot days increases eight-fold in the last decade; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a> and Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). This increase is more pronounced in the north of West Africa (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1c</a>). While the impacts of human activities are particularly evident on regional surface temperature, the impacts on rainfall are less clear. The model is able to accurately reproduce the decadal variations of annual rainfall with the wet years during the 1950s, the droughts of the late 1970s and 1980s and the recovery of rainfall, which starts in the 1990s compared to observations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>). However, the simulated annual rainfall time series in the factual and in the counterfactual simulations are almost identical, showing a similar correlation with observation (R = 0.54 and R = 0.56 for factual and counterfactual simulation, respectively) and no significant change in the last decade (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). The changes are hardly or not significant when we consider the number of rainy days or the onset of the rains, which neither of which seems to be modified with the human activities in the climate model. However, more significant changes are detected for rainfall intensity and in heavy rainfall in the Sahel over the last decade, which can be deemed the impacts of human activities (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>; Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). This is particularly clear when we consider the number of rainy days exceeding 50 mm/day (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>), where we found a significant increase of 27.7% in the last decades between the factual and the counterfactual simulations.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ensemble mean of simulated counterfactual (thin black) plus standard deviation of the 100 members (grey envelope) and factual climate condition (red) of mean surface temperature (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), annual rainfall (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), number of very hot days (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) and number of very heavy rainy days (
     <span class="bold">d</span>). See Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> for the definition of the climate indices. The thick black line represents the observed annual mean temperature (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and annual rainfall (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) from CRU data. All values are shown on average across West Africa (20°W to 15°E; 4°N to 18°N).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_49167_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1420" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>User-relevant indices of climate in 2000–2009 with mean counterfactual climate condition and factual climate condition, differences between factual and counterfactual climate simulations (relative differences for all indices except for mean temperature and onset day). All values are shown on average across West Africa (20°W to 15°E; 4°N to 18°N). One (two) star(s) indicates that the difference in the ensemble mean is significant at the 1% (0.1) level. The three columns on the right indicate the number of the 100 runs that pass a Student’s test or a Kolmogorov test, which agree with the sign of the difference of the ensemble mean at the 5% significance level.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>User-relevant Indices</th>
      <th>Counterfactual</th>
      <th>Factual</th>
      <th>Difference</th>
      <th>Student t-Test</th>
      <th>KS Test</th>
      <th>Sign Agreement</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Annual Mean Temperature</td>
      <td>26.9</td>
      <td>28.0</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">1.0**</span>
      </td>
      <td>100</td>
      <td>100</td>
      <td>100</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Annual Rainfall</td>
      <td>974.8</td>
      <td>983.9</td>
      <td>0.9%</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>62</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Annual Rainy Days</td>
      <td>82.1</td>
      <td>82.6</td>
      <td>0.7%*</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>64</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Heavy Rainfall Events</td>
      <td>6.8</td>
      <td>7.6</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">11.6%**</span>
      </td>
      <td>32</td>
      <td>10</td>
      <td>99</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Very Heavy Rainfall Events</td>
      <td>1.7</td>
      <td>2.2</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">27.7%**</span>
      </td>
      <td>85</td>
      <td>43</td>
      <td>100</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Rainfall Intensity</td>
      <td>14.4</td>
      <td>15.0</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">3.9%**</span>
      </td>
      <td>25</td>
      <td>11</td>
      <td>94</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Very Hot Days</td>
      <td>0.0</td>
      <td>0.1</td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">841.0%**</span>
      </td>
      <td>82</td>
      <td>83</td>
      <td>100</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Onset Day</td>
      <td>160.2</td>
      <td>160.8</td>
      <td>0.6*</td>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>0</td>
      <td>66</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
