<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Heat distribution (and its associated temperature variation) is important in both the Earth and the human body and our understanding and measurements of it need to be improved in the interest of human health (since human thermal homeostasis is largely dependent on environmental temperature). In this light, recognition that ocean heat uptake plays a key role in modulating human-caused global surface warming has been one of the many valuable ancillary benefits of research aiming to understand the 1998–2013 hiatus. Identifying and accounting for errors in ocean heat uptake estimations has been vital in this improved understanding ( 
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fyfe 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>) and will be instrumental in improving the accuracy of future climate predictions. For instance, climate models accounting for these recent advances suggest a transition to a positive phase of the Interdecadal Pacific Oscillation, which will increase the warming rate of global surface temperature ( 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hawkins 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thoma 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>). Similarly to climate studies, thermal physiology research employing calorimetric methods has shown that temperature measurements at a single region of the body’s core do not (on average) reflect whole-body thermal strain [( 
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flouris &amp; Cheung, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenny 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenny 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meade 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stapleton 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stapleton 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Webb, 1986</xref>), including reviews ( 
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Benzinger 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 1961
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taylor 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Webb, 1995</xref>)]. In addition to their limited accuracy, such measurements contain a significant time lag, which makes them less effective for scientific purposes and potentially problematic when used in health-related settings. Indeed, core temperature readings are notorious for responding with delays of 10–30 minutes ( 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenny &amp; Jay, 2013</xref>), even when the human body undergoes extreme discomfort, such as a sudden passive immersion in 12°C water ( 
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flouris &amp; Cheung, 2009</xref>). Interestingly, a similar time lag exists in the Earth’s warming rate phenomenon, since 80% of the heat added to the climate system is being taken up by the ocean ( 
 <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC, 2014</xref>). As a result, even if greenhouse gas concentrations were to drastically reduce, the planet would continue to warm for many decades ( 
 <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC, 2014</xref>).
</p>
