<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12803-sec-0016" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concluding remarks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the foundational studies of local adaptation demonstrated adaptation to elevation in plant populations in the California Sierra Nevada region (Clausen et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0014">1941</a>). Since Clausen et al.'s landmark study, we have learned that climate adaptation in plants is very common, although not ubiquitous (Blanquart, Kaltz, Nuismer, Gandon, &amp; Ebert, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0009">2013</a>; Hereford et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0054">2009</a>). We have also learned that adaptation can be rapid (e.g., Franks et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0040">2007</a>) and that it can involve Mendelian and non‐Mendelian (i.e., epigenetic) inheritance (Feng, Jacobsen, &amp; Reik, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0030">2010</a>; Lynch &amp; Walsh, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0071">1998</a>) of few or many genes (Anderson, Willis, &amp; Mitchell‐Olds, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0005">2011</a>; Bradshaw &amp; Schemske, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0011">2003</a>; Fournier‐Level et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0033">2011</a>). However, since Clausen et al., human‐caused climates are changing rapidly, and now, there is great concern about potential range shifts and whether plant species can respond through adaptation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The finding that there can be a rapid adaptive response to an extreme climate event across the range of a habitat specialist plant contributes to our understanding of plant species distributions and potential persistence under climate change. Resurrecting older genotypes and comparing them to contemporary populations is gaining fast recognition as an important way to empirically test the effects and ramifications of climate change (Franks et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0037">2008</a>, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0038">2018</a>), but few studies have done so. We encourage participation in efforts such as Project Baseline (Etterson et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0028">2016</a>) and other seed bank programs to facilitate further research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate models predict an increasingly hot and dry future in California, with temperature increases of 1.5–1.8°C by 2,100 and substantial reductions in precipitation (Ackerly, Cornwell, Weiss, Flint, &amp; Flint, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0001">2015</a>; Cayan, Maurer, Dettinger, Tyree, &amp; Hayhoe, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0013">2008</a>). Forecasts also predict a greater proportion of precipitation falling as rain rather than snow (Cayan et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0013">2008</a>), which will compress timing of water availability. Thus, there will likely continue to be strong directional selection for traits and phenotypes that correspond with drought tolerance or escape (Etterson &amp; Mazer, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0029">2016</a>; Franks et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0040">2007</a>; Jump &amp; Peñuelas, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0060">2005</a>; Schneider &amp; Mazer, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0093">2016</a>). Importantly, although we found evidence for adaptive response, we also found evidence for reduced phenotypic variation. Thus, as climate continues to become hotter and drier, and intense directional selection continues, subsequent reductions in genetic variation (i.e., additive genetic variation) may make adaptation increasingly difficult (Anderson et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0004">2012</a>; Jump &amp; Peñuelas, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0060">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future investigations into selection for adaptive genotypes will be necessary to improve our understanding of climate adaptation in wild systems. Future work could expand to measure performance under various levels of simulated drought and to test for interactive effects of habitat characteristics (i.e., soil type, soil moisture, community composition, etc.). Research is also needed to investigate not only the magnitude of climate stress, but also its duration (i.e., consecutive events) to understand how different populations of a species range can and may respond to stress and selection, including peripheral populations. Finally, research on the specific mechanisms of adaptive response (i.e., gene action, epigenetics, maternal provisioning, etc.) to strong and rapid climate stress in field conditions is greatly needed.</p>
</sec>
