<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12803-sec-0014" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rapid, contemporary evolution</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the resurrection approach, we found compelling evidence that phenological traits shifted in an adaptive manner during the intense drought, and this may partially explain how the species range of this plant has remained stable over recent decades (Sexton &amp; Dickman, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0095">2016</a>), whereas other species are exhibiting range shifts due to severe drought and climate change (Crockett &amp; Westerling, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0020">2017</a>; Serra‐Diaz et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0094">2015</a>). We documented a significant reduction in time to emergence that would be adaptive in hotter and drier climates, accompanied by a reduction in variance in emergence time in the drought generation. Drought generation plants generally emerged earlier, and subsequently achieved greater height, biomass, and fruit mass during the experiment. There was no difference between generations in SLA (discussed below), and in contrast to emergence patterns, drought generation plants generally flowered later than pre‐drought plants and did not show differences in variance between generations in these traits. Nevertheless, flowering time is a strongly differentiated trait among populations (discussed below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two lines of evidence suggest that the observed differences in the drought generation may have been adaptive. First, the faster seed emergence observed in the drought generation is consistent with field experiments with this species in which earlier emergence in seedlings translated into greater fitness under drought stress (Sexton et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0097">2011</a>). The evolutionary changes in phenology did not vary by elevation (i.e., no significant generation by elevation interaction), although populations varied greatly in their responses across the range (Figure 
  <a rid="eva12803-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12803-fig-0002">2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, variance in some phenological and morphological traits was reduced in the drought generation, suggesting natural selection or bottleneck events may have occurred. Rapid increases in temperature have been shown to be associated with a reduction in genetic variation for traits affected by climate (Jump &amp; Peñuelas, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0060">2005</a>). With the exception of days to first flower, all traits had reduced variance in the drought generation (Table 
  <a rid="eva12803-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#eva12803-sup-0001">S4</a>); however, only days to emergence exhibited significant variance reduction (Table 
  <a rid="eva12803-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#eva12803-sup-0001">S3</a>). By comparison, SLA, an important trait for drought tolerance but not necessarily drought avoidance (Ackerly et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0002">2002</a>), was not found to vary significantly by population or generation. However, drought generation plants generally flowered later, opposite to emergence responses, suggesting that flowering time may have been under selection, but in a direction consistent with greater drought tolerance rather than avoidance. Early flowering is indicative of drought escape in annual plants because early flowering allows plants to complete their life cycle before the onset of drought. However, late flowering might potentially indicate drought tolerance or at least a strategy of growing more slowly and conserving resources during drought. Franks (
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0036">2011</a>) found that 
  <span class="italic">Brassica rapa</span> plants that flowered early had low water use efficiency, whereas plants that flowered later had greater water use efficiency, indicating greater drought tolerance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above changes in phenotypic variance might potentially reflect changes in additive genetic variance, since genetic variance and phenotypic variance are often related, but this was not possible to determine from this study. A change in phenotypic variance is still notable, since this is a change in the population and one that could potentially influence the results of future selection. Reductions in trait variance could also be due to bottlenecks (i.e., genetic drift) and due to reduced population sizes under drought conditions. However, if the observed changes were due mainly to genetic drift, we would predict random trait mean shifts in adaptive and nonadaptive directions and reductions in variance across all or most traits. Instead, variance reductions align with trait shifts related to drought avoidance and are generally consistent among populations. Although the resurrection approach alone only provides evidence for evolution, rather than providing the mechanism (Franks et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0038">2018</a>), the idea that this phenotypic shift was caused by selection rather than by drift is probably the most reasonable assumption. Drift would be expected to take much longer to produce a significant phenotypic change (Conner &amp; Hartl, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0016">2004</a>), and drift alone is even less likely if the direction of change is generally consistent among populations and if emergence time is controlled by multiple genes (which would be expected to drift independently and not produce a strong directional change). Thus, although genetic drift may have contributed to evolutionary shifts between generations, we consider selection to have been a more likely agent of change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether the observed differences between generations were partially the outcome of adaptive transgenerational plasticity is an open question. Nevertheless, evidence for such “anticipatory” parental effects is weak based on prior studies (Uller, Nakagawa, &amp; English, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0106">2013</a>). Enhanced offspring quality through increased seed mass is one common maternal effect in plants (Roach &amp; Wulff, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0087">1987</a>). However, we controlled for maternal family seed mass effects in our models, and the results of the next‐generation growth chamber experiment confirm that earlier emergence in the drought generation is likely to be a genetic effect. Although we found evidence for reduced variances perhaps due to natural selection, these still may have been influenced by maternally derived epigenetic changes (Germain et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0044">2013</a>). For self‐fertilizing plants such as 
  <span class="italic">M. laciniatus</span>, broad‐sense heritability, which includes maternal effects, is the most relevant agent of adaptive potential (Conner &amp; Hartl, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0016">2004</a>). Thus, although the above effects are conflated in field‐collected seeds, examining first‐generation traits in highly selfing species is potentially as or more important than examining subsequent generation traits for understanding realistic rapid adaptive response. Moreover, our results are consistent with other genetically based adaptive patterns in this species (Sexton et al., 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0097">2011</a>), supporting the hypothesis that the observed trait shifts are genetically based and are adaptive under drought. In the Sexton et al. (
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0097">2011</a>) study, 
  <span class="italic">M. laciniatus</span> seedling emergence was shown to be under strong natural selection in the field in a fast‐drying, range‐edge environment experiment. A future aim is to understand to what extent epigenetic effects on gene expression or changes in allele frequencies caused the adaptive patterns observed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seed quality and longevity is known to decline with seed age (Harrington, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0051">1972</a>), and we attempted to account for this in our study. Seed quality could also affect results if a nonrandom portion of seeds do not germinate, and thus, their correlated traits are not represented; that is to say, the “invisible fraction” effect (Grafen, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0046">1988</a>; Weis, 
  <a rid="eva12803-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12803-bib-0109">2018</a>). The cut tests coupled with results from the postsown GA group, in which nearly all cells that were treated germinated within a few days, rule out seed death as important influences in our study. Storage effects may have influenced germination results since emergence was higher in the refreshed generation in growth chambers, although growth chamber conditions were better for all populations (i.e., day length, temperature). To our knowledge, no published study has applied postsown GA treatment as a test of viability. In light of our findings, this technique could be a useful tool for studies diagnosing the above issues or investigating seed banks.
 </p>
</sec>
