<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is increasing evidence that, similar to commercial fisheries, recreational fisheries can be prone to severe declines and collapse [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref013">13</a>]. However, data limitations make it a challenge to conduct stock assessments and quantify resilience in these recreational fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref061">61</a>]. Using the data-limited bonefish catch-and-release fishery of Florida Bay, this study illustrates the utility of using different catch indices derived from FDD (e.g., catch, species richness associated to the catch, proportion of positive trips) to reconstruct historical abundance trends and determine, with a certain degree of confidence, major shifts in the trajectory of catch time-series. Analyses of bonefish catches in ENP guide reports pointed to a decline in bonefish catch and to changes in bonefishing effort in Florida Bay since the early 1980s. From these data, we identified three phases in the bonefish recreational fishery over the past 40 years: 1980–1988, 1989–1999, and 2000–2014. Bonefish catches in guided trips were increasing and highest in the first phase, decreasing with some stability in the second phase, and lowest in the third phase, with a shift to a declining trend between 1995 and 1999. Trends in the proportion of a bonefish positive trip and catching success when bonefish were targeted by guided trips followed the trends in catch, indicating declines and suggesting major population changes and/or shifts in bonefishing effort dynamics (i.e., fishing allocation time, spatial distribution, incorporation of alternative fisheries) starting in 1999–2000.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite their utility in quantifying and assessing changes in the abundance of fishery species, as illustrated by this study and others, it is worth nothing that FDD are subject to various biases and limitations. For example, the number of reports was limited in some years, especially at the beginning of the time-series, which could have produced anomalies in the CPUE and affected our assessment of temporal trends. In addition, FDD are subject to potential biases since they are inherently affected by fishing dynamics and angler behavior, which may cause CPUE to deviate from abundance, resulting at times in spurious inferences [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref062">62</a>]. Following best practices in working with FDD, we standardized the catch data [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref047">47</a>] by using a series GAMs that accounted for variation in temporal (e.g., month, season), spatial (e.g., fishing areas), catch structure associated with shifting tactics (e.g., PCO axes), and effort dynamics (e.g., hours fished, number of fishermen). These standardizations allow for extracting underlining patterns in FDD since they account for variation in fishing behavior and other known sources of variability [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref015">15</a>]. The GAMs, however, did not include other possible variables that may have influenced fishing effort such as the socioeconomic and other environmental factors conditioning fishing trips (e.g., gas and market prices, regional economic indicators, storms etc.), also shown to be important, but more rarely accounted for [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref046">46</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, the concordance among the FDD indices of catch, species richness and the proportion of positive trips provided confidence in a pattern of a declining trend for bonefish in Florida Bay starting in the late 1990s. Importantly, these results agree with findings and angler concerns previously reported [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref033">33</a>]. The only other FDD study of bonefish in the region, which used tournament records in the Florida Keys to develop an index of bonefish abundance, showed a declining trend between 1997 and 2010, which the authors attributed to increasing fishing pressure [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref023">23</a>]. In a survey of fishing guides (n = 171), Larkin et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref002">2</a>] reported that half of the respondents surveyed in 2001 perceived a decline in the bonefish population in the Florida Keys. In a follow-up survey of the most experienced bonefish guides (n = 64), Frezza and Clem [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref033">33</a>] reported a 78% decline in bonefish abundance in Florida Bay, higher than reported for any other area in South Florida, particularly for the period 2001–2012. Thus, our study contributes additional resolution to the dynamics of bonefish populations in South Florida, emphasizing a declining trend starting in the late 1990s.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We hypothesized that the pattern and timing of decline documented in our analyses could result from four key mechanisms: 1) shifts in fishing effort and angler behavior; 2) fishing pressure effects (i.e., indirect or direct effects of fishing mortality); 3) habitat/environmental effects; and 4) multiple interactions among these factors [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref063">63</a>]. Previous work has indicated that major shifts in catch similar to the one observed in the bonefish FDD may be associated with changes in fishing behavior and effort dynamics [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref013">13</a>]. For instance, sharp declines in catch can occur after giving-up density is reached; that is, the density or stock size that causes anglers to start abandoning the fishery resource [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref004">4</a>]. Indeed, the significant increase in species richness associated with the bonefish catch after 1999 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0184776.g002" href="#pone.0184776.g002">Fig 2b</a>) suggests that fishing and effort dynamics shifted as bonefish catches and positive trips declined. Similarly, Frezza and Clem [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref033">33</a>] reported a 37% decrease in effort over time by guides interviewed in their survey. However, when looking at the records that reported targeting bonefish, the success of catch also declined after 2000, suggesting that the reduction in catch was mostly associated with changes in abundance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are numerous examples of how fishing pressure can directly influence the abundance and diversity of exploited species [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref064">64</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref066">66</a>], including among recreational fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref067">67</a>]. For bonefish, previous studies had reported relatively low fishing mortality for South Florida [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref068">68</a>], although higher mortality has been observed in the Bahamas due to post-release predation by sharks and physiological effects (up to 40%; [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref069">69</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref071">71</a>]). Nevertheless, based on two stock assessment models (i.e., a stochastic age-independent continuous population model and a catch-free assessment model), Larkin [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref023">23</a>] estimated an increasing trend in fishing mortality since the mid-1980s in Florida Bay and the Keys, and suggested that even relatively low mortality could reduce bonefish stock abundance if effort and releases were high. The 1999 breakpoint observed in our FDD coincides with the point where annual mortality estimated by Larkin [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref023">23</a>] surpassed 10%. Furthermore, for long-lived fish species such as bonefish (19–21 years, [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref031">31</a>]), relatively low mortality may reduce stock abundance by compounding over time (i.e., accumulating and intensifying), resulting in non-linear declines [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref067">67</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a challenge, given the current data and models, to determine whether changes in bonefish populations may have occurred due to fishing mortality or recruitment effects or a combination of the two. Stocks can become susceptible to depletion through local recruitment overfishing (i.e., a fishing level that reduces recruitment of the exploitable stock) and/or lack of regional connectivity strength (i.e., depletion of a regional stock; [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref072">72</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref073">73</a>]). In Florida Bay, the abundance of spawning-capable bonefish could have been reduced to such an extent that recruitment was reduced to levels that could not compensate for fishing effects. Bonefishing in Florida became officially catch-and-release only after 2013 (a one fish bag limit was allowed prior, mostly as trophy catch). A survey study showed that anglers perceived a major shift in bonefish size after 2000 (from 8-10lbs to 2-6lbs), indicating the possibility of an erosion of the cohort of larger bonefish that could result in recruitment overfishing [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref074">74</a>]. The likelihood of local recruitment overfishing should be tested using simulations and population dynamic modeling (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref075">75</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref076">76</a>]). Alternatively, South Florida bonefish populations may be dependent on regional recruitment that may be eroded due to non-local fishing, harvest, or other large-scale habitat or environmental effects. In other areas in the Caribbean basin, bonefish are being harvested without any management oversight [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref027">27</a>], thus potentially reducing the importance of these areas as sources of larvae to South Florida bonefish populations. For other taxa, such as lobsters, corals and reef fishes, Florida is typically considered a sink with a high degree of self-recruitment and high larval retention [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref077">77</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref079">79</a>]. Whether the same is true for bonefish is unknown, but ongoing studies of genetic population structure should shed light on this issue (Adams et al., unpub. data).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in seascape structure at broad spatial scales (e.g., the mosaic of seagrass habitat patches) can regulate differential responses in the demography of marine species [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref080">80</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref082">82</a>], influencing the productivity of fisheries in coastal environments [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref083">83</a>]. Starting in 1987, Florida Bay experienced a major drought-related seagrass die-off that affected 30% of the bay and triggered long-term alterations, including losses and changes in seagrass cover, algal blooms, sponge mortality, and reductions in spiny lobster landings and shrimp populations (i.e., one of the main bonefish prey items) [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref037">37</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref084">84</a>]. These multiple interacting disturbances may have affected bonefish numbers and their recreational catches in a number of ways. For example, changes in angler behavior and effectiveness can be influenced by a number of factors such as: poor water clarity (i.e., bonefishing is largely a sight-based fishery); redistribution of bonefish to suboptimal areas and emigration; relocation of fishing effort (i.e., potentially leading to hyperstability); alterations to bioenergetics, trophic dynamics and predation risk (including post-release mortality); and reduced habitat quality for recruits. Both quantitative assessments (Larkin [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref023">23</a>] and this study) pointed to a declining period in bonefish catch during and immediately after the seagrass die-off (i.e., a negative slope from 1988 to 1992), supporting the premise for an immediate role of this disturbance event, but further analyses relating bonefish catch with seagrass spatiotemporal dynamics and other associated environmental parameters are needed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, recent work points to the importance of the interactive effects of environmental factors and fishing on fisheries resilience [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref063">63</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref085">85</a>]. Good examples of this include cases where truncation of the population structure due to fishing increases vulnerability to unfavorable environmental conditions by reducing the number of resistant age cohorts or those with a higher capacity to regenerate subsequent populations [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref063">63</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref085">85</a>]. It is altogether plausible that post-release mortality may have accentuated immediately or years after the seagrass die-off disturbance (i.e., through changes in fish fitness due to habitat loss, fragmentation and associated effects on prey-predator dynamics) to exacerbate the bonefish decline. However, this remains unresolved. Lagged, interacting and accumulating effects could explain why the catch stabilized following the seagrass die-off until catch later shifted to below average conditions in the late 1990s (e.g., hyperstability, [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref062">62</a>]). Linking the FDD and indices of abundance time series to drivers is the subject of ongoing work. Further, a similar hypersalinity and drought event in summer 2015 is currently unleashing another wave of seagrass die-off and algal blooms [
  <a rid="pone.0184776.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0184776.ref030">30</a>], providing an opportunity to more closely examine the effects of these major disturbances events on the structure and resilience of the Florida Bay recreational fisheries. In sum, our study shows that by assessing FDD with different metrics, we were able to reconstruct the pattern of catch and bonefishing effort, allowing for increased temporal resolution of the abundance dynamics of a data-limited fishery, and for the development of hypotheses about possible mechanisms causing population decline. The data-limited nature of most recreational fisheries, and the increase in a use of catch-and-release as a fisheries management strategy, highlight the need to develop further data integration approaches and tools that help assess fish population trends and the overall sustainability of recreational fisheries.
 </p>
</sec>
