<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The climate change simulations of forest growth did not account for growth restrictions due to limited access to nutrients, mainly nitrogen or phosphorus. Forest growth in higher CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations may become nutrient limited in nutrient deficient sites (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wieder et al., 2015</xref>). As PREBAS projections of future growth were made assuming current forest practices continue in the future (
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sved and Koistinen, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Minunno et al., 2019</xref>), here no provision was made for potential adaptive responses by the forest owners, e.g., aiming for more variation in stand structure, stand age or silvicultural management (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blennow, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Montoro Girona et al., 2017</xref>), introducing new tree species or varieties (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Laakkonen et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sousa-Silva et al., 2018</xref>), or striving to maximize positive synergies between ecosystem services (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kuuluvainen and Gauthier, 2018</xref>). Current total volume of growing tree stock in Finland is 2.5 billion m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> with a total annual increment of 107 million m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>, which corresponds to annual average 6.8 and 3.2 m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> ha
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> in southern and northern Finland, respectively. Total volume of roundwood harvested from forests was a record high 72.4 million m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> in 2017, about 17% higher than the average of the preceding ten-year period (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vaahtera et al., 2018</xref>). Current forest policies in Finland aim to increase the annual cut to over 80 million m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> in the next decades. Our simulations indicate that these plans could be feasible in a changing climate, however, increased cutting levels would also imply a lower growing stock than that in our simulations which assumed continuing the current harvest intensity. This would have further implications on C sequestration that need to be explored separately. We did not study the impact of climate change and cutting regimes on biodiversity indicators, such as the amount of dead wood, but others have found significant effects of bioenergy extraction on dead wood levels (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hof et al., 2018</xref>) and conflicting objectives of wood production and biodiversity conservation (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mönkkönen et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Angelstam et al., 2019</xref>). In their comprehensive review on the retention approach for forestry, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lindenmayer et al. (2012)</xref> argued that the practice of permanently retaining significant elements of the original forest is crucial for maintaining multiple forest values, such as biodiversity and carbon stocks. Recently, partial harvest methods were found adequate for regeneration for sustainable forest management in Canadian boreal forests (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Montoro Girona et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>).
</p>
