<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition, we excluded datasets that we deemed lower in quality. High-quality datasets are essential for generating accurate predictions; however, this standard must be balanced against the need to obtain a sufficient quantity of data to be able to predict as wide a variety of environments as possible. In general, our preference for data (from highest quality to lowest quality) was as follows; we accepted data only from 
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">ii</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">iii</italic>.
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">
    <italic class="italic">i</italic>)
   </label>
   <p class="p">Recent standardized continental or national geochemical surveys (
    <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 1,000s of samples). Soil Se is difficult to quantify; therefore recent surveys were preferred to older surveys because quantitative analyses have improved greatly during recent decades, and, as a result, the limit of detection is generally lower now than it was in the past. Typically, soil Se concentrations are low, and therefore it is imperative to have datasets that accurately quantify low concentrations of Se in the soil. In addition to recent surveys, we required datasets with large sample sizes that cover heterogeneous environments. This heterogeneity was important to be able to describe soil Se concentrations accurately in as many different environments across the globe as possible. Therefore, continental or national geochemical surveys were the most advantageous datasets, because they have been collected recently, have high sample sizes that cover a broad geographic range, and are collected and analyzed in a standardized way that minimizes the occurrence of error when aggregating datasets. The highest limit of detection for the broad-scale geochemical surveys was 0.2 mg Se/kg.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">
    <italic class="italic">ii</italic>)
   </label>
   <p class="p">Recent standardized regional geochemical surveys (
    <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 100s of samples). To increase the geographic coverage of our dataset, it was important to include regional geochemical surveys. Although these surveys are smaller, they still have the advantage of being able to quantify low soil Se concentrations accurately. Furthermore, these surveys typically collected samples in a standardized manner throughout the covered range and do not focus on particular areas (e.g., Se “hotspots”). The environmental heterogeneity within these datasets is lower than in continental surveys, but these datasets were particularly helpful because we were able to fill particular gaps within our dataset that were not described by larger-scale studies. Because the highest limit of detection for the broad-scale geochemical surveys was 0.2 mg Se/kg, datasets with a limit of detection &gt;0.2 mg Se/kg were not used in the analysis.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">
    <italic class="italic">iii</italic>)
   </label>
   <p class="p">Recent local surveys (
    <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 10s of samples). Several localized surveys have been conducted, and although the data quality may be high, the inclusion several local surveys into the model undoubtedly introduces error resulting from differences in sample handling, processing, and analytics. Therefore, these datasets were used sparingly and only for specific environments where broad-scale standardized surveys have not been conducted (e.g., tropical areas). Because the lowest limit of detection for the broad-scale geochemical surveys was 0.2 mg Se/kg, datasets with a limit of detection &gt;0.2 mg Se/kg were not used within the analysis. Some local surveys were excluded, however, because they were known to come from hotspot areas with elevated soil Se concentrations.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">
    <italic class="italic">iv</italic>)
   </label>
   <p class="p">Local/regional surveys displayed as colored paper maps, typically from surveys conducted before the advent of geographic information systems (GIS). Several datasets exist as printed maps that illustrate Se concentrations as contours without any indication of sample point distributions. Lithology has frequently been reported as the dominant factor controlling soil Se concentrations, and as a result many Se concentration maps simply follow the boundaries of geological or soil maps without considering other factors such as SOC, pH, or clay content. Such illustrations are simply incorrect. When comparing soil Se maps from similar regions of southern New Zealand that were published in 2016 (
    <xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>) and the in mid-1960s (precise date unknown) (
    <xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>), it is clear that the two maps have no correlation. To illustrate this lack of correlation, the map from the 1960s was digitized, and for each of the 2016 data points (
    <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 347), the corresponding concentration based on the digitized map was recorded. Because the data of the digitized map were binned (i.e., grouped based on a range of concentrations), the concentration was assigned a random value within the range of the bin. A linear regression was made between the two datasets with a corresponding 
    <italic class="italic">R</italic>
    <sup class="sup">2</sup> value of 0.015 (
    <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sfig08" class="xref">Fig. S8</xref>), which is exceedingly low. Assuming that the modern map is an accurate representation of current Se distributions, using the contour map for modeling purposes would result in an entirely inaccurate prediction. The side-by-side comparison of these two datasets is advantageous because we can validate older maps with new data; however, few datasets exist for validation. Because of the inherent limitations of such maps, we deemed such data types unsuitable for our modeling purposes and did not include them in our analysis.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
