<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The potential to adapt is supported by a growing body of evidence that shows populations throughout the world are becoming less sensitive to high temperatures; for example, see reviews by Boeckmann and Rohn (
 <xref rid="c8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) and Hondula et al. (
 <xref rid="c26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, there is variation in the magnitude of the declines in sensitivity that have been observed between studies (e.g., 
 <xref rid="c7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bobb et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schwartz et al. 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Todd and Valleron 2015</xref>), across locations (
 <xref rid="c12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gasparrini et al. 2015a</xref>), and over time (
 <xref rid="c3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Åström et al. 2016</xref>). There are also overall limits to adaptation (
 <xref rid="c52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Woodward et al. 2014</xref>) as, for example, air conditioning penetration reaches 100% or as physiological tolerance reaches biological limits. In addition, many studies neglect to unpick the factors that have driven declines in sensitivity to heat and whether the declines are due to autonomous or planned adaptation (
 <xref rid="c45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Petkova et al. 2014b</xref>). Such omissions preclude an understanding of the policies that could help foster the most efficient adaptation practices. Multiple data sets on factors such as air conditioning penetration, human behavior, activation of heat health warnings, and changes in health care provision are needed to address this issue, but such data sets are rarely available at a sufficient temporal resolution (several decades) to elucidate the effects. The research needed to reveal these important insights will require an interdisciplinary approach that combines quantitative and qualitative methods.
</p>
