<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison to existing literature</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results reveal several factors underlying the implementation climate for health care interventions in SEHOS. Current diagnostic models comprise of six subconstructs that contribute to a favorable implementation climate: 1) tension for change; 2) compatibility; 3) relative priority; 4) organizational incentives and rewards; 5) goals and feedback; and 6) learning climate.
  <a rid="b6-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmdh-12-173">6</a> When analyzing this, the current implementation climate in Curaçao is mainly affected by the subconstructs of compatibility, relative priority, organizational incentives and rewards, goals and feedback, and learning climate. Compatibility could be seen as the degree of tangible fit between meaning and values and how they align with own norms, values and perceived risks, and needs.
  <a rid="b6-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmdh-12-173">6</a> Our results showed suboptimal compatibility, in the factor (vision of the organization), since the vision of the organization was, according to the participants, not always seen as a solid fit. This observation had some overlap with the subconstruct of relative priority, where the vision of the organization was also not always shared among the health care professionals, leading to different priorities and a different perception of the importance of the implementation and contributing to an unfavorable implementation climate. The lack of the subconstruct, organizational incentives, and rewards (associated with extrinsic incentives such as promotions, and performance) was reflected mainly in the underlying factors of personal development and resources. The participants expressed the feeling that they were not compensated or rewarded sufficiently for their inputs, and also, not offered learning opportunities. This could contribute to the sense of a less favorable implementation climate.
  <a rid="b6-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmdh-12-173">6</a> Besides, the subconstruct of goals and feedback, which is described as “the level to which goals are communicated, acted upon, and fed back to the staff...”,
  <a rid="b6-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmdh-12-173">6</a> the implementation climate was reflected through the factors communication and transparency. This factor described how the existing communication and transparency could potentially lead to an unfavorable implementation climate. These two factors could also be linked to the previously researched high-power distance and masculinity of organizational cultures in Curaçao, where the “less powerful” in society reflected a tendency to accept (and expect) the unequal distribution of power and the preference for achievement, heroism, and assertiveness as opposed to the need for cooperation, modesty, caring for the weak, and quality of life.
  <a rid="b12-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b12-jmdh-12-173">12</a>–
  <a rid="b14-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14-jmdh-12-173">14</a> The first subconstruct for a favorable implementation climate; tension for change ie, the degree to which stakeholders perceive the current implementation climate, was not per se reflected in the results of this study.
  <a rid="b6-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmdh-12-173">6</a> Yet, the fact that all participants voluntarily signed up for the workshops and training, without receiving any financial or time compensation, could be a sign that the stakeholders perceived the current situation as intolerable and are in need for change. As a result, it does not inform us adequately, about its effects on the implementation climate for change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The participants of this project were health professionals who underwent clinical leadership training and worked together as an interdisciplinary team to develop a care pathway. The expectations were that this process would contribute to the development of a new strategic vision that would serve as a blueprint for a favorable change in the subconstruct of compatibility and relative priority. The expected change would also enhance collaboration, which could lead to more transparency and therefore a more positive subconstruct of goals and feedback. Its contribution to personal development would also facilitate better organizational incentives and rewards, which although considered extrinsic as personal development, were also partially intrinsic.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our model, we chose for the creation of a care pathway as these have been proven to be beneficial in improving the quality and safety of health care practices.
  <a rid="b15-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15-jmdh-12-173">15</a> As this study focused on how to identify and overcome barriers hindering a healthy implementation climate, it probably also explains the reason for the respondent’s strong emphasis on the limiting factors we identified in the themes of our result. We anticipated that the process would involve health care professionals from different sectors which could trigger or enable reflections in the participants and help (re-)define professional roles within a local context. Our choice of an interprofessional health improvement project was aimed at developing the clinical leadership capabilities of a mixed team of health care professionals while engaged in the development of a care pathway of their choice. This approach was also expected to foster participation and accountability in the implementation process as shown by our group, and has also been shown as a successful quality improvement initiative in previous research in developed countries.
  <a rid="b16-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16-jmdh-12-173">16</a> Although most of the focus in the literature is on clinician-related barriers, several barriers reported in our study align with some of these barriers such as lack of staff involvement, available resources, and insufficient staff.
  <a rid="b17-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17-jmdh-12-173">17</a> Our findings demonstrate that in the transformation of health care systems, a sound understanding of the organizational culture (implementation climate) and the quality of the workforce (clinical leadership abilities) are essential determinants for success.
 </p>
</sec>
