<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the findings from this study show that some of the positive subconstructs for a favorable implementation climate in the hospital organization we studied were lacking, while some of those that were identified were suboptimal. The lack of compatibility, relative prioritization, and lack of organizational incentives and rewards all demonstrate this. In addition, the lack of clearly defined goals and feedback pose potential threats to future projects and innovations. The inability to satisfy all the subconstructs seemed to be the consequences of the lack of sufficient resources and infrastructure in the current health system and an estranged organizational culture where the flow of communication is not optimal, and the organization’s vision is not transparent and clear to its employees. All these factors should be considered and if possible mitigated or improved to get favorable outcomes in new projects and improve the health care overall. The participants’ experience of the health care leadership training and interdisciplinary care pathway development showed that our project could mitigate some of these unfavorable factors. Finally, it is important to mention that on completion of this study, the hospital embraced some of the recommendations for change and solicited the support of a professional human resource development company to guide the implementation of the pressure ulcer care pathway as well as provide administrative support to the health care professionals. The participants of this clinical leadership project are now a group of “process changers” who are championing health care improvement within the organization. As the project progresses, we shall be monitoring the implementation process and searching to understand the consequences and effects on health care delivery as they emerge.</p>
</sec>
