<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resources</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Health care workers expressed resources as one of the barriers that prevented working on new policies and implementing innovations that could potentially improve the health care delivery in the hospital. The comments of the participants showed that human resources (staffing, both in numbers and competencies and skills), physical structures (infrastructure), and education were the significant determinants of resource shortage. Participants mentioned that often they were understaffed, as well as not always fully equipped or trained for the given tasks.</p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>I need another internist with a specialty in infectious diseases. Unfortunately, there is a fixed quota to the number of internal medicine specialists that are allowed to work on the island. We have already exceeded that number which is another limitation so to say. In essence, we need an additional person, but because of all of the different rules hiring another specialist is quite tricky. [P4]</p>
  <p>It is no longer doable. Patients have become more complicated. We have many surgeries a day, except on Friday and lately, we have had many temporary workers. Because they are primarily involved in the basic care, they cannot give the support (specialized care) we need in the surgery department, and that is not responsible care. [P1]</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The respondents mentioned physical means, ie, material as another challenge in the current health care system on the island. The lack of funding expressed itself in a shortage of medicines, tools, and a lack of digital equipment. However, experiences of the participants showed that it was not always the lack of physical means, but also the improper allocation of the means that could result in a shortage.</p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>Yes, patients should receive reliable care, but if you don’t have the means to provide the services sufficiently […] and if the staff needs to take courses and there is limited funding to attend these courses, then the process runs into jeopardy. Despite the fact that funds are limited, we still do a lot by being creative. For example, recycling materials and redesigning it for other purposes. [P3]</p>
  <p>There are not enough decubitus matrasses. Meanwhile it is just a cheap investment. I heard that they just cost a hundred and fifty gulden (equivalent to 84 USD). That is apparently ten times cheaper than the treatment for a chronic decubitus wound. [P9]</p>
 </div>
</sec>
