<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="subjects" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Settings and participants</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fieldwork was conducted in May 2017 at SEHOS, Curaçao. To attain the study objectives, participants with different backgrounds/professions were included, with the aim of obtaining various perspectives on the current implementation climate in the hospital. A purposive sampling method was used to assure a variety in profession. We selected the respondents from the test group (n=25), who were trained to become health care leaders within the hospital. 
  <a rid="t1-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="table" href="#t1-jmdh-12-173">Table 1</a> contains the demographic characteristics of the participants. A total of ten participants participated in the study and the group consisted of nurses, doctors, management, and paramedics as shown in 
  <a rid="t1-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="table" href="#t1-jmdh-12-173">Table 1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In-depth semi-structured individual interviews were conducted with the use of a preconstructed topic guide that explored the respondents’ personal views of the current implementation climate as well as of the organizational structure itself. The topic guide was based on existing literature and included questions on the following topics: 1) respondents’ role within change processes in the hospital; 2) the organizational climate and culture (which included the vision of the organization); and 3) leadership in the hospital.
  <a rid="b6-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmdh-12-173">6</a> Due to the semi-structured nature of the topic guide, participants were encouraged to elaborate on their answers and additional questions were asked to clarify on certain topics. The interviews were held separately and lasted an average of 25 minutes (ranging from 7 to 35 minutes), nine interviews lasted between 20 and 35 minutes, and only one interview was shorter than expected due to the need to attend to an emergency by the participant (see 
  <a rid="t2-jmdh-12-173" ref-type="table" href="#t2-jmdh-12-173">Table 2</a>). A separate group meeting was organized for the participants to reflect and discuss the preliminary findings, which served as a member check of the results and if they recognized and agreed with the preliminary data outcome. During this meeting no new themes were identified, and the participants agreed with the presented analysis.
 </p>
</sec>
