<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vision of the organization</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the current vision of the organization, the participants expressed the following three opinions. First, they were unaware of the current vision of the hospital. Participants had no idea of what the long-term plans were as well as what the hospital expected of them. They experienced that a lack of transparency was responsible for the unawareness. Second, they mentioned that the current investments and policy changes revealed a lack of a long-term vision to support these investments. Last, participants mentioned that the vision of the board did not always align with their vision.</p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>We do not have a long-term vision of the board of directors. It is just band-aid solutions. [P9]</p>
  <p>The organization is open-minded towards changes; however, they do not know what they would like to change. For example, one could be open-minded, but if one does not know what it is that needs to change and how to achieve this, then in such a case, it is not a change, but just spinning around in circles. [P6]</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis showed that several underlying factors caused this negative view on the current long-term vision. A lack of communication and transparency from the hospital administrators was one of the reasons, which will be elaborated later. Next to that, a lack of medical knowledge and know-how among the management staff were viewed upon as a cause of the negative perception of the current vision. Participants mentioned that hospital administrators and senior management staff were often positioned too far from the routine of clinical practice, resulting in them not understanding the current issues in the frontline of care. Furthermore, they observed that some “team leads” in the department lacked the professional capacities to formulate a well-structured policy because they did not have the proper management training. Nevertheless, the participants emphasized that it was important to involve staff in the creation of a long-term vision and to communicate this transparently to all staff members.</p>
</sec>
