<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>We thank Polar Field Services Inc. and Kangerlussuaq International Science Support (KISS) for providing the logistical support that assisted the conceptualization of the manuscript, with assistance from K. Young, S. Zager, and K. Cosper. We also thank H. Johnson (Brown University) for computing support. RCM outputs from MAR3.9 were provided by X. Fettweis. RCM outputs from RACMO2.3p2 were provided by B. Noël and M. van den Broeke. 
  <span class="bold">Funding:</span> This research was funded by a NASA Cryosphere Program grant managed by T. P. Wagner. 
  <span class="bold">Author contributions:</span> J.C.R. conceptualized the project, developed the methodology, carried out the data analysis, and wrote the original manuscript. L.C.S. acquired the funding, provided supervision, assisted with development of the methodology, and co-wrote the manuscript. D.v.A., S.W.C., M.G.C., L.H.P., and A.H. assisted with development of the methodology and edited the manuscript. 
  <span class="bold">Competing interests:</span> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <span class="bold">Data and materials availability:</span> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors. All data can also be accessed online from the following data centers: MOD09GA and Landsat data from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://lpdaac.usgs.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://lpdaac.usgs.gov</span>, maintained by the NASA EOSDIS LP DAAC at the USGS/EROS Center, Sioux Falls, South Dakota; MOD10A1 data from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nsidc.org/data/mod10a1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://nsidc.org/data/mod10a1</span>, maintained by the National Snow and Ice Data Center DAAC at Boulder, Colorado; and AWS data from GAP/PROMICE (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://promice.org/DataDownload.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://promice.org/DataDownload.html</span>).
 </p>
</div>
