<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bare ice presence index</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The daily classified bare ice maps derived from MODIS were used to calculate a summer June, July, and August (JJA) bare ice presence index (or exposure frequency) (fig. S5). The bare ice presence index varies between 0 and 1 in any given summer and is defined as the number of times a pixel is classified as bare ice divided by the total number of valid observations of that pixel (i.e., when not cloud-obscured) between June 1 and August 31. The mean number of valid pixel observations for the whole ice sheet ranged between 45 and 61 days (50 to 68%) and averaged 56 days (62%) between 2001 and 2017. We find that there is some variability between the number of valid observations in June, July, and August (fig. S6). However, the variability is small (SD = ±1.3 days) and cannot explain the observed fluctuations of bare ice presence between 2001 and 2017. Seasonal variability in the number of valid observations therefore does not appear to have biased our results (fig. S6).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Validation of the bare ice presence index was achieved with comparison to in situ albedo measurements derived from 21 PROMICE/GAP automated weather station (AWS) measurements around the ice sheet (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>). AWS albedo is measured by Kipp &amp; Zonen CNR1 or CNR4 net radiometers, which measure downward and upward shortwave radiation fluxes with a specified uncertainty of less than 5% (
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>). Downward shortwave radiation was corrected for tilt and was only calculated when solar zenith angles were larger than 70°. Daily albedo was calculated by integrating the hourly averaged albedo data over a 24-hour period. Bare ice was defined as daily albedo &lt;0.55, and summer bare ice presence index was calculated in the same way as the MODIS bare ice maps. This threshold is based on in situ portable spectrometer and unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) albedo measurements, which indicate that bare ice is rarely brighter than 0.55. We find that our MODIS bare ice presence product is in close agreement with that measured by the AWS with an 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> equal to 0.82 (fig. S7).
 </p>
</sec>
