<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec25" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additional files</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2653_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="label">Additional file 1: Figure S1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Methylation level distribution for non-CpG sites (&gt;0 %). 
     <span class="bold">Figure S2.</span> non-CpG dinucleotide methylation preferences. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S3.</span> CpG methylation level distribution in genes. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S4.</span> non-CpG methylation level distribution in genes. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S5.</span> Average CpG methylation in different gene partitions. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S6.</span> The overlap for brain differentially hypo-methylated (A) and hyper-methylated (B) gene features. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S7.</span> CpG methylation in relation to gene expression in brain. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S8.</span> Relative CpG methylation for CGIs divided over three genomic regional classes. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S9.</span> Relationship between non-CpG methylation level and gene length. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S10.</span> Average gene length for 40 groups of percentiles of non-CpG methylated genes. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S11.</span> Non-CpG methylation in relation to gene expression in brain. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S12.</span> CpG methylation level distribution in TEs and their 2 kb flanking regions. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S13.</span> Non-CpG methylation level distribution in TEs and their 2 kb flanking region. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S14.</span> CpG methylation in relation to TE expression in the brain. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S15.</span> Standardized gene expression from qPCR (Fold Change) as a function of the gene expression calculated from RNA-seq. 
     <span class="bold">Figure S16.</span> Whole genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) vs. Reduced representation bisulfite sequencing (RRBS) in blood. 
     <span class="bold">Table S1.</span> Average and median gene expression in brain for genes associated with differentially methylated CGIs. 
     <span class="bold">Table S2.</span> Average and median gene expression levels for upper and lower 2.5 % non-CpG methylated genes (brain). 
     <span class="bold">Table S3.</span> Blast2GO gene ontology annotation. 
     <span class="bold">Table S4.</span> Methylation profiles in two blood RRBS samples. 
     <span class="bold">Table S5.</span> Primer information for the genes used for qPCR validation. (DOCX 1636 kb)
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2653_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM2" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="label">Additional file 2:</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Full GO-enrichment analysis for differentially methylated gene features: 
     <span class="bold">Tables S1</span> to 
     <span class="bold">S6</span>. (XLSX 169 kb)
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2653_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM3" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="label">Additional file 3:</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Full GO-enrichment analysis for genes associated with differentially methylated CGIs: 
     <span class="bold">Tables S1</span> to 
     <span class="bold">S4</span>. (XLSX 130 kb)
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2016_2653_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx" id="MOESM4" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="label">Additional file 4:</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Full GO-enrichment analysis for upper and lower non-CpG methylated genes: 
     <span class="bold">Tables S1</span> to 
     <span class="bold">S6</span>. (XLSX 126 kb)
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
