<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Non-CpG gene methylation in brain tissue</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To discover if there is a functional signal related to non-CpG methylation we divided all genes according to their non-CpG methylation level in brain and used the upper and lower 2.5 % to perform GO enrichment analysis. Genes with no or very low non-CpG methylation (lower 2.5 %) are largely involved in transcriptional/translational processes (gene expression, mRNA metabolic process, ribosome biogenesis, and translation; Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">4</a>: Tables S1-S3). The genes with the highest methylation (upper 2.5 %) in terms of TSS and TTS non-CpG methylation are mainly involved in system development, glial cell differentiation, gliogenesis and glial cell fate specification (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">4</a>: Tables S4, S5), while genes with highly non-CpG methylated GB are frequently involved in processes linked to the immune system (adaptive immune response, leukocyte mediated immunity, B cell mediated immunity) and cell adhesion (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">4</a>: Table S6). Genes in the lower 2.5 % have significantly higher expression (TSS; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001, GB; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 1x10
  <span class="sup">−11</span>, TTS; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 1x10
  <span class="sup">−06</span>) compared to the highly non-CpG methylated genes (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Table S2). In addition, we found a positive correlation between non-CpG methylation level and gene length (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figures S9, S10), a pattern consistent with recent reports in mammals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. This suggests that the observed differences are biased towards longer genes, where genes involved in protein, DNA, and RNA metabolism are generally shorter compared to genes in the upper non-CpG methylation percentiles (involved in gliogenesis, cell-adhesion or immune response). Additionally, a negative correlation between non-CpG methylation levels and gene expression was observed in all gene features, earlier described by Laine et al. 2016 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>] (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S11).
 </p>
</sec>
