<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Asian highlands, the high mountainous areas of Afghanistan, Bhutan, China, India, Mongolia, Nepal, Pakistan and Russia, contain rich biological diversity and provide important ecosystem services for downstream human communities. The region has also some of the greatest species endemism on the planet and the great variation in climate, topography, and elevation underpins rich cultural diversity (Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). However, climate change has greatly impacted both biological diversity and ecosystems services in these areas (Aryal, Brunton, &amp; Raubenheimer, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Kujala, Moilanen, Araujo, &amp; Cabeza, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). The variation of climate effects that have been detected in the Asian Highlands shows progressive substantial changes at several levels from species to ecosystems (Yu, Luedeling, &amp; Xu, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Impacts of climate change on the hydrology, biodiversity, and ecosystems in this area have been reported which include glacial melting, changes in streamflow, groundwater scarcity, altitudinal shifts, reduction in plant and animal habitats, biodiversity loss, and grassland desiccation (Pressey, Cabeza, Watts, Cowling, &amp; Wilson, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Shrestha &amp; Bawa, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Walther et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). Furthermore, many studies foresee that future climate change would have even greater impacts on biodiversity in Central Asia (Chen, Li, Deng, Fang, &amp; Li, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Garcia, Cabeza, Rahbek, &amp; Araujo, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Zhang, Zhang, &amp; Sanderson, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). It is important to understand the results of these changes in terms of habitat composition, structure and function and the responses of animal geographical distribution, which can guide conservation actions and government efforts in the Asian Highlands in response to these changes (Xu &amp; Grumbine, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
