<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Brown bear (
 <italic class="italic">Ursus arctos</italic>) is a solitary, non‐territorial species with a promiscuous or polygamous mating system (Jerina, Jonozovic, Krofel, &amp; Skrbinsek, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34645-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). It has a circumglobal distribution in the northern hemisphere, occurring in North America (The United States and Canada), Europe, and northern and Central Asia (McLellan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Many of these regions are experiencing rapid climate change (Shrestha, Gautam, &amp; Bawa, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In Central Asia and the Asian Highlands, brown bear distribution is mostly limited to higher elevation areas where more pronounced effects of climate change have been reported (Aryal, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Aryal et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). In these regions, brown bear distribution and presence may be impacted by changing thermal regimes, vegetation, and prey abundance. Such changes may potentially increase human–bear conflicts due to shifting in distribution of resources and possibly increasing scarcity of key resources such as water and food. In the same way, decrease in species diversity in the region due to climate change (Bertelsmeier, Luque, &amp; Courchamp, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Seim et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) might directly affect the distribution and abundance of the brown bear by reducing food resources. Reduced food abundance may result in increased incidences of brown bears moving to anthropogenic areas in search of food, which could lead to increased levels of livestock depredation and human–bear conflict. However, little is known regarding how brown bears habitats will be affected by future climate change in this region. To date, there are few published studies which assess the potential impacts of climate change on brown bears and their habitats (Roberts, Nielsen, &amp; Stenhouse, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), and none in Asia. However, in recent years, a growing interest in the ecological and evolutionary mechanisms of habitat change due to climate change has promoted development of new models for predicting biodiversity futures (Anderson, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Here, we model the current suitable habitats for brown bears and predict the change in their future distribution due to climate change in Central Asia and the Asian Highlands. We used bioclimatic variables and biophysical layers of Central Asia combined with presence data of brown bear to understand their current and future distribution. Such information will be helpful in managing brown bear populations and designing future conservation policies in Asia.
</p>
