<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38" class="p">The climate-driven impacts in the region were shown to be variable across crop types and also geographically for a particular crop. Temperature-induced impacts were beneficial for maize yields, but negative for sorghum and soybean yields, with sorghum yields suffering by much higher magnitudes. Although crop yields were negatively affected by the temperature rise (sensitivity), maize was worst affected per 1 °C increase, followed by soybean and sorghum. However, the actual impacts realized for each crop, as explained earlier, is a function of yield sensitivity to a fixed change in climate and the actual observed climate trends in the crop growing regions. Both maize and soybean growing regions showed cooling (maize regions cooler than soybean regions); however, sorghum growing regions were subjected to substantial warming, which lead to negative temperature-induced impacts on sorghum yields, and positive impacts on maize yields. Similarly, all crops benefitted from a unit rise in precipitation; however the magnitudes of the sensitivity varied, with sorghum being the most sensitive, followed by maize and soybean. The observed precipitation trends were highest for maize growing region, followed by soybean and the least for sorghum, although all regions showed wetting trends. The resultant precipitation induced impacts were hence, maximum for maize, followed by sorghum and soybean. Overall, the regional effect of climate (combined temperature and precipitation) was shown to be beneficial to maize and soybean yields (although low magnitude) and slightly detrimental for sorghum. This is primarily due to the positive precipitation impacts countering (or advancing) the negative (or positive) temperature-induced impacts. Despite evaluating the climate impacts for the entire region, we still strongly suggest that the county-specific impacts be given attention while studying climate impacts as these can be, and have been shown to be substantially different than regional magnitudes. Hence, different regions have to be investigated in terms of their susceptibility/robustness against changes in climate to develop robust and meaningful, and realistic strategies to mitigate climate’s negative impacts on crops and the sensitivity and climate impacts maps can serve considerably in this regard.</p>
