<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Growth in stalagmite S1 resumes around 3800 yrs BP with δ
 <sup class="sup">18</sup>O values indicating wetter conditions (
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189447.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>
 </bold>). The resumption concurs with a period of wetter conditions suggested by other proxy data from the Peloponnese [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. The generally wetter conditions indicated by our record last until 3150 yrs BP, although interrupted by two periods of drier conditions. The first drier phase develops rapidly at 3550 yrs BP and lasts until 3400 yrs BP. This phase is roughly divided in half by a brief return to wetter conditions at 3450 yrs BP. The second dry phase also develops rapidly and is centered around 3200 yrs BP (
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189447.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>
 </bold>) (see extended discussion below). The drier periods are also characterized by enriched δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C values interpreted as indicating reduced biological activity above the cave, supporting the δ
 <sup class="sup">18</sup>O signal (
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0189447.s002" class="xref">S2 Fig</xref>
 </bold>). In Mavri Trypa a transition towards drier conditions starts ~3150 yrs BP, marking the gradual end of the wetter period. The transitional period is one of high-amplitude isotopic fluctuations on a decadal scale, superimposed on a centennial scale trend towards less negative δ
 <sup class="sup">18</sup>O values, indicating reduced precipitation. Overall more arid conditions are evident from 3100 yrs BP until 2950 yrs BP when growth in S1 terminates again. At this time, there is regional and local evidence from the eastern and central Mediterranean for drier conditions e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. High-resolution stable isotope records from Jeita Cave [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>], Renella Cave [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>], Sofular Cave [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>], and Nar Gölü [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>] all show that aridity starts to develop around 3200 years BP but that the most arid conditions only occur after 3200 yrs BP (
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0189447.s003" class="xref">S3 Fig</xref>
 </bold>). From a chronological perspective, these records are some of the most robust paleoclimate records for the period around 3200 yrs BP (
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0189447.s004" class="xref">S4 Fig</xref>
 </bold>).
</p>
