<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-ijerph-12-11254" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Danish Eulerian Hemispheric Model (DEHM)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We applied the Danish Eulerian Hemispheric Model (DEHM) in this study, a 3D dynamic atmospheric chemistry-transport model covering the Northern Hemisphere using a polar stereographic projection (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-12-11254-f001" href="#ijerph-12-11254-f001">Figure 1</a>). It has a horizontal resolution of 150 km × 150 km and 20 vertical layers extending to a height of 100 hPa. DEHM comprises a comprehensive chemistry scheme including a full SO
  <sub>x</sub>-NH
  <sub>x</sub>-NO
  <sub>x</sub>-O
  <sub>3</sub>-VOC chemistry module with 58 chemical components and 122 reactions as well as nine primary particles including black carbon [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-12-11254">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-12-11254">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-12-11254">16</a>]. In addition, there are sub-modules describing atmospheric chemistry and transport of mercury [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-11254">4</a>], fluxes and atmospheric transport of CO
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-12-11254">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-12-11254">18</a>] as well as atmospheric transport and environmental fate of persistent organic pollutants (POPs) [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-12-11254">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-12-11254">20</a>]. It is driven by meteorological data from a numerical weather prediction model, e.g., the MM5 weather forecast model, which is applying global analysed meteorological data as input.
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-11254-f001" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The DEHM model domain, including the sub-division into the major source areas North America (orange), Europe (dark green) and Asia (light green), applied in 
    <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot2-ijerph-12-11254" href="#sec3dot2-ijerph-12-11254">Section 3.2</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ijerph-12-11254-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mercury chemistry scheme applied in the mercury sub-model of DEHM is based on the Tropospheric Chemistry Module (TCM) [
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-12-11254">21</a>], which consists of three gas phase compounds: Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span>, HgO, HgCl
  <sub>2</sub>; 1 particulate phase Hg and nine aqueous phase compounds. Ozone is the most important oxidant for the formation of reactive gaseous mercury (RGM) and total particulate mercury (TPM) in this scheme. An additional fast oxidation rate of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> to HgO is assumed during polar sunrise over sea-ice in the Arctic in order to simulate the Atmospheric Mercury Depletion Events (AMDEs), which accounts for up to about half of the deposition from the atmosphere [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-12-11254">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-11254">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-11254">5</a>]. It is a simple, but useful parameterization [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-11254">4</a>]. Theoretical studies suggest that reactions with atomic bromine (Br) can account for the reactivity of Hg during AMDEs [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-11254">22</a>]. The understanding of these processes is not yet complete [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-11254">13</a>], and they are not included in the model version applied in this study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are no re-emissions after AMDE in the Arctic in DEHM, which means that the calculated total deposition of Hg can be considered to be a model estimate of the maximum possible Hg deposition in the Arctic. Furthermore, the model does not have Hg re-emissions from ocean and soil, which are also important sources of atmospheric Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span>. The contributions from these sources are assumed to be included in the global background concentration of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> of 1.5 ng/m
  <span class="sup">3</span>, which is used as initial and boundary conditions in all the simulations. This background concentration represents the current background concentration depending on the current anthropogenic and natural emissions as well as re-emissions. However, it is possible to estimate the influence of the anthropogenic emissions on the background concentration via post processing if the contribution from the global background concentration is known. This is done by assuming that only anthropogenic emissions of Hg
  <span class="sup">0</span> contribute to the global background concentration and that the natural emissions and re-emissions are assumed to be constant with 4200 tons Hg based on estimates from AMAP [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-12-11254">1</a>]. The background concentration can then be calculated from the following expression: 
  <div id="FD1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">(1)</span>
   <div id="mm1" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">H</span>
     <div class="msubsup">
      <span class="mi">g</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">b</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">c</span>
       <span class="mi">k</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mn">0</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mn">1.5</span>
     <span class="mi">n</span>
     <span class="mi">g</span>
     <span class="mo">/</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <span class="mi">m</span>
      <span class="mn">3</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">H</span>
         <div class="msubsup">
          <span class="mi">g</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">u</span>
           <span class="mi">s</span>
           <span class="mi">e</span>
           <span class="mi">d</span>
           <span class="mo"> </span>
           <span class="mi">e</span>
           <span class="mi">m</span>
           <span class="mi">i</span>
           <span class="mi">s</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mn">0</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">+</span>
         <span class="mn">4200</span>
         <span class="mo"> </span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
         <span class="mi">o</span>
         <span class="mi">n</span>
         <span class="mi">n</span>
         <span class="mi">e</span>
         <span class="mi">s</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mi">H</span>
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span class="mi">g</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">e</span>
         <span class="mi">m</span>
         <span class="mi">i</span>
         <span class="mi">s</span>
         <span class="mo"> </span>
         <span class="mn">2005</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mn">0</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">+</span>
       <span class="mn">4200</span>
       <span class="mo"> </span>
       <span class="mi">t</span>
       <span class="mi">o</span>
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mi">n</span>
       <span class="mi">e</span>
       <span class="mi">s</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all the simulations presented here, the contribution from the background concentration is known. Therefore, this post-processing procedure has been used for all the presented results. The ozone concentrations are provided by the SOx-NHx-NOx-O
  <sub>3</sub>-VOC chemistry module, and Black Carbon concentrations, which are applied in the model for the production of particulate Hg in the aqueous phase chemistry, are provided by the particle module in DEHM.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model evaluations against measured Hg concentrations in air show reasonable agreement with predicted concentrations from DEHM with input of real meteorology [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-11254">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-11254">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-12-11254">6</a>]. DEHM has also successfully been applied to study the transport and fate of a range of other chemical compounds to the Arctic, including sulphur and sulphate [
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-12-11254">15</a>], Pb [
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-12-11254">6</a>], Persistent Organic Pollutants (POPs) [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-12-11254">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-12-11254">20</a>,
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-11254">23</a>] and Decamethylcyclopentasiloxane [
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-12-11254">24</a>]. The model was previously applied to study the effect of climate change on future atmospheric levels of ozone and particulate matter [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-12-11254">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-12-11254">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-12-11254">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-12-11254">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-12-11254">29</a>] and related impacts on health [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-12-11254">30</a>] as well as on the fate of POPs in the Arctic [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-12-11254" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-12-11254">31</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
