<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds infected by tick-borne pathogens</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds can be infected by different genuses of Anaplasmataceae, i.e., 
  <span class="italic">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</span> (de la Fuente et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B15" href="#B15">2005</a>), 
  <span class="italic">Rickettsia rickettsia</span> (Lundgren et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">1966</a>) and 
  <span class="italic">Coxiella burneti</span> (Babudieri and Moscovici, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">1952</a>). We have not found any experimental data confirming that birds infected by the Anaplasmataceae can transfer these pathogens to ticks. The 
  <span class="italic">Babesia</span> spp. appears to be host specific, at least to the class, and some of them to one species (Peirce, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B58" href="#B58">2000</a>), no mammal 
  <span class="italic">Babesia</span> sp. has been found infecting birds. Some species of 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> can infect birds, notably 
  <span class="italic">B. garinii</span>, 
  <span class="italic">B. valaisiana</span>, 
  <span class="italic">B. turdi</span> (Gylfe et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B29" href="#B29">2000</a>; Richter et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">2000</a>) and 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi</span> s.s. (Anderson and Magnarelli, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">1984</a>; Anderson et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">1986</a>), but probably not 
  <span class="italic">B. afzelii</span> (Kurtenbach et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">2002</a>), although this notion has been challenged by the findings of Franke et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">2010</a>). Hasle et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">2010</a>) found an odds ratio for 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection of 4.3 for ticks parasitizing the 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp., i.e. 3.5 for 
  <span class="italic">B. garinii</span> and 30.3 for 
  <span class="italic">B. valaisiana</span>. This indicates that the 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp. are more susceptible for infection with these 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> genospecies than other birds, and that the ticks got the pathogen during feeding on the bird. Thus, the 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp., apart from being likely to carry ticks, were more likely to carry 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span>-infected ticks than other bird genera. Therefore, the 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp., especially the blackbird, may be important in the spreading and hosting of 
  <span class="italic">B. garinii</span>, which is the main agent for neuroborreliosis (van Dam et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">1993</a>; Balmelli and Piffaretti, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">1995</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> species causing tick-borne relapsing fever are transmitted by soft ticks, 
  <span class="italic">Ornithodorus</span> spp., which have a different biology from the 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>-like ticks in that they live in nests and burrows and have a feeding time of just a few minutes Johnson and Golighty (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B42" href="#B42">2000</a>). These ticks would not be prone to long-range transport by birds, but the birds may contract the 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span>, which can be transmitted further, as suggested for 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia hermsii</span>, by (Schwan et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transport of tick-borne pathogens from one endemic area to another could have an impact, even if the pathogens already occur there, by spreading new strains to new areas.</p>
</sec>
