<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introducing new tick species</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although it has never been demonstrated that a new tick species, or a new tick pathogen, actually has been established in a new locality after being seeded there by birds, the evidence strongly suggests that this could happen. Hasle et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">2009</a>) studied northward migrating birds on four bird observatories situated north of the Skagerrak and Kattegat (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a>). From 9.768 passerine birds examined they found seven nymphs of 
  <span class="italic">Hyalomma rufipes</span>. The 
  <span class="italic">Hyalomma</span> species have a northern distribution limit in Southern Europe and North Africa (Estrada-Peña et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">2004</a>), and these nymphs would have had to be transported all the way from the Mediterranean to Norway, the last 130–150 km over open sea. Although many 
  <span class="italic">Hyalomma</span> individuals may be brought to Norway every year, they would not settle in a cold temperate climate. Also, a larva of 
  <span class="italic">Dermacentor</span> sp. was found on a willow warbler, 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus trochilus</span> on Akerøya, Hvaler, an island off the Southern Norwegian coast. No 
  <span class="italic">Dermacentor</span> sp. is endemic in Norway. These findings demonstrate that non-endemic tick species can be transported to new places, across geographic barriers. Considering an influx of 30–80 million passerines crossing the sea every spring, millions of ticks will be transported every year, and transport of exotic species would not be a rare event. The limiting factor will not be the ticks' dispersal ability, but the suitability of the area the ticks are released for the survival and reproduction of the ticks. A suitable climate is one of the prerequisites for establishing a tick species. For 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>, which has its northern border of distribution in Norway and Sweden, the distribution correlates well with the isolines for the first frost night, number of days with snow cower, and the length of the growth season (Jaenson et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">2009</a>). As these isolines overlap we cannot from these data tell which climatic factor is the most important. As ticks are prone to desiccation (Daniel and Dusbábek, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">1994</a>), microclimatic conditions of sun, soil and vegetation cover will determine the individual ticks' chance of survival, much like in the Parable of the Sower (Mattew 13:5). 
  <span class="italic">Dermacentor reticulatus</span>, which occurs in North Germany, is a vector for 
  <span class="italic">Babesia canis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">F. tularensis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Rickettsia slovaka</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. Burnetii</span>. It needs to complete the whole life cycle during one year (Dautel et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">2006</a>), which unlikely could take place during a normal year in Norway. However, future climate change could make Norway hospitable for this species. Conceivably, individual specimens of 
  <span class="italic">D. reticultus</span> could transmit diseases after being transported to Norway by birds. An indirect evidence of this is a case of 
  <span class="italic">Babesia canis</span> in a Norwegian dog that had not been abroad. 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> is the main vector for 
  <span class="italic">B. canis</span> (Øines et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Study area of Hasle et al. (
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">2009</a>).
    </span> The participating bird observatories were: (1). Lista, (2). Jomfruland, (3). Store Færder, (4). Akerøya. Northward migrating birds would have to cross The North Sea, Skagerrak or Kattegat.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fcimb-03-00048-g0001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from protection from frost and desiccation, a good tick habitat will depend on appropriate hosts. e.g., islands that harbor only small animals cannot support the full life cycle of 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>, as the adults need hosts of a certain minimum size (Jaenson et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B41" href="#B41">1994</a>). Possibly, some tick species may be host specific, although this is controversial (Randolph, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For establishing a new population, an ecological 
  <span class="italic">niche</span> must be available. According to the Competitive exclusion principle, two different species cannot sustainably occupy the same 
  <span class="italic">niche</span> (Hardin, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B31" href="#B31">1960</a>). However, this is a theoretical consideration, and very similar species, like 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">I. persulcatus</span> may have different climate requirements, e.g., 
  <span class="italic">I. persulcatus</span> is much more cold-resistant than 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> (Tokarevich et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">2011</a>). Therefore, their 
  <span class="italic">niches</span> are not exactly identical. Furthermore, in a transient situation sympatric distribution can occur, as is shown in a recent publication showing a shift in the distribution range of 
  <span class="italic">I. persulcatus</span> toward North and West in Karelen, Russia, into areas previously occupied by 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> (Bugmyrin et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B10" href="#B10">2013</a>). It is shown for 
  <span class="italic">I. persulcatus</span> (Filippova, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">2002</a>) as well as 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span> (Oliver et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">1993</a>) that they can readily mate and breed with 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>, but the offspring is sterile. In a situation with coexistence, the reproductive success of the least abundant species would suffer much more than the most abundant species (Hasle, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">2010</a>). Ticks seeded in an area occupied by another species with which they can interbreed would have a very low chance of copulating with the same species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change, as well as changes in vegetation, is expected to influence the distribution of different tick species (Estrada-Peña, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">2001</a>; Gray et al., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">2009</a>). Global warming would be expected to push a Northern limit of a distribution range further north. Such changes take place over decades, and dispersal by mammalian tick-hosts would be sufficient to keep up with the changes within a continent. However, if a geographical barrier, e.g., a sea, like Skagerrak and Kattegat, separates two hospitable areas, one with a tick species, and one without that species, and if the ecological 
  <span class="italic">niche</span> is not occupied by another tick species, transport by birds would be a possible mechanism.
 </p>
</sec>
