<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transfer of pathogens through co-feeding</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transmission of a tick-borne pathogen through co-feeding has been demonstrated for the tick-borne encephalitis-virus (TBEV) on 
  <span class="italic">Myodes glareolus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Apodemus sylvaticus</span> (Labuda and Randolph, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">1999</a>), but no data exists for such transmission of TBEV on birds. In Waldenström et al.'s material (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B72" href="#B72">2007</a>) they found three TBEV-positive 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinius</span>, one nymph and two larvae, on one individual European robin, 
  <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span>, which strongly suggests that the bird either was viremic or that transmission through co-feeding did occur.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also, for 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> this mechanism has been suggested for mammals. Gern and Rais (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">1996</a>) demonstrated transmission of 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi</span> between co-feeding 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> on AKR/N mice in the laboratory. By using a generalized linear model (GLM) Hasle et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">2010</a>) found that ticks that were co-feeding on birds with ticks infected with one genospecies of 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> had an increased probability of being infected with the same genospecies. A tick co-feeding with another tick with 
  <span class="italic">B. afzelii</span> had an odds ratio of 3.9. If the statement that birds cannot be infected with 
  <span class="italic">B. afzelii</span> is correct, this is an indication that non-systemic transmission between co-feeding ticks has occurred. For 
  <span class="italic">B. valaisiana</span> the odds ratio for ticks co-feeding with other ticks with 
  <span class="italic">B. valaisiana</span> was 760, compared to the average prevalence. The latter could partly be explained by the effect of feeding on the 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp., and by systemic infection of the bird. Geller et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">2013</a>) found the same strain of 
  <span class="italic">B. afzelii</span> (PGau) on two 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> nymphs that were feeding on the same Great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), a finding that suggests transmission through co-feeding.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The existing data support the hypothesis that all the three mechanisms of spreading tick-borne pathogens by birds may occur in the nature.</p>
</sec>
