<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The increase in species richness in our plots was smaller in the second decade (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>a), suggesting a slowing down of species upward shifts. The separate consideration of colonisation and disappearance of species, however, showed that the number of colonisations decreased only slightly, whereas the number of disappearances increased markedly (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b). Species disappearances at the alpine–nival ecotone can indicate retracting lower range margins, as expected through warming‐driven competitive displacements (Engler 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Lenoir &amp; Svenning, 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). In particular, cold‐adapted species have been found recently to have experienced range contractions in the Alps (Rumpf 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>) and alpine Mediterranean species have been shown to decline, possibly as a result of the combined effects of warming and a reduction in precipitation (Pauli 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Species disappearances on Schrankogel, however, did not only concern subnival–nival species (AR1), but also alpine–subnival pioneer species (AR2) and alpine species (AR3) in similar proportions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>b). Species colonisation numbers remained stable in all altitudinal species groups, except for AR1, where they dropped significantly (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>a). We therefore cannot unequivocally attribute the observed species turnover to warming‐driven range dynamics. The detection of leading edge shifts driven by climate warming is hampered by the stochastic nature of processes, such as the propagation of diaspores, germination and establishment of seedlings. Similarly, the disappearance of species may either be the final stage of a population decline or the result of an unsuccessful species establishment, which are difficult to disentangle (Grytnes 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Further, projected directional range shifts and associated local species extinctions in temperate and boreal mountains (Engler 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) may still require longer periods for the usually long‐lived perennial alpine plants. Species dwelling in cold environments may persist even in climatically unsuitable habitats, and thereby accumulate an extinction debt (Dullinger 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012a</xref>). Yet, the increase in richness in our plots was mainly driven by alpine–subnival pioneer species (AR2), whereas the number of subnival–nival species (AR1) decreased slightly (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>), which could already be an indication of warming‐driven range shift dynamics. This also accounts for the fact that newly appearing species all belong to the lower elevation groups (AR3 and AR4; Table 
 <xref rid="nph15290-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>), which is in line with increasingly rising species numbers on mountain summits in Europe (Steinbauer 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>).
</p>
