<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes class="notes">
 <title class="title">Authors’ information</title>
 <p id="Par62" class="p">Bruce A. Wilcox received his undergraduate and graduate education from University of California at San Diego (BA, biology; PhD population biology) and Yale University (MS, ecology and evolutionary biology). A founder of the field of conservation biology and the journal 
  <italic class="italic">Conservation Biology</italic>, he also was the founding editor of EcoHealth and first Chief Executive of the International Association for Ecology and Health. His current research focuses on integrative research and its applications in environmental health, tropical disease research, and global health. He is a frequent consultant and advisor to international agencies including the World Health Organization on ecological and complex systems applications to environmental health challenges, particularly tropical disease prevention and control.
 </p>
 <p id="Par63" class="p">Michel de Garine-Wichatitsky has a backgroung in Veterinary Medicine (DVM, Ecole Nationale Vétérinaire de Maisons-Alfort) and received his post-graduate education in Ecology at the University of Montpellier in France (MSc, PhD, HDR). He is a Senior Researcher for the French agricultural research and international cooperation organization CIRAD, currently based in Bangkok with the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine of Kasetsart University, and Research Associate with the Department of Biological Sciences, University of Zimbabwe. His career has been devoted to research, higher education and management of biodiversity and health in tropical regions, including South-East Asia, Southern Africa and the South Pacific. Michel has embraced multiple aspects of “wildlife-livestock-human interfaces” and enthusiastically adopted multi- and inter-disciplinary approaches associating ecology, veterinary medicine, anthropology, parasitology and epidemiology.</p>
 <p id="Par64" class="p">Bernadette Ramirez, Ph. D, Provides support for and coordinates projects studying population health vulnerabilities to vector-borne diseases and ways to increase population resilience against the impact of climate change in Africa and southeast Asia. Bernadette joined WHO-TDR in June 2007 with over 20 years of academic and research experience in health product innovation, drug discovery, vaccines and the development of diagnostics for infectious tropical diseases.</p>
 <p id="Par65" class="p">Pierre Echaubard, Ph. D, is a health ecology researcher. He specializes in infectious diseases ecology and evolution, vector-borne diseases adaptive management and the linkages between biodiversity and health. He is currently focusing on operationalizing protocols applying Social-Ecological Systems approaches to VBD control and health development in Myanmar, Cambodia, Thailand and Lao PDR, including developping indicators assessing outcomes and processes in relation to community engagement, adaptive capacity building and resilience. He has academic experiences and postgraduate degrees from the University of Montpellier, France, the ETH Zurich, Switzerland and a PhD in infectious disease ecology and evolution from Laurentian University, Canada. He is associate editor of the journals Infection Genetics and Evolution (Elsevier) and guest editor for Evolutionary Applications (Wiley).</p>
</notes>
