<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In cities with a Mediterranean climate (Med-cities), people have to deal with cold in winter, which can be either dry or wet, and heat in summer, with high or low humidity. In the transitional seasons, over short periods of time, the climatic conditions can change from one extreme to another. Therefore, dealing with bioclimatic comfort and weather conditions in a Mediterranean climate may be more complicated than in more extreme environments [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. These challenges are increasing since the Mediterranean climate-type regions are among the most vulnerable to the impacts of the changing climate [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. In the Mediterranean basin itself, since many cities are old, they are compact and densely populated [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Furthermore, Med-cities often lack shading in public places, and when shading elements exist they are often designed in ways that do not provide sufficient shade during the hot hours, nor is their potential to reduce heat stress fulfilled [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Although air conditioning is essential in the long hot season, it is mainly used in areas with higher socio-economic standing while poor populations have less access to air conditioning [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. In Med-cities, as a part of the local mentality, windows remain open for most of the hot months. Many activities, particularly social gatherings, occur in outdoor locations such as shaded balconies, courtyards, and outdoor restaurants [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. These cultural behaviors increase the potential for contact with mosquitoes that may be vectors for infectious diseases. All the characteristics above make the residents of the Med-cities susceptible to the impacts of climate change.
</p>
