<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Use of the fundamental niche of an experimental population to infer niche filling at the species level involves the assumption that the thermal niche of the experimental population is conserved across individuals in central and marginal populations. Such thermal niche conservatism has been observed empirically for several marine species [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and may be expected for highly mobile, widely dispersing or migratory species with high inter-population connectivity, or recently established populations in new thermal environments [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] (
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). Importantly, niche conservatism underpins prevailing methods used to understand climate change impacts on species distributions (i.e. species distribution models, bioclimatic envelope models, ecological niche models) [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Nevertheless, many species can display marked population-level differences in thermal tolerance limits [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Studies that link the fundamental niche with absolute temperatures or temperature variability in a given location also tend to make species-level inferences about thermal sensitivity, based on case studies of single populations [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In doing so, these studies make the implicit assumption that individuals from other (untested) populations of the same species will be locally adapted or acclimatized. Temperature regimes can vary considerably across a species' geographical distribution in terms of seasonal variability and/or temperature extremes (see §4, below). Under such circumstances, in order for the relationship between a populations' thermal sensitivity and local climatic conditions to hold, a necessary assumption is that the thermal niche of the majority of individuals in different populations changes as a function of changes in thermal regimes throughout a species range. That is, populations living under different thermal regimes are assumed to be adapted or acclimatized to their local climate. 
</p>
