<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While many studies project future range shifts for wildlife, the spatial configuration and connectivity of future habitats has been less well addressed. Our work predicts that VIWTP habitat will become increasingly fragmented and confined to mountaintops. Climate change will likely cause fragmentation of VIWTP habitat by facilitating infilling of trees and shrubs into previously open alpine tundra [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>], a process already documented at high elevations on Vancouver Island [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. The effects of habitat fragmentation on VIWTP persistence will depend on their home range size and dispersal ability. Substantial movement of VIWTP genes occurs across the landscape and high allelic richness is found even among the most isolated populations [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Female White-tailed Ptarmigan in Colorado can move long distances to other breeding areas without incurring reproductive or survival costs during the breeding season [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. These studies suggest that ptarmigan may be able to persist on Vancouver Island despite increasing habitat fragmentation due to their apparent ability to move between patches, at least for the initial periods of change. Still, our results predict the disappearance of nearly all of the ptarmigan habitat south of Strathcona Provincial Park by the 2080s. Large areas of unsuitable low elevation habitat act as a barrier to VIWTP gene flow, as the southern populations appeared to be smaller and more temporally variable [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Thus, these southern populations may well be extirpated by climate-induced habitat loss within 70 years. The ability of ptarmigan to disperse between smaller and more spatially fragmented habitat patches will be an important predictor of VIWTP long-term viability, and future research should examine VIWTP dispersal distance as a function of future climates in order to inform management and conservation of the subspecies.
</p>
