<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We defined moisture availability using thresholds of vegetation greenness, similar to the approach used by Guerra et al. (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) and following work by Suzuki et al. (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). Recent work by Baeza et al. (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) has shown that NDVI is a good predictor of malaria prevalence, typically better than rainfall when irrigation levels are low to moderate. Using NDVI allowed us to retain pockets of suitable transmission conditions such as river tributaries or irrigated land where transmission may be supported, while eliminating areas that are too dry for too long to support mosquito populations, regardless of temperature regime (Gething et al. 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>, Guerra et al. 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Differences in rainfall within sufficiently humid regions may impact transmission, but NDVI has been shown to be a stronger predictor than precipitation for large geographic areas (Baeza et al. 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). We created pixel-wise monthly mean NDVI values from the USGS eMODIS product (Jenkerson et al. 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), using dekadal (10-day interval) data from 2001–2011 for the African continent from the Famine Early Warning System Network (FEWS NET) data portal (
 <span xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://earlywarning.usgs.gov/fews/africa/index.php" class="uri" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://earlywarning.usgs.gov/fews/africa/index.php</span>), aggregated from 250 meters to 0.1 degree resolution. We masked out pixels that did not have at least two consecutive months of NDVI above 0.125; this is slightly more conservative than the 0.1 limit of Suzuki et al. (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>).
</p>
