<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data sets and Mt. Pinatubo eruption</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volcanically induced changes in the Southern Ocean Atlantic sector are examined after the 1991 Mt. Pinatubo eruption. For that we restrict the analysis to 1980–2005 period comparing available observational data sets and output from the Last Millennium Ensemble experiment from the Community Earth System Model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> (CESM-LME, described in the next section). For the Mt. Pinatubo response all anomalies are calculated relative to the 1980–2005 mean. The anomaly time series is de-trended over the same period, as a way to minimize CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced long-term trend that could skew the results. For the same period (1980–2005), we also examined the average of the CESM-LME ensemble containing only the volcanic forcing, that allows us to isolate the volcanic signal on the SST.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all the analysis we considered only the austral summer (DJF), because of the smaller sea-ice extension in the Weddell Sea during this season. In addition, the maximum response to volcanic activity is in the summer for both hemispheres, which is probably a result of shallow mixed layers at this time of the year, that respond more rapidly to changes in the heat flux
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. This means that in the Mt. Pinatubo analysis the austral summer of the year of the eruption (1991) consider December from this year and January and February from the next year (1992). For all the other years we used the same approach.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We utilized SST data from the Extended Reconstructed Sea Surface Temperature version 5 (ERSSTv5)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA). The product has a spatial resolution of 2° and covers January 1854 up to 2015. Also, the Hadley Centre Sea Ice and Sea Surface Temperature (HadISST) data set
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, with 1° latitude-longitude grid from 1870 to 2017. Other data sets used are oceanic reanalysis such as the Simple Ocean Data Assimilation (SODA) reanalysis version 3.4.1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, that uses an ocean general circulation model to assimilate available 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> temperature and salinity profiles, also data from satellite, forced by European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) ERA-Interim
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. The product is a gridded data set of monthly values from 1980 to 2015, at 0.5° horizontal resolution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. The Ocean Reanalysis System 4 (ORAS4) from ECMWF is also compared, with spatial resolution of 1° and monthly data from 1958 to 2017
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
