<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data sets and Mt. Pinatubo eruption</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volcanically induced changes in the Southern Ocean Atlantic sector are examined after the 1991 Mt. Pinatubo eruption. For that we restrict the analysis to 1980–2005 period comparing available observational data sets and output from the Last Millennium Ensemble experiment from the Community Earth System Model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span> (CESM-LME, described in the next section). For the Mt. Pinatubo response all anomalies are calculated relative to the 1980–2005 mean. The anomaly time series is de-trended over the same period, as a way to minimize CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced long-term trend that could skew the results. For the same period (1980–2005), we also examined the average of the CESM-LME ensemble containing only the volcanic forcing, that allows us to isolate the volcanic signal on the SST.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all the analysis we considered only the austral summer (DJF), because of the smaller sea-ice extension in the Weddell Sea during this season. In addition, the maximum response to volcanic activity is in the summer for both hemispheres, which is probably a result of shallow mixed layers at this time of the year, that respond more rapidly to changes in the heat flux
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
   </span>. This means that in the Mt. Pinatubo analysis the austral summer of the year of the eruption (1991) consider December from this year and January and February from the next year (1992). For all the other years we used the same approach.
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We utilized SST data from the Extended Reconstructed Sea Surface Temperature version 5 (ERSSTv5)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span> from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA). The product has a spatial resolution of 2° and covers January 1854 up to 2015. Also, the Hadley Centre Sea Ice and Sea Surface Temperature (HadISST) data set
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>, with 1° latitude-longitude grid from 1870 to 2017. Other data sets used are oceanic reanalysis such as the Simple Ocean Data Assimilation (SODA) reanalysis version 3.4.1
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>, that uses an ocean general circulation model to assimilate available 
   <span class="italic">in situ</span> temperature and salinity profiles, also data from satellite, forced by European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts (ECMWF) ERA-Interim
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span>. The product is a gridded data set of monthly values from 1980 to 2015, at 0.5° horizontal resolution
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. The Ocean Reanalysis System 4 (ORAS4) from ECMWF is also compared, with spatial resolution of 1° and monthly data from 1958 to 2017
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model configuration and Last Millennium eruptions</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All results from the Last Millennium (LM, 850–1850) are obtained from the CESM-LME
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. The model configuration used the Community Earth System Model version 1.1 with the Community Atmosphere Model version 5
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
   </span>. The spatial resolution of the atmosphere and land components is ∼2° and the ocean and sea-ice components use ∼1° spatial resolution and 60 layers as ocean vertical resolution
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. There is a total of 30 ensemble members of forced runs for the period between 850 and 2005, which are a combination of full forcing runs evolving in time and runs considering of each forcing individually with all other forcings fixed at values from the year 850. These are volcanic only, solar
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
   </span>, land use
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
   </span>, greenhouse gas, ozone-aerosol
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
   </span> and orbital only
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
   </span>. The ensemble approach allows improved estimate of the uncertainty from internal variability and modeling process
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>. The volcanic eruptions are one of the most important forcings from the LM
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
   </span>, CESM-LME uses eruptions from reconstruction version 1
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>. This reconstruction
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span> accounts a total of 53 ice cores (32 from the Arctic and 22 from Antarctica), composing a comprehensive stratospheric volcanic sulfate mass loading for the past 1500 years
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the LM eruptions analysis, we consider the output from 10 full forcing and 5 volcanic-only ensemble members. This analysis has been restricted to the period 850–1850, to exclude any CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced trends in the full forcing runs. The ensemble average is used to reduce the internal variability
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
   </span>. All anomalies presented in the LM eruptions analysis are calculated relative to the 850–1850 mean. The eruptions were selected according to a previous study that used the same model outputs
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. The authors only selected eruptions with a peak aerosol mass mixing ratio greater than 10
   <span class="sup">−8</span> and classified them in regions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. Here we selected only the tropical and southern eruptions, since both regions have shown to influence the southern extra-tropics ocean
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All seven selected eruptions were averaged together. The year of the eruption is referred as Yr0 in the composite analysis, which means that all 7 eruptions from the 15 ensemble members were averaged. The composite evolution starts in the year before the eruption (Yr-1) and includes the 6 subsequent years (Yr + 1 to Yr + 6). As in the Mt. Pinatubo section, we only analyze austral summer (DJF) results, for that we considered the average of December, from the year of the eruption, January and February, from the subsequent year.</p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The significance levels presented are determined according to the Wilcoxon Rank Sum test at 90%
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. The set of the composite years (7 eruptions from 15 ensemble members, total of 105 events) are compared with the full time series from all ensemble members. This is the nonparametric version of the t-test, which only makes the assumption of independence between the time series and equal variance, but not that the data have a known distribution
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
   </span>. We use the closest model grid points from the original historical stations from the SR4
   <span class="italic">/</span>WOCE (SR4 transect from World Ocean Circulation Experiment)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>, which captures the subsurface inflow and outflow of Weddell circulation.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
