<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volcanic eruptions are important elements of the climate system, driving transient changes to global climate on interannual to decadal timescales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Large explosive eruptions are capable of injecting sulfate aerosols into the stratosphere, which are responsible for reducing incoming shortwave radiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. The global response is an overall cooling of Earth’s surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. The eruption of Mt. Pinatubo in 1991 was the largest eruption of the 20
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">th</span>
  </span> century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. It caused global sea surface cooling of 0.3–0.4 °C
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> with impacts on weather and hydroclimate throughout the world
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Nonetheless, its size is comparably small relative to the eruptions of the past millennium, before 1850 where anthropogenically driven warming was insignificant
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Thus, understanding the range of regional impacts associated with past large volcanic eruptions is crucial for assessing the impacts of potential future eruptions. This is particularly relevant given the potential for future anthropogenic warming to modify the impacts of volcanic eruptions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Southern Ocean is a vulnerable region to climate change, in part because of the presence of floating ice shelves around most of Antarctica’s coastline
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. In addition, it is the site of dense water formation (i.e. Antarctic Bottom Water) and unique ecosystem communities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. The Antarctic Peninsula ice shelves and ocean near it deserve special attention because of ongoing changes to ecosystems and ocean-atmosphere-cryosphere dynamics due to climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. The Weddell Sea region off the Antarctic Peninsula has been widely impacted by recent permanent ice-shelve collapse
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> and thinning (i.e. Larsen Ice Shelf)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Antarctic Peninsula ice shelves are highly susceptible to changes in ocean circulation, as observed in the Larsen C ice loss through basal melting
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> and intrusion of warm ocean waters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. After a large eruption sea-ice extension responds more to ocean temperature and circulation changes than to the direct radiative forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Climate simulations have shown that the eruption aftermath in Antarctica is an initial sea-ice expansion followed by its contraction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> linked primarily to the strengthening of the Southern Hemispheres stratospheric polar vortex and a chain of regional feedbacks. The connectivity between large-scale dynamics and local processes after an eruption in the Southern Ocean highlights several relevant features that lack of studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, as ocean temperature exchange and regional polar interaction between ocean-atmosphere and sea-ice.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate models can provide valuable insight into the physical mechanisms driving responses to volcanic eruptions. The use of ensembles is particularly valuable, due to the large extent of internal climate variability which can mask the forced response to eruptions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Here we make use of the Community Earth System Model Last Millennium Ensemble (CESM-LME
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>), which contains multiple realizations of the climate over the 850–2005 period. This allows us to examine both the effects of the 1991 Mt. Pinatubo eruption individually, and the potential impacts of larger Last Millennium (LM, 850–1850) eruptions more broadly, to identify common physical mechanisms in the Southern Ocean response to eruptions.
 </p>
</sec>
