<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mechanism for Surface Warming</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results indicate that the surface temperature off the Antarctic Peninsula is not primarily responding directly to the radiative forcing effect from volcanism, but is driven by the delayed response of ocean dynamics in the first year after the eruption (Yr + 1). We believe that the dynamical response is as follows and schematically represented in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>, with respect to:
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par20">
     <span class="bold">
      <span class="italic">Winds</span>
     </span>: The westerlies become stronger and their southernmost extension also shifts south into most of the Weddell Sea(Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6-1a</a>). At the same time, along the outflow region in the Weddell Sea near the Antarctic Peninsula, the northward winds are displaced southward (Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6-1b</a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par21">
     <span class="bold">
      <span class="italic">Surface Circulation</span>
     </span>: As a response to the wind changes, the southern limit of the ACC becomes stronger (Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6–2a</a>), enhancing mixing at the Weddell Sea outflow region (Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6–2b</a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par22">
     <span class="bold">
      <span class="italic">Subsurface Circulation</span>
     </span>: At the subsurface layer, ~400 m depth, the inflow region is somewhat warmer in 0.08 °C (Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6–3a</a>). At the same time that the WG outflow is weakened (Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6–3b</a>). This means that the subsurface water that is normally exported out of the WG gets trapped in the region near the Antarctic Peninsula.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par23">The enhanced mixing and the subsurface water accumulating in the outflow region, due to weaker outflow, brings up warmer and saltier subsurface waters, as the Warm Deep Water (WDW, Supplementary Fig. 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S7</a>). This water gets trapped at the surface outflow region because of the wind changes.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematics from the suggested mechanism in the Weddell Sea near the Antarctic Peninsula after a large eruption. The surface and vertical section in the location of SR4
     <span class="italic">/</span>WOCE stations represent the temperature anomaly for the year after the eruption (Yr + 1). The wind circulation is represented in yellow and blue thick arrows. The red arrows represent the ACC southern extension. The inflow and outflow of the WG are in green and blue, respectively. In the surface the WG is represented by the thin arrows and along the depth as dotted contours with notations for vectors coming in and out of the vertical plane.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45190_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1062" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results show that Weddell Sea dynamics are the primary driver of warming off the northern tip of the Antarctic Peninsula following major volcanic eruptions. This warming is a response of the WG to the southward shift and strengthening of the Antarctic westerlies, together with the southward wind anomaly at the WG outflow region. In this region, warm and salty WDW waters, through convective mixing, reaches surface layers. Because of the anomalous wind response, the outflow is weakened and trapped leading to the positive SST anomaly detected.</p>
</sec>
