<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Modern Eruption of Mt. Pinatubo</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of the Mt. Pinatubo eruption on the Atlantic sector of the Southern Ocean is investigated using observations (Extended Reconstructed Sea Surface Temperature version 5 - ERSSTv5
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> and Hadley Centre Sea Ice and Sea Surface Temperature - HadISST
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>) for sea surface temperature (SST) and oceanic reanalysis (Simple Ocean Data Assimilation version 3.4.1 - SODA3
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> and Ocean Reanalysis System 4 - ORAS4
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>) for SST and wind stress. We combine the observational results with the output from CESM-LME
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, which contains 15 realizations (10 runs considering all natural and anthropogenic forcing factors and 5 volcanic-only runs) of the 850–2005 period including the effects of volcanism. The use of 15 ensemble members allows an improved estimate of the uncertainty due to internal variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. All results shown here are restricted to the austral summer (DJF, see Methods for definition), since the volcanic response was identified to be larger during this season
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> and there is less presence of ice in the Weddell Sea. For the Mt. Pinatubo analysis the anomalies of SST and related fields are calculated relative to the 1980–2005 climatological mean, which contains the anthropogenic signal
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. The time series are de-trended, over the same period, to minimize the effects of long-term positive trend of increased greenhouse gases and ozone depletion forcing. The evolution of the observed SST spatial pattern for the Mt. Pinatubo eruption from the year of the eruption (Yr0, 1991) to Yr + 3 (1994) is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>DJF SST [°C] after Mt. Pinatubo eruption. Left-hand column for ERSSTv5 
     <span class="bold">[(a),(d),(g),(j)]</span>, central column for SODA 
     <span class="bold">[(b),(e),(h),(k)]</span> and right-hand column for CESM-LME 
     <span class="bold">[(c),(f),(i),(l)]</span>. Each row represents different years from 1991 (Yr0, the eruption year) to 1994 (Yr + 3). The delimited area marks the region off Antarctic Peninsula (60°-48°W, 61°-67°S).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45190_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e441" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the year of eruption (Yr0, 1991) the SST anomaly presents similar pattern in all observational data sets (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a,b</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). There is a cold anomaly of about −1 °C in the western region and in the Weddell Sea. At the same time that a warm anomaly is present in the northeast region (mostly north of 66°S) ranging from 0.3 °C (ERSSTv5 and HadISST) to 1 °C (SODA and ORAs4). On the other hand, the model ensemble average from CESM-LME (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>) shows a cold anomaly (−0.6 °C) between 54°S and 66°S and a warm anomaly off the Antarctic Peninsula in the Weddell Sea of 0.6 °C. In the year following the eruption (Yr + 1, 1992, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d,e,f</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>) the general pattern of all data sets is similar. There is negative anomaly in the SST, north of 60°S it reaches −1 °C. The warm anomaly distribution is spatially smaller than Yr0, it occurs in the eastern sector (~ 0.2 °C), but also in a small region off the Antarctic Peninsula. ERSSTv5, HadISST and ORAs4 show a smaller warming of ∼0.3 °C; SODA and CESM-LME presents higher values of about 0.8 °C.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At Yr + 2 (1993, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1g,h</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>), the warming in the Weddell Sea reaches its largest value (0.8 °C), accompanied by a warming north of the Antarctic Peninsula for all observational data. For CESM-LME ensemble average the warm anomaly has decreased, off the Antarctic Peninsula to 0.4 °C, and northward of the Peninsula to 0.2 °C. The cold anomaly has decreased for all data sets compared to the previous year. During Yr + 3 (1994, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1j,k</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>) the anomaly north of the Antarctic Peninsula almost disappears and the warm anomaly in the Weddell Sea is still present for all data sets. However, CESM-LME (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1l</a>) shows the opposite pattern.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results from all observational data sets show an overall similar pattern, albeit differences in anomalies magnitude. The same pattern is somehow present in the CESM-LME ensemble average; however, all anomalies are underestimated and spatially smoothed. CESM-LME simulation results contrasts from the observations at Yr0. In the observational data sets the warming response off the Antarctic Peninsula starts in the first year after the eruption (Yr + 1, 1992) and extends to Yr + 2 (1993), while in CESM-LME it appears in the year of the eruption (1991) and persists until 1993 (Yr0 to Yr + 2). The average of the CESM-LME volcanic-only ensemble members (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>) shows the warming response near the Peninsula only from Yr + 1 to Yr + 2 (1992 to 1993). Therefore, the warming seen at Yr0 (1991) does not seem to be related to the volcanic forcing. It should be noted that although there is warming off the Antarctic Peninsula post eruption for all data sets, the warming is not unique to this region, particularly in the observational data sets. This could indicate an issue with the simulated response to forcing in the CESM-LME, but there could also an important contribution from internal climate variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We focus here on the Antarctic Peninsula due to its potential in contributing towards future sea level rise through ice shelf failure
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. To help understand the evolution of the detected positive SST anomaly in this region, we explore the time series for a specified region off the Antarctic Peninsula (60°-48°W, 61°-67°S, area marked in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Results (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>) show that the largest averaged signal for this region after the eruption is a sea surface warming during the second subsequent year (Yr + 2, 1993): CESM-LME (0.2 ± 0.45 °C), ERSSTv5 (0.4 °C), SODA and ORAS4 (0.85 °C) and HadISST (0.7 °C). CESM-LME presents the smaller warming off the Antarctic Peninsula because of the ensemble average that showed large variability (±0.45 °C). Analysis of CESM-LME simulation results allows us to separate the volcanic signal from other forcings. The volcanic-only ensemble average shows the same positive anomaly near the Antarctic Peninsula at Yr + 2 (1993) of ∼0.2 °C (orange line in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), which attributes this warming to the volcanic forcing.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>DJF SST anomaly time series and zonal averaged wind stress changes after Mt. Pinatubo eruption. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) SST anomaly [°C] time series for the Antarctic Peninsula region (60°-48°W,61°-67°S). (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Zonal averaged wind stress [N m
     <span class="sup">−2</span>] for the South Atlantic Ocean (70°W-30°E, 40°-70°S). The dashed line represents SODA reanalysis and the continuous line CESM-LME. The grey dotted lines represent CESM-LME ensemble spread. Black lines are the climatology mean for 1980–2005.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45190_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e520" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zonal wind stress changes obtained with the results of SODA and CESM-LME reveal similar behavior (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). After the Mt. Pinatubo eruption, at Yr + 1, the prevailing westerlies have increased in magnitude (4 to 10% from the climatological mean) and its southern extension shifted southward (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). The maximum wind stress position is determined by the zonal wind stress weighted mean latitude based on the latitude where it is greater than 50% of its maximum
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. During the first year after the eruption (Yr + 1, 1992) the southward shift is of ~0.54° latitude in CESM-LME (magenta continuous line in Fig. 2b) and ~1.30° latitude in SODA (magenta dotted line in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). By 1993 (Yr + 2, blue lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>) the averaged zonal wind stress becomes smaller than the climatological mean (black lines). A southward shift
  <span class="italic">/</span>expansion and straightening
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> of the westerly wind system is related to poleward shifts in the Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. A shift of the westerlies can draw more water from deeper layers to the surface around Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> and modify subsurface temperature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aftermath of a volcanic event is an overall decrease in the SST
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, which acts to offset the anthropogenic warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. The anomalous warming observed here has the opposite response with the potential to impact sea-ice production and melt, given the high sea-ice sensitivity to the stability of the seawater column
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This indicates a potential contribution to enhance thinning of the Larsen Ice Shelf in the Antarctic Peninsula
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
