<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">Two sampling strategies were applied during this study to the five case study sites. One strategy collected samples every month from December 2014 to November 2015 and analytical work was performed by Scottish Water Scientific Services (SWSS) for raw water samples and final potable water (i.e. treated) samples. Analysis by SWSS followed a scheduled sampling programme and certified analytical protocols approved by the Drinking Water Quality Regulator (DWQR) for Scotland and the United Kingdom Accreditation Service (UKAS)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. All data were extracted and processed for statistical analysis from the Scottish Water Laboratory Information Management System (LIMS). Potable water parameters comprised ammonium, chloride, colour, conductivity, fluoride, pH, nitrate, nitrite, soluble reactive phosphate, sulphate, total organic nitrogen ratio (TON.ratio), total organic carbon (TOC), total organic nitrogen (TON), light transmittance at 220 nm, 254 nm, 270 nm, 350 nm, turbidity, bromide, bromodichloromethane, bromoform, chlorate, chloroform, dibromochloromethane, total trihalomethanes, free chlorine, temperature, total chlorine, aluminium, calcium, copper, iron, lead, magnesium, manganese, phosphorus, potassium, sodium, zinc, the hydrophobic organic fraction (HPO), transphilic organic fraction (TPI), and hydrophilic organic fraction (HPI) of TOC. Raw water parameters comprised alkalinity, ammonium, chloride, colour, conductivity, fluoride, pH, nitrate, nitrite, soluble reactive phosphate, sulphate, TON.ratio, TOC filtered, TOC, TON, light transmittance at 220 nm, 254 nm, 270 nm, 350 nm, UV transmittance, turbidity, bromide, temperature, aluminium, calcium, copper, iron, lead, magnesium, manganese, phosphorus, potassium, sodium, zinc, chlorophyll, the hydrophobic organic fraction (HPO), transphilic organic fraction (TPI), and hydrophilic organic fraction (HPI) of TOC. THMs were measured using a modified in house method based on EPA Method 524.2 for purgeable organic compounds in water by capillary column gas chromatography mass spectrometry. Fractional separation of Natural Organic Matter (NOM) into Hydrophobic (HPO), Transphilic (TPI) and Hydrophilic (HPI) fractions was performed by filtering water samples through a 0.45 µm nylon membrane (Millipore, Darmstad, Germany) before pumping the water through a series of chromatographic columns containing Amberlite® XAD 4 and XAD 7 resins (Sigma Aldrich, Darmstad, Germany) for the fractional separation. Each fraction was eluted from the resins using an alkali solution (0.1 M NaOH) and rinsed with an acidic solution (0.1 M HCl). A Total Organic Carbon analyser (Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) was used to determine the concentration of the DOC in each fraction
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. Measured potable and raw water characteristics for each calendar month were compiled Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S3</xref> as Supporting Information.
</p>
