<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">where 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>
 <sub class="sub">c</sub>, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub>, and 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>
 <sub class="sub">c</sub>, 
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub>, and 
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> refer to the per unit prices and costs of concrete and steel products, as well as fossil fuel energy, respectively; 
 <italic class="italic">u</italic>
 <sub class="sub">c</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">u</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> are parameters that indicate how many tonnes of concrete and steel can be substituted per cubic meter of panels, respectively, and 
 <italic class="italic">u</italic>
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> is the parameter that indicates the amount of bioenergy (MWh) that can be produced per cubic meter of captured harvest residues. Bioenergy displaced power and heat for residential and industrial uses, and for simplicity, we measured both energy types using MWh. Δ
 <italic class="italic">Q</italic>
 <sub class="sub">panel</sub> and Δ
 <italic class="italic">Q</italic>
 <sub class="sub">residue</sub> are the volume changes in panel production and harvest residues between the baseline and the strategies. Note that 
 <italic class="italic">u</italic>
 <sub class="sub">c</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">u</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> are constants while 
 <italic class="italic">u</italic>
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> varied across FMUs as each had a different fuel mix that was displaced by harvest residues. To be consistent with the calculation of displacement factors, we assumed that all concrete and steel products are domestically produced in BC—we included net revenue changes in those two industries in the mitigation cost, though we realized that most steel used in BC is imported and thus the profit changes in the steel industry actually occur outside of BC.
</p>
