<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linear regressions of Sahel rainfall</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our SVD analysis of the original predictors confines any trend entirely to the leading mode time series, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, i.e., the “sum” or “warming” mode, while the residual mode, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub>, i.e., the “difference” or NARI, is completely devoid of any significant trend. We model standardized Sahel rainfall 
  <span class="italic">y</span>, our predictand, by linear regression on 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> (see Section “
  <a rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec10">Use of time-dimensional singular vectors as predictors</a>” in the Appendix):
  <div id="Equ6" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">6</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M11" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ \widehat{y}=a{p}_1+b{p}_2 $$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M12" display="block" class="math">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <span class="mi">y</span>
      <span stretchy="true" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mi">a</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">p</span>
      <span class="mn">1</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span class="mi">b</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">p</span>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10584_2018_2341_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regression coefficients 
  <span class="italic">a</span> and 
  <span class="italic">b</span> and the correlation coefficients between simulated and predicted Sahel rainfall for the multi-model mean and for observations are reported in Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>. Since the SVD-based predictor time series are standardized and mutually uncorrelated, and predictand time series are standardized, the regression coefficients, 
  <span class="italic">a</span> and 
  <span class="italic">b</span>, are precisely the correlation coefficients of the predictand and corresponding predictors. In the twentieth century, correlation of the multi-model mean simulation of Sahel rainfall with its SST-based regression is 0.574 and correlation in observations is 0.633. Both terms in the regression contribute, but 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> contributes more (since 
  <span class="italic">b &gt; a</span>): late twentieth century Sahel drought is explained by the absence of North Atlantic warming, relative to warming of the global tropical oceans. The (positive) sign of 
  <span class="italic">b</span>, the regression coefficient multiplying 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> (NARI), is consistent across centuries. However, its magnitude and explanatory power vis à vis Sahel rainfall are drastically diminished in the twenty-first century. Over the twenty-first century, the correlation between the simulated Sahel rainfall and its in-sample prediction is 0.801. The multi-model ensemble achieves this high a correlation essentially through a positive correlation between Sahel rainfall and warming, captured by 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>. This happens because the coherence among models in projections of twenty-first century precipitation change has increased considerably from CMIP3 to CMIP5 (Biasutti 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2013</a>): a majority of models in CMIP5 project a future increase in Sahel rainfal to go along with warming (Schewe and Levermann 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2017</a>), in analogy to paleoclimate reconstructions of the “Green Sahara”, when summer insolation was stronger than now (de Menocal et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>). Among the models with a twenty-first century correlation coefficient between 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and Sahel rainfall larger than 0.45 (thus explaining ~ 20% of the variance with the single predictor 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>), seven of nine project future wetting (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a> in Supplementary Materials). In sum, regression models between centuries are nearly orthogonal: 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub>, analogous to the difference of predictors or NARI, explains a larger fraction of twentieth century variation, while 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, analogous to the sum of predictors or warming, alone explains the externally forced twenty-first century change.
 </p>
</sec>
