<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation concerns and co-management</div>
 <p id="Par78" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a growing interest in LEK research in order to provide complementary data for several small-scale fishery species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>]. With the difficulties and vulnerability of the marine ecosystem, LEK correctly acquired and aggregated at appropriate spatial-temporal scales becomes an important marine species conservation tool [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>]. The management of these coastal resources in fishing villages can also be better achieved by exploring data of this nature, which provide information on the ecology, behaviour and presence of these species in the environment [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par79" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present work, we present LEK data on the ecology of sardines that corroborated scientific research. Other data generated in the interviews that were not validated by the scientific literature can be tested and incorporated into new hypotheses before carrying out a scientific study. According to Drew (2005), an analysis of the components of traditional ecological knowledge can reveal new information and thus contribute to the formulation of testable hypotheses in order to improve scientific infrastructure. Silva et al. (2014) also reveal the importance of generating new scientific questions through ethnoecological data [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>]. The LEK about sardines acquired here may complement pre-existing scientific data. Due to the high cost and lack of resources for investments in traditional samplings, data of this nature become important for conservation practices and development [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par80" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the low stock levels of the sardine population in the Iberian Region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>], participation among the actors involved in fishing regulations should be carried out in an interactive manner [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>]. Ecological knowledge data on spawning and the time of fat accumulation may provide researchers an additional source of data to better understand the reproductive behaviour of this species from the fishermen’s point of view. Analysing this knowledge can contribute to a better understanding and reduction of internal conflicts between fishing managers, politicians and the community about the correct time for harvesting this species. In addition, LEK data acquired from these traditional communities are important because it reveals the most recent changes in environmental processes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par81" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The new data (trophic ecology, habitat and behaviour) that emerged during the interviews can serve as a starting point for research on the population structure of sardines. On a larger spatial scale, this kind of data, with adequate treatment, becomes important in the construction of management and conservation plans for sardines. Finally, we can note that the LEK of the sardines in Peniche should (and did) treat all stakeholders as being within a continuously adaptive framework [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
