<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Descriptive statistics of fishermen’s profiles</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 87 interviews were conducted in the fishing community of Peniche. The interview sites were predominantly in the Port of Peniche (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 71) followed by the city centre (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 16). The average age of the respondents was 58.25 years, with a minimum of 25 years and a maximum of 76 years. More than half of the interviewees (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 59) were born in Peniche and are active (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 49) in the fishing currently. According to the Portuguese educational classification, 58 individuals belonged to the 1st Cycle, 19 to the 2nd Cycle, 5 to the 3rd Cycle and 5 to Secondary Education. There were no illiterates or individuals with higher education in the sample. The fishing experience varied from 3 to 60 years, but fishing experience average was 39.08 years. The average monthly income source related to fishing, including retirees, is 810.5 Euros, ranging from 208.0 to 3000.0 Euros. A total of 50 fishermen interviewed supplement their income with income from other activities. Of these fishermen, 31 informants do so through work related to fishing (maintenance of fishing nets) and the rest in other autonomous activities.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">a</span> Main area of the fishing port of Peniche, Portugal where the interviews with the fishermen were carried out. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> A fisherman doing maintenance of purse seine nets. Credits: HO Braga. (Images published under previous consent of the participants)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13002_2017_181_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main types of boats mentioned by the fishermen were: trawlers, artisanal fishing boats, trawl nets, coastal boats, and sports boats. Trawlers were further sub-classified by fishermen into trawlers (larger boats) and “rapa” (smaller boats). Boats were measured 93 times during the interviews. Of these, the boats mentioned were as follows: trawlers (35), artisanal fishing boats (38), “rapa” (14), trawl nets (3), coastal boats (2) and sport boats (1). Six Fishermen have said they have fished in more than one type of boat, those being 3 in both artisanal fishing boats and trawlers and 3 in artisanal fishing boats and trawl nets. Only 17 of the fishermen interviewed are boat owners.</p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fishermen interviewed were questioned about their preferred schedule of sardine capture during the fishing campaigns
  <span class="italic">.</span> A cycle called "It is six in the morning and six in the afternoon" was the most cited by fishermen (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 27). Other respondents mentioned both sunrise and sunset (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 17), day and night (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 16), preferably day (N = 16), preferably night (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 9), and only at sunset (N = 2).
 </p>
</sec>
