<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishermen’s Interviews</div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Semi-structured interviews [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>] were conducted from June to September 2016 to obtain data on LEK about the European pilchard. The state-owned company Docapesca - Portos e Lotas granted permission for administering the interviews to the fishermen of Porto de Peniche. Fishermen were interviewed over successive visits in the fishing warehouses of the Port of Peniche and at the main meeting points of the fishing community. Brook and McLachlan (2008) sees this type of involvement with the community as indispensable [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. The objectives of the work and the statement of informed consent to participate in the research were provided to the fishermen through the Statement of Informed Consent (IC) [see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interviews were mainly conducted through manual transcription and occasionally with a digital audio recorder. The interviews with fishermen were conducted randomly - always before or after the arrivals and departures of the fishing teams and when they were doing net and fishing gear repairs. The interview script [see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>] was structured in 2 parts: Profile of fisherman (age, schooling, fishing time, time of residence in Peniche, income source, type and length of boat, fishing time at sea and time to catch sardines) and LEK of European pilchard (folk taxonomy, habitat, behaviour and migration, development of sardines, spawning, fat accumulation season and uses, beliefs and food taboos). The educational profile of the interviewees followed the Portuguese educational classification: A (1st Cycle: 1–4 years of study), B (2nd Cycle: 5–6 years of study), C (3rd Cycle: 7–9 years of study) and D: (Secondary Education: 10–12 years of study).
 </p>
</sec>
