<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human uses, beliefs and food taboos about European pilchard</div>
 <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great majority of fishermen (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 81) in our ethnoecological study indicated the great economic importance of Iberian sardines, 
  <span class="italic">S. pilchardus,</span> to the local community of Peniche. According to data from the Statistics Yearbook of the Central Region of 2015 made by Portugal’s National Statistical Institute (INE), sardine fisheries officially yielded approximately 1223 tons of fish and 3517 thousand Euros for the municipality of Peniche in 2015 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. This fact proves the strength of this economic activity for this region.
 </p>
 <p id="Par75" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The summer was highlighted among the respondents as being the most important season for sardine fishing, local commerce and tourism. In this season, the sardines are in the fattening stage [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>], and their fat content is high [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. The sardine in this period has a flavour and aroma that is more appreciated by the consumers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>], which makes this species more economically profitable. When the fat content is low (2–5%), this fish is less preferred by consumers and is normally sent to the canning and fish meal industries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. In other seasons, sardines are primarily used as baitfish for demersal fishing or for the canning industry [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. All sardine uses known to the scientific literature were also mentioned by the fishermen during the interviews.
 </p>
 <p id="Par76" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taboos are unwritten social rules that regulate human behaviour and can both govern and affect human social life and serve to manage a local biological resource [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>]. In the local community of Peniche, there were no significant taboos or food aversions regarding sardines by fishermen (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 6). In local communities of the Amazon and in the Atlantic Forest in Brazil, taboos and aversions were also not associated with herbivorous fish or invertebrate eaters [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>]. According to Begossi (2004), this can be an adaptive strategy of local inhabitants to fish of higher trophic levels that can more easily accumulate toxins by eating a variety of prey (plants, invertebrates and other fish) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>]. This may be one of the reasons that there are few fishermen with taboos or sardine aversions. Another hypothesis is that these social rules may be losing strength over the years due to the exodus of fishermen to other economic activities, many of whom leave due to the low economic profitability of this profession and the difficulties imposed by European Union legislation on Portuguese artisanal fisheries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par77" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding medicinal purposes, 9 fishermen indicated that sardine can treat high cholesterol levels and patients with cardiac problems. In a study about the fauna and the role of taboos in the conservation of animals in a forest reserve in southeastern Cameroon [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>], sardine (
  <span class="italic">Sardina sp.</span>) are used medicinally to treat cardiovascular diseases, which was also indicated in our survey by some fishermen (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 9). In the Sierra de Segura (Albacete, Spain), 
  <span class="italic">S. pilchardus</span> is used for medicinal purposes in the treatment of sore feet and blisters in modern times and is marketed in the Spanish markets as food [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
