<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spawning and fat accumulation season</div>
 <p id="Par68" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding reproduction, spawning of sardines occurs in batches of eggs [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. The spawning of the Atlantic sardines occurs mainly on the western coast of Portugal between the Nazaré Canyon and the Minho river and in the Cantabrian Sea [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Along the western Iberian coast, the spawning season of this pelagic species ranges from September to May, with spawning peaking in November to the north of Portugal from October to April [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Nunes and collaborators (2011) showed that the spawning peak occurs mainly between December and February along the Portuguese coast. According to fishermen from Peniche, the main months of spawning are also December, January and February. This period as a whole (from October to April) included the months most cited by the respondents (Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par69" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a variation in the duration of spawning times in the European waters of the North-East Atlantic, ranging from 3 months per year up to 8 months to the south and west of the Iberian Peninsula for large fish [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. A similar pattern was found in responses of our interviewees from Peniche, in which 72 fishermen said that the Atlantic sardine spawn time can range from one to 8 months (Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par70" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The winter was cited by 12 fishermen as being the season during which sardine spawn the most along the Portuguese Coast, and others (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 12) said that the spawning occurs 2 to 4 times a year. This point aligns with the scientific information that Atlantic sardines exhibit a prolonged spawning period during the year, with more pronounced spawning mainly in the colder months of the year [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] (Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par71" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">S. pilchardus</span> begins to store fat reserves before the breeding season between late summer and autumn [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. However, sardines can also accumulate fat from late spring to autumn [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. Most months cited by fishermen (June through October) fit the range of months for the accumulation of fat found in the scientific literature (Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
