<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The speed of migration could influence the degree to which bird species can respond to climate change (Hurlbert &amp; Liang, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Some of the predicted shifts in probability of occurrence in our study suggest that shorebirds may advance their migration calendars in response to weather. Most assessments of the effects of climate change on avian migration phenology have used data from arrival areas on the breeding grounds, and far fewer have used field data from passage areas (Gordo, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; but see La Sorte &amp; Fink, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Weather, and in particular temperature in the northern hemisphere, plays a large role in the speed and timing of migration (Chambers, Beaumont, &amp; Hudson, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Gordo, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Although photoperiod is generally accepted as the primary trigger for onset of migration (Gwinner, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>), environmental conditions in departure areas allow birds to fine‐tune their departure dates. Furthermore, weather patterns encountered 
 <italic class="italic">en route</italic> may influence progression speed in response to wind favorability and stopover duration in response to body condition and food supplies (Gordo, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Rainfall can slow passage rates, but can also greatly influence the availability of stopover habitats in the dynamic wetlands across the Great Plains (Bartuszevige et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Cariveau et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Gordo, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Sofaer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Wind, including speed and direction aloft, is also an important factor for migration (Thorup &amp; Rabol, 
 <xref rid="ece32755-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>).
</p>
