<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Knowledge production, with overlapping local and scientific forms (Agrawal, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>), is an iterative process that engages local stories, narratives, and formal and informal institutions. Creating a productive space through coproduction of knowledge removes barriers to climate change adaptation (Dilling &amp; Lemos, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Engle &amp; Lemos, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Moser &amp; Ekstrom, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0108" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Rice et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0138" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). For example, the NOAA‐funded, Great Lakes Integrated Sciences + Assessments (GLISA) Center acts as a boundary organization (Guston, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>) connecting science and researchers to end users and policymakers via knowledge networks and boundary chains (Bidwell et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Lemos, Kirchhoff, &amp; Ramprasad, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0205" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Because climate change impacts usually disproportionately affect low‐income communities and people of color (Shonkoff, Morello‐Frosch, Pastor, &amp; Sadd, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0313" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), who are underrepresented in climate change‐adaptation planning, GLISA implemented the Ready and Resilient project for these communities in Saint Paul, MN, USA (Phadke et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0124" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The project “aimed to meet [its resilience] goal via two pathways: first, to reinvigorate community networks in the city and second, to eliminate barriers to participation that members of minority and low‐income communities face” (Phadke et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0124" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The project team created chains of boundary organizations that linked GLISA to local social networks via multiple community partner organizations that were working in four Saint Paul neighborhoods (Phadke et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0124" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). This approach facilitated trust and built on existing social networks that included community partners and local residents.
</p>
