<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For a number of years the GB potato industry has been concerned about the potential establishment of the predominant European 
 <italic class="italic">Pectobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> species and strains, therefore this issue warrants further consideration. We found that the mean projected soil temperatures across all potato crop locations in GB were 15.0, 17.1, 17.3, and 15.1°C for June through to September under the low CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions 2040s scenario, and 18.0, 20.7, 21.6, and 18.7°C for June through to September under the high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions 2080s scenario. As is evident from the tuber slice assay (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205711.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>), these temperatures are all close to the optimal value for Pba lesion development and highly sub-optimal for the predominant European blackleg and soft rot pathogens (Pbr, Ppa, and Dsol). This provides evidence that temperatures are a limiting factor for the widespread establishment of these pathogens in GB. Nevertheless, in the tuber slice assay there were still significant levels of disease caused by Pbr, Ppa, and Dsol at the lower temperatures. The experimental results therefore show that the predominant European pathogens can cause disease under conditions currently seen in GB, but are not expected to outcompete Pba and become the predominant blackleg and soft rot pathogens in the future, at least based on their projected capacity to cause disease in tubers under future GB conditions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205711.g006" class="xref">Fig 6</xref>). These findings do not preclude, however, the potential for the European pathogens to gain a foothold in England and Wales, given the expected increase in the suitability of temperature conditions for these species. Both Ppa and Pbr have been confirmed in GB; an annual blackleg survey conducted in England and Wales identified Ppa and Pbr as the causes of blackleg in 7.3% and 0.8% of stocks in which the disease was found during official inspections in 2015 [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Nevertheless, there is no evidence that the incidence of disease caused by strains of pectolytic bacteria other than Pba has increased over the last 6 seasons [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. All crops in which Pbr has been found have been grown directly from seed imported from the Netherlands, with the exception of single cases in 2014 and 2015, both in seed from German origin. Ppa has also been found to cause disease in crops grown from seed of Danish, German and Netherlands as well as GB origins. The widespread origins of seed stocks infected with Pbr and Ppa suggest that both pathogens have either spread rapidly or have been circulating in European potato for many years. Dsol has also been confirmed in GB; it was first isolated on a seed potato crop (non GB origin) in England and Wales in 2007 [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], and in Scotland was found in two ware crops of non-Scottish origin in 2009 [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Results from the annual surveys strongly suggested that the principal source of Dsol was infected seed of non-UK origin [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. In all but one finding of disease caused by Dsol the planted seed stock had either been directly imported from the Netherlands or previously multiplied in England and Wales from a seed stock originating in the Netherlands. It was therefore concluded that the source of 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> infecting potatoes in England and Wales was exclusively seed of non-UK origin and that there was no evidence for horizontal spread of 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> spp. to seed stocks of UK origin. The lack of observed horizontal spread could partly be explained by the lower aggressiveness of Dsol relative to Pba under GB conditions that was highlighted in this study. Scotland implemented an extensive monitoring scheme that included growing crop surveys and post-harvest tuber testing of all non-indigenous origin seed and ware crops, and other high risk crops, such as irrigated stocks, stocks grown near watercourses contaminated or previously contaminated with 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> spp., and close contact crops (grown on farms with previous Dickeya positives). Scotland also introduced new legislation in 2010 that prescribes ‘nil tolerance’ for symptoms caused by Dickeya spp. in all classes of seed potatoes. Since the introduction of this new legislation, no new 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> infections have been found [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. There has also been a marked decline in the number of non-Scottish origin crops grown in the country, due to use by the industry of Scottish-origin seed. Thus, our third take-home message for the GB potato industry is to reinforce the importance of the current high standards of 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> monitoring as the weather in Britain warms, to prevent this pathogen gaining a foothold in potato growing areas. In addition, the ‘nil tolerance’ approach enforced by Scotland could ultimately be beneficial in England and Wales.
</p>
