<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">An important caveat to our results is the limitations of the empirical energy demand elasticities on which we base our projections. The finest-resolution internationally comparable energy-use data are the annual records of International Energy Agency (IEA) member countries. This presents an unavoidable trade-off between scope and fidelity, as top–down empirical climate responses constructed from these data have the geographic and sectoral coverage necessary to construct coarse-scale global projections of impacts, but struggle to replicate the fine spatial-, temporal scale of bottom-up local demand responses captured by empirical studies that employ subnational data over limited geographical domains
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>. In DCSW, IEA annual national fuel consumption observations in 204 countries over the years 1978–2010 are regressed on population-weighted national average exposure to numbers of days in different average temperature intervals. The resulting estimates are potentially subject to spatial and temporal aggregation bias. Large countries that span different climatic zones or incorporate regions that vary in the size and characteristics of stocks of energy-using durables (e.g., air conditioners, insulation) exhibit heterogeneous local energy demand responses to temperature. DCSW’s estimates represent the mean within-country response that is a weighted average of these effects. By exploiting very large samples of high-frequency data, other studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup> are also better able to capture the nonlinear response of energy demand to temperature with greater fidelity, by statistically identifying the distinct marginal effects of exposure to many temperature intervals—but over restricted geographic domains (California zip codes, US regions, Mexican municipalities, or EU countries). By contrast, IEA data’s coarse resolution only permits identification of the effects of days with average temperatures of &lt;12.5 °C and &gt;27 °C, with each additional hot day or cold day having the same effect, irrespective of how far into the tails of the temperature it happened to be.
</p>
