<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We instead performed a systematic review of Web of Science, Medline, BIOSIS, the Cochrane library, OpenGrey, and Google Scholar to generate a pooled estimate of the dose–response curve between ragweed and RSR based on all available studies that met a clearly established set of criteria. We used the following major search terms as Medical Subject Headings (MeSH) and all-field text words, as appropriate: immunology, pollen, aeroallergen, allergy, allergens, atopy, sensitize (or sensitise), sensitized (or sensitised), sensitization (or sensitisation), hypersensitivity, skin test, and Immunoglobulin E. The initial search identified 1,923 potentially relevant papers (see Figure S1). A first filter of the search results (see Table S1) retained 50 papers that included estimates of RSRs for human populations within Europe (RSRs for 144 locations in total). Two authors (M.A. and I.L.) independently screened the remaining papers and extracted the following study information using standardized forms: location (country, place name), time period, sample characteristics (number, age, and population-based or allergy patients), the reactivity marker used (e.g., skin prick test, specific ragweed Immunoglobulin E), and the RSR. We then further excluded 15 papers that did not clearly report the sensitivity to ragweed alone, that involved a highly restricted sample population (e.g., institutionalized elderly, weed-sensitive allergy patients, patients with symptoms restricted to the ragweed season), that were undertaken more than two decades ago (i.e., pre-1993), or that had a small sample size (&lt; 50 individuals). Finally, for studies that reported multiple RSRs at a single location (such as a series of annual sensitization observations, observations over several time periods, or observations for more than one age cohort) we selected a single RSR value representing the baseline period and the general population. Ultimately, the review comprised 66 location-specific RSRs from 35 studies and 20 European countries (see Table S2).</p>
