<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>We thank T. Moon for comments on an earlier version of the manuscript, X. Fettweis for providing MAR simulations, and P. Langen for assistance with the HIRHAM snowpack model. Resources supporting this work were provided by the NASA High-End Computing (HEC) Program through the NASA Advanced Supercomputing (NAS) Division at Ames Research Center and by the University of Alaska’s Research Computing Systems (RCS). Open-source software was used at all stages, in particular NumPy (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.numpy.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.numpy.org</span>), CDO (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://code.mpimet.mpg.de/projects/cdo/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://code.mpimet.mpg.de/projects/cdo/</span>), matplotlib (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://matplotlib.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://matplotlib.org/</span>), QGIS3 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://qgis.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://qgis.org/</span>), and TimeManager (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/anitagraser/TimeManager" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/anitagraser/TimeManager</span>). 
  <span class="bold">Funding:</span> A.A. was supported by NASA grant NNX16AQ40G and NSF grant PLR-1603799; A.A., M.A.F., and D.J.B. were supported by NASA grant NNX17AG65G; R.H. was supported by NSF grant PLR11603815 and NASA grant NSSC17K0566; R.M. was supported by the European Research Council under the European Community Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/ 2007-2013)/ERC grant agreement 610055 as part of the ice2ice project; and S.A.K. was funded, in part, by Carlsbergfondet and the Danish Council for Independent Research. 
  <span class="bold">Author contributions:</span> A.A., M.A.F., and M.T. jointly developed the experimental design with contributions from R.H. D.J.B. designed and performed the uncertainty analysis, and A.A. performed and analyzed the simulations. C.K. implemented all project-related code changes. R.M. processed firn depth and climate forcing from HIRHAM5, and S.A.K. provided uplift rates. All authors jointly wrote the manuscript and contributed with interpretation. 
  <span class="bold">Competing interests:</span> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <span class="bold">Data and materials availability:</span> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors. The PISM code is available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/pism/pism/tree/v1.0-millennium-study" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/pism/pism/tree/v1.0-millennium-study</span>. The model simulations are archived at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://arcticdata.io" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://arcticdata.io</span> (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.18739/A2Z60C21V" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.18739/A2Z60C21V</span>) and HIRHAM5 RCM output at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://polarportal.dk/en/groenlands-indlandsis/nbsp/links/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://polarportal.dk/en/groenlands-indlandsis/nbsp/links/</span>. All datasets used in this study are publicly available except the uplift rates, which may be requested from S.A.K.
 </p>
</div>
