<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">Networks are gaining attention as an effective means of capturing different forms of participation and relations under one umbrella (Borgatti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2009</xref>; Hanneman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2005</xref>; Ibarra and Andrews 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">1993</xref>; Scott and Carrington 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">2011</xref>; Wasserman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" class="xref">1994</xref>). Network analysis is an appropriate building block for RAP as it offers both a theoretical framework for understanding the causes and consequences of relationships and a methodological framework for visualizing and measuring these relationships (Marsden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">1990</xref>; McCarty and Bernard 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2003</xref>). Networks can provide essential resources, knowledge, and information that otherwise are not available within a single actor (Bodin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2006</xref>; Newman and Dale 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2005</xref>). They can also influence and spread effective agricultural practices, thus enhancing widespread action for adaptation. Networks help identify key actors, gatekeepers and bridges (Burt 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2002</xref>; Granovetter 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">1973</xref>) in the adaptation structure who, with the right support, can offer valuable contributions. Detailed network maps are created from the interactions of actors for one or more types of relationships, which are then measured applying network metrics (Borgatti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2009</xref>; Wasserman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" class="xref">1994</xref>). The mapping and measurement of networks are important to understand and visualise the overall structure and the different pathways linking all levels within the adaptation regime.
</p>
