<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have developed and presented an automated approach for evaluating the effectiveness of marine reserves in Mexico, and perhaps around the world. Here we highlight MAREA’s utility for evidence-based management, and comment on a few of its shortcomings. The findings from Isla Natividad are used purely to validate the relevance of MAREA rather than to discuss particularities of the marine reserve effectiveness, which has been described before [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref010">10</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref043">43</a>]. We use examples from the case study to build on the utility of MAREA and discuss ways in which results can be interpreted to inform management.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The causal inference techniques used by MAREA have been suggested [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref047">47</a>] and used [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref021">21</a>] before in other ad hoc studies. This approach reduces ambiguity in the interpretation of results. For example, invertebrate density decreased through time inside and outside of the reserve (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0191821.g005" href="#pone.0191821.g005">Fig 5h</a>). In this case, a before–after evaluation of the reserve (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> ignoring the control site) would have incorrectly concluded that the reserve failed to protect invertebrates. On the other hand, a control–impact approach (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> compare reserve vs. control site only in 2016) would have identified higher densities inside the reserve, concluding that the reserve increases invertebrate density. However, by executing a formal difference-in-differences approach for causal inference, MAREA identifies the changes through time and across sites, and estimates the effect of the reserve on density at 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 91.21 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). This approach reveals that invertebrate densities decrease in both sites through time, but the decrease is faster for the control site, thus yielding a positive value for 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The approach used by MAREA to estimate the effect of the reserve on biological indicators requires cautious interpretation of the results. The value of the 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>2</sub> coefficient represents the difference between the temporal trends of the reserve and control sites [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref021">21</a>]. As exemplified by the case of invertebrate densities, a positive value (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>2</sub> &gt; 0) does not necessarily indicate an increase in the indicator through time, but rather a positive difference with respect to the temporal trend of the control site. The inverse occurs for negative values of 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MAREA provides in-depth analysis and a convenient snapshot overview of the effect of the reserve, allowing users to rapidly identify trends. However, users must interpret multiple indicators at a time to better understand the results. For example, with additional knowledge of local environmental variability (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> indicator B5: Natural Disturbance), we can better understand the trends in invertebrate densities. As reported before [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref008">8</a>], hypoxic conditions that have occurred in Isla Natividad can cause decreases in invertebrate densities, and reserves buffer the negative effect. While MAREA automates the analysis and makes results replicable, proper interpretation will still depend on the user. Results produced by MAREA can only aid in management and decision making when results have been correctly interpreted.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Socioeconomic and governance indicators typically lack a control site, which impede us from using the causal inference techniques employed to measure biological changes [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref025">25</a>]. However, we can still extract useful information from them. Again, by combining results from multiple indicators, MAREA can provide insights into the effect of the reserve. For example, lobster and sea cucumber have shown increases in densities, landings, and income. We cannot conclude that landings and income from these species have increased due to the reserve, but we can at least conclude that landings have not decreased. While further information on market behavior of each fishery is needed, these results provide insights into the state of the reserve and its associated fisheries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As for the governance information, it is difficult to establish causal links between the state of the reserve and the governance structures present in the community. However, providing a single platform (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> scorecard) or document (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> technical report) where biological, socioeconomic, and governance information is comprehensively included can aid in management. By using MAREA, this information will be reported across reserves in a standardized way, and can help managers identify overarching patterns across sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By making results straightforward to interpret, MAREA may also assist in communication with a broader stakeholder community. While stakeholder involvement in the design and implementation phases of marine reserves is important, that may not be sufficient for ensuring long-term buy-in or success. The scorecard is easily understandable by experts and non-experts, and can be used as an effective tool for communicating the results of annual evaluations. Additionally, the technical report can serve as a tool for managers and scientists to rapidly produce and communicate information at a more technical level.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We recognize that the seven objectives and 29 indicators used by MAREA might not fully describe a reserve in countries other than Mexico. In order to ensure the applicability of the tool to reserves in other countries, further testing in other regions should take place. However, the proposed objectives and indicators provide a starting point to perform the evaluation, to which managers and users can add other indicators (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> larval dispersal or connectivity) that are relevant to their reserve. Furthermore, MAREA’s value is that it provides a free, simple, and replicable way to perform rigorous impact analysis. The tool can easily be used by fishers, CSO members, and managers in government agencies, providing transparency of the analysis and results. In addition, it can empower and enable local managers and fishers to respond to local change and adapt by allowing direct and easy access to the information.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An evident limitation of MAREA is its dependence on data obtained through a BACI design, and the amount of samples needed to estimate coefficients in 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0191821.e001" href="#pone.0191821.e001">Eq (1)</a>. It is not uncommon for control sites or baselines to be absent. Properly designing marine reserves by identifying control sites and establishing a baseline before the implementation of the reserve is enough to overcome this issue; reserves for which there is no control site and baseline cannot be evaluated with MAREA. Typical underwater surveys require that at least 12—16 transects are performed for each site (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> reserve and control) each year. This provides at least 48 samples (12 samples per site, per year), enough to avoid overfitting 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0191821.e001" href="#pone.0191821.e001">Eq (1)</a>. However, these problems can be easily avoided during the design and implementation phases by anticipating what data will be needed in the eventual evaluation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To the best of our knowledge, MAREA is the first tool designed to evaluate marine reserves. Previous work [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref023">23</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref025">25</a>] addressed MPA evaluation and provided the foundation for our contribution. However, these did not intended to create user-friendly tools to aid in the evaluation. Conservation management tools that automatize complex calculations can have an important impact in management [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref064">64</a>]. The use of open data science enables the creation of open-access tools that can address technical gaps and inprove management [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref028">28</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effectiveness of marine reserves continues to be a matter of debate [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref044">44</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref065">65</a>]. With current targets set to increase ocean protection, it is important that we understand the effects of our interventions [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref038">38</a>] so we can better inform management [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref047">47</a>]. It is therefore important that academics, managers, fishers, and CSOs have access to open access tools like MAREA. This is particularly relevant for Mexico and other Latin American countries, where management agencies are often understaffed and underfunded [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref066">66</a>], or where materials are often not available in their language. In this context, MAREA provides a simple and replicable way to align management objectives with performance indicators. The proposed methodologies, especially the way in which biological indicators are evaluated, provide valuable information for managers. We acknowledge there is room for improvement in the way in which socioeconomic and governance data are analyzed. Despite this, providing a unifying platform where all indicators can be analyzed and comprehensively presented represents a valuable step towards effective evidence-–based management [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref047">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first release of MAREA is now available, and it will continue to be developed and maintained to keep up to date with the literature. This process will incorporate new features, and enhance current ones, aiming to improve user experience and expand the scope of the analysis. Other modifications may also include addition of more objectives and indicators to ensure applicability in other regions, full translation into other languages to avoid any ambiguities introduced via the automatic translation, or reporting effects over time in percentages to aid interpretation. Yet, we believe that this first release represents a major step towards effective, replicable evaluation and management of marine reserves.</p>
</sec>
