<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unsustainable fishing practices threaten biodiversity, conservation, economic and social outcomes [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref002">2</a>]. Marine Protected Areas (MPAs; and marine reserves, in which all extractive efforts are prohibited) are frequently proposed to aid in the recovery of fish and invertebrate stocks [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref006">6</a>] by limiting or restricting fishing effort and gears.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empirical evidence shows that MPAs increase biomass [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref007">7</a>], enhance resilience to climatic impacts [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref009">9</a>], and preserve genetic diversity [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref010">10</a>]. Compared to MPAs that grant partial protection, marine reserves have higher levels of biomass, density, richness, and larger organisms [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref003">3</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref011">11</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref013">13</a>]. However, these effects are often measured as biological changes within the reserves through time, and many lack a control site for comparison [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref014">14</a>].This approach does not account for other factors (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> system-level changes in productivity caused by predatory release [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref015">15</a>]; or favorable environmental conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref016">16</a>]) for which one must control [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref017">17</a>] in order to causally attribute a biological change to the reserve. Other studies have used a control-impact comparison approach that uses control sites but does not address temporal variability [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref018">18</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref020">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A smaller fraction of studies have used a before-after-control-impact (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> BACI) design comparing reserves to control sites before and after implementation [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref021">21</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref022">22</a>], which allows the use of causal inference techniques that estimate the effect of the reserve. For example, in ref [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref021">21</a>] authors use a BACI design and observe increases in lobster catches –a proxy for abundances– after reserve implementation for protected and control sites. However, the temporal changes in the reserve were greater than in the control site, suggesting a positive effect of the reserve on lobster catches. But even when proper causal inference can be drawn, results are often different across reserves. Effects of reserves on ecological and economic outcomes are highly heterogeneous, and often depend on the specific ecological, economic, and social context.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standardization of marine reserve evaluation is not new. The IUCN framework “How is your MPA doing?” [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref023">23</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref024">24</a>] provides a comprehensive list of biological, socioeconomic, and governance indicators, and insights into how these may be measured or collected. But this framework stops short of analysis, and provides a user with little guidance about establishing causal inference about the reserve. Recent work [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref025">25</a>] integrates these three dimensions via the Social Ecological Systems Framework [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref026">26</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref027">27</a>] and suggests the use of causal inference techniques to provide a measure of the effect of conservation interventions. However, neither of these approaches provide a user-friendly tool that ensures replicability and scalability of the analysis, particularly when used by the fishers and decision makers themselves.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An increasingly popular way to make science accessible, reproducible, scalable, and replicable is through Open Science and the development of open-access tools [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref028">28</a>]. The Ocean Health Index [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref029">29</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref030">30</a>], for example, successfully standardized a way to measure the health and benefits of the oceans. This approach has been implemented at a global scale, but also at country-level [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref031">31</a>], and regionally [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref032">32</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref033">33</a>]. Open access tools are not limited to conservation, and have also been developed to evaluate fishery performance [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref034">34</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref035">35</a>], design territorial use rights for fisheries (TURFs, [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref036">36</a>]), and improve decision making in the hydro power industry [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref037">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The purpose of this paper is to describe a user-friendly tool, called “MAREA”, to rigorously systematize the evaluation of marine reserve effectiveness in terms of fisheries and marine conservation goals. The tool is in the form of an open-source application that uses state-of-the-art methods from program evaluation to compare a reserve to control sites along a number of biological, economic, and governance dimensions. We first provide a list of commonly stated management objectives and match them to appropriate indicators. We then develop a simple approach to analyzing these indicators building on causal inference techniques [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref021">21</a>], which help us understand the effect of management interventions [
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref025">25</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191821.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191821.ref038">38</a>]. To implement the analytical approach, we introduce the Marine Reserve Evaluation Application (MAREA), an open source, web–based tool that automates the framework described in this paper and enables its broader use. Finally, we present a case study on the evaluation of a marine reserve established by the fishers of Isla Natividad (Mexico) in 2006, to demonstrate the potential of MAREA.
 </p>
</sec>
