<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3695913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840843</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-07766</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068292</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intra-Seasonal Flexibility in Avian Metabolic Performance Highlights the Uncoupling of Basal Metabolic Rate and Thermogenic Capacity</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Flexibility in Metabolic Performance</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>Magali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lewden</surname><given-names>Agn&#x000e8;s</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>Fran&#x000e7;ois</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>D&#x000e9;partement de biologie, chimie et g&#x000e9;ographie, Universit&#x000e9; du Qu&#x000e9;bec &#x000e0; Rimouski, Rimouski (QC), Canada, Groupe de recherche sur les environnements nordiques BOREAS, Rimouski, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line><institution>Centre d&#x02019;Etudes Nordiques</institution>, Qu&#x000e9;bec (QC), Canada, Centre de la Science de la Biodiversit&#x000e9; du Qu&#x000e9;bec, Montr&#x000e9;al, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Munn</surname><given-names>Adam&#x000a0;J.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>The University of Wollongong, Australia</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>Magali.Petit@uqar.qc.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: MP AL FV. Performed the experiments: MP AL. Analyzed the data: MP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: FV. Wrote the manuscript: MP FV. </p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e68292</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Petit et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Petit et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Stochastic winter weather events are predicted to increase in occurrence and amplitude at northern latitudes and organisms are expected to cope through phenotypic flexibility. Small avian species wintering in these environments show acclimatization where basal metabolic rate (BMR) and maximal thermogenic capacity (M<sub>SUM</sub>) are typically elevated. However, little is known on intra-seasonal variation in metabolic performance and on how population trends truly reflect individual flexibility. Here we report intra-seasonal variation in metabolic parameters measured at the population and individual levels in black-capped chickadees (<named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Poecile</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">atricapillus</named-content></italic>
</named-content>). Results confirmed that population patterns indeed reflect flexibility at the individual level. They showed the expected increase in BMR (6%) and M<sub>SUM</sub> (34%) in winter relative to summer but also, and most importantly, that these parameters changed differently through time. BMR began its seasonal increase in November, while M<sub>SUM</sub> had already achieved more than 20% of its inter-seasonal increase by October, and declined to its starting level by March, while M<sub>SUM</sub> remained high. Although both parameters co-vary on a yearly scale, this mismatch in the timing of variation in winter BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> likely reflects different constraints acting on different physiological components and therefore suggests a lack of functional link between these parameters.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Discovery grant (9045333) from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (NSERC) of Canada <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/index_eng.asp">http://www.nserc-crsng.gc.ca/index_eng.asp</ext-link> and Nouveaux chercheurs grant (132032) from the Fonds de Recherche du Qu&#x000e9;bec sur la nature et les technologies <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fqrnt.gouv.qc.ca">http://www.fqrnt.gouv.qc.ca</ext-link>/ to FV. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>With global changes comes a higher frequency of unpredictable weather events [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. These short-term environmental fluctuations can affect animal species through changes in demography, phenology [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and genetic variability [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], for example by disturbing the timing of reproduction [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] or by favouring genotypes that produce flexible rather than stable phenotypes [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This may be particularly important for northern latitude species where warming is accelerated relative to lower latitudes [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], especially in winter [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and where the occurrence and amplitude of short term stochastic events are predicted to increase [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Phenotypic flexibility, the rapid and reversible transformations of phenotypic traits that allow individuals to adjust their behaviour and physiology to predictable or stochastic changes in the environment [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], should provide a certain capacity to buffer these variations [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, in natural settings, little is known on how animals adjust their phenotype to intra-seasonal changes in ecological conditions [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Winter at northern latitudes is typically considered a challenging season for resident bird species [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Since they remain active throughout the cold season, low ambient temperatures force these animals to increase energy expenditure for thermoregulation [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] while short days, snow and ice cover may reduce foraging time and food availability [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In small bodied species, thermoregulatory constraints are exacerbated because of their large surface area relative to volume, which increases heat loss [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], in addition to their limited ability to carry thick insulative plumage. Small birds therefore use physiological adjustments to improve cold tolerance [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and their chances of survival. Seasonal acclimatization is typically associated with a winter increase in metabolism visible in parameters such as basal metabolic rate (BMR; physiological maintenance cost) and summit metabolic rate (M<sub>SUM</sub>; maximal thermogenic capacity) [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, although cold acclimatization has been investigated for decades [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], most field studies lack the required temporal resolution to address questions regarding individual physiological adjustments in response to intra-seasonal variations in ambient conditions [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Studies typically compare phenotypic traits such as BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> on a seasonal basis, comparing values from individuals captured in winter with data collected on different individuals captured in summer [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>To face stochastic winter conditions, small birds could use two mutually non-exclusive strategies. First, they could maintain a constant and elevated winter metabolism. This strategy would increase survival during extreme thermal events but it would also presumably be associated with high and often unnecessary maintenance costs. Second, birds could use phenotypic flexibility to rapidly adjust their physiology to prevailing conditions. In this situation, however, individuals may have to invest considerable resources in physiological readjustments (e.g. adjustment in organ size [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]). As far as we know, only two studies have provided data on intra-seasonal metabolic changes in response to winter climate variations in small free-living birds [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]; both of these reflected a phenotypic flexibility strategy. Swanson and Olmstead [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] observed that cold ambient temperature was associated with elevated metabolic performance in dark-eyed juncos (<named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Junco</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">hyemalis</named-content></italic>
</named-content>), black-capped chickadees (<named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Poecile</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">atricapillus</named-content></italic>
</named-content>) and American tree sparrows (<named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Spizella</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">arborea</named-content></italic>
</named-content>). This was visible at the population level on a between-year timescale for BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> and on a between-month (i.e. intra-seasonal) timescale for M<sub>SUM</sub> (there were not enough data for testing the effect on BMR). Furthermore, ambient temperature preceding measurements appeared to affect metabolic performance within relatively short periods, between one and 30 days, depending on the species. Similar findings were reported by Broggi et al. [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] in great tits (<named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Parus</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">major</named-content></italic>
</named-content>) where BMR changed throughout winter and responded to ambient temperature averaged over the preceding week.</p><p>If ambient temperature exerts such a proximal effect on winter metabolic performance, one would therefore expect adjustments in metabolic parameters over the course of the season, with peak capacity observable at the coldest time of winter. However, data on the shape of metabolic transformations within seasons are lacking, albeit being called for [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Furthermore, although seasonal changes in metabolic performance are interpreted as a clear and evident example of phenotypic flexibility in response to winter constraints [<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], within individual data to support this statement are still lacking for free-living wintering birds. Our understanding of intra-seasonal and intra-individual variation in metabolic performance of birds wintering at northern latitudes therefore remains poor.</p><p>Here we report results of a study where we followed intra-seasonal changes in metabolic performance over two consecutive winters in a population of black-capped chickadees from eastern Canada. We measured changes in BMR to assess variations in physiological maintenance costs and we measured changes in M<sub>SUM</sub> to follow adjustments in winter thermogenic capacity. These measurements were also performed in August of each year to obtain a summer reference point for comparison. Our first objective for this part of the study was to determine patterns of variation in BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> within winter. We expected a gradual increase in metabolic performance beginning in autumn to reach a peak at the coldest of winter (i.e. January&#x02013;February), followed by a gradual decline to reach summer values [<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Our second objective was to confirm that these patterns were also visible within individuals and therefore confirm that observations at the population level reflect individual phenotypic flexibility.</p><p>Previous studies suggested a functional link between BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] but some evidence rather suggests that these variables reflect physiological systems acting independently [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. BMR would mainly reflect energy requirements of internal organs [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] while M<sub>SUM</sub> would reflect the size of muscles involved in active shivering [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Given recent contrasting findings, including in our own model species [<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], we also had an interest in testing the relationship between BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> with an extensive dataset.</p><p>Metabolic expansibility (ME), the ratio of maximal over minimal metabolic rates (M<sub>SUM</sub> / BMR) [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], is interpreted as the capacity of an organism to increase its level of heat production for a given size of metabolic machinery [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Therefore, variations in ME should also be a useful variable to evaluate co-adjustment of physiological maintenance costs and thermogenic capacity. We thus report inter- and intra-individual variation in ME throughout winter.</p><p>To meet our objectives, 228 individuals were captured during winters 2010 and 2010-11 and had their metabolic performance measured within the following 24h. Of this number, 56 individuals were recaptured and remeasured between one and five times within a same winter.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2.1"><title>(a) Capture and handling</title><p>This study was carried out within the For&#x000ea;t d&#x02019;Enseignement et de Recherche Macp&#x000e8;s, Qu&#x000e9;bec, Canada (48&#x000b0; 30&#x02019; N, 68&#x000b0; 52 W) between January and March 2010 (n = 56) and from October 2010 to March 2011 (n&#x000a0;= 149). Data from summer individuals were collected in August 2010 (n = 12) and 2011 (n = 11). To attract chickadees and facilitate capture, 18 feeding stations were set up within the forest with an average distance between stations of 1.9 km (see 30,32 for a description of the stations). Feeders were regularly filled with black sunflower seeds. On capture days, feeders were removed and homemade potter traps (15 cm x 15 cm x 15 cm) baited with seeds were placed on a tray installed on a wooden fence pole. All birds were caught during morning (between 08:00 and 13:00) and removed from traps within one minute of capture. Weather stations in the forest [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] recorded temperature data allowing us to track ambient temperatures over the two years of the study.</p><p>Birds caught for the first time were banded with a USGS numbered metal band as well as a unique combination of three plastic color bands to allow further identification from a distance. For each capture, birds were first weighed then had the length of their beak, head plus beak, tarsus, tail and wing measured [<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Following these measurements and depending on capture success, up to four birds per day were brought to the field station for metabolic measurement.</p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title>(b) Ethics statement</title><p>All bird manipulations were approved by the animal care committee of the Universit&#x000e9; du Qu&#x000e9;bec &#x000e0; Rimouski (CPA-37-09-68) and have been conducted under scientific and banding permits from Environment Canada - Canadian Wildlife Service (Permit Number: 10704H).</p></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title>(c) Respirometry</title><p>Once at the field station, birds were maintained in separate cages (39 cm x 43 cm x 31 cm) supplied with food (sunflower seed) and water <italic>ad libitum</italic> until measurements were made. Cages were kept in a room receiving natural light through a window and maintained quiet to avoid disturbance. At around 13: 00, we began M<sub>SUM</sub> trials by measuring two birds in parallel using Fox, Box oxygen analyzers (Sable Systems, Las Vegas, NV, USA). This was followed by a second trial on the remaining two birds, which began before 15: 00. Briefly, birds were first weighed (&#x000b1; 0.1 g) and body temperature was measured with a thermocouple reader (Omega model HH-25KC, NIST-traceable, Omega, Montr&#x000e9;al, Qc, Canada) using a copper-constantan thermocouple inserted into the cloacae approximately 10 mm deep. Then, birds were put in a stainless steel metabolic chamber fitted with a perch and were exposed to helox gas (21% oxygen, 79% helium) using an average flow rate of 1109 ml.min<sup>-1</sup> controlled by mass flow valves (Sierra Instruments, Side-Trak&#x000ae; Model 840 (Monterey, CA, USA)). We recorded oxygen consumption of each bird using a sliding cold exposure protocol [<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] with a decrease in ambient temperature of 3&#x000b0;C every 20 minutes, starting at 0&#x000b0;C in winter and at 6&#x000b0;C in summer. We ended the trials when birds became hypothermic, which was easily identifiable in real time as a steady decline in oxygen consumption for several minutes. Body temperature was measured again immediately after taking birds out of their chambers. We assumed a bird had reached its M<sub>SUM</sub> when body temperature after a trial was &#x02264; 38&#x000b0;C [<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] (mean body temperature after M<sub>SUM</sub> measurement = 33.6 &#x000b1; 0.2&#x000b0;C). Data from individuals showing a body temperature above this threshold were discarded. Birds were weighed again after measurements and the average body mass was used for the M<sub>SUM</sub> analysis. Birds were then brought back to their cage with food and water <italic>ad libitum</italic> until BMR measurement starting at 19: 00.</p><p>Each day, all four birds had their BMR measured simultaneously overnight (from 19: 00 to 06:00). Individuals were maintained at 30&#x000b0;C throughout the trial (within the thermoneutral zone for this species [<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]) and received a constant flow of air. Birds were weighed before and after measurements and average mass was used in BMR analyses.</p><p>Oxygen analyzers were adjusted each day to 20.95% using CO<sub>2</sub>-free dry air and mass flow valves were carefully calibrated for air and helox using a bubble-O-meter (Dublin, OH, USA) once per winter. Metabolic rate calculations were done with ExpeData software, v 1.2.6 (Sable Systems, Las Vegas, NV, USA). M<sub>SUM</sub> and BMR calculations were based respectively on the highest and lowest averaged 10 minutes of oxygen consumption per measurement sequence according to Lighton&#x02019;s equation 10.1 [<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The instantaneous measurement technique [<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] was used for M<sub>SUM</sub> while BMR was calculated using the steady state approach. The duration of BMR trials (around 11 hours) insured that birds were post-absorptive at time of BMR measurement (which was obtained after 6 h 40 min &#x000b1; 8&#x000a0;min of recording on average). Since wintering birds use mostly lipids as substrate for shivering [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], we estimated energy consumption using a constant equivalent of 19.8 kJ.L<sup>-1</sup> O<sub>2</sub> and converted to Watts [<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. After BMR measurements, birds were put back in their cage with access to food and water until release at capture site around 2 hours later.</p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title>(d) Sexing individuals</title><p>130 individuals (56 females and 74 males) caught for this study were sexed by PCR [<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] or dissection. We determined sex of the remaining 98 birds using their morphometric data in a discriminant analysis [<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Overall, 85 individuals were identified as females, 107 as males and 36 birds remained undetermined.</p></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title>(e) Statistical analysis</title><sec id="s2.5.1"><title>Inter-seasonal variation</title><p>We first studied inter-seasonal variation in body mass and metabolic performance. To do so, we used a linear mixed effect model (LME) to test for effects of &#x0201c;year&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;season&#x0201d; (winter or summer), &#x0201c;sex&#x0201d; (male, female or undetermined) and interaction term &#x0201c;year*season&#x0201d;, using bird ID as random parameter, on whole BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME. We also included the variable &#x0201c;relative time of capture&#x0201d; (time since sunrise / day length, hereafter &#x0201c;time of capture&#x0201d;) for body mass analyses. We then used the same model including body mass as a covariate to analyse variations in mass-independent metabolic performance.</p></sec><sec id="s2.5.2"><title>Intra-seasonal variation</title><p>To study intra-seasonal variation (i.e. within winter) in parameters of metabolic performance, we used the same model but this time testing for the effects of &#x0201c;year&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;month&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sex&#x0201d; and the interaction term &#x0201c;year*month&#x0201d;, again using bird ID as random parameter. &#x0201c;Time of capture&#x0201d; was also considered when analysing variations in body mass. To study effects on mass-independent variables we repeated the analyses including body mass as a covariate.</p><p>We saved residuals from those LMEs to study relationships between whole and mass-independent winter BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>.</p><p>Variables were removed from models when non-significant and results from final models are presented. In cases where the interaction term year*month was significant, we ran separate analyses by year. We used Tukey tests to investigate differences between months and between sexes. Analyses on metabolic parameters showed the same final patterns whether or not body mass was included as a covariate. We therefore present results for mass-independent BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME. Data for these variables without mass corrections are available in the Supporting Information files (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068292.s001">table S1</xref>-S2). In all cases, residuals were tested for normality using the one sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Population data are presented as least square means &#x000b1; s.e.m., and intra-individual data are shown as predicted values (original values corrected for the effects that were found significant at the population level).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>(a) Temperature</title><p>During the first winter of the study (2009-2010), chickadees experienced mean daily temperatures below 0&#x000b0;C from December to March (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">table 1)</xref>. The coldest average temperature was recorded in December, and the lowest minimal temperature was measured in February. During the second year (2010-2011), mean temperatures fell below 0&#x000b0;C from November to March and reached their coldest mean ambient and minimal values in January (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">table 1)</xref>. However, the following months remained relatively cold as minimal temperatures changed by less than one degree in the next two months. Overall, the second winter of the study was colder than the first and had more months with minimal temperatures below -25&#x000b0;C.</p><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Monthly minimal, mean and maximal temperatures (&#x000b0; C) recorded by weather station within the study area.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">2009/2010<hr/>
</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">2010/2011<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">min</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">max</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">October</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">November</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-12.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">December</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-20.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-16.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">January</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-21.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-26.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">February</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-24.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-26.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">March</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-15.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-26.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">August</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>(Data for August 2011 not available)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>(b) Inter-seasonal variation in body mass and metabolic performance</title><p>Peak values in average metabolic performance were recorded in February for both years (see below). We therefore calculated inter-seasonal variation in body mass and metabolic parameters between peak of winter and summer using values measured in February and August.</p><p>Average body mass did not vary between years or seasons but positively varied with time of capture (F<sub>1,70</sub> = 11.2, p &#x0003c; 0.01). Males were also on average 10.5% heavier than females (sex: F<sub>2,112</sub> = 59.8, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001, males: 12.06 &#x000b1; 0.07 g; females: 10.91 &#x000b1; 0.08 g, undetermined 11.31 &#x000b1; 0.10 g, Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.0001). BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME were all influenced by body mass (BMR: F<sub>1,112</sub> = 32.5, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.0001; M<sub>SUM</sub>: F<sub>1,109</sub> = 29.6, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.0001, ME: F<sub>1,98</sub> = 5.0, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05). Mass-independent BMR was 5.9% higher in winter relative to summer (season: F<sub>1,116</sub> = 16.5, p &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g001">Figure 1A)</xref> while average values for mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> were 34.2% higher at the peak of winter relative to August (season: F<sub>1,115</sub> = 135.5, p &#x0003c; 0.0001). However, this latter effect depended on the year (year*season: F<sub>1,117</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.2, p &#x0003c; 0.01). Mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> was 13.4% higher in the first winter relative to the second, which led to a M<sub>SUM</sub> being 41.9% higher than in summer during the first year compared to a 26.4% seasonal difference during the second year (Tukey: p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001 in all cases) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g001">Figure 1B)</xref>. Mass-independent ME was 25.0% higher in winter (6.2 x BMR) than in summer (5.0 x BMR, season: F<sub>1,111</sub> = 56.9, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001) and this effect was also dependent on the year (year*season: F<sub>1,109</sub> = 5.2, p &#x0003c; 0.05). Mass-independent ME was 11.4% higher in the first winter than in the second with a ME 32.7% higher relative to summer in the first year compared to a 17.4% difference between winter and summer during the second year (Tukey: p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001 in all cases) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g001">Figure 1C)</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0068292-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068292.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Inter-seasonal variation of mass-independent BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME.</title><p>Data are least square means for BMR (A), M<sub>SUM</sub> (B) and ME (C) controlling for year, season, sex and body mass with bird ID as random parameter. Different letters indicate significant difference between seasons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0068292.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3.3"><title>(c) Intra-seasonal variation of body mass and metabolic performance</title><p>As for the inter-seasonal analyses, we found no year effect on average body mass in wintering black-capped chickadees. However, body mass varied over time within winter (month: F<sub>6,212</sub> = 8.3, p &#x0003c; 0.0001) increasing by 4.0% between October and December (Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.01) and remained constant until August (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g002">Figure 2</xref>, Tukey: p = 0.07). Mass also differed between sexes (F<sub>2,218</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;146.8, p &#x0003c; 0.0001) with males being on average 11.5% heavier than females (males: 12.00 &#x000b1; 0.05 g; females: 10.76 &#x000b1; 0.06 g, undetermined 11.18 &#x000b1; 0.07 g, Tukey: p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001) and, as these birds are fattening up on a daily basis [<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], body mass was positively affected by time of capture (F<sub>1,225</sub> = 57.1, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p><fig id="pone-0068292-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068292.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Intra-seasonal changes in body mass.</title><p>Data are least square means of body mass controlling for year, month, time of capture, sex with bird ID as random parameter. Different letters represent significant difference between months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0068292.g002"/></fig><p>Mass-independent BMR (body mass: F<sub>1, 218</sub> = 83.1.2, p &#x0003c; 0.0001) did not change between years but varied within winter (month: F<sub>6,321</sub> = 6.1, p &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g003">Figure 3A)</xref>. BMR progressively increased by 5.9% between October and February (Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.05) and then decreased by 5.5% between February and March (Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.0001).</p><fig id="pone-0068292-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068292.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Monthly variation at the population and individual levels in mass-independent BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub>and ME.</title><p>Population data (black line and dots) are least square means for BMR (A), M<sub>SUM</sub> (B) and ME (C) controlling for year, month, sex, body mass and bird ID as random parameter. In B and C - dotted line, open dots and uppercase: 1<sup>st</sup> year; solid line, black dots and lowercase: 2<sup>nd</sup> year. Different letters represent significant difference between months within a year. Predicted values calculated from LMEs (see text for details) are used to visualize data from individuals captured more than once (grey lines).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0068292.g003"/></fig><p>As for BMR, mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> (body mass: F<sub>1,204</sub> = 97.6, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001) did not differ between years but varied within winter (month: F<sub>6,270</sub> = 37.1, p &#x0003c; 0.0001). Average M<sub>SUM</sub> increased by 25.0% between October and February and weakly decreased by 5.2% between February and March. However, the month effect also depended on the year (year*month: F<sub>3,266</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.0, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). Separated analyses by year showed that the M<sub>SUM</sub> peak observed in February was only apparent in 2010, where it reached a value 31.9% higher than our intra-seasonal reference point in October, before declining by 13.3% between February and March (Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.01). During the second year, mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> increased steadily throughout winter to reach a peak in March with a value +20.7% higher than that measured in October (Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.0001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g003">Figure 3B)</xref>.</p><p>Mass-independent winter metabolic expansibility (body mass: F<sub>1,156</sub> = 8.2, p &#x0003c; 0.01) varied with month (F<sub>6,253</sub> = 18.3, p &#x0003c; 0.0001) with average mass-independent ME increasing by 19.8% between October and March. However, the month effect was also dependent on the year (year*month: F<sub>3,253</sub>&#x000a0;= 4.9, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01). Separated analyses revealed that during the first year, mass-independent ME reached a peak (6.5 x BMR) in February (+27.0% relative to October 2011) before decreasing non-significantly in March (-2.6%, Tukey: p = 0.8). During the second year, mass-independent ME reached its highest value (6.2 x BMR) in March (+19.6% relative to October, Tukey: p &#x0003c; 0.0001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g003">Figure 3C)</xref>.</p><p>For all metabolic parameters, visual inspection of predicted values for recaptured individuals showed a high level of variability between birds but consistency in their position relative to others (i.e. there were &#x0201c;high&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;low&#x0201d; BMR/M<sub>SUM</sub> individuals). Individual patterns were comparable to that observed at the population level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g003">Figure 3)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3.4"><title>(d) Relationship between BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>
</title><p>Linear regression between residuals of whole BMR and whole M<sub>SUM</sub> extracted from linear mixed effect models resulted in a significant but weak positive relationship between these parameters (n = 269; r<sup>&#x000b2;</sup>
<sub>adj</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.04; p &#x0003c; 0.001). The relationship was not significant when using residuals from models controlling for body mass (p = 0.4).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study is the first to document, with an extensive dataset, intra-seasonal and intra-individual patterns of change (e.g. reaction norm [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]) in metabolic performance of free-living birds wintering at northern latitudes. As expected, both BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> were higher in winter relative to summer and increased during the coldest months of winter. However, average BMR and average M<sub>SUM</sub> followed dissimilar paths with BMR declining to summer level in the spring while M<sub>SUM</sub> tended to remain high, resulting in the highest metabolic expansibility being recorded in March. Variations in metabolic performance observed at the population level reflected that observed within individuals.</p><sec id="s4.1"><title>(a) Inter-seasonal variation in metabolic performance</title><p>Mass-independent basal metabolic rate, interpreted here as the energy expenditure of physiological systems remaining active in a resting bird, peaked at 0.27 W in wintering black-capped chickadees. This is comparable to values measured in wintering chickadees from Ohio (0.26 W) and Wisconsin (0.27W) [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] but lower than the ones measured in birds spending their winter in New York (0.29) [<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], South Dakota (0.30 W) [<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and Alaska (0.42 W) [<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. It is therefore not surprising to find that the 6% seasonal increase in mass-independent BMR observed here is much lower than the +14% found by Cooper and Swanson in birds from South Dakota [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This seasonal variation is, however, in the relatively large range of seasonal changes observed in other temperate free-living resident passerines (from -4.3% in <named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Carpodacus</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">mexicanus</named-content></italic>
</named-content> [<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] to +36.3% in <named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Passer</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">montanus</named-content></italic>
</named-content> [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]). Assuming the seasonal elevation in BMR reflects an increase in maintenance costs [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], it therefore appears that black-capped chickadees from our study site only face a moderate rise in maintenance energy demand in association with seasonal cold acclimatization relative to other populations. If temperature is one of the drivers of winter metabolic performance [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], it is likely that differences between populations reflect physiological responses to local conditions.</p><p>As for BMR, the seasonal increase in M<sub>SUM</sub> (+34%) was in the range of previously reported observations. Seasonal changes in mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> range from +16.2% in <named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Sitta</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">carolinensis</named-content></italic>
</named-content> [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] to +42.4% in <named-content content-type="genus-species">
<named-content content-type="genus">
<italic>Picoides</italic>
</named-content>
<italic><named-content content-type="species">pubescens</named-content></italic>
</named-content> [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], with black-capped chickadees from South Dakota showing a 26.3% increase in winter mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> relative to summer [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4.2"><title>(b) Intra-seasonal variation in metabolic performance and the uncoupling of BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>
</title><p>Temperature has been suggested as one of the drivers of winter metabolic performance [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and this led us to predict a gradual increase in BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> during winter where a peak would be observed during the coldest months of the season. Seasonal variations in BMR were of lower amplitude than expected but changes in average values were consistent with our prediction. Although significant differences were only clear when comparing February with October, November and March, BMR clearly tended to be higher during December, January and February, the coldest months of winter (both years combined, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">table 1)</xref>. However, BMR declined rapidly in March, when ambient temperatures were still relatively cold (-16&#x000b0;C and -27&#x000b0;C mean minimum temperature in 2010 and 2011 respectively), which suggests that temperature may not be the sole driver of winter BMR phenotype in chickadees.</p><p>In contrast, intra-seasonal changes in average M<sub>SUM</sub> differed between years. During the first winter, M<sub>SUM</sub> peaked in February and declined in March while in the second year M<sub>SUM</sub> increased until the end of our measurements in March. M<sub>SUM</sub> variations were therefore consistent with our predictions for the first year, where February was the coldest month based on minimal temperature, but were counterintuitive for the second year where no decline in M<sub>SUM</sub> were observed. It must be noted, however, that cold energy-demanding temperatures lasted much longer during the second winter since, although daily temperatures were already warming by March, minimal temperatures were as cold in March as in January. It is therefore likely that birds maintained their thermogenic capacity to its maximal level as long as days with very cold temperature prevailed. As metabolic expansibility is the ratio of M<sub>SUM</sub> on BMR, and given the differences in range of intra-seasonal changes in BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>, variations in ME were inevitably affected by changes in M<sub>SUM</sub>. It was therefore of no surprise to find similar variation when comparing ME and M<sub>SUM</sub>.</p><p>The contrast in BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> patterns goes in hand with the hypothesis that these components of metabolic performance respond to different sets of environmental constraints [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Comparing intra-seasonal patterns of change in BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> relative to summer values also suggests a certain level of independence between these parameters. Although it was moderate, the increase in mass-independent BMR between seasons (+5.9% comparing August and February) was the same as that detected between October and February (+5.9%). In fact, the increase in BMR started after November, when birds began to face minimal temperatures below -10&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">table 1)</xref>, and remained relatively steady until February (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g004">Figure 4A)</xref>. In contrast, the inter-seasonal change in mass-independent M<sub>SUM</sub> (+34.2% between August and February) was higher than that measured within season (+25.0% between October and February). In fact, M<sub>SUM</sub> had already achieved 21.8% of its inter-seasonal increase when we began our measurements in October (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g004">Figure 4B)</xref> meaning that, although the largest change in M<sub>SUM</sub> appeared between January and February (+45.4% of total inter-seasonal increase, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g004">Figure 4B)</xref>, this parameter began to change well before the beginning of sub-zero mean ambient temperatures (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">table 1)</xref>. These results therefore suggest that flexible adjustments in thermogenic capacity appear relatively early in autumn (before October) while physiological components reflected in BMR only begin to change later (from November).</p><fig id="pone-0068292-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0068292.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Visual representation of the monthly winter increment in metabolic performance.</title><p>Increment in mass-independent BMR (A) and M<sub>SUM</sub> (B) relative to summer values. Data measured in August are used as the summer phenotype reference point (August = 0%, black star, dashed line) while maximal levels of BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> recorded in winter are considered representative of the &#x0201c;peak&#x0201d; winter phenotype (February = 100%). Monthly changes in metabolic performance (values above lines) are presented in percent of total inter-seasonal difference. Dotted lines represent BMR variations below the summer reference point.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0068292.g004"/></fig><p>Why would BMR begin to increase later in autumn and decline earlier in the spring than M<sub>SUM</sub>? The reasons for the uncoupling of these variables are not clear. However, if one considers M<sub>SUM</sub> as a variable mainly influenced by the size of shivering muscles [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and BMR as reflecting changes in size and activity of the main digestive organs in response to cold acclimatization [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] then it is likely that those metabolic parameters reflect different sets of physiological constraints acting relatively independently, both being associated with winter [<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Pectoral muscles would start changing early in the season in association with the appearance of cold ambient temperatures (note that sub-zero minimal temperatures were already recorded in October), whereas winter BMR variations would likely reflect changes in diet and in the amounts of food consumed (to sustain an increasing daily energy expenditure, DEE). Chickadees feed mainly on insects during summer but eat up to 50% vegetal matter during winter [<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] while food supplementation by feeders may represent only up to 21% of their daily energy intake [<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Snow typically starts to fall in November at our field site while insects are already visible by March. Therefore, it could be that the combination of a winter increase in DEE and changes in natural diet digestibility and energy content leads to a restructuring of the digestive apparatus, and in turn changes in BMR, appearing independently from those observed in M<sub>SUM</sub>. The proximal effect of cold ambient temperature on parameters of metabolic performance [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] would therefore be much more influential for M<sub>SUM</sub> than for BMR. Experimental research is needed to test this &#x0201c;metabolic uncoupling&#x0201d; hypothesis and to determine what biotic and/or abiotic factors trigger seasonal changes in parameters of metabolic performance.</p><p>Given the seasonal mismatch in variations of BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>, it is therefore of no surprise to find a lack of significant correlation between these parameters when controlling for body mass in regression analyses. Independence of BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> has also been observed by others [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], but findings remains conflicting [<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Experimental manipulations of BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>, for example by combining diet and temperature treatments, should therefore be conducted to confirm findings.</p></sec><sec id="s4.3"><title>(c) Intra-individual variation in winter metabolic performance</title><p>Studies on seasonal variation of avian metabolic performance are typically conducted at the population level [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and, although it is rarely stated, they generally assume that population patterns are reflective of those observable within individuals. As far as we know, this is the first study to document with an extensive dataset seasonal variation of metabolism at both the population and individual levels in a resident bird species. Our findings support the common assumption; patterns observed at the population level reflected intra-individual variation in body mass, mass-independent BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g003">Figure 3A&#x02013;C)</xref> and are therefore representative of average individual phenotypic flexibility.</p></sec><sec id="s4.4"><title>(d) Is metabolic expansibility a meaningful variable?</title><p>In this study, we considered metabolic expansibility as an indicator of the capacity of an organism to produce heat (because it was based on M<sub>SUM</sub>) for a given size of metabolic machinery (which would be reflected by BMR) [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, the lack of correlation between BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>, as observed by others [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], as well as the temporal mismatch in these parameters during seasonal acclimatization suggest a lack of a functional relationship between BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub>. Although BMR includes the resting energy consumption of physiolgical components involved in active thermogenesis (i.e. muscles), evidences suggest that, in the context of cold acclimatization, its variations are mainly influenced by activity and size of organ systems involved in energy acquisition and digestion [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], while M<sub>SUM</sub> would mostly reflect active energy consumption of shivering muscles [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. It therefore becomes apparent to us that metabolic expansibility, as we defined it earlier, may lead to misleading conclusions about machinery adjustments. We therefore suggest caution with the interpretation of this variable and recommend interpreting variations in BMR and M<sub>SUM</sub> separately to infer on animals metabolic capacity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068292.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><title>Inter-seasonal variation in body mass, BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME.</title><p>Data are least square means controlling for year, season and sex (and time of capture for body mass) with bird ID as random parameter.</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0068292.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0068292.s002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><title>Intra-seasonal variation in body mass, BMR, M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME.</title><p>Data are least square means controlling for sex, year, month and the interaction year*month for M<sub>SUM</sub> and ME, with bird ID as random parameter. Body mass analysis also included time of capture as covariate.</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0068292.s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to the Corporation de la For&#x000ea;t d&#x02019;Enseignement et Recherche Macp&#x000e8;s who granted us access to the field facilities. We especially thank Cl&#x000e9;ment Mandin for his help and enlightened discussions during these two years of fieldwork. We also thank Jos&#x000e9;e-Anne Otis, Philip Bertrand, Jean-Fran&#x000e7;ois Lamarre, Myriam Milbergue and St&#x000e9;phane Orio for their help and advices in catching birds as well as Jonathan Coud&#x000e9;, Danie Mass&#x000e9; and Pauline Dub&#x000e9; for technical and administrative support. We are deeply grateful to Yves Turcotte for training M.P. and A.L. in bird catching and banding, to Alain Caron for statistical advices and to Sabrina Clavijo Baquet, Grisel Cavieres, Deborah Buehler and Quinn Fletcher for their comments on an earlier version of this paper.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Easterling</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meehl</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Changnon</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karl</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Climate Extremes: Observations, Modeling, and Impacts</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>289</volume>: <fpage>2068</fpage>-<lpage>2074</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.289.5487.2068">10.1126/science.289.5487.2068</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11000103">11000103</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11000103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Forcada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trathan</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Life history buffering in Antarctic mammals and birds against changing patterns of climate and environmental variation</article-title>. <source>Glob Change Biol</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>2473</fpage>-<lpage>2488</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Canale</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Adaptive phenotypic plasticity and resilience of vertebrates to increasing climatic unpredictability</article-title>. <source>Clim Res</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>135</fpage>-<lpage>147</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3354/cr00897">10.3354/cr00897</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Laaksonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eeva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaisanen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehikoinen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Climate change, migratory connectivity and changes in laying date and clutch size of the pied flycatcher</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>114</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>-<lpage>290</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.2006.0030-1299.14652.x">10.1111/j.2006.0030-1299.14652.x</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Van Der Jeugd</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eichhorn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Litvin</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Keeping up with early springs: rapid range expansion in an avian herbivore incurs a mismatch between reproductive timing and food supply</article-title>. <source>Glob Change Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1057</fpage>-<lpage>1071</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2008.01804.x">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2008.01804.x</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>IPCC</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <source>Climate Change 2007: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>. 996pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>DesJarlais</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>B&#x000e9;langer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blondlot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bouffard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Savoir s&#x02019;adapter aux changements climatiques</article-title>. <publisher-loc>Montr&#x000e9;al</publisher-loc>;. <fpage>128</fpage> p..</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic flexibility and the evolution of organismal design</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>228</fpage>-<lpage>233</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0169-5347(03)00036-3">10.1016/S0169-5347(03)00036-3</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McKechnie</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic flexibility in basal metabolic rate and the changing view of avian physiological diversity: a review</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol B-Biochem Syst Environ Physiol</source>
<volume>178</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>-<lpage>247</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00360-007-0218-8">10.1007/s00360-007-0218-8</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17957373">17957373</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Evidence for a proximate influence of winter temperature on metabolism in passerine birds</article-title>. <source>Physiol Biochem Zool</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>-<lpage>575</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/316696">10.1086/316696</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10521324">10521324</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10521324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Seasonal energetics of Mountain Chickadees and Juniper Titmice</article-title>. <source>Condor</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>-<lpage>644</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1369795">10.2307/1369795</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Seasonal acclimatization of thermoregulation in the black-capped chickadee</article-title>. <source>Condor</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>638</fpage>-<lpage>646</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1369467">10.2307/1369467</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liknes</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Seasonal variation in cold tolerance, basal metabolic rate, and maximal capacity for thermogenesis in White-breasted Nuthatches <italic>Sitta carolinensis</italic> and Downy Woodpeckers <italic>Picoides pubescens</italic>, two unrelated arboreal temperate residents</article-title>. <source>J Avian Biol</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>-<lpage>288</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3677259">10.2307/3677259</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Houston</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Why hoard? The economics of food storing in tits, <italic>Parus</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>-<lpage>23</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/beheco/1.1.12">10.1093/beheco/1.1.12</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Seasonal Metabolic Variation in Birds: Functional and Mechanistic Correlates</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Current Ornithology</source> Volume <volume>17</volume>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc> pp. <fpage>75</fpage>-<lpage>129</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McNab</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name> (<year>1971</year>) <article-title>On the Ecological Significance of Bergmann&#x02019;s Rule</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>845</fpage>-<lpage>854</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1936032">10.2307/1936032</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Seasonal adjustments in metabolism and insulation in the dark-eyed junco</article-title>. <source>Condor</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>538</fpage>-<lpage>545</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1368185">10.2307/1368185</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Seasonal acclimatization of metabolism in Eurasian tree sparrows (<italic>Passer montanus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol</source>
<volume>151</volume>: <fpage>519</fpage>-<lpage>525</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cbpa.2008.07.009">10.1016/j.cbpa.2008.07.009</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18804172">18804172</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Scholander</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1950</year>) <article-title>Heat regulation in some arctic and tropical mammals and birds</article-title>. <source>Biological Bulletin</source>
<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>-<lpage>258</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1538741">10.2307/1538741</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14791422">14791422</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14791422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McKechnie</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Sources and significance of variation in basal, summit and maximal metabolic rates in birds</article-title>. <source>Curr Zool</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>-<lpage>758</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Seasonal metabolic acclimatization in mountain chickadees and juniper titmice</article-title>. <source>Physiol Biochem Zool</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>-<lpage>395</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/342256">10.1086/342256</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12324895">12324895</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12324895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dekinga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koolhaas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Time course and reversibility of changes in the gizzards of red knots alternately eating hard and soft food</article-title>. <source>J Exp Biol</source>
<volume>204</volume>: <fpage>2167</fpage>-<lpage>2173</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11441058">11441058</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11441058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Broggi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohtola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koivula</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al.</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Sources of variation in winter basal metabolic rate in the great tit</article-title>. <source>Funct Ecol</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>-<lpage>533</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2435.2007.01255.x">10.1111/j.1365-2435.2007.01255.x</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekinga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Shorebirds&#x02019; Seasonal Adjustments in Thermogenic Capacity Are Reflected by Changes in Body Mass: How Preprogrammed and Instantaneous Acclimation Work Together</article-title>. <source>Integr Comp Biol</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>394</fpage>-<lpage>408</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/icb/icr044">10.1093/icb/icr044</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21700573">21700573</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dutenhoffer</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Relationship of basal to summit metabolic rate in passerine birds and the aerobic capacity model for the evolution of endothermy</article-title>. <source>Physiol Zool</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>1232</fpage>-<lpage>1254</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baudinette</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacMillen</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Maximum metabolism and the aerobic factorial scope of endotherms</article-title>. <source>J Exp Biol</source>
<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>-<lpage>56</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8228784">8228784</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8228784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jalvingh</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekinga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Acclimation to different thermal conditions in a northerly wintering shorebird is driven by body mass-related changes in organ size</article-title>. <source>J Exp Biol</source>
<volume>209</volume>: <fpage>3141</fpage>-<lpage>3154</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1242/jeb.02338">10.1242/jeb.02338</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16888062">16888062</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16888062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liknes</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Intraspecific Correlations of Basal and Maximal Metabolic Rates in Birds and the Aerobic Capacity Model for the Evolution of Endothermy</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e34271</fpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0034271">10.1371/journal.pone.0034271</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22479584">22479584</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479584</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Energetic bottlenecks and other design constraints in avian annual cycles</article-title>. <source>Integr Comp Biol</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>67</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/icb/42.1.51">10.1093/icb/42.1.51</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21708694">21708694</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21708694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liknes</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic flexibility of body composition associated with seasonal acclimatization in passerine birds</article-title>. <source>J Therm Biol</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>-<lpage>370</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtherbio.2011.06.010">10.1016/j.jtherbio.2011.06.010</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Saarela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hohtola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Seasonal thermal acclimatization in sedentary and active pigeons</article-title>. <source>Isr J Zool</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>-<lpage>193</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1560/VAPN-M8YA-U3KU-DTK9">10.1560/VAPN-M8YA-U3KU-DTK9</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jalvingh</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekinga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Thermogenic side effects to migratory predisposition in shorebirds</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source>
<volume>292</volume>: <fpage>R1287</fpage>-<lpage>R1297</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17138724">17138724</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17138724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lewden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Dominant black-capped chickadees pay no maintenance energy costs for their wintering status and are not better at enduring cold than subordinate individuals</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol B-Biochem Syst Environ Physiol</source>
<volume>182</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>-<lpage>392</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00360-011-0625-8">10.1007/s00360-011-0625-8</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Arens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Metabolic and ventilatory acclimatization to cold stress in house sparrows (<italic>Passer domesticus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Physiol Biochem Zool</source>
<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>579</fpage>-<lpage>589</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1086/430235">10.1086/430235</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15957112">15957112</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15957112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mandin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Daily variation in markers of nutritional condition in wintering black-capped chickadee <italic>Poecile atricapillus</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Ibis</source>
<volume>154</volume>: <fpage>791</fpage>-<lpage>802</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1474-919X.2012.01262.x">10.1111/j.1474-919X.2012.01262.x</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Pyle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <source>Identification Guide to North American Birds, Part 1</source>. <publisher-loc>Bolinas, California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Slate Creek Press</publisher-name>. 732 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Drymalski</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Sliding vs static cold exposure and the measurement of summit metabolism in birds</article-title>. <source>J Therm Biol</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0306-4565(96)00005-8">10.1016/0306-4565(96)00005-8</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gessaman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Nocturnal hypothermia in seasonally acclimatized Mountain Chickadees and Juniper Titmice</article-title>. <source>Condor</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1650/7597">10.1650/7597</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rising</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Seasonal Variation in the Metabolism and Thyroid Activity of the Black-Capped Chickadee (<italic>Parus atricapillus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Condor</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>-<lpage>203</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1366730">10.2307/1366730</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Lighton</surname><given-names>JRB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <source>Measuring metabol ic rates: A manual for scientists</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>. 216pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bartholomew</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vleck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vleck</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Instantaneous Measurements of Oxygen Consumption During Pre-Flight Warm-Up and Post-Flight Cooling in Sphingid and Saturniid Moths</article-title>. <source>J Exp Biol</source>
<volume>90</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vaillancourt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prud&#x02019;Homme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guglielmo</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Energetics of a long-distance migrant shorebird (Philomachus pugnax) during cold exposure and running</article-title>. <source>J Exp Biol</source>
<volume>208</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>-<lpage>325</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1242/jeb.01397">10.1242/jeb.01397</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15634851">15634851</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yacoe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Metabolic adjustments of small passerine birds for migration and cold</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Physiology - Regulatory, Integrative and Comparative Physiology</source>
<volume>245</volume>: <fpage>R755</fpage>-<lpage>R767</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6362436">6362436</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gessaman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Energy Metabolism: Errors in Gas-Exchange Conversion Factors</article-title>. <source>Physiol Zool</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>-<lpage>513</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Double</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>RJG</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A DNA test to sex most birds</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1071</fpage>-<lpage>1075</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-294x.1998.00389.x">10.1046/j.1365-294x.1998.00389.x</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9711866">9711866</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9711866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Desrochers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Sex determination of black-capped chickadees with a discriminant analysis</article-title>. <source>J Field Ornithol</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lehikoinen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Seasonality of the Daily Weight Cycle in Wintering Passerines and Its Consequences</article-title>. <source>Ornis Scand</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>216</fpage>-<lpage>226</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3676769">10.2307/3676769</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The Relationship of Metabolic Performance and Distribution in Black-Capped and Carolina Chickadees</article-title>. <source>Physiol Biochem Zool</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>-<lpage>275</lpage>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20151817">20151817</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20151817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chaplin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>Daily energetics of black-capped chickadees, <italic>Parus atricapillus</italic>, in winter</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol</source>
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>-<lpage>330</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00695350">10.1007/BF00695350</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Metabolic rate and temperature regulation of winter acclimatized black-capped chickadess <italic>Parus atricapillus</italic> of interior Alaska</article-title>. <source>Ornis Scand</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>138</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3676097">10.2307/3676097</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Metabolic characteristics and body composition in house finches - Effects of seasonal acclimatization</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol B-Biochem Syst Environ</source>
<volume>165</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>-<lpage>305</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF00367313">10.1007/BF00367313</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic flexibility of metabolic rate and organ masses among tree sparrows Passer montanus in seasonal acclimatization</article-title>. <source>Acta Zoolog Sin</source>
<volume>52</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>-<lpage>477</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Maldonado</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavieres</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Veloso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Canals</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sabat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Physiological responses in rufous-collared sparrows to thermal acclimation and seasonal acclimatization</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol B-Biochem Syst Environ Physiol</source>
<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>-<lpage>343</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00360-008-0317-1">10.1007/s00360-008-0317-1</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19011873">19011873</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>V&#x000e9;zina</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekinga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piersma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic compromise in the face of conflicting ecological demands: an example in red knots Calidris canutus</article-title>. <source>J Avian Biol</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>-<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-048X.2009.04763.x">10.1111/j.1600-048X.2009.04763.x</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Black-capped chickadee (<italic>Parus atricapillus</italic>)</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stettenheim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>The birds of North America, n&#x000b0;39</source>: <volume>20</volume>
<comment>p, </comment>
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Academy of Natural Sciences</publisher-name>; <publisher-loc>Washington D.C.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The American Ornithologists Union</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brittingham</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Temple</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Use of winter bird feeders by black-capped chickadees</article-title>. <source>J Wildl Manage</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>110</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/3808797">10.2307/3808797</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wiersma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cold- and exercise-induced peak metabolic rates in tropical birds</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>20866</fpage>-<lpage>20871</lpage>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0707683104">10.1073/pnas.0707683104</ext-link>. PubMed: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18093954">18093954</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18093954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>