<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Will the difficulty of forecasting weather be affected by climate change? To answer this question, the first step is to recognise the chaotic nature of atmospheric dynamics
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Despite the increase in resolution and complexity of weather forecast systems, atmospheric forecasts face an insurmountable predictability limit
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. This stems from the intrinsic properties of the atmospheric attractor—a high-dimensional geometric object on which all the possible atmospheric states settle—and is often referred to as the “butterfly effect”, or dependence on initial conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. Atmospheric turbulence injects energy at all spatial and temporal scales, generating chaos and limiting short-term predictability. Predictability further depends on space and time, so that the detection and interpretation of changes is extremely complex
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, predictability is not a constant, and can be strongly affected by the large-scale atmospheric configuration from which the forecast is initialised
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. For example, mid-latitude transitions from blocked to zonal atmospheric states are less predictable than a persistent large-scale zonal flow
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. By large-scale zonal flow, we refer to a strong eastward (zonal) jet with few meridional oscillations. If the proportion of predictable vs. unpredictable patterns were to change under anthropogenic forcing, the atmosphere’s intrinsic predictability would also change accordingly. The task of diagnosing changes in atmospheric predictability—and more generally in mid-latitude atmospheric dynamics—under anthropogenic forcing is therefore beset with difficulties
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Achieving this when focusing on averaged quantities, such as climate variability indices, presents serious challenges
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
