<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Authors’ contributions</title>
 <p class="p">MXT analysed and interpreted the data, and drafted the manuscript. AH designed the questionnaire. MXT, JX, and XL conducted the field survey. AH, SHE and PB revised and edited the manuscript. SC, JX, QL, YS, PW, GSH, and CW reviewed the document. All authors contributed to the final version of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
  <p class="p">We thank the China National CDC and all local CDCs getting involved in this study for their assistance in the distribution and return of questionnaires. All survey participants are greatly appreciated for their valuable contributions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Competing interests</title>
  <p class="p">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p class="p">The datasets during and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p class="p">The study was approved by the University of Adelaide (Approval No. HS-2013-052), the University of South Australia (Approval No. 0000032268), Monash University (Approval No. CF13/3263-2013001642), Anhui Medical University (Approval No. 2013007) and the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (Approval No. ICDC-2013002). Informed consent was obtained from individual participants. This consent procedure was approved by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, and conducted in accordance with its guidelines.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Funding</title>
  <p class="p">This study has been funded by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade through the Australian Development Research Awards Scheme under an award titled ‘How best to curb the public health impact of emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases due to climate change in China’ (Project ID: 66888) and the National Basic Research Program of China (973 Program) (Grant No. 2012CB955504). The views expressed in the publication are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade or the Australian Government. The Commonwealth of Australia accepts no responsibility for any loss, damage or injury resulting from reliance on any of the information or views contained in this publication.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
