<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Coastal and inland regions with high levels of disturbance from agriculture and other human activity may be particularly vulnerable to both increases in pathogens as well as increases in DOM following high precipitation events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. This in turn increases the threat of exposure to contaminated water and infectious diseases. In the Laurentian Great Lakes region the nexus of high human activity, heavy dependence on surface water resources, and climate change is creating substantial concerns for water quality and human pathogens
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>. This is illustrated here by a case study of the effects of heavy precipitation and runoff on river discharge, water transparency, and SIP where the Manitowoc River flows into Lake Michigan (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>). Following several smaller rain events in June, 2011, a heavy rain event on June 21 increased discharge from the Manitowoc River by an order of magnitude, releasing large inputs of darker, highly UV-absorbing terrestrial DOM into Lake Michigan in the vicinity of Red Arrow Beach, reducing the SIP by 22% (Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>). Then warmer temperatures and less precipitation in July reduced river discharge and DOM inputs as well as increased photobleaching, with a subsequent 75% increase in SIP from this low until another high precipitation event in late July. Because the input of pathogens increases in a manner similar to the input of DOM during heavy precipitation events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>, the threat of infectious disease is compounded during these events, especially when rainfall coincides with abundance of the primary vectors of pathogens. 
</p>
