<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used the Co-existence Approach (CA) to reconstruct the Mean Annual Temperature Range (MATR), Coldest Month Mean Temperature Range (CMMTR) and Warmest Month Mean Temperature Range (WMMTR). The CA reconstructs a range of equally possible values within which a fossil plant community could have co-existed, rather than an absolute value with error margins
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b93" class="xref">93</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b94" class="xref">94</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b95" class="xref">95</xref>. Whilst some authors have taken the mid-value of the range and plotted these with the highest and lowest values of the range as error bars, this is not recommended as it can lead to spurious uses of reconstructions by non-experts
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b93" class="xref">93</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b94" class="xref">94</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b95" class="xref">95</xref>. The CA is robust at reconstructing temperature changes of 1 °C
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b95" class="xref">95</xref>, which is sensitive enough to identify the large-scale climate changes proposed by previous estimates of terrestrial temperature changes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>. These climatic parameters have been reconstructed for all Eocene – Oligocene pollen assemblages recorded in TEVIS using the Palaeoflora database
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b93" class="xref">93</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b94" class="xref">94</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b95" class="xref">95</xref>. We have also used the data available from Australia’s Virtual Herbarium
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b96" class="xref">96</xref> and the Atlas of Living Australia
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" class="xref">97</xref> to define climatic ranges for species identified as nearest living relatives to southern hemisphere Eocene – Oligocene plants. The CA reconstructs possible ranges within which a fossil plant assemblage could have co-existed and has been widely applied to palaeoclimate studies of the EOT and other geological intervals
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. Locations were grouped into regions based on their palaeo-latitude and palaeo-longitude and then these were plotted chronologically to produce regional MATR, CMMTR and WMMTR reconstructions.
</p>
