<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">Infection with 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> leads to diarrhoea, fever and abdominal cramps, usually 1–3 days after the initial infection. Symptoms generally last for 4–6 days but in some individuals the patient may need to be hospitalised. Although there are a number of potential pathways of transmission for 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic>, the consumption of raw or undercooked eggs or poultry are recognised to be of major importance. Several thousand 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> species (serotypes) have been identified and these have differing routes of transmission. For example 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> Enteritidis is commonly associated with eggs whereas 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium is associated with a wider variety of foods [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>]. A recent study in England estimates that there are just under 39,000 cases of 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> a year leading to just over 11,000 GP consultations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. This is a large reduction in cases in comparison to the early 1990’s. In contrast to 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> outbreaks are common and so as a disease it is likely to be prominent in public consciousness. Nonetheless 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> is not a priority pathogen identified by the Food Standards Agency for specific action [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. Older research focusing upon England and Wales at a time when levels of 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> disease was higher, estimated that in 2000 it led to over 8500 hospital admissions and 119 deaths NB more estimated deaths than Campylobacter: [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. It has been estimated that the average cost of a 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> case is around £1000 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>]. Multiplying this by the estimated community cases produces a total UK cost of £39million p/a (This assumes that the costs of reported and non-reported cases are similar and so is probably an overestimate).
</p>
