<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">In terms of highlighting whether levels of illness with 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> is higher in rural or urban areas no UK studies have been conducted. No difference has been found in studies in the USA, Germany and France [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. A New Zealand found higher disease incidence in rural areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. This lack of association is backed up by recent microbiological work suggesting that local domestic animals (e.g. cows and sheep) are not a major source of 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> in humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. There are also no UK studies examining which socioeconomic groups are most affected. US studies have found lower disease incidence in areas with poorer educational attainment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. However, this contradicts a Canadian study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. There are no UK studies examining differentiation between ethnic groups, but in the US minority populations tend to suffer disproportionally [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. In terms of the age distribution of cases in England the reported highest incidence of disease was is in the under 4 s reducing until age 14. From this point incidence is fairly constant.Similar age distributions are reported in Scotland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>] and Northern Ireland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. The increasing use of proton pump inhibitors may increase susceptibility to 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>] and the use of these in older populations is increasing.
</p>
