<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The distribution of known archaeological sites may be biased by factors such as the easy recognition of diagnostic tools, research history and preferences, site preservation potential or certain geomorphological processes. Large dune fields and cover sands may have buried archaeological sites. In Iberia, large inland dune fields are known, including the Tierra de Pinares sand of the Duero Basin [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] the Manchega Plain in the Tagus Basin [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A compilation of the luminescence and radiocarbon data by the latter authors suggests that these aeolian sands were deposited during the Late Glacial and the Holocene (Tierra de Pinares) as well as during the LGM (Manchega plain). Near the coast, several dune fields are depicted in the Mapa Geomorfol칩gica de Espa침a y del margen continental (Instituto Geol칩gico y Minero, 2005) [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. These may have been active after the Solutrean or Magdalenian occupations: luminescence dating of dune sands south of the Tagus delta yielded deposition ages between 20.5 and 11.6 ka ago, providing evidence for continuous aeolian activity in the coastal hinterland of Portugal during the last termination [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Other aeolian sediments include loess deposits of the Tagus Basin and at various locations in Catalonia [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. These deposits can attain a thickness of over ten meters, but are a more local occurrence, probably insufficient to cause significant sampling bias. Other sites may have been lost or covered due to erosion and deposition of sediments in floodplains or on slopes. In addition, Hoyos-G칩mez [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] considered the lack of Lower and Middle Solutrean layers in some sites of the Cantabrian region to be a result of reactivation of the karst. Sea level retreat during the LGM exposed large coastal plains (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0225049.g001">Fig 1</xref>) which, most probably, were inhabited by humans and flooded by rapid sea level rise during the Late Glacial. Additionally, Aura et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] discuss geological and taphonomic processes that may have been responsible for mixing Solutrean with younger [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] overlying materials in few sites in Northern Iberia and the Mediterranean region.
</p>
