<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Such fluctuating competition between subspecies and probably geographical origins within a same subspecies (Danish and Dutch populations) has not been observed in other bird species. It was also recorded in the breeders of the pioneering and largest French colony of cormorants at the Lac de Grand‐Lieu (Loire Atlantique department). The colony was initially created by wintering birds belonging to the continental 
 <italic class="italic">Ph. c. sinensis</italic> subspecies, but rapidly invaded by the marine subspecies 
 <italic class="italic">Ph. c. carbo</italic> (Marion &amp; Le Gentil, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The situation became even more complex with the recent use of inland areas up to 300 km from the sea by the marine subspecies during wintering (Fonteneau &amp; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Fonteneau, Paillisson, &amp; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). These changes between eastern and western migrating routes could also explain the recent and strong use of Spain as a wintering area, once France became progressively saturated and exported part of its own migrating birds toward Spain. Spain became the second most important wintering area in Europe after France in 2003 with about 75,000 cormorants (Del Moral &amp; de Souza, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Van Eerden et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0808" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) vs. around 12,000 in 1990 (Troya &amp; Bernués, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>). An increase in 
 <italic class="italic">sinensis</italic> birds along the western migrating route was also observed down to Morocco where they competed with African populations of 
 <italic class="italic">Phalacrocoras carbo maroccanus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ph. C. lucidus</italic> (A. Qninba, pers. com.). Changes in migrating routes have rarely been observed in other birds (Gramet &amp; Dubaille, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1983</xref>; Merkel &amp; Merkel, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1983</xref>; Feare, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>; Marion &amp; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>; Mewes, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0806" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>; Schmidt, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Fiedler, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Todte et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ławicki, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
