<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">ScPDSI does not account for the effect of increased atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration on plant physiology, which is hypothesized to diminish PET‐induced soil drying by increasing water use efficiency of plants (Cook et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58044-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Mankin et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58044-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Swann et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58044-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). We thus compared scPDSI from CMIP5 with soil moisture from CMIP5 during 1950–2016 over the Caribbean as in Cook, Ault, and Smerdon (
 <xref rid="grl58044-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Simulated soil moisture in the coupled land surface models of CMIP5 is a more explicit and physically based representation of the surface moisture balance than the simple bucket model used in scPDSI and includes responses of vegetation to climate and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. If CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> effects on water use efficiency have a large water savings effect, we would expect the model soil moisture to show substantially less drying than scPDSI. For each CMIP5 model considered in the Caribbean (
 <xref rid="grl58044-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Table S2</xref>), there was a significant correlation between scPDSI and soil moisture anomalies (ranging from 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> = 0.23 to 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> = 0.85, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), with an average correlation of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> = 0.69 (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; Figures 
 <xref rid="grl58044-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>b and 
 <xref rid="grl58044-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>), and drying trends in scPDSI were not systematically more severe than in soil moisture (
 <xref rid="grl58044-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supporting Information S1</xref>). This suggests that scPDSI accurately reflects surface moisture balance in these models, in spite of the simple water balance formulation it uses, and that CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> effects on plant physiology and PET‐induced drying trends were small in the Caribbean over the analysis period.
</p>
