<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The state of Alaska manages all fisheries operating within three nautical miles of shore and a small set of fisheries operating in the USA exclusive economic zones (&gt;3 nautical miles). Alaskan commercial fisheries are delineated by taxa (either species or species group), the area harvested, and the gear used to harvest them. State managed fisheries are mostly managed using some form of limited entry where access is controlled, but can be bought or sold among parties. Any individual harvesting in a state managed fishery requires a permit specific to the taxa, area fished and gear used. All landed catches and revenue in Alaskan commercial fisheries are required to be reported. The Commercial Fisheries Entry Commission (CFEC) tracks landings and revenue by permit and permit-holder residency. Therefore, reported catch and revenue are assigned to communities where the permit holder resides. For confidentiality reasons, the CFEC cannot report very small fisheries that have less than four permit holders per community. Therefore, these fisheries are not included in our analysis. Management of sablefish and halibut fisheries switched to individual transferable quota systems in 1995, which could alter the revenue and catches in these fisheries. However, excluding catches and revenues for these species does not change the results in this study.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used community level gross fishing revenues data collated by the CFEC. These revenues represent the sum of annual gross fishing revenues attributable to CFEC commercial fishing permits registered to a specific Alaskan community. Some communities have seen changes and permit migration. We ran these analyses using revenue per permit fished to account for these changes, and there is no change in the results or conclusions. All revenue data were adjusted for inflation to 2013 USD using the US annual average consumer price index (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bls.gov/cpi/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bls.gov/cpi/</span>). To evaluate spatial patterns in diversification, we used revenue data aggregated to USA census areas (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). Population and demographic information by census area were taken from USA 2010 census data (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://file:///D:\preeditjobs\NPG\natcomm\ncomms14042\www.census.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.census.gov</span>). Salmon price data was provided by CFEC summary data. Prices were adjusted for inflation to 2013 USD using the USA annual average consumer price index.
 </p>
</sec>
