<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diversification has long been a critical attribute of traditional fishing economies
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a>. For subsistence fishing communities around the North Pacific, salmon have often been the core of their economies, but intertidal shellfish, and marine fish and marine mammals were often important, especially when salmon returns were low
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>. Recognizing the tendency of open-access fisheries to develop too many fishing boats, and in response to depleted fish stocks, ‘limited entry' was introduced, which has reduced access for many people and forced specialization for efficiency. As access to fisheries is limited, buying into additional fisheries can be difficult and costly. However, the results presented here suggest that such investments likely have substantial long-term benefits to communities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diversification has clear benefits to fishing communities, but it can be challenging to achieve. Key limitations, especially for small communities, are access to capital to purchase fishing rights and permits, and to develop capacity for processing seafood products, and physical access to a wide array of fishing resources. Not all Alaskan stocks are fully exploited and rights for many fisheries can be purchased in markets, yet these fishing permits and rights can be prohibitively expensive. For example, permits for access to some Alaskan salmon fishing opportunities can be in excess of $300,000 (USD). In Alaska, we see patterns of diversification that follow geographic access to resources as well as economic development (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). Communities in Southeast Alaska where diverse fishing opportunities exist in close proximity had the highest levels of diversity. Importantly, the small level of diversity needed to mitigate most of the risk in this social-ecological system (due to the log-linear relationship) could markedly reduce these barriers to diversification.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diversification also carries risks such as loss of efficiency due to lack of specific knowledge as well as high capital costs. Diversification has been mostly thought of as an individual level strategy
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a> not a community one, therefore, a community's ability to influence diversification has been limited. Yet, fishing by individuals provides a vital revenue stream into communities, which supports many other supporting industries through commerce as well as infrastructure through taxes. Importantly, the constraints on community diversification are likely to be different than those on individuals. There are often legal restrictions that may prevent individuals from owning diverse fishing rights. High capital costs, which may be prohibitive for individuals, could be reduced within communities through directed efforts such as permit pooling or lease programs. For example, Alaska Native Corporations or economic development organizations (organizations whose goals are to improve the economic standing of native Alaskans and specific regions within the state) currently use some of their resources to help people become more competitive in specific fisheries. An alternative strategy could be to use resources to help communities with limited access to capital gain more diverse fishing opportunities. Could communities circumvent some of the loss in efficiency by distributing specialist fishers among diverse opportunities, rather than having many diverse individuals? The benefits of diversification are clear and fishing dependent communities need policies and potentially novel practices that enable opportunities and encourage diversification and flexibility.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over the last decade, there has been considerable interest and effort towards implementing ecosystem-based fisheries management under which multiple objectives and stakeholders, rather than single species, are considered in the management of fishing sectors and ecosystems
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. Diversification lends itself nicely to an approach that calls for exploitation distributed across ecosystem components
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a>, while creating important buffers against variability and regime shifts. This approach may also have ecosystem benefits. As some stocks get smaller and the costs of harvest increase, switching among fishing opportunities to more abundant stocks may reduce pressure on stocks in decline.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we show that diversification and the ability to opportunistically shift the composition of species exploited can buffer communities against unexpected and large-scale ocean regime shifts and changing markets. Ecosystems can undergo significant shifts in composition, but often maintain their overall productivity. While delivery of ecosystem services is provided primarily by abundant species
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>, the species that are abundant now may not be in the future. Additionally, species that have small market share now may demand premium prices in the future. Diversification provides opportunities to take advantage of emerging changes and buffers against disaster; it is a tangible means to increase the resilience and adaptive capacity of coupled human-natural systems. Due to the immense complexity of the ecosystems, markets, and the feedbacks between them, we will always have limited scientific capacity to anticipate future changes. Thus, there is critical need to employ strategies that enable sustainable communities despite deep and irreducible uncertainty about the future conditions of the coupled human-natural system they depend on.
 </p>
</sec>
