<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Climate change alters plant-derived inputs to soil in the form of litter production and rhizodeposition, raising questions about the way and intensity with which they are affected (
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>37</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>38</italic>
 </xref>). If terrestrial plant productivity does increase with warming by increasing nutrients available from decomposition, then more litterfall may be expected. However, higher temperatures affect plant physiology and lead to higher evaporation and plant transpiration, exacerbating water shortage effects. In addition, acclimation to warming is likely to dampen potential responses. Climate change is also expected to increase the intensity and frequency of climate extremes, for instance, through increased drought periods and periodically extreme rainfall conditions. Some studies simulating moderate drought conditions in extratropical ecosystems counterintuitively found an increase in aboveground litter production, but only in the short term (
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>39</italic>
 </xref>). By contrast, studies from humid and subhumid tropical forests found no changes or only slight decreases in the production of aboveground litter under moderately induced drought (
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>40</italic>
 </xref>). Persistent drought, however, leads to species turnover and less aboveground biomass, resulting in less litter production (
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>39</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>40</italic>
 </xref>). Increasing aridity in geographical gradients also results in decreased aboveground litter production (
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>41</italic>
 </xref>). The quality of litter decreases with drought in all biomes, even if total litterfall remains constant, partly because of elevated nutrient resorption prior to leaf senescence (
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>42</italic>
 </xref>) and the production of carbon-based, recalcitrant structural compounds under drought (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). These changes not only slow down mineralization rates, nutrient release, and nutrient cycles that may increase or decrease plant diversity through species turnover, depending on environmental conditions (
 <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>43</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>44</italic>
 </xref>), but also affect CO
 <sub>2</sub> release to the atmosphere and therefore feedback to climate.
</p>
