<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Increasing aridity can cause large changes in nutrient cycling and enhances the impact of ultraviolet radiation on litter decomposition (
 <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>45</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>46</italic>
 </xref>), which may cause an imbalance in nutrient cycling with negative effects on plant diversity (
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>47</italic>
 </xref>). Decreases in plant growth and belowground carbon allocation in grasslands as a consequence of drought have also been reported (
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>48</italic>
 </xref>), and drought has legacy effects on soil microbial communities that can affect plant-plant interactions (
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>21</italic>
 </xref>) and even neutralize PSFs through increased water demand linked to higher nutrient demand with positive PSFs (
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>28</italic>
 </xref>). In dry ecosystems, soil microbes can buffer the negative effects of drought on seed germination and plant growth in a species-specific way, so that plants such as legumes that are more dependent on specific coevolved microbes are more sensitive and less buffered by soil microbiota than other species (
 <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>49</italic>
 </xref>). PSFs also play a key role in plant recruitment by influencing seed germination and seedling establishment, which are, in turn, important in regulating plant diversity and community dynamics (
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>14</italic>
 </xref>). The susceptibility of different plant species to soil biota determines their relative abundance, as soil pathogens reduce recruitment and survival of different species (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). In contrast, other soil microorganisms offer protection from pathogens or modify nutrient availability, thereby benefitting some plant species over others (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>7</italic>
 </xref>). Our knowledge on how PSFs can affect plant communities and ecosystem dynamics can help us forecast potential trajectories of ecosystem change under different climate change scenarios.
</p>
