<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the concerns of health authorities in China is the possible influence of climate change on vector-borne diseases, especially malaria, a mosquito-borne disease which the authorities aim to eradicate by 2020 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>]. Malaria is a life-threatening parasitic disease, which has been a serious public health problem in China and many other countries. 
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium vivax</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium falciparum</italic> are two predominant species of 
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium</italic> in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>], and the primary vectors are 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> mosquito species breeding in the streams, pools, paddy fields and other water bodies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>]. Considerable efforts have been made to address this public health issue in China, which has resulted in a significant decline in its occurrence during the 1980s and 1990s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. The reduction in malaria is considered to have been due to exponential improvements in the socioeconomic status and public health interventions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. However, early this century there was a re-emergence of the disease over several years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Malaria incidence rapidly increased after 2000 and reached its peak in 2006, during which there were 64,178 cases reported in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. Incidence then decreased markedly between 2007 and 2014 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) when there were 3078 cases reported, most being concentrated in the southwest region—Yunnan Province, central and east region—Anhui, Henan and Jiangsu provinces [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. Possible reasons for this re-emergence may include meteorological factors, climate change, increased mosquitoes and imported cases, as studies in China have indicated that these factors could have impacts on the transmission of malaria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]. Given the high-density population, rapid economic development, urbanization and increasing numbers of international travelers in China, there is an urgent need to understand the effectiveness of current infectious disease control and prevention of malaria in the face of climate change. 
</p>
