<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23" class="p">We used the Community Earth System Model version 1 (CESM1) from NCAR
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup> with the CAM4 option for its atmospheric component to make two multi-century simulations plus a 150-year pre-industrial control run. The CESM1 is a widely used fully coupled climate model that simulates the Arctic SIC and climate realistically (Supplementary Figures 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1c</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">2c, d</xref>). The CESM1 was run with grid spacing of 2.5° lon × ~2.0° lat for the atmospheric model, and ~1.0° lon × ~0.5° lat for the sea-ice and ocean models. The three simulations include a pre-industrial control (CTL) run with CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fixed at 284.7 ppmv for 150 years, a standard 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> run with fully coupled dynamic sea ice and a 1%-per-year increase in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> for 235 years reaching 10.36 times of the pre-industrial CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> level, and a fixed sea-ice (FixedIce) run. The FixedIce run is the same as the standard 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> run except that all the internally calculated ice–atmosphere, ice–ocean, and ocean–atmosphere fluxes north of 30°N were applied to the sea-ice fractional areas temporally interpolated from the monthly climatology of the CTL run, in contrast to the standard 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> run in which these fluxes were applied only to the ice faction existed at the time in the model. Over a small fraction of the Arctic sea-ice area north of 30°N (mainly along the sea-ice margins at lower latitudes, Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">9</xref>), where sea ice melted away completely (mainly in the latter part of the simulation) and thus the ice model did not calculate these fluxes, the monthly climatology of these fluxes from the CTL run was temporally interpolated and applied to the CTL SIC fraction of these small areas, except for surface absorbed shortwave (SW) radiation which was calculated using the CTL albedo values and model-internally calculated downward SW radiation. The CTL ice-atmosphere fluxes (including LH, SH, evaporation, upward LW radiation, and surface stress) and ice-ocean fluxes (including heat, salt, freshwater, SW radiation, and stress fluxes) did not account for internal changes in surface temperatures and other fields, and therefore they could potentially suppress long-term changes in the Arctic if applied widely. For example, the upward LW radiation from the CTL run lacked the increasing trend associated with surface warming and therefore could weaken the Arctic warming in the lower troposphere. However, because the use of the CTL fluxes occurred only over a very small fraction of the total sea-ice area along the initial ice margins where SIC was low to start with (i.e., SIC was low in the CTL run for the small number of grid cells where the CTL fluxes were applied to the low SIC fraction; Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">9</xref>), the effect of this deficiency is likely to be small. The difference between the standard 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and FixedIce runs comes mainly from the application of the internally calculated fluxes over a fixed sea-ice cover from the control run in the FixedIce experiment.
</p>
