<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The model, predicting topsoil (0.3 m) carbon concentration in fine earth as a function of land use, soil type, management and climate data (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq2" class="xref">Equation 2</xref>), was created by applying a multiple linear regression analysis using a combined forward and backward stepwise regression method. The model complexity was managed using the following model selection criteria: the Akaike information criterion (AIC), the corrected Akaike information criterion (AICc) and the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) rule
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62" class="xref">62</xref>. In the present study, the model constructed with the AICc selection criterion was used, because BIC gave considerably lower R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>
 <sub class="sub">adj</sub> and RPD values (ratio of performance to deviation following a K-fold cross-validation procedure) and the AIC model had 36 parameters, of which only 30 are significant (p &lt; 0.05), whereas the AICc model had 30 parameters that are all significant. Moreover, for very low SOC concentrations (&lt;1%) the model error of the AICc model was remarkably smaller as compared to the AIC model
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>. Hence the AICc model captures all important trends in the data without overfitting and has been selected in order to make realistic predictions in the context of the present research. Beside linear terms, first- and second order (non-linear) interactions between the input variables were taken into consideration during model construction. The effect of land use was incorporated in the model by estimating model parameters land use independent or specific for 1, 2 or 3 land uses. A detailed overview of the different variables by term of the model can be found in Meersmans 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (2012a)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref>. Subsequently, modelled SOC contents are converted into SOC stock after taking soil depth, rock fragment content and fine earth’s bulk density into account
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>. Country-wide total SOC stocks were obtained by summing organic carbon stocks for all pixels and multiplying by the pixel area.
</p>
