<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Colonization and establishment: hybridization and polyploidy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hybridization can act as a stimulus to invasion (Ellstrand and Schierenbeck 
  <a rid="b97" ref-type="bibr" href="#b97">2000</a>; Schierenbeck and Ellstrand 
  <a rid="b256" ref-type="bibr" href="#b256">2009</a>) and occurs on a continuum from the combining of largely reproductively isolated genomes to the mixing of distinct populations within a species. Hybridization offers many potential advantages during invasion. It may increase adaptive potential through the injection of genetic variation and the formation of beneficial gene combinations (Anderson 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">1948</a>). Hybridization is known to result in transgressive segregation, where phenotypic variation in the hybrids exceeds that of the parents (Rieseberg et al. 
  <a rid="b242" ref-type="bibr" href="#b242">2003</a>). In sunflowers and Louisiana irises, there are particularly compelling cases for hybridization facilitating the colonization of novel habitats (Rieseberg et al. 
  <a rid="b242" ref-type="bibr" href="#b242">2003</a>, 
  <a rid="b243" ref-type="bibr" href="#b243">2007</a>; Arnold et al. 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over the short term, heterosis (improved performance of hybrid offspring) could be important for overcoming demographic stochasticity associated with initial establishment (Drake 
  <a rid="b90" ref-type="bibr" href="#b90">2006</a>; Keller and Taylor 
  <a rid="b156" ref-type="bibr" href="#b156">2010</a>; Rius and Darling 
  <a rid="b245" ref-type="bibr" href="#b245">2014</a>). Although heterosis is transitory in most cases (Hochholdinger and Hoecker 
  <a rid="b138" ref-type="bibr" href="#b138">2007</a>), fixed heterozygosity can be maintained across generations in allopolyploids (assuming disomic inheritance occurs) and asexually reproducing species (Ellstrand and Schierenbeck 
  <a rid="b97" ref-type="bibr" href="#b97">2000</a>; Rieseberg et al. 
  <a rid="b243" ref-type="bibr" href="#b243">2007</a>). In addition, if dominance is the primary cause of heterosis, the advantage of hybridization may continue in later generations and facilitate the purging of genetic load (Burke and Arnold 
  <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">2001</a>). Alternative mildly deleterious alleles can become fixed within diverging populations due to the effects of genetic drift. Hybridization between these lineages could produce descendants with an intrinsic fitness advantage over their parents that is maintained if the combined effects of recombination and natural selection erode the frequency of these deleterious alleles (Ellstrand and Schierenbeck 
  <a rid="b97" ref-type="bibr" href="#b97">2000</a>; Burke and Arnold 
  <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">2001</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic tools can help in identifying the consequences of these processes because they can be followed across different parts of the genome. This applies particularly to plants where invasive taxa often arise as hybrids (Moody and Les 
  <a rid="b199" ref-type="bibr" href="#b199">2007</a>; Ainouche et al. 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2009</a>; Schierenbeck and Ellstrand 
  <a rid="b256" ref-type="bibr" href="#b256">2009</a>). One famous case is of the damaging riparian invasive 
  <span class="italic">Tamarix</span> species in the USA. The main invasive lineage arose from hybridization between two introduced species, 
  <span class="italic">T. chinensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">T. ramosissima</span>, which have largely separate ranges with some overlap in Asia, but do not appear to hybridize there (Gaskin and Schaal 
  <a rid="b116" ref-type="bibr" href="#b116">2002</a>). Genome-wide neutral markers revealed that hybrids dominate the invasive range, and the level of introgression is strongly correlated with latitude (Gaskin and Kazmer 
  <a rid="b115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b115">2009</a>). A corresponding latitudinal cline in cold hardiness suggests that hybridization may have contributed to the rapid adaptation of 
  <span class="italic">Tamarix</span> to climatic extremes in North America (Friedman et al. 
  <a rid="b110" ref-type="bibr" href="#b110">2008</a>). In reed canarygrass, multiple introductions into North America of genetic material from different European regions have mitigated the impact of genetic bottlenecks (Lavergne and Molofsky 
  <a rid="b165" ref-type="bibr" href="#b165">2007</a>). This species has higher genetic diversity and heritable phenotypic variation in its invasive range relative to its native range. Comparisons of neutral differentiation (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub>) to differentiation in quantitative traits among populations (
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>ST</sub>) provide evidence for rapid selection of genotypes with greater vegetative colonization ability and phenotypic plasticity in the introduced range.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hybridization is expected to be important from the perspective of invasiveness under climate change for two reasons. First, evidence is growing that climate change is increasing rates of hybridization, as species that were previously geographically isolated come into contact with each other (Garroway et al. 
  <a rid="b114" ref-type="bibr" href="#b114">2010</a>; Muhlfeld et al. 
  <a rid="b203" ref-type="bibr" href="#b203">2014</a>). Second, evidence from genomic studies is revealing that genes associated with climate change adaptation can be of hybrid origin (Becker et al. 
  <a rid="b23" ref-type="bibr" href="#b23">2013</a>; De La Torre et al. 
  <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">2014</a>). Thus, when hybrids are formed, they may contribute to rapid adaptation under climate change. Although most information on hybridization comes from plants, hybridization is also likely to play an important role in the adaptation of animal lineages to climate change. Genomic comparisons have indicated introgression of invasive genes across lineage boundaries affected by climate in birds (Taylor et al. 
  <a rid="b287" ref-type="bibr" href="#b287">2014</a>) and stick insects (Nosil et al. 
  <a rid="b208" ref-type="bibr" href="#b208">2012</a>). Introgressed genotypes can be favoured under changing climatic conditions as evident in hybridization events in swallowtail butterflies (Scriber 
  <a rid="b262" ref-type="bibr" href="#b262">2011</a>) and in 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles</span> mosquitoes (Besansky et al. 
  <a rid="b30" ref-type="bibr" href="#b30">2003</a>). Genome scans across multiple related species along climate gradients are likely to provide many other examples of candidate genomic regions associated with climate adaptation and exchanged through hybridization and introgression.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polyploidy has occurred frequently in the evolutionary history of angiosperms, often associated with hybridization events (Wood et al. 
  <a rid="b319" ref-type="bibr" href="#b319">2009</a>). There are several examples of recently derived invasive polyploids (Ainouche et al. 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2009</a>; Schierenbeck and Ellstrand 
  <a rid="b256" ref-type="bibr" href="#b256">2009</a>; te Beest et al. 
  <a rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24">2012</a>), and polyploidy is over-represented among alien plant taxa (e.g. Pandit et al. 
  <a rid="b212" ref-type="bibr" href="#b212">2011</a>). Polyploidy is associated with several advantages (reviewed in Otto and Whitton 
  <a rid="b211" ref-type="bibr" href="#b211">2000</a>; Comai 
  <a rid="b71" ref-type="bibr" href="#b71">2005</a>; Otto 
  <a rid="b210" ref-type="bibr" href="#b210">2007</a>; te Beest et al. 
  <a rid="b24" ref-type="bibr" href="#b24">2012</a>) that could aid in invasion, including pre-adapting species to the environmental conditions in the new range (e.g. Henery et al. 
  <a rid="b134" ref-type="bibr" href="#b134">2010</a>), masking deleterious alleles (Otto and Whitton 
  <a rid="b211" ref-type="bibr" href="#b211">2000</a>; Otto 
  <a rid="b210" ref-type="bibr" href="#b210">2007</a>), restoring fertility through chromosome doubling (e.g. Ainouche et al. 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2009</a>) or through changes to the reproductive system to that contribute to colonization ability (e.g. Robertson et al. 
  <a rid="b246" ref-type="bibr" href="#b246">2011</a>). In addition, allopolyploids benefit from fixed heterozygosity due to the combining of divergent parental genomes. This feature may have contributed to the evolutionary success of polyploids over diploids in the Arctic enabling them to survive dramatic shifts in climate (Brochmann et al. 
  <a rid="b43" ref-type="bibr" href="#b43">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the best examples of polyploidy contributing to invasion success is tetraploid spotted knapweed, 
  <span class="italic">Centaurea stoebe</span>. Although both diploids and tetraploids were introduced into the USA from Europe, invasive populations are dominated by tetraploids (Treier et al. 
  <a rid="b296" ref-type="bibr" href="#b296">2009</a>). Tetraploids are pre-adapted to a wider range of climates compared to diploids, and following introduction, they may have further adapted to their introduced environment (Treier et al. 
  <a rid="b296" ref-type="bibr" href="#b296">2009</a>; Henery et al. 
  <a rid="b134" ref-type="bibr" href="#b134">2010</a>). A classic example of hybridization and polyploidy coinciding with invasion is 
  <span class="italic">Spartina anglica</span>. This species is a recently formed allopolyploid (12×) that is highly invasive compared to its parental species, is able to colonize a broader range of habitats and exhibits substantial phenotypic plasticity (Thompson 
  <a rid="b290" ref-type="bibr" href="#b290">1991</a>; Ainouche et al. 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2009</a>), despite a strong genetic bottleneck that occurred during its formation (Baumel et al. 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">2001</a>). Neo-allopolyploids often undergo extensive alterations to their genome and transcriptome, and genomic studies of 
  <span class="italic">S. anglica</span> are dissecting the genetic, epigenetic and expression changes following hybridization and genome duplication (Salmon et al. 
  <a rid="b252" ref-type="bibr" href="#b252">2005</a>; Ainouche et al. 
  <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2009</a>; Chelaifa et al. 
  <a rid="b59" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59">2010</a>). However, the mechanism by which 
  <span class="italic">S. anglica</span> has become invasive remains elusive, and it is not known whether the success of this species reflects fixed heterosis and restored fertility of the hybrid following genome duplication, or phenotypic novelty due to epigenetic and transcriptome remodelling.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whole-genome and reduced-representation genomic approaches are invaluable for detecting hybridization, and more powerful than any other method to quantify the extent of introgression of genomic material and (potentially) functional genes involved in environmental tolerance and invasiveness. They have been used to estimate rates and genomic extent of hybridization (Larson et al. 
  <a rid="b163" ref-type="bibr" href="#b163">2013</a>; Parchman et al. 
  <a rid="b213" ref-type="bibr" href="#b213">2013</a>) and identify the potential for genetic swamping, or hybrid incompatibilities that may be deleterious to native species (Fitzpatrick et al. 
  <a rid="b104" ref-type="bibr" href="#b104">2010</a>). Applying genetic and genomic methods to recent polyploids poses extra challenges due to the presence of multiple genome and gene copies; this can complicate short-read alignment and 
  <span class="italic">de novo</span> assembly of genomes, but can also be useful in establishing patterns of relatedness among species and populations (Griffin et al. 
  <a rid="b125" ref-type="bibr" href="#b125">2011</a>). Reference genomes are especially valuable tools in these cases and are helping to reveal within-species diversity and hybrid origins of polyploids (e.g. Evans et al. 
  <a rid="b100" ref-type="bibr" href="#b100">2014</a>; Marcussen et al. 
  <a rid="b184" ref-type="bibr" href="#b184">2014</a>), and reduced-representation library methods can now be applied even without a reference genome (Lu et al. 
  <a rid="b181" ref-type="bibr" href="#b181">2013</a>). Genomic studies of several plant groups are pointing to porous species barriers across thousands of years where ongoing hybridization and gene flow between species is present despite species maintaining their morphological integrity (e.g. De La Torre et al. 
  <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">2014</a>; Griffin and Hoffmann 
  <a rid="b124" ref-type="bibr" href="#b124">2014</a>). Such a dynamic process of hybridization and polyploidy may also occur among different chromosomal races within a species as in the case of buffel grass, which is weedy and invasive in some areas of its current range and consists of different polyploids that vary in their environmental distributions and invasiveness (Kharrat-Souissi et al. 
  <a rid="b157" ref-type="bibr" href="#b157">2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
