<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic and evolutionary studies of invasive organisms</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An increasing number of studies have documented evolutionary changes in invasive populations, typically over ecological timescales (Lee 
  <a rid="b170" ref-type="bibr" href="#b170">2002</a>; Prentis et al. 
  <a rid="b225" ref-type="bibr" href="#b225">2008</a>; Whitney and Gabler 
  <a rid="b316" ref-type="bibr" href="#b316">2008</a>). These studies have shown that evolutionary adaptation can be rapid in a broad range of invasive organisms. Examples include copepods adapting to different salinity levels (Lee and Petersen 
  <a rid="b172" ref-type="bibr" href="#b172">2002</a>), soapberry bugs adapting to new host plants (Carroll et al. 
  <a rid="b54" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54">2001</a>), and invasive weeds adapting through mimicry to evade eradication (Barrett 
  <a rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17">1983</a>). Moreover, several of the documented examples of rapid evolutionary adaptation involve responses to climate change over a few decades. These include the evolution of 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila</span> body size and inversion frequencies following invasion across continents with latitudinal climate variation (Huey et al. 
  <a rid="b143" ref-type="bibr" href="#b143">2000</a>), the evolution of rabbits along a heat gradient following invasion into Australia (Williams and Moore 
  <a rid="b318" ref-type="bibr" href="#b318">1989</a>), and changes in flowering time in 
  <span class="italic">Solidago</span> goldenrods following introduction into Europe (Weber and Schmid 
  <a rid="b313" ref-type="bibr" href="#b313">1998</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent work has continued to reinforce the notion that evolutionary genetic changes in invasive species can be rapid and often involve responses to climate. For instance, purple loosestrife, 
  <span class="italic">Lythrum salicaria,</span> has invaded wetlands across an introduced range that covers a latitudinal gradient extending in eastern North America from 39°N to 48.5°N. Along this gradient, Colautti and Barrett (
  <a rid="b67" ref-type="bibr" href="#b67">2013</a>) showed an adaptive cline in flowering time, with earlier flowering at the northern invasion front, where it increases survival and fruit set, but with selection against earlier flowering in the south where it decreases vegetative growth. Climate adaptation involving changes in flowering traits has been recorded in several other invasive plant species (Moran and Alexander 
  <a rid="b201" ref-type="bibr" href="#b201">2014</a>). Evolution of traits in response to climate in invasive species has also been found for a range of animals. In 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila subobscura</span>, introduced into Chile in the late 1970s, evolutionary divergence in thermal preferences among populations from different climates has weakened clines in chromosomal inversion (Castañeda et al. 
  <a rid="b57" ref-type="bibr" href="#b57">2013</a>). Likewise, physiological tolerances appear to have diverged in response to climate in the mite 
  <span class="italic">Halotydeus destructor</span> (Hill et al. 
  <a rid="b137" ref-type="bibr" href="#b137">2013</a>). Several researchers have argued that evolution in invasive species can provide general answers to questions of whether species will be able to adapt to rapid climate change (Moran and Alexander 
  <a rid="b201" ref-type="bibr" href="#b201">2014</a>), including those about the speed of evolutionary change, the specific nature of the change that has occurred and factors that might limit evolutionary change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from their use to investigate adaptive changes, genetic tools have also been used to understand the dynamic nature of invasive processes. In particular, genetic markers have been widely used to detect invasive organisms, investigate patterns of historical movement in invasive species and examine the role of genetic variation in ensuring the success of invasions (Armstrong and Ball 
  <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">2005</a>; Lawson Handley et al. 
  <a rid="b166" ref-type="bibr" href="#b166">2011</a>; Blanchet 
  <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2012</a>). Most past studies have focussed on markers thought to be selectively neutral, initially allozymes and then later microsatellites, AFLPs and other DNA markers. These markers can indicate the status of invasive species, origin of invasive populations and the levels of genetic variation in invading populations when compared to the populations of origin. Recent examples include tracking invasions of the winter annual 
  <span class="italic">Geranium carolinianum</span> in China from multiple origins (Shirk et al. 
  <a rid="b264" ref-type="bibr" href="#b264">2014</a>), identifying a key translocation event in the invasion by a coregonid fish of a major Scandinavian watershed (Præbel et al. 
  <a rid="b223" ref-type="bibr" href="#b223">2013</a>), the use of mtDNA markers and microsatellites to trace the invasion history of eastern mosquitofish (
  <span class="italic">Gambusia holbrooki</span>) into Australia (Ayres et al. 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2012</a>) and determining multiple origins of invasive acacias in South Africa and South Australia (Le Roux et al. 
  <a rid="b168" ref-type="bibr" href="#b168">2011</a>; Millar et al. 
  <a rid="b196" ref-type="bibr" href="#b196">2012</a>). Genetic markers have also provided much information on the biology of invasive species, such as modes of reproduction (Weeks et al. 
  <a rid="b314" ref-type="bibr" href="#b314">1995</a>; Ali et al. 
  <a rid="b6" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6">2014</a>; Molins et al. 
  <a rid="b198" ref-type="bibr" href="#b198">2014</a>), movement patterns and rates (Bronnenhuber et al. 
  <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011</a>; Kirk et al. 
  <a rid="b158" ref-type="bibr" href="#b158">2011</a>; Berthouly-Salazar et al. 
  <a rid="b29" ref-type="bibr" href="#b29">2013</a>) and predator–prey relationships (Kasper et al. 
  <a rid="b153" ref-type="bibr" href="#b153">2004</a>; Blanchet 
  <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2012</a>; Valdez-Moreno et al. 
  <a rid="b298" ref-type="bibr" href="#b298">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These types of studies are now being supplemented with a range of genomic and transcriptomic approaches that are providing answers to questions about the origins of invasive populations at a new level of resolution, providing new ways of monitoring for invasive organisms, and leading to an understanding of the nature of the changes that underlie adaptive shifts. We consider the promise provided by these studies within the context of detecting and managing biological invasions as climate change proceeds, and within a framework of the different steps involved in detecting and responding to an invader, understanding its source, and then tracking its impact on the surroundings (Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
