<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spread</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding the spread/expansion phase of an invasion has similarities with species range projections in climate change biology (Caplat et al. 
  <a rid="b53" ref-type="bibr" href="#b53">2013</a>). To expand its range into new environments, a species requires appropriate dispersal traits and tolerance of a range of environments or capacity to experience the new environment as consistently receptive. Dispersal traits are a key characteristic of invasive species, and dispersal occurs through direct movement (in the case of animals) or indirect movement, by seed or vegetative dispersal (in the case of plants), dispersal through soil or water (e.g. the plant pathogen 
  <span class="italic">Phytophthora cinnamomi</span>) or human-mediated dispersal (e.g. weedy species along roadsides, cane toads in transport vehicles and vertebrates on ships).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic studies on populations can be used to test ecological hypotheses about dispersal patterns in invasive species once these have become established in a new area and started to spread, including the widely documented lag phase before populations disperse widely (Richardson et al. 
  <a rid="b241" ref-type="bibr" href="#b241">2011</a>). For instance, Rohfritsch et al. (
  <a rid="b248" ref-type="bibr" href="#b248">2013</a>) used genomic data to map the spread of an invasive oyster across Europe following its introduction from Asia. This approach is particularly powerful when combined with ecological models that predict the extent to which populations are expected to occupy new space across time or maintain refugia under a changing climate, both of which should be reflected in patterns of genetic variation (Fordham et al. 
  <a rid="b106" ref-type="bibr" href="#b106">2014</a>). For example, genomic approaches have been used to understand patterns of spread in Australian 
  <span class="italic">Acacia</span> species that have subsequently invaded southern Africa. These include estimating the impacts of human-assisted dispersal in the native range prior to introduction (Le Roux et al. 
  <a rid="b169" ref-type="bibr" href="#b169">2013</a>) and better forecasting of the effects of climate change by accounting for genotypic variation (see Millar et al. 
  <a rid="b195" ref-type="bibr" href="#b195">2011</a>; Thompson et al. 
  <a rid="b291" ref-type="bibr" href="#b291">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population genomic data can also be used to understand the impact of spreading invaders through hybridization and introgression. As discussed above, invaders spreading into non-native habitat, particularly under climate change, are expected to hybridize with local species where reproductive isolation is incomplete. This can lead to the incursion of genes from the invaders into native species. As a consequence, local species can become genetically ‘polluted’, resulting in the loss of species integrity. Genomic markers provide a way of detecting such pollution (e.g. Yamazaki et al. 
  <a rid="b322" ref-type="bibr" href="#b322">2005</a>; Sampson and Byrne 
  <a rid="b253" ref-type="bibr" href="#b253">2008</a>; Millar et al. 
  <a rid="b196" ref-type="bibr" href="#b196">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mechanisms of dispersal can evolve, as in the case of leg length in the cane toad (Phillips et al. 
  <a rid="b218" ref-type="bibr" href="#b218">2006</a>), and seed dispersal in 
  <span class="italic">Abronia umbellata</span> (Darling et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2008b</a>). In these cases, genomic studies on quantitative traits can provide information on the genes and pathways involved. Dispersal evolution may involve traits directly involved in movement, such as cane toad leg length, or more subtle changes that nevertheless enhance dispersal potential, such as altered timing of reproduction that increases seed dispersal. Genomic data can identify the nature of these evolved changes in mechanisms that alter the potential of populations to spread. For instance, QTLs have been isolated that control the formation of rhizomes in perennial wild rye that represents an important trait facilitating colonization in weedy ryegrass species (Yun et al. 
  <a rid="b329" ref-type="bibr" href="#b329">2014</a>). Understanding the genomic basis of traits involved in non-human-mediated dispersal may aid in predicting the invasive potential of suspect species before introduction or at the establishment stage (Pérez et al. 
  <a rid="b215" ref-type="bibr" href="#b215">2006</a>), as well as projecting their future spread in cases where dispersal traits can evolve.
 </p>
</sec>
