<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We obtained species distribution data for amphibians, mammals, and from refs. 
 <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref> and 
 <xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>. Climatic data were obtained from the ISIMIP project (
 <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>) (see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">SI Materials and Methods</italic>
 </ext-link> for further details on all data used). We used two types of SDMs, generalized boosted regression models (GBM) and generalized additive models (GAM), to model the relationship between the bioclimatic variables and current species’ distributions. These two widely used models were selected due to their good performance compared with other modeling approaches (
 <xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>
 <xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>) and to provide a contrast between an additive model (GAM) and a classification and regression tree-based modeling approach (GBM) (see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">SI Materials and Methods</italic>
 </ext-link> for details on the approaches used, model validation, pseudoabsence selection, and spatial autocorrelation). Species’ probabilities of occurrence were projected for current (1995) and future (2080) conditions under the assumption of different dispersal scenarios (see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">SI Material and Methods</italic>
 </ext-link> for the definition of the respective 30-y time periods and details on the dispersal scenarios). Projections of species current and future probabilities of occurrence varied between the different SDM/GCM combinations. To document this variation, we calculated the coefficient of variation among the eight different estimates of projected species richness, based on summed probabilities of occurrence, for each grid cell (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Figs. S4 and S5
 </ext-link>). We also calculated the variation of the changes in mean probability of occurrence, across a species range, among all species for each of the different SDM/GCM combinations (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Figs. S10 and S11
 </ext-link>).
</p>
