<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We documented relationships between phenotypic traits recognized as being critical to fitness and genetic variation at a very fine spatial scale in female mule deer. These results provide insight into the genetic structuring of the population and the possible genetic drivers shaping the diversity of phenotypes and migration strategies seen in this important game species. These findings have potential implications for conservation and management, particularly in light of contemporary climatic changes and white-tailed deer expansion (Latham et al. 
  <a rid="b39" ref-type="bibr" href="#b39">2011</a>), as both migration timing and body condition are influential traits for mule deer survival and reproduction that vary among individuals in a population (Monteith et al. 
  <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011b</a>, 
  <a rid="b46" ref-type="bibr" href="#b46">2013</a>). Examining these traits conjointly provided a more complete picture of the genetic contributions to important phenotypic traits in this population and cervids in general.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic-migration correlations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fall and spring migration dates were more similar among related females. An individual's mtDNA haplogroup also was a stronger predictor of fall than spring migration – even when controlling for winter or summer range. The mtDNA haplotype effect is particularly striking, given there appears to be virtually no spatial clustering of haplotypes (Fig. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a>). Female philopatry and relatedness among social groups would explain the pattern in the form of learning (e.g., the majority of white-tailed deer fawns follow their mother's migration route; Nelson 
   <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">1998</a>); however, our model accounted for such effects through the range covariates (i.e., if daughters were following their mother's migration path they would also share a winter and summer range), and the diversity of haplotypes suggests many different matrilines. In addition, upon examination of individual migratory routes, we found only two deer that shared an identical route. An analysis including males could test this hypothesis (
   <span class="italic">sensu</span> Nielsen et al. 
   <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">2013</a>) or at least be viewed as an independent replicate as males are more prone to disperse (Nelson 
   <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">1993</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, Colorado represents a confluence of several different refugial lineages (Latch et al. 
   <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2009</a>), with recolonization routes and so-called hybrid hot spot clusters falling directly in northwestern Colorado (Swenson and Howard 
   <a rid="b77" ref-type="bibr" href="#b77">2005</a>). We hypothesize that the mtDNA effect we documented is either: (i) reflective of different refugial histories and biogeography of the mtDNA lineages (Latch et al. 
   <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2009</a>), where for example, mule deer originating in northern regions would have locally adapted phenotypes and distinct haplotypes linked to earlier migration times than those from the south (a carryover effect); or (ii) due to differences in energetics related to mtDNA, where, for example, Toews et al. (
   <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2014</a>) showed that mitochondrial introgression (where different haplotypes had different energetic outputs) was responsible for differing migratory behavior in a warbler transition zone.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monteith et al. (
   <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>) and Lendrum et al. (
   <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2013</a>) showed that spring migration timing is closely linked to plant phenology, as deer aim to arrive on their summer range close in time to the peak of plant productivity. Spring arrival dates are more likely to follow plant phenology on individual deer summer ranges, whereas fall migration is linked to weather (temperature and snow on summer range) and individual characteristics such as age and condition. Monteith et al. (
   <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>) suggested that prime age individuals in the best condition can adopt a strategy by which they stay on summer range for longer time periods to consume higher quality vegetation in spite of the potential for being caught in adverse weather, while poorer quality individuals cannot take on such risks. The individual characteristic hypothesis of Monteith et al. (
   <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011b</a>) provides support for the energetics scenario (ii above), whereby individuals with certain haplotypes might be better suited for taking on the risks associated with remaining on summer range later in the season due to associated differences in energetics.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fine-scale natal dispersal has been shown to have a heritable basis in albatross (Charmantier et al. 
   <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">2011</a>), and genotype–phenotype associations are thought to be important next steps in migration studies (Liedvogel et al. 
   <a rid="b41" ref-type="bibr" href="#b41">2011</a>). For the carryover effect to be true, the mtDNA lineages must reflect nuclear differences that (at least partially) encode for differences in migratory behavior or have a physiological effect. While our results cannot tease apart a specific nuclear or mitochondrial effect, given the mtDNA migration effect shown in warblers (Toews et al. 
   <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2014</a>), we think this is worth following up on using both biochemical modeling and genome-wide scans (i.e., with mtDNA haplotype as the response measure or interaction term). Importantly, recent development in the western United States has raised concerns over the sustainability of mule deer migratory routes (Sawyer et al. 
   <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2005</a>, 
   <a rid="b67" ref-type="bibr" href="#b67">2009</a>), and under climate change, there is the potential for trophic mismatch for migratory species, whereby migrations occur asynchronously with plant phenology (Post et al. 
   <a rid="b59" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59">2008</a>). Monteith et al. (
   <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011b</a> suggested that plasticity in mule deer migration might allow the species to avoid such mismatches; however, if there is a genetic basis for the variability in migration among individuals, there may be less plasticity and more natural selection at work (Nelson 
   <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">1998</a>). Mitochondrial introgression with white-tailed deer is likely to be unidirectional (Carr et al. 
   <a rid="b6" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6">1986</a>), which could jeopardize the adaptive potential if hybridizations increase. However, we note that there is no evidence of white-tailed deer presence in our study area, and thus, hybridization is not a concern at this point. The potential for loss of migratory routes to development combined with climate change and hybridization highlight the importance of maintaining the existing genetic variability in diverse migratory phenotypes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic–condition correlations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fat is an important determinant of fitness for mule deer (Bender et al. 
   <a rid="b2" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2">2007</a>; Johnstone-Yellin et al. 
   <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">2009</a>; Tollefson et al. 
   <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">2010</a>). We identified two genetic markers as having relationships with fat, although the relationships were antagonistic (i.e., one had a positive relationship with fat and the other negative). Similar results have been seen in studies of both the Kentish plover (
   <span class="italic">Charadrius alexandrinus</span> L.; Kupper et al. 
   <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2010</a>) and the blue tit (
   <span class="italic">Parus caeruleus</span> L.; Olano-Marin et al. 
   <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">2011</a>). With the contrasting signals of the two markers, interpretations of what these relationships represent become muddled. Olano-Marin et al. (
   <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">2011</a>) viewed the negative correlation as evidence for direct effects of the neutral loci, with the positive correlation due to inbreeding. Inbreeding in our study area is not supported by the 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>IS</sub> values and difficult to imagine given the population size and deer ecology.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the evidence for a mixing of different mitochondrial lineages and effect sizes, the negative relationship to body fat of RT30 (0.99 probability and nearly double the effect size as all other loci) is the most likely to be genuine. However, given the concern over spurious HFCs, we must still consider the possibility of Type I errors (i.e., false positives). The potential for type I errors is of particular concern when detecting local effects and examining multiple models (Szulkin et al. 
   <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). In light of this concern, we highlight three points of support for the recorded relationship. First, the effect sizes of the significant coefficients were substantially greater than those of the other loci (Fig. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>). Second, we refit all models that had significant coefficients, but with a strong mean 0 multivariate normal prior on the coefficients. This approach shrinks all estimates toward 0, acting as a penalty and reducing the number of significant covariates (Gelman et al. 
   <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">2012</a>). In the case of the SLH – fat correlation, all significant results (probability of an effect &gt; 0.95) remained. Lastly, the proximity of a locus in question relative to genes of known effect can be taken as supportive evidence for understanding single-locus HFCs (Von Hardenberg et al. 
   <a rid="b84" ref-type="bibr" href="#b84">2007</a>; Kupper et al. 
   <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2010</a>). Slate et al. (
   <a rid="b72" ref-type="bibr" href="#b72">2002</a>) observed considerable synteny in ruminants, and more than half of the microsatellites used in their deer linkage map had been used for the same purposes in cow and sheep. When we screened RT30 against the annotated cow genome (using 
   <span class="sc">blast</span>), both primers colocalized with 100% identity to a region with the closest known gene being that of TBC1D1. Interestingly, this gene regulates cell growth and differentiation and has been shown to influence fat metabolism in mice and humans (Stone et al. 
   <a rid="b76" ref-type="bibr" href="#b76">2006</a>; Chadt et al. 
   <a rid="b8" ref-type="bibr" href="#b8">2008</a>). Given the combination of divergent mtDNA lineages in our study area and panmixia (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 1), a slight disruption of co-adapted alleles that are linked to fat metabolism could explain the negative correlation between this locus and fat (we emphasize these results represent a small effect as body fat was predicted to decrease body fat by &lt;0.2% in the model). This is predicted to outcome when locally adapted lineages mix, and it has been recently suggested for grizzly bears in an area where they are subject to large-scale human-assisted migration (Shafer et al. 
   <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the above lines of evidence offer support to the effect of RT30 on fat being genuine, given the small number of loci examined, we must remain skeptical about this relationship. Rather, we present these findings as noteworthy and in need of confirmation by studies with larger samples and with genomic methods.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions and evolutionary applications</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have shown fine-scale relationships between genetic variation and phenotypic traits in mule deer that have not been found in previous work on this species. Our study identified fine-scale genetic correlates to both migration timing and body fat that are likely overlooked (and probably unexpected) in this species. These results have potential management implications for mule deer, which are under substantial human pressure from a multitude of stressors (Sawyer et al. 
   <a rid="b66" ref-type="bibr" href="#b66">2006</a>). The genetic polymorphisms in this population that are linked to phenotypic traits related to phenology and metabolic variation could prove important in the face of climate change and other anthropogenic stressors that are likely to affect both optimal timing of migration and the role of fat stores in survival and reproduction. Monitoring hybridization with white-tailed deer should also be considered with respect to the mtDNA effect, as introgression is likely to go from white-tailed to mule deer (Carr et al. 
   <a rid="b6" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6">1986</a>) and could alter the adaptive potential. Efforts should be made to better characterize additional drivers behind this phenotypic and genetic variation in an effort to maintain a diversity of phenotypes that might best be able to adapt to novel conditions. Screening for similar associations in more imperiled deer populations (and cervid species) may help shed light on local population dynamics and better inform management decisions.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
