<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding variation in phenotypic traits related to fitness in wild populations is fundamental to the study of evolution and ecology. Such traits can be related to genetic variation at relatively fine spatial scales, and knowledge of these relationships can provide insight into important eco-evolutionary processes such as inbreeding depression, local adaptation, population structure, and speciation (Kupper et al. 
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2010</a>; Olano-Marin et al. 
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">2011</a>; Shafer and Wolf 
  <a rid="b69" ref-type="bibr" href="#b69">2013</a>; Shafer et al. 
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">2014</a>). Moreover, these relationships can have implications for developing and implementing conservation and management plans that strive to account for evolutionary processes (e.g., maintenance of gene flow through protection of corridors or minimizing possible effects of inbreeding).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relationships between fine-scale genetic variation and phenotypic traits have been identified using a variety of methods. Chief among these in wild populations are heterozygosity–fitness correlations (HFCs; see Chapman et al. 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2009</a>) and correlations among genetic differentiation and phenotypic or ecological divergence (Shafer and Wolf 
  <a rid="b69" ref-type="bibr" href="#b69">2013</a>). Heterozygosity–fitness correlations are typically calculated between heterozygosity at neutral loci and phenotypic traits presumed to be proxies for fitness (Szulkin et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). Correlations can occur with a multilocus heterozygosity (MLH) metric, indicating a general genome-wide effect of inbreeding, or heterozygosity at a single locus (single-locus heterozygosity; SLH), indicating local (either direct or indirect) effects due to linkage to a gene that affects fitness (Hansson et al. 
  <a rid="b30" ref-type="bibr" href="#b30">2004</a>). For the latter, individual neutral markers are hypothesized to show associative overdominance as a result of the consequences of deleterious alleles or a fitness advantage at those linked loci (Frydenberg 
  <a rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25">1963</a>; Houle 
  <a rid="b32" ref-type="bibr" href="#b32">1989</a>; David et al. 
  <a rid="b21" ref-type="bibr" href="#b21">1995</a>; David 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1997</a>; Pamilo and Palsson 
  <a rid="b52" ref-type="bibr" href="#b52">1998</a>). Screening for HFCs can be described as a tantalizing pursuit; significant relationships are rarely found and care must be used with interpretation as overall effect sizes often are variable and small (Chapman et al. 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2009</a>; Kardos et al. 
  <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2014</a>), and numerous concerns (but also caveats) related to the HFC exist (Szulkin et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). Given the potential for false positives with SLH correlations, confidence in these relationships can be bolstered by appropriate statistical analyses and by examining the location of loci on the annotated genome of a related species that might provide 
  <span class="italic">post hoc</span> links to causative agents (Von Hardenberg et al. 
  <a rid="b84" ref-type="bibr" href="#b84">2007</a>; Kupper et al. 
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2010</a>; Kardos et al. 
  <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In slight contrast, correlations between genetic differentiation and phenotypic (or ecological) divergence have been identified across taxa and appear to be relatively robust (Shafer and Wolf 
  <a rid="b69" ref-type="bibr" href="#b69">2013</a>; Sexton et al. 
  <a rid="b68" ref-type="bibr" href="#b68">2014</a>). While this pattern is generally regarded as evidence for local adaptation (Nosil 
  <a rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" href="#b50">2012</a>), ancestral (allopatric) divergence and secondary contact can confound interpretations of this correlation (Bierne et al. 
  <a rid="b4" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4">2013</a>) and, similar to HFCs, must be factored into interpretations and models. But beyond these caveats, correlations between phenotypic traits and both genetic diversity and differentiation can provide important indications of inbreeding and local adaptation that should be considered by managers (Shafer et al. 
  <a rid="b70" ref-type="bibr" href="#b70">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mule deer ecology and evolution</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cervids (family 
   <span class="italic">Cervidae</span>) are an ecologically important group of ungulate that have been the focus of numerous investigations into the relationship between genetic variation and phenotypic traits. Da Silva et al. (
   <a rid="b19" ref-type="bibr" href="#b19">2009</a>) showed that juvenile roe deer (
   <span class="italic">Capreolus capreolus</span> L.) survival was correlated with MLH; likewise, red deer (
   <span class="italic">Cervus elaphus</span> L.) birth weight, neonatal survival, and lifetime breeding success increased significantly with heterozygosity (Coulson et al. 
   <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">1998</a>; Slate et al. 
   <a rid="b71" ref-type="bibr" href="#b71">2000</a>), and individuals with the smallest antlers tended to have lower heterozygosity (Perez-Gonzalez et al. 
   <a rid="b54" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54">2010</a>). Furthermore, studies have shown correlations between genetic differentiation and social groups in white-tailed deer (
   <span class="italic">Odocoileus virginianus</span> Zimm.; Miller et al. 
   <a rid="b43" ref-type="bibr" href="#b43">2010</a>), and niche overlap in mule deer (
   <span class="italic">Odocoileus hemionus</span> Raf.; Pease et al. 
   <a rid="b53" ref-type="bibr" href="#b53">2009</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among cervids, mule deer present an interesting species for which to examine correlations between phenotypic traits and genetic variation. Latch et al. (
   <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2009</a>, 
   <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2014</a>) showed that across their range, there are multiple phylogeographic lineages that presumably represent different refugia, although the species shows minimal population-level genetic structure at large geographic scales (Cullingham et al. 
   <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2011b</a>; Powell et al. 
   <a rid="b60" ref-type="bibr" href="#b60">2013</a>). Female mule deer also display fine-scale genetic structuring, likely due to the existence of related social groups (Cullingham et al. 
   <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2011b</a>; Colson et al. 
   <a rid="b12" ref-type="bibr" href="#b12">2013</a>). In addition, hybridization with white-tailed deer can occur, resulting in fairly widespread genetic introgression (Carr et al. 
   <a rid="b6" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6">1986</a>; Cathey et al. 
   <a rid="b7" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7">1998</a>). Mule deer also exhibit substantial variation in important phenotypic traits such as body size and migratory behavior, both across their range (Anderson 
   <a rid="b1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1">1981</a>; Wallmo 
   <a rid="b85" ref-type="bibr" href="#b85">1981</a>), and within populations (Monteith et al. 
   <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>; Lendrum et al. 
   <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2013</a>). Lastly, mule deer are the subject of extensive management programs throughout North America, due to their importance as a game species [e.g., it was estimated that more than 30 000 mule deer were harvested in the state of Colorado in 2013 (Colorado Parks and Wildlife 
   <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">2014</a>)].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both the aforementioned phenotypic traits are of paramount importance for survival and reproduction in this species. Condition is a fitness proxy as individuals rely heavily on fat and protein stores for survival on winter range when forage quality is low (Wallmo et al. 
   <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">1977</a>; Torbit et al. 
   <a rid="b83" ref-type="bibr" href="#b83">1985</a>). Body fat also influences annual survival of adult females (Bender et al. 
   <a rid="b2" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2">2007</a>), pregnancy and twinning rates (Johnstone-Yellin et al. 
   <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">2009</a>; Tollefson et al. 
   <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">2010</a>), and the probability of a female rearing a fawn through the summer (Johnstone-Yellin et al. 
   <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">2009</a>). Deer across much of their range migrate from high altitude, productive summer range to low altitude winter range and back again in the spring. Migrations typically match changes in resource availability (Fryxell and Sinclair 
   <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">1988</a>), with mule deer attempting to optimize migratory timing relative to both plant productivity and weather (snow depth and temperature) on their summer range (Monteith et al. 
   <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>; Lendrum et al. 
   <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2013</a>). The timing of migratory onset is clustered around a few weeks each year, but individuals show different strategies in terms of early or late onset dates (Monteith et al. 
   <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>; Lendrum et al. 
   <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2013</a>). Thus, migration timing is of clear interest in understanding the ecology of this species and, importantly, recent work has identified a clear genetic component to differences in this trait in other taxa (Ruegg et al. 
   <a rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" href="#b64">2014</a>; Toews et al. 
   <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both individual condition and migration are of interest to wildlife managers as recent anthropogenic development may threaten migratory routes for mule deer (Sawyer et al. 
   <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2005</a>, 
   <a rid="b67" ref-type="bibr" href="#b67">2009</a>), and climate change could cause trophic mismatches (Post and Forchhammer 
   <a rid="b58" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58">2008</a>), with phenotypic plasticity in migration being suggested as a potential buffer for mule deer against this process (Monteith et al. 
   <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011b</a>). The importance of winter condition to deer survival has led to active research into means of improving winter condition through habitat manipulation and supplemental feeding (Bishop et al. 
   <a rid="b5" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5">2009</a>; Bergman et al. 
   <a rid="b3" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3">2014</a>). The existence of genetic correlations to these traits could provide insight into the effectiveness of management programs and aid managers in making decisions in light of evolutionary processes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we examined the relationship between genetic variability and phenotypic traits in a wild mule deer population of the Piceance Basin, Colorado. Using an extensive data set consisting of more than 100 individual animals, we combined phenotypic, behavioral (global positioning system [GPS]), and genetic data to (i) examine whether genetic differentiation was correlated with migration timing, (ii) screen for specific mitochondrial haplotypes associated with migration timing, and (iii) test whether heterozygosity (multilocus and single locus) was associated with body mass and fat. We discussed the results in light of the phylogeographic history of mule deer and the metabolic role of the mitochondrion and highlight the importance of considering evolutionary processes in the management of this species.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
