<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic-migration correlations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fall and spring migration dates were more similar among related females. An individual's mtDNA haplogroup also was a stronger predictor of fall than spring migration – even when controlling for winter or summer range. The mtDNA haplotype effect is particularly striking, given there appears to be virtually no spatial clustering of haplotypes (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a>). Female philopatry and relatedness among social groups would explain the pattern in the form of learning (e.g., the majority of white-tailed deer fawns follow their mother's migration route; Nelson 
  <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">1998</a>); however, our model accounted for such effects through the range covariates (i.e., if daughters were following their mother's migration path they would also share a winter and summer range), and the diversity of haplotypes suggests many different matrilines. In addition, upon examination of individual migratory routes, we found only two deer that shared an identical route. An analysis including males could test this hypothesis (
  <span class="italic">sensu</span> Nielsen et al. 
  <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">2013</a>) or at least be viewed as an independent replicate as males are more prone to disperse (Nelson 
  <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">1993</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, Colorado represents a confluence of several different refugial lineages (Latch et al. 
  <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2009</a>), with recolonization routes and so-called hybrid hot spot clusters falling directly in northwestern Colorado (Swenson and Howard 
  <a rid="b77" ref-type="bibr" href="#b77">2005</a>). We hypothesize that the mtDNA effect we documented is either: (i) reflective of different refugial histories and biogeography of the mtDNA lineages (Latch et al. 
  <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2009</a>), where for example, mule deer originating in northern regions would have locally adapted phenotypes and distinct haplotypes linked to earlier migration times than those from the south (a carryover effect); or (ii) due to differences in energetics related to mtDNA, where, for example, Toews et al. (
  <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2014</a>) showed that mitochondrial introgression (where different haplotypes had different energetic outputs) was responsible for differing migratory behavior in a warbler transition zone.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monteith et al. (
  <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>) and Lendrum et al. (
  <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2013</a>) showed that spring migration timing is closely linked to plant phenology, as deer aim to arrive on their summer range close in time to the peak of plant productivity. Spring arrival dates are more likely to follow plant phenology on individual deer summer ranges, whereas fall migration is linked to weather (temperature and snow on summer range) and individual characteristics such as age and condition. Monteith et al. (
  <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2011a</a>) suggested that prime age individuals in the best condition can adopt a strategy by which they stay on summer range for longer time periods to consume higher quality vegetation in spite of the potential for being caught in adverse weather, while poorer quality individuals cannot take on such risks. The individual characteristic hypothesis of Monteith et al. (
  <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011b</a>) provides support for the energetics scenario (ii above), whereby individuals with certain haplotypes might be better suited for taking on the risks associated with remaining on summer range later in the season due to associated differences in energetics.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fine-scale natal dispersal has been shown to have a heritable basis in albatross (Charmantier et al. 
  <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">2011</a>), and genotype–phenotype associations are thought to be important next steps in migration studies (Liedvogel et al. 
  <a rid="b41" ref-type="bibr" href="#b41">2011</a>). For the carryover effect to be true, the mtDNA lineages must reflect nuclear differences that (at least partially) encode for differences in migratory behavior or have a physiological effect. While our results cannot tease apart a specific nuclear or mitochondrial effect, given the mtDNA migration effect shown in warblers (Toews et al. 
  <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2014</a>), we think this is worth following up on using both biochemical modeling and genome-wide scans (i.e., with mtDNA haplotype as the response measure or interaction term). Importantly, recent development in the western United States has raised concerns over the sustainability of mule deer migratory routes (Sawyer et al. 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2005</a>, 
  <a rid="b67" ref-type="bibr" href="#b67">2009</a>), and under climate change, there is the potential for trophic mismatch for migratory species, whereby migrations occur asynchronously with plant phenology (Post et al. 
  <a rid="b59" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59">2008</a>). Monteith et al. (
  <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2011b</a> suggested that plasticity in mule deer migration might allow the species to avoid such mismatches; however, if there is a genetic basis for the variability in migration among individuals, there may be less plasticity and more natural selection at work (Nelson 
  <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">1998</a>). Mitochondrial introgression with white-tailed deer is likely to be unidirectional (Carr et al. 
  <a rid="b6" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6">1986</a>), which could jeopardize the adaptive potential if hybridizations increase. However, we note that there is no evidence of white-tailed deer presence in our study area, and thus, hybridization is not a concern at this point. The potential for loss of migratory routes to development combined with climate change and hybridization highlight the importance of maintaining the existing genetic variability in diverse migratory phenotypes.
 </p>
</sec>
