<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample collection and DNA extraction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured adult (&gt;1 year old) female mule deer using helicopter net gunning in four winter range study areas in the Piceance Basin of Northwestern Colorado (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>). Deer were captured in either December 2010 or March 2011. These dates were chosen because during December, deer have recently migrated from summer range and typically are in their best physical condition, while March represents the end of winter when deer typically are in their worst condition. Deer were transferred to processing sites where we weighed them using a portable scale, estimated body condition by palpating the rump (Cook et al. 
  <a rid="b13" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13">2001</a>, 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15">2010</a>) and measured the thickness of their subcutaneous rump fat and longissimus dorsi muscle using a portable ultrasound (Stephenson et al. 
  <a rid="b74" ref-type="bibr" href="#b74">1998</a>, 
  <a rid="b75" ref-type="bibr" href="#b75">2002</a>; Cook et al. 
  <a rid="b13" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13">2001</a>). The above measurements were used to calculate the percent ingesta-free body fat (hereafter fat) of each deer following Cook et al. (
  <a rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15">2010</a>). Deer were fit with store-on-board GPS radio collars (Advanced Telemetry Systems, Isanti MN, USA) set to attempt a relocation on one of three schedules (once every 5 h, once every 60 min, or once every 30 min – meaning the relocation schedules varied by individual). Blood samples were taken for genetic analysis, and DNA was extracted using the DNeasy™ Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen, Inc., Valencia, CA, USA) following the manufacturer's protocol.
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(A) Winter range areas Ryan Gulch [RG], South Magnolia [SM], North Magnolia [NM] and North Ridge [NR]) and simplifications of migratory routes, with arrows indicating general location of summer ranges for mule deer in the Piceance Basin and (B) location of study within the United States. Adapted with permission from Lendrum et al. (
    <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2013</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0007-0937-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
