<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Is the change adaptive?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Establishing that an observed phenotypic shift has a genetic basis is a necessary condition for inferring adaptive evolution in response to climate change, but it is not entirely sufficient because genetic changes might not be adaptive. In particular, genetic drift (Lande 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b62" href="#b62">1976</a>), gene flow (Garant et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">2007</a>), and inbreeding (Keller and Waller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">2002</a>) can all cause maladaptive genetic changes. Similarly, establishing that an observed phenotypic shift has a plastic basis does not confirm that the change is adaptive – it might instead be the result of environmental stress. Five basic approaches might be considered for inferring the adaptive nature of phenotypic changes: reciprocal transplants, phenotypic selection estimates, genotypic selection estimates, comparison to neutral expectations, and Q
  <sub>ST</sub>–F
  <sub>ST</sub> comparisons.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reciprocal transplants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most direct test for the adaptive significance of a phenotypic change is to reciprocally transplant individuals between environments (Endler 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">1986</a>; Kawecki and Ebert 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">2004</a>; Hereford 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">2009</a>; Blanquart et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2013</a>). This approach is obviously difficult in an allochronic context, but it can be implemented in some situations. In particular, adaptive evolution is confirmed if contemporary genotypes have higher fitness in the contemporary environment than do resurrected genotypes from past environments (e.g., Decaestecker et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">2007</a>). Given that resurrection is feasible for only a small subset of organisms, an alternative approach is to use laboratory or mesocosm experiments to test contemporary genotypes in simulated present and past environments. Higher fitness in the former implies that adaptation to present environments has reduced fitness (owing to trade-offs) in past environments. On the other hand, failure to find higher fitness in present than in past environments does not mean that adaptive evolution is absent – because fitness trade-offs are not always evident between environments (Bennett and Lenski 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">2007</a>; Blanquart et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2013</a>). Note that this approach can be used (with the usual caveats) to assess the adaptive significance of genetic differences (by using individuals from common-garden experiments), plastic differences (by using individuals from experimental manipulations), and their combination (by using individuals captured from the wild).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenotypic selection estimates</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If a given phenotypic change is adaptive, it was likely driven by selection – and so one inferential approach is to measure selection in nature. Specifically, adaptation can be inferred when selection acting during a phenotypic change would be predicted to favor that change (e.g., Swain et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b102" href="#b102">2007</a>; Crozier et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2011</a>). Note, however, that measuring contemporary selection is not sufficient for inferring past selection – because selection can vary through time (Siepielski et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" href="#b97">2009</a>; Siepielski et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b98" href="#b98">2011</a>). Implementing this approach therefore requires long-term datasets of selection. An additional limitation is that the direction of phenotypic change could correspond to the estimated direction of selection without the two being causally linked (Merilä et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b75" href="#b75">2001</a>) – although the estimation of selection on breeding values can reduce this concern (Hadfield et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b76" href="#b76">2012</a>; see above). Also, as noted earlier, accurate estimates of selection are extremely difficult to obtain in most natural populations.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genotypic selection estimates</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analogous to the phenotypic selection approach, investigators can ask whether observed shifts in allele frequency correspond to selection on those alleles. This selection can be estimated either directly or indirectly. Directly, one can genotype individuals and then measure their fitness (e.g., Fournier-Level et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">2011</a>) or, if individuals cannot be tracked in this manner, allele frequency differences can be measured between age groups. These approaches are attended by many of the same issues that were discussed immediately above for phenotypic selection. Indirectly, one can test for genomic signatures of past selection (e.g., Storz 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b101" href="#b101">2005</a>; Foll and Gaggiotti 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2008</a>). Limitations here are that it can be difficult to ascertain the relative contributions of selection as opposed to other factors (e.g., population structure and recombination), and when the past selection took place (Barrett and Hoekstra 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">2011</a>; Nachman and Payseur 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b78" href="#b78">2012</a>). An additional limitation of these genotypic approaches is that selection at the genotypic level does not necessarily reflect selection at the phenotypic level. For example, selection on polygenic traits can be very difficult to detect at the individual loci that influence those traits (McKay and Latta 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b73" href="#b73">2002</a>; Le Corre and Kremer 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b65" href="#b65">2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison to model predictions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A long tradition in evolutionary biology – particularly in paleontology – has been the use of null models of evolutionary change (e.g., Brownian motion or genetic drift) to infer the role (or not) of natural selection (review: Sheets and Mitchell 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b96" href="#b96">2001</a>). Specifically, natural selection is typically inferred when the rate or directionality of change exceeds the confidence bounds of a null model. A limitation of this approach is its low inferential power even when strong external evidence supports the role of selection (Bell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">2006</a>). More recently, increased inferential power has come from formally comparing alternative models with and without natural selection (e.g., Clegg et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">2008</a>; Hunt et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">2008</a>). This null model approach is not very common in the context of contemporary climate change, although Crozier et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2011</a>) might be considered in this class.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Q
   <sub>ST</sub>–F
   <sub>ST</sub> comparisons
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This approach is also rooted in null model thinking. Specifically, theory predicts that selection will cause patterns of quantitative trait variation to differ from patterns of neutral marker variation (Lande 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" href="#b63">1992</a>; McKay and Latta 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b73" href="#b73">2002</a>; Leinonen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b67" href="#b67">2008</a>; Whitlock 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b111" href="#b111">2008</a>). In particular, divergent selection is often inferred when the among-population proportion of genetically based trait variance (Q
   <sub>ST</sub>) exceeds the among-population proportion of neutral marker divergence (F
   <sub>ST</sub>). This approach has a number of limitations. Of particular concern, the accurate estimation of Q
   <sub>ST</sub> requires a common-garden study (e.g., Leinonen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b67" href="#b67">2008</a>), which is difficult to implement in an allochronic context. Also in play is the previously noted problem that genotype-by-environment interactions can make inferences misleading with respect to natural populations. A partial solution to this problem can come from using natural populations to estimate the phenotypic Q
   <sub>ST</sub> analog (P
   <sub>ST</sub>: Leinonen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b66" href="#b66">2006</a>), although interpretation remains difficult (Brommer 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">2011</a>). Many additional concerns attend Q
   <sub>ST</sub>–F
   <sub>ST</sub> comparisons (Hendry 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">2002</a>; Leinonen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b67" href="#b67">2008</a>; Edelaar et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">2011</a>), although some of these can be reduced through careful planning or by adopting improved approaches (e.g., Ovaskainen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b81" href="#b81">2011</a>; Karhunen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">2013</a>). To date, however, Q
   <sub>ST</sub>–F
   <sub>ST</sub> comparisons have not been much used in the context of contemporary climate change.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
