<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What is the specific selective force?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if the overall adaptive significance of a phenotypic trend has support from the above approaches, the specific environmental driver remains to be established (Wade and Kalisz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b109" href="#b109">1990</a>; MacColl 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b71" href="#b71">2011</a>). This remaining question is of particular concern because climate change is often correlated with other environmental changes that might influence phenotypic change, such as changing rates of exploitation by humans, increasing or decreasing pollution, habitat loss and degradation, and increasing impact from invasive species. Inferring that climate change, or a specific aspect of climate change (e.g., temperature, pH), is the causal force thus requires additional effort. Three basic routes to such inferences are possible: common sense, phenotype–environment correlations, and experimental selection/evolution.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Common sense</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The easiest, and certainly still the most common, approach for inferring a specific environmental driver is through existing knowledge and intuition. For example, if (1) organisms reproduce when particular resources become available in the spring, (2) climate change is causing those resources to become available earlier, and (3) the organisms are reproducing earlier, we might feel safe in assuming that climate change is the cause of the observed phenotypic change. Although intuition often might be correct, it is not inevitably or always simplistically so. For example, climate warming is generally assumed to advance the spring phenology of temperate organisms, whereas it actually retards the emergence of alpine ground squirrels (
   <span class="italic">Urocitellus columbianus</span>; Lane et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2012</a>). At the end of the day, any adaptive ‘story telling’ (
   <span class="italic">sensu</span> Gould and Lewontin 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">1979</a>) should be accompanied by formal hypothesis testing using the following methods.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenotype–environment correlations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another common inferential approach is to 
   <span class="italic">quantify</span> the association between trait change and specific aspects of climate change (e.g., Quinn and Adams 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" href="#b86">1996</a>; Crozier et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2011</a>). If a tight correlation is found, especially across multiple independent locations/populations, support for that environmental driver is enhanced. Ideally, multiple potential drivers would be simultaneously assessed so as to determine their independent and interactive effects. A difficulty in implementing this approach is that evolution, and sometimes plasticity, cannot perfectly track environmental change (Quinn and Adams 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" href="#b86">1996</a>; Both and Visser 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">2001</a>), and so the failure to find a tight trait–environment association does not necessarily mean that the environmental factor is unimportant. This problem can be partially circumvented by also adding a complementary space-for-time replacement (e.g., Phillimore et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" href="#b83">2010</a>). If, for instance, temperature is suspected to be the primary factor driving temporal changes in phenotype, similar associations might be expected across spatial temperature gradients. Of course, we return here to the above-mentioned concern that temporal and spatial drivers might not be the same (see also Fukami and Wardle 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">2010</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental selection/evolution</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental studies are often deemed necessary to conclusively isolate the role of a particular environmental factor in shaping a particular ecological or evolutionary response (Bender et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">1984</a>). The best manifestation in the context of climate change would be to experimentally manipulate a specific candidate driver in nature, such as through artificial warming of the environment experience by a natural population. With appropriate replication and controls, and following the confirmation of genetic or plastic change and its adaptive significance (as above), exceptionally strong evidence thus would be provided for causal effects. This approach is obviously difficult to apply in nature, and so most such studies instead use controlled laboratory or mesocosm settings (e.g., Van Doorslaer et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b108" href="#b108">2007</a>). Although such studies are extremely informative, their relevance to nature is sometimes uncertain. And, of course, experimental manipulations cannot conclusively confirm the specific driver of phenotypic/genetic changes in other (nonexperimental) populations – although ambiguity is lessened if responses are consistent across replicates/contexts and are very similar to those in natural populations.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
