<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive evolution occurs when the genetic constitution of a population changes as a consequence of natural selection. Thus, to demonstrate that adaptation has occurred, evidence is needed for genetic change and that natural selection has been the causal force. Given that the genetic underpinnings of most traits are still not known (Ellegren and Sheldon 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">2008</a>; Mackay et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b72" href="#b72">2009</a>; Anderson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">2013</a>) and that the accurate measurement of natural selection is difficult (Kingsolver et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">2001</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">2012</a>; Kruuk et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b58" href="#b58">2003</a>; Hersch and Phillips 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">2004</a>; Morrissey and Hadfield 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b76" href="#b76">2012</a>), obtaining hard evidence to conclusively demonstrate adaptive evolution in the wild represents a major and ongoing challenge. Given these logistical difficulties, and following from the traditional view that natural selection is a powerful force (Endler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">1986</a>), a frequent default has been to infer adaptive evolution based simply on evidence that mean phenotypes have changed in ways that intuition suggests are adaptive. This is not enough.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One major reason the above intuition-based inferences are not sufficient is that phenotypic change can be the result of either genetic change or phenotypic plasticity, the latter occurring when individuals of a given genotype adjust their phenotype according to the conditions they experience (West-Eberhard 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b110" href="#b110">2003</a>). Indeed, a number of phenotypic differences originally thought to be genetically based were subsequently attributed to phenotypic plasticity (e.g., James 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">1983</a>; Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">2008</a>; Teplitsky et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b104" href="#b104">2008</a>). In the wake of such demonstrations phenotypic plasticity is increasingly adopted as a parsimonious model that is to be rejected only if direct evidence is obtained for genetic change: That is, plasticity is treated as a null model. The reality, however, is that inferences regarding phenotypic plasticity also should be supported by a specific set of evidentiary criteria (see below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another major reason why the above intuition can fail is that phenotypic changes may or may not be adaptive. On the one hand, maladaptive or nonadaptive genetic changes can occur owing to genetic drift or gene flow, rather than natural selection. On the other hand, maladaptive or nonadaptive plastic changes might occur as a result of stress, nutrient limitation, and a host of other reasons (Gotthard and Nylin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">1995</a>; Grether 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">2005</a>). In reality, then, genetic versus plastic changes and adaptive versus nonadaptive changes should be treated as alternative models to be compared based on the weight of evidence. In the present paper, we consider these issues in the context of contemporary global (climate) change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The possibility of evolution in response to climate change started to gain attention in the late 1980s and early 1990s (e.g., Holt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">1990</a>; Lynch and Lande 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b69" href="#b69">1993</a>; Bürger and Lynch 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">1995</a>). Interest has since accelerated rapidly – in the last two decades more than 30 review and perspective articles have emerged on the topic (Merilä 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" href="#b74">2012</a>), and 12 new reviews are published in this issue. At the same time, concerns have been voiced about the quality of inference: In particular, few studies have convincingly demonstrated that observed phenotypic shifts have a genetic basis (Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">2008</a>; Merilä 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" href="#b74">2012</a>). Likewise, despite the promise and enthusiasm associated with using molecular genetic and genomic approaches to detect climate-driven evolution (Hoffmann and Daborn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">2007</a>; Reusch and Wood 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b90" href="#b90">2008</a>), few studies have been able to realize it (but see: Umina et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b106" href="#b106">2005</a>; Balanyá et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" href="#b3">2006</a>) and fewer still have been able to link genetic changes to phenotypes and to confirm that the changes are adaptive.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the scarcity of evidence for genetic change, increasing support has emerged for its main alternative. That is, many studies have now reported a role for plasticity in shaping phenotypic responses to contemporary disturbances such as climate change (e.g., Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">2008</a>; Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">2008</a>; Hendry et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">2008</a>; Teplitsky et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b104" href="#b104">2008</a>). Partly for this reason, it has become increasingly common for authors to assume a role for plasticity unless direct evidence for genetic change has been obtained: that is, the null model approach mentioned above. In most cases, however, the lack of genetic evidence stems from the lack of actual tests for genetic change rather than concrete evidence that no genetic change has occurred. In such instances, all that can be stated with certainty is that the relative contributions of genetic change and plasticity are unknown. In addition, the general point made above that plastic responses might or might not be adaptive also applies to climate change. For instance, Teplitsky et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b104" href="#b104">2008</a>) provided evidence that climate-driven plastic decreases in the body size of red-billed gulls (
  <span class="italic">Larus novaehollandiae;</span> Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>) were likely the result of environmental stress, rather than adaptive responses.
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Examples of model species utilized in research on genetic underpinnings of climate change responses. (A) The great tit (
    <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), (B) red-billed gull (
    <span class="italic">Larus novaehollandiae</span>), (C) red squirrel (
    <span class="italic">Tamiasciurus hudsonicus</span>), (D) pink salmon (
    <span class="italic">Oncorhynchus gorbuscha</span>), (E) grove snail (
    <span class="italic">Cepaea nemoralis</span>) and (F) field mustard (
    <span class="italic">Brassica rapa</span>). Photograph credit: (A): S. Caro, (B): J. Merilä, (C): C. Kolacz, (D): A. P. Hendry, (E): M. Ozgo, (F): S. Franks.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0007-0001-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beyond this ambiguity about genetic versus plastic changes and adaptive versus nonadaptive changes, another inferential difficulty comes in determining the specific environmental factor causing a particular phenotypic/genetic change (Endler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">1986</a>; Wade and Kalisz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b109" href="#b109">1990</a>; MacColl 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b71" href="#b71">2011</a>). A well-known example of this problem is the difficulty in confidently ascribing phenotypic trends in fish stocks to the effects of fishing versus other environmental changes (e.g., Kuparinen and Merilä 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">2008</a>). In the context of climate change, increasing temperatures are often coincident with many other environmental changes that shape phenotypic responses, whether genetic or plastic. Thus, the demonstration that a phenotypic change is genetic or plastic and adaptive or not does not necessarily provide confirmation that climate change, or more specifically climate warming, is the specific cause.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present paper, we outline approaches that have been used for making the above inferences in relation to climate change. Our major goal in doing so is to consider in detail what the various methods can and cannot tell us about proximate and ultimate causes. One of our key points is that evolution and plasticity (whether adaptive or not) should be treated as alternative models to be weighed against each other in light of data. That is, one alternative should not be considered a ‘null’ model to be assumed unless it can be rejected in favor of another.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After drafting the present paper, we provided it to experts who were well positioned to evaluate the strength of evidence for adaptive evolutionary responses to climate change in particular taxa (
  <span class="italic">viz</span>. fish, birds, mammals, amphibians and reptiles, marine animals and plants, terrestrial invertebrates, freshwater invertebrates, terrestrial plants, and marine phytoplankton) or in the context of particular topics (Bergmann's rule, theoretical models). The results of these assessments form the rest of this special issue (Boutin and Lane 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2014</a>; Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">2014</a>; Collins et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b119" href="#b119">2014</a>; Crozier and Hutchings 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">2014</a>; Franks et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">2014</a>; Kopp and Matuszewskib 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">2014</a>; Reusch 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b89" href="#b89">2014</a>; Schilthuizen and Kellermann 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b95" href="#b95">2014</a>; Stoks et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b100" href="#b100">2014</a>; Teplitsky and Millien 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b103" href="#b103">2014</a>; Urban et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b107" href="#b107">2014</a>; Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>). We therefore close with a brief synopsis of those contributions. We hope that the end result is a balanced account of what is currently known about nature of phenotypic responses to climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
