<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This survey demonstrates that African American physicians in the National Medical Association understand that climate change is happening; 97% hold this view. This stands in contrast to public understanding that climate is happening–which in Spring 2014 was 64% [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-11-12473">7</a>] but is similar to the 96% rate found among physician members of the American Academy for the Advancement of Science (most of whom were academic research scientists) in 2008 [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-11-12473">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several possible interpretations of this finding should be considered. As physicians, trained in the biomedical sciences working in disciplines shaped by scientific evidence, participants might have a greater appreciation for the significance of a global consensus on the part of climate scientists and national academies of science about the reality of climate change. The evidence for this is limited given that only 29% of respondents thought the consensus of climate scientists was over 80%, when, in fact, it is 97% or greater [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-11-12473">12</a>]. Since the initial group of participants heard the preliminary results of the survey at the March Colloquium, this could have influenced the second group of participants. While it is impossible to know for sure that this did not happen, it is unlikely that these busy physicians shared influential information with other members. In addition, this seems unlikely to alter their medical judgment about the health problems of their own patients.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another possible explanation is that people who experience the effects of climate change are more likely to be convinced that it is happening [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-11-12473">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-11-12473">14</a>]. The large majority of survey participants (88%) responded that outside their clinical work, they had personally experienced some degree of climate change; this stands in stark contrast to the rate at which members of the American general public feel that they have personally experienced climate change—35% in 2014 [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-11-12473">7</a>]. African American physicians may be more attuned to having personally experienced climate change because they may practice in locations where change has been more apparent, or because they take care of people who are more vulnerable to climate change’s health effects. Sixty-nine percent of respondents had a primary work setting within an urban area where urban heat island effects, poor air quality, and the synergy between the two may be factors that affected patient experience and thus practitioner opinion. In addition, NMA members care for disproportionate numbers of Medicaid and Medicare recipients and other vulnerable people with lower incomes, and higher rates of chronic diseases.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the participation rate in the survey was high for a physician survey (30%), one needs to show caution in generalizing the results. We surveyed only NMA members; the majority of African American physicians in the U.S. are not NMA members.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conversely, there are reasons to suggest that our findings are at least generally indicative of the experiences and views of African American physicians in the U.S. Our respondents work in 33 different states of various sizes, indicated a range of political leanings, and included a strong mix of clinical specialists (over 40%) as well as primary care practitioners (53%). The health effects identified overlap appreciably with the responses to the open-ended question; and both reflect the health issues described in the U.S. National Climate Assessment, specifically injuries from extreme weather, air pollution-related increases in the severity of illness for lung and cardiovascular disease; heat-related effects; and increased allergic sensitization and symptoms [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-11-12473">1</a>]. Lastly, the practice locations of respondents are consistent with their observations: 69% of respondents practice in urban areas where heat plus air pollution present a double threat to many vulnerable people (heat is a threat in the most rural areas also). Longer ragweed pollen seasons found in much of the country (urban, suburban, and rural) further exacerbate the problem. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents expressed strong support for policy solutions at the national level to reduce the impact of climate change and protect and prepare the population. Moreover, they feel strongly that physicians and their associations should assume a leading role in advocating for sustainability as well as measures that address the health effects of climate change. In support of these approaches, 82% would like policy statements from their professional associations. Since many physicians belong to more than one professional association, this opinion may be a key to empowering physician communities to become involved. The respondents demonstrated a strong sense of self-efficacy in that they believe that their own actions—in their professional lives and personal lives—can make a difference. Research supports the key role of self-efficacy as a necessary condition for climate change action [
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-11-12473" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-11-12473">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondent’s assessment of their own knowledge base also provides direction for future work. Only one quarter of survey respondents feel very or moderately knowledgeable about the association between climate and health impacts, while almost half feel only modestly knowledgeable. If physicians are going to follow through on the actions favored by large majorities, including having physicians educate their patients and the public about the connections between climate change and health, then continuing education about the relationship between climate and health is a pressing need. Overwhelmingly, respondents identified continuing medical education, undergraduate medical education, and patient education materials as needs.</p>
</sec>
