<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies surveying the Canadian general population identified substantial differences in opinion at the regional level: respondents within provinces contributing the most to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions (Alberta and Saskatchewan) believed the least that humans are the cause of climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Although we expected a similar variation in our survey on the forest sector, we did not find such a marked trend, and the views on the existence of climate change and its causes were consistently similar across the studied provinces (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0197689.s003" class="xref">S3 File</xref>). In contrast, the province of origin was the best predictor of perceptions about the impacts of climate change on forests and the risk that this currently poses. Although the underlying causes of these differences between provinces can be varied and complex, we suggest that this is likely due to the direct exposure to climate change related extreme disturbance events [
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] rather than different provincial legislation or culture. Previous studies have found that most forest sector employees have experienced the effects of climate change mainly through disturbances and extreme events [
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. For example, an unprecedented outbreak of the mountain pine beetle in the 1990s and 2000s affected over 18.1 million hectares in British Columbia and Alberta, and has been directly linked to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Fire activity in the western boreal forests has also increased in recent years, and and some recent catastrophic wildfires have also been linked to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0197689.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. These phenomena have strongly impacted the forest sector in these provinces and have undoubtedly contributed to an increased perception of the associated risks. However, it is not possible to state unequivocally the causes behind these geographical patterns.
</p>
