<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is projected to alter the distribution of vector borne diseases and malaria is no exception. Children under five years of age and pregnant women continue to be at risk. One of the key millennium development goals is to halve, halt, and reverse the scourge of malaria by 2015. The disease has not yet been halved, although a significant reduction in malaria incidences has been recorded [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">1</a>]. These little gains achieved to date are under threat from climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Malaria is sensitive to climate change in the sense that the vector that spreads malaria and the parasite that causes the disease are sensitive to climate variables especially rainfall and temperature. Research on the impact of climate change on the dynamics of malaria is still ongoing [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">2</a>–
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">6</a>]. However, most studies tend to consider the effect of temperature alone on the dynamics of malaria, neglecting the impact of incorporating rainfall in the mathematical models of malaria transmission. Understanding the role of temperature and rainfall in malaria transmission is of particular importance in light of climate change as changes can alter vector development rates, shift vector geographical distribution, and alter transmission dynamics. Climate change is widely expected to significantly affect the global spread, intensity, and distribution of malaria. The question is, how is climate change going to affect the gains made thus far in trying to reduce the burden of malaria? That is a question which was once answered by Tanser et al. [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">7</a>] using spatial models and which we also seek to answer using a mathematical model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study seeks to build a mathematical model in conjunction with the use of Geographical Information Systems (GIS) that will enable prediction and mapping of the current and potential future distribution of malaria in Africa as a result of climate change. The study will highlight how combining regional climate models with mathematical models of malaria transmission provides valuable tools for better understanding of future disease scenarios as climatic conditions change. We modify our previous work [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">4</a>] to incorporate rainfall into the model. We focus on the construction of a realistic, climate-based malaria transmission model that captures the combined effects of both rainfall and temperature on malaria infection dynamics. This approach permits us to gain insight into the effect of climate change on malaria transmission. However, to reduce the complexity of the model genetic variation in vector competences is not explored in the same way as rainfall is not partitioned into runoff and infiltration in this paper.
 </p>
</sec>
