<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A model incorporating rainfall and temperature is analysed regarding malaria transmission. Results from the model suggest that the optimum temperature window for peak falciparum malaria transmission is 30–32°C. This is in agreement with other studies [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">4</a>, 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">5</a>]. Furthermore, results from model analysis suggest that daily rainfall in the range of 15–17 mm is ideal for the spread of malaria. Perhaps the most interesting but unexpected result is that by 2040 malaria is projected to die out on the southern fringe of the disease in Africa. The fact that the same result was detected using projections from two different GCM models makes this a key result. A drying trend is the likely driving force for this change [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">18</a>]. This finding has implications for malaria elimination in some regions of Africa. In other words, the result offers hope that the international goal of shrinking the malaria map may be achieved in southern Africa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results of this study suggest that due to climate change endemic malaria will become an increasing problem in the African highlands; this seems to be in agreement with other studies [
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">5</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">7</a>, 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">19</a>–
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">22</a>]. A warming trend is the likely factor driving the projected increase in malaria endemicity in the highlands, though socioeconomic factors such as land use change and drug resistance can also be attributed to increases in malaria incidences in highlands too.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model has the following limitations: (i) it did not consider the role of human migration neither did it consider other climate variables in particular relative humidity as the tropical anopheline mosquitoes prefer humidities above 60% [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">23</a>]; (ii) it did not consider the role of socioeconomic factors in malaria transmission dynamics but it would be interesting to incorporate these factors to ascertain whether climate change in combination with these factors will amplify malaria transmission in the highlands. Despite these limitations, the model is reasonable enough to be able to give a realistic picture of malaria in the African continent. Thus, results from the study will be useful at various levels of decision making, for example, in setting up an early warning and sustainable strategies for climate change and adaptation for malaria vectors control programmes in Africa. These results can be generalized to other tropical regions outside Africa.
 </p>
</sec>
