<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P6" class="p">The impact of climate change on PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> mortality is estimated to result in 55,600 (−34,300 to 164,000) deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> in 2030 and 215,000 (−76,100 to 595,000) deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> in 2100 (
 <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figures 1b</xref> and 
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2b</xref>). Mean estimates of PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> mortality increase in 2100 in all regions except Africa (−25,200 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 3b</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 3, Supplementary Figure 2b</xref>). The greatest increases in mortality in 2100 occur in India (80,200 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, 40 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> per million people), Middle East (50,400 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, 45 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> per million people) and East Asia (47,200 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, 43 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> per million people), although the Former Soviet Union shows greater mortality per million people in 2100 (11,800 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, 57 deaths yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> per million people). Similar to ozone mortality, there are substantial spatial differences within each region, including both increases and decreases in mortality. For PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>, a large decrease in mortality is projected in RCP8.5 relative to 2000 (when accounting for changes in both emissions and climate)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>, but climate change alone increases mortality, partially counteracting the decrease associated with declining emissions in RCP8.5. Without climate change, the decrease in PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>-related mortality would be roughly 16% greater in 2100 relative to 2000. Propagating uncertainty in RR to the mortality estimates leads to coefficients of variation (CVs) of 8–31% (2030) and 11–46% (2100) for the different models, but the spread of model results increases overall CVs to 123% in 2030 and 106% in 2100. In both years, one model (GISS-E2-R) yields a decrease in global mortality from climate change while the other three (2030) or four (2100) show an increase. Uncertainty in modeled PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> concentrations in 2000 makes a similar contribution to the overall uncertainty (50% in 2030 and 52% in 2100) compared with uncertainty in modeled PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> concentrations in future years (50% in 2030, 48% in 2100). Uncertainty in RR makes a negligible contribution in both periods (&lt;1%), as the multi-model mean is small and different models disagree on the sign of the influence. Considering present-day population and baseline mortality rates (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>), we estimate 23% and 33% lower mortality in 2030 and 2100, respectively, mostly associated with the increase in projected baseline mortality rates through 2100.
</p>
