<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P10" class="p">The spread of results among models highlights the uncertainty in the effect of climate change on air quality. Further improvements in chemistry climate models are needed to better model the interaction and feedbacks between climate and air quality, including the sensitivity of biogenic emissions to climate change, the effects of meteorological changes on air quality (e.g., aerosol-cloud interactions, secondary aerosol formation, wet deposition, and gas-aerosol partitioning), and the impact of climate change on wildfires. Stratosphere-troposphere exchange of ozone is also important, as is the impact of land use changes on regional climate and air pollution. Our results are specific to climate change as projected under RCP8.5 and would differ for other scenarios. We estimate the effect of climate change as the difference between simulations with future climate and year 2000 climate, both with year 2000 emissions, although global emissions of PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> and its main precursors decrease under RCP8.5. Had we instead modelled future emissions with present vs. future climate, we would likely have attributed smaller changes in air pollution and mortality to climate change, given the projected emission reductions. Whereas the net effect of missing and uncertain processes does not clearly indicate an under- or overestimate for the effect of climate change on air quality, we likely underestimate the magnitude of the health impact by omitting mortality for people under 25, and morbidity effects. We also neglect possible synergistic effects of a warmer climate to modify air pollution-mortality relationships. Although a few studies have suggested stronger relationships between ozone
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup> and PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup> and health at higher temperatures, there is insufficient evidence to include those effects here.
</p>
