<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>We would like to thank NRCan, GLIMS, U.S. Geological Survey, CMEMS, the National Centers for Environmental Information, the Government of Canada, and the World Glacier Monitoring Service for access to datasets. We would also like to thank P. Whitehouse for processing the CMEMS data. We thank two anonymous reviewers for their insightful suggestions that improved the manuscript. 
  <span class="bold">Funding:</span> A.J.C. was supported by a Leverhulme Early Career Fellowship and the Department of Geography, Durham University. Additional funding was provided by the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, University of Ottawa, and Canada Foundation for Innovation. B.P.Y.N. and M.R.v.d.B. acknowledge funding from the Netherlands Earth System Science Centre (NESSSC) and the Polar Program of the Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research (NWO/NPP). 
  <span class="bold">Author contributions:</span> A.J.C. led the analysis, writing, and compilation of graphics and tables. L.C. contributed image data and expertise, and B.P.Y.N. and M.R.v.d.B. contributed atmospheric climate model data and analysis. C.R.S., M.J.B., M.J.S., and R.G.B. designed the study and contributed knowledge. All of the authors contributed to the writing of the manuscript. 
  <span class="bold">Competing interests:</span> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <span class="bold">Data and materials availability:</span> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors. Data are publically available from the Polar Data Catalogue (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.polardata.ca/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.polardata.ca/</span>).
 </p>
</div>
