<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion|conclusions" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis indicates a rapid increase in the rate of glacier retreat in the CAA since the start of the 21st century. The evidence does not support ocean temperatures as the driver of the regional trends in glacier retreat along the western side of either Baffin Bay or Nares Strait, despite ocean forcing being recognized as a key driver of glacier frontal retreat on the eastern side of Baffin Bay in west Greenland. Both ocean temperature measurements and reanalysis data show predominantly cold waters, both on a broad regional scale (up to 100 km from the coast) and closer to glacier fronts (where data are available within 20 and 5 km). In contrast to west Greenland, CAA glaciers are relatively thin at their grounding lines (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>) and tend to occupy shallower water. They are, therefore, less vulnerable to deep ocean temperature changes, and the mean ocean temperatures at shallower depths have been too low to have driven the observed region-wide patterns of retreat (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results from the 1-km downscaled RACMO2.3, however, demonstrate a significant correlation between marine-terminating glacier front retreat rates and SMB components (mean ablation rate, ablation area ratio, and mean runoff) over the period 1958–2015. The relationship is quantitatively robust and occurs across the region. Moreover, temporal variations in retreat rates and surface runoff rates are largely synchronous, suggesting that there is a rapid response of CAA marine-terminating glacier fronts to near-surface atmospheric warming. External forcings on the fluctuations of marine terminating glaciers have been noted in varying degrees in other locations on Earth, but the regional dominance of atmospheric temperatures in driving marine-terminating glacier retreat has not been observed elsewhere.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Glacier frontal retreat rates have followed a similar trend to the rates of surface mass loss in the CAA, which have accelerated since ~2000 (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). We suggest that the mechanisms by which increased surface air temperatures drive rapid retreat of marine-terminating glaciers in this region are likely to be much the same as those that drive retreat of the land-terminating glaciers. That is, increased melt and subsequent meltwater runoff reduces mass delivery to glacier termini through reductions in glacier flow, with the consequence that glaciers thin and retreat in their ablation areas (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). Other mechanisms observed on marine-terminating glaciers in Greenland, such as increased surface melt amplifying the delivery of ocean heat to the terminus via the creation of an upwelling plume at the grounding line (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>), are less likely to be a primary mechanism behind regional glacier retreat in the CAA. This is because most of CAA glaciers terminate in shallow water, making them less vulnerable to intrusion of warmer deep water. However, this mechanism could be important on the local scale for the few CAA glaciers that terminate in deep water, although further research is required to examine this.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is now widely acknowledged that ocean temperature increase has been the dominant driver of glacier retreat in other polar regions in recent years, particularly along the western Antarctic Peninsula, around the West Antarctic Ice Sheet, and in western Greenland. In contrast, we show that, in the CAA, the substantial rise in atmospheric temperature in the 21st century has outweighed any regional impact of changing ocean temperature on marine-terminating glacier frontal behavior. It follows that ocean temperature cannot be assumed to be the primary driver of marine-terminating glacier retreat in all polar regions and that studies of local processes are needed to understand the impacts of climate change on glacier behavior.</p>
</sec>
