<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the northern high latitudes, one of the regions thought to be highly vulnerable to environmental change is the Canadian Arctic Archipelago (CAA), which contains the greatest area of global land ice outside the ice sheets in Greenland and Antarctica (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). With a glaciated area of ~146,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, the CAA has the potential to contribute 199 ± 30 mm to global mean sea level rise (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Rates of ice mass loss from the CAA have increased sharply during the 21st century (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>), from the Queen Elizabeth Islands (QEI) in the north [31 ± 8 gigatons (Gt) year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2004–2006, increasing to 92 ± 12 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2007–2009] (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) to Baffin and Bylot Islands (BBI) further south (from 11.1 ± 3.4 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in 1963–2006 to 23.8 ± 6.12 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2003–2011) (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). Although total ice mass loss is known, changes in individual glaciers have not been analyzed regionally.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is increasing evidence in both polar regions that rates of frontal ablation of ice flowing into the ocean are strongly controlled by subsurface ocean temperatures (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>). Unprecedented warming of the Arctic Ocean and surrounding water bodies (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>) therefore makes pan-Arctic marine-terminating glaciers vulnerable to rapid retreat (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>). Oceanic forcing has already been recognized as a key control on the fluctuations of outlet glaciers in western Greenland (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>), where rates of submarine melting are up to two orders of magnitude greater than surface melt rates (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>). Warming of subpolar North Atlantic water entering Baffin Bay is considered to be triggering an increase in the rate of submarine melting of Greenland’s outlet glaciers (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>). However, on the Canadian side of Baffin Bay, the role of oceanic forcing on marine-terminating glaciers has not been directly investigated and is largely unknown, although it has been hypothesized that ocean temperatures might be influencing glacier retreat (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With over 300 marine-terminating glaciers in the CAA, dynamic feedbacks associated with glacier frontal changes have clear potential to influence decadal-scale ice losses from the region. Recent studies have shown that increasing ice discharge to the ocean has contributed to recent mass loss from the CAA in some locations (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). For example, ~62% of current ice discharge (i.e., via calving) from the QEI is channeled through Trinity and Wykeham glaciers, southeast Ellesmere Island, where flow speed has markedly accelerated over the past 10 to 15 years (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). In this area, at least half of the observed thinning rate at the glacier termini has been attributed to changes in ice dynamics rather than to surface mass balance (SMB) changes (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). Changes taking place at the terminus of marine-terminating glaciers form a crucial component of mass balance (
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>) and have a major influence on coastal ecosystems, and yet, long-term regional patterns and trends in the frontal changes of glaciers in the CAA have never been examined. Here, we present a comprehensive analysis of decadal changes in the frontal positions of 300 marine-terminating glaciers in the region. We analyze ocean temperature measurements, together with downscaled 1-km-resolution regional climate model output, to evaluate the relative importance of oceanographic and atmospheric influences on the observed changes in glacier frontal positions since the late 1950s.
 </p>
</sec>
