<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RACMO2.3 downscaled to 1-km data source</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A detailed reconstruction of SMB between 1958 and 2015 is available from the RACMO2.3 statistically downscaled to 1 km. The model is a downscaled version of the 11-km RACMO2.3, corrected for biases in elevation and bare ice albedo, and provides regional SMB data at a scale suitable for measuring mean values within individual glacier basins in the CAA. The SMB output is in millimeter w.e. year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The methods used in producing the model, along with accuracy assessments based on in situ mass balance measurements, are reported in Noël 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). These are summarized as follows. The SMB values from both the 11- and 1-km versions of RACMO2.3 were assessed against 4356 stake measurements within the CAA. Correcting for elevation and bare ice albedo bias during the downscaling process significantly improved the accuracy. Assessment with observational data showed that, relative to the 11-km model, the 1-km downscaled version of RACMO2.3 has a much improved mean SMB bias (40 mm w.e.), RMSE (380 mm w.e.), and 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> (0.74). The product uncertainty for SMB was estimated at 11.0 and 4.5 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for Northern CAA (NCAA = QEI) and Southern CAA (SCAA = BBI), respectively. To obtain these estimates, the 4356 in situ SMB measurements from 1961 to 2016, e.g., from Sverdrup Glacier on Devon Island (yellow dots in fig. S5), were binned in 250 mm w.e. intervals for which the mean bias was estimated (i.e., modeled minus measured SMB), which was then applied to total ablation and accumulation areas across the region (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). The RACMO2.3 product was further evaluated using independently derived mass changes from ICESat and CryoSat-2 altimetry measurements. The downscaled dataset shows good agreement with the altimetry records, and both winter accumulation and summer ablation are accurately resolved. In addition, the SMB product falls well within ICESat/CryoSat-2 measurement uncertainty. Ice mass loss estimates from the downscaled SMB product are similar to estimates from other mass loss studies (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>). Mass loss in 2004–2009 was estimated at 33.8 ± 11.5 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for the NCAA and 24 ± 4.5 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for the SCAA (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). For comparison, a study by Gardner 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) estimated mass loss from GRACE (Gravity Recovery and Climate Experiment) to be 39 ± 9 and 24 ± 7 Gt year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for NCAA and SCAA, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
