<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
  <p>Supplementary material for this article is available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/3/eaau8507/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/3/eaau8507/DC1</span>
  </p>
  <p>Fig. S1. Sample glaciers on southeast Devon Island, illustrating the database compilation and analysis methods.</p>
  <p>Fig. S2. Mean relative change per year (as the percentage of glacier length in ~2000), separated by latitudinal degrees.</p>
  <p>Fig. S3. Ocean temperature in situ measurement locations and marine-terminating glacier buffer limits.</p>
  <p>Fig. S4. Mean ocean temperatures from WOD13 measurements available within glacier front buffer regions.</p>
  <p>Fig. S5. Modeled climate data accuracy assessment on Sverdrup Glacier, on north Devon Island (75.5°N, 83°W).</p>
  <p>Fig. S6. Change in surface meltwater runoff over time (mm w.e. a
   <span class="sup">−1</span>).
  </p>
  <p>Fig. S7. Mean runoff calculated from RACMO2.3 statistically downscaled to 1 km resolution for glaciers, ice caps and ice fields in the CAA.</p>
  <p>Fig. S8. Temperature trends from six weather stations in the CAA.</p>
  <p>Table S1. Image sources from which CAA glacier frontal positions were mapped.</p>
  <p>Table S2. Mean absolute and relative length change rates in each time period, for glaciers in the CAA.</p>
  <p>Table S3. Glacier counts for overall (1958–2015) glacier length change bins (see 
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Figs. 4</a> and 
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">6</a>).
  </p>
  <p>Table S4. Spearman’s rank (
   <span class="italic">r</span>
   <sub>s</sub>) correlations between mean relative change rates and mean ocean temperature at each depth.
  </p>
  <p>Table S5. Ocean temperature measurements descriptive statistics.</p>
  <p>Table S6. Spearman’s rank (
   <span class="italic">r</span>
   <sub>s</sub>) correlations between overall (1958–2015) glacier front change rates (as the percentage of basin length) and mean SMB components.
  </p>
  <p>Table S7. Mean glacier runoff (mm w.e. a
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) and mean frontal change rates (% a
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) for glaciers separated by latitudinal degrees and time periods for BBI and QEI.
  </p>
  <p>Data file S1. Marine terminating glaciers (&gt;2 km2 in size) on Baffin and Bylot Islands (BBI): data used in statistical analysis.</p>
  <p>Data file S2. Marine terminating glaciers (&gt;2 km2 in size) on the Queen Elizabeth Islands (QEI): data used in statistical analysis.</p>
 </div>
</div>
