<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">With the current parameterisations in PAGE-ICE, adding the significant corrections from the nonlinear Arctic feedbacks to the base estimates of the mean total economic effect of climate change makes the 1.5 °C target ($638 trillion) marginally more economically attractive than the 2 °C target ($646 trillion). While the total economic effects of the 1.5 °C and 2 °C scenarios are statistically equivalent (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>), we have several reasons to believe it would be prudent to aim for emissions towards the bottom end of the range covered by these scenarios. First, the PAGE-ICE model, in common with other aggregate IAMs, does not explicitly model other known climatic tipping elements such as Amazon rainforest, boreal forest, coral reefs and El Niño–Southern Oscillation (ENSO), as well as ocean acidification and climate-induced large-scale migration and conflict
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup> (we cannot reject the null hypothesis that the total economic effects of climate change are the same for these scenarios either at the 5% or at the 10% significance level). Some of these effects are already included implicitly in the highly uncertain non-economic and discontinuity impact sectors in PAGE-ICE, contributing to the long upper tails in the distributions of the total economic effect of climate change in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5a</xref>; even with the current parameterisations, the upper tails in the distributions are at their lowest for the 1.5 °C scenario. It is possible that with an explicit modelling of the other climatic and societal tipping elements, as well as with comprehensive representation of the impacts of rising temperatures and increasing extreme weather events on economic growth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>, both the economic effect of climate change with legacy Arctic feedbacks, and the additional impacts due to the nonlinear PCF and SAF, would be higher compared to those reported here. The associated global risks are minimised at lower emissions. Second, it is possible that recent reduction trends in the costs of mitigation technologies such as solar power
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>, which are captured by PAGE-ICE, could accelerate further if appropriate policy instruments such as carbon prices are implemented globally. Third, PAGE-ICE does not account for possible co-benefits of deep mitigation as part of a wider green growth transition in economy
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>
 </sup>. All these factors advocate for pursuing the target well below 2 °C as the way of avoiding substantial ecological and socio-economic losses from climate change (see Supplementary 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">Discussion</xref> for further details)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
