<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Water column measurements of PP in Lake Superior, although limited, vary in magnitude and display no steady increase (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref> and others therein) in contrast to what we present here. We posit that this discrepancy stems from the fact that traditional water column measurements have been few and relatively infrequent
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>, whereas the sedimentary record is an integrated signal of the entire year—capturing total annual patterns in PP. Traditionally, water column measurements are taken once in the spring and once in the summer at one or two locations, but not every year. No measurements of PP have been taken during ice-covered months, which omits a potentially substantial contribution to total annual PP (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref> and others therein) when using traditional measurements alone. That said, the direct measurements of PP in the ice-free season on Lake Superior display little or no seasonal variation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>. At any point in time primary productivity rates may remain constant but if the growing season becomes longer, net PP and subsequent export to the sediments can increase. Owing to this fact and others discussed above, we interpret the observed increases in sedimentary TOC and δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C
 <sub class="sub">org</sub> values as increases in export production (that is, an increase in the amount of OM produced by PP that is not recycled) due to the increasing length of the growing season (that is, longer ice-free and stratified periods associated with increasing surface water temperatures
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>). Indeed, a recent modelling study
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref> shows increasing total annual gross primary productivity with increasing temperature and decreasing ice-cover (simulation period 1985–2008) in Lake Superior.
</p>
