<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, we simultaneously examined cross‐environment genetic correlations of ecologically important traits of male sticklebacks exposed to different temperatures and their transcriptional responses during warm acclimation to explore the genomic basis of phenotypic plasticity. Male sticklebacks that developed under warm winter conditions were smaller in size and invested less in nuptial coloration at the beginning of the reproductive phase and had lower survival compared to control individuals (see also Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Our quantitative genetic results demonstrated the presence of significant genetic variation and plasticity across different thermal environments in body size and nuptial colouration of male sticklebacks. Genetic correlations between environments showed no evidence of G × E (i.e., no genetic variation in plasticity), suggesting that different genotypes showed similar plasticity patterns for size and nuptial colour in this population. It is interesting to note that a previous study of marine sticklebacks in a more northern population (Sylt‐Rømø Bight, Germany) showed a significant G × E for size of offspring from parents acclimated to different temperatures, suggesting that reaction norms had the potential to evolve (Shama et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The nonvariable plasticity pattern observed in our study population may be adaptive if these responses allowed the sticklebacks to avoid more catastrophic consequences of the temperature change, for example by shifting their investment from reproduction towards self‐maintenance in a warmer environment. In this low‐latitude population living close to the species’ thermal limit, this plasticity pattern may have evolved under strong natural selection, which probably eroded genetic variation in thermal reaction norms (Pigliucci, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). Our transcriptome results indicate that the expression of genes related to metabolism, cellular homoeostasis and regulatory signalling may underlie these changes in life‐history traits.
</p>
