<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recent work that makes use of 
 <italic class="italic">participatory</italic> geographic information systems (PGIS), 
 <italic class="italic">critical</italic> GIS (Harvey et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2005</xref>), and 
 <italic class="italic">feminist</italic> GIS (Elwood 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2008</xref>) may offer potentially fruitful areas of exploration for this type of integration. These are a result of increased concern in the 1990s over unequal power relations and access, and privileging of certain masculine epistemologies within spatial information and geographic information systems that can overshadow more marginalized or less powerful perspectives (Aitken and Michel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">1995</xref>). Examples of such work can be found within literature on planning and governance (McCall 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2003</xref>) and for mapping the social values of local people with regards to natural resources (Tyrväinen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">2007</xref>; Bernard et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2011</xref>; Villamor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">2014</xref>). Kwan (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2002a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">b</xref>) advanced this work with respect to gender and feminist studies by conceptualizing how 
 <italic class="italic">critical</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">participatory</italic> GIS could be merged with feminist epistemologies to better integrate quantitative and qualitative data within spatial visualizations, as well as for bringing more comprehensive perspectives to issues of political and social change. Since then, 
 <italic class="italic">feminist</italic> GIS has emerged as a dynamic research line (Sui and DeLyser 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">2012</xref>). This line is inclusive of works such as those focused on impacts of GIS in women’s lives (McLafferty 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">2005</xref>) and gender and agriculture (Harman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2013</xref>). We see opportunities for advancing the scope of such integrated and spatially explicit methods that could encompass intersectional understandings within broader scale analyses of farmer vulnerability and of farmer understandings of agroecosystems. This type of work could build not only on so-called ‘relief maps’ that highlights both the traditional use of the word “relief” in mapping, but also the removal of anxiety or pain and which can be used to explore spatial mapping applications of intersectionality (See Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> for an example from Rodó-de-Zárate 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">2014</xref>). These maps have three dimensions, the social (power) dimension, the geographical dimension, and the psychological dimension and serve to illustrate how space, power, and privilege/oppression are connected. 
</p>
