<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Co-infection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data from this study show that co-infections of malaria parasites are common, and our estimate in the great tit of 82% is consistent with the high frequencies of infection with multiple parasites in natural populations of other European bird species reported by Valkiūnas et al [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>]. Despite this high prevalence of co-infections, there does not appear to be a negative effect of co-infection on Plasmodium parasitaemia. This could be evidence for a more synergistic/benign type of interaction as summarized in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>], where a parasite induces prolonged infection or better establishment of another parasite. In addition, the possibility that the latter could influence Leucocytozoon parasitaemia, cannot be excluded, as this was beyond the scope of this investigation. Another important consideration is that, while this study only considers a co-occurrence of parasites, effects might vary with the number of parasites involved in co-infections.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large number of Leucocytozoon multiple infections observed, as opposed to multiple Plasmodium and Haemoproteus infections, might indicate Leucocytozoon parasites to be opportunistic parasites which can only establish themselves once a host’s immune system is weakened by prior infections thereby facilitating their establishment. This is in accordance with Cornet and Sorci [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B51" href="#B51">51</a>] who investigated the virulence consequences of parasite-induced immunosuppression on the risk of contracting opportunistic diseases in Gammarus pulex. Their study suggests that parasite exploitation of the host depends on the risk of contracting opportunistic diseases. Parasites should therefore limit their suppression of the host’s immune response if opportunistic infections will result in host death, but should not have to change their exploitation if the risk associated therewith is low. Accordingly, opportunistic Leucocytozoon lineages might not impose significant virulence costs to their hosts so as to allow for infection opportunity. As Leucocytozoon parasitaemia was not tested in this study, it is impossible to know if multiple Leucocytozoon infections result in higher parasitaemia than single infections and is a definite avenue for future investigation. If this is a case of facilitated, opportunistic infection, it would be evidence that not all lineages have equal infection potential.
 </p>
</sec>
