<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Parasite persistence</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The differences observed in the present study with regard to 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium, Haemoproteus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> lineage turn-over within hosts might be an indication of the differential strategies applied by different parasites when infecting their hosts, and might be explained by two levels of interaction: within-host competition between parasite lineages and host immune defense.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> parasites in the great tits might not be as effective at competing for resources as 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> parasites, and as a result cannot increase in frequency to such an extent as to gain enough of a competitive advantage over Plasmodium parasites to be able to persist within the host’s blood in the presence of 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>. This would not necessarily imply any transmission disadvantage for Leucocytozoon, which might choose to undertake larger-scale sexual reproduction, while Plasmodium infection consists of a globally larger number of asexual parasites. This possibility is illustrated by a study on rodent malaria (Plasmodium chabaudi) where Taylor et al [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>] compared infection dynamics of two lineages when inoculated individually into hosts or as co-infections with different initial inoculation frequencies. This was done to test whether competitive interactions between parasites occur in terms of infection of hosts and transmission to vectors. The authors concluded that malaria parasites might have evolved to maximize transmission from mixed-genotype infections, as asexual abundance did not correlate with transmission success in co-infections. This would therefore imply that different parasites involved in co-infections might differentially invest in either asexual or sexual reproduction, thereby ensuring transmission potential to the parasite occurring in lower numbers in the presence of competition. This may, however, hold true only for mixed infection with lineages belonging to the same genus and which share the same vectors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another explanation for the differences in turn-over among lineages could be the host’s immune system. Hosts are not passive victims of parasite infections, but actively launch a defensive campaign in the form of the immune system (for a full review on the mechanisms by which haemosporidian parasites evade the host’s immune response see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>]). The immune components and defense strategies applied during infection will vary amongst different host species, especially with regard to inflammatory response and adaptive immunity (for a review, see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B47" href="#B47">47</a>]). Little information is available on the evolutionary history of 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>. One can speculate that in this study system, the bird’s immune system might be more competent at fighting off Leucocytozoon infection than either 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> infections, indirectly inferring a competitive advantage to the latter and resulting in greater lineage and infection status turn-over.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It must also be noted that the possibility exists that hosts might be able to clear parasites of all genera equally efficiently, but repeat infection probability of 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> parasites (which occur in greater abundances than other parasites within the study population) is higher than for 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> parasites which show a greater lineage diversity, but at lower prevalences. This could result in an artefact illusion that 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> infection is more persistent. This possibility could be tested by serial sampling throughout the season.
 </p>
</sec>
