<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analyses were performed with the freeware R-Cran Project [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B39" href="#B39">39</a>]. A Fisher’s exact test was performed to determine differences in the frequency of lineage identity changes and infection status (infected vs. uninfected) changes between 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infections in recaptured individuals. Parasitaemia data were log transformed to achieve normality. A Welch two-sample t-test was used to assess the difference in parasitaemia between the two most prevalent 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> lineages, SW2 (
  <span class="italic">P. polare</span>) and SGS1 (
  <span class="italic">P. relictum</span>), as sample sizes for other recorded lineages were too low to be considered. Paired t-tests were performed to determine whether an individual’s parasitaemia changed between years of capture. Linear mixed models (lmer) in the lme4 package [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">40</a>] were performed on parasitaemia data to determine whether there is a relationship between concurrent infection with 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> parasitaemia. 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> parasitaemia was considered as response variable with bird identity and year of capture as random factors and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infection as fixed effect. To assess the virulence (i.e. affect on host body mass) of co-infection, linear mixed models were performed on a subset of data containing only occurrences of lineage SGS1 (n = 83) and considering 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infections as presence or absence values only. Body mass was considered as response variable with bird identity as random factor and sex and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infection as fixed effects. Likelihood ratio tests (LRT) were used to compare “goodness of fit” between models containing and excluding the fixed effect of interest. Probability values of 
  <span class="italic">p</span> ≤ 0.05 were considered significant.
 </p>
</sec>
