<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Differences in parametric and structural representations of vegetation and soil processes in ESMs, as well as uncertainties in simulated climate drivers, result in a wide range of carbon stock estimates. As we will show, biases induced by such parametric and structural differences in the initial state of vegetation biomass (i.e., during the pre-industrial (PI) period following model spin-up) often persist into future biomass predictions. In addition, poor representations of carbon allocation processes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>, inconsistent definitions of biomass in wood and in roots across ESMs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>, and uncertainties in allocation trade-offs in a changing climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> also enlarge uncertainties of projected carbon allocation in the terrestrial biosphere, increasing the range of carbon–climate feedback estimates. Another challenge to minimize uncertainties in ESMs is accurately representing the types and fractional coverage of global forests
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Despite the creation of several observationally constrained estimates of biomass in above- and below-ground vegetation compartments over the past few decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>, the uncertainties of observation-based forest biomass due to different retrieval techniques
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup> and upscaling procedures in regions with sparse data availability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup> remain large and poorly quantified. Confidence in the feedback of the vegetation carbon cycle in forest ecosystems to climate change thus requires accurate representation of carbon stocks, forest distribution, and allometric relationships between biomass compartments and the responses of underlying processes to environmental conditions in coupled ESMs.
</p>
