<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">While climate can influence vertebrate populations at large scales
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>, most taxa evaluated have either large ranges or are migratory. Amphibians have relatively small ranges and may not track climate changes as well as more mobile taxa
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, and thus be more sensitive. Climate change is expected to affect both mean and variance of environmental temperature and water availability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>, and this shift is accelerating
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>. As ectotherms with permeable skin, amphibians are sensitive to environmental temperature and moisture
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>, and we expect that demographic rates in amphibians are especially sensitive to a changing climate, especially to increases in the frequency or intensity of extreme conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. Typically, local conditions, unrelated to weather, buffer against climatic fluctuations. However, the current magnitude and rate of climate change suggest that forcing of regional water availability (i.e., drought) and temperature has the potential to over-ride local variation in these characteristics, leading to an alignment in among-population demographic rates. For example, many temperate amphibian species exist as metapopulations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>, but demography in populations fluctuates in response to local conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>, suggesting that large metapopulations are maintained when regional synchrony (due to broad-scale environmental variation) is low.
</p>
