<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Chikungunya and Zika viruses, which have emerged more recently as public health crises, are less well-studied in the context of climate change. Like dengue, these viruses are transmitted primarily by 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> in the tropics and sub-tropics and by 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">albopictus</italic> in temperate zones and other settings where 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> are absent [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. While dengue, chikungunya, and Zika viruses all have sylvatic cycles involving forest mosquitoes and non-human primates, recent global outbreaks have been dominated by urban transmission by 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">albopictus</italic>. Because these viruses are transmitted by the same vectors, and vector physiology dominates much of the transmission process, most early models of climate-dependent chikungunya and Zika transmission assumed that these viruses would exhibit similar thermal responses to dengue [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. However, several virus-specific transmission models have been developed recently. A monthly model for chikungunya in Europe, constrained by the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">albopictus</italic>, found that the A1B and B1 scenarios (older climate change scenarios, roughly comparable to intermediate scenarios RCP 6.0 and 4.5 in current climate assessments) both correspond to substantial increases in chikungunya risk surrounding the Mediterranean [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. An ecological niche modeling study conducted early in the Zika epidemic found that dengue is likely to expand far more significantly due to climate change than Zika [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] (but epidemiological differences among these three viruses remain unresolved [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]). While the combined role of climate change and El Niño has been posited as a possible driver of the Zika pandemic’s severity [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], there is little evidence that anomalous climate conditions were a necessary precursor for Zika transmission. The climate suitability of the region was present and adequate for outbreaks of dengue and chikungunya, transmitted by the same mosquitoes, making the introduction of another arbovirus plausible. In contrast to statistical models, global mechanistic forecasts accounting for climate change are scarce for both chikungunya and Zika, given how recently both emerged as public health crises, and how much critical information is still lacking in the basic biology and epidemiology of both pathogens.
</p>
