<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, we apply a new mechanistic model of the spatiotemporal distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic>-borne viral outbreaks to resolve the role climate change could play in the geographic shifts of diseases like dengue, chikungunya, and Zika. Whereas other mechanistic approaches often rely on methods like dynamic energy budgets to build complex biophysical models for 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], and subsequently (sometimes) extrapolate potential epidemiological dynamics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], our approach uses a single basic cutoff for the thermal interval where viral transmission is possible. The simplicity and transparency of the method masks a sophisticated underlying model that links the basic reproduction number, 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">0</italic>
 </sub>, for 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic>-borne viruses to temperature, via experimentally-determined physiological response curves for traits like biting rate, fecundity, mosquito lifespan, extrinsic incubation rate, and transmission probability [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The models examine the relative sensitivity of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">0</italic>
 </sub> to temperature, conditioned on the presence of the mosquito vector and independent of other factors that might influence transmission, including precipitation, vector control, and prior immune history. The temperature-dependent 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">0</italic>
 </sub> model is easily projected into geographic space by defining model-based measures of suitability and classifying each location in space as suitable or not. We parameterize the model using a Bayesian approach to account for uncertainty in the experimental data. The threshold condition in our model (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">0</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>) &gt; 0) defines the temperatures at which transmission is not prevented, rather than the more familiar threshold at which disease invasion is expected (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">0</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>) &gt; 1, which cannot be predicted in the absence of assumptions about vector and human population sizes and other factors). We then classify each location by suitability in each month based on already published projections under current climate in the Americas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>].
</p>
