<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant responses to high temperature, in addition to the damage triggered by this stress, vary widely among species and functional groups (Klockmann, Günter, &amp; Fischer, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Marias, Meinzer, &amp; Still, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0143" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; O'Sullivan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0177" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Slot &amp; Winter, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0214" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Teskey et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0225" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Wujeska‐Klause, Bossinger, &amp; Tausz, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0245" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Accordingly, the susceptibility of a plant to extremely high temperatures, a situation commonly observed during heat waves, appears to depend on a series of characteristics and adjustments at morpho‐anatomical (crown architecture, leaf size, and shape), physiological (transpiration rate and maximum stomatal conductance), and molecular (production of heat shock proteins, low‐weight compounds, and activation of the antioxidative defense system) levels (Bita &amp; Gerats, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Galmés, Kapralov, Copolovici, Hermida‐Carrera, &amp; Niinemets, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0087" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Griffin &amp; Prager, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Obata et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0167" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Scafaro et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0201" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Slot &amp; Winter, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0214" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Teskey et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0225" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Wujeska‐Klause et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0245" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0253" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Moreover, the vulnerability of a species to high temperatures also depends on its growth strategy. For example, in tropical forests, fast‐growing plants in high‐light environments tend to be more tolerant to high temperatures than slow‐growing species typical of shadier locations (Slot, Garcia, &amp; Winter, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0213" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Slot &amp; Winter, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0214" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Wright et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0244" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Although there are many factors that may influence species susceptibility to high temperature, it is important to note that most of the forest dieback events across several biomes appear to involve the association of this stress with drought (Adams et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Allen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Park Williams et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0178" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Will et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0243" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35663-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Similarly, high temperature combined with flooding can further compromise the performance of plant species through additional damages to the photosynthetic process, changes in root respiration, and also by compromising the synthesis of structural components (e.g., cell wall). However, it is important to note that only a few studies have addressed the links between these two stresses in great detail (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-2004" ref-type="ref">2017a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-2005" ref-type="ref">2017b</xref>; Donovan, Stumpff, &amp; McLeod, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-2007" ref-type="ref">1989</xref>; Lin, Lin, Syu, Tang, &amp; Lo, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-2013" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), and thus, our knowledge about this topic, especially on wood species, is rather fragmented.
</p>
