<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P17" class="p">In order to illuminate the first-order causes of locally increased land SAT variability, we compare mean changes in the surface energy budget between land locations in which low-frequency SAT variability increases with warming and land locations in which low-frequency SAT variability decreases with warming in the two GFDL model experiments (
 <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 4b and 4d</xref>) and in the CMIP5 runs (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 13b</xref>). In all experiments, there is little difference in climatological radiative surface energy availability (↓R
 <sub class="sub">s</sub>, see Methods) between the locations where SAT variability increases and the locations where SAT variability decreases (i.e., ↓R
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> changes similarly in 
 <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 4b</xref>, ↓R
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> changes similarly in 4d and ↓R
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> changes similarly in 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 13b</xref>). However, in all experiments, climatological sensible heating (↑SH) increases more and climatological latent heating (↑LE) increases less over locations where SAT variability increases (
 <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 4c, 4d</xref> and 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 14b</xref>). This can be partially explained by moisture availability (approximated here as precipitation multiplied by the latent heat of vaporization, ↓LP), which increases less over regions where SAT variability increased. Thus, land regions where local SAT variability increased tend to be regions where moisture availability declines with warming. Over these locations, incident radiation variability is able to have a stronger influence on SAT variability, because proportionally more incident radiation is converted to sensible (rather than latent) heat flux
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. Many low- to mid-latitude land regions should fit this description, since land amplification of warming is likely to cause an increase in aridity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>–
  <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
