<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">The comparison of EIVs (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>) pointed out the ongoing adaptation of the flora to the changes that occurred in the city over the last century. In particular, an expansion of all shade-tolerant categories at the expense of heliophilous ones was observed (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4A,D</xref>). Analogous findings were reported for the cities of Plzen, Brussels, Zurich and Halle using data collected over a similar timespan
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. The observed changes could be correlated to urbanistic and structural modifications of the city, which include a general enlargement of the main avenues and planting of trees in parks and streets
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. The currently present tree lines can, therefore, be considered responsible for the settling of many understory and sciophilous species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>, like 
 <italic class="italic">Hedera helix</italic> L. and 
 <italic class="italic">Trachycarpus fortunei</italic> (Hook.) H. Wendl. Pteridophytes also largely contributed to the shade-tolerant plant category (light index categories 1 to 5) while they were poorly represented in the historical flora list, being probably underestimated. Moisture index changes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4B,E</xref>) mainly reflected the anthropic changes of the city, like the widespread use of irrigation systems inside Bologna’s historical centre. This practice inevitably overshadows the effects of climate changes on floral biodiversity, as long as the soil moisture content is artificially modified. F index data collected for Bologna’s city centre showed an increased presence of hygrophilous plants (categories 6 to 8, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4B</xref>) analogously to what reported for several other European cities
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup> like Plzen, Halle and Brussels
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. This trend was confirmed by EIVs analysed for lost and acquired species (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4E</xref>) with a net gain of hygrophilous species in the 2018 flora. As previously demonstrated for other cities, for example Boston
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>, irrigated areas turn out to be a shelter for species that otherwise would be no longer present in the area, such as hygrophilous species like 
 <italic class="italic">Epilobium montanum</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Equisetum arvense</italic> L. and 
 <italic class="italic">Eclipta prostrata</italic> (L.) L., which were recently found in Bologna. However, it is not possible to exclude the presence of such species from the 1894 flora. In fact, at that time the city centre was characterized by a wide extension of channels that probably hosted a large number of plants, including many hygrophilous species, which were not recorded by Gabelli as these channels were not investigated.
</p>
