<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results|discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test the above hypothesis and to understand the underlying mechanisms, we conducted a field manipulation experiment in an alpine meadow of the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau. The unique feature of this alpine meadow is a wide span of SWC from extremely wet to dry conditions and the high warming sensitivity (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>). Our experiment consisted of three temperature treatments, including ambient (C), +1.5°C (W1.5), and + 2.5°C (W2.5) soil temperatures (STs) at a depth of 10 cm. On average, across 3 years, warming significantly decreased SWC by 2.3 and 5.8%, respectively, with W1.5 and W2.5 treatments (fig. S1). Measured NEP, gross ecosystem productivity (GEP), and ecosystem respiration (ER) all showed diverse responses to warming among years (fig. S2) and among the seasons within the year (fig. S3). Across all the measurements, GEP, ER, and NEP followed hump-shaped response surfaces with ST and SWC (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). The response surface resulted from a quadratic relationship of GEP, ER, and NEP with SWC and an exponential relationship with ST (
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E4" href="#E4">Eq. 4</a> in the “Statistical analysis” section and fig. S4). A clear ridge along an SWC of 29.9 ± 2.4% (i.e., the optimum SWC) emerged from the hump-shaped response surfaces. GEP, ER, and NEP increased with SWC below its optimum but decreased above the optimum. The SWC optimum tended to shift toward larger values as temperature increased (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Response surfaces showing the relationships between ST and SWC versus GEP, ER, or NEP across plots and years.</div>
   <p>Observed values (black crosses) are the means of five replications of C fluxes, and modeled values (colored surfaces) are predictions from the models fitted with observations.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav1131-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hump-shaped response surfaces can help us to explain diverse warming effects on GEP, ER, and NEP with changing SWC (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). When SWC was higher than its optimum (the ridge of the hump-shaped surface), warming-induced increase in ST (red arrows) and decrease in SWC (black arrows) both promoted GEP (blue dashed arrows represent their combined effects). When SWC was below the optimum, the combined positive impact of increasing temperature with negative impact of decreasing SWC under experiment warming resulted in either an increase or a decrease in GEP. As GEP response was always greater than that of ER in this study, the response pattern was similar for both GEP and NEP (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). Warming alone consistently promotes plant growth and enhances GEP under adequate moisture availability (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). Warming also accelerates microbial decomposition of soil organic C and thus increases ER (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). Under water deficits, the negative impacts of warming-induced droughts limit both carbon uptake and ER (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>). Since plant photosynthesis is more sensitive to drought than respiration (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>), GEP decreased more than ER, leading to a decrease in NEP and a positive carbon-climate feedback under low SWC.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Response surfaces showing the relationships between ST and SWC versus ecosystem C fluxes (i.e., GEP, ER, and NEP) across plots and years.</div>
   <p>Observed values (bubbles) are the means of each measurement of GEP, ER, and NEP. Modeled values (colored response surfaces with contour lines) are predictions from the models fitted with observations. The red arrows represent the effects of increasing temperature, and the black arrows indicate those of warming-induced decrease in SWC. The blue dashed arrows represent the potential changes of ecosystem C fluxes in combination of the two driving forces of changing ST and SWC.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav1131-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a nonlinear statistical model to discern the relative effects of warming-induced changes in temperature and SWC on GEP, ER, and NEP. Our analysis demonstrated that increasing ST under warming treatments alone always raised GEP, ER, and NEP across the full range of SWC (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). However, warming-induced decreases in SWC stimulated GEP, ER, and NEP in its high range but depressed them in the low range (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). Changes in these carbon fluxes formed linear scaling relationships with SWC. As a consequence, the warming effect was linearly scaled up or down with SWC, depending on which ranges the warming-induced decreases in SWC fell. Below the optimum, warming-induced decline in SWC reduced carbon fluxes to offset the stimulation caused by increasing ST, leading to either decreases in GEP, ER, and NEP under severe dry conditions or minor increases in these carbon fluxes under moderate dry conditions (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). Above the optimum, warming-induced changes in SWC and ST both stimulated GEP, ER, and NEP. Their combination amplified each other to produce a much stronger stimulation than their individual effects (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). While the patterns of water scaling were similar between the two levels of temperature treatments, the magnitudes of impacts were higher under the W2.5 treatment than those under the W1.5 treatment (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The simulated changes in GEP, ER, and NEP caused by warming-induced increasing ST (red line), warming-induced decrease in SWC (black line), and the combination effects of ST and SWC (ST + SWC, blue line) under two warming treatments (W1.5 and W2.5).</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav1131-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test whether this water scaling pattern is generalizable across ecosystems, we conducted a global meta-analysis. We examined warming impacts on NEP in relation with ambient precipitation, due to fewer data points reported on warming-induced changes in SWC in the literatures from the study sites (table S1). However, precipitation is a good proxy for SWC at both site levels (figs. S5 and S6) and the global scale as shown in another synthesis study (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>). In general, warming-induced changes in NEP were highly correlated with ambient precipitation (
  <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.003) but not with the magnitude or duration of experimental warming (table S2) or mean annual temperature (table S2). This relationship holds even when experimental data only from the temperate zone were used and those from other climate zones (e.g., tundra ecosystems) were excluded. Overall, warming significantly reduced NEP under low precipitation but increased it under high precipitation.
 </p>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Global synthesis of experimental warming-induced relative changes in NEP with ambient precipitation.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav1131-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This water scaling can well explain conflicting results reported from previous case studies on warming-induced changes in ecosystem carbon fluxes (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>). Increases in plant growth, GEP, ER, or NEP under experimental warming were mostly detected in wet ecosystems, such as subtropical forests with a mean annual precipitation (MAP) of 1778 mm (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>), temperate spruce forests with a MAP of 1480 mm (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>), and alpine meadows with a MAP of 966 mm (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>). In contrast, the warming-induced decreases in these ecosystem carbon fluxes were mainly reported in dry ecosystems, such as semiarid grasslands with a MAP of 375 and 241 mm (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>), high arctic tundra with a MAP of 197 mm (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>), and high arctic polar semidesert with a MAP of 122 mm (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study, to our knowledge, reconciles mechanisms revealed from site-level experiments with patterns of water scaling of warming effects at global scales. Our experiment in the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau revealed a flipping pattern, as did from the boreal forest experiment (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>), that warming effect was negative under dry conditions but positive under wet conditions. This flipping pattern is confirmed by our meta-analysis to be generalizable across experiments in different ecosystems. Our combined study suggests that water availability represents a strong, consistent mechanism underlying diverse, sometimes contradictory, responses of carbon processes to climate warming observed from different ecosystems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beyond revealing a generalizable pattern of water scaling, our study has also developed a continuous (i.e., quadratic) function (
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E4" href="#E4">Eq. 4</a> in the
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“Statistical analysis” section) to represent scaling of carbon fluxes with SWC. This function allowed us to identify thresholds of SWC between stimulating and inhibiting warming effects on carbon fluxes (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Figs. 2</a> and 
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">3</a>). The threshold becomes higher under high (W2.5) than low (W1.5) temperature treatments. This continuous function also allowed us to attribute observed ecosystem responses to direct warming effects versus indirect warming effects through changes in SWC (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). Direct warming effects at our alpine meadow site were always positive along SWC gradients for all the GEP, NEP, and ER, whereas indirect warming effects through changes in SWC were positive under wet conditions but negative under dry conditions. This water scaling function has the potential to improve model prediction of carbon cycle feedback to climate change. Models have used a variety of response functions, such as linear (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>), Gaussian (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>), exponential (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>), and reverse exponential (
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>), to represent carbon cycle responses to SWC. These functions are apparently not sufficient to represent a full spectrum of C cycle responses to water availability. For example, the linear response function is likely to work well when one ecosystem is prevailingly under either dry or wet condition. In comparison, this study reveals that a continuous function is needed to represent a full spectrum of hydrological regulation of the C cycle and its feedback to climate warming to improve model prediction of C cycle responses to climate warming (
  <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
   <span class="italic">35</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings shed light on future climate-carbon feedback at least in a couple of ways. Future warmer conditions will lead to variable feedbacks of ecosystems to climate warming, depending on moisture conditions. Ecosystems in very dry regions most likely decrease carbon uptake under warming conditions and thus cause a positive feedback to climate warming. In contrast, ecosystems in wet regions possibly generate a negative feedback. Moreover, warmer climate will results in chronically lowering soil moisture. Lowering soil moisture will stimulate warming effects in wet regions but exert a strong braking effect on, or even reverse, the potential benefit of climate warming on ecosystem carbon uptake in dry regions. Thus, this and other studies suggest precipitation thresholds to regulate NEP variation at regional and continental scales (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, our and many other field warming experiments provide compelling evidence on water regulation of ecosystem feedback to climate warming at both temporal and spatial scales. The revealed water scaling represents a generalizable pattern for understanding ecosystem-climate feedback from local to global scales. A continuous function of water scaling is needed to describe observed shifts of carbon-climate feedback from being negative to positive along the full spectrum of water availability at our experimental site and likely other sites. This water scaling pattern is generally supported by the global meta-analysis that warming stimulates net ecosystem carbon release (i.e., positive carbon cycle feedbacks to climate warming) in low-precipitation regions but enhances carbon uptake (i.e., negative feedbacks) in high-precipitation regions. This water scaling pattern enriches mechanistic understanding of temperature-moisture interactions in affecting ecosystem carbon cycling and its feedback to climate change and has the potential to improve model prediction.</p>
</sec>
