<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of ecosystem CO
  <sub>2</sub> fluxes
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured NEP and ER twice per month during the growing season on clear days from June to September in 2014 to 2016. In May 2014, we installed a 0.5 m by 0.5 m square aluminum frame into the soil at the depth of 3 cm in each plot, with a distance of at least 30 cm from the perimeter of the plot, to seal the canopy chamber (0.5 m by 0.5 m by 0.5 m, polymethyl methacrylate) to the soil surface and provided a plane interface between them. Care was taken to minimize soil disturbance during the installation. NEP and ER were measured using an infrared gas analyzer (LI-6400XT, LI-COR Environmental, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA), which was attached to the transparent canopy chamber. During measurements, two small fans were installed diagonally inside the chamber and fanned continuously to mix the atmosphere. Consecutive recordings of CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations were obtained once every 10 s in 80 s. NEP was calculated by the slope between recording time and concentrations [see the detailed method in (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>)]. Right after the NEP measurements, the chamber was lifted up to exchange air with the outside. Then, we covered an opaque cloth on the chamber and repeated the measurement to obtain ER. GEP was calculated as the difference between NEP and ER.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ST (°C) was measured at a 10-cm depth using a thermocouple probe concurrently with the ecosystem CO
  <sub>2</sub> fluxes measurements. The 10-cm SWC (%
  <span class="italic">V</span>) was measured using a time domain reflectometry instrumentation (TDR 100, Spectrum Technologies Inc., Chicago, USA). All measurements were performed at the same time with C fluxes measurement.
 </p>
</sec>
