<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
  <p>Supplementary material for this article is available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/8/eaav1131/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/8/eaav1131/DC1</span>
  </p>
  <p>Table S1. Site information in global meta-analysis.</p>
  <p>Table S2. Effects of mean annual precipitation (MAP), mean annual temperature (MAT), experimental warming magnitude, duration, and their interactions on relative changes in NEP across global herbaceous ecosystems with a linear mixed-effect model.</p>
  <p>Table S3. Repeated-measures ANOVA results (
   <span class="italic">F</span> values) on the effects of warming (
   <span class="italic">W</span>), year (
   <span class="italic">Y</span>), and their interactions on GEP, ER, NEP, ST (
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>soil</sub>), and moisture (
   <span class="italic">M</span>
   <sub>soil</sub>).
  </p>
  <p>Table S4. Repeated-measures ANOVA results (
   <span class="italic">F</span> values) on the effects of warming (
   <span class="italic">W</span>), measured time (
   <span class="italic">T</span>), and their interactions on GEP, ER, NEP, ST (
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>soil</sub>), and moisture (
   <span class="italic">M</span>
   <sub>soil</sub>) in 2014–2016.
  </p>
  <p>Table S5. Comparison of the nonthreshold and threshold models based on the AIC for GEP, ER, and NEP.</p>
  <p>Table S6. Coefficients of threshold model (means and 95% confidence intervals) (Eq. 4).</p>
  <p>Fig. S1. Seasonal dynamics and means of ST and SWC at 10-cm depth under three warming treatments in 2014 to 2016.</p>
  <p>Fig. S2. Seasonal means of GEP, ER, and NEP under different warming treatments in 2014 to 2016.</p>
  <p>Fig. S3. Warming-induced changes in GEP, ER, and NEP within the year.</p>
  <p>Fig. S4. Relationships between ST and GEP, ER, or NEP across seasons and plots.</p>
  <p>Fig. S5. Relationships between warming-induced response ratio of ecosystem carbon fluxes with monthly precipitation.</p>
  <p>Fig. S6. The relationship between response ratio of monthly mean SWC and monthly precipitation in a precipitation gradient experiment at our study site from 2015 to 2016.</p>
  <p>Fig. S7. Relationships between the modeled and observed values of carbon fluxes with 1:1 line.</p>
  <p>Fig. S8. Relationships between SWC and ecosystem C fluxes within peak growing seasons (July and August).</p>
  <p>References (
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
    <span class="italic">41</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R65" ref-type="bibr" href="#R65">
    <span class="italic">65</span>
   </a>)
  </p>
 </div>
</div>
