<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">In this study, we used 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> simulations, which consider variations of the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration only, and historical, RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 simulations (Representative Concentration Pathways), which consider CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and non-CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> forcing, from eight CMIP5 Earth system models
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>. The models included in the current ensemble are CanESM2, GFDL-ESM2G, GFDL-ESM2M, HadGEM2-ES, IPSL-CM5A-LR, IPSL-CM5A-MR, IPSL-CM5B-LR and MIROC-ESM (see Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>). This selection corresponds to the ensemble used by Gillett 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (2013)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>, but we excluded models, for which data necessary to compute heat exposure were not publicly available. For each of these models, a single realization has been taken into account for each simulation. Data considered in this analysis runs from year 1 to 140, from year 1861 to 2005 and from year 2006 to 2095 for the 1% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, historical and RCP scenarios, respectively. We obtained the evolution of heat exposure from daily data to compute annual statistics. And only then, we interpolated the results onto a common grid for analyses purposes (CanESM2 grid, with a 2.8° spatial resolution), as suggested by Diaconescu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (2015)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup> for extreme heat indices. No bias correction has been applied to climate model outputs, similarly to other studies on CCE [e.g.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>].
</p>
