<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The predominant 
 <italic class="italic">Pectobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> strains in Europe (Ppa, Pbr, and Dsol) have been confirmed in GB but have yet to become established [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. As the trend towards hotter summers in GB in recent decades is expected to continue [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], there is a concern that they could cause increased disease problems in the future, given the known effects of temperature on aggressiveness, pathogenicity differentiation, competition and species selection. There is therefore a need to assess the potential for a temperature-induced shift in the prevalence of non-indigenous but confirmed 
 <italic class="italic">Pectobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> spp. in GB, to guide strategies for agricultural adaptation to climate change. An increased frequency of drier summers is also expected for GB, which could affect soil moisture levels and thus risk of mother-tuber rotting. Projections of the relationship between land suitability for potato production and water resource availability show that growing rainfed potatoes in GB will become increasingly difficult as the climate changes, with a consequent increase in demand for supplemental irrigation [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. It is anticipated that this demand will be met in the short-term via additional water abstraction licenses (e.g. abstraction in winter, and storage in a reservoir) and license trading, and through various short-term coping strategies, such as improved irrigation technology (scheduling) and equipment, modification of soil structure to improve soil moisture retention, and installation of rainwater harvesting equipment. In the long-term, however, a geographical shift of potato production to regions with suitable agroclimate and water availability is considered as the most viable option for the GB potato industry [
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205711.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Thus, a further research priority is to assess the implications of such a geographical shift on risk of establishment of the non-indigenous European 
 <italic class="italic">Pectobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Dickeya</italic> strains.
</p>
