<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">Variance components and genetic correlations were estimated using a character state approach (treating the same trait measured in different environments as separate traits)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>
 </sup> using the ‘MCMCglmm’ package
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>
 </sup>. Models were fit as multivariate GLMMs with offspring body size in the four temperature treatments as Gaussian response variables. Only those families that hatched in all four experimental treatments (n = 31) were included in these analyses. Variance components were calculated for the animal term or FS family term for each environment-specific body size (random term: ~us(trait):animal or ~us(trait):FS family, respectively). Since traits in different environments could not be measured on the same individual, the ~idh(trait):units structure of MCMCglmm was used to estimate covariance between environment-specific body sizes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">75</xref>
 </sup>. All final models used contained full-sibling family (FS family) as a random effect as opposed to fitting an animal random effect (which takes into account the resemblance among all individuals in the data set irrespective of their level of relatedness
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" class="xref">97</xref>
 </sup>) because the study design contained a single generation with large sibling groups, and the additive genetic and maternal variance components could not be partitioned from total genetic variance due to the FS family design (see also ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>). Also, analyses using animal as the random effect showed inflated genetic variance components and heritabilities, and very low environmental variance components compared to models fit using FS family, indicating less bias in estimating genetic effects when using FS family. Dam (individual female) was also not modelled as an additional random effect as maternal variance was redundant within the family effect (i.e. no half-sibling families were produced). Dam °C, offspring °C, egg size and density were modelled as fixed effects. Model fits were assessed by their Deviance Information Criteria (DIC) scores including random effects, whereby a ΔDIC greater than 2 represents a significantly better model fit
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" class="xref">98</xref>
 </sup>. Weak but informative priors of half the observed variance were used, and the covariance between temperature-specific body sizes was set to zero to account for measurements stemming from separate individuals (see also ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>). Markov chains were run for 400 000 iterations, with a burn-in of 100 000, and every 100
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> value was kept to generate posterior distributions of random and fixed parameters. Genetic correlations (r
 <sub class="sub">G</sub>) were calculated as the covariance between traits (body size in two temperatures) divided by the square root of the product of both traits. Significance was assessed by estimating the proportion of estimates from the posterior distribution that overlapped zero, with a non-significant r
 <sub class="sub">G</sub> indicative of a G × E interaction
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" class="xref">97</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
