<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig6" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Impact of sea-level changes and solid Earth deformation on Antarctic past and future ice sheet evolution. Frames show model-predicted contribution from the AIS to global mean sea level (GMSL) (
   <span class="bold">a</span>) over the last 40 ka relative to the modern, (
   <span class="bold">b</span>) during a 10 ka mid Pliocene warming of 2 °C relative to an initial state similar to the modern except that the Earth system has fully equilibrated from the last deglaciation, and (
   <span class="bold">c</span>, 
   <span class="bold">d</span>) under future climate warming relative to a modern pre-industrial state at 0 model years in which (
   <span class="bold">c</span>) CO
   <sub>2</sub> is doubled and the oceans are warmed by 2 °C at the start of the simulation, and (
   <span class="bold">d</span>) RCP 8.5 climate warming is applied and additional mechanisms promoting ice loss are included. The black line in 
   <span class="bold">a</span> shows the results of a simulation that adopts an ELRA bedrock deformation model (relaxation time 3 ka) and no sea-level coupling. The black line in 
   <span class="bold">c</span> shows the results of a simulation in which the positions of the solid Earth surface and sea surface are fixed. Red and blue lines show output from a coupled ice sheet–sea level model that includes the feedback of solid Earth deformation and sea surface height changes on ice dynamics. These simulations adopt two different radially varying Earth models: “HV” (red lines) has a lithospheric thickness of 120 km and upper and lower mantle viscosities of 0.5 and 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">21</span> Pa s, respectively; “LVZ” (blue lines) has a 50 km thick lithosphere, a low viscosity zone of 10
   <span class="sup">19</span> Pa s down to 200 km depth, and upper and lower mantle viscosities below that of 0.2 and 3 × 10
   <span class="sup">21 </span>Pa s, respectively. Frames (
   <span class="bold">a</span>), (
   <span class="bold">b</span>) and (
   <span class="bold">d</span>) were created from results of Pollard et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
   </span>, and frame (
   <span class="bold">c</span>) was created from the results of Gomez et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
   </span>
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8068_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1231" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
