<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions
 </div>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In each phase-out scenario starting in 2018, CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions from fossil fuels decline at an approximately linear rate of 0.30 (FAST), 0.23 (MID) or 0.18 (SLOW) GtC yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> from their 2018 peak (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), consistent with energy sector fossil fuel phase outs over 30, 40 or 50 years respectively. These rates are scaled up for the 2030 phase-out scenarios to achieve phase-outs over the same time periods. The near-linear rate of decline in CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions is partly coincidental as each sector is treated differently as detailed below. We extend the analysis of ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, which considered emissions impacts of fossil fuel energy generation. At 42% of global CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions in 2015 (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>), energy generation is the largest sector but by no means the only significant one. We separately consider transport (24% of 2015 emissions) and industry (19% of 2015 emissions), covering 85% of global CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions. The remaining 15% of emissions (from residential, service and other aggregated sources) are combined with the energy sector in our scenarios. This is on the basis that it is less straightforward to find robust lifetime assumptions from these sectors, and in the absence of better information we proceed on the assumption that any transformation that could be implemented in the energy sector could also be put into effect elsewhere at the same rate.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Land use-related CO
  <sub>2</sub> is abruptly set to zero in the first year following the phase-out start. This is on the basis that humanity would be concerned enough under a phase-out scenario to prevent additional deforestation. In the context of the simple climate model used in this study this is a conservative estimate, as land use change (a negative forcing) scales with cumulative land use CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
