<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ensemble generation</div>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainty in ensemble projections is driven by the uncertainty in the input parameters to FaIR. ECS and TCR are drawn from a joint lognormal distribution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>
  </span> (correlation coefficient 0.81) informed by the ECS and TCR from the abrupt4xCO2 (instantaneous quadrupling of CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations) and 1pctCO2 (compound annual 1% increase in CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations) results from CMIP5 climate models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>
  </span>. The slow and fast time constants of ocean thermal response (
  <span class="italic">d</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">d</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) are drawn from normal distributions based on the analysis of ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, and carbon cycle response parameters drawn from normal distributions based on ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. The scaling factors for ERF uncertainty for 11 different anthropogenic forcing components are drawn from normal, composite normal or lognormal distributions and are informed by AR5 estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. In total, 1000 sample parameter sets are drawn and the model spun up for the historical period and then projected forward. Ensemble members not falling within the historical uncertainty of observational temperature change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> are rejected.
 </p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The posterior (temperature-constrained) distributions of each input parameter are shown in Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>, with the correlations between parameters and each parameter with 2100 temperature change in Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>. In the experiment design, uncertainties are uncorrelated with each other except for ECS and TCR. In reality there is a weak positive correlation between 
  <span class="italic">d</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and ECS (or TCR), but constructing a joint distribution with one lognormal variable and one normal is problematic, so we take 
  <span class="italic">d</span>
  <sub>1</sub> to be uncorrelated with ECS. We find there is a negative correlation in the posterior distributions between ECS or TCR and present-day aerosol ERF, which is expected
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>
  </span>, and positive correlations between total ERF and both aerosol ERF and 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>2x</sub>, although as these factors are not independent this is also expected.
 </p>
</sec>
