<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish surveys</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All fish species from 13 pre-selected families that span the full range of trophic groups, from piscivores to detritivores (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s002" href="#pone.0191448.s002">S2 Table</a>) were counted in 50 x 5 m transects. Two dives were conducted at each site which spanned approximately 300 m along the reef edge. In each dive 2–3 transects were run parallel to the reef edge (5–6 replicate transects in total per site). Transects were placed randomly at different depths to span the depth range of the reef, but a maximum dive depth of 26m was imposed by dive safety regulations. Fish counts at each site therefore had relatively broad depth ranges, depending on the reef profile (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s001" href="#pone.0191448.s001">S1 Table</a>). This design was used to maximise survey coverage of the fish assemblage on the reef. The fish survey sites corresponded to the dive sites at which the benthic video transects were placed; both methods spanned the same depth range at each site. Siganids (rabbitfishes) were not observed at all and therefore a total of 12 families were counted (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s002" href="#pone.0191448.s002">S2 Table</a>). The density and size classes of species were estimated using standard underwater visual census (UVC) techniques for coral reef fishes [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref038">38</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref039">39</a>]. The size of all species &gt;5 cm total length (TL) were estimated in 5 cm size classes (e.g. 6–10 cm TL, 11–15 cm TL, 16–20 cm TL etc), to obtain biomass values based on published length—weight relationships [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref040">40</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref042">42</a>]. Biomass was calculated as a derived variable for the fish assemblage because it is a good indicator of energy flow within the coral reef ecosystem. A fixed size category for the smallest species was used because: simplifying counting procedures across a wide range of species improves accuracy [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref043">43</a>]; any differences in biomass in these small species between sites will be smaller than the 5 cm size class accuracy used; and to enable these small species to be included in total biomass calculations. Fixed size classes were as follows: i) all Chaetontidae species were assigned a length size class of 6–10 cm, with the exception of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">xanthocephalos</span>, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">lineolatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Heniochus</span> spp. which were recorded as 11–15 cm; ii) small acanthurids, 
  <span class="italic">Ctenochaetus</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Acanthurus nigrofuscus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">leucosternon</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Zebrasoma scopas</span>, were assigned a length size class of 11–15 cm; iii) 
  <span class="italic">Centropyge</span> spp. (Pomacanthidae)–were assigned a length size class of 6–10 cm. A total of 110 species were identified and assigned to 12 functional trophic groups (piscivores, omnivores, corallivores, invertivores, planktivores, detritivores, grazer-detritivores and 5 herbivore categories, 
  <span class="italic">sensu</span> Green and Bellwood [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref044">44</a>]) using a classification system for the WIO [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref045">45</a>] (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191448.s002" href="#pone.0191448.s002">S2 Table</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
