<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing effects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was not designed to look at fishing effects because it was based on the premise that there is no reef fishing in Chagos Archipelago, however, there was a small Mauritian fishery targeting grouper (Epinephelidae) and snapper (Lutjanidae), which operated from the 1970s until 2010 when the Chagos MPA was designated [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref023">23</a>]. Populations of piscivore and omnivore trophic categories were similar between atolls, exemplified by the coralgrouper 
  <span class="italic">Plectropomus laevis</span>, which was abundant and observed at all but three sites. However, two snappers 
  <span class="italic">Lutjanus bohar</span> (piscivore) and 
  <span class="italic">Lutjanus gibbus</span> (omnivore) were significantly correlated with differences in fish assemblages across atolls. The highest biomass of these two species was found in Peros Banhos lagoon sites (up to 861 kg/ha and 530 kg/ha, for 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">bohar</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibbus</span>, respectively). Apparently, the fishery did not operate in the lagoons (BIOT Fisheries Officer, pers. comm. 2014), but since our study is the first to report on fish biomass in the lagoons there are no previous comparable data. For 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">bohar</span> moderate biomass levels were found on forereefs at Salomon, Peros Banhos and Blenheim, but were lower at Diego Garcia and GCB, while biomass of 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibbus</span> was highly variable across all forereefs. Our surveys also suggest that three large species of grouper, 
  <span class="italic">Epinephelus fuscoguttatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">multinotatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">tauvina</span> may have been overfished in the past since they were absent at most sites. While there is also some illegal fishing in BIOT, 80% by weight of illegal catches detected by the BIOT patrol vessel is shark [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref056">56</a>] and therefore this poaching can be considered minimal in terms of impacts on reef fishes. Our results suggest that further research is needed to distinguish between possible latent fishing effects or natural biotic/abiotic drivers of some grouper and 
  <span class="italic">Lutjanus bohar</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recreational fishery operates outside the MPA at the naval base in Diego Garcia and is having an impact on fish biomass [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref023">23</a>]. Our total biomass estimates with maximum values of ~3,500 kg/ha (12 families) do not include sharks and trevally and therefore cannot be directly compared with the estimates of &gt;9,000 kg/ha reported from 2010–2012. However, comparing relative biomass between atolls from the 2010–2012 survey [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref023">23</a>] with our survey in 2014 shows similar differences, with highest values at Peros Banhos, followed by GCB, then Salomon, and the lowest values at Diego Garcia. This supports Graham et al.’s [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref023">23</a>] conclusions that the recreational fishery is having an impact. Nevertheless, we measured extremely high biomass values at 10 of the 13 sites (1,501–3,000 kg/ha at six sites, and &gt; 3,000 kg/ha at four sites). These biomass estimates are similar, when the same families are considered, to biomass at other uninhabited and protected reefs of the French territories in the Mozambique Channel [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref057">57</a>], providing strong support for using Chagos Archipelago as a reference benchmark for unfished reef fish populations in the WIO.
 </p>
</sec>
