<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trophic dynamics in the reef fish assemblages</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herbivory and detritivory contribute significantly to the trophic dynamics and hence biomass production on coral reefs [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref058">58</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref059">59</a>]. Indeed, the diversity of herbivores and detritivores seen on modern reefs, illustrated by the parrotfishes (Labridae: Scarinae) and surgeonfishes (Acanthuridae), has been linked to the massive expansion of shallow coral reef habitats over the last 5 million years [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref060">60</a>]. In the Chagos Archipelago, the grazer-detritivores was the trophic group that differed most significantly between atolls. This group comprises a suite of acanthurids (“ring-tail” surgeonfishes [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref044">44</a>]), such as 
  <span class="italic">Acanthurus tennenti</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">xanthopterus</span>, that harvest mouthfuls of soft sediment on dead coral substrate, as well as on sand, which contain the diatoms and microbes of their diet [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref061">61</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref062">62</a>]. Their highest densities at GCB and Diego Garcia (&gt;500 and &gt;600 individuals/ha, respectively) corresponded with low hard coral cover. In contrast, low numbers of these surgeonfishes were seen at Peros Banhos, Salomon and Blenheim (&lt;130, &lt;14, &lt;170 individuals/ha, respectively), where hard coral cover was high. These results suggest that these “grazer-detritivore” surgeonfish species may thrive where their benthic food sources have increased due to coral mortality [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref063">63</a>] so potentially may serve as indicators of reef degradation. The prevalence of the detritivory role is also supported by one of the most common reef fishes in the world, the bristletooth surgeonfishes 
  <span class="italic">Ctenochaetus</span> spp. [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref064">64</a>], with the combined density of two species 
  <span class="italic">Ctenochaetus truncatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">striatus</span> of ~850 individuals/ha, the second highest of all the 110 species surveyed (
  <span class="italic">Caesio</span> spp. density was the highest: 936 individuals/ha). We propose that the importance of detritivory in recovery of degraded reefs and in cycling carbon within coral reef systems is not well quantified and therefore an important area for future research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A strong relationship between hard coral cover and corallivores has been widely reported [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref054">54</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref065">65</a>] and was confirmed here with significantly higher densities of obligate coral-feeding butterflyfishes at Peros Banhos and Salomon atolls where there was relatively higher live coral cover. These coral specialists are clearly highly vulnerable to coral mortality and, as such, have long been used as potential indicator species for monitoring coral reef health [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref066">66</a>]. The third trophic group that differed significantly between atolls was the planktivores, comprising several acanthurids (three 
  <span class="italic">Naso</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Acanthurus thompsoni</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Paracanthurus hepatus)</span>, two chaetodontids, two balistids and 
  <span class="italic">Caesio</span> spp. The biomass of this group was three times higher at GCB, with a mean biomass of 1,045 kg/ha, compared to 338kg/ha for other atolls, and this was largely due to the caesionids and 
  <span class="italic">Naso hexacanthus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">N</span>. 
  <span class="italic">brevirostris</span>. Further, three planktivores were strongly correlated with the ordination: 
  <span class="italic">Paracanthurus hepatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Acanthurus thompsoni</span> and the chaetodon 
  <span class="italic">Hemitaurichthys zoster</span>. Drivers of planktivore populations on coral reefs are still poorly understood, but their food items are associated with reef edges and proximity to deep water [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref067">67</a>]. These acanthurid species are all zooplanktivores [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref068">68</a>], suggesting waters at GCB may be zooplankton-rich. Thus, higher Acanthuridae densities overall at GCB reefs appear to reflect two different and unrelated trophic pathways: increased access to soft benthic surfaces due to coral mortality for the grazer-detritivores and higher zooplankton densities for planktivores. Finally, it was notable that the density and biomass of the piscivore and omnivore trophic groups, species that represent important target fishery species [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref039">39</a>], were not significantly correlated with fish assemblage patterns across the archipelago, suggesting that benthic differences did not directly affect these higher trophic level taxa. Thus, when data were aggregated by trophic group, only three groups differed significantly and these appeared to be influenced by reduced coral cover due to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref022">22</a>] and natural variability in zooplankton, both bottom-up control pathways.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It was surprising that none of the five herbivore trophic groups, which included all the parrotfishes, were significant in explaining differences in fish assemblages between sites. We found species-level analyses were more informative than aggregated trophic group analyses and demonstrated species from within seven trophic groups were highly related to differences in the fish assemblages across the reefs of the Chagos Archipelago. 
  <span class="italic">Scarus niger</span> had the strongest correlation with fish assemblage structure across the archipelago, with highest biomass on the high coral cover northern atolls (182 kg/ha at Peros Banhos), and the lowest at Diego Garcia and the low coral cover reefs of GCB (3 kg/ha and 11–27 kg/ha, respectively). This species is one of the most ubiquitous parrotfishes across the Indo-Pacific [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref069">69</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref070">70</a>] and feeds on the top 1–2 mm of dead coral substrate [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref062">62</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref071">71</a>], though it probably removes epilithic algae while feeding. 
  <span class="italic">Scarus niger</span> was associated with the highly abundant surgeonfish 
  <span class="italic">Acanthurus nigrofuscus</span>, known to graze similar substrate types but feeding on epilithic algae [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref060">60</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref062">62</a>]. These two species correlated most closely with the assemblages at Salomon Atoll sites, particularly on the outer forereefs where live hard coral, 
  <span class="italic">Acropora</span> and rugosity were highest, but also at the Peros Banhos lagoon sites where turf algae and dead coral were relatively high. This result may reflect “feeding complimentarity” by a parrotfish and a surgeonfish, accessing different algal prey within the same benthic substrate [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref072">72</a>]. It also illustrates the challenges in using trophic categories as a proxy for ecological function. Herbivorous fishes have been implicated in the top-down control of reef benthos, as their grazing of recently dead coral substrate prevents the rapid colonisation of macroalgae. Further, over-fishing of herbivores has been invoked to explain declines in coral cover and they are consequently considered to play a key functional role in maintaining coral reef resilience [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref011">11</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref073">73</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref075">75</a>]. Parrotfishes (Labridae; Scarinae) are a significant component of this herbivorous fish community on account of their size, numerical abundance and hence biomass [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref014">14</a>]. They are also targeted in many reef fisheries and are frequently used as indicators for the condition or resilience of reefs [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref076">76</a>]. However, recent work on the intricacies of parrotfish feeding modes and diets [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref060">60</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref071">71</a>] indicates that assigning species with similar feeding modes into broad trophic groups may over-simplify their functional role in reef resilience. Further, we show that parrotfish population densities can vary by up to 43-fold between reef sites in the absence of fishing and so caution against assumptions that declines in parrotfish populations are necessarily due to fishing.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The largest parrotfishes, 
  <span class="italic">Cetoscarus ocellatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Chlororus strongylocephalos</span>, showed completely opposing patterns in their distribution with 
  <span class="italic">Cetoscarus ocellatus</span> closely associated with healthy reefs with high coral cover at the northern atolls (Peros Banhos and Salomon). In contrast, 
  <span class="italic">Chlorurus strongylocephalos</span> was strongly correlated with reefs at GCB which had the lowest live coral and the highest cover of calcareous algae, soft coral and macroalgae. This opposing pattern in the distribution of these two high-biomass parrotfish, functionally termed “excavators” [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref044">44</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref063">63</a>], can be explained by their feeding behaviour. 
  <span class="italic">Cetoscarus ocellatus</span> are territorial, non-schooling, harvest small areas of reef and are associated with reefs of high live coral cover (M. Samoilys, pers. obs.). In contrast, 
  <span class="italic">Chlorurus strongylocephalos</span> prefers disturbed reefs which offer a larger benthic surface area for excavating the dead coral reef matrix [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref071">71</a>]. They feed on these substrates, typically in large schools if the disturbed substrate is of sufficient area (H. Choat, James Cook University, pers. comm. 2016). The Indian Ocean endemic, 
  <span class="italic">Chlorurus enneacanthus</span>, was observed to have a similar feeding strategy to 
  <span class="italic">Chlorurus strongylocephalos</span> (M. Samoilys pers. obs.). These 
  <span class="italic">Chlorurus</span> species conform to reports from the Philippines where some parrotfish species prefer areas of reef that have become damaged, for example from cyclones [
  <a rid="pone.0191448.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191448.ref021">21</a>]. The patterns seen here suggest bottom-up control of parrotfish populations by coral cover in positive (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">niger</span>, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ocellatus</span>) or negative (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">strongylocephalos</span>) relationships. These pathways therefore need to be considered when examining the role of parrotfishes in influencing coral recovery trajectories.
 </p>
</sec>
