<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laboratory and field studies linking abiotic conditions to tick demography and behaviour</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes</span> ticks spend more than 95% of their lives on or just below the ground surface digesting a blood meal, moulting, in diapause or seeking a host (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20140051F1" href="#RSTB20140051F1">figure 1</a>). The conditions at the ground thus seem critically important to tick survival and habitat suitability. Research on 
  <span class="italic"> Ixodes scapularis</span> conducted around the time of the discovery of Lyme disease, indicated that tick populations in coastal Massachusetts, USA, were only found after mild winters [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C35">35</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C36">36</a>]. At this time, 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span> in the northeastern United States appeared to be restricted to coastal southern New England [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C37">37</a>], a zone of relatively cool summers and warm winters compared with inland sites. These observations led to the conclusion that extreme cold and heat were unsuitable for this species, limiting its distribution and affecting its population dynamics. At the time of these observations, researchers mistakenly considered their study organism a distinct, northern species of tick that had been named 
  <span class="italic">I. dammini</span>. Only later, when it was revealed that the New England ticks under study belonged to populations of a widespread species, 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span>, were many of the conclusions revised [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C14">14</a>]. The presence of 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span> in much colder climates of Minnesota and Wisconsin and in much warmer climates of Georgia and South Carolina provided evidence that the species tolerated a considerably wider range of conditions. 
  <div id="RSTB20140051F1" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Conceptual model linking climate change to tick-borne disease in humans. Each arrow linking boxes represents an opportunity to fill in knowledge gaps. For example, determining how climate change at global and regional scales influences the key abiotic variables for ticks at local scales is critical. A mechanistic understanding of how specific abiotic variables interactively determine demographic, developmental and behavioural processes in tick vectors and dynamics of tick-borne pathogens requires further development. How climate-driven dynamics of ticks and pathogens affect risk of human exposure, how non-climatic factors influence risk, and how risk is translated into disease incidence are crucial variables for further study. (Online version in colour.)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20140051-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Later laboratory experiments repeatedly demonstrated the importance of humidity and temperature for tick survival [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C38">38</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C40">40</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes scapularis</span> is highly susceptible to desiccation when relative humidity drops below approximately 90% [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C38">38</a>]. Even a few hours at low humidity can be lethal, but ticks returned to humid air may suffer little mortality [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C40">40</a>]. As ticks are very capable of avoiding desiccating conditions, for instance by remaining in the humid leaf litter or soil until conditions become more favourable, dry conditions may not directly restrict tick populations, although long dry periods can reduce longevity [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C41">41</a>]. Environmental conditions may also constrain ticks' ability to quest for hosts. In summer, for instance, high temperatures and low relative humidity limit tick movement and questing activity [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C42">42</a>]. Thus, hot and dry summer conditions may delay or prevent ticks from obtaining the necessary blood meal. This delay may not be very restrictive as questing ticks seem able to survive for several months or longer [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C24">24</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C26">26</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C43">43</a>]. However, there may be combinations of biotic and abiotic conditions where ticks rarely quest and encounter blood-meal hosts, which could potentially limit tick populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comprehensive experiments with 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> similarly illustrate the interactive effects of temperature and humidity on survival of questing immature stages [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C44">44</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C48">48</a>]. Low relative humidity (
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 50%) permits survival when temperatures are below 5°C, but relative humidity above 
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 70% is required when temperatures exceed 
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 15°C. These studies also have shown that 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> employs sophisticated movement patterns to seek favourable microclimatic conditions, e.g. under leaf litter or in the soil, when air becomes too warm or dry. For instance, a large saturation deficit reduces activity levels of 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> but apparently has little impact on survival because it is unrelated to tick abundance in the subsequent year [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C49">49</a>]. As a consequence of these behavioural adaptations, the relevance of laboratory-determined lethal conditions to demographic patterns in nature remains elusive. Climatic restrictions on questing behaviour and host encounters (e.g. saturation deficits; [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C50">50</a>]) deserve more research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cumulative temperature appears to control the length of development of most developmental stages of 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span>. The ability of ticks to oviposit and eclose within a single season depends on cumulative degree days, although the precise number of degree days varies between studies (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C24">24</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C51">51</a>]). Similarly, rates of development of immature ticks in the field and laboratory are correlated with temperature [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C52">52</a>]. These results have led several authors to postulate that high mortality associated with longer developmental periods might limit the distribution of 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span> to warmer regions, but that climate warming will cause northward range expansion [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C31">31</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C32">32</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C53">53</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C55">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cold winter temperatures appear to have a more direct effect than do warm temperatures on 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes</span> survival and population dynamics. Newly moulted nymphal and gravid female 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span> overwinter before emerging in spring to quest for a blood-meal host or oviposit, respectively. Even short-term exposure to extreme cold (e.g. below −15°C) can be lethal to 
  <span class="italic">I. scapularis</span> [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C39">39</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C56">56</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C44">44</a>] so cold winter weather could be responsible for a significant amount of mortality, and might constrain 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes</span> populations. Establishing the lower critical temperatures in the laboratory, however, is similarly of dubious relevance to climatic limitations in nature, if ticks can escape extreme conditions for sufficient periods. A recent field experiment by Brunner 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C57">57</a>], for instance, found that the hazard of overwintering mortality of nymphs in field enclosures was essentially constant in two locations, regardless of temperature. In addition, a recent laboratory study by Herrmann &amp; Gern [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C58">58</a>] suggested that frequent temperature variation may be more important for 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> survival than low temperatures, so relating laboratory results to natural environments remains a challenge.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, increasingly strong evidence indicates that the latitudinal and altitudinal limits of 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">I. persulcatus</span> distributions in Europe are determined by cold temperatures. Expansions of tick populations northward and to higher elevations correlated with climate warming have been documented in Sweden [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C59">59</a>], Norway [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C60" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C60">60</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C61">61</a>], European Russia [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C62">62</a>], the Czech Republic [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C63">63</a>] and the UK [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C64">64</a>]. Tick density and/or prevalence of infection with tick-borne pathogens such as tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV) is correlated with either temperature (positively) or altitude (negatively) in Switzerland [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C65">65</a>], Norway [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C61">61</a>] and Sweden [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C66">66</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C67">67</a>]. And similarly, incidence of tick-borne disease correlates with mild winters and warm, humid summers in Sweden [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C67">67</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C68">68</a>], Hungary [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C69">69</a>], Slovakia [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C70">70</a>] and European Russia [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C62">62</a>]. Importantly, climatic effects on human behaviour that could influence their contact rates with ticks, independently of climatic effects on ticks, also might contribute to these correlations [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C66">66</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, while there are good reasons to think that the survival and development of 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes</span> ticks may be limited by temperature and humidity (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20140051F2" href="#RSTB20140051F2">figure 2</a>), these limitations may only manifest at the extremes of their ranges and where ticks are not able behaviourally to avoid inhospitable conditions. Within regions that have more permissive conditions, the direct effects of temperature and humidity may be more subtle or even relatively unimportant compared, for instance, with the abundance of hosts (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTB20140051C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20140051C71">71</a>]). 
  <div id="RSTB20140051F2" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Key processes in the life cycle of ixodid ticks controlling their population dynamics and effects on risk of exposure to tick-borne pathogens. Arrows indicate the potential for temperature and humidity variables to affect each process. (Online version in colour.)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20140051-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
