<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we used the KMA scenario because it was the only available high-resolution gridded climate change scenario required for local impact assessment and adaptation study. This may indicate the predictions from this study may not accurately reflect the true state of knowledge concerning potential future conditions affecting the epidemics of KBB in Jeonnam province. This is because there are inherent uncertainties in climate projections from GCMs due to fundamental variations in initial conditions as well as structural differences in the models. Therefore, we examined whether the KMA scenario-based approach can accommodate the uncertainty from multiple GCMs. For this, we compared the potential epidemic risks of KBB simulated with the single KMA scenario and multiple scenarios from 11 GCMs. Since the multiple scenarios could be obtained by statistical downscaling to point locations where more than 30 years’ climatological data exist, we selected 7 KMA Automated Synoptic Observing System (ASOS) stations in the major kiwifruit growing administrative districts in Jeonnam province for the comparison test, which are the Jindo (175), Haenam (261), Wando (170), Jangheung (260), Goheung (262), Yeosu (168), and Gwangju (156) (shown in 
 <xref rid="f1-ppj-35-459" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Statistical downscaling was conducted using the method implemented by 
 <xref rid="b5-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Cho (2013)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="b17-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Cho (2016)</xref>. Briefly, we selected daily scale scenario data from 11 GCMs (information on the GCMs refers to Table 1 in 
 <xref rid="b17-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Cho, 2016</xref>). The scenario data of 11 GCMs were bias-corrected and spatially downscaled to the 7 ASOS stations using the non-parametric quantile mapping method. Thirty years of observed historical data obtained from the ASOS stations were used as a reference for the quantile mapping method.
</p>
