<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Studies across the UK indicate that disease incidence is higher in less deprived areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>], although because these studies are based upon reported cases of 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacte</italic>r, some differences may be due to differential reporting [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. Gillespie et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>] found in England and Wales that 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacte</italic>r disease incidence was slightly higher in individual’s whose work was often done in an office or other professional environment in comparison to those whose jobs were more manual. However, disease incidence was highest in people working in semi-routine occupations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. This same study found that the incidence of 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> disease was greatest in the Pakistani population in comparison to the white population. Levels in other ethnic groups such as Indian, Black and Chinese were lower. Turning to gender, this study found that the incidence of disease was slightly higher in males than in females, a result confirmed in Scotland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>]. In terms of the age distribution of reported cases the greatest incidence appears to fall on infants. Incidence then decreases for the ages 2–13 years but rises again until age 22. Incidence then remains relatively constant between ages 22 and 69 before falling from age 70 onwards [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. Similar distributions are reported in Scotland and Northern Ireland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. In terms of trends over time, as the UK population ages the number of reported 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> cases has increased in older individuals. However, as well as the absolute number of reports increasing it has also been observed that 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> incidence is increasing in older people [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>].
</p>
