<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Character-based assignment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">P-Gnome failed to produce a diagnostic rule set that that could distinguish all 398 species sequenced in this study. Results using subsets of the data were more successful. Complete diagnostic rule sets were generated and successfully tested for both 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span>. The rule set for 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza </span>could not distinguish between sequences of E. 
  <span class="italic">leucocephalos </span>and 
  <span class="italic">E. citrinella </span>due to their near congruence. In addition, P-Elf failed to correctly identify single sequences from the species 
  <span class="italic">E. chrysophrys </span>and 
  <span class="italic">E. elegans</span>. The former sequence was short (594 bp) and might have lacked important diagnostic characters. However, the latter sequence was of typical length (694 bp) and only exceptional in that it contained 5 polymorphic sites from the sequence used to generate the rule set. Both of these species were incorrectly identified as 
  <span class="italic">E. aureola</span>, though this identification would vary if the input tree were altered.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of 22 groups of lumped species, all but five could be resolved using diagnostic characters (see Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>). For example, the species pair 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix coturnix </span>and 
  <span class="italic">C. japonica </span>possessed 10 diagnostic nucleotide sites, two short of recognition by the MOTU threshold but still easily distinguishable. More complex rule sets were required when more species were involved (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Aythya </span>ducks). The remaining groups featured virtually no variation between species. These include 10 members of the herring gull complex (
  <span class="italic">Larus </span>spp.) and the species pairs 
  <span class="italic">Gallinago gallinago/G. delicata</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cuculus canorus</span>/
  <span class="italic">C. optatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis flammea</span>/
  <span class="italic">C. hornemanni</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella/E. leucocephalos</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
