<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laboratory methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extraction, PCR, and sequencing reactions follow the procedures described in Kerr et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>]. Only sequences greater than 500 bp and containing fewer than 10 ambiguous base calls were included in analyses. The sequence from one 
  <span class="italic">Anas crecca </span>specimen was omitted from analysis due to suspicion that it was actually an 
  <span class="italic">A. crecca </span>× 
  <span class="italic">A. carolinensis </span>hybrid based on morphology and molecular results. Collection data, sequences, and trace files are available from the project 'Birds of the eastern Palearctic' at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodinglife.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.barcodinglife.org</span>. All sequences have also been deposited in GenBank (Accession nos 
  <span ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="GQ481247" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GQ481247</span> - 
  <span ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="GQ482920" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GQ482920</span>). A complete list of the museum catalog numbers, BOLD process identification numbers, and GenBank accession numbers for each specimen analyzed is included in Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We supplemented the data gathered in this study with sequences from North American congeners (accessible from the "Birds of North America - Phase II" project folder at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.barcodinglife.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.barcodinglife.org</span>) to examine divergences within transcontinental species and between sister species pairs. This added 849 sequences from 227 species, of which 66 species were shared with the Palearctic dataset. A list of BOLD process identification numbers and GenBank accession numbers for these sequences are listed in the Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2" href="#S2">2</a>. In total, 2,523 sequences from 559 species were included in the analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
