<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species boundaries in Palearctic Birds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Divergence levels between closely related species were highly variable, ranging from approximately 0-16%; however, some of these values may be inflated for under-sampled genera and families. Recent studies have detached rate variation in the mitochondrial genome from factors such as population size, body size, and other life-history traits [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B52" href="#B52">52</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">54</a>]. While some authors contend that rate variation in birds is highly irregular [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>], a recent thorough review demonstrated relatively minor variation and upheld the occurrence of clock-like evolution [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. Consequently, we attribute the limited divergence between some sister species to recent speciation events. Studies documenting recent and rapid diversifications often address subspecific variants rather than full species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B56" href="#B56">56</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B57" href="#B57">57</a>]. Still, low sequence divergence does not necessarily indicate that species should be synonymised [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B58" href="#B58">58</a>]. Low sequence divergence is particularly common in superspecies complexes, including those divided between continents, but the species within them remain valid units for both ecological studies and conservation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four species pairs and the large white-headed gulls included in this study featured virtually no variation for COI and could not be distinguished using any of the approaches employed in this study. Low divergence in mitochondrial markers had been previously demonstrated in each of these cases. Lumping has been considered for some, including 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis flammea/hornemanni </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B59" href="#B59">59</a>] and the recently split 
  <span class="italic">Gallinago gallinago/delicata </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>], but more evidence is required. The cause of shared mitochondrial haplotypes between 
  <span class="italic">Cuculus canorus </span>and 
  <span class="italic">C. optatus </span>has not been resolved (hybrids have never been documented [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">60</a>]), but their taxonomic distinction has been asserted based on song differences [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B61" href="#B61">61</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella </span>and 
  <span class="italic">E. leucocephalos </span>are exceptionally interesting in that they are the most phenotypically distinct of these pairs and a survey of nuclear markers revealed genetic divergence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>]. They are known to hybridize extensively and introgression is a likely explanation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>]. Species boundaries in the large white-headed gulls may have also been confused by contemporary hybridization, though shallow history and slowed rates of evolution have also been implicated [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">63</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B64" href="#B64">64</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nearly one tenth of the species (7.5%) analyzed in this study contained divergent mitochondrial lineages, with divergences averaging 3.6%. While divergence at a single mitochondrial gene alone is insufficient evidence to define new species boundaries, it is cause for new hypothesis testing. Several recently split species that are morphologically similar to their nearest relative, such as the swallow 
  <span class="italic">Riparia diluta </span>and the warbler 
  <span class="italic">Locustella amnicola</span>, represent taxa that barcodes would flag for closer scrutiny. Distributions of most of the divergent lineages in this study conform to one of four previously documented phylogeographic trends (summarized in Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>): a unique lineage in the Caucasus region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>]; a unique lineage in the Sakhalin region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>]; divergent lineages divided into eastern and western populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">25</a>]; divergent lineages on either side of the Bering Strait [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>]. Species with multiple lineages can display more than one of these patterns. A few lineages appear to be parapatric, which could indicate areas of overlap or hybrid zones [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B67" href="#B67">67</a>]. Past climate change and its effect on historical habitat distribution is likely responsible for shaping patterns of genetic divergence in modern populations, but whether or not these populations were divided by the same historical events is difficult to determine without dating divergence times. While the COI sequences mostly appear to be evolving in a clocklike fashion, dating is risky given the absence of adequate calibration points and the reliance on various assumptions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most species exhibited surprisingly limited variation between Old World and New World populations. Of the approximately 140 species with Holarctic distributions, 43% are represented in this study. Only 11 of these 61 species (18%) possessed intraspecific divergences great enough to signal likely species-level differences by either the NJ or MOTU method. The Bering Sea has served a variable but clear role as a barrier to gene flow for birds, particularly non-marine species. Several trans-Beringian species have already been split in recent years, due partly to molecular evidence (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Brachyramphus marmoratus/B. perdix </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Picoides tridactylus/P. dorsalis </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Pica pica/P. hudsoni </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>]). Still, caution must be exercised when identifying species boundaries between allopatric populations. For example, one of the Palearctic 
  <span class="italic">Lanius excubitor </span>specimens from this study appears to belong to the North American clade, suggesting that some modern exchange might occur between the continents. Though it is more common for Palearctic species to invade the Nearctic, the reverse pattern has also been observed [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>]. Correct interpretation of this result requires further study with additional specimens.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This survey has identified a number of species that demand further taxonomic scrutiny (see Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>). It is likely that some of the divergent lineages identified here represent distinct species. Of course, genetic distances do not always correspond to species limits [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>]. Alternative explanations for the divergent lineages observed include historical phylogeographic isolation, female-restricted dispersal, or male-biased gene flow [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]. The common phylogeographic patterns observed in many of the divergent lineages support the idea of historical isolation. Areas of secondary contact must be further studied to evaluate the gene flow between lineages [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">70</a>]. In a few exceptional cases genetic lineages appear largely sympatric, including within 
  <span class="italic">Alauda arvensis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Delichon dasypus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</span>. Nuclear copies of mitochondrial sequences (numts) are an unlikely explanation given the absence of stop codons and heterozygous peaks. 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus </span>was also noted by Johnsen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B29" href="#B29">29</a>], who attributed the aberrant phylogeographic pattern to admixture of historically separated lineages. This situation is paradoxical compared to suspected introgressed genomes used to explain limited divergence in sister species. Selective sweeps are frequently invoked to explain the limited variation observed in mitochondrial markers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>], which raises the question of how two mtDNA lineages manage to persist in one species but not another. Ongoing research of species limits and evolutionary histories is clearly still necessary in the Palearctic.
 </p>
</sec>
