<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Taken together, the results of the future climate indices analyses indicate that a 2°C global temperature rise above pre-industrial levels will reduce the prevalence of 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tabaci</italic> outdoors in Mediterranean France in July and August as conditions become sub-optimal for survival. The rise in temperature could potentially lead to a greater threat to the UK in the months of June and September and/or a shift northwards in distribution (up to and including southern UK) as conditions in the UK become more favourable. These results differ from previous studies that suggest a northward spread for 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tabaci</italic> across France as a result of future climate change and an increase in its range throughout southern Europe but not northern Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0221057.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0221057.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. However, the Gilioli study ([
 <xref rid="pone.0221057.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]) used a physiologically based population dynamics model to map the potential distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tabaci</italic> in Europe. The population of immatures and adults were constrained with a temperature dependent mortality rate function linked to a development rate function. Although the model outputs correspond closely to the known limits of 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tabaci</italic> distribution outdoors in Europe, by linking mortality to the suitability for development they did not take account of any other factors, such as the influence of cold weather. Furthermore, the climate data used was limited to monthly mean minimum and maximum temperatures with an interpolation routine based on geographical location and the time of sunrise used to derive hourly temperature data. Unlike the current study, which used a suite of climate model projections, the climate change scenario tested was flat (1 and 2°C were added to each hourly temperature).
</p>
