<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Excessive exposure to UV radiation is associated with many negative health effects, including increased skin cancer risk [
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B194-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>,
 <xref rid="B195-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>], eye damage, and suppressed immune function [
 <xref rid="B196-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>], with further deleterious health effects becoming more apparent. In instances of sunburn, skin injury results from penetration of UVB into the dermal and epidermal layers, causing damage to cutaneous blood vessels and eccrine sweat glands [
 <xref rid="B197-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. Mild artificial sunburn appears to attenuate SRs and sensitivity for at least 24 h, with potential for impaired thermoregulatory function if this occurs over a large body surface area [
 <xref rid="B197-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. Greater time spent outdoors by children compared to adults, poor sunscreen habits, and increasing UVB levels increase the likelihood of sunburn in a pediatric population, with potential for thermoregulatory dysfunction. Specific dermal conditions have been shown to impair thermoregulation and reduce heat tolerance [
 <xref rid="B198-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. Evidence is currently limited with regard to sunburn and thermal tolerance, but further studies examining the acute and chronic effects on eccrine sweat gland function and vascular responses are necessary in light of changing environmental conditions. Evidence of UVB-induced alterations in cutaneous vasodilation have recently been reported in adults but, as an important component of the thermoregulatory response, may have relevance for thermoregulation in both children and adults. Children rely more heavily on cutaneous vasodilation and ‘dry’ heat losses for thermoregulation compared to adults, making decrements in this response potentially more problematic. Nitric oxide (NO) is a potent vasodilator, produced from the substrate L-arginine via nitric oxide synthase (NOS) isoforms, and is necessary for full expression of the cutaneous vascular response to both local [
 <xref rid="B199-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>,
 <xref rid="B200-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>,
 <xref rid="B201-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>] and whole-body heating [
 <xref rid="B202-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>]. Recent work by Wolf et al. [
 <xref rid="B203-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>,
 <xref rid="B204-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>] indicates deleterious effects of acute UV radiation exposure on cutaneous microvascular function. Specifically, an acute dose of UVB radiation (300 mJ.cm
 <sup>2</sup>, 75 s) was shown to attenuate NO-dependent vasodilation on the ventral forearm, likely via its putative degradation of 5-methyltetrahydrofolate (5-MTHF) and subsequent reactive oxygen species (ROS) signaling [
 <xref rid="B203-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>]. A further study by this group [
 <xref rid="B204-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>] indicated attenuated NO-dependent skin blood flow responses to a local heating protocol (42 °C) following acute broad spectrum UV radiation exposure (450 mJ.cm
 <sup>−2</sup>, 75 s) versus control (non-exposure). UV radiation-mediated reductions in NO-dependent vasodilation were prevented with application of SPF 50 sunscreen or ‘simulated sweat’. Notably, this was conducted under very acute conditions (60–75 s) in a young, healthy adult population, but consideration must be given to implications in children and adolescents. Children often spend greater time outdoors than adults, and rely more heavily on dry heat losses, shunting a greater proportion of Q to the skin during passive and exercise heat exposure. Whether long-term effects of chronic, repeated UV exposure on cutaneous vascular reactivity translate to meaningful physiological outcomes and compromised thermoregulatory function is currently unknown. As average global temperatures rise and broad spectrum UV radiation exposure increases, in part due to decreasing atmospheric ozone [
 <xref rid="B187-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>], understanding if these factors modulate cutaneous vascular responses, and thus thermoregulation, is certainly warranted.
</p>
