<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P7" class="p">In a previous study, 
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Achakulwisut et al. (2018</xref>, hereafter “A2018”) demonstrated that monthly mean FD concentrations measured at ground-based sites across the Southwest largely covary on interannual time scales between 2000 and 2015, and that this regional behavior is significantly associated with fluctuations in the Standardized Precipitation-Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) aggregated between 1 to 6 months across southwestern North America. The strongest correlations were observed with the 2-month SPEI (SPEI02), which is related to soil moisture at shallow depths (
 <xref rid="R78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vicente-Serrano et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2015</xref>; see 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Figure S1</xref> in the 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">supporting information</xref>). This relationship is consistent with results from wind tunnel and field experiments, including those from arid and semiarid regions, demonstrating that the threshold wind speed increases with soil moisture (e.g., 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chepil, 1956</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ishizuka, 2005</xref>) and that declines in soil moisture can lead to a reduction in protective vegetation cover and soil stability and a slower recovery from disturbance, thereby increasing wind erosion of exposed soil (
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Field et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Munson et al., 2011</xref>). Additionally, dust emissions from agricultural operations have been shown to be closely related to soil moisture conditions (
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Funk et al., 2008</xref>).
</p>
