<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the threats for large mammals in mountainous regions is climate change (Granados &amp; Brodie, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), because mountain regions are sensitive to warming (IPCC 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). It affects animal species by modifying their local habitats (Sexton, McIntyre, Angert, &amp; Rice, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; IPCC (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change), 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Climate change has already altered the future availability of suitable habitats for mountain ungulates such as the wild yak (
 <italic class="italic">Bos mutus</italic>), chiru (
 <italic class="italic">Pantholops hodgsonii</italic>), kiang (
 <italic class="italic">Equus kiang</italic>), Tibetan gazelle (
 <italic class="italic">Procapra picticaudata</italic>), Przewalski's gazelle (
 <italic class="italic">Procapra przewalskii</italic>) (Luo, Jiang, &amp; Tang, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Schaller, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>), and Himalayan musk deer (
 <italic class="italic">Moschus chrysogaster</italic>) (Lamsal, Kumar, Aryal, &amp; Atreya, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Warmer winters have been shown to increase adult survival of Alpine ibex (
 <italic class="italic">Capra ibex</italic>) (Jacobson, Provenzale, von Hardenberg, Bassano, &amp; Festa‐Bianchet, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). Plant phenology changes due to warming caused reduced periods of access to high‐quality forage leading to declines in young recruitment of Alpine ibex and bighorn sheep (
 <italic class="italic">Ovis Canadensis</italic>) (Pettorelli, Pelletier, von Hardenberg, Festa‐Bianchet, &amp; Coté, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Habitats for the giant pandas on mountain ranges at the edge of the Tibetan Plateau have already shown fragmentation due to climate change (Shen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Also, climate change can decrease the abundance of species (Aryal, Brunton, &amp; Raubenheimer, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Thomas, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>), not only because of disappearing habitats (Tamburello, Côté, &amp; Dulvy, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), but also because mountain ungulates and other mammals are especially sensitive to warming temperatures in montane regions (Hansen, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Haynes, Kung, Brandt, Yongping, &amp; Waller, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The harmful effects of climate change for ungulates are of critical importance as large mammals have a lower tolerance for deviation of body core temperature (van Beest &amp; Milner, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Fuller, Mitchell, Maloney, &amp; Hetem, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Jessen, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). Ungulates in southeastern Norway showed suboptimal movement behavior above their critical temperature thresholds in changing climates (van Beest &amp; Milner, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Therefore, it is essential to have a better understanding of how species distributions and habitat use patterns are affected by changing climate regimes in order to inform discussions on potential management options.
</p>
