<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Hole et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) highlighted the need to project future habitat for species affected by climate change in order to aid in conservation and management efforts and identify critical habitats. Environmental niche models (ENMs) are valuable spatial ecological tools to better assess the relationship between species distributions and environmental factors, and understand future steps for species management and policy (Elith &amp; Leathwick, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Salas, Seamster, Boykin, Harings, &amp; Dixon, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Wiens, Seavy, &amp; Jongsomjit, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). In this study, we used niche models (Elith &amp; Leathwick, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Peterson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) to project availability of suitable environmental conditions for argali species using various climate projections derived from general circulation models (GCMs), and postprocessed via application of a simple statistical downscaling method. We contrasted future projected climate envelope suitability results produced from combinations of four GCMs and two greenhouse gas concentration trajectories for two future time periods. Our methodology used five niche models to predict environmental argali habitat suitability in contrast to all other wild sheep habitat climate change studies which used a single modeling technique. To account for the uncertainties of each statistical model and improve predictions of the current distribution of a species (Araújo, Whittaker, Ladle, &amp; Erhard, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Marmion, Parviainen, Luoto, Heikkinen, &amp; Thuiller, 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), we did an ensemble of five ENMs to assess the agreement or disagreement of their predictions. Combining ENMs within an ensemble could add information not shown in one single algorithm (Meller et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34103-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
