<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is strong evidence indicating that the mean body mass of bird populations can change over periods of a few years (Gosler, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Gosler, Greenwood, &amp; Perrins, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Price, Grant, Gibbs, &amp; Boag, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1984</xref>), as well as fluctuating from day to day (Broggi, Koivula, Hohtela, &amp; Orell, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Newton, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1969</xref>). One mechanism responsible for these changes involves the deposition of more body fat in colder weather, as insulation and insurance against reduced and unpredictable food availability (Krams et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Newton, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1969</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>). Another may be the deposition of more fat under conditions of greater disease risk, in order to buffer against reduced foraging efficiency as a result of disease (Speakman, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). However, these benefits come at a cost, because increased mass leads to decreased maneuvrability and therefore increased predation risk (McNamara &amp; Houston, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>). Consequently, birds will maintain smaller fat reserves when predators are abundant than when predators are scare (Lilliendahl, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>). Climate change associated with increasing winter temperatures (Jenkins, Perry, &amp; Prior, 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) may thus be expected to lead to a reduction in body mass in small birds, because the trade‐off between higher body mass to compensate for cold‐weather‐induced starvation and lower body mass to reduce predation risk will shift away from starvation. There is also strong evidence to suggest that both natural selection (Bosse et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) and adaptive phenotypic plasticity (Gosler et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34812-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>) can cause bird phenotypes to change over periods of only a few years.
</p>
