<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Paleomagnetism is an often-used method for the age modelling of lacustrine sediments, especially where measurements of 
 <sup class="sup">14</sup>C are unsuccessful. Radiocarbon dates are limited in Lake Superior, as macrofossils for dating are rarely present, and sediments of gravity and piston cores present in the current study are too old for 
 <sup class="sup">210</sup>Pb dating. Thus, the alignment of paleomagnetic secular variation (PSV) records is the best method for dating Lake Superior sediments
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>. PSV records document regional variations in inclination and declination, which reflect variations in the Earth's magnetic field with time. Ferromagnetic grains (for example, magnetite) align themselves with the local magnetic field during or shortly after deposition, upon consolidation of the sediments the motion of these grains is constrained. Any magnetization acquired by the magnetic grains long after deposition is then removed in the laboratory by alternating field demagnetization at low fields. In contrast, the natural remanent magnetization removed at higher demagnetization fields is assumed to have resulted from burial in the presence of the local magnetic field
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" class="xref">41</xref>. The PSV records from the post-glacial sediments are 10–100 year averages of the regional field, due to a 1–2 cm bioturbation zone present in the top portions of Lake Superior sediments
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" class="xref">38</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" class="xref">39</xref>. By correlating PSV records from Superior with PSV records from regional, well-dated sites (small lakes in the region), ages can be assigned to sediment cores
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>. natural remanent magnetization, providing inclination and declination data for correlative purposes, was completed in 2004 at Michigan Technological University—Earth Magnetism Laboratory under the direction of Dr Suzanne Beske-Diehl for piston core BH02-10P (Split Rock—SR) and by Dr Julie Bowles at the Institute for Rock Magnetism at the University of Minnesota for the piston cores BH09K-SUP09 (Keweenaw—KW) in 2009 and BH11IR-SUP11 (Isle Royale—IR) in 2012. PSV data for the three piston cores were compared to a previously dated core, LU83-8 (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref>). Site-specific age–depth profiles for each of the three piston cores were completed using LU83-8 ages and associated PSV features
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" class="xref">43</xref> (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Tables 3–5</xref>). For this study only features and associated ages of inclination were used in constructing the final age–depth model (regression line), due to the lack of features observable/present in the PSV declination data. Ages of inclination features apparent in each of the cores are presented as calibrated years before 1950. Correlative features for each of the three cores are listed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Tables 3–5</xref> and shown in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>. The equation of the regression line (linear in SR and KW and fifth degree polynomial in IR) from the resulting plot of age versus depth from correlation with the previously dated core LU83-8 was then applied along the length of each of the cores providing the final age-depth assignments. Small amounts of Mazama ash, which is dated at 7700, cal YBP
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref> were identified in the Isle Royale and Keweenaw piston cores
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref>, and included in the age models (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>).
</p>
