<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Integrated climate change impact of Nr in China</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the national scale, anthropogenic Nr in China's ecosystem has a cooling effect on a GTP
  <sub>20</sub> basis in theory (−100 ± 414 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e) and a warming effect (322 ± 163 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e) on a GTP
  <sub>100</sub> basis (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S7</a>). However, the uncertainty of GTP
  <sub>20</sub> is so large that it is hard to conclude whether Nr causes cooling or warming in practice. The uncertainty is largely caused by the climate effects of atmospheric Nr. The collective climate-change impact of gaseous Nr emissions is cooling (in theory) at −50±328 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e on a GTP
  <sub>20</sub> basis but warming at 408±112 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e on a GTP
  <sub>100</sub> basis, respectively, while the climate-change impact of Nr addition into the terrestrial ecosystem is cooling at −50 ± 86 and −86 ± 51 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e, respectively. The climate forcers of these two components offset each other through the Nr flows and exchanges between the atmosphere and the land.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative contributions of agriculture and industry sectors are illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4</a>. The overall impact of industrial Nr is cooling (−287 ± 306 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e) on a GTP
  <sub>20</sub> basis but converts to warming (136 ± 107 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e) on a GTP
  <sub>100</sub> basis. The reason is that the cooling effects are largely from the short-lived agency, i.e., NO
  <sub>x</sub> emissions from fuel combustion. The effect of agriculture Nr is dominated by the long-lived effect of N
  <sub>2</sub>O emissions. As a result, agriculture shows a net warming effect and a minor difference at two timescales, at 187 ± 108 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e on a GTP
  <sub>20</sub> basis and 186 ± 56 Tg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e on a GTP
  <sub>100</sub> basis, respectively. The climate effects of Nr from agricultural and industrial sources cancel each other out on a GTP
  <sub>20</sub> basis, but together contribute to warming effect on a GTP
  <sub>100</sub> basis.
 </p>
</sec>
