<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Past literature has evidenced that insects have important effects in the nutritional history of Africa, Asia, and Latin America [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], such as the Yukpa people in Colombia and Venezuela who use certain insects in their meat dishes. There are also studies exploring 
 <italic class="italic">zonocerus variegatus</italic>, bee larvae, and pupae in southern Nigeria, which are all rich in protein [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Researchers have shown that insects are a good source of protein and micronutrients [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Zielińska, Baraniak, Karaś, Rybczyńska, and Jakubczyk [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] pointed out that insects have high levels of monounsaturated fatty acids and polyunsaturated fatty acids, which satisfy human requirements for amino acids. Moreover, Poma, Cuykx, Amato, Calaprice, Focant, and Covaci [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] noted that compared to common animal products (meats, fish, eggs), insects (locusts) can even serve as a replacement for common proteins. That study encouraged the consumption of insect foods. Existing literature refers to insect foods as insect-based food [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], insect food [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], and insects as food [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. This indicates that insect foods do not yet have a standard name, although a global population of 2 billion people considers insects a part of their traditional diet and more than 1900 types of insects are used by humans for food [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. In remote rural and biodiversity-rich tropical countries, insects have been an important source of protein and micronutrients for thousands of years [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], with the world’s most common edible insects accounting for 31% of beetles, followed by caterpillars, bees, wasps, ants, etc. [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. In Europe, edible insect foods are relatively novel foods [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], and companies already sell edible insect products, such as the French company Micronutris, which sells the cricket 
 <italic class="italic">sigillatus</italic>, tablette-tenebrio’s chocolate, aldente-aenebrio pasta and crackers, etc., [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] while Finnish chain bakery Fazer sells ‘Fazer Cricket Bread’ made from glutinous flour [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Not only that, the European Union’s non-profit organization, IPIFF (International Platform for Insects as Food and Feed, IPIFF), promotes the use of insects and insect-derived products as a source of human consumption and animal feed, and believes that it can be cultured with fewer resources (such as land, water, feed, energy), while generating lower greenhouse gas emissions and pollutants. It is likely to be the most common source of protein for aquaculture and livestock animals, and it is believed that insect proteins will become a generally accepted dietary component of Western society. Not only Western countries however, as palm weevil and cricket have also been cultivated on a commercial scale in Thailand [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], and similar commercial farming models are being developed in Africa [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. In Taiwan, although it started late, there is an ecological rehabilitation of the Fuyang enterprises that have both green energy and alternative food. In Europe, foods such as insect flour and insect crackers exist. In Asia, Thailand has a well-developed insect-eating culture, and insect dishes including fried silkworm pupae and fried crickets are eaten in Taiwan. This study’s discussion on this topic means that insect foods, as food products which have insect ingredients, are on the market and can be presented in any form. For example: cricket biscuits, cricket bread, fried insects (such as grasshoppers, pupae, meal-worms) and so on.
</p>
