<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our modeling study uses an analog-based approach; i.e., for each day in the past a westerly jet position is modeled (using the insolation-westerly position relationship see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>) and then a certain ensemble of analog days is identified using the NCEP/NCAR reanalysis dataset. As this dataset has been explored in many climatological studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> we can speculate on past circulation patterns and teleconnections by making inferences using the modern pattern as an analog.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observational record from recent decades indicates that reorientation of the westerly jet stream (together with associated changes in the precipitation pattern) tend to occur in years when the North Pacific is relatively warm and when the tropical Pacific and the Indian Ocean are relatively cool, such as during the decay period of a La Niña event
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. The weak zonal insolation gradient during the early Holocene compared to the present gradient correlates with a weaker zonal sea-surface temperature gradient than at present
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. This may have resulted in the regular occurrence of broad-scale circulation patterns resembling those of a La Niña event over the northern Pacific and adjacent Asian land mass during the early Holocene (or at least a more frequent occurrence of such patterns during the early Holocene than during the middle and late Holocene). However, clear proxy evidence for such an inference is lacking. Furthermore, simulation with an ESM has indicated that remnants of the Laurentide Ice Shield may have intensified the wave structure of the westerly jet stream
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, thus leading to a marked reorientation of the axis of the westerly jet stream in eastern Asia and the resulting pattern of precipitation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results also suggest that the Holocene decline in Northern Hemisphere summer insolation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> caused a southeastward shift in the axis of the westerly jet stream (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), thereby relocating the rain band across the Beijing area, which is likely to have caused the mid-Holocene precipitation maximum in that area. By analogy with modern climate records, a longer retention of the westerly jet stream in a transitional position during the summer may result from a frequent development of strong El-Niño events and the associated increase in the sea-surface temperature gradient between the mid-latitudes and the tropical Pacific
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This interpretation is in accordance with proxy data, which indicate an increase in the El-Niño–Southern Oscillation (ENSO) variability between the middle and late Holocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, as has also been supported by modeling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Previous modeling has indicated a connection between the ENSO and the EASM over long time-scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, and the ENSO may ultimately be attributable to intensified African and Asian monsoons and broad-scale orbitally induced east–west circulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>, illustrating the complexity of the eastern hemisphere circulation system. Although our study may provide some hints that low–mid-latitude teleconnections in the eastern hemisphere are rather stable across time-scales it was not set up to prove these teleconnections. There is still much controversy about the Holocene ENSO development, but our study can signal future research directions on the ENSO-EASM relationships.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The consistent spatiotemporal precipitation pattern revealed by our empirical and minimal modeling approaches contradicts results obtained for the Holocene from simulations using ESMs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. Our minimal model is based on the relationship between modern insolation and broad-scale wind fields. The position, orientation, and speed of the westerly jet depend largely on the broad-scale atmospheric temperature pattern. Both are represented well in reanalysis data. Precipitation is inferred from observational data and not taken from the reanalysis. Our simple analog-based simulation appears to reproduce better the proxy-inferred Holocene precipitation trends and quantitative precipitation anomalies than ESMs of far greater complexity. This is because the same mesoscale processes that control the present-day seasonal relationships between the position and orientation of the westerly jet stream and monsoonal precipitation patterns are also likely to have been responsible for the Holocene precipitation pattern. Most of the processes related to the formation of clouds and rainfall work on a subgrid-scale in ESMs and are parameterized. For example, wave activity within the jet (e.g., mesoscalic wave disturbances) causes the small-scale strong air uplift that leads to cloud formation and eventually to precipitation. Surprisingly, retaining these mesoscale relationships appears to be more important for simulating EASM precipitation changes than an accurate representation of broad-scale long-term variability in insolation-driven ocean–atmosphere interactions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been shown that increasing the accuracy of the representation of mesoscale processes in models used to predict precipitation changes in China over the next few decades can even produce a reversal in regional precipitation trends
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Achieving an improved representation of the mesoscale circulation processes involved in interactions between the EASM and the westerly jet stream is therefore of utmost importance for a reliable prediction of future precipitation levels in Asia. Pollen-and model-based precipitation reconstructions from this study could be used to validate paleoclimate simulations from such a new generation of models.
 </p>
</sec>
