<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rainfall patterns as inferred from a minimal empirical model</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modern wind records indicate that the typical zonal orientation of the westerly jet-stream axis regularly changes to a southwest/northeast orientation over eastern Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This results in an extreme northerly position for the westerly jet stream, placing it over northeastern China and eastern Mongolia, which is reflected by a characteristic precipitation surplus on the eastern part of the Tibetan Plateau and by a precipitation deficit in northern and north-central China
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We, therefore, hypothesize that contrasting regional moisture patterns, as depicted by the three clusters of pollen-based moisture trends, result from a change in orientation and/or zonal displacement of the westerly jet stream in summer due to a hemisphere-wide reorganization of atmospheric circulation as a result of orbitally driven insolation changes.</p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test this hypothesis we established a minimal empirical model (see the Methods section) that relies solely on the modern relationship between insolation, the position of the westerly jet stream, and precipitation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). A similar model was used successfully to simulate temperature changes on astronomical time-scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. The model estimates empirical transfer functions between daily insolation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> and the daily position of the westerly jet stream (within the 100–120°E corridor)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a, b</a>). Applying these transfer functions to the long-term insolation curve allows us to model past positions of the westerly jet stream. Past precipitation is then estimated for each paleowind position through comparisons with the precipitation patterns of modern analogs (from daily APHRODITE precipitation data covering the 1950–2007 period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modern relationship between insolation and the position of the westerly jet stream, and modeled Holocene winds: 
     <span class="bold">a</span> relationship between the daily climatological position of the westerly jet stream and daily insolation levels (black), and the fitted second-order polynomial (blue); 
     <span class="bold">b</span> observed (black) and predicted (blue) annual cycles in the position of the westerly jet stream; 
     <span class="bold">c</span> modeled 250 hPa wind for 2 ka (black) and 9 ka (red) on the day of the year when the westerly wind stream reached its most northerly position, indicating the position and orientation of the westerly jet stream during the early Holocene compared with the late Holocene (for version with wind vectors see Supplementary Fig. 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9866_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e898" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of the fact that our minimal empirical model contains only those nonlinearities and feedbacks represented in the observed climate of the last few decades and ignores potential changes in the past moisture source, the similarity of the reconstructions is impressive. The simulated temporal trends (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1g–i</a>) and spatial patterns obtained for precipitation following cluster analysis (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1j–l</a>) are mostly in good accordance with those from the pollen-based precipitation reconstructions, including an increase in precipitation during the Holocene in southern China, a band of records with a mid-Holocene maximum that extends from the southeastern Tibetan Plateau via north-central China to northeastern China, and a widespread reduction in precipitation in most of western China and Yunnan Province. This visual inspection is also confirmed by correlation analyses between observed and simulated precipitation time-series. The mean correlation of the raw records (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 101) with the model results is 0.11 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01). We assume that the low (yet significant) correlation is caused by spatial shifts between the exact location of the trends in the simulated and reconstructed trends (e.g., the northward shift of the decreasing cluster in southern China in the simulation). It could also originate from a number of low-resolution and thus noisy records. This is indicated by a mean correlation of the spatially and temporally smoothed records results of 
  <span class="italic">R</span> = 0.35 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01) when accounting for the low-resolution records by calculating the weighted mean of the correlations with the number of observations per record as weight.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing selected high-resolution proxy-records with corresponding regional results from the minimal empirical model indicates agreement not only with respect to the major trends in precipitation but also, in most cases, with respect to the magnitude of the changes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). For example, a long-lasting mid-Holocene precipitation maximum of ~100 mm above the average precipitation values in both the early and late Holocene was indicated for the Lake Gonghai record (north-central China) by both approaches. However, model-inferred anomalies from a number of sites are smaller than those in the pollen-based reconstruction. This may be due to the impact of long-term feedback mechanisms (e.g., slow vegetation and soil response to precipitation change) that in the past enhanced the sensitivity of precipitation to variations in insolation, but which are not reflected in modern climatological observations and are therefore not taken into account in our minimal empirical model.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Reconstructed and simulated precipitation of selected sites in China and Mongolia. Pollen-based reconstructions of annual precipitation (mm/year; black circles are original data points, red lines is loess smoothed values (span: 0.5, left scale) compared to simulated precipitation anomalies (mm/year, blue lines, right scale) using a minimal empirical model of selected sites. Correlation coefficient and 
     <span class="italic">p</span>-values are indicated (i.e., between loess-smoothed reconstructions and simulated time-series from the respective grid-cell). Central map shows the locations of the sites: only sites that had a sufficiently high-resolution and a reliable age model were selected (see Supplementary Table 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a> for further details). (Note axes are not on the same scale.)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9866_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e939" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the early Holocene our minimal empirical model simulates a southwest to northeast orientation of the westerly jet stream, extending from the Tarim Basin in northwest China to eastern Mongolia (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) and resulting in dry surface conditions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1f</a>). The main summer rain band of the EASM, which is always located to the south of the westerly jet stream
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, is responsible for the reconstructed early-Holocene moisture maximum in the northeastern part of the Tibetan Plateau (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>,  
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). According to the pollen-based reconstructions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>) and in contrast to the modeled results (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1j</a>), the rain band did not extend any further to the northeast of the Tibetan Plateau, possibly because of the weakened jet stream in the northern regions (see reconstructions in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> and modern analog circulation pattern
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>), reflecting the weak meridional temperature gradient in the early Holocene. Dry surface conditions in Mongolia and a weak jet stream are also supported by a dust provenance study from the Japan Sea indicating that dust from the remote Taklamakan desert is reduced relative to dust from the nearby Gobi desert
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. A weak jet stream usually also leads to a weakening of the jet stream-induced adiabatic circulations which may, in turn, reduce the amount of rainfall
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Both pollen-based reconstructions and model-based simulations indicate that the early Holocene was rather dry in most parts of southern China (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c, i</a>) (a conclusion also supported by paleoclimate simulations using ESMs), probably because the EASM traversed the area so rapidly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. Only the most southwesterly part of China (Yunnan Province) received high levels of precipitation, probably carried into the area by an enhanced Indian Summer Monsoon as suggested by analogies to modern circulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> and in accordance with evidence from a proxy synthesis from the Indian monsoon region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Sketch maps of eastern Asia showing the major summer precipitation and circulation characteristics for early, middle, and late Holocene. Original results were derived by applying pollen-based transfer functions to 101 fossil pollen records and using a minimal empirical model based on present-day relationships between insolation, the position of the westerly jet stream, and spatial distribution patterns for precipitation. (EASM—East Asian Summer Monsoon, ISM—Indian Summer Monsoon)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9866_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1017" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite overall agreement, we also observe certain mismatches between proxy-based and model-based results. Most striking is the difference in the reconstructed precipitation levels for the late Holocene in dry land areas of northwestern China and Mongolia. While pollen-based reconstructions indicate late-Holocene precipitation maxima in these areas, the simulation indicates a decrease since the mid-Holocene. This mismatch likely originates with the pollen-based reconstructions. As has been speculated before, in dry areas pollen assemblages may rather reflect precipitation-to-evaporation (PE) ratios than precipitation alone
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. But additionally, the predictive strength of our model is likely to be less outside the transition area of the monsoonal rain band, such as the northwestern-most part of the study area (in accordance with results of model evaluation), because processes other than westerly-monsoon interactions dominate precipitation generation there.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Site-to-site mismatches may also originate from local or site-specific peculiarities of some of the pollen archives, which can distort the regional-scale representativeness of the respective pollen record because of variations in, for example, the pollen source area and human impact on vegetation.</p>
</sec>
