<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most proxy records suggest that the LGM was colder and drier than today. The reduction in moisture is, for instance, clearly documented by increased percentages of semi-desert taxa (
 <italic>Artemisia</italic>, 
 <italic>Chenopodiaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Ephedra distachya</italic>) and steppe vs. forest vegetation in pollen records of Padul [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] and the Alborán Sea (MD95-2043 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]; ODP976 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]). Dry climatic conditions may also be deduced from the formation of clay dunes in the Manchega Plain, dated to the time frame between 18 and 28 ka [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Pollen records of core MD95-2042 retrieved from the Iberian shelf off southern Portugal suggest that the LGM was less cold and dry than the end of MIS3 or than stadial periods correlating with Heinrich Stadials [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. However, high percentages of 
 <italic>Ericaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Pinus</italic> point to relatively humid conditions not necessarily dryer than today. The d
 <sup>18</sup>O-speleothem record of Eagle cave, located in Central Iberia, suggests that the LGM was drier than the end of MIS3, when Iberian glaciers reached their maximum extent [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The same record shows peaks in less negative values, indicating aridity during HS 2 and HS 3. Global climate models included in the Palaeoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project (PMIP3) simulate higher precipitation for the LGM than for the pre-industrial period in the Western Mediterranean, as explained by southward migration of the North Atlantic Jetstream and related storm tracks [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, very limited evidence for this positive anomaly is found in palaeoclimate archives, and the notion of dryer and colder conditions than today appear to be more likely, according to the present state of knowledge.
</p>
