<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The direct and indirect health impacts of climate change and climate-sensitive disasters are a growing concern for human health [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The health impacts pathways of both climate-sensitive disasters and climate change have numerous commonalities [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>] suggesting the potential for synergist and complementary actions. However, the commonalities between these pathways have not previously been discussed. Considering climate-sensitive disasters in terms of their risk components (hazard, vulnerability, exposure and adaptive capacity) enables clear identification of the commonalities in the health impact pathways of disasters and climate change, where climate change is understood as a driver of hazard frequency and intensity. The framework presented here identifies climate change as a risk driver for many hydrological, climatological, biological and meteorological hazards. These climate-sensitive hazards have the potential to directly and indirectly impact health. They also have the potential to develop into disasters through interactions with various degrees of a community’s exposure, vulnerability and adaptive capacity. Subsequently, these disasters also directly and indirectly impact health. 
</p>
