<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p"> Climate change will affect people differently according to their cultural, economic, environmental and social context. A number of studies raise the need to recognize the importance of social differentiation as a crucial determinant of vulnerability (Adger and Kelly 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1999</xref>; O’Brien et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2007</xref>; Ribot 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2010</xref>, Tschakert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">2012</xref>). The integration of a social science perspective in climate change occurs slowly and the feminist research perspective on climate change occurs even more slowly. Without a “sociology of climate change” (MacGregor 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2010</xref>, p. 137), we will not be able to understand the root causes of the climate crisis and will fail to tackle global warming. People and groups are situated within broader socio-cultural, political and economic relations. Indeed, the capacity to adapt and respond to change is shaped by power relations determining access to resources, information and the availability of options and choices (Tschakert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">2012</xref>; Djoudi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2013</xref>). These factors are related to the social identities and positions of people and groups. Gender is a key element of these identities and relations. Furthermore, vulnerability and adaptive capacity are dynamic in nature, and changes affecting them at one level can have profound and hidden implications at other levels (Pelling 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2010</xref>). Thus, if the root causes of vulnerability are not taken into account, potential solutions might exacerbate rather than reduce existing injustices, while leaving challenges of climate change unaddressed (MacGregor 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2010</xref>). Concerns about women and gender within the climate change literature need to be located within this context.
</p>
