<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="BIO013839F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>
   <span class="bold">Ecological selection forces acting on the body size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span>.
   </span> Open arrows symbolize selection pressures on 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are present, solid arrows when they are absent. Arrow length in each pair indicates presumed relative selection strengths in sympatry and allopatry, respectively. Conditions on the left side act to increase body size and they gain in importance in allopatry on the islands. Those on the right side act to reduce body size and they lose significance on the islands. When 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> takes over the vacant space, which creates a new selection regime. The widened food base permits a higher population density. It probably increases intraspecific, interference competition, which in turn selects for a large body size. And the take-over of foraging sites on the inner parts of branches and on the trunk, normally occupied by 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, gives more opportunity for obtaining food by pecking and tearing, which selects for a large size. In sympatry on the mainland, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> forages mainly in the canopy periphery, which requires high manoeuvrability and is expensive in energy. A low body mass improves manoeuvrability and reduces energy costs for locomotion and, in addition, facilitates access to tight spaces in the canopy periphery. The frequent use of outer branch parts by 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland therefore selects for a small body size. But when 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> exploits the foraging sites of the absentees on the islands, it cuts down on its use of the canopy periphery, which relaxes selection for a small body size. Conflicting selection forces therefore cancel out at a larger body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands than on the mainland where it coexists with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>.
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
