<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although some canonical uncertainties in quantifying future economic impacts are largely removed when focusing on the historical period—such as future discounting uncertainty (e.g., refs. 
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>, and 
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>) and the limits of accounting for future changes that fall well outside of historical experience (
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>)—other uncertainties must be considered.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, uncertainty in the exact magnitude of the temperature optimum creates uncertainty in the sign of the historical climate impact in some countries (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1816020116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>). However, the sign of the impact on inequality is robust (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>), primarily because the mean temperature of so many poor countries lies in the extreme warm tail of uncertainty in the optimum (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). For these countries, it is “very likely” (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>) that historical warming has reduced economic growth and lowered per capita GDP (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1816020116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>). As a result, although uncertainty in the magnitude of the response of regional temperature to historical forcing creates uncertainty in the magnitude of impact at a given decile of the country-level economic distribution (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>), the sign of the impact on the lower deciles (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>)—and therefore on inequality (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>)—is robust.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sign of the inequality impact is also robust to the inclusion of lagged responses (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1816020116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
  </span>). Lagged responses can compensate the growth effects of temperature fluctuations, leading to decreases in both the growth benefit in cool countries and the growth penalty in warm countries (
  <a rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" href="#r4">4</a>). These lagged responses reduce the calculated magnitude and probability of warming-induced increases in economic inequality. However, even with a 5-y lag, there is still 66% likelihood that historical warming has increased country-level inequality.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The availability of socioeconomic data also creates uncertainty. Because growth effects cumulate, the length of time over which economic impacts are evaluated can meaningfully affect results (
  <a rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" href="#r4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>). However, data availability creates an inherent tradeoff between evaluating fewer countries over a longer period and evaluating more countries over a shorter period. We repeat our primary analysis using a larger, shorter sample. Overall, the pattern of impact is robust, but the cumulative magnitude is larger over the longer period (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1816020116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>). This expansion over longer periods suggests that the full impact of warming since the Industrial Revolution has been even greater than the impact calculated over the past half century.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our approach to quantifying the impact of global warming on economic inequality is also limited by its reliance on country-level relationships between temperature and economic growth. Our analysis focuses on country-level data because their wide availability (in both space and time) allows us to use empirical relationships to quantify how historical temperature changes have affected economic outcomes around the world. The impact of climate change on the evolution of within-country inequality is a critical question (e.g., ref. 
  <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>), but would require either strong assumptions about how within-country income distributions respond to aggregate shocks at the country level, or comprehensive subnational data on incomes (which are currently unavailable for most country-years around the world). Although our population weighting provides some indication of global-scale individual-level inequality (
  <a rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" href="#r9">9</a>), documenting the impact of global warming on within-country inequality remains an important challenge.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many countries in our sample have experienced rapid urbanization and economic development for reasons unrelated to climate, and such trends could plausibly alter how economies respond to subsequent climate change. Because past work did not find statistically significant evidence that higher incomes reduce temperature sensitivities (
  <a rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" href="#r4">4</a>), we do not attempt to model this moderating effect here. However, if increasing urbanization or economic development has reduced the temperature sensitivity of economies over our study period, this effect will be implicitly included in our estimated impact of temperature on GDP growth and inequality—that is, we have estimated the effect of temperature on growth for economies that are rapidly urbanizing. Explicitly quantifying the role of these moderating influences is an important avenue for future work, as it will be critical for understanding how future climate change will affect the level and distribution of global income.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trade between countries has likely already influenced the impacts of global warming on population-weighted inequality. First, a large part of the reduction in historical inequality during our sample period has been due to the unprecedented growth in incomes in East Asia [and particularly China (
  <a rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" href="#r9">9</a>, 
  <a rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" href="#r10">10</a>)], much of which was built on critical trading relationships with high-income countries. In a no-trade counterfactual, China would likely grow much less rapidly. Thus, because of China’s large population and small sensitivity to historical warming (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>), repeating our analysis in a no-trade counterfactual would likely result in smaller reductions in per capita GDP in the lower deciles of the population-weighted income distribution (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). However, trade can also serve as a buffer against climate shocks, particularly in poor countries (e.g., ref. 
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>). Thus, the economic impacts of global warming—which has substantially increased the occurrence of extremes (e.g., ref. 
  <a rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" href="#r21">21</a>)—would likely have been even greater in poor countries in a no-trade counterfactual, amplifying the impact on between-country inequality.
 </p>
</sec>
