<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because data for terrestrial bird species are fairly evenly distributed in time through most of the 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> century (see Figure B in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0183051.s001" class="xref">S1 Appendix</xref>), we decided to evaluate temporal changes in the relationship between body mass and year of collection with this group of species. For that purpose, we split the series of each species into two periods of time: one from the earliest date of collection (
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 1915) to 1950, representing a relatively low intensity of change in environmental conditions, and the other from 1951 to the latest date of collection (
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 2013), representing a relatively high intensity of change in environmental conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Note that the increase in globally averaged temperature over the period 1901–2012 was about 0.89°C, while the increase over just the period 1951–2012 was about 0.72°C [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Thus, the rate of change in ambient temperature for our second period (
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 0.12°C per decade) is almost four times greater than for our first period of time (
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 0.03°C per decade). For each species and period of time, we calculated the partial correlation for the year of collection (r
 <sub class="sub">year</sub>) using (absolute) latitude, longitude and sex as covariates in the regression models. Then, we evaluated difference in the mean value of r
 <sub class="sub">year</sub> between both periods of time, using a paired 
 <italic class="italic">t-</italic>test for dependent samples. These analyses were done with Statistica (version 8.0) software, and statistical significance was established at the α = 0.05 level. Finally, to take into account phylogenetic relationships among species, we estimated the relationship between body mass and the year of collection separately for each period of time (i.e., before and after 1950), using phylogenetic generalized linear mixed models (PGLMM) [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], with (absolute) latitude, longitude, and sex as covariates. Then, the significance of each regression coefficient was estimated from Markov chain Monte Carlo p-value (pMCMC). In addition, as in the Bayesian MCMC context it is possible to directly obtain samples of the regression coefficients from the posterior distribution for each period of time, we were able to generate a new distribution from the differences between regression coefficients (iteration by iteration) between both periods (“after 1950” minus “before 1950”). Based on this new (delta) distribution, we evaluated a temporal change in the effect of each factor through the pMCMC value.
</p>
