<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Over time, a new suitable habitat for 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sphenanthera</italic> would be generated while its normally suitable habitat would be lost. To show this change, we expanded the areas around the studied area to generate the future suitable habitat of 
 <italic class="italic">S. sphenanthera</italic>. The highly suitable habitat of 
 <italic class="italic">S. sphenanthera</italic> under the climate change scenarios of SRES-A1B and SRES-A2 was shifted to the north and gradually reduced (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">Figs. 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4</xref>). By the 2020s, the highly suitable habitat area in eastern Gansu would be significantly reduced. The same situation would occur in Shaanxi, Hubei and Henan provinces with habitat fragmentation in the study area (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">Figs. 3A</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">3D</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">3G</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4A</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4D</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4G</xref>). By the 2050s, there would be a highly suitable habitat in the east of Gansu, which is located in the north of the studied area. There was little or almost no highly suitable habitat in Hubei. The highly suitable habitats of 
 <italic class="italic">S. sphenanthera</italic> would continue to reduce in Shaanxi and Henan, with further habitat fragmentation occurring in the study area. In the meantime, outside of the studied area, new highly suitable habitats are likely to appear in northern Gansu, central Shaanxi and central Shanxi (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">Figs. 3B</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">3E</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">3H</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4B</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4E</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4H</xref>). By the 2080s, in the study area, the highly suitable habitat of 
 <italic class="italic">S. sphenanthera</italic> would fall sharply and only a little area in parts of southern Shaanxi and west Henan would remain. However, outside of the study area in northern Gansu, central Shaanxi and central Shanxi, new highly suitable habitat areas would be further expanded, leading to a new distribution area of 
 <italic class="italic">S. sphenanthera</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">Figs. 3C</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">3F</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3" class="xref">3I</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4C</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4F</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">4I</xref>).
</p>
