<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This paper used the global climate data in the fifth report published by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) and the corresponding regional downscaling method to analyze the climate elements in the future (2019–2050). The projected climate change data for the study area in the Loess Plateau from 2019 to 2050 are from the World Climate Research Programmer’s (WCRP) coupled model inter-comparison project phase 5 (CMIP5) multi-model dataset. The multi-model dataset is produced by a simple averaging method based on 21 global climate system models. 
 <xref rid="ijerph-15-02504-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref> lists the basic information of the 21 Global Climate Models (GCM) and the associated institutions. Based on the GCM data, the National Climate Center of China used RegCM4.0 for downscaling and obtained the projected climate data of different scenarios from 2019 to 2050 in the Loess Plateau with a spatial resolution of 0.5°. The projected climate data mainly include daily precipitation, daily mean, maximum and minimum temperature, daily mean relative humidity, daily mean atmospheric pressure, daily mean radiation intensity, and the daily mean wind speed. It must to be noted that CMIP5 divides the future greenhouse gas emission scenarios into four types (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5), and they are called the Representative Concentration Pathway [
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-15-02504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In the four RCP scenarios, RCP4.5 radiative forcing is stable at 4.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. After 2100, the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> equivalent concentration is stable at about 650 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−6</sup> [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-02504" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. In order to limit greenhouse gas emissions, it is necessary for countries worldwide to change their current energy systems and use more electric energy and low-emission energy technologies. Comparatively, the RCP4.5 scenario is a moderate scenario that is always used for future climate change prediction. In this paper, we therefore analyzed the precipitation, potential evapotranspiration, and water suitability on the Loess Plateau based on the RCP4.5 scenario.
</p>
