<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study reveals two little known adverse effects of Hg (primarily MeHg) on the bodies of red-crowned cranes in China’s Zhalong Wetland. First, the prey of these cranes contained measurable levels of T-Hg and MeHg, but the dietary exposure level of this population to Hg was below the Hg toxicity threshold. Second, the Hg concentration levels in the feathers and eggshells of these cranes were significantly high and were correlated with those in their internal organs (i.e., liver, kidneys, and muscles). However, the Hg content in the feces of the water bird was either low or even below the detection limit.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The finding of this study agreed with the conclusion drawn by Eisler [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>] with respect to the bioaccumulation of Hg in the habitat of the red-crowned crane. According to Eisler [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>], Hg is not only bioconcentrated by organisms but also biomagnified through the food chain. Barr [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>] determined that loons laid fewer eggs when the Hg concentrations in their prey averaged 300 to 400 ppb. Furthermore, they did not lay eggs when this average exceeded 400 ppb. In the current study, the Hg contents in all of the prey did not exceed the allowable concentration limit (200 ppb) recommended by Agah et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] and the toxicity threshold concentration (300 ppb) provided by Barr [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. This result suggests that the incidence of Hg in prey does not contribute highly to the diets of water birds (such as red-crowned cranes and other water fowls) in this region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study reveals that MeHg dominates the Hg content in prey tissues and in the bodies of water birds. This finding is consistent with those of many previous researches. According to Burger and Gochfeld [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>] and Evers et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>], muscle tissue provides the protein used to form feathers. Furthermore, the feathers are among the few body compartments in which MeHg can be remobilized. Therefore, the Hg concentrations in feathers during growth can indicate MeHg contamination in the body of the red-crowned crane. In the current study, the T-Hg concentrations in the feathers of the red-crowned crane in Zhalong Wetland were similar to the average Hg concentrations in the Little Egrets of Tai Lake (0.64 ppm) and Poyang Lake (0.41 ppm) in Southern China as well as those of Common Eiders in Aleutian Island (0.98 ppm) and in the Amchitak and Kiska area (0.64 ppm) as reported by Zhang et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>] and Burger et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. However, the concentrations determined by the present study were lower than those in the Little Egrets of Pearl Delta (2.09 ppm) (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) in China.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current study, the increasing Hg content in the feathers of red-crowned cranes demonstrated that crane feathers are prone to Hg contamination, as with the feathers of many other birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. The T-Hg and MeHg concentrations in the feathers of the red-crowned crane exceed those in their internal organ tissues (liver and kidney). This finding contradicts those of many previous researches. This discrepancy is most likely influenced by external contamination (i.e., atmospheric deposition) because exogenous fractions of heavy metals cannot be completely removed by washing alone [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. Therefore, the use of crane feathers as indicators of Hg pollution may be challenged, and further research is recommended.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The T-Hg and MeHg concentrations in the eggshells are strongly correlated with those in the liver and kidney. However, they are not significantly correlated with the concentrations in the muscle. This result agrees with that of Evers et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>], which postulates that MeHg in the muscle contributes only slightly to Hg concentration in the developing egg. Burger et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>] reported that the T-Hg content in eggs normally ranges between 10 and 20 % of that in the liver. In the present study, the eggshells of the red-crowned crane removed Hg from its body, as indicated by the relatively high T-Hg and MeHg concentrations therein. The eggshells of birds such as the Great Tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] and common loon [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] perform a similar function. Given that Chinese law prohibits the intentional killing of wild cranes and the picking of their eggs, the eggshells of these birds can effectively indicate the Hg risk level to the red-crowned crane.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results showed that the T-Hg concentrations in feces were low and that MeHg concentrations therein were below the analytical detection limit. Dauwe et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] determined that the Great Tit could excrete Hg from its body. Hence, its feces can indicate the pollution levels in a metal-contaminated region. Conversely, Leonzio et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] reported that the total Hg and MeHg concentrations in feces are limited. Our results confirm this finding because the feces of the red-crowned crane do not always reflect the contamination status of Hg in its body. Thus, excretions may not be a suitable indicator of Hg risk level.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar to the results reported by Takazawa et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>] and Malik et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>], we determined relatively high Hg contents in the kidney and liver tissues of the red-crowned crane. According to these previous studies, the livers and kidneys of water fowls are prone than other internal organs to the accumulation of many toxic metals, such as Hg. According to Eisler [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>], Hg concentrations that exceed 3 ppm in kidney or liver tissue are presumptive evidence of an environmental Hg problem. In the present study, however, the T-Hg concentrations in the internal organs of the red-crowned crane were below the concentration threshold of Hg toxicity, thereby suggesting that the Hg risk level to the red-crowned crane was low.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The daily Hg intake of the red-crowned crane (39.94 to 48.03 ppb) was significantly lower than the concentration at the sublethal effect level recommended by Eisler [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>] for sensitive aquatic bird species (i.e., 100 to 500 ppb day
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). Hence, we regard the level of dietary exposure of the migratory red-crowned cranes to Hg as safe in China. However, the elevated Hg levels in the buffer zone of Zhalong Wetland and the detectable levels of T-Hg and MeHg in red-crowned cranes should be examined further.
 </p>
</sec>
