<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Common vampire bats (hereafter “vampire bats”, 
 <italic class="italic">Desmodus rotundus</italic>) occur throughout much of South America to northern México [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Vampire bats feed regularly on the blood of mammals and can transmit rabies virus to prey [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], sometimes causing substantial impacts to agricultural economies when rabies virus is transmitted to cattle [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Vampire bats have not yet been documented in recent history in the United States, but have been documented within about 50 km of the U.S. state of Texas (U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) and Méxican Secretariat of Agriculture, Livestock, Rural Development, Fisheries, and Food (SAGARPA); see the data package for this project and methods section). Fossil records indicate that vampire bat species (genus 
 <italic class="italic">Desmodus</italic>) existed in what is now the U.S. previously [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], and these fossil records indicate that now-extinct species of vampire bats were in the U.S. from 30,000 years ago until 5,000 years ago. Fossils of different species of vampire bat have been found in the western U.S. from west Texas to northern California and in the eastern U.S. in Florida and West Virginia [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Fossils of vampire bats have also been found in Cuba and date to the Holocene [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
