<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are limitations in using results from controlled greenhouse experiments to predict nutrient losses in field conditions. We chose to use microcosms with sterilized sand and AM fungal inoculation (together with the addition of microbial communities) to successfully detach the effect of mycorrhizal fungi on leachate properties. Our microcosms resembled Dutch dune grasslands with similar plant community and vegetation density and AM fungal strains that were isolated from the field site. However, the results do not mirror real conditions as there is absence of soil macrofauna, limited rooting depth, and lower number of AM fungal taxa compared to natural communities. The AM fungal strains used are indigenous from the field site, and therefore the ecosystem functions that are provided by decreasing nutrient leaching and maintaining plant diversity can be also attributed to the mycorrhizal communities in the field site. However, it is important to consider that different fungal taxa influence plant nutrient uptake and nutrient leaching properties differently (Köhl &amp; Van der Heijden, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Martínez‐García, Ochoa‐Hueso, Manrique, &amp; Pugnaire, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) and that lower mycorrhizal diversity compared to natural ecosystems may decrease AM fungal multifunctionality; therefore, our results cannot be applied generally to every ecosystem. Moreover, the rainfall scenarios used in this experiment are not representative of climatic predictive models but simulate a general intensification of rainfall based on higher precipitation amount and higher frequency of rainfall events than in the region of our study system. Further field studies assessing how real climate change scenarios impact on ecosystem properties (such as in Martínez‐García, De Dios, &amp; Pugnaire, 
 <xref rid="gcb13785-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) are also needed to predict accurately nutrient losses in ecosystems.
</p>
