<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f4" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Adherens junction (AJ) pathway and 
   <italic class="italic">S. pistillata</italic> +6°C-pH (sty6pH) and 
   <italic class="italic">B. europaea</italic> +12 °C-pH (bala12pH) fold changes.
  </title>
  <p class="p">Fold changes of sty6pH (left) and bala12pH (right) genes are represented by a color scale. A dot stands for an insignificant contig annotation corresponding to each organism and ref. 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref> for an average fold change value of several contig annotations. AJs are mediated through calcium-dependent cadherins linked to the actin cytoskeleton via α-and β-catenins
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" class="xref">49</xref>. Chrodate-like classic cadherins were not observed in the cnidarian 
   <italic class="italic">Nematostella</italic>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" class="xref">49</xref>, as well as in our studied corals, however, the cadherin genes found belong to the protocadherin subfamily of cadherin superfamily. Regulation of AJs can be by α-catenin interactions with actin-associated proteins (Afadin and VCL), via the small GTPase RAC1 and Cdc42
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" class="xref">50</xref>, or alternatively through posttranslational modifications of AJ components. Cadherin-catenin complexes are negatively regulated by tyrosine phosphorylation of β-catenin by receptor tyrosine kinases or cytoplasmic tyrosine kinases; SRC, Fyn and YES1 and positively regulated by casein kinase II (CKII) and protein tyrosine phosphatases (PTPs). Additional regulation is through GTPase-activating protein IQGAP binding to RAC1, which is thought to displace the latter from interacting with β-catenin, thereby freeing β-catenin to interact with α-catenin. Dissociation of β-catenin is likely to render cadherin susceptible to proteasome-mediated degradation or recycling back to the cell surface
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" class="xref">50</xref>. WNT signaling acts as a positive regulator, activating transcription factors by stabilizing β-catenin and promoting its binding to TCF (transcription factor3). Various growth factors, including: HGF, FGF, and TGFβ2, regulate cadherin expression indirectly via transcription factor SNAI2/Slug, which eventually inhibits cadherin expression. Transcriptional activation of β-catenin is stimulated via TGF-beta signaling by enhancing the interaction between CREBB-binding protein and SMAD3
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" class="xref">51</xref>. Adhesion of neighboring cells can also be mediated via NOTCH and DLL1 or nectin, which results in lateral inhibition of cell differentiation and firm adhesion.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="srep42405-f4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
