<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Choice of parameters</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The parameter values used for all of the numerical simulations, which are given in the Source Data file, are within their realistic ranges. The rate of technological growth is around 1.5–2.0% year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in developed countries and is higher in some developing countries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. In turn, the rate of growth in the yield per unit of sustainable harvest, 
  <span class="italic">g</span>
  <sub>f</sub>, depends on the specific natural resource, where values that were considered in the literature vary from 
  <span class="italic">g</span>
  <sub>c</sub> down to much lower (even negative) values
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Next, the value of 0 ≤ 
  <span class="italic">a</span> ≤ 1 (unitless) also depends on the particular system. In a fishery, for example, if non-sustainable harvest would imply catching all the fish and sustainable harvest would imply keeping the fish population size fixed, then 
  <span class="italic">a</span> would be the growth rate of the fish (i.e., 2% year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for large fish and higher rates for smaller fish)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>; In agriculture, sustainable management implies the use of environmentally friendly pest control methods and effective water management, which may result in a comparable crop yield (
  <span class="italic">α</span> ≲ 1), but may be more expensive (
  <span class="italic">λ</span> &gt; 1)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. In turn, the ratio between 
  <span class="italic">c</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) and the direct costs, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>2</sub> (Eq. 
  <a rid="Equ10" ref-type="" href="#Equ10">9</a>), determines the relative portion of 
  <span class="italic">c</span> that is needed per unit of harvest. Specifically, 
  <span class="italic">c</span> (and thus the ratio) is initially small but increases due to technological changes. Also, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>2</sub> may vary with 
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>2</sub> if the cost varies among regions (e.g., if near-shore regions are depleted, the average direct cost of harvest may increase). Next, note that 0 ≤ 
  <span class="italic">μ</span> ≤ 1 (unitless) can be chosen arbitrarily by the policymaker, as it does not affect the harvest strategy and the future value of the natural resource; rather, it determines the currency unit, which, in turn, determines the relative role of the discount and the price in determining the future value of the natural resource. A reasonable choice would be the portion in the basket of goods of the natural resource (e.g., the portion of agricultural products in consumption is ~5% in the United States and is higher in various developing countries), but 
  <span class="italic">μ</span> may be higher if non-market goods are incorporated. Finally, a variety of utility functions that incorporate both 
  <span class="italic">c</span> and 
  <span class="italic">f</span> were suggested in the literature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, including the two that are used here (Eqs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">B2</a>, 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">B10</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, where estimates of 
  <span class="italic">η</span> vary between 1 and 3 (unitless)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, and suggested values for 
  <span class="italic">ρ</span> varies between 0 and 3% (year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
