<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tropical Atlantic capacitor effect</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What induces the early winter atmospheric circulation anomalies long after dissipation of the tropical Pacific signal of ENSO? ENSO charges the tropical Indian Ocean but also the tropical Atlantic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, as observed in early winter of ENSO-decay year (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>). Although the warmer Indian Ocean condition persists from the El Niño peak through September, the tropical Atlantic warming further lingers until early winter (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). To confirm robustness of this persistent warming, we analyse a 10-member simulation of the Pacific Ocean-Global Atmosphere (POGA) pacemaker experiment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> where the tropical Pacific SST anomalies are restored towards observed counterparts. POGA reproduces the tropical Atlantic warming in a comparable magnitude with observations until early winter of ENSO-decay year (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b, c</a>). Furthermore, POGA successfully captures the Siberian high weakening (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>), although Arctic sea-ice increase is not well simulated. A POGA simulation with another model shows that the tropical Atlantic warming is less persistent and the Siberian SLP anomalies are weak
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>, further supporting the key role of the tropical Atlantic warming to the Eurasian anomalies.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Simulated surface climate anomalies in El Niño-decay year. Longitude–time section of sea surface temperature (SST) anomalies over 10°–20°N regressed onto ENSO(–1) in 
     <span class="bold">a</span> HadISST (1958–2015) and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> CESM1 ensemble mean (1958–2013). The time evolution is from January of ENSO-decaying year through June of the subsequent year. Regressed anomalies of 
     <span class="bold">c</span> SST and 
     <span class="bold">d</span> sea level pressure (SLP) in early winter onto ENSO(–1) for CESM1 ensemble mean. Black dotted contours and hatching in 
     <span class="bold">d</span> indicate statistical significance at the 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 level
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11359_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e571" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
