<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">The past few years have seen both an increase in violence as well as an increase in extreme weather events, prompting a continued policy discourse about the potential associations between climate change and security risks. Since 2013, there has been the largest increase in violence and armed conflict since the termination of the Cold War, although there is still evidence of longer term declines in terms of conflict lethality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>]. At the same time, while attribution of any specific weather event to climate change remains challenging, we are observing more events that are consistent with the predicted impacts of climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>]. Even if it is possible to implement stringent climate policies that would limit end of century global warming to 1.5 °C, some effects of climate change, such as sea-level rise, may be irreversible [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>] and the burden of these impacts may be highly unequal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. While there are still important questions about whether, how, and when the physical impacts of climate change may be implicated in armed conflict and violence [see recent papers such as [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>]] as well as possibilities for cooperation [see recent papers such as [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]], the potential extent of the climate impacts on many aspects of human wellbeing continues to prompt both scholarship and policy. As a result, researchers and practitioners have made substantial progress in our understanding of how climatic changes may alter or enhance the propensity for new violence or interact with existing conflicts. More tightly coupling the efforts of the research community with the needs and experience of policymakers could further enhance the development of evidence-based policy to more rapidly and effectively address the challenges presented by climate change and conflict.
</p>
