<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">These evolutions in the climate of the Massif are likely to induce major changes in the dynamics of the snowpack
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, cryosphere
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>, hydrosphere
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup> and biosphere
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. They could lead to major, but complex changes in hydrological regimes, especially in the upper alpine valleys, through changes in the relative contribution of their glacial and nival components
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>. Increased frequency in frost-thawing alternations could also enhance gelifraction, which, together with degradations in the permafrost
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>, could increase rockfall occurrence
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup> in the future. These changes might also force human activities to adapt to such shifts of the isotherms and rain-snow line. Major impact are expected on winter sports, leading ski resorts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup> to higher elevations in parallel with the migration of biomes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup> and environments. Given the narrowness and vulnerability of high mountain environments, this could potentially lead land-use conflicts. Increased anthropogenic pressure on these vulnerable areas has the potential to further perturb their fragile ecosystems, highlighting the need for sustainable development and planning strategies.
</p>
