<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Much of our understanding of likely impacts from climate change in the coming decades comes from climate models. Atmosphere‐Ocean General Circulation Models (AOGCMs)
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">36</xref> use the laws of physics to compute atmospheric, oceanic, and other environmental variables, and represent different processes and interactions in the climate system, at a series of evenly spaced “cells” or unit areas around the globe. Although important tools in our understanding, they are complex and require considerable computational resource to run. For this reason, the cells used by state‐of‐the‐art global climate models typically span a large area in order to reduce the number of calculations required: in turn, the outputs generated are coarse. While these outputs are useful for identifying global and regional trends, we need to adapt them for local use (eg, to assess the likely impacts of climate change in a particular coastal city or tropical community). This is accomplished using “downscaling” methods,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref> which involve using either statistical approaches or a higher resolution model over a limited area to add greater detail.
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref> Unlike short‐term weather forecasts, which are dependent on the initial state of the atmosphere, longer‐term projections from climate models are largely dependent on trajectories of global development and on how fluctuating concentrations of GHGs impact the balance of sunlight absorbed by the Earth and energy radiated back into space. Thus, these longer‐term projections are subject to substantial uncertainty not related to the climate system. In the most recent model simulations, these trajectories are characterized by the representative concentration pathways (RCPs),
 <xref rid="epi412359-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref> a comprehensive dataset of changes to the Earth's energy balance under different possible futures. However, even when models are run with the same RCP, intermodel variability arises due to differences in how models represent processes, leading to different projected future climate states. For this reason, a multimodel ensemble is often used, in which uncertainty is considered to be represented by the spread of model projections.
</p>
