<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Human behaviour is indisputably influenced by religious beliefs and religion (Hulme 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Slimak &amp; Dietz 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). Such behavioural influences include the way in which people perceive and interact with the physical environment. Climate change is widely considered as being ‘the most complex and serious environmental issue that human societies have ever faced’ (O’Brien, St. Clair &amp; Kristoffersen 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>:3). Consensus between scientists and researchers alike is that Africa, with its many developing countries, will be most impacted by this global crisis (Mendelsohn 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Toulmin 
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; UNFCCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Adaptation and mitigation are crucial when it comes to managing the impacts of climate change. However, when it comes to climate change adaptation, a greater focus on the human dimension of climate change than on mitigation strategies is required. As Jenkins (
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>:17) puts it, climate change threatens to ‘disinherit cultures of the concepts and practices that sustain a way of being human’; and therefore, changes in climate are inextricably linked to the social context within which they take place (Lorenzoni et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; O’Brien et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). This allows for the development and implementation of context-specific strategies where a community’s individual climate change issues and needs can be addressed (Richards et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>:113), as part of the social context referred to by Lorenzoni et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>) and O’Brien et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) concerns peoples’ beliefs.
</p>
