<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Overall, we found that species diversity and richness within and next to cushions is lower compared to control areas, indicating net competitive interactions between cushions and other plant species (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34276-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>). Such negative or neutral interactions have been documented in other studies as well (e.g., de Bello et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34276-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Dvorsky et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34276-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Bowman &amp; Swatling‐Holcomb, 
 <xref rid="ece34276-bib-0501" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), but surprised us given that 
 <italic class="italic">Silene</italic> has been shown to increase species percent cover and richness (Bonanomi et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34276-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Although disturbance reduces both species richness and diversity, it has no effect on species interactions, as measured by RII. In undisturbed areas, species richness peaked at middle elevations instead of declining linearly with elevation. We suspect this is due to high levels of biotic competition at low elevations (Supporting Information Table A6 in Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece34276-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>) and high levels of abiotic stress at upper elevations, as well as an intermediate disturbance effect by grazing at middle elevations. Compared to higher elevations, grazing is most intense at lower elevations and reaches intermediate disturbance levels at middle elevations on mountain slopes, likely increasing species richness in these areas. Furthermore, the unnatural elevational tree line in Switzerland, which has been anthropogenically established due to many centuries of land use and grazing, could cause species richness to be highest at middle elevations where the subalpine–alpine ecotone is reached.
</p>
