<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chronology</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use an age of 130.9 ± 1 ka (2σ) for the onset of the Eemian based on correlation to the base of an abrupt warming event recorded in speleothem δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records from the Northern Alps (SCH-5 and HÖL-10; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4i</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This event is inferred to represent the initiation of the interglacial in the Alps, where interglacial conditions were established at latest by ~130 ka
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This age is earlier than the start of the last interglacial when inferred from an abrupt intensification of the Asian Monsoon recorded by speleothem δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records from Sanbao Cave in China
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span> and linked to the North Atlantic warming following the Heinrich Event 11, but coincides, within the chronological uncertainties, with a smaller monsoon intensification event
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Although there will always remain ambiguities in such event-stratigraphic correlations, we have chosen to use the event in the Alpine speleothem records as the starting point for the Eemian in Sokli. This correlation is supported by recent U/Th dating of a stalagmite from the Korallgrottan (Coral Cave) in northern Sweden, indicating deglaciation of central parts of the northern Fennoscandian Ice Sheet and onset of stalagmite growth by 130.17 ± 0.66 ka (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4i</a>) (Personal communication: Frank, N. Institute of Environmental Physics, Heidelberg, Germany). An early deglaciation of the Fennoscandian Ice Sheet is also inferred from a speleothem record from the Okshola cave in Northern Norway
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. The latter record is, however, dated by alpha-spectrometry having a comparatively low chronological precision. We argue that the Sokli site became deglaciated earlier than the Korallgrottan site during the penultimate deglaciation, by analogy to the last deglaciation when the Sokli site is estimated to have become ice free about 1 ka before the Korallgrottan
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. Based on this phasing and the dating from Korallgrottan, we analogously infer that Sokli had been deglaciated at the time of the Alpine warming starting at 130.9 ka. We therefore use this date for the transition into the Eemian at Sokli.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the end of the Eemian we use an age of 117.5 ± 0.5 ka (2σ), based on U/Th dating of several speleothem records from Belgium indicating establishment of cold and dry conditions, suggesting end of interglacial conditions in Northern Europe (Han-9; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4i</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Similarly, a major 3% drop in calcite δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O recorded in a speleothem record from Entrische Kirche cave in Austria
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> indicates a decline in temperatures along with other climatic changes at ca. 118 ka (TKS; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4i</a>). This abrupt cooling is, however, not as prominent in other Alpine speleothem δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. A concurrent end of interglacial temperatures in the high latitude North Atlantic region is further suggested by δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O data from the NGRIP and NEEM ice cores
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4f</a>) that has been linked to a shift in the ocean circulation interpreted from proxy records in a core (MD99-2289) from the eastern Norwegian Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Here, the arrival of ice rafted tephra from Jan Mayen and an abrupt drop in the sediment calcium content suggest that the strong Eemian inflow of Atlantic Water via the Norwegian Atlantic Current came to an end, and that the eastern Norwegian Sea became dominated by Arctic Water. This event may also correlate with a first ice-rafted detritus pulse recorded at the Eirik Drift south of Greenland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. With glacial-like climatic conditions thus established in the eastern Norwegian Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, we find it very unlikely that warmer than present summer temperatures would have prevailed in Northern Fennoscandia. Earlier work on Sokli
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> used a tentative Eemian chronology based on alignment of the pollen-based 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>jul</sub> curve with a SST record from the Norwegian Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. However with the availability of local absolute dating for Northern Fennoscandian deglaciation, this chronology is revised here.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Sokli sequence, the beginning of forest development at the base of pollen Zone II marks the onset of interglacial conditions, while the decline is placed where the boreal forest is replaced by birch forest at the base of pollen Zone VII (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). We thus assign the ages of 130.9 ± 1 ka (2σ) and 117.5 ± 0.5 ka (2σ) to the bases of Zones II and VII, respectively.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the age uncertainties within the Eemian, we model the sediment deposition as a Poisson process (the P_Sequence option) using Oxcal 4.3
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. In the P_Sequence option, the parameter, 
  <span class="italic">k</span>, needs to be specified as it defines the size of each depositional event and therefore how variable and uncertain the sedimentation is. It is possible for Oxcal to estimate the 
  <span class="italic">k</span> by using the variable 
  <span class="italic">k</span> option
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>, however having only two age control points, this is impossible for the Eemian sequence. We therefore apply a 
  <span class="italic">k</span> estimated by the variable 
  <span class="italic">k</span> function from a 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-dated lake sequence deposited in the Sokli basin during the Holocene, showing a moderate variation in deposition rate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. By contrast, deposition during the Eemian appears generally stable, based on the homogenous lithology (diatom gyttja) and the stable sediment pollen concentration (represented by the marker grain fraction; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) which during a period of consistent vegetation structure (boreal forest) suggests a stable sedimentation rate. We therefore regard the age uncertainty estimates of the Eemian Sokli record as conservative. The chronological errors suggested by the age–depth model (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>) are largest in the Mid Eemian, increasing with distance from the tie points, reaching 2σ values of ~1500 a.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The silty ice-lake beds below tie point 1 likely represent a shorter time interval than suggested by a linear extrapolation. Following the later MIS 2 and MIS 4 glaciations at Sokli, the durations of glacio-lacustrine sedimentation are estimated at less than 100 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span> and up to ca. 400 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>. Based on these analogues, we show the glacio-lacustrine section (Zone I) as representing 250 years in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>. In the age–depth modelling the parallel core covering the end of the Eemian is assumed a continuous extension of the main sequence. Some hiatus or overlap is likely, however, there is no clear indication of either in the microfossil content. The assumed continuity is supported by the pollen zonation, which finds no zone boundary at the base of the parallel core, but Zone VI runs from the main sequence into the parallel core.
 </p>
</sec>
