<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vulnerable habitats for ecological and economic species</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We fitted a total of eighteen Bayesian spatial models, corresponding to the eighteen species selected using the ecological or economic criteria (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). All environmental predictors affected species abundance, except for the seabed and slope variables (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). The spatial distribution of the considered species was mainly driven by SSS, Chl-
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentration and distance to the coast (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). Overall, species abundance increased in areas with higher Chl-
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentrations and lower SSS values (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). Contrarily, 
  <span class="italic">Caranx crysos</span> showed a negative relationship with Chl-
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentration (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). The rugosity was also a relevant factor for some species, highlighting the preference that some species, such as 
  <span class="italic">Centropomus</span> spp. and Shark group, have for flat bottoms, while 
  <span class="italic">Lutjanus analis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">jocu</span> preferred more complex seabeds. The SST was relevant only for 
  <span class="italic">Cynoscion</span> spp., whose abundance increased towards warmer waters (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). None of the environmental variables used were able to explain the abundance of 
  <span class="italic">Xiphopenaeus kroyeri</span>, and the best selected model included only the spatial component as a relevant predictor (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, while some species clearly presented preference for deeper areas (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">crysos</span>, 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">analis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">jocu</span>, 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">bonaci</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Ocyurus chrysurus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Scombrid group</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Seriola dumerili</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Tunas group</span>), most were more abundant in shallow waters (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
