<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec020" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Artisanal fisheries</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulations show that the lobster stock has undergone a total biomass depletion of approximately 81% compared to the unfished system (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g003" href="#pone.0212485.g003">3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g005" href="#pone.0212485.g005">5A</a>); although in terms of abundance the drop is 53% (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g005" href="#pone.0212485.g005">Fig 5B</a>). Golden crab presents a similar pattern between abundance and biomass, where the proportional difference in simulated biomass is 4% and observed abundance is less than 1% (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g005" href="#pone.0212485.g005">Fig 5</a>). Juan Fernández morwong shows a reduction in almost 11% of its biomass compared to an unfished ecosystem. The overall effect of artisanal fishing, with the exception of golden crab and spiny lobster, is reflected discreetly in a few functional groups: a decrease of 4% in the abundance of octopus; less than 3% drop for yellowtail amberjack; less than 1% decrease for other crustaceans (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g005" href="#pone.0212485.g005">Fig 5A</a>); and an increase around 3% in mollusc and sea urchin biomass; Moray eels have a small increase of 2% in biomass, which is not reflected in the abundance (which has a reduction of less than 1%).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the artisanal fleet, bait catches are focused on a few functional groups divided in two categories according to the level of fishing impact. First a high impact category composed of the catches of the functional groups: large pelagic fishes, J.F. morwong, moray eels and yellowtail amberjack with average annual catches of 84.5 (+/-5.5), 83.8 (+/-3.9), 63.4 (+/-3.2) and 51.3 (+/-2.9) tonnes respectively (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g006" href="#pone.0212485.g006">Fig 6A</a>). A second category less impacted is composed of small pelagic fishes, small benthic fishes and large benthic fishes that present annual historical catches close to 3 tonnes.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0212485.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0212485.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Summary of the catch distribution for the total bait caught from artisanal fisheries (A)), the total artisanal bycatch (B)) and the industrial bycatch (C)). The upper and lower limits of boxes represent the 25
    <span class="sup">th</span> and the 75
    <span class="sup">th</span> percentile and the middle line the 50
    <span class="sup">th</span> percentile of the data distribution. The whiskers represent the range of the catches.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0212485.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spiny lobster fishery shows the highest levels of bycatch, mainly composed of octopus with an annual average of 5.18 (+/-2.7) tonnes and other crustaceans with 1.91 (+/-0.99) tonnes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g006" href="#pone.0212485.g006">Fig 6B</a>). In addition, there is incidental catch of corals, sea urchins and deposit feeders with average catches of 0.46 (+/-0.24), 0.3 (+/-0.15) and 0.01 (+/-0.003) tonnes annually respectively (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g006" href="#pone.0212485.g006">Fig 6B</a>). For the golden crab fishery, other crustaceans are the main bycatch with an average of 1.08 (+/-0.03) tonnes annually (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g006" href="#pone.0212485.g006">Fig 6B</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
