<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec036" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The JFRE Atlantis model has proven to be beneficial for describing the status of the JFRE commercial and artisanal fisheries. Also, providing insights into the impact on the ecosystem that would be expected to result from changes in fishing pressure (i.e. Artisanal fishery). Industrial fishing is located on the deep seamounts and restricted to larger trawler vessels based out of mainland Chile. Due to concerns about the level of depletion and the rate of recovery, these fisheries have been closed since 2006 for orange roughy and 2012 for alfonsino. This industrial fishing has a fairly localized impact on both target species and bycatch. In the case of alfonsino, it has an important direct effect with a high depletion of the biomass of this species. For the orange roughy stock, no significant depletion of the total biomass was observed. An explanation of this is that the observed drop in catches is due to other factors associated with availability such as alteration of reproductive behavior, reduction of available habitat or strong inter-annual variation of recruitment. Despite this low estimated reduction in total biomass, the recovery towards historical population sizes has been slow due to their life characteristics such as extremely slow growth. As for bycatch, both industrial fisheries present a high level of bycatch and this is associated with sessile or low mobility species such as coral and benthic sharks. Seamount fisheries are characterized by fine resolution intensive fishing activities. While the JFRE model provides valuable general insights, improvements in the spatial resolution of the model to focus on this particular feature would improve the precision of the estimates. Greater temporal detail would also be beneficial but this is difficult when the fishery is only operating for a short time. However, if it does reopen in some of the seamounts that are not protected, then the collection of monitoring data that can be used by the model to provide timely information on ecosystem effects should be considered.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within the JFRE there is a long-term traditional coastal artisanal tightly-knit fishing community that mainly targets spiny lobsters, J.F. Morwong and recently golden crab. This artisanal fishing has a low impact on the ecosystem and is mainly concentrated in the crustaceans fishery. The lobster fishery represents the greatest artisanal fishing effort and has the greatest impact on the ecosystem. This fishery has generated a significant depletion of the large sized lobster stock with a substantial reduction in the total population biomass. Given the current state of the population, it is not advisable to increase fishing effort. An increase would have a negative effect on catches and financial returns from the fishery. In addition, this increase in fishing effort (irrespective of what it does to catches) may pose a significant problem for the traditional fisheries management of this fishery, breaking down socially enforced management structures. In terms of the ecosystem, the model indicates that a decrease in the abundance of large lobsters has generated an increase in the population of sea urchins. Although this increase does not yet seem to be sizeable, it is still advisable to be careful not to lead the ecosystem towards a regime shift. In addition, it was found that a moderate increase in the fishing effort focused on other species of finfish and crustaceans will not have a significant impact on the ecosystem. Moreover, this change could have a positive socio-economic impact as a result of productive diversification.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This ecosystem model can be used strategically for the management of the JFRE fisheries. Since this is the first ecosystem modeling approach for JFRE, it is advisable to perform some updates especially aimed at reducing uncertainty associated with the input information. Updating information on the trophic relationships among the key species that make up the ecosystem is most urgent. In addition, it is necessary to have time series (monitoring) of the abundance of these key species. While there are some aspects that can be improved, added or updated, this model provides a new and more comprehensive approach for analyzing the current and future status of the JFRE. The JFRE Atlantis model is a comprehensive tool that can provide insights, for example, about the sustainability of the ecosystem under different levels of fishing pressure under a climate change scenario, or to establish which are the main drivers of the ecosystem productivity. In other words, this model is a tool that can help the fisheries managers responsible of this vulnerable marine ecosystem understand its dynamics and its core interactions.</p>
</sec>
