<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec030" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystem</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aside from the sharp decline in lobster biomass, the artisanal fishery has an small overall impact on the ecosystem. One reason for this is because, beyond the direct removal of the lobsters, the amount of biomass removed as bycatch or bait by the fishery is very small compared to the total estimated available biomass for the potentially affected functional groups.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of predation, the decrease in lobster biomass did not have a strong impact on the ecosystem. The spiny lobster is an opportunist and generalist group with a wide spectrum of prey [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref085">85</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref086">86</a>], this means that the impact on the prey was not centered only on one item type, which means that the effect of a reduction in lobster biomass is dampened by dispersion over many groups. Species such as sea urchins and molluscs are the most influenced by the abundance and biomass decrease of lobsters (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g005" href="#pone.0212485.g005">Fig 5</a>). In terms of how a decline in spiny lobster biomass influences its predators, the model again suggests it does not have a major impact. According to the simulations this is because the lobster does not represent the main item of any species, and most of its predators are species that can feed on other functional groups. The species that feed on lobster (e.g., large benthic fish, moray eels, octopus and sharks) can focus their effort on capturing other functional groups that are more available when the abundance of lobster is low.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the strong depletion of the large sized spiny lobster due to fishing, a more marked growth of the populations of urchin was expected. The adult lobster has been reported as a key species controlling the abundance of sea urchin populations elsewhere [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref087">87</a>]. Empirical observations in other systems indicates that top-down control of sea urchins by spiny lobster stops the overgrazing effect of the urchins on macroalgae. This mechanism decreases the probability of the creation of barrens of sea urchins avoiding extreme changes in the structure of the ecosystem [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref087">87</a>]. Within the modelled system, although there is an increase in the biomass of sea urchins (3%; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g006" href="#pone.0212485.g006">Fig 6</a>), it is more moderate than expected, based on observations from other ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref087">87</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref088">88</a>]. In JFRE, unlike other ecosystems, moray eels are also one of the main predators of sea urchin, controlling its abundance. Therefore, in the absence of spiny lobster that trophic role is being carried out by the moray eels and may be an ecosystem stabilizer (more details 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s021" href="#pone.0212485.s021">S13</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s022" href="#pone.0212485.s022">S14</a> Figs). The strength of this relationship remains to be verified in the real system, but if it is the case, then a greater decrease in eel abundance and biomass could result in major ecosystem change due to increased sea urchin populations and overgrazing of the macro-algal habitat as seen elsewhere [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref087">87</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref088">88</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another direct means in which fisheries can influence the JFRE is via the bait fishery. There is a two stage bait fishery associated with the capture of crustacean (lobster and golden crab) [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref089">89</a>]. In the first stage capturing pelagic species that are used to catch larger species, which are later used as baits in the crab and lobster fisheries. In the model, this bait fishery is mainly associated with 4 functional groups: i) Large pelagic fishes, and which make up the first-order baits; ii) J.F. morwong; iii) the moray eels; and vi) yellowtail amberjack. These last three make up the baits used in the traps.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the non-trivial levels of catches in the bait-fishery, the model does not report a depletion of the biomass in these functional groups due to the high total biomass levels for these groups. This means that the total bait catch levels are a small proportion of the total biomass for each of these abundant functional groups. The J.F. morwong is the only functional group that shows a biomass reduction, which is mainly explained by: 1) lower overall biomass in comparison to the other functional groups (partly because it is a single species whereas the other groups are composites of several species); 2) the depletion effect corresponds to the cumulative effect of both the bait fishery and the small direct fishery for J.F morwong.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of the moray eel, the stability in the biomass masks a change in abundance. The model indicates that there are fewer but larger eels (i.e. less abundance but a slight increase in biomass). This increase in the biomass of moray eels likely results from the combined effect of:</p>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>An increase in prey biomass, due to the reduction of the predation effect of lobster there is an increase in the availability of several prey that are also part of the diet of moray eels (i.e. sea urchin, other crustaceans and mollusc). This increase in prey results in a larger food supply and therefore an increase in individual body mass, generating larger moray eels.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Reduction in intraspecific competition. The slight reduction in the moray eels abundance due to the bait fishery, reduces the intraspecific competition for food, increasing the effective availability of prey for moray eels.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The baits used for the spiny lobster and golden crab fisheries are composed of species of high trophic level (e.g. large pelagic fishes and yellowtail amberjack) that generally would not be part of the diet of these species or at least not in those quantities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g005" href="#pone.0212485.g005">Fig 5</a>; [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref067">67</a>]). This change in diet may have a seasonal impact increasing the trophic level of these functional groups, but under the current configuration of the model this is not being analyzed. This change in diet (i.e. amount and type of nutrients) would influence the survival and growth of lobster, most likely via a food subsidy [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref090">90</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref091">91</a>] but also with higher energy content prey becoming more available.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The small overall footprint of the bait fishery also masks spatio-temporal heterogeneity. The high level of spatial aggregation of fishing effort in a small area means there is still significant potential for a larger effect in that area [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref090">90</a>]. This is not implicitly represented in the model given its current configuration (uniform fishing mortality) and is something that should be added in future updates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other ways in which fisheries may potentially affect the JFRE is via bycatch. The levels of bycatch reported by the model are similar to those previously estimated for the artisanal fisheries of the archipelago [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref067">67</a>]. While both the modelled crustacean fisheries have similar fishing gear (traps), there is a marked difference in the total amount of bycatch (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g007" href="#pone.0212485.g007">Fig 7</a>). This difference is mainly due to the bathymetric distribution of the species. The lobster fishery operates from 3 to 200 meters [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref089">89</a>] and the golden crab fishery from approximately 300 to 600 meters [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref033">33</a>]. This marked bathymetric division is reflected in the bycatch composition of each fishery, which is characterized by species associated with the respective bathymetric ranges [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref067">67</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly in both cases the amount of bycatch is not sufficient to cause significant or widespread effects; the bycatch of the artisanal fleet in the JFRE appears to affect very few functional groups and does not have an important overall impact on the ecosystem at its current levels.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We should, however, be cautious about this model-based bycatch finding. This is especially relevant for coral bycatch, which is composed of coral species that can live for hundreds of years and whose growth is extremely slow [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref092">92</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref093">93</a>]. The representation of these groups in the model was fairly rudimentary and is unlikely to have captured the true delays involved in this slow growth and maturity. In addition, the model does not differentiate between the two types of coral (deep and shallow), which could further mask the ecological effect of this removal. A more detailed analysis of this effect needs to model both corals separately. Therefore, the removal of corals could have a larger and longer term impact than what is reported by the model.
 </p>
</sec>
