<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">End-to-end models</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address this question, a holistic and integrated perspective is needed. One approach is to integrate the management and assessment of fisheries under an ecosystem’s framework. In the last decade, mainly due to technological advances, new approaches and tools have been developed to explicitly consider the entire exploited marine ecosystem [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref039">39</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref041">41</a>]. Multispecies models that focus on the fishery, its target species and their closest connections in the ecosystem (or their other main drivers) is one valid approach [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref041">41</a>]. However, in this case it was judged insufficient given the spatial and temporal processes that structure the functioning of the ecosystem surrounding the JFRE (e.g. the effect of the eddies on the productivity, larval connectivity). End-to-end models attempt to incorporate all the physical and ecological components of the ecosystem (including the human components), integrating them at different spatial and temporal scales [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref039">39</a>]. These tools provide insights into ecosystem functioning, as well as the impact of human activities [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref039">39</a>]. One of the largest end-to-end modeling platforms operating under a spatial framework is the Atlantis model [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref039">39</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref042">42</a>]. This model has been used for nearly two decades and is regularly being modified and applied to address new questions related to ecosystem functioning, management strategies, climate-change impacts and monitoring [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref043">43</a>]. All these attributes make Atlantis well suited to explore and understand the impact of fishing activity on the vulnerable JFRE. This study aims to evaluate the impact (direct and indirect) of different fisheries on the Juan Fernández Ridge ecosystem by implementing an End-to-End model for this region.
 </p>
</sec>
