<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Main biological processes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Atlantis includes several biological and ecological processes [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref046">46</a>] which are tailored to match the system being modelled. The JFRE model incorporated the following processes:
 </p>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Seasonal Migration</span>: Three functional groups (dolphins, yellowtail amberjack and sea birds) migrate in and out of the model domain.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Spatial distribution and Seasonal variation</span>: Spatial distribution (proportion by area) and its seasonal variation (if appropriate) were used (
    <a rid="pone.0212485.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0212485.t001">Table 1</a>; more details 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s010" href="#pone.0212485.s010">S2</a>–
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s016" href="#pone.0212485.s016">S8</a> Figs and 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s004" href="#pone.0212485.s004">S3</a>–
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s006" href="#pone.0212485.s006">S5</a> Tables).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Diel Vertical migration</span>: The pattern of the diurnal vertical migration through the watercolumn was used for zooplankton (large, medium and small) and for invertebrates such as squid and octopus and for fishes with not strict demersal or pelagic distribution.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Recruitment and larval connectivity</span>: Recruitments were based primarily as a variant of the Beverton-Holt model or a fixed number of offspring per reproducing adult (
    <a rid="pone.0212485.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0212485.t001">Table 1</a>). The spatial distribution of the recruitment (larval connectivity) was based on a biophysical model (as described above; more details 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s019" href="#pone.0212485.s019">S11 Fig</a> and 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0212485.s008" href="#pone.0212485.s008">S7 Table</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Temperature effect on biological processes</span>: The main processes affected by temperature in the JFRE model were physiochemical nutrient cycling, physiological rates, reproduction output, survival and spatial distribution. Details regarding the formulation of these processes can be found in the Atlantis manual [
    <a rid="pone.0212485.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref046">46</a>]. The parameterization of these processes for the Juan Fernandez was based on available literature on the tolerances of species in the system (e.g. the range of temperatures they are observed to inhabit) and from metabolic and ecological studies on similar species from other systems.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
