<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model calibration and metrics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calibration of the model aims to reproduce the observed system trends and the patterns observed in the ecosystem such as catches and abundance of the functional groups. This model calibration was performed in two stages (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g002" href="#pone.0212485.g002">Fig 2</a>):
 </p>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Bringing the model to equilibrium: The biomasses of the functional groups were taken to a state of equilibrium avoiding the extinction or overgrowth of any one group. This included a spin-up simulation of 31 years under a constant fishing pressure with all biomasses remaining within a factor of 2 of their initial biomasses. Subsequently, the biomass and size structures at the end of the simulation were used as the initial condition of the model for all subsequent runs. The hindcast of the model started in 1950.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Fine calibration: A refined calibration based on a pattern oriented approach [
    <a rid="pone.0212485.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref070">70</a>] was used to adjust the outputs of the model to the patterns and time series observed in the ecosystem (i.e. catches and biomass).
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A model skill assessment was carried out to evaluate the performance of the model to reflect the observed trend and magnitude of the observational data for the JFRE. Model efficiency, Reliability index and Pearson correlation between the estimated and observed landings was used to test the model performance as proposed by Olsen et al [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref071">71</a>]. Only the catches of spiny lobster, orange roughy, alfonsino and the abundance of fur seal were used in this assessment as these were the only time series available.
 </p>
</sec>
