<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec034" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Projections</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The future (controlled) increase in fishing appears to be a viable option for all artisanal fisheries in this system, except for the lobster fishery where an increase is detrimental to the lobster population and its catches. For example, a 50% increase in fishing mortality for crustaceans over the current value sees the total removal of lobster dropping below the BAU scenario (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g008" href="#pone.0212485.g008">Fig 8</a>). This reduction can be linked to:
 </p>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The current depletion of the oldest age classes of the population. The current size structure of the population in based on ages below the minimum landing size. This means, that even when there is an increase in fishing mortality, the overall increase in catch will not be significant. This finding is not in conflict with real world observations, where the size structure of the catches are centered on the minimum landing size with few individuals in the larger sizes [
    <a rid="pone.0212485.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref067">67</a>]. Actually, it has been proposed that this is a “recruitment fishery”, where the catches are based on what recruits to the minimum legal size of the fishery each year [
    <a rid="pone.0212485.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref089">89</a>].
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The extra reduction in larger sizes results from the increase in fishing mortality which further diminishes the reproductive potential of the lobster. This reduction of reproductive potential will have a direct impact on the total population recruitment and therefore the future number of lobsters that will enter the fishery. This relationship between reproduction, biological recruitment and fisheries production has been previously demonstrated for other lobster species [
    <a rid="pone.0212485.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref103">103</a>].
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p specific-use="continuation" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While scenarios explicitly exploring spatial dynamics in the system were not considered here, based on the spatial dynamics of the JFRE artisanal fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref038">38</a>], it is likely that an increase in fishing effort and decrease in catch will have negative effects on fisheries management. The historical tenure of discrete fishing spots for each boat (owned by a fisher or family) has been part of the traditional management system and has been identified as the main controller of fishing effort [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref067">67</a>]. Therefore, if the fishing effort is increased (more boats or more fishing capacity), the need for increased fishing grounds will increase the probability of spatial overlap of the territorial footprint of different fisher’s fishing areas. This increase in the probability of overlapping fishing sites increases the risk of conflict, which could endanger the traditional cooperative management of this fishery. Considering all of the above, increasing the fishing effort in spiny lobster, does not seem the most appropriate approach, especially as it leads to:
 </p>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>a reduction in overall catch compared to the BAU scenario (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g008" href="#pone.0212485.g008">Fig 8</a>) and, given the increased effort assumed by the scenario, the reduced catch results in lower CPUE resulting in lower financial returns to the fisher and impacts on the local economy and community;
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>a potential increase in the risk of conflict between fishers, due to the spatial structure of the fishing fleet and the traditional spatial ownership of fishing areas;</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>a significant increase in the amount of bait used which is ultimately lost as waste or as food for other organisms (e.g., smaller lobsters, fish, other crustaceans)—as there is fewer crustaceans to catch even with the higher bait use—and therefore it would be better to use the fish in a more appropriate way (e.g. sell them at the market).</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of the golden crab fishery, this increase in fishing mortality enhances the catches and does not have a very strong impact on the biomass of this group. This means that the stock and the ecosystem could potentially support an increase in fishing mortality of golden crab with minimal apparent risk of having a major impact. Other assessments of this resource estimate that it is an underdeveloped fishery and there have been suggestions of further development of the fishery, as an alternative to the lobster fishery [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref064">64</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the modelled artisanal finfish fishery, despite a 100% increase in the current fishing mortality rate the total reduction of biomass and the catches are lower than the increase of 50% fishing mortality for the crustacean fishery (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g007" href="#pone.0212485.g007">7</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0212485.g008" href="#pone.0212485.g008">8</a>). This is because the main source of fishing mortality for finfish is associated with the crustacean fishery’s bait fishery [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref067">67</a>]. Beyond the bait fishery other fishing pressure is minimal for finfish and therefore the total increase in fishing mortality imposed on finfish by the crustacean’s bait fishery is higher than the increment in the artisanal finfish fishery alone.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of the impact of industrial fisheries, even though the fishery has been closed for several years, the biomass of orange roughy and coral are still below the unfished scenario at the end of the model run. This is because both functional groups continue to recover from the impact of fishing. This slow recovery was expected especially due to the slow growth of these functional groups, which makes it difficult to quickly return to levels of virgin biomass. Coral are species of very low resilience and ability to recover from this type of disturbance [
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref092">92</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0212485.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0212485.ref093">93</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
