<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">ITQs vary in design (e.g., tenure length, rules regarding transferability), which may impact resilience. For example, ITQs have been observed to decrease variability in landings and exploitation rates for multi-species fisheries, but this effect is only present when the ITQ right is durable and secure (Essington et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2012</xref>), namely when rights have an appropriately long tenure. In fact, secure rights have also been shown to provide higher asset values from the fishery (Grainger and Costello 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2011</xref>). It is widely recognized that ITQ fisheries are less likely to experience a collapse in landings or to have excessive overfishing, and they typically lead to better compliance with catch limits compared to the absence of rights (Townsend 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" class="xref">1990</xref>; Worm et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" class="xref">2006</xref>; Costello et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2008</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2010</xref>; Essington et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2012</xref>; Melnychuk et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">2012</xref>; van Putten et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" class="xref">2013</xref>). Well-designed ITQs can lead fishers to support lower TACs (Costello et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2010</xref>), and to avoid short-term resource degradation (Essington et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2012</xref>). Long-term rights can also in some cases promote the conservation of non-target species or habitats (ECR-2). One example is fishers voluntarily retiring bottom longlines known to damage corals (Arnason 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2002</xref>). However, when ITQs are allocated only to target species, there may be little incentive to avoid by-catch of non-target species, and therefore multi-species ITQs have been created to diminish by-catch discards (Costello et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
