<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Upward wave propagation and ozone-dynamics interaction</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand how the stratospheric temperature signals are generated, we investigate the mean vertical transport of momentum by atmospheric waves through the tropopause region (100 hPa) between 45°N and 75°N before the maximum monthly mean polar cap temperature signal in 50 hPa occurs. The vertical component of the Eliassen-Palm (EP) flux vector (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub>) in this region is an indicator for the momentum transported from the troposphere into the stratosphere by planetary waves
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Here, 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> is integrated over the two months preceeding the month showing the maximum temperature signal
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> of each dataset, respectively. Its correlation with the stratospheric temperature is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. In the ERA-Interim reanalysis (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), the ECHAM6 model data (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>) and the ECHAM6-SWIFT model data (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>) clear relations of these two quantities are apparent. In all datasets higher values of 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> are related to higher stratospheric temperatures in the following months. All correlations are statistically significant at the 95% confidence level. Also in ERA-Interim the mean of the distributions of 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> at 100 hPa and temperature at 50 hPa are significantly different at the 95% confidence level when comparing the LICE and HICE conditions. In LICE 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> tends to be higher, indicating an enhanced propagation of planetary waves into the stratosphere. By the momentum deposited this way, the stratospheric circulation is disturbed, resulting in higher temperatures. While the LICE and HICE experiments for ECHAM6 show no statistically significant difference in the mean of these distributions, in the ECHAM6-SWIFT LICE and HICE experiments both, 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> and temperature, are significantly different. In contrast to ECHAM6, ECHAM6-SWIFT is able to simulate a qualitatively improved impact of Arctic sea-ice loss on the stratospheric winter circulation. This suggests that wintertime stratospheric dynamics and its impact on tropospheric wave behaviour
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> can be improved by the implementation of interactive stratospheric ozone chemistry.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Relation between the vertical component of the EP-Flux [10
     <span class="sup">5</span> kg s
     <span class="sup">−2</span>] in winter at 100 hPa between 45°N and 75°N and the polar cap (60°N to 90°N) mean temperature [K] at 50 hPa in the following months with PDFs for ERA-Interim reanalysis data (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), ECHAM6 model simulations (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) and ECHAM6-SWIFT model simulations (
     <span class="bold">c</span>). Bold mean values for the distributions means indicate a statistical significant difference between the LICE and HICE dataset according to a two-sided students t-test.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43823_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e556" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One reason for the improved response is the interaction of propagating planetary waves with the stratospheric polar vortex and its dynamical relation to stratospheric ozone. In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> the vertical component of the EP flux (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub>) at 100 hPa between 45°N and 75°N and its connection to polar-cap stratospheric ozone in the following spring is shown. Momentum is transported through the tropopause to high latitudes where it is deposited. This disturbs the stratospheric polar vortex, leads to warming of the polar cap and to poleward and downward transport of ozone with the amplified residual circulation, resulting in the positive correlation between 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> and ozone
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Linear regression analysis for the ECHAM6-SWIFT HICE and LICE simulations shows that both relations are statistically significant exceeding the 95% confidence level, proving that wave forcing entering the stratosphere in winter impacts the stratospheric ozone volume mixing ratio (VMR) in spring, which impacts stratospheric temperature because of its radiative properties. Lower values of 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> result in lower polar cap temperatures which allows the formation of more Polar Stratospheric Clouds (PSC) leading to activation of chlorine species through heterogeneous reactions. With the return of sunlight this results in chemical destruction of ozone, further steepening the relation between polar cap ozone and 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub>, particularly for low values of 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">z</span>
  </sub> on the left hand side of Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, where the colder conditions allow for more significant chemical ozone losses. Because these mechanisms are ignored when ozone is prescribed, including the interactive ozone scheme SWIFT leads to clear improvements in the dynamical response of the model.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Relation between the vertical component of the EP-Flux [10
     <span class="sup">5</span> kg s
     <span class="sup">−2</span>] in winter at 100 hPa between 45°N and 75°N and the polar cap (60°N to 90°N) mean ozone volume mixing ratio [ppm] at 50 hPa in the following March for ECHAM6-SWIFT.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43823_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e618" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
