<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Species diversity displays distinct large-scale geographic patterns, which in turn are controlled by both historical and contemporary environmental conditions. The European flora provides one of the best-known examples of how current species distributions and richness patterns are strongly affected by not only contemporary climatic conditions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>, but also environmental changes linked to late Quaternary glacial-interglacial climate change
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>. These historical legacies reflect both deep-time extinctions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>, and a more recent impact of Pleistocene glaciations on European environments
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref> and biota
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>. The effects of contemporary environmental conditions on functional diversity (FD – range and variability in the trait composition of a species assemblage or region
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>) have been studied at large spatial scales
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>. However, the relative importance of historical climates in shaping current FD remains mostly unexamined, but see refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref> for efforts in this direction. Such lack of knowledge is astounding, given the importance of FD for ecosystem functioning
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref> and services
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>, in addition to the role of FD as a determinant of how species, communities, and ecosystems respond to changing environmental conditions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>.
</p>
