<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stimuli and Procedure</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stimulus in this experiment was a graph showing annual global temperature, rather than temperature change as in the previous experiment. This was to ease the estimation of global temperature, as estimating average temperature change may be more difficult than estimating average temperature. Specifically, the graph showed the global annual mean surface air temperature in Celsius (°C) from 1880 to 2017 (
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>), generated from estimates based on land and ocean data
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn003" href="#fn003">
   <span class="sup">3</span>
  </a> provided by NASA. The graph was changed from land only to land and ocean to show a more representative view of the annual global temperature over years. The graph subtended 23.4° of visual angle in width (783 pixels) and 13.6° in height (450 pixels), assuming that participants were seated 50 cm from a computer monitor with a resolution of 1920 pixels × 1080 pixels.
 </p>
 <div id="fig4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Experiment 2 Methods. Using the BubbleView technique, the graph on the left was covered by a black mask, and only a small circular area around the mouse was transparent. Participants had to move their mouse to see the graph.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpsyg-10-01541-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As in the previous experiment, participants were randomly assigned to the temperature condition (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 87) or the neutral condition (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 90). To measure participants’ attention, we used a novel online attention-tracking tool called BubbleView (adapted from 
  <a rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref25">Kim et al., 2017</a>). The entire graph, including the x-axis and the y-axis, was covered by a black mask, and only a small circular area around the mouse was transparent where the participant could see the underlying graph (see 
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>). Participants were asked to move their mouse to see the content of the graph. The black mask was the same size as the graph. The transparent circular area subtended 1.2° of visual angle (diameter = 40 pixels). We tracked participants’ mouse location as a proxy for visual attention.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After viewing the graph, participants were asked to estimate the average global temperature (°C) in the temperature condition, or the average value in the neutral condition from 1880 to 2017. They were asked to provide an estimate between 13 and 16 (the bounds of the y-axis). After providing the estimates, participants were presented with a petition to stand with the Nature Conservancy to call on United States leaders to stand strong on climate change, and were asked whether they were willing to sign it. Participants also indicated whether they were willing to donate to Natural Resource Defense Council. The order of the petition and the donation question was random. If participants were willing to sign the pledge, they provided their name and email which were then forwarded to 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://change.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">change.org</span>. If participants were willing to donate, they were asked to indicate the amount of donation (which was only hypothetical). At the end of the experiment, participants in both conditions provided their demographic information and rated their political orientation on the same 11-point scale. As in the previous experiment, we divided participants into a liberal group and a conservative group. In the temperature condition, the mean rating on the political orientation scale was −0.82 (47 liberals and 29 conservatives). In the neutral condition, the mean rating on the political orientation scale was 0.11 (32 liberals and 39 conservatives).
 </p>
</sec>
