<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">While most governments report net emissions from land use based on their national communications to the UNFCCC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>], only 19 countries have delineated managed and unmanaged land areas for their territory based on a review of the latest communications submitted by governments through 2015 and Common Reporting Format (CRF) tables submitted in 2018 (note: CRF tables are only submitted by Annex I parties to the convention) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). There are several reasons that may explain this situation. Approximately 85 out of the 195 member governments are developing economies and still use the Revised 1996 IPCC guidelines for reporting their emissions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>], which is in accordance with UNFCCC reporting requirements for developing countries. The revised 1996 IPCC guidelines pre-date the development of the managed land concept as a proxy to anthropogenic emissions and removals that was introduced in the 2003 IPCC Good Practice Guidance for Land Use, Land-Use Change and Forestry (LULUCF) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>], and incorporated into the 2006 IPCC Guidelines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. The latter documents require full representation of land use in the country, with all land being subdivided into one of the following land-use categories: forest land, cropland, grassland, wetlands, settlements and other land. In addition, forest land, wetlands and grassland must be divided into managed and unmanaged sub-categories, and although there are no GHG reporting requirements for unmanaged lands, countries are encouraged to report their areas. As more developing countries adopt the 2006 IPCC guidelines or even start using the 2003 LULUCF guidance, a complete representation of land use will need to be developed, and countries will have to determine which portions of their territory meet their definition of managed land.
</p>
