<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts on food, social and ceremonial catch potential</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Catch potential was projected to decrease for the majority of species harvested for FSC purposes under both scenarios of climate change across BC’s marine environment (
  <a rid="pone.0145285.s009" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0145285.s009">S6 Table</a>), with the change in relative cumulative catch potential by 2050 showing strong positive correlation with latitude (RCP 2.6: 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span>
  <span class="italic">=</span> 0.744; RCP 8.5: 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span>
  <span class="italic">=</span> 0.876; 
  <a rid="pone.0145285.g003" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0145285.g003">Fig 3</a>). Furthermore, the number of species projected to decline by 2050 under climate change showed a strong negative correlation with latitude (RCP 2.6: 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span>
  <span class="italic">=</span> 0.94; RCP 8.5: 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </span>
  <span class="italic">=</span> 0.95; 
  <a rid="pone.0145285.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0145285.g004">Fig 4</a>). These correlations strengthened for both relationships under the upper range of climate change (i.e., RCP 8.5).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0145285.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0145285.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between latitude and cumulative change in catch potential (%) by 2050 from the baseline (0%) under the lower (RCP 2.6; blue) and upper (RCP 8.5; red) scenarios of climate change.</div>
   <p>Shaded bars represent 95% confidence intervals (data available in Table A in 
    <a rid="pone.0145285.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0145285.s002">S1 Text</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0145285.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0145285.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0145285.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Correlation between latitude and (a) the number of species exhibiting declines in catch potential by 2050 (yellow) and (b) the percentage of the total number of surveyed species in the respective domestic fishing area exhibiting declining abundance by 2050 (blue).</div>
   <p>Declines are exhibited under both the lower (RCP 2.6) and upper (RCP 8.5) scenarios of climate change. Shaded bars represent 95% confidence intervals (data available in Table B in 
    <a rid="pone.0145285.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0145285.s002">S1 Text</a>). 
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0145285.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While relative catch potential increased with latitude, all First Nations’ DFAs included in this analysis were projected to experience cumulative decreases in species abundance and corresponding catch potential, with less severe declines at higher latitudes. DBEM estimates suggested that the southern territories (Tsawwassen, Tla’amin, and Maa-nulth First Nations) will likely be exposed to a reduction in catch potential (between -15.2% and -27.8%) coinciding with both the upper and lower ranges of climate change. In contrast, the northern DFAs (Haida and Tsimshian First Nations) and those situated along the central or north-eastern coasts of Vancouver Island (Heiltsuk and ‘Namgis First Nations, respectively) were projected to experience lower relative reductions in relative catch potential for each territory, with estimates falling between -3.2 and -8.2%.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few trends emerged when comparing changes across latitudes (
  <a rid="pone.0145285.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0145285.g005">Fig 5</a>). For instance, projections for DFAs situated along the North and Central Coasts of British Columbia (Gitga’at and Haida, and Heiltsuk and ‘Namgis, respectively) indicated neutral or positive shifts in catch potential for white sturgeon (
  <span class="italic">Acipenser transmontanus</span>), kelp greenling (
  <span class="italic">Hexagrammos decagrammus</span>), and two species of perch (
  <span class="italic">Rhacochilus vacca</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Brachyistius frenatus</span>) under both scenarios. While varying regionally, both scenarios also suggested either a slight cumulative decline or negligible change in catch potential for clams, rockfish, lingcod, and sculpins across the North and Central Coast DFAs.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0145285.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0145285.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Change in relative catch potential by taxonomic group for each region, ordered from north to south.</div>
   <p>Regions in BC’s marine environment include the North Coast, Haida Gwaii, the Central Coast, the west coast of Vancouver Island (WCVI), and the Strait of Georgia. Projected changes in catch potential under the lower (RCP 2.6; blue) and upper (RCP 8.5; red) scenarios of climate change are denoted. </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0145285.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, territories situated along the west coast of Vancouver Island (WCVI) and the Strait of Georgia tended towards more severe declines across taxonomic groups and species in comparison with those projected for the North and Central Coast regions. The exceptions to this included scallops and eulachon (
  <span class="italic">Thaleichthys pacificus</span>), which displayed more variable trends: for instance, catch potential for eulachon found in the Hecate Strait along the North Coast was projected to exhibit declines similar to those in the WCVI region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Catch potential for Pacific herring (
  <span class="italic">Clupea pallasii</span>) was projected to decrease in all study areas under both climate change scenarios, with DBEM estimates ranging from -26.0 to -49.2%. The results from AquaMaps and Maxent corroborated this projected decline, but offered more conservative estimates (-2.2 to -17.0%). Similarly, declines in salmon, which are cultural keystone species for First Nations on the Pacific Northwest Coast [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref049">49</a>], are anticipated for all regions under both scenarios.
 </p>
</sec>
