<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial trends and regional offsets</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important concern highlighted by this study is the unequal distribution of relative losses in catch potential associated with regional ecological differences and poleward range shifts. In addition to coastwide declines in catch potential that are suggested when viewing cumulative effects on taxonomic groups (e.g., salmon and clams), species-based estimates reveal a stronger differential that correlates with latitude (i.e., impacts are less severe moving polewards).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While there is increasing support for establishing equitable resource sharing agreements between Nations [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref095">95</a>] that might offer opportunities to offset such declines, the means by which such agreements could be achieved are uncertain [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>]. Although appearing feasible in theory, three key issues arise from the prospect of applying these agreements to offset regional impacts: the scale of resource-sharing agreements, the extended time frame, and the requirement of reciprocity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Firstly, resource sharing agreements have both existed and been discussed primarily in a localized context, such as a single river system [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>], rather than at the regional level. For example, reciprocal agreements between First Nations historically allowed for shared use of a harvesting or processing site in exchange for another [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref097">97</a>]. Although such resources sharing agreements could aid in increasing First Nations’ participation in commercial harvests for manila clams and geoducks along the North and Central Coasts, where their abundances are projected to sufficiently increase under climate change so as to offset other regional losses, the cost of travelling to these regions may offset the prospective benefits. Similarly, FSC harvests hinge upon the feasibility of accessing resources locally, making trans-regional trips unlikely to prove viable or desirable.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The remaining two issues of time frame and reciprocity are intertwined, and relate to the circumstances that facilitated resource exchanges. Many of the key traditional institutions that generated considerable adaptive capacity for First Nations primarily supported responses to seasonal or inter-annual fluctuations in resource abundance and availability through reciprocity [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref044">44</a>], or operated as measures to prevent such long-term declines through spatial management [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref098">98</a>], selective fishing [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref099">99</a>], and forms of mariculture [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref100">100</a>], among other strategies. Since reciprocal agreements were intended to provide insurance against future resource scarcity, they inherently pivoted on the exchange of resources or access rights. Given that the scenarios presented in this analysis suggest that all species are likely to exhibit a relative decline in abundance in the southern regions of British Columbia, few arrangements remain where species could be traded or access rights exchanged in accordance with this principle. An exception may occur for commercial fisheries, given the potential increased abundance of warmer-water species (e.g., sardines) that is projected to occur within BC’s waters under climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
