<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Given the uncertainty in scenarios of future climate scenarios, impact assessments should incorporate data from a range of climate models that effectively simulate historical climate over the area of interest (
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guisan et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, to predict the future potential distribution of CAS on a global scale, the Hadley Global Environment Model 2-Atmosphere Ocean (HADGEM2-AO), Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory Coupled Model v3 (GFDL-CM3) and Model for Interdisciplinary Research on Climate (MIROC5) for 2050 (average for 2041–2060) and 2070 (average for 2061–2080) were obtained from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) of the fifth assessment of the International Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in 2010 (
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moss et al., 2010</xref>). Four possible greenhouse gas concentration trajectories were selected that ranged from low (RCP 2.6) to high (RCP 8.5) and corresponded to increases in global radiative forcing values in the year 2100 relative to preindustrial values (2.6, 4.5, 6.0 and 8.5 w/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, respectively). Additionally, it was assumed that the global mean temperature will increase by 0.3 °C–4.8 °C by 2100 across all RCPs (
 <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Vuuren et al., 2011</xref>). Four climate change scenario/year combinations were selected to simulate the future influence of potentially extreme climatic variations on the geographical distribution patterns: RCP 2.6-2050, RCP 8.5-2050, RCP 2.6-2070 and RCP 8.5-2070. All future climate projection data were download from the WorldClim Database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org</ext-link>). All current and future data had a spatial resolution of 2.5 arc min (approx. ∼5 km resolution at the equator).
</p>
