<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Homogeneous and reproducible triple 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N isotope labelling allowed the simultaneous quantification of all major N turnover systems in the investigated intact beech seedling—soil-mesocosms under persistence of plant-microbe interactions during the experimental incubation period. This is expected to have resulted in comparable realistic rates of gross N turnover. The N cycle revealed by this approach was characterized by high rates of microbial mineralization–immobilisation turnover. The comparably low soil inorganic N concentrations in the range of daily rates of gross inorganic N production and consumption rates show that microbial N turnover largely controlled soil inorganic N availability. The dominance of NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup> over NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> as a source for beech seedling N nutrition is in line with earlier studies at the site conducted with adult trees [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Generally significantly larger N uptake in June than in August (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0158823.g006" class="xref">Fig 6</xref>) confirmed an earlier study [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], showing highest N uptake capacity of beech seedlings at the onset of the growing season. Such studies on N uptake capacity also indicated that glutamine is of high importance for N nutrition of beech seedlings [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. Here, the homogeneous application of double-labelled 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-carbon (
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C)/
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N glutamine to intact soil showed that 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N but not 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C was retrieved in mycorrhizal and plant tissues (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0158823.g006" class="xref">Fig 6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0158823.s008" class="xref">S6</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0158823.s009" class="xref">S7</xref> Tables). This suggests that either uptake of intact glutamine was not significant under such realistic field conditions or glutamine derived C was already subjected to respiration in the mycorrhizal mantle [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. These findings show the limitation of uptake capacity studies to explain actual 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> uptake of organic N in the presence of microbial competition.
</p>
