<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It needs to be noted that the experimental findings from the space-for-time climate change experiment on the significant contribution of nutritional limitations to the drought sensitivity of European beech on marginal calcareous soil cannot be directly linked to the results of potential species range distribution modelling (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0158823.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>), as this statistical modelling approach is not based on physiology or biogeochemistry. The statistical model used in this study compares presence or absence of beech with climatic parameters only so that regional differences in N availability and their impacts on beech seedling N nutrition are not considered. The present study suggests that this problem could be tackled by the use of indices of N limitation such as atmospheric N deposition and soil C:N ratios in statistical species range models, which should improve their performance with regard to predicting regional differences in vulnerability and resilience of beech stands in a changing climate. Dynamic vegetation models so far focus on light and water as determinants of stand development and species competition in a changing climate. Our work shows that N dynamics is a critical component to be included in such models. The presented data facilitate testing whether dynamic vegetation models coupled to process-oriented biogeochemical ecosystem models [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] can consider effects of climate change on beech performance more comprehensively, taking also into account N availability as mediated by soil microbes. For this purpose, such biogeochemical test data on plant-soil-microbe N dynamics is urgently needed also for other forest stands. The inclusion of microbial nutrient dynamics in such models is also important in the light of recent observational evidence that nutrient availability could dominate as control of net ecosystem productivity in forests at a global scale [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>].
</p>
