<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where previous studies (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>) rely largely on a combination of fishery-dependent data and fish diets or focus on single species and use older methodologies that can be questioned (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>), we used CSIA-AA to analyze stable isotopes embedded within the tissues of eight different species of seabirds. This enabled us to generate a fishery-independent index of TP for eight marine predators for over 125 years, which both avoids the known biases inherent in catch data (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>) and extends the timeline of analysis beyond the catch data period (since 1950). We demonstrate that TP declined broadly in the North Pacific from 1890 to the present (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>), likely due to a decrease in high-TL fish and an increase in low-TL squid (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). RF models (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>) indicate that these changes are due not only to commercial fishing but also to a complex interaction of ecomorphology (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>), prey availability (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>), and climate (fig. S4) factors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are seabirds fishing down marine food webs? From 1950 to 1995, the seabird TP declines we observed are similar to the reported changes in global catch MTL [0.2; (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>)] but more pronounced than the estimated MTL for the North Pacific alone (0.05). Subsequent catch analyses (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>) suggest that global MTL may have increased from 1980 to 2015, which we found in only one of eight species in that period. The dominant species pattern we documented was declining or stable TP (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>). The species ensemble model shows a gradual rate of decline in TP over time that doubles after 1950 (table S1) or during the rise of industrial fishing. Although CSIA-AA has been used variously (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
   <span class="italic">35</span>
  </a>) to estimate TP, our results do not appear sensitive to different formulations of TP from CSIA-AA data (see fig. S3). Because many of these seabird populations we analyze are rebounding from historical bottlenecks (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>), their aggregate fishing power may not approach that of commercial fisheries over this period. However, more research in this area is needed. Studies at global (
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>) and basin (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>) scales suggest that seabirds consume prey biomass on par with commercial fisheries. However, such models often extrapolate fine-scale temporal observations during the breeding season, when seabirds provision their chicks, and thus are subject to propagation errors and large model uncertainties.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bayesian diet reconstructions displayed a visible shift from fishes to squids (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). This result is sensitive to prey TL (fig. S8), and we further assume that prey TLs are themselves consistent over the study period. Future modeling efforts might examine how pervasive trophic downgrading or shifts in prey size distributions (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>) might influence trends in predator TPs. Despite these assumptions, TP determined by CSIA-AA is considered insensitive to shifts at the base of the food web (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>) and to basin scale N cycling dynamics (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). Our diet reconstruction aligns with the global expansion in cephalopods (
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>) and with the declining catch of high-TL flying fish and goatfish (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In line with a hierarchal theory of ecological indicators (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>), model outputs show that ecomorphology and prey availability have direct and dominant influences on TP, and that climate also factors (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5A</a>). Both the partial dependence (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4B</a>) and variable interaction plots (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5C</a>) reveal a complex set of nonlinear relationships. The direction of these relationships and the underlying mechanisms rely largely on how catch data might reflect actual abundance. For goatfish, TP increases with catch, and therefore, we might expect goatfish landings (TL = 3.56) to reflect abundance. Given that Hawaii-based goatfish catch has dropped (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>), TP for goatfish consumers might correspondingly also decline due to dietary replacement. Squid abundance is notoriously unpredictable (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>). The positive model relationship between squid catch and TP that we find may reflect provisioning for fish that are seabird prey. Generally, the lagged climate series are higher ranked than the raw data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5B</a>), which may indicate that climatic forcing of prey abundance is not immediate. From ecomorphology, the highest TP occurs in species with low wing loading and high forage ranges, who might search large regions efficiently for high-TL targets.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few of the seabird species that we study here [sooty tern (SOTE), BRNO, and WTSH] forage in association with predatory fish schools (
  <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
   <span class="italic">42</span>
  </a>). The failure of such fisheries in certain locations has seen a commensurate response in some seabird diets (
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>). Our predictive models for TP across time incorporate a variety of drivers (climate, ecomorphology, and fisheries) that can influence all eight seabird species. The catch data comprising our model inputs (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>) essentially assess competitive exclusion by commercial fisheries, and not the commensal relationship whereby predatory fish like tunas concentrate seabird prey close to the ocean surface. Such dynamics would be better assessed by quantifying the concurrent availability of spatially explicit catch and the movements of tuna-associated seabirds across time. Although insufficient data exist at this time, a combination of active acoustic and microtag tracking (
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
   <span class="italic">46</span>
  </a>) may help better understand how the commercial catch of tunas affects tuna-associated seabirds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Being central-place foragers (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
   <span class="italic">47</span>
  </a>), seabirds may maximize foraging efficiency (
  <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">
   <span class="italic">48</span>
  </a>) yet respond opportunistically to prey availability at sea. Therefore, we expect that the seabird TPs we observe integrate the various ecosystem factors that determine the distribution and abundance of prey, ultimately reflecting and approximating ecosystem status. Although the data and methods presented here may resolve some issues posed by catch MTL, essentially replacing human predators with seabirds and diet studies with CSIA-AA, understanding seabird TP patterns themselves ultimately relies on true fish abundance trends. These data, although important, are both logistically demanding and elusive (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). The replication of our analysis in other regions, through available historical specimens, may also hold insights into the status of marine ecosystems and the future of seabird populations.
 </p>
</sec>
