<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robust indicators of ecosystem health are critical to understand threats, guide management of resilience, and promote sustainability in marine ecosystems (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Because food web dynamics capture both species and their ecosystem interactions (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>), they are a common means to assess ecosystem status. One such intuitive indicator used for commercial fisheries is the mean trophic level (MTL). At the global scale, MTL shows or obscures a variety of trends and signals including the overharvesting and collapse of large predators [“fishing down food webs”; (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>)] and the proliferation of fisheries targeting low-TL species [“fishing through food webs”; (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>)]. This metric has been challenged as a true indicator of ecosystem status, however, because MTL is generated from commercial catch data that incorporate a wide array of biases (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). Developing TL metrics from fishery-independent data, as a result, could advance the sustainable management of marine ecosystems (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An increasingly popular technique, compound-specific stable isotope analysis of δ
  <span class="sup">15</span>N in amino acids (CSIA-AA), holds promise for developing ecosystem indicators (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>). Embedded within the tissues of most organisms is a memory of their ecosystem experience (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>). Age, biogeography, diet, and other relationships can be described through a variety of tissue tracers (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>). CSIA-AA is unique in that it compares the relative enrichment of 
  <span class="sup">15</span>N to 
  <span class="sup">14</span>N (δ
  <span class="sup">15</span>N) in trophic and source amino acids, building upon earlier bulk stable isotope methods, by yielding a robust and unbiased estimate of an organism’s trophic position (TP) (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>). Applications of this technique to date, however, have largely addressed single species questions (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>) or food web models (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>). CSIA-AA has not been applied to a fishery-independent data stream to assess marine ecosystem status over time or to test the various drivers of the observed trends.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we examine whether broad shifts in food web structure are reflected in a 125-year time series of seabird tissues from the central North Pacific. As a taxon, seabirds may serve as good indicators of marine ecosystem trophic state (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>). To begin, seabirds represent a diverse array of high-TL fish consumers capable of integrating much of an ecosystem’s food web dynamics. Foundational research using bulk stable isotopes suggested that the seabird TP may track prey availability (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). However, the results of those studies can be questioned because of the sensitivity of bulk isotopes to shifts at the ecosystem base, due to changing ocean productivity and nutrient recycling (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>). Further development with multispecies approaches shows promise, as seabirds exhibit a wide array of foraging strategies, prey selection, and geographic affinities that provide a diverse perspective to document and analyze environmental change (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>). On a practical level, seabird specimens are readily accessed at large breeding colonies, from fishery bycatch and strandings, and, importantly, are well represented in natural history collections.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use CSIA-AA to determine the TP of eight seabird species through time (1891 to 2016). First, we describe the historical trends, interpret the differences among species, and use hierarchical models to estimate prey shifts given established dietary preferences. Next, we use random forest algorithms (RFs) to quantify the relative importance of climate, commercial fisheries, and ecomorphology to long-term TP changes. Our results provide new insights into trophic web dynamics in pelagic ocean basins over time and highlight the potential of using CSIA-AA–derived TPs in seabirds as a meaningful indicator of ecosystem status. These multispecies, fishery-independent indicators may inform ecosystem-based management (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
