<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prey item composition and longitudinal record</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The only exhaustive survey (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>) of these species diets provided prey composition during 1978 to 1980. Samples were regurgitates collected in the Northwestern Hawaiian Islands from 1978 to 1980. We substituted red-tailed tropicbirds (
  <span class="italic">Phaethon rubricauda</span>) for white-tailed tropicbirds, because the latter are unavailable, and both species are solitary foragers that target epipelagic prey. Species otherwise self-represent. We sourced spatially reconstructed catch data for major prey taxa from the Sea Around Us (SAU) database (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>). This provided data for the seabird foraging area (10° to 44°N, 140° to 235°W) for Carangidae (jacks), Exocoetidae (flying fish), Mullidae (goatfish), and Ommastrephidae (flying squids). These four taxa (fig. S9) constituted 65% of the mean diet volume for the seabirds we studied. SAU reconstructs catches through composites of Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) data with best estimates of unreported catch, both landed and discarded. Catch distribution was approximated through FAO area presence, latitudinal range, range-limited polygon generation, depth range, habitat preference, and equatorial submergence. In the absence of catch-per-unit-effort data, catch data may approximate fishing pressure and relative abundance (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent analysis (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>) provided invertebrate TL. We calculated seabird TL as a function of stomach contents using
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div id="m2" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">TL</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span stretchy="true" class="mo">(</span>
      <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
       <div class="munderover">
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span class="mo">=</span>
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">P</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">j</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mtext">TL</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">j</span>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="true" class="mo">)</span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">1</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>where 
  <span class="italic">P</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub> is the proportion of the 
  <span class="italic">j</span>th food item based on the literature dietary data and TL
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub> is the MTL of the 
  <span class="italic">j</span>th prey item family (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">
   <span class="italic">50</span>
  </a>). We plotted TL estimates at 1980 over the fitted TP series (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>). Hierarchal Bayesian mixing models (Supplementary Methods) generated prey proportions over time, using prey TL to reconstruct the TP series.
 </p>
</sec>
