<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The studies of DNA methylation potentially mediating epigenetic effects in wild animal populations are at their infancy, and even basic information on individual variation in methylation levels, consistency in methylation at different life stages, and inter-generational resemblance is lacking. Yet, DNA methylation and other pathways of epigenetic alterations of gene expression can have profound effects on the formation and maintenance of phenotypic variation and thus major potential, and yet largely unexplored, consequences for ecological and evolutionary processes.</p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this correlational study, we contribute to start filling some of these major gaps of knowledge by focusing on a class of highly conserved genes contributing to the circadian clock system. We first analyzed age- and sex-related variation in methylation levels at six focal genetic 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> in a wild population of barn swallow, and found variation in methylation according to age and between males and females. Second, individuals were highly consistent in relative methylation levels between the nestling and the yearling life stage at most 
  <span class="italic">loci</span>. Third, offspring resembled their genetic mother and their attending father in methylation particularly at the nestling stage. The occurrence of extra-pair fertilizations in the barn swallows allowed to identify some hints of stronger resemblance between the offspring and their genetic father compared to the non-genetic social father, possibly suggesting inheritance of methylation levels not only mediated by common-environment effects. In addition, methylation at clock 5′-UTR was found to positively covary between breeding mates. Finally, by largely expanding a previous dataset, we confirmed that methylation at clock poly-Q negatively predicts a major phenological fitness trait, breeding date, of females but not males and we provided novel evidence that breeding date is not predicted by methylation at the other 
  <span class="italic">loci</span>. Admittedly, in the present study we did not investigate the environmental factors that govern variation in methylation levels, which was found to occur among years (clock 5′-UTR and per3) but not among colonies. The ecological causes and the ontogenetic and sex-dependent mechanisms behind variation in methylation levels thus remain to be elucidated.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in mates</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found evidence for non-random mating (i.e. assortative mating according to its definition in
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>) according to methylation at clock 5′-UTR but not at the other 
   <span class="italic">loci</span>. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first evidence for positive assortative mating according to methylation profile in any vertebrate species. Since the clock gene is believed to be involved in photoperiodic responses, including timing of spring phenological events in birds
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span>, positive assortative mating for methylation may result from an effect of methylation at this 
   <span class="italic">locus</span> on timing of arrival from migration and pre-breeding activities, favoring the pairing between individuals with synchronized life cycles. An alternative interpretation is that similarity in methylation during the breeding season arises as an effect of synchrony in breeding activities, therefore being the consequence, rather than the cause, of synchronization of spring life-cycle events.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in relation to sex and life stage</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found clear evidence for variation in methylation in relation to age and sex. At clock poly-Q and timeless, nestlings had higher methylation than older individuals and females had higher methylation than males. The pattern was more complex and partly reversed for clock 5′-UTR, as methylation was lower in nestlings than in adults among females but not males, and was lower in female than male nestlings whereas no difference existed at the adult life stage.</p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We are aware of two cases where age-related variation in methylation in birds has been studied in the wild. Methylation at the avian glucocorticoid receptor gene did not differ between nestling and adult superb starlings (
   <span class="italic">Lamprotornis superbus</span>) whereas methylation at the agouti-related neuropeptide varied with age in the black grouse
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>. In humans, DNA methylation changes over the lifespan, but predominantly in the first year of life and throughout later childhood and adolescence, becoming more stable in the adulthood
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span>. As a general pattern, repetitive elements are usually heavily methylated and become hypomethylated with age; gene promoters can be hypo- or hypermethylated according to their biological function and the presence of multiple methylated CpG sites in promoters causes stable silencing of genes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
   </span>. At the mechanistic level, changes in the expression of enzymes regulating methylation could lead to generalized or gene-specific modulation of methylation with age
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>. The present age-related variation in methylation may contribute to cause the age-dependent variation in phenological traits, which is strongly expressed in barn swallows
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sex differences in DNA methylation have been studied in humans and other mammalian model organisms
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
   </span>, seldom in domestic birds
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span>, while information on sex differences from the few studies of non-artificially selected avian models in the wild is extremely limited
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>. Barn swallows show variation in behaviors that may depend on circadian rhythmicity and photoperiodic responses according to sex, including for example timing of migration
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
   </span>. The sex-related differences that we observed in methylation may therefore partly account for such behavioral sex differences. In the present study, however, we did not investigate the environmental factors, if any, that could contribute to generate the observed variation of methylation levels according to age and sex, and very limited knowledge of methylation in wild vertebrates prevented us from speculating on which factors could in fact be responsible for such age- and sex-dependency.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within-individual consistency in methylation at the nestling and adult stage</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DNA methylation landscape is dynamically patterned during development and also at later life stages
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
   </span>, implying that methylation can change during life, as present results suggest to be the case at four 
   <span class="italic">loci</span> (see above). However, individuals that at the nestling stage had high methylation also did so at the 1-year old stage at four of the six 
   <span class="italic">loci</span> that we investigated, implying that 
   <span class="italic">relative</span> methylation levels tended to remain constant across individuals during the first year of life. Consistency of methylation level has been previously documented during the first life stages (e.g. from childhood to first pregnancy) in humans
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
   </span>. The present results thus suggest that individual consistency in behavioral patterns that is observed at phenological or other behavioral traits that may depend on circadian clocks, can partly result from consistency of individual methylation level during life
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. Cry1 and per3 represented an exception to the positive relationship between methylation levels at different life stages, with cry1 even showing a negative relationship between life stages. However, the mechanism and the function, if any, of such negative relationship for cry1 remains obscure at present.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in parents and offspring</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results from the mother-offspring resemblance analyses clearly showed high resemblance at the nestling stage but such associations almost completely vanished as offspring reached the adult stage. Mother-offspring resemblance could arise via shared-environment effects. Additional, not necessarily mutually exclusive mechanisms that can induce resemblance in methylation are via the maternal germline, genetically-based variation in susceptibility to methylation and/or early maternal effects mediated by egg quality.</p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, for per2 we found evidence for differential resemblance of maternal methylation levels with methylation of offspring of either sex. This result is consistent with observations of offspring sex-specific inheritance of methylation levels of either parent in ICR (Imprinting Control Regions)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extra-pair fertilizations afforded an opportunity to indirectly test for environmental effects on father-offspring resemblance in methylation. The results, in this respect, were complex and only partly conclusive. For clock poly-Q there was a significant paternity by paternal methylation interaction effect on offspring methylation at the nestling stage, conclusively showing that resemblance with the offspring was larger for genetic that for non-genetic fathers. Hence, for clock poly-Q there was evidence for inheritance of methylation levels independent of environmental effects. Such father-offspring resemblance could arise because of transmission of paternal methylation levels via germinal cells and/or via genetic effects on susceptibility to methylation in prenatal or early postnatal life stages. Inheritance of methylation levels at clock poly-Q can have major ecological consequences because in the barn swallow methylation at clock poly-Q predicts variation at spring phenological traits
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>. Father- (and mother-) offspring resemblance in methylation could possibly contribute to establish parent-offspring resemblance in phenology traits.
  </p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the other five 
   <span class="italic">loci</span>, the interaction effect between paternity and paternal methylation at the nestling stage was either marginally non-significant after FDR correction (clock 5-UTR), or far from statistical significance (remaining 
   <span class="italic">loci</span>), implying no statistically significant difference in the slopes of the relationships between methylation of the offspring and that of their genetic compared to non-genetic, social fathers. However, a closer inspection of the relationships within either paternity group suggested that the relationships between offspring and genetic-fathers at some 
   <span class="italic">loci</span> had larger associated effect sizes (
   <span class="italic">t</span> values) than those between offspring and social fathers at the nestling or at the adult stages of the offspring. Albeit non-conclusive, these results may thus suggest father-offspring resemblance of methylation levels independent of environmental effects also at the other 
   <span class="italic">loci</span>, besides clock poly-Q. In fact, the relationships between methylation of the non-genetic, social fathers and the offspring that they attended were not statistically significant. However, for clock poly-Q the relationship between methylation of the offspring at the nestling stage and that of their social father was negative, rather than null or positive as expected in the case of no or, respectively, non-null environmental effects. The interpretation of the latter result is open to speculation. Because the genetic father-offspring relationship was positive, whereas the relationship was negative for the social father, it might be speculated that mothers generating extra-pair offspring were fertilized by extra-pair males whose methylation level was negatively correlated with that of their mate. The function of such differential assortative mating
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span> with the social mate compared to the extra-pair mate might consist in increasing the epigenetic diversity of the offspring, with potential advantages in terms of adaptation to unpredictable ecological conditions, in line with the theory that considers the function of extra-pair fertilizations as a mean to increase phenotypic diversity of the offspring
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the parent-offspring resemblance analyses suggested that genetic parents of either sex can differentially contribute to determine offspring methylation at individual 
   <span class="italic">loci</span> and at different offspring life stages. Genetic fathers, in particular, seemed to contribute to offspring methylation at some 
   <span class="italic">loci</span> of the clock genes also at the adult stage, whereas this was not the case for genetic mothers. In addition, the effect of methylation of the social (non-genetic) father on methylation of the extra-pair offspring was very weak, suggesting only minor, if any, effects of shared environment between fathers and offspring on resemblance in methylation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation and breeding date</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic polymorphism at clock has been shown to be associated with phenological variation in several, though not all, vertebrate species tested so far
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
   </span>, including the barn swallow
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span>. Besides genetic polymorphism, however, methylation state may also intervene in regulating clock-dependent photoperiodic responses. In a previous study we showed that methylation at the clock poly-Q predicted timing of breeding of old female barn swallows from the same geographical area where the present study was carried out
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>. To assess the robustness of the previously reported relationship, here we considerably expanded the sample size of the previous study and confirmed that large methylation at clock poly-Q is associated with early breeding in females but not in males. The relationship between breeding date and methylation at clock poly-Q held for both yearling (not tested in a previous study
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>) and older individuals, which are known to breed on average at different times
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. As previously noted
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, the sign of the relationship between methylation at clock poly-Q and breeding date is consistent with the expectation. This is the case because increasing methylation levels are expected to reduce the expression of CLOCK/BMAL1 transcription factor, thus reducing the transcriptional activation of the clock genes.
  </p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the present analyses on an expanded sample disclosed a marginally non-significant (P = 0.062) negative association between breeding date, independently of sex and age, and methylation at the clock 5′-UTR 
   <span class="italic">locus</span>, which was not previously detected
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, suggesting that methylation at other regions of clock may also be functionally relevant to timing of breeding. However, we did not find any hint for an association between methylation at other four circadian clock genes and breeding date in both sexes, which were not tested in the previous study.
  </p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Populations of birds and other organisms have undergone rapid phenotypic changes in phenological traits during the last decades, likely in response to climate change
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
   </span>, which have occurred at a pace that may be difficult to explain by invoking relatively slow micro-evolutionary processes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
   </span>. The observed association between methylation at clock and breeding date (present study) or migration dates
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, and the observation of parent-offspring resemblance in methylation at this gene may help explaining rapid phenological change in the barn swallow and, potentially, also in several other bird species
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
   </span>. This is the case because methylation at clock poly-Q, which shows high resemblance between genetic parents and young offspring, may mediate phenological shifts at least in early life stages, with likely carry-over consequences in adulthood, independently of any micro-evolutionary change in population genetic composition at clock.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concluding remarks</div>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, we found extensive evidence for differential variation in methylation levels according to sex and age, whose physiolocal and ecological causes remain to be elucidated. In addition, we also showed extensive, yet 
   <span class="italic">locus</span>-dependent parent-offspring resemblance in methylation levels, with a hint that, for fathers, resemblance with the offspring is more strongly mediated by variation in germline methylation, genetic variation in susceptibility to methylation or sperm factors rather than by extrinsic environmental factors during early life stages. Such intergenerational resemblance in methylation has obvious implications for estimates of genetic heritability of traits that depend on clock genes. There is widespread evidence that rapid phenological changes have occurred in animal populations in response to climate change, and the fast pace of such changes has proven difficult to be reconciled with micro-evolutionary changes in populations. Epigenetic effects can rapidly generate phenotypic plasticity in phenological and other traits. The association between methylation at clock and phenological traits, in combination with intergenerational resemblance in methylation levels can thus provide a mechanistic basis to interpret the rapid phenological changes that populations have recently undergone in response to climate change.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
