<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The complete version with full details of the Statistical analyses section is reported in the SOM. For clarity, the description of the statistical analyses is here organized so to correspond to the main sub-sections of the 
  <span class="italic">Results</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because methylation variables are proportions, dependent methylation variables were always arcsin√x-transformed.</p>
 <sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in pair members</div>
  <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested if methylation was correlated between males and females forming the same social breeding pair in linear mixed models (LMM) assuming a Gaussian error distribution with methylation of females as the dependent variable, methylation of the male mates as the independent variable, and year and colony as random factors.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in relation to sex and life stage</div>
  <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in methylation according to sex and life stage was also analyzed in LMMs. For each 
   <span class="italic">locus</span>, each methylation datum of parents and offspring was classified according to sex (male: 1; female: 2) and life stage (parent and 1-year-old offspring: 1; offspring at the nestling stage: 2). In the models, methylation was considered as the dependent variable, sex and life stage as fixed effect factors (with their two-way interaction), and year and colony as random effects. In addition, we also included a random factor family, i.e. a factor where the father (whether genetic or social), the mother, and their offspring at both the nestling and the adult stage were assigned the same code. The effect of the sex by life stage interaction is always presented in the 
   <span class="italic">Results</span>, but when it was non-significant it was excluded from the model including the main effects. In these analyses, we also tested for the (random) effect of year and colony on methylation, by comparing the model including both random effects with reduced models that contained only the year or, respectively, the colony effects, by likelihood ratio tests.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation at the nestling and 1-year-old recruit stage</div>
  <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationship between methylation at the 1-year-old stage (dependent variable) and at the nestling stage (independent variable) was analyzed in LMMs with year and colony as random effects.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in parents and offspring</div>
  <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationship between methylation at the nestling stage or at the 1-year-old recruit stage and methylation of the father and mother was analyzed in LMMs where we included methylation of the nestling as the dependent variable and methylation of the father and of the mother as independent variables. In addition, we included a factor ‘paternity’ to account for the fact that the father was the genetic or, respectively, the social, non-genetic father of the offspring. The interaction between paternity and methylation of the father allowed us to test whether the relationship between nestling’s and father’s methylation differed between genetic and social fathers. Finally, we also included a factor offspring sex to account for variation in methylation between male and female offspring and its interaction with maternal methylation, to account for any differential effect of methylation of mothers on methylation of sons as compared to daughters. The interaction between paternal methylation and offspring sex was not tested because of admixture of genetic and social fathers (see also SOM). The effect of sex as well as the effect of the interaction between paternity and paternal methylation were removed from final models when statistically non-significant. However, even when the paternity by father’s methylation was statistically non-significant, we still reported and inspected the within-paternity group relationships because these could provide information as to whether the 
   <span class="italic">strength</span> (not the 
   <span class="italic">slope</span>) of the relationship between nestling and father differed according to paternity (see also SOM).
  </p>
  <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As an exception to the above modelling approach, because of very high collinearity between mates at clock 5′-UTR (r = 0.648, n = 64, P &lt; 0.0001; see also 
   <span class="italic">Results</span>), for this 
   <span class="italic">locus</span> the relationships with the mother or the father were tested in separate models.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Breeding date in relation to methylation</div>
  <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested whether methylation at the six 
   <span class="italic">loci</span> statistically predicted breeding date. We thus designed LMM with sex and age (yearling vs older) as fixed effects and methylation, and their two-way interactions as predictors. In the models we also included year as a random factor and, in addition, a factor ‘family’ which accounted for the fact that in the dataset pairs of mates and, in some cases, trios (two parents plus one breeding offspring) were included. In the analyses on the effect of methylation at the two clock 
   <span class="italic">loci</span>, where we also considered information on methylation and breeding date already reported in a study based in both Italy and Switzerland
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, we also included a random factor ‘study area’ (Italy or Switzerland). Because the mean and the variances of the clock 5′-UTR and clock poly-Q between the present methylation data and those previously reported
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span> differed, methylation data were standardized to a mean of 0 and a variance of 1 within the two datasets.
  </p>
  <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because repeated tests were run on the same individuals at the six 
   <span class="italic">loci</span>, the results of the statistical tests were corrected according to the false discovery rate (FDR) procedure (see also SOM). Throughout the 
   <span class="italic">Results</span>, uncorrected P values are presented and those that remained significant after FDR correction are marked with a ‘
   <span class="sup">†</span>’.
  </p>
  <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analyses were run using SAS 9.3 statistical package.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec24" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample sizes</div>
  <p id="Par59" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We sampled 58 pairs of breeding adults, and their recruited offspring both as nestlings and as 1-year-old recruits. Of these breeding pairs, 5 had two recruited offspring and 1 had three recruits included in the sample (65 offspring in total). The 65 offspring comprised 54 males (39 WPO and 15 EPO) and 11 females (8 WPO and 3 EPO). This sex-bias in recruitment is typical of the barn swallow and other birds due to female-biased natal dispersal
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The size of the sample for each parental sex, life stage and individual 
   <span class="italic">locus</span>, after exclusion of the outliers (i.e. observations that deviated more than 3 standard deviations from the mean), is reported in details in the SOM.
  </p>
  <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information on breeding date was available also for for 37 offspring that were recruited as yearling breeders. In addition, we considered breeding date and methylation data at the two clock
   <span class="italic"> loci</span> for 58 males and 26 females that were already included in a previous study
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Regione Lombardia administration gave permission for this study (permits no. 2959 and 11316; see also 
   <span class="italic">Compliance with guidelines and regulations</span> section at the bottom of the main text).
  </p>
  <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All experiments were performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. All experimental protocols were approved by the Regione Lombardia administration (permits no. 2959 and 11316) following approval by the Istituto Superiore per la Protezione e la Ricerca Ambientale (ISPRA).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
