<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental conditions can induce regulation of the expression and function of genes via epigenetic effects, without directly altering nucleotide sequence
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Epigenetic programming can produce differential gene expression among individuals, thus generating phenotypic differences even from the same genetic substrate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Epigenetic alterations can occur in response to a wide variety of extrinsic environmental 
  <span class="italic">stimuli</span> ranging from nutritional conditions to social and chemical stress
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. Epigenetic alterations, in turn, are heritable
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> and thus have the potential to result in transmission of new phenotypes across multiple generations. The possibility that ancestors’ experiences result in epigenetic transmission across generation borders of phenotypic traits has obvious, tremendous and yet poorly explored implications for ecological and evolutionary processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Indeed, heritable epigenetic effects are known to affect phenotypic variation at major life-history traits including physiology, morphology and behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Epigenetic modulation of gene expression occurs through major classes of mechanisms that include DNA methylation, histone modifications, the effect of non-coding RNAs, and the activity of chaperones
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. DNA methylation, particularly at the palindrome dinucleotide sequences 5′CpG3′ at the 5 position of cytosine, is generally regarded as the most common epigenetic mark in mammals, although information for other vertebrates is scanty. Methylation of cytosines located in gene promoters modulates gene transcription, is involved in alternative promoter usage and regulation of enhancer activity, and often causes downregulation of the gene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Epigenetic effects mediated by DNA methylation may be a key mechanism that controls variation in behavioral traits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. For example, methylation at the dopamine receptor D4 (DRD4) gene is related to exploratory behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>, while methylation at the dopamine receptor and serotonin transporter is related to novelty seeking behaviour in great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. In addition, methylation at the agouti-related peptide is significantly related to sexual coloration in the black grouse (
  <span class="italic">Lyrurus tetrix</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA methylation can also be transmitted across generations, generally meaning that offspring resemble their parents in methylation levels, as shown exclusively by laboratory studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Such inheritance of methylation states can arise via different pathways. First, ‘true’ transgenerational inheritance occurs via the germline if methylation profile of the gametes is carried over to the zygote and later developmental stages. Rigorously demonstrating ‘true’ transgenerational inheritance of methylation profiles is extremely difficult, particularly in the wild, as it requires showing that ancestors resemble their F3 or later-generation descendants. Despite these difficulties, some studies have provided evidence for transgenerational inheritance of responses to parental experiences including diet, stressful conditions and exposure to toxins
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, and via gamete-mediated inheritance of methylation marks. Such transmission by germline methylation has been demonstrated in studies of the effects of vinclozolin in mice on anxiety-like behaviors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span> and also in a single study of birds under laboratory conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. However, it must be emphasized that while environmentally driven changes in DNA methylation has been repeatedly documented to be inherited in plants, the evidence for transgenerational environmental effects on methylation is still scanty and contentious for taxa like vertebrates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An alternative pathway of methylation inheritance is via ‘soma-to-soma’ interactions. These can occur when the prenatal environment in terms for example of in utero conditions or egg composition directly affect the methylome of the developing offspring
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. In addition, RNA molecules stored in sperm and components of the seminal fluid also have the potential for transgenerational transmission of epigenetic traits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Such soma-to-soma effects can also occur via general environmental effects whenever ancestors’ experience of environmental conditions causes a new epigenetic mark and phenotype to arise
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> and ancestors tend to reinstate similar environmental (e.g. physical or social) conditions across subsequent generations, causing the same epigenetic mark to re-appear in descendants
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Finally, parent offspring resemblance may arise because of transgenerational genetic effects, whereby similarity in methylation levels in parents and offspring arises because of similarity in their genetic background
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inheritance of methylation may not necessarily occur symmetrically from either parental genome, as exemplified at a paradigmatic extreme by parental sex-specific genetic imprinting
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. The evidence for the relative contribution of maternal versus paternal methylation states to descendant methylation patterns in humans and other vertebrates is mixed and parental sex-specific inheritance effects may vary among taxa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is worth emphasizing that, independently of the exact mechanisms that determine resemblance in methylation states across generations, any such resemblance has extremely important ecological and evolutionary consequences because it implies that new epigenetic phenotypes can be carried over to subsequent generations independently of genetic inheritance. Yet, to the best of our knowledge, no study has been published to date on any vertebrate species in the wild where resemblance in methylation at the single-
  <span class="italic">locus</span> level between parent and offspring has been investigated.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first main aim of this study thus was to investigate whether offspring, at their nestling stage and also once they attain sexual maturity, resemble their parents in CpG methylation at five highly conserved genes (clock, per2, per3, cry1, timeless), using a small, migratory bird, the barn swallow (
  <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) as a study system. In doing so, we also tested for any differential effect of methylation state of either parent on methylation of offspring of either sex, and on age- (nestling vs adult) and sex-specific variation in methylation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. Stemming from current interest on control of timing of major life cycle stages in the barn swallow
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, in the present study we focused on methylation at ‘clock’ genes whose products dynamically interact to elicit rhythmic patterns of transcription, translation, biochemical and physiological processes, and behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> and are thus involved in circadian rhythmicity and photoperiodic responses (see also Supplementary Material). In addition, we tested for resemblance in methylation levels between pair members because similarity in methylation profiles at photoperiodic genes might influence mate choice or, reciprocally, synchronization in reproductive behavior might result in resemblance in methylation levels between pair members.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our goals, we measured methylation at the focal 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> in blood cells of 65 barn swallows (from 58 social pairs) when they were nestlings and when they were subsequently recruited as 1-year-old sexually mature adults, and in their parents. Because nucleated erythrocytes in barn swallows and other birds represent a large fraction of nucleated blood cells
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, our methylation data essentially reflect methylation of erythrocytes. Parent-offspring resemblance in methylation can result from diverse mechanisms, which are extremely difficult to tease apart (see above), especially in the wild. When extra-pair fertilizations occur, however, two types of families are naturally established: first, families where parental fathers (i.e. the males that attend the offspring) are also the genetic fathers of the offspring (hereafter, within-pair offspring, WPO) that they attend; second, families where the parental father is the ‘social’, but not the genetic father (hereafter, ‘social father’) of one or more of the offspring (hereafter, extra-pair offspring, EPO) that they attend. Extra-pair fertilizations, which are common in the barn swallow
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, afford an opportunity to get an insight into the contribution of different mechanisms of parent-offspring resemblance in methylation states, and we therefore subjected the 65 sampled offspring to genetic parentage tests. If genetic father-WPO resemblance in methylation is stronger than social father-EPO resemblance, a mechanism of inheritance mediated by the paternal germline or via non-genetic sperm and seminal fluid constituents can be invoked. Because the reciprocal condition whereby mothers attend non-genetically related offspring in their nest is very uncommon in barn swallows
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, as in the majority of altricial birds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, no such approach could be undertaken to assess the relative contribution of maternal germline/egg effects as compared to postnatal environmental effects.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Very limited background knowledge on methylation in wild birds, however, prevented us from formulating explicit predictions on the differential father-offspring relationships according to paternity and on sex- and age-dependency of methylation levels.</p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a previous study focusing on two clock 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> (clock poly-Q and clock 5′-UTR) we showed that methylation at the clock poly-Q was statistically associated with spring migration and breeding date in the same barn swallow population
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. The previous analysis was restricted to relatively old (two or more years) individuals and focused on just two 
  <span class="italic">loci</span>. Here, we expand the analysis of the association between methylation at these two 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> and breeding date, which is a major fitness trait because in barn swallows it predicts both seasonal reproductive success and offspring quality
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>, on a much larger sample of birds and we also assess whether methylation at other genes besides clock is related to breeding date. The importance of such replication studies to test for consistency of results has been repeatedly advocated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. In the analyses of breeding date in relation to methylation at clock 5′-UTR and clock poly-Q, we thus also considered the data included in Saino 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> (see also below).
 </p>
</sec>
