<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in parents and offspring</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results from the mother-offspring resemblance analyses clearly showed high resemblance at the nestling stage but such associations almost completely vanished as offspring reached the adult stage. Mother-offspring resemblance could arise via shared-environment effects. Additional, not necessarily mutually exclusive mechanisms that can induce resemblance in methylation are via the maternal germline, genetically-based variation in susceptibility to methylation and/or early maternal effects mediated by egg quality.</p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, for per2 we found evidence for differential resemblance of maternal methylation levels with methylation of offspring of either sex. This result is consistent with observations of offspring sex-specific inheritance of methylation levels of either parent in ICR (Imprinting Control Regions)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extra-pair fertilizations afforded an opportunity to indirectly test for environmental effects on father-offspring resemblance in methylation. The results, in this respect, were complex and only partly conclusive. For clock poly-Q there was a significant paternity by paternal methylation interaction effect on offspring methylation at the nestling stage, conclusively showing that resemblance with the offspring was larger for genetic that for non-genetic fathers. Hence, for clock poly-Q there was evidence for inheritance of methylation levels independent of environmental effects. Such father-offspring resemblance could arise because of transmission of paternal methylation levels via germinal cells and/or via genetic effects on susceptibility to methylation in prenatal or early postnatal life stages. Inheritance of methylation levels at clock poly-Q can have major ecological consequences because in the barn swallow methylation at clock poly-Q predicts variation at spring phenological traits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Father- (and mother-) offspring resemblance in methylation could possibly contribute to establish parent-offspring resemblance in phenology traits.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the other five 
  <span class="italic">loci</span>, the interaction effect between paternity and paternal methylation at the nestling stage was either marginally non-significant after FDR correction (clock 5-UTR), or far from statistical significance (remaining 
  <span class="italic">loci</span>), implying no statistically significant difference in the slopes of the relationships between methylation of the offspring and that of their genetic compared to non-genetic, social fathers. However, a closer inspection of the relationships within either paternity group suggested that the relationships between offspring and genetic-fathers at some 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> had larger associated effect sizes (
  <span class="italic">t</span> values) than those between offspring and social fathers at the nestling or at the adult stages of the offspring. Albeit non-conclusive, these results may thus suggest father-offspring resemblance of methylation levels independent of environmental effects also at the other 
  <span class="italic">loci</span>, besides clock poly-Q. In fact, the relationships between methylation of the non-genetic, social fathers and the offspring that they attended were not statistically significant. However, for clock poly-Q the relationship between methylation of the offspring at the nestling stage and that of their social father was negative, rather than null or positive as expected in the case of no or, respectively, non-null environmental effects. The interpretation of the latter result is open to speculation. Because the genetic father-offspring relationship was positive, whereas the relationship was negative for the social father, it might be speculated that mothers generating extra-pair offspring were fertilized by extra-pair males whose methylation level was negatively correlated with that of their mate. The function of such differential assortative mating
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span> with the social mate compared to the extra-pair mate might consist in increasing the epigenetic diversity of the offspring, with potential advantages in terms of adaptation to unpredictable ecological conditions, in line with the theory that considers the function of extra-pair fertilizations as a mean to increase phenotypic diversity of the offspring
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the parent-offspring resemblance analyses suggested that genetic parents of either sex can differentially contribute to determine offspring methylation at individual 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> and at different offspring life stages. Genetic fathers, in particular, seemed to contribute to offspring methylation at some 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> of the clock genes also at the adult stage, whereas this was not the case for genetic mothers. In addition, the effect of methylation of the social (non-genetic) father on methylation of the extra-pair offspring was very weak, suggesting only minor, if any, effects of shared environment between fathers and offspring on resemblance in methylation.
 </p>
</sec>
