<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation in parents and offspring</div>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationship between methylation at the nestling stage or at the 1-year-old recruit stage and methylation of the father and mother was analyzed in LMMs where we included methylation of the nestling as the dependent variable and methylation of the father and of the mother as independent variables. In addition, we included a factor ‘paternity’ to account for the fact that the father was the genetic or, respectively, the social, non-genetic father of the offspring. The interaction between paternity and methylation of the father allowed us to test whether the relationship between nestling’s and father’s methylation differed between genetic and social fathers. Finally, we also included a factor offspring sex to account for variation in methylation between male and female offspring and its interaction with maternal methylation, to account for any differential effect of methylation of mothers on methylation of sons as compared to daughters. The interaction between paternal methylation and offspring sex was not tested because of admixture of genetic and social fathers (see also SOM). The effect of sex as well as the effect of the interaction between paternity and paternal methylation were removed from final models when statistically non-significant. However, even when the paternity by father’s methylation was statistically non-significant, we still reported and inspected the within-paternity group relationships because these could provide information as to whether the 
  <span class="italic">strength</span> (not the 
  <span class="italic">slope</span>) of the relationship between nestling and father differed according to paternity (see also SOM).
 </p>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As an exception to the above modelling approach, because of very high collinearity between mates at clock 5′-UTR (r = 0.648, n = 64, P &lt; 0.0001; see also 
  <span class="italic">Results</span>), for this 
  <span class="italic">locus</span> the relationships with the mother or the father were tested in separate models.
 </p>
</sec>
