<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation analyses</div>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed a total of six 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> at five clock genes: clock, per2, per3, cry1, and timeless. When we started the present work no barn swallow genome sequence was available. We therefore decided to exploit the synteny between passerine birds to isolate the barn swallow genomic sequences of interest. Mainly, the genomes of 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicollis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus trochilus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Pseudopodoces humilis</span>, were used. Except for clock, where PCR primers for the poly-Q exon and 5′-UTR region of the gene, specific for barn swallow, were already available
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>, we concentrated our attention on the promoter region of the other selected genes. A 5,000 bp region upstream of the predicted ATG start codon was identified in the different species, sequences were aligned and the portions conserved in all species were examined to identify candidate CpG methylation sites, flanked by DNA sequences suitable for PCR primer design. For each specific gene the primers were designed to cover the greatest possible number of CpG sites within the promoter region, taking into account the necessary length of the PCR amplicon, length of the target sequence, and primers that avoided CpGs. Sequences were designed using PyroMark Assay Design software (Qiagen, Germany). The identified primers were used to amplify the homologous sequence present in the barn swallow genome. Those fragments were purified (Wizard SV Gel and PCR clean-up System, Promega, Madison, Wi, USA) and sequenced (BMR genomics, Padua, Italy) to confirm their homology and to design specific PCR primers required for bisulfite pyrosequencing. Primer sequences are reported in SOM (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2S</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One µg DNA (concentration 50 ng/µl) was treated using EZ DNA Methylation-Gold™ Kit (Zymo Research, Orange, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Final elution was performed with 30 µl of M-Elution Buffer. Bisulfite-treated DNA was stored at −20 °C and used shortly after treatment. Analysis of DNA methylation was performed using previously published methods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>, with minor modifications. Briefly, a 50 µl PCR was carried out in 25 µl of GoTaq Green Master mix (Promega, Madison, WI, USA), 1 pmol of the forward primer, 1 pmol of the biotinylated reverse primer, 50 ng of bisulfite-treated genomic DNA and water. The biotin-labelled primers were used to purify the final PCR product using Sepharose beads. The PCR product was bound to Streptavidin Sepharose HP (Amersham Biosciences, Uppsala, Sweden) and the Sepharose beads containing the immobilized PCR product were purified, washed, denatured using a 0.2 M NaOH solution, and washed again using the Pyrosequencing Vacuum Prep Tool (Pyrosequencing, Inc., Westborough, MA), as recommended by the manufacturer. Then, 0.3 µΜ pyrosequencing primer was annealed to the purified single-stranded PCR product and pyrosequencing was performed using the PyroMark MD System (Pyrosequencing, Inc.). The degree of methylation was expressed as percentage of methylated cytosines divided by the sum of methylated and unmethylated cytosines (%5mC). Every sample was measured three times and the average of the replicates was used in statistical analyses. Assays which did not result in good quality pyrograms were repeated. If after 3 replicates the pyrogram quality was still not satisfactory according to pyrosequencing quality controls, the measure resulted in a missing value (see below and SOM for sample sizes). Each assay also included a bisulfite conversion check to verify full conversion of the DNA.
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean coefficients of variation of methylation levels for the different 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> was: clock 5′-UTR: 1.0%; clock poly-Q: 1.3%; cry1: 18.5%; per2: 1.0%; per3: 19%; timeless: 1.0%. The frequency distributions of methylation levels at the six 
  <span class="italic">loci</span> is reported in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1S</a> in SOM
 </p>
</sec>
