<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This study provides additional evidence that shows the reliance of urban food systems on transportation, energy, and telecommunication infrastructure, and highlights the need to address vulnerabilities in supporting infrastructure as a leading disaster risk mitigation strategy for reducing food system disruption as a result of extreme weather events. In Toronto, interruptions to electricity could create the most significant food access and food safety impacts, while interruptions to the transportation network and fuel could significantly disrupt food distribution. In addition to their current household-level interventions, public health practitioners and policy makers should begin to address these underlying food system risks at the city level. This study also demonstrates that city-wide resilience building strategies that mitigate the risk of extreme weather events are not sufficient. Specific areas (and populations) within a city will be disproportionately impacted by food system disruptions. People who are already food insecure will be most affected. Thus, cities also need to prioritize neighbourhood-level food resilience plans for neighbourhoods most vulnerable to extreme weather events, taking into account their most vulnerable populations. In the long-term, risk mitigation will require policy initiatives that address food insecurity, including investing in building more supermarkets and other healthy food access mechanisms in vulnerable neighbourhoods to improve food access and availability, as well as developing robust emergency response plans. In the short-term, integrating food access into the Toronto’s neighbourhood emergency response plans, making sure that food banks have sufficient resources to meet increased demand and that supermarkets, grocery and convenience stores have adequate business continuity plans, insurance and back-up power, should be risk mitigation priorities. The food retail industry will need to be engaged to support these strategies.</p>
