<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig1" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Recent and projected surface air temperatures in context of past abrupt warming events in the northern hemisphere. Recent annual surface air temperature (SAT) anomalies for 2014–2016 relative to 1890–1970 (
   <span class="bold">a</span>; refs.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
   </span>), CMIP5 projected SAT anomalies by the end of the century in RCP 8.5 (
   <span class="bold">b</span>), and paleoclimate records spanning the past 19,000 years that document abrupt Arctic warming in concert with abrupt warming in the mid-latitude North Pacific and North Atlantic basins (
   <span class="bold">c</span>). Colored dots on map in 
   <span class="bold">b</span> represent the locations for the paleoclimate datasets plotted in 
   <span class="bold">c</span>. Record-breaking Arctic warming in recent years was associated with anomalously high SSTs in the Northeast Pacific despite a cold spot in the North Atlantic (
   <span class="bold">a</span>). Projected SATs show an amplified response in the Arctic and North Pacific, whereas North Atlantic SSTs undergo relatively modest warming in the first century (
   <span class="bold">b</span>). 
   <span class="bold">c</span> Paleoclimate archives spanning the last 19,050 years (1950 = year 0). From top: Greenland δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O records from NEEM 19,000–10,000 years ago (dark blue
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
   </span>) and NGRIP (light blue
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
   </span>), An alkenone-based UK’37 SST reconstruction from the Gulf of Alaska reflecting Summer SST (dark green
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>); the youngest data point represents the core top measurement taken in 2004 (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
   </span>); September SST data from Ocean Station Papa (145°W, 50°N) from 2007 to 2015 are plotted on the same axis (light green squares; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pmel.noaa.gov/ocs/data" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.pmel.noaa.gov/ocs/data</span>). An SST reconstruction based on faunal assemblages from the central North Atlantic (plum
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
   </span>), and a reconstruction of the average North Atlantic SST anomaly relative to Holocene values (pink
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
   </span>). A composite record of the global temperature anomaly for the past 20,000 years relative to the 1980–2004 mean (blue
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
   </span>). Atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentrations from 19,000 years ago to present based on ice cores measurement and modern measurements
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
   </span>. Gray shaded bars represent two episodes of rapid warming in Greenland that are coeval (within age uncertainties) with abrupt SST increase in the Northeast Pacific and North Atlantic, increases in CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration, and intervals of widespread hypoxia in the North Pacific
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span> and Holarctic megafauna extinctions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Pink bar denotes changes since 1950
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5337_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e428" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
