<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Global mitigation policies, developed to reduce deforestation and increase carbon sequestration in the world's forests, include CDM (Clean Development Mechanism), REDD (Reducing Emissions from Deforestation in Developing Countries), and REDD+ (Reducing Emissions from Deforestation and Forest Degradation in Developing Countries). Globally, while REDD and REDD+ have enhanced stewardship and reduced land degradation, deforestation continues to increase in Indonesia, Malaysia, and parts of Africa and South America, and the discontinuities between top‐down policies with activities occurring at the project or community level can be seen in the implementation of such programs. Concerns have arisen about equity and the policies' effectiveness (Harlan, Pellow, &amp; Roberts, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Paladino &amp; Fiske, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Parks &amp; Roberts, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0174" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). In an examination of 9 cases in Uganda, Nel (
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0165" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0166" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) finds that benefits are asymmetrical, and local people are often affected by “expulsion and marginalization”. However, research on the Khasi Hills Project in India indicates that community‐based forest management has the potential to provide an effective strategy for mitigating powerful drivers of deforestation, and can be even more successful if supported through internationally recognized and certified carbon projects, including both REDD+ and Afforestation and Reforestation (Poffenberger, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0178" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The concept of REDD+ is evolving and one of the more promising approaches is “Jurisdictional REDD,” which spans different land‐use types across landscapes and with multiple stakeholders in a subnational jurisdiction (Fishbein &amp; Lee, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). More broadly, this area of research indicates that global‐scale initiatives need to connect more effectively to local environmental and social contexts (Angelsen &amp; Rudel, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Fiske et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Lansing, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0141" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Leach &amp; Scoones, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0142" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Paladino &amp; Fiske, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
