<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The early seedling growth parameters were also significantly affected by simulated drought stress. Root length, shoot length and fresh weight decreased significantly with an increase in PEG 6000 concentration (-0.01 –-5.34 MPa), and all the seedlings had perished at a PEG 6000 concentration of 20% (-5.34 MPa). Our results support the idea that seed germination and early seedling growth are impacted by simulated drought stress [
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>] Early seedlings were significantly inhibited when soil water potential was at a PEG 6000 concentration of 18% (-4.29 MPa), corresponding to that observed in the field in Nov. (-4.30 MPa). Results of the water-controlled experiment confirmed these observations and indicated poor drought resistance in 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic>. Ten growth indicators of 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic> seedlings were significantly inhibited by drought stress (-0.01 –-4.46 MPa) and seedlings perished at 1/5 WHC (-5.64 MPa). The fact that root/ shoot ratio declined with the decrease in relative soil water content is not in accordance with the normal response of plants, which is to increase belowground organ biomass to encourage nutrient and water update under drought conditions. This suggests that 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic> seedlings are not able to dynamically adapt to water deficit via responses in morphology. Hence, the implication is that seedlings in field had also been suppressed by drought stress, and a range of soil water potentials from -5.34 MPa to -5.64 MPa are fatal for 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic> seedlings. These results also indicated that seed germination and seedling establishment in the field had been suppressed during the seedling establishment period from Sep. to Feb. In accordance with the findings of other plant studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>], low water availability significantly inhibited the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic> seedlings. Conversely, higher soil moisture content culminated in an increase in leaves and larger leaf areas of seedlings, which resulted in a greater photosynthetic rate as well as a higher biomass. When experiencing drought stress, most plants will reduce their aboveground biomass and allocate more resources to their belowground biomass, so as to improve the likelihood of survival by increasing access to water and nutrients [
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0182012.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Interestingly, the root/shoot ratio of 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic> seedlings declined with the decrease of soil moisture. Therefore, susceptibility to drought stress along with low phenotypic plasticity in a changing environment might be a major factor in the regeneration failure of 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic>.
</p>
