<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">First, for each of the 55 focal species, the models quantified individual species’ environmental envelope by estimating the best combination of environmental conditions, based on all of the parameters listed above, that describe its current global distribution. Sea surface and sea bottom environmental conditions were used for pelagic and demersal species, respectively. Second, we used these species-specific environmental envelopes to project the probability of occurrence of a given species in each spatial cell of the ocean according to environmental conditions associated with that cell. Third, using projected future sea surface temperature and salinity only, we projected ‘current’ (2000–2010), mid-21st century (2040–2050) and end of 21st century (2090–2100) species distributions, based on high-resolution modelled hydrological conditions (temperature and salinity) of the Gulf provided by the Regional Oceanographic Modelling group of the AGEDI LNRCC programme [
 <xref rid="pone.0194537.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The oceanographic model projected changes under the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5, representing a high-greenhouse-gas-emissions, business-as-usual scenario [
 <xref rid="pone.0194537.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. For the current period, we calculated the spatial anomalies of the high resolution (0.0275
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> latitude x 0.0275
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> longitude) model outputs over a coarser resolution grid (0.25
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> latitude x 0.25
 <sup class="sup">o</sup> longitude). We attempted to use the best available information to correct for systematic biases between the coarser global-scale and the finer local-scale environmental data. Mesoscale patterns that are represented in the finer resolution dataset may be smoothed out when the data were aggregated to the coarser resolution. However, such mesoscale patterns are unlikely to dramatically alter the pattern of changes in projected habitat suitability averaged at the Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ) levels in our vulnerability analysis. We then applied the spatial anomalies of both the current and future periods to the global environmental data described above to correct for the bias between modelled outputs and global data products from the synthesis of observational data. This procedure helped retain the high resolution spatial features of the model outputs. Next, we projected the spatial distribution of the 55 focal species using the three environmental niche models and the processed environmental model outputs (i.e., based on climatological annual averages of predicted changes in salinity and temperature). The projected current and future spatial distributions of each species were further limited to the known depth range of the species and their affinity to the coast.
</p>
