<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenotypic plasticity, the ability of organisms to adjust their phenotype to the environment, represents an important means by which organisms shift their phenology in response to environmental variation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. For example, anthropogenic change has made the climate more variable from year to year, thereby inducing selection for phenotypic plasticity in timing of breeding
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. This adaptive evolution of population-level phenotypic plasticity requires individual variation in plasticity; therefore, predictions of population or species persistence will require insights in the ecological processes maintaining this type of variation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the key factors influencing optimal timing of breeding is predation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> as it is postulated as a motivator for colonial and synchronous breeding
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. However, a key unresolved question is whether synchronization is an ultimate adaptive strategy (i.e., females choosing to breed at the same time as neighboring females), or rather a proximal result of a common response to an environmental cue (i.e., females all deciding to initiate breeding in the narrow window when conditions are good)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Predators can induce seasonal increases in predation, and therefore may induce synchrony (or asynchrony) by nature of their hunting strategy. For example, the European sparrowhawk (
  <span class="italic">Accipiter nisus</span>) hunts by surprise attack and times its reproduction to coincide with the peak of fledging of their passerine prey, such as great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Therefore, in the presence of sparrowhawk predators, great tit females may shift their timing of breeding in order to mismatch with the peak in sparrowhawk hunting. If all females respond by starting to breed at one particular time, synchrony may increase with predator presence. In our population, great tits respond to sparrowhawk cues (calls) by decreasing time invested in conspicuous behaviors (singing), and increasing time invested in vigilance (alarm calling)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Not all birds respond equally because individuals differ in heritable behaviors affecting predation risk, such as exploratory tendency assayed during short-term captivity (ranging from slow to fast behavior, with fast individuals being more likely to encounter predators and thus being more at-risk). For example, in response to predator cues, individuals improve maneuverability by decreasing body mass
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, which fast explorers (at-risk individuals) do more strongly than slow explorers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Therefore, we predicted that all individuals do not respond the same to predator presence, thereby potentially decreasing breeding synchrony. We studied the consequences of these behavioral strategies for timing of breeding using replicated multi-year spatiotemporal manipulations in the wild.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We manipulated perceived predation levels (PPLs) during spring and summer (March through July) among 12 nest box plots of great tits over a 2-year period (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). As a low-PPL treatment, we broadcast songs of a bird species, the common blackbird (
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>), which is neither a predator nor a competitor of great tits. As a high-PPL treatment, we broadcast calls of the European sparrowhawk. Our playback frequency matched natural vocalization frequencies, and we broadcast on a 4 day on 4-day off scheme to avoid habituation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Our playback design may have also altered individuals’ perception of temporal variance in risk, another factor influencing anti-predator behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>, although competing theories debate whether mean rather than variance is important for prey to interpret predator cues
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Birds decreased risky communication behaviors (detailed above) in the high-PPL treatment but actual predator numbers were not affected (based on weekly counts)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, verifying that our manipulations influenced perceived—not actual—predation levels. In this vein, our aim with this study is to determine how behavioral types differ in their adjustment of reproductive investment in response to perceived levels.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Experimental design. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Study area of 12 nest box plots (rectangular boxes) situated in Southern Germany. Colored great tit symbols represent each plot’s treatment (blue: low perceived predation level (PPL): orange: high PPL) in the first (left-hand bird) and second (right-hand bird) year of study. Scale bar is 1 km. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> The among-individual variance (
     <span class="italic">V</span>
     <sub>I</sub>), the residual within-individual variance (
     <span class="italic">V</span>
     <sub>e</sub>), and the cross-year repeatability (
     <div id="IEq1" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$R = \frac{{V_{\mathrm{I}}}}{{V_{\mathrm{I}} + V_{\mathrm{e}}}}$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M2" class="math">
        <span class="mi">R</span>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <div class="mfrac">
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">V</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">V</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">+</span>
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">V</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq1.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>) for timing of breeding (and other traits) were calculable for the low-PPL and high-PPL environment since six plots received the same treatment (3 low, 3 high) across years. The phenotypic cross-context correlation (
     <div id="IEq2" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$r_{{\mathrm{P}}_{{\mathrm{L}},{\mathrm{H}}}}$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M4" class="math">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">r</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">P</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">L</span>
            <span class="mo">,</span>
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq2.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>) between a female’s timing of breeding under low versus high PPL was calculated using data from six plots that changed treatment across years. This parameter represents an attenuated estimate of the among-individual cross-context correlation (
     <div id="IEq3" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M5" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$r_{{\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{L}},{\mathrm{H}}}}$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M6" class="math">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">r</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">L</span>
            <span class="mo">,</span>
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq3.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>) that our unique partial crossover study design allowed estimating (for details, see Methods). 
     <span class="bold">c</span> This in turn enabled us to differentiate between four distinct scenarios describing how individual reaction norms for timing of breeding (and other traits) varied as a function of PPL (detailed in main text). Those scenarios differed in whether treatment-specific among-individual variance was absent (
     <div id="IEq4" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M7" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$V_{{\mathrm{I}}_{\mathrm{L}}} = V_{{\mathrm{I}}_{\mathrm{H}}}$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M8" class="math">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">V</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">L</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">V</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq4.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>) versus present (
     <div id="IEq5" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M9" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$V_{{\mathrm{I}}_{\mathrm{L}}} \ne V_{{\mathrm{I}}_{\mathrm{H}}}$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M10" class="math">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">V</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">L</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">≠</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">V</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq5.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>) and whether reaction norm crossing was absent (
     <div id="IEq6" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M11" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$r_{{\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{L}},{\mathrm{H}}}} = 1$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M12" class="math">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">r</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">L</span>
            <span class="mo">,</span>
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <span class="mn">1</span>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq6.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>) versus present (
     <div id="IEq7" class="inline-formula">
      <div class="alternatives">
       <span id="M13" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$r_{{\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{L}},{\mathrm{H}}}} &lt; 1$$\end{document}</span>
       <div id="M14" class="math">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">r</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">L</span>
            <span class="mo">,</span>
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
        <span class="mn">1</span>
       </div>
       <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Article_IEq7.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      </div>
     </div>). Here we illustrate possible scenarios given the assumption that mean breeding date is similar in both contexts, and the variance is either the same or higher under high-PPL
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9138_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e568" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three plots received the low-PPL treatment in both years, three plots the high-PPL treatment in both years, and six plots changed treatment across years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). This partial crossover design allowed us to estimate the statistical parameters (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>) required for making inferences regarding how PPL treatment affected the relative timing of breeding among types of individuals (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>). Assuming that the sparrowhawk’s strategy is to produce nestlings when their prey would normally exhibit a peak in fledging production
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, PPL manipulations should increase PPL particularly for peak and late-breeding great tits. Thus, only individuals that shift to breed earlier are likely to reap a pay-off in decreased risk. Moreover, owing to optimal shifts in how vigilance-foraging trade-offs are resolved, increased PPL should also generally decrease investment in foraging, increasing relative costs of egg production, and decrease clutch size
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a null hypothesis, we considered that birds would not adjust timing of breeding as a function of PPL (scenario 1, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>). Alternatively, we expected that our manipulations of PPL would influence breeding decisions (scenarios 2–4, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>). First, birds might differ in how they modify timing of breeding as a function of PPL. Sparrowhawks induce temporal variation in predation danger, therefore, individuals may shift their breeding timing to avoid the predation peak. Though responding differently, individuals may respond such that individuals breeding relatively early under low PPL would still breed relatively early under high-PPL (scenario 2). Alternatively, as at-risk individuals would benefit most from advancing timing of breeding relative to other types, only they may alter their timing of breeding, resulting in crossing reaction norms (scenarios 3 and 4) and decreased breeding synchrony with increasing PPL (as in scenario 4). We predicted that increased PPL would affect the at-risk individuals more relative to other breeders, and thus expected to see results similar to scenario 3 or 4. Previous research implies that life-history trade-offs and spatiotemporal variation in social environments equalize long-term fitness associated with slow versus fast exploration behavior in wild great tit populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. We thus propose here that individual plasticity in timing of breeding constitutes a key adaptive component facilitating the coexistence of these alternative behavioral strategies.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We find that under low PPL, faster exploring birds breed later relative to slower exploring birds; and under high PPL the pattern is reversed and breeding synchrony decreases as a result. In addition, we find that the timing of breeding affects reproductive success, but that behavioral types have overall equal fitness by using alternative routes. We therefore conclude that these alternative behavioral strategies thus explain variation in phenology and plasticity in reproductive behavior, with implications for evolution.</p>
</sec>
