<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To assess associations with contemporary and historic climate, we obtained from the aforementioned maps climate variables for each sampling location. Tables S2 and S3 show climate data used for modeling prokaryotic communities in the Tibetan Plateau and in northern North America, respectively, and are available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dropbox.com/sh/erekiq5l29tvqfj/AAAH9MoPB31qa6_LFmpXIKbYa?dl=0" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.dropbox.com/sh/erekiq5l29tvqfj/AAAH9MoPB31qa6_LFmpXIKbYa?dl=0</ext-link>. To assess associations between contemporary prokaryotic distributions and contemporary and historic climate, we constructed regression models. We constructed separate models for the distributions of OTU richness and Shannon diversity and the relative abundance of all families (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 53) and OTUs (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 317) occurring in 40 or more samples. We used leave-one-out cross-validation to assess model performance and perform model selection. We performed all-subset model selection with all of the climatology dates. In the absence of any clear nonlinearity, we employed linear models to further minimize the risk of overfitting. Diversity response variables (richness and Shannon diversity) were log-transformed prior to modeling, and relative abundance response variables were logit-transformed. To assess robustness of our findings to modeling choices, we (i) repeated regression modeling with the original climatologies rather than PCs using a two-step variable selection procedure in which the top ∼5 variables were chosen using only 1960–1969 and contemporary climatologies and then all-subset model selection was performed over all time periods for these top variables (all-subsets is computationally impractical with 120 variables) and (ii) fitted gradient-boosted regression models with all PCs rather than performing all-subset model selection.
</p>
