<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The indicators for the freeze-up and breakup dates as a function of latitude were obtained by computing the empirical probability density function of the days at which a chosen threshold of 15% sea-ice cover was passed, counting all model grid points in the interval of 2° latitude. A positive transition indicated a freeze-up event, while a negative transition indicated a breakup event. The method is robust to the choice of the sea-ice variable because it gives the same results if sea-ice thickness with a threshold of 0.1 m is used. It is also not sensitive to the subjective choice of the thresholds as long as they are considered representative of low sea-ice conditions; a variation of ±50% around the chosen values did not lead to substantial changes in the overall statistics. To avoid counting successive events of melting and refreezing, it was decided to only consider the last melting event before the first freezing of the next sea-ice season and the last freezing event before the seasonal melting. During data collection, the algorithm also collected the area of the ocean (within the latitudinal band) that was characterized by first-year ice. The same algorithm was applied to the historical climate and future scenario simulations, as well as to satellite data for validation. Not all variables were available for all the models in the ESGF servers because of the recent overhauling (table S1). Given the use of empirical probability density functions, the medians and other statistical descriptors were nevertheless computed over a large number of data points. The CMIP5 daily variables considered were near-surface atmospheric temperature and sea-ice thickness, while snow depth was available from CMIP5 models on a monthly basis. All values not corresponding to a sea-ice–covered ocean were masked. The analysis was performed for first-year ice only, with 2° latitudinal bands from 58°N to 84°N. The latitudinal empirical probability density functions and the relative statistical descriptors (10th, 50th, and 90th percentiles) were computed for freeze-up day, breakup day, maximum sea-ice thickness, day of maximum sea-ice thickness, maximum snow depth, month of maximum snow depth, minimum near-surface temperature, and day of minimum near-surface temperature (see fig. S4 for an example). If the corresponding first day of sea ice fell within the same (or previous) month of the snow season starting, then we used that day as the starting day of the snow season and the sea-ice season. Otherwise, we used the first day of the following month for the snow season. For ascribing the last day of snow cover, if the snow season showed to end within the same month when sea ice vanished, then we chose the first day of the corresponding month, otherwise, we used the 15th of the previous month. The day of maximum snow depth was instead assumed to be the midmonth day of the corresponding month.</p>
