<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Incoming solar radiation was retrieved for both scenarios and at each considered latitude from the ERA-interim European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts climatological (1979–2010) downward surface solar radiation (
 <xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">56</italic>
 </xref>). The incoming radiation was converted to visible wavelengths (400 to 700 nm) and then to photosynthetically active radiation (PAR) and, lastly, was corrected for surface albedo and light extinction through snow and sea ice with a Semtner-like sea-ice thermodynamic model (
 <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">57</italic>
 </xref>). Because of the lack of information from CMIP5 models on sea-ice halodynamics, we limited our investigation to the biological production of the bottom sea-ice habitable space, operationally defined as the sea-ice biologically active layer (BAL) (
 <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">57</italic>
 </xref>). This layer comprises the permeable part of sea ice that extends from the bottom-most sea ice upward until the brines volume reaches the 5% limit. The BAL fraction can be calculated given its boundaries. At the lower sea-ice interface with the ocean, seawater is assumed to be at freezing point, and brine volume is considered to be at 100%, i.e., all medium is liquid. At the upper interface, the BAL is delimited by the brines volume being 5% at the maximum. Given the computation of sea-ice bulk salinity after (
 <xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">56</italic>
 </xref>), brine salinity and brine/sea-ice temperature were calculated from thermal equilibrium. Given the BAL sea-ice temperature, the dynamics of the BAL thickness were reconstructed with a cubic function, as done for sea-ice thickness. The computed physical variables needed by the ocean component of the biogeochemical model were seawater temperature, seawater salinity, wind speed, and PAR. The computed physical variables needed by the sea-ice component of the biogeochemical model were BAL thickness, temperature, bulk salinity, brine salinity, brine volume, and PAR.
</p>
