<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Meteorological conditions across Mullins and Friedman glaciers were monitored from 2008–2013 using automatic weather stations (AWS) at four locations
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). These stations recorded (1) total downwelling (global) short-wave solar radiation; (2) surface barometric pressure; (3) air temperature and relative humidity (RH) at ground level (5 cm) and mast height (1.8 m); and (4) mast height wind speed and direction. Each station sampled environmental conditions every 3 min and logged averages at 15 or 30 min intervals, for example, ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" class="xref">52</xref>. In addition, for the period 2010–2013, AWS01 (77.9096°S, 160.59789°E; 1,642 m MSL), located within the critical zone on Mullins glacier, employed a Kipp and Zonen CNR 4 net radiometer installed at mast height to record (6) total downwelling (global) short-wave solar radiation (enclosed thermopile pyranometer; measurement range of 0–2,000 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> and a resolution of &lt;1 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>), (7) upwelling short-wave solar radiation (enclosed thermopile pyranometer; measurement range of 0–2,000 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> and a resolution of &lt;1 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>), (8) downwelling longwave radiation (enclosed thermopile pyrgeometer, measurement range of −220 to +200 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>), (9) upwelling longwave radiation (enclosed thermopile pyrgeometer, measurement range of −220 to +200 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>), and (10) internal CNR4 housing temperature (Pt-100 thermistor). For this study, we use data from AWS01 during the period from 01/01/2011 to 12/31/2012 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). This two-year time interval displays the greatest overlap with nearby meteorological stations and shows minimal gaps due to intermittent sensor failure. On the basis of the strong consistency among data recorded at AWS01 and nearby AWS03, which itself has a 9-year continuous data set, as well as the minimal variation noted in annual weather conditions monitored at nearby long-term weather stations (∼30 years continuous data)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" class="xref">51</xref>, we conclude that our 2-year data inventory from AWS01 well represents modern conditions at our site. In addition, the strong similarity in data from AWS01—located in the critical zone of Mullins glacier, and AWS04 located at the same elevation in the critical zone of Friedman glacier (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>)—indicates that AWS 01 is representative of the critical zone meteorology on both glaciers.
</p>
