<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The approach shown here also allows an opportunity to explore the potential for competition for refugia sites among interacting organisms (as has been done much more extensively for lizards and snakes, e.g. 
 <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Goller 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref146" ref-type="bibr">Sears 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2016
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref100" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Alcaide 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2017
 </xref>). For example, 
 <xref rid="f12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref> shows the location of refugia available to an organism—for example a predator or dominant competitor—with a lower thermal optimum (here, T
 <sub>opt</sub> = 25°C) and lethal limit, vs. one by an organism with a higher thermal limit (T
 <sub>opt</sub> = 28°C), its prey. In this example, as in 
 <xref rid="f12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>, the predator/dominant competitor dominates in cooler microhabitats, and the prey/subordinate competitor can only persist in microrefugia that are unfavourable to the predator/competitive dominant (
 <xref rid="ref168" ref-type="bibr">Wethey, 1983</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref169" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>). Using a spatially explicit model for multiple species can be useful to predict patterns of vertical zonation that results from the interaction between the physical environment experienced by an organism and its physiological limits and biotic interactions (
 <xref rid="ref96" ref-type="bibr">Lewis, 1964</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Connell, 1972</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref168" ref-type="bibr">Wethey, 1983</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref169" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref153" ref-type="bibr">Somero, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Garza and Robles, 2010</xref>). For example in the Pacific coast of North America, the thermal limit of the seastar 
 <italic>Pisaster</italic> may prevent its excursion into the mid intertidal zone, where its prey (such as the mussel 
 <italic>Mytilus californianus</italic>) can then survive (
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Fly 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2012
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref119" ref-type="bibr">Monaco 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2015
 </xref>).
</p>
