<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We have three groups of key independent variables. Group One measures general conditions related to cranberry growing and contains 3 variables. 
 <italic class="italic">General conditions</italic> is a dummy variable that measures responses to the survey item “Over the past 5 to 10 years, how are conditions in general for cranberry growers?” (1 = getting worse, 0 = remaining the same or getting better). In the questionnaire, we provided 3 response categories: getting worse, remaining the same, and getting better. In the analyses, we combined the categories of remaining the same and getting better because only 5.5% of respondents chose getting better. It is impossible to know precisely what types of conditions growers referred to when they answered this survey question. Nevertheless we argue that it is acceptable to assume that this question primarily reflects growers' perceptions of an assortment of environmental conditions, and to a lesser extent, their perceptions of other, non-environmental conditions of cranberry production. This is because, first, we positioned this survey question amongst questions on specific environmental pressures/conditions. Thus, growers may have thought primarily of environmental conditions when they answered this question. Second, we calculated the bivariate correlations between the dummy variable on general condition and a series of variables measuring growers' perceptions of the severity of environmental pressure (12 variables) and non-environmental pressures (8 variables). The results show that a group of 5 variables on environmental pressures and only 1 variable on non-environmental pressures (i.e. the concern over price of cranberry) are significantly (a = 0.10) albeit weakly correlated with the variable on general conditions. None of the other variables examined are significantly correlated with the variable on general conditions and the magnitude of the correlations are weak. 
 <italic class="italic">Weather importance</italic> measures responses to the survey item “Have weather-related issues become more important (worse) over the past 5 to 10 years?” (1 to 5 scale: not important to very important). 
 <italic class="italic">Weather counts</italic> records the number of responses from each cranberry grower to the survey item “which of the following specific weather-related events severely impacted your cranberry production from 2010- present? Check all that apply.” Respondents chose from 6 answer categories: high precipitation in short amount of time, drought, summer heat wave (temperature above 90 for several days), warmer winter, hail or sudden frost event, and other. Respondents who chose “other” were invited to elaborate on their responses in the questionnaire; and all these respondents wrote salt-water incursion as their elaboration.
</p>
