<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The maximum entropy (MaxEnt) model, based upon the maximum entropy principle and using ‘presence-only’ species data (
 <xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Phillips, Anderson &amp; Schapire, 2006</xref>), has excellent predictive performance for threatened or range-restricted species (
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Elith et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hernandez et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans &amp; Graham, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pearson et al., 2007</xref>). We employed MaxEnt 3.4.1 for modelling. The responses of multivariate nonlinear models based on highly correlated climate variables can result in model overfitting (
 <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morlini, 2006</xref>), which will also occur when such models are applied to data outside the training conditions (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Graham, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morlini, 2006</xref>). To prevent multicollinearity and increase transferability effectiveness, we removed all environmental predictors with high pairwise correlation (Pearson’s correlation &gt; 0.85, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-6" class="xref">Table S1</xref>). Among highly correlated variables, we selected those with more direct physiologically roles in limiting the survival and reproduction of 
 <italic class="italic">P. amabilis</italic>. We also deleted climate variables with a relatively low percentage contribution to the model performance. The contribution of each climate variable was assessed by the Jackknife procedure in MaxEnt (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2" class="xref">Fig. S2</xref>). These operations created a model of better performance with a balance between an underfitted model with few parameters and an overfitted model with too many correlated explanatory variables (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burnham &amp; Anderson, 2002</xref>). The final set of selected bioclimatic variables included mean annual temperature (MAT, Bio1), temperature seasonality (TS; standard deviation of monthly mean temperature value, Bio4), min temperature of coldest month (MTCM, Bio6), mean temperature of driest quarter (MTDQ, Bio9), annual precipitation (AP, Bio12), precipitation of driest month (PDM, Bio14), precipitation of wettest quarter (PWeQ, Bio16) and precipitation of warmest quarter (PWaQ, Bio18).
</p>
