<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our environmental association tests can be considered robust to deviations from the underlying demographic structure, as candidate loci were intersected across different 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>‐values. Additionally, LFMM were calibrated based on the distribution of adjusted 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>‐values, so the incidence of false discovery rates was low (François et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Interestingly, we found latitudinal and altitudinal gradients in the distribution of adaptive genetic variation. While the former gradient was also found in the honeybee 
 <italic class="italic">A. mellifera</italic> (Chávez‐Galarza et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Henriques et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>), and is probably related to climatic conditions, the altitudinal gradient suggests different adaptations to current highland and lowland areas. Our findings thus reveal the presence of locally adapted bees, which should be preserved to maintain evolutionary potential (Hoffmann &amp; Sgrò, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Sgrò, Lowe, &amp; Hoffmann, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). While lowland populations of 
 <italic class="italic">M. subnitida</italic> are expected to shift to higher elevations by 2050 (Supporting Information Figure 
 <xref rid="eva12794-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S6</xref>), current highland populations are at risk, since highlands will have no climate analogs in the future (Colwell, Brehm, Cardelús, Gilman, &amp; Longino, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Giannini et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Conservation actions should thus prioritize the protection of current highland populations while improving the connectivity between highlands and lowlands, preserving or restoring foothill and mountain forests (Giannini et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
