<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33" class="p">Genuine assessments of the conservation status of species should be based on detailed evaluation under all of the five IUCN Red List criteria (A–E criteria
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>
 </sup>); however, the appropriate rating may be established if any one of the criteria is taken into account
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>
 </sup>. As detailed and reliable population-level data are generally lacking for many taxa, especially for tropical species as is the case of the Atlantic Forest snakes, it is not possible to meet the demands of all IUCN criteria. In this sense, the distribution area, the key parameter of B criterion, has been used to provide analyses on the conservation status of data-poor species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" class="xref">118</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" class="xref">120</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, from the individual range of each species in current and future times, it was possible to estimate the conservation status of snake species of the Atlantic Forest at the end of this century, according to the Sub criterion B1 (extent of occurrence – EOO). Thus, based on distribution data resulting from future climate shifts, we proposed the following threat categories in a regional context: 1. Extinct (EX): occurrence = 0 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>; 2. Critically Endangered (CR): occurrence &lt; 100 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>; 3. Endangered (EN): occurrence &lt; 5,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>; 4. Vulnerable (VU): occurrence &lt; 20,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>; 5. Nonthreatened (NT): occurrence &gt; 20,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. It is important to emphasize that this classification is not intended to provide the current conservation status of the Atlantic Forest snakes, but rather it provides the first indication of a future condition imposed by redistribution of species in response to climate change.
</p>
