<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because &gt;80% of female hawksbills in the eastern Pacific nest along low‐relief beaches on islands and peninsulas within mangrove estuaries (Gaos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Liles, Peterson, Seminoff, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015b</xref>), climate‐driven sea‐level rise threatens viability of current nesting beaches. Global mean sea level is projected to rise between 0.26 and 0.98 m (Church, Clark, &amp; Cazenave, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), but to as high as 1.14 m when accounting for Greenland and Antarctica ice loss (DeConto &amp; Pollard, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), by 2100. Under sea‐level rise scenarios of 0.1, 0.5, and 0.9 m, Fish et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) estimated that 4%, 26%, and 51% of total beach area, respectively, would be submerged from 11 low‐elevation beaches (1.25–3.09 m) with gentle slope (1.8–5.8°) used by nesting hawksbills on Barbados (Caribbean), with similar estimates (i.e., 14%, 31%, and 51%, respectively) for 13 low‐relief hawksbill nesting beaches on Bonaire (Caribbean; Fish et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Given that most hawksbill nesting beaches at Bahía de Jiquilisco and Estero Padre Ramos have an elevation of ≤1 m above mean sea level with marginal slope (&lt;2°), beach loss of 4%–51% likely represents a conservative estimate for our sites under sea‐level rise scenarios of 0.1–0.9 m by 2100. Indeed, vulnerability of nesting beaches to sea‐level rise was exemplified by a flooding event that occurred at Bahía de Jiquilisco in 2015, where all eight nesting beaches were temporarily inundated from extraordinarily high tides and precipitation, resulting in total mortality of 30 hawksbill clutches.
</p>
