<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Some turtle populations appear to be capable of spatially adapting nest placement to align the current thermal niche of the nest environment with changing climatic conditions, whereas others seem relatively inflexible. For example, female painted turtles from five distinct populations across their geographic range that were translocated to a common environment differed in choice of nesting date and nest depth, but did not differ in shade cover, resulting in similar incubation regimes across populations despite differences in local climate at their locations of origin (Refsnider &amp; Janzen, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In contrast, individual hawksbills in the Caribbean are highly consistent in their nest microhabitat preferences, including vegetative cover above nests within and between years (Kamel &amp; Mrosovsky, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006b</xref>), suggesting that female hawksbills are relatively constrained in their ability to alter nesting behavior (Kamel, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Although hawksbills at Bahía de Jiquilisco and Estero Padre Ramos are highly consistent in their selection of vegetative cover, they exhibit locally specific adaptations shaped by microhabitat differences at each site (Liles, Peterson, Seminoff, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015b</xref>). For example, nest placement by hawksbills at Bahía de Jiquilisco is restricted to the narrow tract of secondary forest measuring 10–15 m wide adjacent to the high water line at most beaches, whereas nest placement at Estero Padre Ramos extends nearly twice the distance inland within intact second‐growth forest that is present &gt;100 m landward from the high water line at most beaches (Liles, Peterson, Seminoff, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015b</xref>). Such adaptations may indicate the potential for development of compensatory responses to climate variability through nest‐site choice.
</p>
