<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The accelerated rate at which climate change is projected to occur, together with other interacting anthropogenic threats, may outpace the biological capacity of sea turtles to adapt (Fuentes, Hamann, &amp; Limpus, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). The inability of sea turtles to adaptively respond through behavioral or evolutionary mechanisms (e.g., adjust pivotal temperature; Davenport, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1989</xref>) would require that humans intervene to prevent local extinctions, such as watering, shading, and clutch relocation to modify sand temperatures and reduce egg and hatchling mortality (Hill et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Jourdan &amp; Fuentes, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Wood et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Indeed, we found that hawksbill clutches relocated on the beach and protected in shaded hatcheries had higher hatching success, produced higher proportions of male offspring, and produced fitter hatchlings than clutches protected in situ at Bahía de Jiquilisco and Estero Padre Ramos. However, we are not suggesting egg relocation as a panacea that should be employed without careful consideration of local conditions, species biology, and conservation objectives. Previous studies have highlighted negative consequences of hatcheries using poor management practices, such as low hatching success (Boulon, Dutton, &amp; Mcdonald, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>), biased sex ratios of hatchlings (Morreale, Ruiz, Spotila, &amp; Standora, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1982</xref>), and increased hatchling mortality (Pilcher &amp; Enderby, 
 <xref rid="ece34774-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). We contend, however, that egg relocation can contribute substantively to recovery efforts under appropriate circumstances. Our results underscore the importance of empirical assessments to evaluate potential mitigation strategies for severely depleted populations of highly endangered species that may be unable to respond sufficiently to climate change.
</p>
