<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15" class="p">The key finding of this study is the dominant (spatial) impact of soil organic matter on soil thermal diffusivity (
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>) supported by empirical evidence, which is shown in model simulations to affect the broad-scale soil thermodynamics and in turn affects the soil organic carbon (SOC) accumulation. Thermal mediation of soil organic layer is known to stabilize the underlying permafrost in relatively warm regions where the climate alone cannot sustain the persistence of permafrost
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. Here we provide a quantitative empirical estimate for the insulation effect of SOC through its impact on 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. We recognize that, apart from heat conduction controlled by 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>, the latent heat associated with soil water/ice phase changes could be substantial in the soil energy budget, especially on the border of permafrost zones (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>), which complicates the permafrost stability. This latent heat could partly explain the slower warming rate of the mean annual permafrost temperature in discontinuous zones during the past decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>. However, this latent heat effect delays but does not prevent the eventual permafrost thawing
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>. Under the long-term climate warming, as permafrost might greatly retreat poleward
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>, heat conduction would finally dominate, inferred from the cold sites outside the permafrost regions today (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>); and the SOC-
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> relationship suggests a significant impact of changes in SOC on soil temperature in the former permafrost regions.
</p>
