<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">The implication of such SOC-
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> feedback for future permafrost dynamics, therefore, depends on the direction and magnitude of soil carbon changes in the future. Although enzyme kinetics theory and short-term observations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> suggest an initially increasing SOC decomposition rate with warming, large uncertainties still remain in the long-term response of soil carbon to climate change, due to uncertainties in the rate of SOC formation (including changes of plant productivity, soil-aggregate formation, etc.)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> and in microbial physiological changes/adaptation to warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. A recent compilation of field warming studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup> showed diverging changes in SOC stock of top 10 cm depth after warming, with statistically neutral change across all studies. These studies are, however, limited by a generally shallow depths of warming treatment, which missed the response of subsoils
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>; as well as a paucity of measurements for SOC stock changes at deeper soil horizons
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>, especially for the formerly frozen soils. Laboratory incubation experiments, though, have demonstrated a high lability of permafrost soils under unfrozen conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. On the other hand, modeling studies mostly projected carbon losses in permafrost soils in the long run, albeit varying rates and magnitudes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. The protection of permafrost by SOC is also manifested in fire disturbances, where the combustion of surface organic layer led to increased soil temperature and deeper thaw depth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, the projected increase in fire activities in the northern high latitudes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup> might also be an important driver of permafrost thaw through the impact of SOC on soil thermal properties.
</p>
