<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study site and treatments</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was conducted at the Columbia Basin Agricultural Research Center (CBARC) near Pendleton, OR, USA (45°42′N, 118°36′W, and 438 m elevation). The study area has a Mediterranean-type climate with cool wet winters and hot, dry summers. The 83-year average (1931–2013) annual precipitation was 421 mm, and the maximum and minimum temperatures were 17.6 and 3.04 °C, respectively (Table 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">S4</a>). About 70% of the total annual precipitation occurs between September and March
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
   </span>. All the experimental plots were within 500-m distance from each other and had similar soil characteristics; soils are classified as a Walla Walla silt loam (coarse-silty, mixed, superactive, mesic Typic Haploxerolls), which is generally a well-drained soil consisting of loess deposits overlying basalt
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil samples for this study were collected from selected long-term plots of the PLTEs. The treatments selected represented management practices differing in soil disturbance, cropping intensity, and SOC concentration (Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). The perennial grass pasture (GP) field was established in 1931 and has not been disturbed since then. The GP plot was a 46 × 109 m field with native grasses such as blue-bunch wheatgrass (
   <span class="italic">Agropyron spicatum</span> Pursh) and Idaho fescue (
   <span class="italic">Festuca idahoensis</span> Elmer) as dominant species. The GP received occasional controlled light grazing until 1985 and has not been grazed since then, but no external fertilizer or biomass inputs have been applied since 1931. Vegetation was sometimes clipped after summer to allow plant regrowth in the following season. The winter wheat-pea rotations (WP-CT and WP-NT) were established in 1964 as a part of a randomized complete block experiment with four replications. Both phases of crop rotations were present each year, allowing for collection of agronomic and environmental data for each crop every year. Tillage management has been modified over time as new tillage equipment became available
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. The WP-CT plots were tilled five to six times within a two-year crop cycle. These plots were moldboard plowed in the fall to a depth of 15 to 18 cm followed by secondary tillage to a depth of approximately 10 cm. Pea plots were cultivated one to three times annually to a depth of approximately 10 cm with a spring-tooth cultivator (John Deere CC, Moline, IL) and the plots were roller-packed using a Dunham Culti-packer (Dunham Co., Dunham, OH) after planting pea. The WP-NT plots were mowed after harvest and surface tilled to a depth of 3–4 cm using a Dunham skew-treader (Dunham Co., Dunham, OH) to breakdown wheat residues to facilitate pea sowing. No mowing or skew-treading was done before sowing wheat into the pea stubble. Herbicides were applied as needed to control weeds in WP-CT and WP-NT plots. The conventionally tilled winter wheat-summer fallow (WF-CT) treatment was established in 1940 and has used moldboard plow tillage since then
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. These plots were part of another randomized complete block experiment with three replications. Primary tillage in the WF-CT was implemented in the spring (late March to early April) of the fallow year. Soils were tilled to a depth of 20 cm, leaving about 7% residue cover. The WF-CT plots were cultivated to a depth of 10 to 15 cm using a field cultivator and harrow. These plots receive five to six tillage passes in a crop rotation cycle.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil sampling and laboratory analysis</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil cores were collected from 0–10 cm and 10–20 cm depths of the WP-CT, WP-NT, and WF-CT cropping systems and from three randomly selected three locations within the GP field using a core sampler (inner diameter 1.85 cm) in summer of 2015. At least four soil cores were collected from each plot, composited by depth increment, thoroughly homogenized, and brought to the laboratory for long-term incubation as well as for soil microbial biomass, SOC, N, and soil pH analyses.</p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the laboratory, soil samples were stored in a refrigerator (4 °C) for soil microbial biomass and potential soil C mineralization (SCM) measurements. All visible plant materials (roots, stems, and leaves) and crop residues were removed, and the soil was sieved using a 2-mm sieve before laboratory analysis. Soil water content was determined gravimetrically by oven drying 10-g soil samples at 105 °C for 24 hr and water content was calculated as a difference between the wet and dry weight of soil samples. Soil pH was measured using an Orion Star A215 pH/conductivity meter (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Beverly, MA, USA) on 1:2 soil to 0.01 M CaCl
   <sub>2</sub> extracts after a 30-min equilibration time
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. Total C and N contents were determined by dry combustion analysis (Flash EA 1112 series, Thermo Finnigan, San Jose, CA) of oven-dried (60 °C, 72 hr) and finely ground (&lt;0.05 mm) soil samples. Soils were ground in a Shatter 1 Box 8530 ball mill (Spex Sample Prep., Metuchen, NJ) for 2 min. Soil pH, which was less than 6.6 in all samples, was used to indirectly detect inorganic C. Studies show that total C in soils with pH &lt; 7.4 is mostly SOC
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span>. Therefore, total C content in soil was considered to be SOC. Soil inorganic N was analyzed as the sum of KCl- extractable NO
   <sub>3</sub>
   <span class="sup">−</span>N and NH
   <sub>4</sub>-N in an autoanalyzer (Astoria-Pacific, Inc. Clackamas, OR). For this, 5 g of soil were extracted with 25 ml of 1 M KCl solution. Soil microbial biomass C (MBC) was determined by the fumigation incubation method
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span> in which approximately a 10-g soil (dry weight equivalent) sample was fumigated in a vacuum desiccator for 48 hr using chloroform, and the samples were incubated for a week in 1-L glass jars. The headspace CO
   <sub>2</sub>-C released from samples during a week-long incubation was determined by a single-cell IRGA system (specifically, the LI-820 CO
   <sub>2</sub> analyzer by LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>. An efficiency factor of 0.41 was used for MBC calculations without subtracting to non-fumigated control
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. Long-term soil C mineralization was analyzed by aerobic incubation of approximately 20 g of soil in 1-L glass jars for 70 days, and CO
   <sub>2</sub>-C released from the incubated samples were measured in LI-820. For this, soil samples were weighed in plastic specimen cups, brought to field capacity (23% g/g water content), and incubated at 20 °C and 30 °C in an HC30 accelerated aging chamber incubator (Hoffman Manufacturing, Inc. Corvallis, OR) in a dark place, and CO
   <sub>2</sub>-C released from the soil samples was measured with LI-820 after 24 h, 3 days, 8 days, and 14 days, and on a weekly interval thereafter. After each gas sampling, CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration and air pressure were re-equilibrated by opening the lids of incubation jars and flushing with a vacuum air pump (Ted Pella Inc. Redding, CA). The specimen cups were weighed every week to determine the soil moisture loss, and the soil water content was brought to 23% by adding deionized water. The SNM was determined as inorganic N on soil samples incubated for SCM. The selected incubation temperature for SCM and SNM represents the maximum possible increases in soil temperature in the IPNW region of USA
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span>. These temperatures are close to long-term annual average soil surface air temperature (19.6 °C) and a maximum summer soil surface air temperature (29.3 °C, i.e., long-term average of June-August) at the experimental site.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis and modeling</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data for soil properties were tested for normality and homogeneity of variance and analyzed statistically by using a MIXED procedure of SAS for randomized complete block experiments with a split-plot arrangement (v.9.3, SAS Institute, Cary, NC). Soil pH, SOC, TN, inorganic N, and MBC data were analyzed considering treatments as the main plot (fixed) factor, soil depths as a split-plot (fixed) factor, and replication as a random factor. Cumulative SCM and SNM data were analyzed using treatments, incubation temperature, and soil depths as fixed factors and replication as a random factor. Since SOC and TN contents in soil were not consistent in all treatments, the cumulative SCM and SNM data were normalized to SOC and TN content, respectively, and analyzed using the same procedure. Treatment means differing in F-test were separated using the LSMEAN procedure of SAS. Statistical significance was evaluated at 
   <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.05 unless otherwise stated. Additionally, the observed SOC mineralization rates (
   <span class="italic">C</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">min</span>
   </sub>) after 70 days of incubation were fitted to the first-order kinetic model that describes SOC mineralization as a function of labile SOC content and decomposition time.
   <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">1</span>
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${C}_{min}={C}_{0}.{t}^{-k}$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">C</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">m</span>
        <span class="mi">i</span>
        <span class="mi">n</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">C</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mn">0</span>
        <span width=".25em" class="mspace"/>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">.</span>
      <div class="msup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">t</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">−</span>
        <span class="mi">k</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48237_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>where, 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">min</span>
   </sub> is SOC mineralization rate, 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
   <sub>0</sub> is the labile pool SOC (mg C kg
   <span class="sup">−1</span>), 
   <span class="italic">k</span> is the decomposition rate constant (
   <span class="italic">day</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <span class="italic">−1</span>
   </span>), and 
   <span class="italic">t</span> is the decomposition time in days. The model parameters were estimated by pooling the observed SOC mineralization data over three replications. Model performance under each treatment variable was compared using Pearson’s correlation coefficient (
   <span class="italic">r</span>) between the observed and predicted values, RMSE, and NRMSE. The RMSE was estimated as a mean squared error between the model-predicted values and the observed values, and NRMSE as a RMSE value standardized with the means of the observed values
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span>. A good model fit has a greater 
   <span class="italic">r</span> value and lower RMSE and NRMSE.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
