<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study site and treatments</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was conducted at the Columbia Basin Agricultural Research Center (CBARC) near Pendleton, OR, USA (45°42′N, 118°36′W, and 438 m elevation). The study area has a Mediterranean-type climate with cool wet winters and hot, dry summers. The 83-year average (1931–2013) annual precipitation was 421 mm, and the maximum and minimum temperatures were 17.6 and 3.04 °C, respectively (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">S4</a>). About 70% of the total annual precipitation occurs between September and March
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. All the experimental plots were within 500-m distance from each other and had similar soil characteristics; soils are classified as a Walla Walla silt loam (coarse-silty, mixed, superactive, mesic Typic Haploxerolls), which is generally a well-drained soil consisting of loess deposits overlying basalt
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil samples for this study were collected from selected long-term plots of the PLTEs. The treatments selected represented management practices differing in soil disturbance, cropping intensity, and SOC concentration (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). The perennial grass pasture (GP) field was established in 1931 and has not been disturbed since then. The GP plot was a 46 × 109 m field with native grasses such as blue-bunch wheatgrass (
  <span class="italic">Agropyron spicatum</span> Pursh) and Idaho fescue (
  <span class="italic">Festuca idahoensis</span> Elmer) as dominant species. The GP received occasional controlled light grazing until 1985 and has not been grazed since then, but no external fertilizer or biomass inputs have been applied since 1931. Vegetation was sometimes clipped after summer to allow plant regrowth in the following season. The winter wheat-pea rotations (WP-CT and WP-NT) were established in 1964 as a part of a randomized complete block experiment with four replications. Both phases of crop rotations were present each year, allowing for collection of agronomic and environmental data for each crop every year. Tillage management has been modified over time as new tillage equipment became available
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. The WP-CT plots were tilled five to six times within a two-year crop cycle. These plots were moldboard plowed in the fall to a depth of 15 to 18 cm followed by secondary tillage to a depth of approximately 10 cm. Pea plots were cultivated one to three times annually to a depth of approximately 10 cm with a spring-tooth cultivator (John Deere CC, Moline, IL) and the plots were roller-packed using a Dunham Culti-packer (Dunham Co., Dunham, OH) after planting pea. The WP-NT plots were mowed after harvest and surface tilled to a depth of 3–4 cm using a Dunham skew-treader (Dunham Co., Dunham, OH) to breakdown wheat residues to facilitate pea sowing. No mowing or skew-treading was done before sowing wheat into the pea stubble. Herbicides were applied as needed to control weeds in WP-CT and WP-NT plots. The conventionally tilled winter wheat-summer fallow (WF-CT) treatment was established in 1940 and has used moldboard plow tillage since then
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. These plots were part of another randomized complete block experiment with three replications. Primary tillage in the WF-CT was implemented in the spring (late March to early April) of the fallow year. Soils were tilled to a depth of 20 cm, leaving about 7% residue cover. The WF-CT plots were cultivated to a depth of 10 to 15 cm using a field cultivator and harrow. These plots receive five to six tillage passes in a crop rotation cycle.
 </p>
</sec>
