<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AFLP profiling and data analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We chose to use AFLPs in our study because, while we are well aware of their limitaions [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref042">42</a>] and the fact that hypervariable genetic markers would have been preferable [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref043">43</a>], we are working on species without genomic resources to refer to (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref044">44</a>]). AFLPs have been shown to be a cost-effective and rapid tool for generating many polymorphic loci useful for inferring population genetic structure of species [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref045">45</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref047">47</a>]. While we may not have achieved the precison we could have using more sensitive molecular markers, we believe our data to be important and a significant contribution to what is known about amphibian population genetic diversity in West Africa. Moreover, an added advantage of using AFLPs is that it allowed us to make direct comparisons with other African studies [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref046">46</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref048">48</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref049">49</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We extracted genomic DNA from tissue samples using a modified CTAB (cetyltrimethylammonium bromide) protocol [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref050">50</a>] and developed AFLPs based on Vos et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref051">51</a>] with minor modifications. We used the two enzymes EcoRI and MseI to conduct digestion of genomic DNA. We then ligated fragments to double-stranded adaptors with T4 DNA ligase. For pre-selective PCR, we used primers complementary to the Eco RI with no added nucleotides and MseI+A. For the selective PCR, we used two pairs primers: ESP1B / MSP3 and ESP1B / MSP6 (
  <a rid="pone.0202010.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0202010.t002">Table 2</a>). The EcoRI selective primer, ESP1B, was labelled with a fluorescent dye (either 6-FAM or VIC, Applied Biosystems) and contained three selective bases, whereas MSP3 and MSP6 (MseI selective primers) contained four bases of extension each (
  <a rid="pone.0202010.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0202010.t002">Table 2</a>). We ran the selectively amplified fragments on an ABI 3130xl Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems) with Gene-Scan LIZ size standard (Applied Biosystems). Finally, we visualized AFLP fragments with GENEMAPPER 4 (Applied Biosystems) in which peaks were called using the default settings except for the peak height detection which was set at 100 Relative Fluorescent Units (RFU). It was assumed that each peak represents a different locus. The threshold intensity for a peak being considered a locus was 100 RFU with a length at least 100 bp. Above 300 bp the resolution was such that it was not possible to accurately identify peaks, so that only peaks between 100-300bp were included in the analysis. The presence or absence of all fragments was confirmed manually. Following Stölting et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref052">52</a>] markers were scored for all the individuals in the same analysis session to prevent scoring errors when analyzing several groups of samples.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0202010.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0202010.t002</span>
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Restriction enzymes, adapters and primers sequences used on the AFLP procedure.</div>
   <p>*Labeled with fluorescence.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0202010.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0202010.t002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5’-3’)</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restriction enzymes</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EcoRI
       <span class="break"/>MseI
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="monospace">G^AATTC</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">CTTAA^G</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">T^TAA</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">AAT^T</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adapters</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EA2
       <span class="break"/>EA3
       <span class="break"/>MA1
       <span class="break"/>MA2
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="monospace">CTCGTAGACTGCGTACC</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">AATTGGTACGCAGTCTAC</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">GACGATGAGTCCTGAG</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">TACTCAGGACTCAT</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-selective primers</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENP
       <span class="break"/>MNP
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="monospace">GACTGCGTACCAATT</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">GATGAGTCCTGAGTAA</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selective Primers</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESP1B
       <span class="break"/>MSP3
       <span class="break"/>MSP6
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="monospace">GACTGCGTACCAATTCAG*</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">GATGAGTCCTGAGTAACGAT</span>
       <span class="break"/>
       <span class="monospace">GATGAGTCCTGAGTAACCTC</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted reproducibility tests by replicating samples, as suggested by Bonin et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref053">53</a>] and Meudt and Clarke [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref054">54</a>]. As recommended, we replicated analyses for a subset of samples (ideally 5–10% of the total number of samples) to detect fragments producing erratic patterns. To do so, we randomly selected 5% of the samples for each preferred primer combination for duplication and then assessed the error rate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the fact that mitochondrial 16S DNA sequences of selected individuals from Ngel Nyaki for both 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">schioetzi</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">bicolor</span> are less than 2% divergent from populations on Mount Oku in the Cameroonian mountains (unpublished data), similar to 
  <span class="italic">Arthroleptis palava</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref031">31</a>], we are confident that genetic differences observed on the Mambilla Plateau are due to population-level differences rather than cryptic species.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic diversity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used GenAlEx v6.5 [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref055">55</a>] to perform frequency and distance-based analyses. Allelic frequencies were estimated following the method of Lynch and Milligan [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref056">56</a>], assuming independent nuclear loci and Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium within populations. The expected Heterozygosity (
   <span class="italic">H</span>
   <sub>E</sub>) was calculated as 2(p)(q) implemented for diploid binary data (dominant markers) and assuming random mating, where q = (1—Band Frequency)^0.5 and p = 1—q.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We converted genetic data into a pairwise individual-by-individual genetic distance matrix and used this to assess genetic structure within populations. This is a true Euclidean metric [see 
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref055">55</a>] as required for the subsequent analysis of molecular variance.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluating the population genetic structure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We performed an Analysis of Molecular Variance (AMOVA) to investigate the hierarchical partitioning of genetic variation among populations and estimate the population genetic differentiation via Φ
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">PT</span>
   </sub>. To do this, each of the sampling sites were treated as populations (other hierarchical analysis such as different groups of fragments or regions were not performed). Φ
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">PT</span>
   </sub> is analogous to 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">ST</span>
   </sub> and used for dominant markers such as AFLP [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref057">57</a>]. This measure was calculated as 
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">AP</span>
   </sub> ⁄ (
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">AP</span>
   </sub> + 
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">WP</span>
   </sub>), where 
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">AP</span>
   </sub> is the variance among populations and 
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">WP</span>
   </sub> the variance within populations. We tested for statistical significance of the Φ
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">PT</span>
   </sub> values using a nonparametric permutation method [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref058">58</a>] with the number of permutations set to 999. By testing significance of the variance components and Φ statistic through a permutational approach removes the assumption of normality, which is unsuitable for molecular data [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref058">58</a>]. Significance levels following corrections for multiple comparisons via Bonferroni tests [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref059">59</a>] were conducted.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last, we investigated population genetic structure using the Bayesian model-based clustering algorithms implemented in STRUCTURE v2.3.3 [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref060">60</a>]. STRUCTURE uses a Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm to cluster individuals into populations based on their genotypes. It generates posterior probabilities of assignment of individuals to each of a given number of 
   <span class="italic">K</span> groups or populations regardless of their site of origin [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref060">60</a>]. For each species, we first ran STRUCTURE on all populations across the entire study area using the admixture model (no prior information) with correlated allele frquencies. We then used the population data (sampling sites) as prior information (LOCPRIOR) to assist the clustering as recommended when the signal of structure is weak [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref060">60</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref061">61</a>]. For both species, a range of 
   <span class="italic">K</span> values from 1 to 10 was performed. We ran batches of five independent runs with a burn-in of 100,000 and 500,000 iterations for each of the 
   <span class="italic">K</span> values. We calculated the ‘optimal’ 
   <span class="italic">K</span> (the number of genetic clusters that best fits these data) using the web version of STRUCTURE HARVESTER [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref062">62</a>]. Below, we report estimates for 
   <span class="italic">K</span> using two methods: (1) the log posterior probability of the data Ln(
   <span class="italic">K</span>) given 
   <span class="italic">K</span> genetic clusters [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref060">60</a>] and (2) Δ
   <span class="italic">K</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref063">63</a>], which is based on the rate of change in the log probability of data between successive 
   <span class="italic">K</span> values.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test for migration within each species, we used STRUCTURE to identify immigrants or individuals with recent immigrant ancestry in the last two generations. The model for this analysis uses population information with correlated allele frequencies. The model was set to GENSBACK = 2 and MIGRPRIOR = 0.001, as suggested by Falush et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref064">64</a>]. Thus, the prior probability that an individual has pure ancestry from its predefined population is 0.999.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the pattern of isolation by distance, we tested for correlation between matrices of geographic and genetic distances (Φ
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">PT</span>
   </sub> pairwise
   <sub>)</sub> using a Mantel test as implemented in GenAlEx v6.5.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although both GenAlEx and STRUCTURE can accommodate missing data, we removed missing genotypes from the analyses for the two preferred combinations of primers for both species in all analyses. Missing data may be problematic for some pairwise distance-based analyses implemented in GenAlEx [
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref065">65</a>]. While GenAlEx provides an option for interpolating the genetic distance for missing loci (by inserting the average genetic distances for each population level pairwise contrast, that is, within a population, or between two populations), we prevent any possible bias by eliminating the missing data from our analyses [see 
   <a rid="pone.0202010.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref055">55</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
