<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for conservation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results contribute to the relatively limited body of knowledge of dispersal in modified landscapes for African amphibians [e.g., 18,81]. Our results suggest that despite considerable habitat degradation (especially in the riparian fragments) gene flow is still occurring (or occurred recently) among forest patches in two Afromontane frog species. This illustrates the importance of these degraded riparian forest fragments to amphibian communities.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Nigeria and all along the Cameroon Volcanic Line [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref088">88</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref089">89</a>], as elsewhere in the tropics [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref090">90</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref091">91</a>], the survival of riparian forest fragments is under threat. Often fragments are not given the official protection garnered by larger patches of continuous forest [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref092">92</a>] with disasterous consequences [
  <a rid="pone.0202010.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202010.ref093">93</a>]. Evidence that these fragments not only harbour biodiversity but also have on-going gene-flow with neighboring continuous forest may provide added leverage to conservation practitioners aiming to protect isolated populations in forest fragments. On the Mambilla Plateau of eatern Nigeria, conservation efforts should focus not only on the existing Ngel Nyaki and Kurmin Danko Forest Reserves but also the small riparian forest fragments on the periphery of these forests as well as the many more like them across the mountains of Cameroon and Nigeria.
 </p>
</sec>
