<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We will use the term “anomalies” to refer to the variability component of the time series. The trend 
 <bold class="bold">
  <italic class="italic">x</italic>
 </bold>
 <sub class="sub">
  <bold class="bold">
   <italic class="italic">i</italic>
  </bold>
 </sub> can be either a linear trend, or a more flexible nonlinear trend obtained, for example, from robust locally weighted regression [
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. We assume that this decomposition is deterministic, unique, and is performed before the start of the main analysis. We also assume that the estimate of the trend is a reasonable proxy for the true unknown trend. While it may be possible to also incorporate the uncertainty in this decomposition, we leave it to future work. The focus here is not on how to properly decompose a time series into a long-term trend and variability, but on the novel methodology for weighting by performance in both. See [
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] for an example of use of an alternative methodology to decompose the data. The use of alternative methods for data decomposition is subject of future research. We describe the decomposition method we use for each dataset in Section 3. The same decomposition is also applied to the observed time series 
 <bold class="bold">
  <italic class="italic">y'</italic>
 </bold>: 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0214535.e004" class="disp-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0214535.e004.jpg" id="pone.0214535.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M4" class="math">
    <msup class="msup">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">'</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msup>
    <mo class="mo">=</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</mi>
    <mo class="mo">+</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">Δ</mi>
    <mi mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</mi>
    <mo class="mo">.</mo>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
  <label class="label">(3)</label>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
