<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted a “common garden” experiment at two sites over 10 years, which created different ecosystems by exchanging plants (same species) and soil between sites, while removing or allowing herbivory, to examine ecosystem functioning (N cycling and ANPP). While experimental ecosystems have been studied, e.g.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, we believe this to be the first 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> field experiment to examine the independent role of abiotic and biotic factors relative to the natural systems. The two sites reflect different microclimates: the 10 years of different weather, and the two site’s different soil moisture and nitrogen properties—abiotic conditions. The plants from each site and absence/presence of herbivory reflect different biotic food web conditions.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Without grasshoppers</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Without herbivory, as traditionally expected
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
   </span>, N cycling and ANPP were driven solely by abiotic conditions (site, year and soil) and the only available biotic factor, plant source, had no effect. One site (B) was 26% more productive due to having greater nitrogen availability, while inter-annual variability in productivity and soil effects were driven by moisture. N may limit ANPP more than moisture, as the more productive site (B) had greater N, but less moisture, than the other site (A). This is consistent with experimental supplementation of N at both sites, that found N to limit ANPP
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
   </span>. In summary, without herbivory (no grasshoppers), the traditional view that ANPP primarily is driven abiotically by microclimate (site), annual weather (year), and soil is supported.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With grasshoppers</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With herbivory (grasshoppers), the relative productivity of the two sites reversed; so the less productive site in the absence of herbivory had a 6% increase in ANPP but was now 15% more productive than the more productive site in the absence of herbivory, which had a 33% decline in ANPP. This occurred even though the more productive site in the absence of herbivory experienced 55% less herbivory (lower grasshopper density).</p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reversal was due to changes in litter decomposition due to herbivory. Litter decomposition rate is biotically affected by the plant species comprising the litter. 
   <span class="italic">P. pratensis</span> litter decomposes faster than 
   <span class="italic">P. smithii</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
   </span> litter, so percent of litter remaining will decrease and N will increase as relative abundance of 
   <span class="italic">P. pratensis</span> litter increases. Grasshopper selective feeding enhanced N at the originally less productive site (A) by increasing the relative abundance of faster decomposing plants (
   <span class="italic">P. pratensis</span>), and diminished N at the originally more productive site (B) by increasing the relative abundance of slower decomposing plants (
   <span class="italic">P. smithii</span>). Preferential feeding arises because grasshoppers prefer green vegetation that is lower in water content, so 
   <span class="italic">P. pratensis</span> at Site B is preferred, while 
   <span class="italic">P. smithii</span> is preferred at Site A
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With herbivory, we also observed that the plant species from the different sites were locally adapted to herbivory, even though they are the same species, with the plants from the site (A) where the herbivore was consistently more abundant being able to cope better with herbivory. A number of field experiments have reported on the importance of local adaptation of plants to herbivory, e.g.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>, and at least one study has hypothesized that this might affect nutrient dynamics
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, grasshoppers affect ANPP through plant source, plant species composition and level of herbivory. Counter to tradition that ANPP is driven by abiotic effects, biotic effects emerge stronger, increasing ANPP at one site and decreasing it at another beyond abiotic limits. This is driven by herbivory creating positive feedbacks that affect productivity, as reported elsewhere, e.g.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. While this did not negate abiotic influences, it surpassed their effect, as hypothesized earlier
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study indicates that focusing solely on the abiotic effects, and ignoring biotic influences, can be very misleading in understanding ecosystem functioning. This includes misrepresenting system productivity by as much as 33%, and misidentifying the most productive system. Furthermore, the biotic influences operate on a local spatial scale (few kilometers). Consequently, we suggest that characterizing ecosystem functioning based solely on large spatial scale abiotic conditions (e.g., precipitation and temperature), as commonly conducted, especially in making climate change projections, may be misleading. Furthermore, environmental changes often change species abundances, including lost and added species, so that novel biotic effects may arise
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. This requires better and more detailed ecological insights
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
