<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Treatments</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pots were randomly assigned to 4 treatments (Site A plants – Site A soil; Site B plants – Site B soil; Site A plants - Site B soil; Site B plants - Site A soil) with 10 replicates for each. Each pot’s soil treatment was provided by soil saved from a hole cut for a pot at the appropriate site. Each pot’s plant treatment was provided by transplanting plants from the appropriate site. Based on abundance and plant size at the sites in June 2004, five 20 cm (±10%) tall individuals of each of two grass species (
  <span class="italic">Poa pratensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Pascopyrum smithii</span>) were planted in a pot. Plants were carefully dug up to maintain root mass (~20 cm around plant) and soil was gently washed away. To help establish plants, 0.25 L of water/pot was provided weekly from June–Sept 2004 and any other plants were removed. To exclude grasshoppers, pots were covered by a nylon insect screen bag (0.5 m tall), which was supported by wire and attached to the pot with plastic clips.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pots had grasshoppers excluded during 2004–2005 (late June–September). Starting in late June 2006, grasshoppers (
  <span class="italic">Melanoplus sanguinipes</span>) at that year’s field density were allowed to feed in half of the pots in each treatment. This was accomplished by placing the appropriate number of grasshoppers in a pot for 1–2 days every 2 weeks, where the number of grasshoppers and length of time the grasshoppers were allowed to feed in a pot was based upon their mean field density over the preceding 2 weeks (See Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> in Supplementary Information). The field density was determined from two (11 AM and 2 PM) weekly counts of grasshoppers in twenty-four 0.1 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> rings
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Five 0.11 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (0.33 m × 0.33 m) control areas were randomly placed immediately outside the grid of 40 pots at each site, but within the experimental area. Grasshoppers were excluded from each control in years 2004–2005, using a 0.5 m high box of aluminum insect screen supported by wooden stakes and attached to garden edging by folding
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. From 2006–2012, the insect screen box was removed, so that grasshoppers had access.
 </p>
</sec>
