<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58884-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the Paris agreement sets an explicit goal of limiting global warming to 2°C or 1.5°C (Article 2), it also targets balancing anthropogenic sources and sinks of greenhouse gases (GHG) by participating nations in the second half of this century (Article 4). Scholars have offered various interpretations of the policy language of Article 4 of the Paris agreement. Although several interpretations are possible (Falkner, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0008">2016</a>; Fuglestvedt et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0009">2018</a>), we interpret the “balance of anthropogenic sources and removals by sinks of GHG” (UNFCCC, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0032">2015</a>) to imply eventual stabilization of atmospheric GHG concentrations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the stabilization of atmospheric GHG concentrations occurs, theory and modeling experiments indicate that on centennial time scales the rate of global temperature increases would steady at significantly lower rates than those of the 21st century (Hansen et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0012">1985</a>; Meehl et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0022">2005</a>; Wigley, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0033">2005</a>). Such scenarios suggest three stages to the anthropogenic fingerprint on global temperatures: (1) a period with an anthropogenic climate signal that cannot be detected due to climate variability being larger than the signal, (2) a period of detectable and strongly increasing transient change as a result of increasing forcing, and (3) a period of slower steady changes for near constant forcing. The focus has thus far been on the time of emergence (ToE) of anthropogenic warming, which quantifies the transition between the first two stages (Diffenbaugh &amp; Scherer, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0007">2011</a>; Hawkins &amp; Sutton, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0013">2012</a>; Mahlstein et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0018">2011</a>) while the time of transition between the latter two has not been probed. Here, we define a “Time of Steady Change” (TSC) as the time of reaching the third stage, which, together with ToE, provides a framework to quantify the duration of the period of rapid climate change (stage 2). This has important implications for understanding regional differences in the trajectory of climate change. While the rate of warming during the period of high transience has more immediate implications for adaptation, this transition from stage 2 to stage 3 is key to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) objective of avoiding dangerous interference with the climate system (which remains relevant under the Paris agreement; Jacquet &amp; Jamieson, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0015">2016</a>), since, for example, a longer period of rapid warming represents a greater challenge to ecosystem adaptation. Moreover, an improved understanding of this transition time will inform decision makers, such as water resource planners, where climate uncertainty has important implications for large‐scale infrastructure investments over long lifetimes such as dams (Hallegatte, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0011">2009</a>; Keller et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0016">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We define TSC as the time when the warming rate is undetectably different from that which we anticipate continuing for centuries (see Figure 
  <a rid="grl58884-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58884-fig-0001">1</a>a and section 
  <a rid="grl58884-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#grl58884-sec-0002">2</a>). This demarcates the transition between the period of high transience in which rapid warming accompanies increasing GHG concentrations (Rogelj et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0025">2012</a>) and the period of steady change in which constant GHG concentrations lead to a significantly reduced rate of sustained warming (Gillett et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0010">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="grl58884-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Framework for estimating the Time of Steady Change (TSC) using the example of global mean surface warming rates from the Representative Concentration Pathway 4.5 (RCP4.5) ensemble. The solid red line indicates the multimodel median (MMM) warming rate over time, and the red‐shaded region indicates the range of uncertainty (
    <div class="inline-formula">±</div>1 multimodel standard deviation). 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">m</span>
     <sub>max</sub>
    </div> is the maximum warming rate in the 21st century. The dotted gray line is the MMM 23rd century warming rate (
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">m</span>
     <sub>end</sub>)
    </div>, and the gray‐shaded region (
    <div class="inline-formula">±
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">ϵ</span>)
    </div> indicates one multimodel standard deviation around 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">m</span>
     <sub>end</sub>.
    </div> The vertical line centered around the year 2127 is the estimated TSC as it coincides with the first of at least 20 consecutive years in which the solid red line falls within 
    <div class="inline-formula">1
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">ϵ</span>
    </div> of 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">m</span>
     <sub>end</sub>
    </div>. (b) The RCP 4.5 Fossil CO
    <sub>2</sub> extended stabilization emission scenario (Meinshausen et al., 
    <a rid="grl58884-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0023">2011</a>). CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions peak in the year 2040, and by mid‐22nd century they have reduced to below 1950 emissions values. (c) The RCP 4.5 MMM global mean absolute temperature change relative to 2201–2300 with 
    <div class="inline-formula">±</div>1 multimodel standard deviation shown in red. The black dotted line indicates the MMM global mean temperature trend over 2201–2300, estimated using linear regression.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="GRL-46-5445-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the ToE literature has identified regions where the anthropogenic signal will be first detectable (Hawkins &amp; Sutton, 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0013">2012</a>; Mahlstein et al., 
  <a rid="grl58884-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58884-bib-0018">2011</a>), TSC provides a framework to characterize the length of time required to transition to a near‐constant climate state as GHG approach stabilization and to identify the regional disparities in the timing of this transition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: In section 
  <a rid="grl58884-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#grl58884-sec-0002">2</a> we describe the methods for quantifying TSC. Section 
  <a rid="grl58884-sec-0006" ref-type="sec" href="#grl58884-sec-0006">3</a> provides a summary of General Circulation Model (GCM) data sets used to quantify TSC. In section 
  <a rid="grl58884-sec-0007" ref-type="sec" href="#grl58884-sec-0007">4</a> we present the results of our analysis and section 
  <a rid="grl58884-sec-0008" ref-type="sec" href="#grl58884-sec-0008">5</a> provides a summary.
 </p>
</sec>
