<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results represent one of the few detailed accounts of the dynamics of well‐conserved stands of South American subtropical rainforests (see also Pizatto 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>, Castanho et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Authors working in subtropical Brazil (Ebling et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Formento, Schorn, &amp; Ramos, 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Castanho et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Pizatto, 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>) also did not find major compositional changes in the mature forests they studied. These findings agree with Souza et al. (
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0084" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), who found that the species composition of the same forests we studied matches patterns generated by quasi‐neutral dynamics, an assembly mechanism intermediate between purely neutral and niche, with a high degree of stochasticity and drift overlaid on environmental affinities. Our study also highlighted that the effects of human impacts on forest changes can vary substantially between regions. Climate change may reduce forest biomass stocks in many tropical regions due to reduced rainfall and increased prevalence of fast‐growing drought‐adapted generalist species with lighter wood, smaller seeds, and smaller adult sizes (Enquist &amp; Enquist, 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Lewis et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Poorter et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Toledo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Contrary to this trend, our data suggest that subtropical mixed rainforests could represent an exceptional global carbon sink, with very high biomass accumulation rates due to the combination of global fertilization effects of rising CO
 <sub>2</sub> concentrations with regionally rising but not damaging temperatures (Lewis et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), lack of water shortage (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), and presence of massive conifers. The aboveground carbon stock of such forests (125.1 Mg/ha) has been estimated to be twice as large as that of semideciduous forests in the same region (Rosenfield &amp; Souza, 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The reduction of these forests to ca. 13% of their original 3,202,134 ha extension (Ribeiro, Metzger, Martensen, Ponzoni, &amp; Hirota, 
 <xref rid="ece35289-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), coupled with pervasive selective logging of abundant and large‐sized araucarias, represents a significant source of CO
 <sub>2</sub> release into the atmosphere.
</p>
