<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body mass</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analyses needed to account for the possibility that several nuisance factors would obscure inter-annual variation in body mass. Mass of passerines can vary with the time of the day (Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1987</a>; Gosler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1994</a>; Macleod et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>), ambient temperature (Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1987</a>; Macleod et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>), season (Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1987</a>; Gosler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1994</a>; Macleod et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>) and moult (Ellegren and Fransson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">1992</a>; Kaiser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">1992</a>; Gosler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1994</a>). Our first analyses were designed to describe changes in expected mass through the years for each species, after accounting for these other sources of variation. We fit data on masses of individual birds using a GAM in which year was a smoothing parameter. The nuisance parameters time when a bird was mist netted (time; hours after the beginning of civil twilight), temperature (mean daily temperature of the day when a bird was mist netted), day (day of the respective mist-netting season when a bird was mist netted) and moult (birds were assigned to be either in moult when more than 20 feathers on the breast, belly or back were growing and/or when they were in primary moult) were entered as fixed effects. All variables except year and moult were treated as continuous covariates; year and moult were fixed, categorical factors. We assume that systematic annual changes in mean body mass are not confounded by daily variation in temperature during the mist-netting season, because daily body mass changes in response to fluctuations in daily temperature during the netting season are the result of birds adjusting food intake to short-term requirements (Gosler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2002</a>; Macleod et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>). Effectively, we are assuming that daily fluctuations in mass with changes in temperature represent a consistent source of noise around a latent typical mass across all years. We believe that this assumption is reasonable because daily temperatures during the mist-netting season and annual mean temperatures were not highly correlated (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.010 between all daily temperatures during the ringing season and their associated annual mean temperatures).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, we examined the extent to which inter-annual changes in mass were associated with changes in average ambient temperatures. In this second set of analyses we replaced the year effect with ambient temperature, conducting two separate linear regression analyses for each species: one with smoothed mean annual temperatures and the second with mean breeding season temperatures as independent variables additional to nuisance factors. We determined which of the representations of temperature was a better predictor of changes in body mass by assessing support for the two models using Akaike's information criterion (AIC) values.</p>
</sec>
