<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data from mist netting</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our data come from birds captured in mist netting as part of an ongoing monitoring effort on the Mettnau peninsula (47.729°N, 8.998°E), Lake Constance, near Radolfzell in south-western Germany. The study area covers about 1 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> and includes various habitats, but predominantly shrubland, wet meadows and reed beds. Since 1972 the mist-netting protocol has remained essentially unchanged, using 52 mist nets (6 m) in a single transect that are set following standardized methods from 30 June to 6 November (Berthold and Schlenker 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">1975</a>; Berthold et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">1991</a>). The only years in which mist netting was not conducted were 1987 and 1999. All mist-netted birds are identified to species, ringed, aged, the time of capture recorded, primary and body molt categorized, and standard measurements taken. Body masses of all birds were determined with an electronic scale with a precision of 0.1 g. The length of the third outermost primary feather (hereafter “feather length”) was measured following Berthold and Friedrich (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">1979</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous work has shown that body mass and morphological characters related to flight may vary with age (e.g. Alatalo et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">1984</a>; Norman 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">1997</a>; Pérez-Tris and Tellerría 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2001</a>). Therefore, we considered only fully grown first-year birds in our analyses, because it is usually not possible to determine the exact age of older individuals. We did not separate the sexes for the analyses because sex could not be determined for juveniles of many species. Only the data from the first capture were used. We assume that among-year variation in sex ratios is negligible. We selected all species for which more than 1,000 first-year individuals were captured, and plotted cumulative percentages of mist-netted individuals on each day of the mist-netting season. Then we defined all birds as regionally (south-west Germany and adjacent areas) born that were mist netted either before the day when a distinct increase in capture numbers occurred, or before the day after which a second increase in numbers occurred for species for which regionally born birds show an influx at the very beginning of the mist-netting season. We interpreted these increases as influxes of non-regional birds, e.g. migrants from north-eastern Europe. Finally, we excluded all species for which an insufficient number of birds was mist netted (below ten first-year regionally born individuals in many years). For some species, not all morphological data were collected in every year.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analysed data from the following 12 species (the date before which birds were classified as being local is give in parentheses): dunnock 
  <span class="italic">Prunella modularis</span> (7 September), robin 
  <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span> (1 September), song thrush 
  <span class="italic">Turdus philomelos</span> (16 September), blackbird 
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span> (25 September), garden warbler 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia borin</span> (18 July), blackcap 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span> (23 August), reed warbler 
  <span class="italic">Acrocephalus scirpaceus</span> (14 July), willow warbler 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus trochilus</span> (23 July), chiffchaff 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus collybita</span> (23 September), great tit 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> (31 August), blue tit 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span> (15 August), and reed bunting 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza schoeniclus</span> (14 September). With respect to migration distance, garden warblers, reed warblers and willow warblers are long-distance migrants wintering in sub-Saharan Africa. Dunnocks, robins, song thrushes, chiffchaffs and reed buntings are short-distance or partial migrants that winter not further than the Mediterranean region or only some individuals of the population migrate. Blackbirds, great tits and blue tits are mainly resident in the region although some individuals may also migrate short distances.
 </p>
</sec>
