<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For most of the bird species examined, the average masses and feather lengths varied from year to year since 1973, and typically this inter-annual variation was non-linear and complex. We found that in approximately half of the species both mass and feather length varied statistically significantly with temperature and that in many of these relationships body size decreased with higher temperatures. However, significant decreases in size with increasing temperatures were only found for five species, either for body mass or feather length, yielding little support for a general and strong adaptation to climate change based on thermal constraints (i.e. Bergmann’s rule). Our interpretation contrasts with that of Yom-Tov et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2006</a>) of the results from a study in Great Britain. There, an increasing trend in body mass of passerines as an adaptation to global warming was assumed, although only six of 14 species showed significant trends in size through time, and not always consistently between two study sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results provide a more direct and robust examination of effects of temperature on birds’ morphologies than previous work because we directly associated morphology with temperature instead of only assuming a systematic variation in morphology through time. Finding direct associations between changes in temperature and morphology is important, because ambient temperature is not the only potential environmental factor which may effect the body size of birds. Several studies have demonstrated changes in morphology through time, and inferred causes unrelated to changes in climate. Decreasing as well as increasing body size of goshawks in Finland and in Denmark were discussed as adaptations to changing diets rather than to changing temperatures (Tornberg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">1999</a>; Yom-Tov and Yom-Tov 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2006</a>). The possibility that the decreases in body mass in four out of five passerine species in Israel between 1950 and 1999 could track changes in food availability was also not excluded by Yom-Tov (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2001</a>). The wing lengths of dippers 
  <span class="italic">Cinclus cinclus</span> in Spain increased between 1985 and 2005 which was discussed as an adaptation to a changing water regime instead of a direct response to rising temperatures (Moreno-Ruedo and Rivas 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2007</a>). Morphology of a species can also vary among habitats (Ulfstrand et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">1981</a>; Blondel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2007</a>), and therefore, changes in morphology could also track changes of habitat in a given study area throughout the study period. Unfortunately, data on factors like changes in habitat availability and structure (Garant et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2005</a>; Blondel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2007</a>) or fluctuations in food quality and quantity as well as fluctuating pressures from predators are not available from our study region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperatures can be indexed in many different ways, although we believe that our chosen temperature indices were appropriate. Meiri and Dayan (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2003</a>) suggested that extreme winter temperatures exert a high selective pressure on body size. Supporting this argument, Meiri and Dayan (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2003</a>) showed that a significantly greater proportion of sedentary bird species conformed with the predictions of Bergmann’s rule. However, such extreme temperatures are avoided by migrants. In our study there was no clear evidence that migration determined whether a species’ morphology would be affected by inter-annual variation in temperatures. The body mass of the long-distance migrant garden warbler showed a strong increasing trend until the late 1990s. However, reed warblers and willow warblers also winter in tropical Africa, but did not increase their body mass throughout the study period. Therefore, different migration strategies of the species did not clearly explain the results of our analyses although the number of long-distance migrants considered here is too low to draw a general conclusion.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interpreting the response of feather length to changing temperatures is potentially more complicated than interpreting variation in body mass. The failure of Yom-Tov et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2006</a>) to detect a general trend in wing length as expected according to Allen’s rule (Allen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1877</a>: “…a marked tendency to enlargement of peripheral parts under high temperature, or towards the tropics...”) may partly be due to an apparent conflict between two geographically varying selection pressures. Gosler et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">1998</a>) described wing length (highly correlated with feather length; Berthold and Friedrich 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">1979</a>; Jenni and Winkler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">1989</a>) as the best general measure of body size. Whereas wing length should decrease in association with increasing temperatures according to Bergmann’s rule, the same measurement is expected to increase under the same conditions according to Allen’s rule. Additionally, conventional wing length measurements (Svensson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">1992</a>) measure the length of the carpal bones (subject to thermoregulatory needs according to either Bergmann’s or Allen’s rule, and to factors related to flight performance like migration, microhabitat selection, foraging ecology, predator avoidance) in conjunction with the longest distal flight feathers (dead tissue not subject to selection with respect to thermoregulatory needs), and therefore represents a combination of traits on which different selection pressures may act. For example, longer wing length is associated with greater migration distances (e.g. Pérez-Tris and Tellerría 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2001</a>; Leisler and Winkler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2003</a>; Fiedler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2005</a>). Further, evidence is accumulating that migrant bird species reduce migration distances and/or the proportion of migrating individuals in populations in connection with global warming (Fiedler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2003</a>; Gordo et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2007</a>). Therefore, climate-mediated changes in migratory behaviour may be affecting the wing lengths of some of the species that we examined.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regardless of the cause of morphological variation, response to environmental heterogeneity could either indicate that selection has resulted in genetically based adaptations, or in purely phenotypic responses (Blondel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2007</a>). Examples where the influence of ecological conditions on body mass and morphological traits has been shown include mallards 
  <span class="italic">Anas platyrhynchos</span> (Pehrsson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">1987</a>), pied flycatchers 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span> (Alatalo and Lundberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1984</a>) and song sparrows 
  <span class="italic">Melospiza melodia</span> (Hochachka and Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">1991</a>). That birds can regulate their mass according to perceived predation risk has been shown in empirical studies, e.g. by Gosler et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">1995</a>) or Lilliendahl (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">1997</a>), and the impact of predation on fledglings may result in selection for high body mass (Naef-Daenzer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2001</a>). However, morphological traits of birds such as body mass, wing length and tarsus length also have heritable components (Boag and Grant 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">1978</a>; Smith and Wettermark 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">1995</a>; Jensen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2003</a>), and thus the observed associations with climatic variation may have a genetic basis. For example, Nowakowski (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2000</a>) discusses inter-annual variation in wing length of reed warblers as a consequence of directional selection caused by aspects of climate. There are hints in our study that significant changes in body size associated with temperature are not caused by phenotypic plasticity alone. When the association of body mass or feather length with at least one temperature variable was significant (13 cases), the AIC value was lower (i.e. the model a better predictor) for breeding season temperature compared to smoothed annual temperatures only in three cases. In eight cases the AIC value was lower for smoothed annual temperatures, suggesting that the long-term temperature trend has a higher influence on average body size in a population than the conditions during the breeding season in which the birds were raised. These results may indicate selection for birds’ sizes across multiple generations, which would be genetically based. However, our data cannot be used to establish selection on genetic variation in size and the extremely low 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>-values in the association of feather length with temperature show that variation of this trait is mainly caused by other factors not considered in this study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, although our results indicate that morphology of birds can respond rapidly to changes in environmental temperatures, this was detected only in a minority of the investigated species. Therefore, we were not able to detect a general trend for body size changes in birds as a reaction to global warming during the last decades, either one caused directly by adaptation to a changing thermal environment (Bergmann’s rule) or otherwise. Potentially, our failure to find general responses to temperature fluctuations is the result of patterns that were too subtle to discover given our existing data. Treating latitude as a surrogate for temperature, Hughes (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2000</a>) estimated that a 3°C change in mean annual temperature corresponds to a shift in isotherms of approximately 300–400 km in latitude. The application of this estimate to the study area would correspond to a southward shift of approximately 150 km during the study period. Studies which found a general association of body size with latitude usually considered much larger ranges (Gould and Johnston 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1972</a>; Groen and Yurlov 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">1999</a>; Storz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2001</a>) as well as longer time scales (Smith and Betancourt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">2003</a>; Yom-Tov 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2001</a>). Therefore, our study period may have been too short, the magnitude of climatic changes too low and/or microevolutionary processes too slow to detect larger or more consistent changes in body size over the period of 34 years. While changes in phenology which are matching fine-scale patterns of climate change (Møller et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2006</a>) have been noted in south-western German birds (Bergmann 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1999</a>; Gatter 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2000</a>; Peintinger and Schuster 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2005</a>), we found less consistent evidence that their sizes have changed. Nevertheless, our results suggest more evidence of a morphological response to changing climate may be found if global temperatures continue to rise as predicted (Houghton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2001</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
