<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we used plot surveys to analyze the distribution characteristics of eight dominant plants in the tundra zone of the Changbai Mountains. The tundra vegetation of the Changbai Mountains is changing. Herbaceous species have encroached and expanded on the alpine shrub tundra vegetation. The abundance of herbaceous plants varied with the elevation and micro-topography, which implies the effects of micro-site associated with climatic and edaphic conditions on plant distribution. Tundra ecosystems are commonly regarded as being highly sensitive to global climate change. Observed changes in plant communities in both Arctic and alpine tundra environments have been associated with recent climate warming [
 <xref rid="B49-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Previous studies suggest that individual species in a community respond differently rather than cohesively to directional climate change [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Our previous results showed that 
 <italic>C. angustifolia</italic> has significantly invaded the shrub tundra zone of the Changbai Mountains during the last 30 years [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. By the 1980s, Changbai alpine tundra was defined as shrub tundra dominated by 
 <italic>R. chrysanthum</italic> and 
 <italic>V. uliginosum</italic> with normal distribution, and there was only sparse herbaceous species in the community [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The present study showed that the dominance of dwarf shrubs has declined. Though 
 <italic>R. chrysanthum</italic> was still the most important dominant species, the dominance of 
 <italic>V. uliginosum</italic> declined seriously. The dominance of six herbaceous species has increased significantly and were between those of 
 <italic>R. chrysanthum</italic> and 
 <italic>V. uliginosum</italic>, which indicates that the herbaceous plant species have encroached on tundra and predominated in the tundra. The shrub community in the tundra is undergoing a major change.
</p>
