<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Presence only data on the occurrence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> in Ecuador were made available for this study by the MSP. From 2000–2012 the MSP sampled aquatic larval mosquitoes from standing water in and around households in cities and towns throughout mainland Ecuador following standard protocols for entomological surveillance recommended by the World Health Organization [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007322.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. These data were collected year-round by vector control technicians from the National Service for the Control of Vector-Borne Diseases (SNEM) of the MSP as part of routine vector surveillance activities. Upon entering households, technicians visually inspected all potential larval habitat sites inside and outside of the home. Live samples of juvenile mosquitoes from positive containers were collected and transported to local vector control offices, where laboratory technicians confirmed species identification. Although the possibility for confusion with 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">albopictus</italic> exists, this species was only recently detected in Ecuador [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007322.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Originally used by the MSP as an indicator of mosquito abundance around households, positive LI records for 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> were used in this study to indicate the presence of mosquitoes at a given location. These occurrence data were de-identified from households and aggregated to the administrative level of parroquia (township or parish) by the MSP for each year of the study. Figures were produced in ArcMap (ver. 10.4, ESRI, Redlands, CA) using shapefiles from the GADM database of Global Administrative Areas, ver. 2.8 (gadm.org), elevation data freely available from NASA’s Shuttle Radar Topography Mission (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/srtm/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">jpl.nasa.gov/srtm</ext-link>), georeferenced mosquito surveillance data provided by the MSP and edited by the authors for this project, and ENM output produced in the course of this study.
</p>
