<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Located next to the Swedish border in southeast Norway (60°10′ N, 12°30′ E), the study area covers about 100 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, of which the 40 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> eastern part of the Varald State Forest constituted an intensively monitored core area. The gently undulating terrain between 200 and 400 m a.s.l. consists of Norway spruce 
  <span class="italic">Picea abies</span> and Scots pine 
  <span class="italic">Pinus silvestris</span> interspersed with scattered birch 
  <span class="italic">Betula</span> spp. and aspen 
  <span class="italic">Populus tremula</span>. A widely distributed dwarf shrub in the field layer is bilberry 
  <span class="italic">Vaccinium myrtillus,</span> an important food plant of forest grouse, including newly hatched broods. The ground-nesting black grouse and capercaillie are large (approximately 1–3 kg live weight, respectively), ground-nesting birds which hatch their 7–9 precocial and nidifugous chicks in early June. Owing to poorly developed thermoregulation during 3–4 days after hatching, the chicks are quite vulnerable to cold weather [
  <a rid="RSPB20171528C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20171528C18">18</a>], and geometrid and sawfly caterpillars are their main food during their first weeks of life [
  <a rid="RSPB20171528C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20171528C19">19</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20171528C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20171528C22">22</a>]. In the study area, the two species occur at moderate densities of 2.5–3 birds km
  <span class="sup">−2</span> in spring, together with a few and patchily distributed hazel grouse, 
  <span class="italic">Bonasa bonasia</span>. Main predators are red fox, 
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes</span>, pine marten, 
  <span class="italic">Martes martes</span>, goshawk, 
  <span class="italic">Accipiter gentilis</span>, and buzzard, 
  <span class="italic">Buteo buteo</span>; other raptors and mammalian predators are seasonal visitors or quite rare.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contiguous with other mixed coniferous forests on all sides—only interspersed with small patches of small abandoned farmlands—the forest has been subjected to timber harvesting for several centuries. Notably, in the 1950s, clear-cutting became the main harvesting regime, replacing the traditional high-grading and selection methods. Cutting blocks were initially rather large (more than 50 ha in the 1960s–1970s), but have successively been reduced in size, today rarely exceeding 20 ha. During the last four decades, the coverage of semi-natural old coniferous forests has decreased to less than 20%, the remaining consisting of middle-aged and young silvicultural stands of pure and mixed plantations of spruce and pine. For more details, see Wegge &amp; Rolstad [
  <a rid="RSPB20171528C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20171528C17">17</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
