<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is a positive relationship between environmental temperature and resting metabolic rate either within individuals that experience a temperature change or among populations or species that have adapted to divergent thermal environments over evolutionary time, particularly in ectotherms whose body temperatures conform to environmental temperatures (Clarke &amp; Fraser, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). It is partly because temperature directly influences kinetic energy of cellular components, demanding more energy at higher temperatures (Gillooly, Brown, West, Savage, &amp; Charnov, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). On the other hand, individual proteins degrade faster at higher temperatures, and absolute rate of protein synthesis is a major contributor to basal metabolic rate. Thus, the resting metabolic rate of each species or population should represent its evolutionary optima according to the trade‐off between the energetic demands needed for its lifestyle and the somatic maintenance at its environmental temperature (Clarke, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). When animals are exposed to warmer temperatures than the temperature at which the population or species has been evolutionarily adapted to live, both direct and indirect effects of temperature on resting metabolic rate may induce phenotypic changes from the molecular to organismal level. The energetic costs of accelerating metabolic rate may have negative impacts on fitness‐related life‐history phenotypes. A recent study of marine sticklebacks has demonstrated that the transgenerational effects of constant acclimation of mothers to elevated temperatures lead to higher and more efficient mitochondrial respiratory capacity and small body size of offspring (Shama et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
