<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the present study, we experimentally tested how long‐term exposure of young individuals to warmer temperatures during winter influences their life‐history traits during the reproductive phase using an ecological model organism, the three‐spined stickleback, at the southern edge of its European range (for studies of central and northern populations, see Leder et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Shama et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Although most studies of climate change impacts focus on the effects of summer temperatures, warm winters should have greater impacts on development and growth of animals with long‐lasting consequences (Williams, Henry, &amp; Sinclair, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). We focussed only on male phenotypes to study molecular mechanisms underlying temperature‐induced plasticity, which can differ substantially between the sexes. In the three‐spined stickleback, the reproductive success of males depends on their investment in red nuptial coloration (Candolin, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). This sexual signal is costly because their maintenance requires a continual intake of carotenoids, which have other important competing functions related to body maintenance (Blount, Metcalfe, Birkhead, &amp; Surai, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Pike, Blount, Bjerkeng, Lindstrom, &amp; Metcalfe, 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Most studies of warm acclimation have examined molecular processes only in some metabolically important tissues such as muscle and liver (e.g., Shama et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Veilleux et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). We examined gene expression plasticity in brain tissue as well as liver to identify potential genes involved in the ability to perceive thermal stress and physiologically acclimate to warm temperatures.
</p>
