<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSION AND MANAGEMENT STRATEGY</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The result of this study demonstrated that fishermen allocate their fishing gear along year, although fish catches are seasonally dynamic, seeing as the fishing season for blue swimming crabs is very short. However, in order to continue to earn, fishermen operate their fishing gear throughout the year. As a result, both catch landing and effort are close to the maximum sustainable yield (TAC). In order to reduce fishing pressure, a reduction is required in relation to fishing gears and temporal allocation arrangements.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, some management strategies of blue swimming crabs in the last decade was focused merely on fish biology (
  <a rid="b9-tlsr-29-1-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9-tlsr-29-1-1">Kunsook 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> 2014
  </a>; 
  <a rid="b5-tlsr-29-1-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5-tlsr-29-1-1">Josileen &amp; Menon 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="b18-tlsr-29-1-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18-tlsr-29-1-1">Sawusdee &amp; Songrak 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="b1-tlsr-29-1-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1-tlsr-29-1-1">Afzaal 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> 2016
  </a>), and give little attention to the dynamic of gear. In practice, fishermen allocate or redistribute their effort (spatially or temporally) by modifying fleet, increasing technology, expanding fishing grounds to response the changing of catch and economic in fisheries (
  <a rid="b4-tlsr-29-1-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4-tlsr-29-1-1">Hilborn &amp; Walters 1992</a>). Considering the operational needs of fisheries management, effort dynamics approach is proposed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that the fishing gear was operated throughout the year, the fishing effort needs to be reduced. Fishing effort is a function of the number of fishing gear (vessel) and efficiency of the fishing gear. Therefore, the management of the fishing effort should consider both aspects. Additionally, the number of fishing gear (vessel) allocated by the fishermen depended on when and where they wanted to fish. Since the fishing effort operates all the way through the year, it should take account of seasonal fishing gear allocation throughout the year. Referring to fishing effort numbers (when fish are captured on MSY) and the seasonal index in relation to fish abundance, the monthly fishing effort allocation is proposed in (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t2-tlsr-29-1-1" href="#t2-tlsr-29-1-1">Table 2</a>). Moreover, the fishing effort allocation fluctuates, depending on the fishing season. It is recommended that January is the minimum allocation (91 trip/month), whereas July is the maximum allocation (208 trips/month).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, fishing effort management can also be arranged by limiting the efficiency of the fishing gear. This is for the reason that the efficiency of the fishing gear will modify the fishing effort. The efficiency of fishing gear can be influenced by the size of the fishing gear, fishing tools and the ability of the fishermen. On this occasion, restrictions to the efficiency of the fishing gear can be undertaken by limiting the size of the fishing gear. For example, the number of fishing traps can be limited based on analysis of the result related to the maximum distance between fishermen’s fishing operations. Furthermore, the management objectives can also be simulated based on the fishing efficiency. If the objectives of fisheries management are to maximise the number of fishermen who work in the fisheries sector, the management alternative is to reduce efficiency, and vice versa.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to implement the result of management tool above, we proposed co-management as management system approach. This is because, blue swimming crabs fisheries in Pangkajene Kepulauan is characterised by small-scale fisheries that there are linkages between human and natural systems. In implementing co-management, governments cannot solve all fishery problems, but communities (fishers, government, researchers and other stakeholder) share the responsibility and authority for the management of the fishery. Community-based fisher groups are mainly pushed to participation in planning, design, implementation, monitoring and evaluation of co-management activities, while the roles of the national government and national agencies are mainly to provide technical assistance and financial assistance.</p>
</sec>
