<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Abundance</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monthly dynamic for CPUE</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three major types of fishing gear were employed to capture blue swimming crabs in Pangkajene Kepulauan, i.e., gillnets, traps and mini trawlers. Seeing as the productivity of the gillnets was highest in contrast to the other fishing gears, the fishing gears were standardised to gillnets. On average, the CPUE for blue swimming crabs in 2013 (3.33 kg/trips) was at its highest in contrast to other years (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4-tlsr-29-1-1" href="#f4-tlsr-29-1-1">Fig. 4</a>). During 2013, the CPUE fluctuated seasonally from 202kg/trips (January) – 4.67kg/trips (July). Meanwhile, the lowest CPUE occurred in 2014. During 2014, the CPUE fluctuated between 1.93kg/trips (January) – 4.63kg/trips (July). The average monthly CPUE for blue swimming crabs fluctuated seasonally. In total, the average monthly CPUE for blue swimming crabs was 3.27±0.79 kg/trips/month. The CPUE reached its lowest value (2.02 kg/trips) in January, whereas productivity increased and achieved its highest value (4.72 kg/trips) in July. After attaining the highest value (in July), productivity decreased until it reached its lowest value (in January).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual dynamics of CPUE</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total fishing effort which was already standardised into gillnets showed that the allocation of fishing efforts was dynamic annually. During the 2009–2011 periods, the fishing effort increased and attained its peak number in 2011 (2826 trips/year). However, after the increasing effort did not respond with significant catches, the fishing effort tended to decrease from 2010–2015 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5-tlsr-29-1-1" href="#f5-tlsr-29-1-1">Fig. 5</a>). Conversely, catches during 2009–2015 were stable and had a tendency to decrease. The increase in catches in 2011 was expected, as a response to a dramatic increase in effort, which indicated a rise in the number of catches (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5-tlsr-29-1-1" href="#f5-tlsr-29-1-1">Fig. 5</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of the fact that the effort and catches were dynamic, productivity (CPUE) was also dynamic. Furthermore, from 2009–2015, productivity was dynamics although was inclined to decrease (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5-tlsr-29-1-1" href="#f5-tlsr-29-1-1">Fig. 5</a>). In 2009, the fishermen were able to catch roughly 1,520 ton/trips/year of fish; however, productivity decreased to 0,971 ton/trips/year in 2015.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing Seasons</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The result of the seasonal index (SI) analysis confirms that the fishing season for the blue swimming crab in Pangkajene Kepulauan consists of two periods (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6-tlsr-29-1-1" href="#f6-tlsr-29-1-1">Fig. 6</a>). The first peak fishing season occurred between May (SI = 170.01) and July (SI = 120.74), whilst the second fishing season took place from August (SI = 97.52) to November (SI = 113.21). Thus, the blue swimming crab fishing season can be categorised as seasonal. The longest consecutive seasonal index (CSI) analysis for blue swimming crabs was 3 (May – July). This signifies that the length of the fishing season for blue swimming crabs is 3 months.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maximum Sustainable Yield</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, in order to understand fish stocks, two models were selected. As a result, it was determined that the Schaefer model provides the best fit for the data. According to the Schaefer model the maximum sustainable yield (MSY) is 2,099,155 kg, whereas the effort level (f
   <sub>MSY</sub>) is 2179 standard efforts. In addition, based on the MSY and f
   <sub>MSY</sub> values, using the precautionary principle (80% of MSY) the total allowable catch (TAC) for blue swimming crabs was 1.679.324 kg and the level of effort was 1.743 trips/year.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
