<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussions</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The closure of tropical seaways accounts for most of the spatial changes in GPI between the Late Miocene and Late Pliocene, but the amplitude is underestimated compared to the modeled GPI changes during the LMLP transition (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>). This may be attributed to the relatively smaller depth and width of tropical seaways applied here, which largely affect the magnitude of the modeled climate response
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Additionally, the timing for TC development is not synchronous over each ocean basin, and the associated mechanisms may be different in each (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). The Cenozoic evolution of genesis potential over the South Indian Ocean is a more progressive process than the abrupt transition that occurs in the western North Pacific, which may be linked with the gradual narrowing of Hadley cell in the Southern Hemisphere (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">14</a>) due to the northward incursion of Australia.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Though TCs have been examined in only a few other deep-time simulations, our results show some qualitative similarities with other models. For example, GPI is lower in the western North Pacific during the Late Pliocene relative to present-day in our model, which is similar to the ensemble mean considered in the Pliocene Model Intercomparison Project
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. The decreased favorability for genesis at low latitudes in the Early Eocene is also consistent with TCs downscaled from an Eocene-like climate simulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. These similarities provide some confidence that our results may be model-independent, but prior work has shown differences among models at basin scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. The precise composition of genesis indices can also affect results, but we show that the main qualitative features and temporal pattern reported here are insensitive to the specific GPI formula employed (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">15</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Notably, proxy records are scarce or absent for constructing the spatial distribution of TC activity during most of the Cenozoic, and the GPI provides little information on TC tracks and landfalls. Therefore, the model results cannot be robustly evaluated by geological evidence. Nevertheless, our study provides a testable relationship between tectonic/CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced climate change and TC behavior, and sheds light on TC responses to very high CO
  <sub>2</sub> levels that may be seen in the future if fossil-fuel emissions continue unabated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Moreover, the substantial variations in genesis regions in most of Cenozoic imply potential changes in the TC-induced vertical mixing in terms of both magnitude and spatial distribution (Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">16</a>, 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17</a>). Given the role that TCs could play in modulating tropical oceans and possibly global climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>, we highlight that future modeling studies targeting deep-time simulations should consider the feedback of TCs associated with upper-ocean vertical mixing.
 </p>
</sec>
