<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiment design for simulating Cenozoic climates</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we first perform seven coupled NorESM-L experiments to simulate the climate of the Early Eocene, Late Eocene, Late Oligocene, Early Miocene, Late Miocene, Late Pliocene, and today (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>
  <span class="bold">)</span>. Each experiment is integrated for 2200 model years, and we analyze the outputs of the last 200 years.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The continental configurations for the Early Eocene, Late Eocene, Late Oligocene, Early Miocene, and Late Miocene are based on the reconstructed paleogeographic maps
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> for 50, 40, 30, 20, and 10 Ma, respectively (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">18</a>). These paleogeographic maps include information on ancient mountain ranges and shorelines, active plate boundaries, and the extent of paleoclimatic belts. We set the mountain lines and coastlines at 1000 m and 0 m, respectively, although uncertainties in estimating paleo-altitude still exist. The shallow ocean basins are set to a depth of 200 m. All these altitude and depth data are interpolated to a 1° × 1° resolution, and then are used to construct the paleo-topography and paleo-bathymetry used in NorESM-L. Regarding the Late Pliocene, we use the reconstructed topography from the Pliocene Research, Interpretation and Synoptic Mapping Project (PRISM3D)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> with modern land-sea mask, following the guidelines of the Pliocene Model Intercomparison Project
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the greenhouse gases, we set atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration to 1120 ppmv for the Early Eocene (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which corresponds to the upper estimate according to a previous synthesis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration is set to 1050 ppmv for the Late Eocene, 700 ppmv for the Late Oligocene, 420 ppmv for the Early Miocene, 350 ppmv for the Late Miocene, and 405 ppmv for the Late Pliocene. The other greenhouse gases (e.g., CH
  <sub>4</sub> and N
  <sub>2</sub>O) are fixed at the pre-industrial levels.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the scarcity of proxies for vegetation during the Cenozoic era, we choose to adopt the same idealized land cover for each of these paleoclimate simulations, except for the Late Pliocene for which we adopt the PRISM3D reconstructions. Specifically, forest is prescribed between 30°S and 30°N, with shrub and grass outside this latitude band. There are no ice sheets on Antarctica and Greenland.</p>
</sec>
