<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The impact of climate change on plant phenology has been described in recent decades, highlighting a hastening of flowering phenology in response to increasing winter and spring temperatures
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1–7</xref>
 </sup>. Long records of flowering dates have been proven extremely valuable to reconstruct past phenology and to predict phenology under future climatic scenarios. In Japan for example, flowering dates of cherry trees (
 <italic class="italic">Prunus jamasakura</italic>) have been recorded for centuries and analyses of these records have revealed that cherry flowering is currently occurring earlier than at any time in the previous seven to 12 centuries, due to the impact of warming and urbanization on phenology
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. This earlier flowering trend has been observed for other fruit trees
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10–14</xref>
 </sup>, which are particularly vulnerable to temperature changes due to their long life span. Peach (
 <italic class="italic">Prunus persica</italic>), apricot (
 <italic class="italic">Prunus armeniaca</italic>), almond (
 <italic class="italic">Prunus dulcis</italic>), plum (
 <italic class="italic">Prunus salicina</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">domestica</italic>) and sweet cherry (
 <italic class="italic">Prunus avium</italic> L.) are amongst the most commercially important 
 <italic class="italic">Prunus</italic> fruit tree species planted in temperate climate zones. In Europe, cherry tree blossom of early maturing cultivars showed an advance up to 4.7 days/°C in Germany
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>, and warmer winters have dramatically affected the sweet cherry production in South-Western France, with a 30% yield in 2007. Warmer winters can as well be associated with delayed spring phenology for some species and, occasionally resulting in abnormal flowering phenology and reduced productivity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15–18</xref>
 </sup>. Models for chill availability predict an increase in the delaying effect of mild winters as temperature increase becomes more pronounced
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>, especially in warmer locations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. In the context of substantial changes to environmental conditions induced by climate change, it will be essential that plant cultivars are well adapted to warmer winter and spring temperatures and to more extreme climatic events such as erratic spring frosts and summer heat waves. This is especially true for perennial fruit crops, which require more than a decade before a new cultivar is released.
</p>
