<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Archaeobotanical macro-remains in Late Paleolithic hunter-gatherer sites in North China are often poorly preserved or not clearly associated with food-production activities, meaning they cannot be directly linked to objects used to cook or eat the plants, and thus to human consumption. This study is based on ancient starch grains identified on grinding stones used directly in food production from nine sites dating from the Late Pleistocene Last Glacial Maximum through the Holocene Climatic Optimum, 
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 25,000 to 5500 cal BP (calibrated years before present, based on radiocarbon dates) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Because these remains of edible plants are found on the grinding stones, we can reliably assume humans were consuming them. While previous starch studies focused on remains from individual sites
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>, these data from multiple sites afford us a long-term, diachronic view for uncovering the changing relationships between people and the cereals they consumed during the cultivation and domestication processes. Exclusively studying starches on such tools also allows us to reliably assume that we are making consideration only of residues from plants whose seeds were ground for consumption. This study demonstrates that foragers who became initial cultivators ate the seeds of grasses not only from the Paniceae tribe, to which millets—the initial cereal domesticates—belong, but also from Triticeae. We assume that due to their recovery from the surfaces of food-processing tools, the changing relative percentages of these tribes’ starch granules are a reliable indicator of cereal food preferences. Looking at the relative percentages between starches from the different tribes provides insights to the trajectory that led to millet as the preferred cereal for domestication. We next place these plant data into the context of climatic fluctuations, which shows correlations, and likely causation, between environmental change and changes in the cereal plants’ distribution and exploitation patterns. We hypothesize that climate change played a crucial role in causing cultivating foragers to increasingly abandon Triticeae species and select Paniceae members as the most suitable plants for domestication, and we model why this happens. We also recognize the limits of starch identifications, such as being limited to the tribe level, and call for additional evidence to test this hypothesis.
</p>
