<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We tested for trade‐offs on both physiological and evolutionary timescales: We tested whether the evolution of increased tolerance of one stressor would lead to a correlated loss in tolerance of the others, and we tested whether simultaneous exposure to these stressors had synergistic physiological effects. To test for evolutionary trade‐offs, we hybridized two populations that were divergent for both heat and salinity tolerance, selected for increased tolerance of either heat, hyperosmotic, or hypo‐osmotic stress in replicate hybrid lines, and then tested whether evolution of increased tolerance to one stressor led to loss of tolerance to one of the others. Selection experiments are one of the most powerful tests for ecological tradeoffs, allowing genetic correlations among traits to be disentangled from correlated sources of selection (Fry 
 <xref rid="eva12394-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Berger et al. 
 <xref rid="eva12394-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). In many laboratory selection experiments, the response to selection depends on standing genetic variation in the source population or new mutations that occur over the time frame of the experiment. By hybridizing populations that were divergent for heat and salinity stress and then selecting for increased tolerance in hybrids, we were able to directly target the alleles responsible for phenotypic divergence between these populations, separated by millions of generations of evolution, and ask whether the alleles responsible for differences in heat or salinity tolerance between the two populations have pleiotropic effects on tolerance of other stressors. We observed physiological, but not genetic trade‐offs to tolerance of multiple stressors. Our results have important implications for biological responses to environmental change, as they imply that the synergistic effects of multiple simultaneous stressors may impose a more important demographic constraint than trade‐offs imposed by negative genetic correlations among stress tolerance traits.
</p>
