<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Dispersal ability is assumed to be related to seed mass such that smaller seeds disperse farther [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. In all scenarios this is implemented according to 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0177778.e004" class="xref">Eq (3)</xref>. In the 
 <italic class="italic">uniform scenario</italic> all species have equal seed mass and hence dispersal distance. In the other scenarios, seed mass is drawn randomly for each species from a typical lognormal distribution, with many small-seeded species and fewer species with larger seeds [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. The mean and standard deviation of the SM distribution are manipulated (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0177778.s001" class="xref">S1 Appendix</xref>). In the 
 <italic class="italic">variable scenario</italic>, seed mass only determines mean dispersal distance, without affecting any other vital rate. Fecundity (the number of seeds produced per unit biomass), germination probability and seedling biomass are here calculated based on the median of the seed mass distribution and thus the same for all species. In the 
 <italic class="italic">trade-off scenario</italic>, seed mass further affects the demographic parameters fecundity (seed number), germination probability, and the biomass of the emerging seedling. Larger seeded species produce fewer seeds, but large seeds have a higher germination probability (due to higher survival rates and greater tolerance of germination to environmental factors) and seedling biomass. These relationships are modelled following scaling relations reported in Jakobsson and Eriksson [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0177778.s001" class="xref">S1 Appendix</xref>) for 50 co-occurring grassland species, the most comprehensive data set known to the author.
</p>
