<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We estimated resting metabolic rate (ml O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> h
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) at the cold range boundary as MR
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub> = (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">lc</sub> − 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">min</sub>)
 <italic class="italic">C</italic> + BMR, where 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">lc</sub> is the lower critical temperatures bounding the lower limit of the thermal neutral zone (TNZ); 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">min</sub> is the coldest winter environmental temperatures at the cold range boundary; BMR is basal metabolic rate (ml O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> h
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>), and 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic> is thermal conductance (ml O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> h
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> °C
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34537-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>, see Section 2.1 for details on parameterization). We calculated metabolic expansibility at the cold range boundary as ME
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub> = MRCRB/BMR. An alternative to cold environments selecting for increased ME
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub> is selection for increased metabolic scope and M
 <sub class="sub">sum</sub> (M
 <sub class="sub">sum</sub> = BMR + metabolic scope). We thus also examine MR
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub>/M
 <sub class="sub">sum</sub> as a cold boundary constraint. We conducted a coarse analysis of warm range boundaries following analogous methods and reported in the discussion, but we focus on cold range boundaries because they are more likely governed by metabolic constraints than are warm range boundaries. At warm range boundaries, the capacity for evaporative cooling may be more limiting than the associated metabolic costs and minimal endogenous heating is favored (McKechnie, Whitfield, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Tieleman &amp; Williams, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). Our estimates of ME
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub> are approximate (see Discussion) in that they do not account for additional factors such as use of solar radiation, convective heat loss, microclimate variation, microhabitat selection, and behavioral thermoregulation (Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Porter &amp; Kearney, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>).
</p>
