<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The geographic distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> extends from the Ethiopian massifs to southern Tanganyika
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. Despite our sampling effort (two field expeditions in 2009, 2015 to Ethiopia and one in 2010 to Kenya-Uganda), we failed to find 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> in many of the localities recorded by Hedberg in his classic monography of this species
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. Much of the forest in these localities is highly degraded, threatened by the advancement of extensive agriculture, cattle rising, forestry, and other human activities (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2.1</xref> for a list of the visited localities for this study and a detailed description of the sampling). Despite this, we were able to sample fresh plant tissue from seven populations of 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2.2</xref>): two populations in the Abyssinian massif (Gifta and Dembecha), two in the Harar Massif (Harenna forest and Agere Maryam), one in Rwenzori Mts. (Albertine Rift), one in Mt. Elgon (west of the Gregory Rift), and one in Aberdare Mts. (east of the Gregory Rift) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). Whenever possible leaves from 8–17 plants, 7–15 m apart were collected from each population. In addition, we added nine localities, obtained from old herbarium specimens (Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew): Cherangani (Kenya), Sasa trail in Mt. Elgon (Uganda), Gikongoro (Rwanda), Teza (Burundi), Tukuyu, Mwakelele, Livingstone Mountains, Mporoto Mountains (Tanzania) and Misuku (Malawi). Altogether, we sampled 16 localities of 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2.2</xref>), representing all major geographic blocks in the distribution of the species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1a</xref>). Three plastid (pDNA) regions were sequenced for a total of 79 individuals. For details on PCR amplification and sequence alignment see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Appendix S1.1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2.3</xref> in the 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Material</xref>. Sources of the material examined, location of vouchers, GenBank accession numbers, and full references are listed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2.2</xref>.
</p>
