<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was performed with 29 captive great tits (12 males and 17 females) in March 2008. Birds were hand-reared and therefore, used to be handled. Birds were housed individually in cages (0.9×0.5×0.4 m), with wooden bottom, top, side, and rear walls, a wire-mesh front, and three perches. The bottom was covered with wood chips. The birds were kept in three rooms under ambient temperature (outside temperature during the experiment: maximum 6°C during the day and minimum −2°C during the night) and natural winter daylight artificially supplemented with fluorescent light tubes under natural photoperiod. They were provided with 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> water, sunflower seeds, a commercial dry mixture (proteins, trace elements, minerals, and vitamins), a fresh mixture of raw heart and live mealworms. Birds were deprived of food 90 min before the start of the experiment in order to stimulate them to enter into torpor, to mimic natural conditions. Birds were introduced in the respirometry chamber at sunset (6:00 pm) and they were removed and returned to their cages at 8:00 am the next morning.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design</div>
  <sec id="s4b1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Treatments</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds were randomly assigned to one of the two treatment groups: an experimental group exposed to the odour of a potential mammal predator (fresh ferret urine), and a control group exposed to the odour of an herbivorous mammal (fresh rabbit urine). We added an absorbent paper soiled with the correspondent odour to a box situated ahead of each respirometry chambers (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). Each test day, we used new papers and cleaned the respirometry chambers.
   </p>
   <div id="pone-0027576-g003" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0027576.g003</span>
    <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <div class="title">Respirometer Schema.</div>
     <p>Schematic representation of the respirometer used in the experiment. From left to right: carbon dioxide and humidity are removed from inlet air thanks to a column containing one layer of Ascarite (A) surrounded by two layers of Drierite (D). Pumps force the air in three different circuits: i) a reference circuit (top) containing an empty chamber used to calculate the amount of oxygen used by the birds in the other chambers, ii) a second circuit (middle) leading to the three chambers containing the birds exposed to predator (ferret) odour, and iii) a third circuit (bottom) leading to the three chambers containing birds exposed to the control (rabbit) odour. In each of these two last circuits, a first valve lead the inlet air either in a compartment containing the urine-damped filter paper, or a compartment containing a dry, odourless, filter paper. A flowmeter setting the flow rate to 250 ml min
      <span class="sup">−1</span> precedes each animal chamber. A second set of valves, installed after each animal chamber, controls from which chamber the oxygen concentration is measured.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="pone.0027576.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We obtained predator odour by placing clean absorbent papers under the cages of five male ferrets (
    <span class="italic">Mustela furo</span> L.). We used ferrets because, even though ferrets are not natural predators of great tits, the scent (especially the one produced by anal sac secretion that they use to mark the territory) is very similar to those of other mustelids, such as 
    <span class="italic">M. erminea</span> and 
    <span class="italic">M. putorius</span>
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Brinck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Brinck1">[37]</a> that include birds in their diets. Ferret scent has been used in several vertebrates that are not depredated by this mustelid, including great tits, and it induced avoidance-associated behaviours (e.g. 
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo1">[28]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo2">[29]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Zhang1">[38]</a>). We chose papers soiled with fresh urine and gland secretions associated to scent-marking behaviour, whereas papers containing faeces were discarded. We placed papers under the ferret cages three days before the experiment, to ensure odour collection. When collecting papers daily for the experiment, we selected wet papers containing recent cues. This method of odour collection has proven successful in previous studies with hole breeding passerines 
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo1">[28]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo2">[29]</a>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The control treatment was obtained by using the same methodology to collect rabbit (
    <span class="italic">Oryctolagus cuniculus</span> L.) urine. We used this odorant control because rabbits are herbivorous and therefore, their chemical cues should not be associated with a predation risk for the birds.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s4b2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body temperature</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At least 72 hours before the start of the experiment, birds were anaesthetized under isoflurane (Forene, Abbott b.v., Hoofddorp, The Netherlands) and a body temperature transponder (IPTT-300, Plexx, Elst, The Netherlands) was implanted under the skin of their back. Body temperature was recorded every 30 min during the first 5 hours of each night's experiment, using a portable reader (DAS-6007, Plexx, Elst, The Netherlands). Two transponders did not work on the day of the experiment, so these birds were removed from the temperature analysis.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s4b3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RMR measurements</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured Resting Metabolic Rate (RMR) in terms of oxygen consumption, during 5 consecutive nights (5 or 6 birds per night), in an open-circuit respirometer (see 
    <a rid="pone.0027576-Caro1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Caro1">[39]</a>; 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). Birds were weighted and isolated in 6 sealed respirometer chambers (0,76 l) and placed in the darkness of a climate cabinet (Sanyo MIR-553, Sanyo E&amp;E Europe BV, Etten-Leur, The Netherlands) at 10°C to induce birds to enter hypothermia. Chambers 1 to 3 were allocated to predator odour, chambers 4 to 6 to control odour. Each morning, the chambers were successively cleaned using dish soap and methanol to remove persistent odours. After the third night, all the chambers and the tubing between the odour source and the chambers were replaced. H
    <sub>2</sub>O and CO
    <sub>2</sub> were removed from the inlet air (blown into the animal chamber) respectively with Drierite® (6 mesh, Sigma-Aldrich Chemie b.v., Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands) and Ascarite® (5–20 mesh, Fluka, Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands). Air flow rate was set to 250 ml min
    <span class="sup">−1</span> with flowmeters (Brooks Instrument b.v., Ede, The Netherlands) previously calibrated using a soap bubble method (Bubble-O-Meter, LLC, Dublin, OH, USA). Oxygen content of outlet air was measured with an oxygen analyzer (Servomex 4100, Servomex BV, Zoetemeer, The Netherlands). Oxygen consumption (ml O
    <sub>2</sub> min
    <span class="sup">−1</span>) was calculated as the difference in oxygen concentration between air from the respirometer chambers and reference air from an empty chamber (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). As only one oxygen analyzer was used, measurements alternated between the six experimental, plus one reference, chambers every 5 min. The oxygen consumption was converted to metabolic rate (kJ 24 h
    <span class="sup">−1</span>) by assuming an energetic equivalence of 20 kJ per liter of O
    <sub>2</sub>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During each night, birds were exposed to two 30 minute periods of odour (half an hour after the birds have been settled in the chamber, and five hours later). The rest of the time, they were exposed to fresh inlet air (see “No odour” compartment on 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). In that way, we simulated two approaches of a mustelid predator at the beginning and in the middle of the sleep period. Furthermore, with this experimental design, we obtained the body temperature and oxygen consumption measurements of each bird under two conditions: odorless air (odorless control) and scented air (treatment: predator or odorous control).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The weight of birds before the experiment did not differ between treatments (F
   <sub>1,26</sub> = 0.17, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.69), but differed between sexes (ANOVA, F
   <sub>1,26</sub> = 5.37, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.03), and the interaction between treatment and sex was not significant (F
   <sub>1,26</sub> = 1.34, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.26).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used two-way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) to analyse the differences between treatments and sexes in the weight lost by birds. We used two-way Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVA) to examine the differences in the Resting Metabolic Rate (RMR) and in the mean body temperature in relation to the treatment and the sex, including the mean weight (the mean between the initial and final body weight) as a covariate. We included the interaction between treatment and sex in all the models. Differences between treatments (between subject factor) in the oxygen consumption and in the body temperature of birds before (odourless condition) and during the scent exposition (time, within subject factor) were analysed separately for the first and second periods of scent exposition by using repeated measure ANOVA. We included the interaction between treatment and time during exposition to test whether there were differences between treatments in the response of birds before (odourless condition) and during each scent exposition.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds were healthy during the study and they did not exhibit any sign of stress due to the implantation or removal of transponders or to the experiment. They resumed their normal behaviour immediately after they returned to their cages after implantation and removal of transponders and after being tested in the respirometry chamber. This experiment was carried out under license of the Animal Experimental Committee of the KNAW (DEC protocol no CTE 0701).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
