<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite being one of the most frequent behaviours of animals, sleep is also one of the less studied behaviours (see 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Lima1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Lima1">[1]</a> for a review). Sleep involves energy saving 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Berger1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Berger1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Zepelin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Zepelin1">[3]</a>, as well as a restorative function for the immune system 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Majde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Majde1">[4]</a>, and/or for the brain (e.g. memory consolidation 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Stickgold1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Stickgold1">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Steriade1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Steriade1">[6]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Tononi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Tononi1">[7]</a>. However, sleep not only has benefits 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Lima2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Lima2">[8]</a>, but also has costs. The most important cost is probably the risk of predation. While asleep, an animal is less responsive to its environment, and may therefore fail to detect cues associated with the presence of a predator. Like any other behaviour, the balance between the benefits and costs may determine when, where and how animals sleep 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Lima1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Lima1">[1]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been shown that animals can change their circadian sleeping period to avoid the risk of predation. For example, free-living rats shifted from nocturnal to diurnal activity in response to human-associated changes in predator (Red Fox, 
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes</span>) activity 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Fenn1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Fenn1">[9]</a>. Such shift in the sleeping period as a response to predation risks has also been suggested in birds. Several small-size species of Procellariiforms evolved toward nocturnal live despite a poor night vision, presumably to avoid predation by skuas (Stercorariidae) or gulls 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Warham1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Warham1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Mougeot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Mougeot1">[11]</a>. Animals may also reduce predation risk by carefully selecting the places where to sleep 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Webb1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Webb1">[12]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Meddis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Meddis1">[13]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Rechtschaffen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Rechtschaffen1">[14]</a>. This may be especially important for monophasic sleepers that tend to concentrate sleep into a single part of the day 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Tobler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Tobler1">[15]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Ball1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Ball1">[16]</a>. Many bird species are monophasic sleepers and at high latitudes during winter, the time they spend sleeping is even longer than the daily period of activity. Birds that nest in cavities often also use these for roosting at night to avoid predation by owls, as roosting in cavities is usually safer than in tree canopies. For example, great tits that did not roost in nest boxes were more predated by owls, and therefore, had a lower overwinter survival than birds that were regularly observed sleeping in nest boxes 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Drent1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Drent1">[17]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, when animals perceive some risk of predation before sleeping, they may also modify how they sleep. It has been shown that collared doves, 
  <span class="italic">Streptopelia risoria</span>, exposed to the presence of a mustelid predator before sleeping increased the number of sleeping interruptions by opening their eyes to scan the environment 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Lendrem1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Lendrem1">[18]</a>. Perceived increase in the risk of predation, not due to the real presence of a predator but to the absence of conspecifics (e.g. doves 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Lendrem1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Lendrem1">[18]</a>), the vigilance levels of conspecifics (e.g. gulls 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Beauchamp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Beauchamp1">[19]</a>) or the distance to risky areas (e.g. mallards 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Lendrem2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Lendrem2">[20]</a>) have also been shown to influence sleep patterns in birds. The position within a group leads also to differences in the perceived risk of predation that may be translated into differences in sleep patterns. For example, Rattenborg and collaborators 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Rattenborg1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Rattenborg1">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Rattenborg2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Rattenborg2">[22]</a> found that when mallards were located on the edge of a group, and therefore, they perceived an increase in the risk of predation, they showed an increase in the proportion of time spent in unihemispheric sleep, compared to when they were safely sleeping surrounded by conspecifics 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Rattenborg1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Rattenborg1">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Rattenborg2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Rattenborg2">[22]</a>. This unihemispheric sleep allows birds to sleep with one hemisphere and scan the environment with the other hemisphere at the same time.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not only the position within a group in social animals but also other factors may increase the susceptibility of animals to the risk of predation while sleeping, by decreasing their ability to monitor the environment. For example, it is known that many bird and mammal species decrease their body temperature during cold nights in order to decrease the costs associated with the maintenance of a constant and elevated body temperature 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Reinertsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Reinertsen1">[23]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-McKechnie1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-McKechnie1">[24]</a>. By entering nocturnal hypothermia, and therefore, reducing their metabolic rate at night, birds can reduce starvation risk. However, this decrease in temperature also entails changes in the sleep pattern 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Clark1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Clark1">[25]</a> that may cause a lower ability to detect an approaching predator while sleeping. Birds are known to be able to modify the degree of their body temperature decrease during the night in relation to the perceived risk of predation. For example, when pigeons were exposed during daytime to a model of a flying hawk, they did not decrease their body temperature as much as control pigeons during the following night 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Laurila1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Laurila1">[26]</a>. This evidence suggests that animals can compensate for their loss of awareness while sleeping, not only by selecting safe places where to sleep but also by modifying their sleep patterns in relation to the perceived risk of predation before getting asleep. However, what happens once the animal is already sleeping? Can sleeping animals obtain information about the risk of predation like awake animals?
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many animals use the chemical cues of predators to ascertain their presence, especially under low visibility conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Kats1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Kats1">[27]</a>. Although evidence is still scarce in birds, recent experiments suggests that different bird species detect and use the chemical cues released by predators 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo1">[28]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo2">[29]</a>. For example, when blue tits, 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>, found predator chemical cues inside the cavity where they were feeding their nestlings, birds delayed their first entry in the nest-box. They perched on the hole of the nest-box and refused to enter more often when the nest-box contained predator odour than when it contained control scents. In those cases, they looked around and inside without entering 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo1">[28]</a>. Hole-nesting birds such as great 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> and blue tits use cavities both for roosting in winter and for breeding in spring, where they can encounter predators such as mustelids. For an accurate assessment of the predation risk before entering a cavity, chemical cues are expected to be more efficient than visual cues, and they therefore may allow birds to avoid a risky encounter inside the cavity 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo1">[28]</a>. However, are chemical cues also useful for sleeping animals to detect an approaching predator during the night?
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study was to analyse whether birds are able to use their chemosensory abilities to detect predators while sleeping. We simulated a natural situation in which a bird is sleeping in a cavity and a predator approaches quietly, so that the bird can only perceive the chemical cues of the predator. As a measurement of how deeply a bird sleeps we used the Resting Metabolic Rate (RMR) and body temperature. The assumption is that a bird that is deeply sleeping consumes less oxygen than an awake and alert bird. We hypothesised that if sleeping birds are able to detect the chemical cues of predators, they would spend less time sleeping and arouse more often. We also predicted that under the risk of predation, birds would not decrease their body temperature as much as birds exposed to a control scent. And as a result of all this, we expected birds exposed to predator chemical cues to lose more weight than control birds and have a higher RMR. Alternatively, if sleeping birds, with reduced body temperature, are not able to detect the scent of predators, we would not expect differences in body temperature, RMR and body weight lost between birds exposed to the different treatments. As an experimental species we used the great tit, a species known to detect and use the chemical cues of mustelids to assess the risk of predation while selecting cavities to sleep 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Amo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Amo2">[29]</a>. We used mustelid urine as a cue for the presence of a predator. Mustelids are crepuscular and nocturnal hunters to which birds may be exposed while sleeping in cavities.
 </p>
</sec>
