<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4b3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RMR measurements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured Resting Metabolic Rate (RMR) in terms of oxygen consumption, during 5 consecutive nights (5 or 6 birds per night), in an open-circuit respirometer (see 
  <a rid="pone.0027576-Caro1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0027576-Caro1">[39]</a>; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). Birds were weighted and isolated in 6 sealed respirometer chambers (0,76 l) and placed in the darkness of a climate cabinet (Sanyo MIR-553, Sanyo E&amp;E Europe BV, Etten-Leur, The Netherlands) at 10°C to induce birds to enter hypothermia. Chambers 1 to 3 were allocated to predator odour, chambers 4 to 6 to control odour. Each morning, the chambers were successively cleaned using dish soap and methanol to remove persistent odours. After the third night, all the chambers and the tubing between the odour source and the chambers were replaced. H
  <sub>2</sub>O and CO
  <sub>2</sub> were removed from the inlet air (blown into the animal chamber) respectively with Drierite® (6 mesh, Sigma-Aldrich Chemie b.v., Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands) and Ascarite® (5–20 mesh, Fluka, Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands). Air flow rate was set to 250 ml min
  <span class="sup">−1</span> with flowmeters (Brooks Instrument b.v., Ede, The Netherlands) previously calibrated using a soap bubble method (Bubble-O-Meter, LLC, Dublin, OH, USA). Oxygen content of outlet air was measured with an oxygen analyzer (Servomex 4100, Servomex BV, Zoetemeer, The Netherlands). Oxygen consumption (ml O
  <sub>2</sub> min
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was calculated as the difference in oxygen concentration between air from the respirometer chambers and reference air from an empty chamber (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). As only one oxygen analyzer was used, measurements alternated between the six experimental, plus one reference, chambers every 5 min. The oxygen consumption was converted to metabolic rate (kJ 24 h
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) by assuming an energetic equivalence of 20 kJ per liter of O
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During each night, birds were exposed to two 30 minute periods of odour (half an hour after the birds have been settled in the chamber, and five hours later). The rest of the time, they were exposed to fresh inlet air (see “No odour” compartment on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0027576-g003" href="#pone-0027576-g003">Fig. 3</a>). In that way, we simulated two approaches of a mustelid predator at the beginning and in the middle of the sleep period. Furthermore, with this experimental design, we obtained the body temperature and oxygen consumption measurements of each bird under two conditions: odorless air (odorless control) and scented air (treatment: predator or odorous control).
 </p>
</sec>
