<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We utilized SOILWAT, a daily time step, multiple soil layer, process-based, simulation model of ecosystem water balance
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" class="xref">39</xref>. SOILWAT has been applied and validated in dryland ecosystems including temperate grasslands
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>, temperate shrub-dominated ecosystems
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref> and temperate dry-domain forests
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" class="xref">41</xref>. Inputs to SOILWAT include daily weather conditions (mean daily maximum and minimum temperature and daily precipitation), mean monthly climate conditions (mean monthly relative humidity, wind speed and cloud cover), latitude, elevation, vegetation (mean monthly live, standing and litter biomass, active root depth profile) and soil properties (texture of each soil layer). SOILWAT estimates processes for each functional plant group including interception by vegetation and litter, evaporation of intercepted water, transpiration and hydraulic redistribution from each soil layer. Transpiration and evaporation are estimated by limiting potential rates with stress functions of soil water potential, atmospheric demand, seasonal leaf area, rooting distribution, vegetation-specific critical soil moisture values of water extraction and shading of canopy and litter
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" class="xref">41</xref>. This is an approach comparable to the modified Jarvis–Stewart model
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" class="xref">43</xref>. SOILWAT estimates hydrological processes including partitioning of precipitation into snowfall and rain, snow accumulation, melt and loss, infiltration into the soil profile, percolation for each soil layer, bare soil evaporation and deep drainage
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" class="xref">39</xref>. PET is calculated using the Sellers' formulation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref> of Penman
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref> which incorporates day length effects. Because estimations of PET with Penman-based equations using data from NCEP/CFSR tend to under-estimate PET in dry regions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" class="xref">46</xref>, we corrected our PET estimates by multiplication with 1.2 based on a comparison with PET values for 1961–1990 (FAO global map of monthly reference evapotranspiration—10′; available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.fao.org/</ext-link>; accessed on 24 Oct 2012)
</p>
