<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on the literature on climate change strategies, we argue that the above‐mentioned activities can be grouped along four main strategic intents: 
 <italic class="italic">governance</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">innovation</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">compensation</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">legitimation</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">Governance</italic> refers to an organization's capabilities of dealing with risks and opportunities related to climate change mitigation and resulting governance mechanisms (Boiral, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Tang and Luo, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) and can be broken down into three corporate activities: GHG management and policy development, organizational involvement, and risk management. 
 <italic class="italic">Innovation</italic> embraces activities that are geared towards the technological improvement of existing products and processes and the development of new ones with the aim of reducing GHG emissions and gaining competitive advantages (Kolk and Pinkse, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Compensation</italic> ‘describes the action taken by a company to balance or offset its CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions, such as buying CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> credits or enhancing carbon sinks’ (Weinhofer and Hoffmann, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) while leaving ‘a company's own technological assets and competencies merely unaltered’ (Kolk and Pinkse, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). This includes the reduction of a company's indirect emissions through supplier involvement. The fourth objective, 
 <italic class="italic">legitimation</italic>, summarizes activities aimed at retaining or gaining legitimacy for doing the respective business. While some of these measures can be of a rather symbolic nature, others relate to compliance issues, political influence and transparency (Boiral, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Talbot and Boiral, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
