<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The latest projections of soil organic carbon (SOC) changes from different Earth system models (ESMs) show a very wide range of values, adding uncertainty on land-atmospheric carbon (C) feedback under climate change (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). Because the soil is the largest terrestrial C pool, different representations of SOC turnover may amplify the magnitude and even the sign of the C balance (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Recent studies suggest that the general soil C sink simulated by 2100 is too optimistic, as ESMs underestimate the mean age of SOC (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>). Moreover, the level of confidence of current projections and the possibility of improving process descriptions of SOC dynamics may be further limited by the exclusion of relevant processes, such as soil erosion (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). This erosional process not only redistributes SOC across the landscape but also generates different feedbacks (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>). In eroding landscape positions, the C that is laterally displaced can be partially replaced with new photosynthates stabilized by the less C-saturated subsoil exposed by erosion, generating a continuous C sink (that is, dynamic replacement) (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). The displaced SOC can be mineralized during transport and preserved in depositional sites with different degrees of efficiency (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>). Depending on the strength of these processes, which remain the topic of scientific debate, erosion has been claimed to induce both a net source and net sink of C (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>). A recent study, for instance, estimates that erosion has offset one-third of C emissions from land cover change since the onset of agriculture (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>). This global-scale analysis highlights how agricultural perturbation of more stable land use (grassland and forest) could generate a C sink over millennia (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>). In these approaches, the net effect of soil erosion on soil-atmosphere C exchange is inferred from the measurement of SOC stock change against a reference soil profile, which may integrate the effect of other drivers in addition to the induced erosion effect on the C cycle (the so-called black box model). For instance, primary productivity and soil respiration can be affected by anthropogenic interventions in eroding/depositional areas, leading to a SOC change not entirely driven by the “erosion effect.” Therefore, inventory-based approaches are really useful for tracking past changes but are unlikely to be useful for predicting future change in which the impacts of projected climate on both vertical C fluxes (photosynthesis and respiration) and, indirectly, C redistribution by rainfall erosivity variation are important drivers. As erosion is a widespread phenomenon, especially on current agricultural land use (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>), any approach oriented toward projecting future changes requires a framework that can dynamically assess variation of drivers at the same time, integrating current erosion rates as a baseline condition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The erosion-induced C feedbacks have been studied at the scale of small hillslopes and watersheds (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>), but the lack of large-scale data, in conjunction with gaps in process understanding, has prevented the coupling of erosion/distribution processes in large-scale modeling. For explaining past changes, several large-scale data-driven approaches (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>) or integrated small-scale modeling (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) studies have been published, but no study to date has attempted to project future changes, which is the subject of this paper.
 </p>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biogeochemistry-erosion model framework</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we use a consistent biogeochemistry-erosion model framework to quantify the impact of future climate on the C cycle, taking into account accelerated water erosion through variation in rainfall erosivity (
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>). The model couples the process-based biogeochemistry model CENTURY (
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
    <span class="italic">19</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
    <span class="italic">20</span>
   </a>) and the RUSLE2015 erosion model (
   <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
    <span class="italic">21</span>
   </a>), the latter based on the Revised Universal Soil Loss Equation (RUSLE). The strength of this approach is that (i) any SOC change related to land use or management activity, including the effect of climate on plant productivity and soil respiration, propagates as a different amount (and type) of displaced SOC, potentially inducing a dynamic feedback, and (ii) land use and management directly affect the soil erosion rates, giving a bidirectional feedback on C balance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This integrated model has already been used to quantify the current impact of erosion in the agricultural soil of the European Union (EU) at a resolution of 1 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> (fig. S1) (
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>), showing a high level of accuracy in simulating dynamic replacement in comparison with previous studies and the overall SOC budget (section S2: figs. S2 to S5). Some of the previous assumptions on sediment distribution that are required for running the model at continental scale were further tested using a delivery/sedimentary model, as detailed in section S3 (figs. S6 and S7 and table S1).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model was run for the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 4.5 climate scenario as simulated by the HadGEM2 climate model, with current erosion (CE) and accelerated erosion (AE), the latter induced by the rainfall erosivity change as calculated recently by Panagos 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>). When the model incorporates erosion, the C balance accounts for C displacement components (see Materials and Methods) and does not generate CO
   <sub>2</sub> fluxes until the C is mineralized. As we were interested in the net C exchange between soil and atmosphere, the net soil C flux was calculated
   <div id="E1" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">net</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">H</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">Tm</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">Bm</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div>where C
   <sub>I</sub> and C
   <sub>H</sub> are the so-called vertical fluxes representing the atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> fixed in litter inputs and released by soil heterotrophic respiration, respectively, while C
   <sub>Tm</sub> and C
   <sub>Bm</sub> are the C mineralized during transport and in the burial deposits. There is limited consensus in the literature about C mineralization during transport and its preservation at depositional sites (
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
    <span class="italic">23</span>
   </a>). To provide a range of model uncertainty, we ran the model with two configurations according to previous model sensitivity analysis (
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>): the first enhancing the erosion-induced C sink effect (e) and the second minimizing it (r) (see Materials and Methods). Last, we calculated the contribution of accelerated erosion (ΔC
   <sub>AE</sub>) on the net C exchange as the difference between the scenario with accelerated and current erosion (both under e and r uncertainty configurations)
   <div id="E2" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m2" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">netAE</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">netAE</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">netCE</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
