<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
  <p>Supplementary material for this article is available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/4/11/eaau3523/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/4/11/eaau3523/DC1</span>
  </p>
  <p>Section S1. Model framework</p>
  <p>Section S2. Model validation</p>
  <p>Section S3. Simplified versus delivery sediment soil budget</p>
  <p>Fig. S1. Modeling framework of the integration between the CENTURY biogeochemistry model application and the RUSLE2015 erosion model.</p>
  <p>Fig. S2. Distribution of LUCAS sampling location for all land uses.</p>
  <p>Fig. S3. Comparison of cumulative SOC stock distribution between simulated and LUCAS values grouped at the national level.</p>
  <p>Fig. S4. Comparison of cumulative SOC stock distribution between simulated and LUCAS values grouped for environmental factors.</p>
  <p>Fig. S5. Comparison of modeled erosion-induced vertical C exchange against inventory-based data.</p>
  <p>Fig. S6. Selected regions where the model configuration intercomparison was run.</p>
  <p>Fig. S7. Simulated C balance components of CENTURY driven by the WATEM model in comparison with the standard original and corrected sedimentary parameterization.</p>
  <p>Fig. S8. Change in soil erosion by 2050 and 2070 due to projected changes in rainfall erosivity.</p>
  <p>Fig. S9. Distribution of change in NPP between depositional and eroding areas for the different scenarios simulated.</p>
  <p>Table S1. Comparison of C budget between different couplings of CENTURY with erosion/delivery sediment parameterizations (Mg C km
   <span class="sup">−1</span> year
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) in the selected regions.
  </p>
  <p>Table S2. Cumulative C budget (Tg C year
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) over the period 2016–2100 at the EU level for scenarios with accelerated (AE) and current (CE) soil erosion.
  </p>
  <p>References (
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
    <span class="italic">36</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
    <span class="italic">44</span>
   </a>)
  </p>
 </div>
</div>
