<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">In the absence of international or domestic legally-binding responsibilities (also known as hard law) for MNCs, several internationally-recognized intergovernmental and non-governmental organizations have been formed within the realm of soft law. Soft law is a quasi-legal instrument that aims to institutionalize a social norm without exerting legally-binding force. Most efforts in this area have been devoted to addressing transparency and disclosure; they aim to create incentives for MNCs to behave ethically sound, specifically where human rights and CSR are concerned (Sutton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">2003</xref>; Backer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2008</xref>). Two important instances of state-involved soft-law innovations are the initiatives of the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) and the United Nations Global Compact (UNGC). The OECD has developed principles that build on the notion of transparency, including the OECD Principles of Corporate Governance (OECD 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2004</xref>) and the Guidelines for Multinational Corporations (OECD 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2008</xref>). These provide “the contours for a system of monitoring and reporting that have a potentially significant application to issues of environmental transparency […] without invoking the formal structures of the domestic legal orders of participating states” (Backer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2012</xref>, 110). The UNGC is perhaps one of the most recognizable initiatives for the collection and disclosure of CSR-related information (Akhtarkhavari 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2010</xref>); it is organized around ten conduct-oriented principles covering subjects such as “human rights, labour, environmental and anticorruption values,” all of which aim to create a framework for corporate accountability (Backer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2012</xref>, 115). Though the UNGC requires an Annual Communication of Progress (CoP), this communication is based on self-reporting. Nonetheless, failing to comply could change an organization’s status to ‘non-communicating’ or ‘inactive.’
</p>
