<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Despite prominent influence of natural variability (Kumar et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Li &amp; Ting, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), the Asian summer monsoon is predominantly affected by greenhouse gases (GHGs) and aerosols in the twentieth century (Singh, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Turner &amp; Annamalai, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). It has been shown that GHGs and aerosols have significant competing effects on monsoon rainfall change, with aerosols dominating the total drying trend during the twentieth century (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). A number of studies have addressed the possible physical mechanisms of aerosol‐induced tropical rainfall and monsoon changes (Ganguly et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012a</xref>; Guo et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Hwang et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Lau et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Unlike GHGs that induce a strong atmospheric moistening through an increase in sea surface temperature (SST), aerosols affect monsoon rainfall largely through changes in atmospheric circulation (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Increased aerosols in the atmosphere could reduce the surface solar radiation (“dimming” effect) that reduces the local SST gradient in the Indian Ocean (Chung &amp; Ramanathan, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Ramanathan et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>) and introduces a hemispheric energy imbalance caused by the spatial inhomogeneity of aerosol distributions (Bollasina et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), as well as increase atmospheric stability through direct and indirect effects (Lau &amp; Kim, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), contributing to weakened monsoon circulation. Some other studies find that aerosols may enhance monsoon rainfall and circulation over the South China Sea and western Pacific (Jiang et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) or cause an earlier onset and enhanced June rainfall over India (Bollasina et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) due to absorbing aerosols such as black carbon (Lau et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>), indicating high complexity and uncertainty associated with aerosol‐monsoon interactions.
</p>
