<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">From an energetics perspective, the response of the climate system to an external forcing involves two components on different time scales: the fast response without the mediation of SST and the slow response due to SST feedbacks (Allen &amp; Ingram, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Andrews et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). The fast and slow components may lead to differing responses in the hydrological cycle, often studied using idealized atmospheric general circulation model (AGCM) experiments with prescribed SSTs (Hsieh et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Richardson et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Shaw &amp; Voigt, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). A number of studies have shown that GHGs may cause compensating effects due to direct radiative forcing (fast response) and SST change (slow response) in atmospheric circulation, particularly over the Asian monsoon region, leading to large uncertainties and model spreads in coupled model simulations (Li &amp; Ting, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Shaw &amp; Voigt, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Also, for GHGs, some studies have emphasized the importance of the fast adjustments in explaining the total rainfall responses (Bony et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Li &amp; Ting, 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). However, for anthropogenic aerosols, it has been shown that the slow response due to SST change may dominate the total monsoon rainfall and circulation changes over India (Ganguly et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012b</xref>) and East Asia (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), while the fast adjustments due to sulfate aerosols contribute to a slightly intensified East Asian monsoon (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), both studies using a single AGCM. How much of the total monsoon response can be explained by the aerosol fast response without the mediation of SSTs? What is the role of SST feedbacks? These questions have not been fully explored for aerosol forcing.
</p>
