<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="RSTB20180550F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Variation in potential and observed thermal safety margins (TSMs) of populations with respect to thermal range position. (
   <italic>a</italic>) Wedge of potential TSMs for organisms with respect to thermal range position. TSMs of all organisms, irrespective of range position or niche type, occur within blue-, red- or grey-shaded areas of the triangle. Blue shading represents the axis of lowest potential sensitivity, where species-specific thermal limits are, on average, conserved across a species range. TSMs therefore decline between the cool and warm edge of a species distribution. Red shading represents the axis of highest potential sensitivity, where upper thermal limits resemble maximum local environmental temperatures (e.g. via local adaptation or phenotypic plasticity). TSMs are therefore close to zero, irrespective of range position. (
   <italic>b</italic>) Frequency of experimental populations from six marine phyla with mean upper TSMs in the upper 90th percentile (i.e. lowest sensitivity) and lower 10th percentile (i.e. highest sensitivity) portion of the observed TSM wedge. Sample sizes are: Arthropoda 
   <italic>n</italic> = 21, Chlorophyta 
   <italic>n</italic> = 25, Chordata 
   <italic>n</italic> = 42, Mollusca 
   <italic>n</italic> = 31, Rhodophyta 
   <italic>n</italic> = 91, Ochrophyta 
   <italic>n</italic> = 51. (
   <italic>c</italic>) Empirical relationships between TSMs and global range position of marine organisms from six marine phyla, based on upper thermal limits extracted from GlobTherm [
   <xref rid="RSTB20180550C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Coloured shapes illustrate TSMs from experimental populations and shaded areas represent their empirical wedge. Upper, middle and lower coloured lines represent 95th percentile, 50th percentile and 5th percentiles of points from each phylum. Solid and dashed black lines indicate overall significant and non-significant relationships of the 95th and 5th quantiles, respectively, across all marine taxa combined. Grey-shaded areas indicate the overall 95% CI of the quantile regressions, across all taxa. Individual plot of Echinodermata (
   <italic>n</italic> = 4) is not presented owing to the small sample size.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="rstb20180550-g1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
