<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="grl58562-sec-0012" class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We would like to thank the two anonymous reviewers for constructive comments. We acknowledge the World Climate Research Programme's Working Group on Coupled Modelling, which is responsible for CMIP, and we thank the climate modeling groups for producing and making available their model output which are available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://esgf-node.llnl.gov/search/cmip5/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://esgf-node.llnl.gov/search/cmip5/</ext-link>. For CMIP the U.S. Department of Energy's Program for Climate Model Diagnosis and Intercomparison provides coordinating support and led development of software infrastructure in partnership with the Global Organization for Earth System Science Portals. We thank Urs Beyerle for the retrieval and preparation of CMIP5 model data. We also acknowledge the providers of observation data of the following products: CMORPH (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/precip/global_CMORPH/3-hourly_025deg" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ftp://ftp.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/precip/global_CMORPH/3-hourly_025deg</ext-link>), GLEAM (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gleam.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.gleam.eu/</ext-link>), AMSR‐E (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.geo.vu.nl/jeur/lprm/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.geo.vu.nl/jeur/lprm/</ext-link>). We also thank Robert M. Parinussa for providing the daily AMSR‐E data from LPRM in local time and Diego Miralles for the derivation of before‐noon evaporative stress estimates for Guillod et al. (
  <xref rid="grl58562-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) that are also used here. This study was supported by the European Research Council (ERC) “DROUGHT‐HEAT” project funded through the European Community's Seventh Framework Programme (grant agreement FP7‐IDEAS‐ERC‐617518).
 </p>
</ack>
