<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we investigated waterbird distribution and association with habitat features in a wetland network in southwestern Spain. For this purpose, we combined regular sampling of waterbird occurrences at fixed localities throughout a complete annual cycle with in-situ data measurements of relevant environmental variables. Owing to the complex and dynamic nature of these wetlands, local environmental variables are expected to be better predictors of waterbird presence than more general, large-scale and often static topo-climatic or average environmental variables [
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. In turn, our study area, which includes the Doñana wetland complex, provides an ideal case study for assessing the impacts of anthropogenic and climate stressors on waterbird populations. The wetland network is one of the most important breeding sites for waterbirds in Europe, but also a key stopover and wintering hotspot for migratory waterbirds coming from Central and Northern Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Further, human and climate impacts on wetlands are particularly severe in this Mediterranean region [
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], a trend that will likely continue and further exacerbate pressures on wetland biodiversity well into the future [
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Accordingly, we framed our results within the current global warming trend that is expected to cause changes in wetland conditions (e.g., increasing salinity and temporality of water bodies) by predicting changes in waterbird occurrence, and hence in habitat suitability, within different scenarios of climate change. In particular, we fitted statistical models to the habitat selection of individual species of waterbirds in this typical Mediterranean wetland network along an annual cycle. We aimed to predict how habitat suitability for each species would improve or deteriorate under three climate change scenarios within the range of predictions of regional climatic models for the next hundred years.
</p>
