<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 2.</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Mean annual warm season heat-related mortality rates (per 100,000) attributable to climate change (
   <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
    <math id="M65" class="math">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</mi>
      <mi class="mi">M</mi>
      <mi class="mi">o</mi>
      <mi class="mi">r</mi>
      <mi class="mi">t</mi>
      <mo class="mo">-</mo>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
     </mrow>
    </math>
   </inline-formula>) for 2070–2099 using climate change projections from Global Climate Model (GCM) HadGEM2-ES run under Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5, when different adaptation modeling methods are applied. Also displayed is 
   <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
    <math id="M66" class="math">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</mi>
      <mi class="mi">M</mi>
      <mi class="mi">o</mi>
      <mi class="mi">r</mi>
      <mi class="mi">t</mi>
      <mo class="mo">-</mo>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
     </mrow>
    </math>
   </inline-formula> with climate change projections from five GCMs run under RCP8.5 with no adaptation (“GCMs”), and 
   <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
    <math id="M67" class="math">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</mi>
      <mi class="mi">M</mi>
      <mi class="mi">o</mi>
      <mi class="mi">r</mi>
      <mi class="mi">t</mi>
      <mo class="mo">-</mo>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
     </mrow>
    </math>
   </inline-formula> with climate change projections from HadGEM2-ES run under two emissions scenarios (RCP2.6 and RCP8.5) with no adaptation (“RCPs”). Blue lines and whiskers denote where impacts have been estimated with adaptation modeling methods employed and red lines and whiskers denote where impacts have been estimated with no adaptation. 
   <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
    <math id="M68" class="math">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <msub class="msub">
       <mi class="mi">A</mi>
       <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">x</mi>
      </msub>
     </mrow>
    </math>
   </inline-formula> denotes the number of adaptation modeling methods that have a range that is greater than or equal to the range for GCMs and/or RCPs. The ranges are quantitatively summarized in 
   <xref ref-type="table" rid="t4" class="xref">Table 4</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text class="alt-text">Graphical representation of the mortality rate attributable to climate change per 100,000 people for fourteen cities, namely, Athens, Budapest, Barcelona, Helsinki, Ljubljana, London, Milan, Paris, Prague, Rome, Stockholm, Turin, Valencia, and Zurich. The range in impacts is plotted as thresh (degree Celsius), thresh (percentage), slope, thresh (degree Celsius) plus slope, thresh (percentage) plus slope, analog, GCMs and RCPs.</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="EHP634_f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
