<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">Long before Paris 2015, there has been an ongoing and flourishing debate among scientists about the time path to contain global warming. The timing issue is largely concerned with the choice of appropriate discount rates (Weitzman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2001</xref>; Nordhaus 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2007</xref>; Heath 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2013</xref>) and how to assess the risk of unlikely but potentially disastrous outcomes, e.g., reversal of the “thermohaline circulation,” also known as the “Great Ocean Conveyor Belt” of the Gulf Stream and the exacerbated release of methane due to global warming from the Arctic permafrost. Here, we abstract from the time path and concentrate on how the abatement burdens should be allocated across regions in the world at a given point in time. Given the urgency to reduce GHG emissions worldwide, the most difficult issue is how the burdens are distributed across regions. Since climate change is a global public good, it requires a global burden sharing rule. The two dominant guiding principles for fair burden sharing are the polluter pays principle and the ability to pay principle. For instance, the Stern Review (Stern 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2007</xref>, p. 23) states that based on income, historic responsibility, and per capita emissions, rich countries should take the primary responsibility to combat climate change. However, the literature on burden sharing emphasizes the free-riding problem as a consequence of climate change being a public good (Gupta 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">1997</xref>). Thus, one important strand in the literature has analyzed the challenge of relating damage caused by climate change to economic activities, which are often occurring in distinct places (see, for example, Edwards and Miller 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2001</xref>; Voigt 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2008</xref> and Dellink et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2009</xref>). This paper contributes to this literature by avoiding the problem of having to establish the causation from polluter to damage experienced, by turning instead to countries own interest. In this paper, we derive the burden sharing rule following the Lindahl equilibrium (hereafter LE), where burden shares are not so much determined by ability to pay or (historical) emissions, but by countries’ interest, e.g., due to expected damages, to combat global warming.
</p>
