<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Zool</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Curr Zool</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">czoolo</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Current Zoology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1674-5507</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5804209</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cz/zow109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">zow109</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long-term data from a small mammal community reveal loss of diversity and potential effects of local climate change</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>Simone</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff1">a</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="zow109-cor1"/><author-comment content-type="other"><p>
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>The first two authors contributed equally to this work.</p></author-comment><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="zow109-FM2"/><!--<email>santoro@ebd.csic.es</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Suarez</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff1">a</xref><author-comment content-type="other"><p>
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>The first two authors contributed equally to this work.</p></author-comment><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="zow109-FM2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rouco</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palomo</surname><given-names>L. Javier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff4">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>M. Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff4">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kufner</surname><given-names>Maura B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff5">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Sacramento</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="zow109-aff1">a</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="zow109-aff1">
<label>a</label>Ethology and Biodiversity Conservation Department, Do&#x000f1;ana Biological Station-CSIC, Am&#x000e9;rico Vespucio s/n, Seville 41092, Spain</aff><aff id="zow109-aff2">
<label>b</label>Departamento de Zoolog&#x000ed;a, Campus de Rabanales, Universidad de C&#x000f3;rdoba, C&#x000f3;rdoba 14071, Spain</aff><aff id="zow109-aff3">
<label>c</label>Wildlife Ecology and Management Team, Private Bag 1930, Dunedin 9054, New Zealand</aff><aff id="zow109-aff4">
<label>d</label>Departamento de Biolog&#x000ed;a Animal, Universidad de M&#x000e1;laga, M&#x000e1;laga 29071, Spain</aff><aff id="zow109-aff5">
<label>e</label>Diego de Onorato 67, Barrio Uritorco, C&#x000f3;rdoba 5003, Argentina</aff><author-notes><corresp id="zow109-cor1"><label>*</label>Address correspondence to Simone Santoro. E-mail: <email>santoro@ebd.csic.es</email>.</corresp><fn id="zow109-FM2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>The first two authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2016-11-08"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author (2016). Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" license-type="cc-by-nc"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="zow109.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Climate change affects distribution and persistence of species. However, forecasting species&#x02019; responses to these changes requires long-term data series that are often lacking in ecological studies. We used 15 years of small mammal trapping data collected between 1978 and 2015 in 3 areas at Do&#x000f1;ana National Park (southwest Spain) to (i) describe changes in species composition and (ii) test the association between local climate conditions and size of small mammal populations. Overall, 5 species were captured: wood mouse <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic>, algerian mouse <italic>Mus spretus</italic>, greater white-toothed shrew <italic>Crocidura russula</italic>, garden dormouse <italic>Eliomys quercinus</italic>, and black rat <italic>Rattus rattus</italic>. The temporal pattern in the proportion of captures of each species suggests that the small mammal diversity declined with time. Although the larger species (e.g., <italic>E. quercinus</italic>), better adapted to colder climate, have disappeared from our trapping records, <italic>M. spretus</italic>, a small species inhabiting southwest Europe and the Mediterranean coast of Africa, currently is almost the only trapped species. We used 2-level hierarchical models to separate changes in abundance from changes in probability of capture using records of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> in all 3 areas and of <italic>M. spretus</italic> in 1. We found that heavy rainfall and low temperatures were positively related to abundance of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic>, and that the number of extremely hot days was negatively related to abundance of <italic>M. spretus</italic>. Despite other mechanisms are likely to be involved, our findings support the importance of climate for the distribution and persistence of these species and raise conservation concerns about potential cascading effects in the Do&#x000f1;ana ecosystem.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>climate change</kwd><kwd>count data</kwd><kwd>N-mixture models</kwd><kwd>rodents</kwd><kwd>spain</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Our planet is experiencing dramatic environmental and climatic change. In the past 100 years, anthropogenic activities have raised the concentration of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, leading to an increase in the Earth&#x02019;s average annual temperature of 0.6&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="zow109-B46" ref-type="bibr">Parmesan 2006</xref>), threatening the integrity of ecosystems (<xref rid="zow109-B55" ref-type="bibr">Walther et al. 2002</xref>). Besides global warming, extreme and sudden changes of seasonal temperatures are currently occurring worldwide and, in particular, in the Mediterranean region (<xref rid="zow109-B2" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. 2014</xref>). In this area, climate models predict increasing mean and maximum temperatures and a reduction in precipitation (<xref rid="zow109-B16" ref-type="bibr">Giorgi and Lionello 2008</xref>).</p><p>Recent studies on ecological effects of climate change have mainly focused on how they affect the species geographical distribution, physiology, phenology, and local abundances (<xref rid="zow109-B21" ref-type="bibr">Jonzen et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B46" ref-type="bibr">Parmesan 2006</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B52" ref-type="bibr">Teplitsky et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B39" ref-type="bibr">Myers et al. 2009</xref>). As well as long-term trends, unpredictable and fast changes in local climate conditions over short periods (so-called &#x0201c;extreme events&#x0201d;) have an important but often overlooked effect on the distribution and persistence of species (<xref rid="zow109-B13" ref-type="bibr">Easterling et al. 2000</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B32" ref-type="bibr">Moreno and Moller 2011</xref>). Many studies have shown that the species geographical distributions are already changing in response to global warming, in particular by shifting toward higher latitudinal and altitudinal ranges (<xref rid="zow109-B55" ref-type="bibr">Walther et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2011</xref>). Changes of duration, seasonality, and intensity of rainfall have also been related to life-history changes among mammals, birds, and amphibians (<xref rid="zow109-B5" ref-type="bibr">Carey and Alexander 2003</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B38" ref-type="bibr">Moritz et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B1" ref-type="bibr">Altwegg and Anderson 2009</xref>).</p><p>Because of their short lifespan and fast life-history responses to environmental changes, small mammals are ideal model species for studying climatic effects on animal population dynamics. Furthermore, they play an important role in their ecosystems as seed dispersers, predators, and main preys of several mammalian carnivores and raptors (<xref rid="zow109-B8" ref-type="bibr">Delany and Delany 1974</xref>). Recently, it has been shown that the elevational limits of many small mammal species in the Yosemite National Park (N America) have shifted northward consistent with the &#x0223c;3&#x000b0;C increase of minimum temperature during the last century (<xref rid="zow109-B38" ref-type="bibr">Moritz et al. 2008</xref>). A study (<xref rid="zow109-B39" ref-type="bibr">Myers et al. 2009</xref>) with collections&#x02019; records of small mammals in the Great Lakes region has shown a marked decline in the presence of northern species accompanied by an increase of southern species over a period similar to the present study. Others have shed light on some mechanisms that modulate the effects of climate on small mammals dynamics. For instance, <xref rid="zow109-B22" ref-type="bibr">Kausrud et al. (2008)</xref> found that reduction and duration of the subnivean space induced by warming-climate had a negative impact on survival and reproductive performance of Fennoscandian rodents consequently altering their cycles. Moreover, studies from paleontological data have linked ancient climate change on the distribution of small mammal species (<xref rid="zow109-B49" ref-type="bibr">Ses&#x000e9; Benito 1994</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B6" ref-type="bibr">Casanovas-Vilar et al. 2010</xref>).</p><p>The present study evaluates the long-term species composition and the possible role of local climate change in the small mammal community at the Do&#x000f1;ana National Park (DNP), a large protected area located in southwest Spain which is part of the Mediterranean Basin hotspot. According to the hypothesis of climate effect on species distribution and abundance, we expect that species&#x02019; abundance vary in response to long-term climate change consistently with their climatic requirements. Therefore we predict that, with local climate warming, the abundance of species for which Do&#x000f1;ana represents the southern limit of the distribution range will decrease whereas abundance of species at the northern limit will increase. We used 15 years of trapping data from a period spanning 37 years (1978&#x02013;2015). First, we described the community dynamics as shown by the proportion of species captures for each campaign. Then, we tested the relationship between climate variation and temporal changes in the small mammal species abundances.</p><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study area</title><p>This study was conducted in DNP (37&#x000b0; N, 6&#x000b0;10&#x02032; W), a plain area (0&#x02013;106 m a.s.l.), located in the southwest of the Iberian Peninsula, in the Guadalquivir River mouth on the Atlantic ocean. This area is one of the most important natural reserves in Europe, designated as a Biosphere Reserve in 1980 with a special protection status. The climate is Mediterranean sub-humid with 2 marked seasons: wet mild winters (mean temperature in January&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) and dry warm summers (mean temperature in August&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) (<xref rid="zow109-B50" ref-type="bibr">Suso and Llamas 1993</xref>). The rainy period occurs between October and April, with a peak in December&#x02013;January (yearly average precipitation&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;600&#x02009;mm year&#x02009;<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;<sup>1</sup>). Three main biotopes can be distinguished in DNP: (1) marshes on a clay area with a regular flood pattern during winter; (2) mobile sand dunes parallel to the sea coast; and (3) scrubland that, according to proximity to the water table, is either xerophytic Mediterranean scrubland (drier), or hygrophytic Atlantic scrubland (more humid) (<xref rid="zow109-B36" ref-type="bibr">Moreno and Kufner 1988</xref>).</p><p>The present study was located in the xerophytic Mediterranean scrubland, which is 65&#x02013;70% covered by xerophytic shrubs (e.g., <italic>Halimium halimifolium</italic>, <italic>Cistus</italic> spp., <italic>Ulex</italic> spp., <italic>Genista anglica</italic>, <italic>Lavandula stoechas</italic>, <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>, and <italic>Thymus mastichina</italic>). Trapping was carried out in 3 different areas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zow109-F1">Figure 1</xref>) named &#x0201c;San Agust&#x000ed;n&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Las Pajareras&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;Las Monjas&#x0201d;. During the study period the land use of these areas was not altered so that no artificial environmental changes occurred.
</p><fig id="zow109-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Study area. The 3 study sites position within the DNP (delimited by borders) located in southern Spain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zow109f1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Study species</title><p>The small mammal community is characterized by low species diversity compared with other areas in the European mainland (<xref rid="zow109-B37" ref-type="bibr">Moreno and Rouco 2013</xref>), and is limited to 8 species: garden dormouse <italic>Eliomys quercinus</italic>, black rat <italic>Rattus rattus</italic>, wood mouse <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic>, algerian mouse <italic>Mus spretus</italic>, mediterranean pine vole <italic>Microtus duodecimcostatus</italic>, western hedgehog <italic>Erinaceus europaeus</italic>, greater white-toothed shrew <italic>Crocidura russula</italic>, and pygmy white-toothed shrew <italic>Suncus etruscus</italic> (<xref rid="zow109-B44" ref-type="bibr">Palomo et al. 2007</xref>). The first 5 are rodents and the others insectivores. Throughout the study period, <italic>E. europaeus</italic> and <italic>S. etruscus</italic> were never caught as the used traps are not appropriate for these species.</p><p>For <italic>E. quercinus</italic>, a generalist species present in the Mediterranean scrubland (<xref rid="zow109-B35" ref-type="bibr">Moreno 2002</xref>), Do&#x000f1;ana represents the southern limit of its geographical distribution. <italic>Crocidura russula</italic> is a small insectivorous rodent adapted to Mediterranean climate and widely distributed in Europe and North Africa (<xref rid="zow109-B29" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000f3;pezFuster 2007</xref>). <italic>Rattus rattus</italic> is a very widespread species with an average body mass of 300&#x02009;g. <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> shows a wide distribution throughout the western Palearctic with a southern limit corresponding to the west Mediterranean coast of Africa (<xref rid="zow109-B31" ref-type="bibr">Montgomery 1999</xref>). <italic>Mus spretus</italic> is associated with the Mediterranean climate and can survive even very dry conditions that no other rodent species can (<xref rid="zow109-B44" ref-type="bibr">Palomo et al. 2007</xref>). <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> and <italic>M. spretus</italic> overlap in their distribution range, and in habitat and food preferences (<xref rid="zow109-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bauduin et al. 2013</xref>). However, <italic>M. spretus</italic> prefers open habitats, whereas <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> prefers greater vegetation cover (<xref rid="zow109-B24" ref-type="bibr">Khidas et al. 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Trapping</title><p>Each trapping area was approximately 1&#x000a0;hectare, and separated from the other sites by at least 1,000 m to ensure independence of data (i.e., no interchange of individuals among sites, <xref rid="zow109-B26" ref-type="bibr">Kufner and Moreno 1989</xref>). Sites were of similar soil type and distance to marshes. The trapping method was consistent throughout the study period. We used 2 types of live-traps that yielded similar capture rates (personal observation): Sherman&#x02019;s live-traps and similar traps manufactured by the technical staff. All the traps were baited with bread soaked in fish oil and placed across a grid, 15 m apart. They were installed just before sunset of the first day and checked each day 2&#x000a0;h after sunrise. Each trapped specimen was individually marked when first captured. Three methods were used to mark animals: toe-clipping (1978&#x02013;2007), subcutaneous microchip (2005&#x02013;2007), and color points micro-tattooing in the tail (2012&#x02013;2015).</p><p>Trapping was performed through 15 years within a period spanning 37 years (1978&#x02013;2015). We carried out 5 <italic>trapping campaigns</italic>, that is, periods of consecutive years of sampling funded by different projects: 1978&#x02013;1981 (<xref rid="zow109-B33" ref-type="bibr">Moreno 1984a</xref>), 1984&#x02013;1985 (<xref rid="zow109-B25" ref-type="bibr">Kufner 1986</xref>), 1986&#x02013;1987, 2005&#x02013;2007, and 2012&#x02013;2015. Trapping data were collected over the 4 seasons except from 2012 onward when sampling was not performed on summer due to the very small number of captures typically made in that season. During each season and site there was a variable number of <italic>trapping sessions</italic> which in turn consisted of a variable number of consecutive <italic>trapping days</italic> over which data were collected.</p><p>We focused on data at 2 different time-scales: (i) for the community species composition analysis we used the total number of captures for each species found at each <italic>trapping campaign</italic>, whereas (ii) for the analysis of species abundances at each site we used the number of captured individuals at each <italic>trapping day</italic> in winter. For the latter analysis, we focused on data from a single season because we needed to define yearly time-intervals short enough to assume that the population size remained approximately constant. We used data from winter because of the higher number of captures and of years for which trapping data were available. For the analysis of species abundances at each site we disposed of a variable number of years (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) as well as of <italic>trapping sessions</italic> (San Agustin, min: 1, max: 4; Las Pajareras, min: 1, max: 2; Las Monjas, min: 1, max: 1) and of consecutive <italic>trapping days</italic> (San Agustin, min: 3, max: 7; Las Pajareras, min: 4, max: 7; Las Monjas, min: 5, max: 7). Different numbers of traps were used in each area over the entire study period (min: 50, max: 150 traps/day, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S1</xref> for details) but we accounted for this variation in the statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Community species composition analysis</title><p>To describe long-term changes at the community level, we used an index of relative abundance consisting of the number of captures for each species per 1,000 traps/days-of-sampling (<xref rid="zow109-B41" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al. 1973</xref>) at each <italic>trapping campaign</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Species abundances analysis</title><p>Methodological issues typically hinder the study of climate effects on dynamics of populations, species, and communities. First, these studies require long-term data collected over a time span broad enough to include climate variations. Second, analyses of counts and presence/absence data should account for imperfect detection to avoid spurious findings (<xref rid="zow109-B30" ref-type="bibr">Mackenzie and Kendall 2002</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B11" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000e9;nes et al. 2015</xref>). Even where encounter histories of individually marked animals are available, estimates of population size by capture-mark-recapture analyses (<xref rid="zow109-B27" ref-type="bibr">Lebreton et al. 1992</xref>) may be difficult to be obtained because of data sparseness and/or limited sample sizes. In these cases, another class of models, so-called Hierarchical Models (HMs, see <xref rid="zow109-B30" ref-type="bibr">Mackenzie and Kendall 2002</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B23" ref-type="bibr">Kery and Royle 2016</xref>) represent a valid alternative if spatial and/or temporal replicates (presence/absence or counts) are available. These models can tease apart variation of the latent (unobserved) variable/s (e.g., abundance, species occurrence) by variation in the observation process (e.g., imperfect detection of individuals or species). More details on the conceptual framework behind HM are given in <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="zow109-BOX1">Box 1</xref>.</p><p>We adapted the <xref rid="zow109-B48" ref-type="bibr">Royle (2004)</xref> HM to the case where temporal (among-years) instead of spatial replicates were drawn so that species&#x02019; abundance estimates at 1 site were obtained. Due to the short lifespans of the studied species and to the large time intervals between <italic>trapping campaigns</italic> we assumed that the within-species temporal correlation among population sizes was negligibly small. For this analysis, we did not use data collected during the 1986&#x02013;1987 <italic>trapping campaign</italic> because for that period we only knew the number of captures for each species per 1,000 traps/days-of-sampling. Due to the small number of captures for some species, we could analyze data from only 3 species: <italic>M. spretus</italic>, <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic>, and <italic>E. quercinus</italic> (this species at San Agustin only). HM analyses were run in R (<xref rid="zow109-B47" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team 2013</xref>) using the function &#x0201c;<italic>pcount</italic>&#x0201d; from the &#x0201c;<italic>unmarked</italic>&#x0201d; package (<xref rid="zow109-B14" ref-type="bibr">Fiske and Chandler 2011</xref>). A separate analysis was run for each area and species (R code in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Appendix S1</xref>).
<boxed-text id="zow109-BOX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Box 1. HMs in a nutshell</p></caption><p>According to the definition that <xref rid="zow109-B23" ref-type="bibr">Kery and Royle (2016)</xref> propose in their book, an HM is a sequence of models ordered by their conditional probability structure. Typically, an HM involves at least one model (or level of the HM model) that refers to a latent (unobserved) variable. The latent variable can consist of: (i) a random effect, where an ecological measurement like presence/absence or count replicates are more similar within than among groups (e.g., site) or (ii) a state variable like the site-specific (real) presence or absence of a species or its population size. The first example resembles the classical random effects models (also called multi-level, or mixed models) with an unobservable latent variable which accounts for non-independence and similarity of sampling replicates within groups. Here, we focus on HMs as that described in the second example where the latent variable is the outcome of natural processes and therefore consists of a real quantity as the occupancy state or the population abundance at a certain site. <xref rid="zow109-B48" ref-type="bibr">Royle (2004)</xref> proposed an HM for count replicates collected at a number of sites through a period short enough to assume that population sizes do not vary over the study period. This 2-level HM considers the observed counts as a function of an observation process which in turn depends on the population size at each site. In mathematical terms it is:
<disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Binomial</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>y<sub>ij</sub></italic>, that is the counts at site <italic>i</italic> at the <italic>j</italic>th occasion is conditional on the local population size (<italic>N<sub>i</sub></italic>) and follows a binomial distribution where <italic>p</italic> is the individual-level probability of detection. The local population size follows a distribution such as:
<disp-formula id="E2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0223c;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Poisson</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Notably, N-mixture models like that illustrated allow for the direct estimation and hypotheses-testing of the factors that affect the spatial structure of abundance (<italic>&#x003bb;</italic>) and/or the detection probability (<italic>p</italic>).</p></boxed-text></p><p>As predictors of abundance in winter, we considered local climatic data collected by a weather station in close proximity to the study areas (downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://icts-rbd.ebd.csic.es/">http://icts-rbd.ebd.csic.es/</ext-link>) in the immediately preceding autumn, during which both <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> and <italic>M. spretus</italic> have a reproductive peak at DNP (<xref rid="zow109-B34" ref-type="bibr">Moreno 1984b</xref>). We considered: (i) the average daily mean temperatures, (ii) the total rainfall, and (iii) the number of extremely hot days, that is, with a mean temperature higher than the 90th percentile of the daily mean temperatures in autumn calculated throughout the entire study period (<xref rid="zow109-B2" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al. 2014</xref>). Over this time, the autumn mean temperatures showed an increasing trend, the total rainfall decreased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>), and the number of extremely hot days increased (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>), as expected by climate change predictions (<xref rid="zow109-B53" ref-type="bibr">Thibault and Brown 2008</xref>). As predictors of individual capture probability we considered 3 variables: daily rainfall and mean temperature during trapping days and number of traps.</p></sec><sec><title>Model selection</title><p>For each case study (area and species), we used Akaike&#x02019;s Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AICc) (<xref rid="zow109-B4" ref-type="bibr">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>), considering the number of trapping days as sample size (see details in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Appendix S1</xref>). To avoid inflated type I error, we considered models separated by less than 2 AICc as equally plausible (<xref rid="zow109-B4" ref-type="bibr">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). First, we modeled the capture probability by considering models with all the possible combinations of the above mentioned predictors (3, 2, 1, or no effect) and holding the abundance constant (only intercept). Then, we retained the model structure for the capture probability from the model with the lowest AICc value and used it to model abundance. For the sake of parsimony, we only considered models with one abundance predictor for each model. By doing so, we finally attained a list of models sorted by growing AICc values, each one representing a specific hypothesis about abundance changes. This approach allowed us to keep the number of tested models as low as possible and address simple hypotheses (<xref rid="zow109-B4" ref-type="bibr">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>).</p><p>For the first 3 winters at San Agustin, we disposed only of the total number of individuals captured during each <italic>trapping session</italic>. We obtained 100 plausible data sets for which the first 3 years <italic>trapping day</italic> counts of individuals were drawn by a multinomial distribution whose sum matched that of individuals captured at the <italic>trapping sessions</italic> level (details in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Appendix S1</xref>). Model selection was performed for each data set separately.</p></sec><sec><title>Goodness of fit</title><p>We used parametric bootstrapping (function &#x0201c;parboot&#x0201d; in &#x0201c;unmarked&#x0201d;) to test the goodness of fit (GOF) of the best model (<xref rid="zow109-B14" ref-type="bibr">Fiske and Chandler 2011</xref>). The GOF test allows validation of the model and provides an estimate of how well a model fits with a set of observations (<xref rid="zow109-B4" ref-type="bibr">Burnham and Anderson 2002</xref>). We used a significance threshold of 0.05 as a cutoff for determining adequate model fit, which was attained in only 4 cases: for <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> in the 3 areas and for <italic>M. spretus</italic> at Las Monjas (<xref ref-type="table" rid="zow109-T1">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="zow109-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>GOF analyses of the best model for <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic>, <italic>Mus spretus</italic>, and <italic>Eliomys quercinus</italic> in each sampling area: San Agustin (SA), Las Pajareras (PJ), and Las Monjas (MN)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling area</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">mean (<italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub> &#x02212; <italic>t</italic>_<italic>B</italic>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">StdDev (<italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub> &#x02212; <italic>t</italic>_<italic>B</italic>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pr (<italic>t</italic>_<italic>B</italic> &#x0003e; <italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.802</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic>Mus spretus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,284</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.931</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic>Eliomys quercinus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0198*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>Notes: Values of Pr(t_B &#x0003e; t0) &#x0003e; 0.05 (remarked by *) indicate lack of &#x0003e; model fit to the data. t0, statistic computed for the real data; t_B, statistic computed for the bootstrap samples; StdDev(t0 - t_B), difference between standard deviation of t0 and t_B.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="zow109-T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Modeling abundance changes for <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> and <italic>Mus spretus</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling area</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">lam (Int)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">lam (rain)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">lam (temp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">lam (tmextr)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">log&#x000a0;<italic>L</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AICc</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;AICc</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AICc weight</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="12" colspan="1"><italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic></td><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">SA</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.241</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.343</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;56.817</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.836</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.378</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.058</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;57.211</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.623</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.787</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.288</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.384</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;57.234</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.669</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.833</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.778</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;88.888</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">184.723</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.887</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">PJ</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.141</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.708</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;37.984</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.146</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.926</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.599</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.123</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;41.041</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.259</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.113</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.871</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;41.411</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.998</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.851</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.208</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;46.392</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.469</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.322</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">MN</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.392</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.911</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;31.449</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.438</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.676</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.338</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;34.018</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.926</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.488</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.927</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33.634</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.807</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.369</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.288</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.075</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33.994</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.527</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.089</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1"><italic>Mus spretus</italic></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">MN</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.718</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.615</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;47.061</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.661</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.530</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;49.777</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.092</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.431</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.714</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.994</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;49.934</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.406</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.745</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.067</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;52.106</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.101</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.440</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><p>Notes: Models are ranked by Akaike&#x02019;s Information Criterion corrected by small sample size (AICc); the lowest value of AICc corresponds to the best-fitting model. Lam, parameter value; df, number of estimated parameters; log<italic>&#x000a0;L</italic>, logarithm of maximum likelihood; <italic>&#x00394;</italic>AICc, difference between the AICc of the current model and the AICc of best model; AICc weight, Akaike weight for each predictor; int, intercept; temp, mean temperature in autumn; rain, cumulative rainfall in autumn, tmextr, number of days with extremely hot temperature in autumn. Note that for <italic>A. Sylvaticus</italic> at San Agust&#x000ed;n a mean value for each parameter has been reported from 100 simulated data sets. For this reason, the number of estimated parameters (df) may be not an integer.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Community species composition</title><p>Species proportional composition has varied substantially over the study period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zow109-F2">Figure 2</xref>). <italic>Eliomys quercinus</italic> showed a marked decline between the 1978&#x02013;1981 and 1986&#x02013;1987 campaigns, after which the species was never trapped again. <italic>Rattus rattus</italic> was captured only in the first campaign. Low numbers of <italic>C. russula</italic> were captured during all the campaigns except the last (2014&#x02013;2015), when it was not captured at all. Although the number of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> trappings was substantial throughout the first 3 campaigns, it declined markedly in the last 2 (from 2005 onward). The only species that showed a marked increase over the 5 campaigns was <italic>M. spretus</italic>, which represented only a small fraction of total captures in the first campaign to become the most captured species in the last 2 (2005&#x02013;2015).
</p><fig id="zow109-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Number of captures (per 1,000 traps/day) by species for each trapping campaign.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zow109f2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Species abundances</title><p>For <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> at San Agustin, the inverse relationship with mean temperature was selected as the most parsimonious model for abundance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="zow109-T2">Table 2</xref>). However, a positive relationship with rainfall and the number of extremely hot days could not be ruled out (&#x00394;AICc&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2). Based on the lowest AICc model, we estimated the mean abundance for each sampling year that varied between a minimum of 2.05 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.55; Temperature&#x02009;=&#x02009;16.86&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) and a maximum of 4.95 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.971; Temperature&#x02009;= 15.19&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zow109-F3">Figure 3</xref>).
</p><fig id="zow109-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Predicted abundance (full black circles), and total captures (full black triangles) for <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> and <italic>Mus spretus</italic>. Abundance was estimated by the lowest AICc abundance model. Predictors of species abundance were: (i) for <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> at San Agustin the daily mean temperature, (ii) for <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> at Las Pajareras the total autumn rainfall, (iii) for <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> at Las Monjas the total autumn rainfall, and (iv) for <italic>Mus spretus</italic> at Las Monjas the number of extremely hot days in autumn. Beside each point the estimated value of the corresponding predictor is shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zow109f3"/></fig><p>At Las Pajareras and Las Monjas, we found strong support for a model that accounted for a positive relationship of rainfall with abundance of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="zow109-T2">Table 2</xref>). From these models, we estimated at Las Pajareras a minimum abundance of 2.29 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;= 1.14; rainfall&#x02009;=&#x02009;91.8&#x02009;mm) and a maximum of 92.59 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;22.26; rainfall&#x02009;=&#x02009;338.5&#x02009;mm) and at Las Monjas a minimum of 12.06 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.86; rainfall&#x02009;=&#x02009;37.32&#x02009;mm) and a maximum of 88.99 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;22.13; rainfall&#x02009;=&#x02009;103.85&#x02009;mm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="zow109-F3">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>Finally, we found that abundance of <italic>M. Spretus</italic> at Las Monjas was inversely related to the number of extremely hot days in autumn (<xref ref-type="table" rid="zow109-T2">Table 2</xref>). From this model, we obtained a minimum abundance of 20.40 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.83; number of extremely hot days&#x02009;=&#x02009;16) and a maximum of 88.07 individuals (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;39.61; number of extremely hot days&#x02009;=&#x02009;6).</p></sec><sec><title>Species capture probability</title><p>At San Agustin, we found that for some of the simulated data sets (see Materials and Methods), the capture probability was inversely related to the higher daily mean temperature, while in others it was positively related also to the number of traps (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). The estimated daily average capture probability for <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> at this site was 0.164 (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.073).</p><p>At Las Pajareras, the best model for capture probability of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> accounted for a positive relationship with the number of traps (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). From this model, we estimated an average daily capture probability that resulted to be the highest we found (0.524; <italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.073) among all the species and sites. For <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic>, we found a positive relationship of number of traps on capture probability also at Las Monjas (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). The average daily probability of capture was 0.223 (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.096).</p><p>For <italic>M. Spretus</italic> at Las Monjas, the capture probability was inversely related to the number of traps (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S5</xref>) and the average daily probability of capture was 0.454 (<italic>SE</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.084).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Trapping records indicate that from late 1970s to the present time the small mammal community at DNP has exhibited a marked change in species composition. In the last 4 years <italic>M. spretus</italic>, the species most adapted to dry conditions, accounts for almost all captures. In addition, for all the cases where sufficient data were available, we found a relationship between local climate change and abundance (<italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> in the 3 study areas and <italic>M. spretus</italic> in 1). Simultaneously, there was a trend toward increased temperatures and decreased rainfall (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figures S1 and S2</xref>). Although other non-exclusive environmental factors are likely to be involved, our findings support the hypothesis that long-term climate change played a role in the local small mammals population dynamics.</p><sec><title>Climate effect hypothesis</title><p>Climate change may affect individuals and populations either directly or indirectly (<xref rid="zow109-B40" ref-type="bibr">Mysterud et al. 2002</xref>). Indeed, physiological mechanisms can be directly triggered by climate change (<xref rid="zow109-B46" ref-type="bibr">Parmesan 2006</xref>). Besides, indirect climate effects may operate by affecting the species&#x02019; ecological niches by means of changes in the environment where they live or in the interspecific relationships (<xref rid="zow109-B54" ref-type="bibr">Tylianakis et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B15" ref-type="bibr">Gilman et al. 2010</xref>). Climate warming is affecting the distribution of species toward higher latitudes and elevations (<xref rid="zow109-B38" ref-type="bibr">Moritz et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B39" ref-type="bibr">Myers et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2011</xref>). As an example, a recent study based on barn owl <italic>Tyto alba</italic> pellet analysis from multiple locations in Italy showed a consistent increase of xerothermophilic species in the small mammal communities since late 70s (<xref rid="zow109-B51" ref-type="bibr">Szpunar et al. 2008</xref>). Coherent with this scenario we found that, <italic>E. quercinus</italic>, a species more related to colder climates than that of Do&#x000f1;ana which represents the southern limit of its distributional range, has gradually disappeared from the trapping records. Conversely, <italic>M. spretus</italic>, distributed in the warm climates of southwest Europe and the western Mediterranean coast of Africa, currently represents nearly all of the species captured. The hypothesis of climate effect was also supported by the observed relationships between abundances of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> and <italic>M. spretus</italic> with, respectively, the amount of rainfall and the number of extremely hot days in the preceding autumn. Our study cannot reveal which mechanisms, if any, modulated the effects (direct or indirect) of climate variation on the DNP small mammal diversity and abundances. It is possible that their fate at Do&#x000f1;ana depended on different physiological responses to climate change (<xref rid="zow109-B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2011</xref>). For instance, lower rainfall during the reproductive peak (autumn) might have determined a reduction in the undergrowth and shrubs that are crucial for <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> and not for <italic>M. spretus</italic> which prefers open habitats (<xref rid="zow109-B24" ref-type="bibr">Khidas et al. 2002</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Other hypotheses</title><p>We cannot discard that other processes could have been involved in the observed changes in the small mammal diversity and abundances. At DNP small mammals play a key role in the trophic chain being the secondary prey of many mammalian carnivores and raptors (<xref rid="zow109-B25" ref-type="bibr">Kufner 1986</xref>) after rabbits <italic>Oryctolagus cuniculus</italic>. In the late 1980s, a greater than 60% decline in the rabbit population at DNP was caused by an outbreak of rabbit hemorrhagic disease (<xref rid="zow109-B9" ref-type="bibr">Delibes-Mateos et al. 2008</xref>) and small mammals have gained importance as a food resource for other predators (e.g., for the Iberian lynx, <xref rid="zow109-B42" ref-type="bibr">Palomares et al. 1996</xref>). Therefore, the observed changes in the DNP small mammal community might have resulted also from top-down control (<xref rid="zow109-B43" ref-type="bibr">Palomares et al. 1995</xref>), a hypothesis that we could not test due to lack of suitable data about time-changing predation pressure on these species.</p></sec><sec><title>Cascading effects</title><p>The observed reduction of small mammal diversity and abundance should warn ecologists and conservationists against the possible cascading effects this might cause in the Do&#x000f1;ana ecosystem. Such a negative impact on ecosystem may occur by altering the dynamic of its predators and other ecological roles of small mammals in the ecosystem (e.g., seed dispersal). For instance, a recent marked decline of wild rabbits in Spain has been shown to reflect higher number of road-killed (due to increased displacements), and lower breeding success of, Iberian lynx <italic>Lynx pardinus</italic> (<xref rid="zow109-B10" ref-type="bibr">Delibes-Mateos et al. 2014</xref>).</p><sec><title>Apodemus Sylvaticus</title><p>The positive association between rainfall and <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> abundance was consistent in all 3 areas, regardless of any difference in study period and habitat. In the San Agustin area, the lowest AICc model for abundance was for the negative association with increased mean temperature; nonetheless, the positive relationship with rainfall was also supported. The positive effect of rainfall is in line with findings from other studies on small mammals in arid and semi-arid regions (<xref rid="zow109-B28" ref-type="bibr">Lima et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="zow109-B12" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az et al. 2010</xref>). A study conducted in the Mediterranean coast of the Iberian Peninsula suggested the positive effect of rainfall on both abundance and reproduction of <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> (<xref rid="zow109-B12" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000ed;az et al. 2010</xref>) which may be explained by higher availability of food resources (vegetative growth, enhanced seed production, and accessibility).</p></sec><sec><title>Mus spretus</title><p>The number of extremely hot days correlated negatively with the abundance of <italic>M. spretus</italic> at DNP. Although caution is needed as data from only 5 years were modeled, this finding is surprising as <italic>M. spretus</italic> is adapted to high temperatures (<xref rid="zow109-B45" ref-type="bibr">Palomo et al. 2009</xref>). However, extreme high temperatures are known to be a cause of heat stress in birds (<xref rid="zow109-B19" ref-type="bibr">Jenouvrier 2013</xref>) and even mortality for some species of mammals (<xref rid="zow109-B17" ref-type="bibr">Greenville et al. 2012</xref>). Although the ecological impacts of extreme events are still poorly understood (<xref rid="zow109-B53" ref-type="bibr">Thibault and Brown 2008</xref>), it has been proposed that they might turn local systems into ecological traps by increasing the extent of trophic mismatches (<xref rid="zow109-B20" ref-type="bibr">Jiguet et al. 2011</xref>). In the future, extreme events are going to increase in multitude and magnitude (<xref rid="zow109-B13" ref-type="bibr">Easterling et al. 2000</xref>); this pattern was already evident at DNP for the study period (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). We encourage that further studies on small mammal diversity at Do&#x000f1;ana explicitly address the potential effects of extreme climatic events.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Counts: abundance and detectability</title><p>Although often not appreciated in past ecological research, counts can provide little information on ecological processes if the level of detectability is not maintained over time and space. HMs overcome this problem by accounting for changes in the observational process (<xref rid="zow109-B23" ref-type="bibr">Kery and Royle 2016</xref>). HMs are gaining popularity among ecologists as a robust approach for studying changes in abundance and distribution also with historic records (see e.g., <xref rid="zow109-B18" ref-type="bibr">Iknayan et al. 2014</xref>). Using HMs, we found that probability of capture varied according to the number of traps or daily mean temperature. Although such effects were in the expected directions (negative effect of temperature and positive of number of traps) for most cases, we cannot explain why the capture probability for <italic>M. spretus</italic> at Las Monjas decreased with an increasing number of traps. We cannot discard it was a stochastic result of limited data set rather than reflecting a causal effect.</p></sec><sec><title>Final remarks</title><p>Albeit other processes such as top-down control and species competition were likely to be involved, our findings support a relationship between changes in the local climate conditions and small mammal community whose diversity declined remarkably at DNP. Such a reduction in diversity and abundance of small mammals is alarming especially for species like, among others, <italic>T. alba</italic> and <italic>Genetta genetta</italic> whose diet, breeding success, and other ecological parameters depend on small mammals abundance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Data</label><media xlink:href="santoroetal-curzool2015-supp_zow109.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study has been supported within multiple projects along the period spanning from 1978 to 2015. We thank many field workers, too numerous to be mentioned individually, whose help has been crucial to obtain the data used in this study. We are also grateful for their insightful criticisms and commentaries to 2 anonymous reviewers, to Simen Pedersen and the Hedmark University of Applied Sciences Conservation Biology class of 2015. Leah Kearns from the Landcare Research provided valuable editorial advice.</p></ack><sec><title>Supplementary material</title><p>
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary material</xref> can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cz.oxfordjournals.org/">http://www.cz.oxfordjournals.org/</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="zow109-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altwegg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Rainfall in arid zones: possible effects of climate change on the population ecology of blue cranes</article-title>. <source>Funct Ecol</source><volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1014</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1021</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dokken</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mastrandrea</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2014</year>
<source>IPCC (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change). 2014. Climate Change 2014: Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability. Part B: Regional Aspects. Contribution of Working Group II to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>. 
<publisher-loc>Cambridge and New York</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauduin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cassaing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Issam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Interaction between the short-tailed mouse <italic>Mus spretus</italic> and the wood mouse <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic>: diet overlap revealed by stable isotopes</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source><volume>91</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnham</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>
<source>Model Selection and Multimodel Inference: A Practical Information-Theoretic Approach</source>. 
<publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Climate change and amphibian declines: is there a link?</article-title><source>Divers. Distrib</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casanovas-Vilar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Paredes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van den Hoek Ostende</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moy&#x000e0;-Sol&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>
<article-title>The European Far West: miocene mammal isolation, diversity and turnover in the Iberian Peninsula</article-title>. <source>J Biogeogr</source><volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1079</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1093</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohlem&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Rapid range shifts of species of climate warming</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>333</volume>:<fpage>1024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21852500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1974</year>
<source>The Ecology of Small Mammals</source>. 
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Edward Arnold</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delibes-Mateos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delibes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreras</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villafuerte</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Key role of European rabbits in the conservation of the western Mediterranean Basin hotspot</article-title>. <source>Conserv Biol</source><volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18680504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delibes-Mateos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Escudero</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gort&#x000e1;zar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Ecosystem effects of variant rabbit hemorrhagic disease virus, Iberian peninsula</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25417710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#x000e9;nes</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beissinger</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Estimating abundance of unmarked animal populations: accounting for imperfect detection and other sources of zero inflation</article-title>. <source>Methods Ecol Evol</source><volume>6</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arrizabalaga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Relative roles of density and rainfall on the short-term regulation of Mediterraneanwood mouse <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> populations</article-title>. <source>Acta Theriol</source><volume>55</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Easterling</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groisman</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karl</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2000</year>
<article-title>Observed variability and trends in extreme climate events: a brief review</article-title>. <source>Bull Am Meteorol Soc</source><volume>81</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiske</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Unmarked: an R package for fitting hierarchical models of wildlife occurrence and abundance</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw</source><volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tewksbury</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>
<article-title>A framework for community interactions under climate change</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>25</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20392517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lionello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Climate change projections for the Mediterranean region</article-title>. <source>Glob Planet Change</source><volume>63</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenville</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dickman</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Extreme climatic events drive mammal irruptions: regression analysis of 100-year trends in desert rainfall and temperature</article-title>. <source>Ecol Evol</source><volume>2</volume>:<fpage>2645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2658</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23170202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iknayan</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tingley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Furnas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beissinger</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Detecting diversity: emerging methods to estimate species diversity</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>29</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24315534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenouvrier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Impacts of climate change on avian populations</article-title>. <source>Glob Chang Biol</source><volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2036</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2057</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23505016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiguet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brotons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devictor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Community responses to extreme climatic conditions</article-title>. <source>Curr Zool</source><volume>57</volume>:<fpage>406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonzen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ergon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vik</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2006</year>
<article-title>Rapid advance of spring arrival dates in long-distance migratory birds</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>312</volume>:<fpage>1959</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1961</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16809542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kausrud</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mysterud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vik</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>&#x000d8;stbye</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Linking climate change to lemming cycles</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>456</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kery</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Royle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>
<source>Applied Hierarchical Modeling in Ecology: Analysis of distribution, Abundance and Species Richness in R and BUGS: Volume 1: Prelude and Static Models</source>. 
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khidas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khammes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khelloufi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aulagnier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Abundance of the wood mouse <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> and the Algerian mouse <italic>Mus spretus</italic> (Rodentia, Muridae) in different habitats of Northern Algeria</article-title>. <source>Mamm Biol</source><volume>67</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kufner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1986</year>. Tama&#x000f1;o, actividad densidad relativa y preferencia de habitat de los peque&#x000f1;os y medianos mam&#x000ed;feros de Do&#x000f1;ana, como factores condicionantes de su tasa. Tesis Doctoral. Universidad Autonoma de Madrid.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kufner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1989</year>
<article-title>Abundancia y amplitud de los desplazamientos de Apodemus sylvaticus en cuatro biotopos de Do&#x000f1;ana que difieren en cobertura vegetal</article-title>. <source>Do&#x000f1;ana Acta Vertebr</source><volume>16</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lebreton</surname><given-names>J-D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burnham</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clobert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1992</year>
<article-title>Modelling survival and testing biological hypotheses using marked animals: a unified approach with case studies</article-title>. <source>Ecol Monogr</source><volume>62</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stenseth</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaksic</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Food web structure and climate effects on the dynamics of small mammals and owls in semi-arid Chile</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>5</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>284</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Fuster</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>
<italic>Crocidura russula</italic> (Hermann, 1780). In: Mu&#x000f1;oz LJP, Gisbert J, Guti&#x000e9;rrez JCB, editors. <italic>Atlas y Libro Rojo de los Mam&#x000ed;feros Terrestres de Espa&#x000f1;a.</italic> Direcci&#x000f3;n General para la Biodiversidad-SECEM-SECEMU, Madrid, 128&#x02013;130.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kendall</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>How should detection probability be incorporated into estimates of relative abundance?</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>83</volume>:<fpage>2387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2393</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1999</year>
<chapter-title><italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</chapter-title> In: Mitchell-<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Amori</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdanowicz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kry&#x00161;tufek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reijnders</surname><given-names>PJH</given-names></name></person-group><etal/>, editors. <source>The Atlas of European Mammals</source>. 
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Poyser</publisher-name>, <fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moller</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Extreme climatic events in relation to global change and their impact on life histories</article-title>. <source>Curr Zool</source><volume>57</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1984a</year>
<italic>Biometr&#x000ed;a, biolog&#x000ed;a y din&#x000e1;mica poblacional del lir&#x000f3;n careto, Eliomys quercinus (L.), en Do&#x000f1;ana</italic>. Estaci&#x000f3;n Biol&#x000f3;gica de Do&#x000f1;ana.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1984b</year> Datos sobre la reproducci&#x000f3;n del rat&#x000f3;n de campo <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> en la Reserva Biol&#x000f3;gica da Do&#x000f1;ana. [In: <italic>Actas II Reuni&#x000f3;n Iberoam. Cons. Zool. Vert.</italic>, J. Castroviejo, ed.].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Lir&#x000f3;n careto. <italic>Eliomys quercinus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1766)</article-title>. <source>Galemy</source><volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kufner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1988</year>
<article-title>Seasonals patterns in the wood mouse population in the Mediterranean Scrubland</article-title>. <source>Acta Theriol (Warsz)</source><volume>33</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rouco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Responses of a small-mammal community to habitat management through controlled burning in a protected Mediterranean area</article-title>. <source>Acta Oecologica</source><volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conroy</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Impact of a century of climate change on small-mammal communities in Yosemite National Park, USA</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>322</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>264</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18845755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lundrigan</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>SMG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haraminac</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seto</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Climate-induced changes in the small mammal communities of the Northern Great Lakes Region</article-title>. <source>Glob Chang Biol</source><volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1454</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mysterud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ottersen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Ecological effects of climate fluctuations</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume>297</volume>:<fpage>1292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1973</year>
<article-title>Correction for sprung traps in catch/effort calculations of trapping results</article-title>. <source>J Mammal</source><volume>54</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreras</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fedriani</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delibes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1996</year>
<article-title>Spatial relationships between Iberian lynx and other carnivores in an area of south-western Spain</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ecol</source><volume>33</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaona</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreras</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Delibes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1995</year>
<article-title>Positive effects on game species of top predators by controlling smaller predator populations: an example with lynx, mongooses, and rabbits</article-title>. <source>Conserv Biol</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomo</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gisbert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>
<source>Atlas y Libro Rojo de los Mam&#x000ed;feros Terrestres de Espa&#x000f1;a</source>. 
<publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc>: 
<publisher-name>Direcci&#x000f3;n General para la Biodiversidad-SECEM-SECEMU</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palomo</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Justo</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>
<article-title><italic>Mus spretus</italic> (Rodentia: Muridae)</article-title>. <source>Mamm Species</source><volume>840</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>
<article-title>Ecological and evolutionary responses to recent climate change</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source><volume>37</volume>:<fpage>637</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>669</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>R Core Team</collab>, <year>2013</year>
<italic>A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</italic>. Vienna: R Foundation for Statistical Computing.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Royle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2004</year>
<article-title>N-Mixture models for estimating population size from spatially replicated counts</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source><volume>60</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15032780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ses&#x000e9; Benito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1994</year>
<article-title>Paleoclimatical interpretation of the quaternary small mammals of Spain</article-title>. <source>Geobios</source><volume>27</volume>:<fpage>753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>767</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suso</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Llamas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1993</year>
<article-title>Influence of groundwater development on the Do&#x000f1;ana National Park ecosystems (Spain)</article-title>. <source>J Hydrol</source><volume>141</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szpunar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aloise</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzotti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cristaldi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Effects of global climate change on terrestrial small mammal communities in Italy</article-title>. <source>Fresenius Environ Bull</source><volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1533</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teplitsky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alho</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yarrall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meril&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Bergmann&#x02019;s rule and climate change revisited: disentangling environmental and genetic responses in a wild bird population</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>105</volume>:<fpage>13492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13496</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thibault</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Impact of an extreme climatic event on community assembly</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>105</volume>:<fpage>3410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3415</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18303115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tylianakis</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Didham</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bascompte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Global change and species interactions in terrestrial ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1363</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19062363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="zow109-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>G-RR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Convey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal/>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Ecological responses to recent climate change</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>416</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>395</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11919621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>