<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change has already allowed many alien species to expand their non‐native ranges (e.g., IPCC, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). For ornamental plants, the main reason for this trend is probably their widespread commercial use beyond climatic conditions they would tolerate in the wild, which gives them a head start when the climate warms (Van der Veken, Hermy, Vellend, Knapen, &amp; Verheyen, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Predictions of increasing suitable range sizes of ornamental plants in a warming Europe likely have similar underlying reasons. Many ornamentals currently cultivated on the continent come from warm(er) regions and hence tend to expand towards north‐eastern and north‐western Europe, in particular, if climatic constraints in these regions are relaxed (cf. Bellard et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Dullinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The 34 non‐native ornamental plants used in this study are also mostly native to warm regions and hence their potentially suitable ranges in Europe tend to increase, on average, despite pronounced idiosyncratic differences. Although the pool of their European congeners contains many warm‐adapted species too (e.g., most species from the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Euphorbia</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Tamarix</italic>), it also includes a considerable number of montane or even alpine species (e.g., from the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Linaria</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Rhododendron</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Senecio</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Viola</italic>). For montane species, climatically suitable ranges are particularly likely to shrink under climate warming (Engler et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Thuiller et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The share of montane species is thus probably a factor restricting range increases of congeners in the more severe climate scenarios.
</p>
