<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Kowloon Peninsula of Hong Kong is an urban environment with mixed land use and high-density settings. In a small area of only 26 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> bounded by mountains in the north and the harbor surrounding the peninsula, there were approximately 1 million people based on the 2011 Census report [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Due to a history of development, despite the small area and large local population, the Kowloon Peninsula has a high percentage of commercial areas, including town centers and commercial landmarks of Hong Kong, such as Tsim Sha Tsui and Mong Kok. Based on datasets delineated from the 1990 coastal boundary, 28.1% of our study area was residential or commercial lands, 13.4% was government, institutional and community facilities, while only 8.9% was public open space including public parks recognized by the 2009 land utilization map from the Planning Department of Hong Kong. Furthermore, due to continuing development and re-development across the Kowloon Peninsula, a notable number of high-rise buildings were observed across the whole region. Based on a set of 2010 building GIS data, the average building height of the study area (excluding lands from reclamation after 1990) was 26.8 m, with a standard deviation of height of 14.0 m, while the highest one in 2010 reached 87.8 m. This urban morphology has formed a complex environment that can influence the microclimate, for example, with urban canyons that affect both ventilation and air temperature [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Significantly high temperatures and relatively low wind speeds were therefore widely observed across the high-density environment in summer. However, despite such factors being associated with thermal distress in hot summer days [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], previous studies have documented that cold temperatures can contribute to health risks in local people [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], due to the sudden decrease in temperature. In addition, cold spells (e.g., 2008 Chinese winter storms; the January 2016 East Asia cold wave) are expected to increase through climate change in Hong Kong. Based on records retrieved from the weather station located at the Hong Kong Observatory (which is also within urbanized built-up areas of Hong Kong and within our study area), the average temperature of December 2010 was 2.7 °C higher than the average temperature of December 1910, and 1.2 °C higher than temperature of December 1960. Such increasing temperatures can result in a significant drop in temperature during an extreme cold event that can contribute to higher mortality or morbidity risk. Therefore, it is necessary to include winter perceived temperature in modelling to develop better protocols of sustainable urban development.
</p>
