<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One challenge for future wheat breeding is to modify the reproductive stage timing to suit local climatic conditions while maintaining or even increasing yield potential (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Langer et al., 2014</xref>). In most instances, wheat breeders have been guided by a set of highly productive wheat check lines or genotypes that in principle have optimal DH and PH. However, optimal synchronization has not always been achieved in rain fed winter wheat. In this study, a major objective was to define optimal DH and PH for winter wheat grown under low rainfall cold temperature (ME12, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Braun et al., 2010</xref>) and fit the most sensitive stages of crop development to the most favorable time and weather conditions of the wheat cycle. A method of calculation was used to categorize genotypes into different DH and PH groups, and random genotypes were selected from each category to determine how these influenced GY. Optima DH and PH were calculated across all locations and years together and GY was maximized at 194.9 DH and at 76.0 cm PH. However, optima DH and PH varied with location. Specifically, Diyarbakir is warmer and wetter (higher temperatures and total amount of rainfall) than Konya and Maragheh and earlier genotypes are better adapted to Diyarbakir. Konya and Maragheh are cooler and winter wheat (later genotypes) is better adapted to these regions. These specificities and requirements in each location studied herein showed that to improve GY, selection must target various optima DH and PH. This was shown by a 18.6% increase in GY when selection targeted optima DH and PH obtained from Diyarbakir, Konya, and Maragheh separately compared to targeting one overall (across all locations and years) optima DH and PH. A wheat breeding line with optima DH and PH for each location was selected and these can be used as checks in the field in demonstration plots for calibration during selection procedures (
 <bold class="bold">Supplementary Table 
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3" class="xref">S2</xref>
 </bold>). Moreover, in international breeding programs targeting many different regions, multiple optimal DH and PH ranges must be identified according to the target regions to avoid the risks of limiting the amount of progress in those regions.
</p>
