<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55" class="p">Phase change materials (PCMs) absorb or release “latent heat” when they change phases (e.g. from solid to liquid). The latent heat of the PCMs can be used to create cooling by absorbing heat while the PCMs are melting from solid to liquid. PCMs have been investigated for applications as building materials to store solar energy, for cooling and heating in indoor environments and for energy efficiency (Sharma et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2009</xref>; Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">2012</xref>). Similarly, PCMs make thermal-regulated clothing that alleviates heat strain and improves thermal comfort (Gao 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2014</xref>). A number of studies on personal cooling using PCMs showed its effectiveness in alleviating heat strain in occupational settings (Bennett et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">1995</xref>; Choi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2008</xref>; Chou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2008</xref>; Reinertsen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">2008</xref>; Gao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2011a</xref>), and during and after sports and exercises (Webster et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" class="xref">2005</xref>; House et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2013</xref>; Zhao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">2015a</xref>). However, few studies have tried to apply PCMs to improve thermal comfort from a heat wave perspective (Gao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2012</xref>). Further applications of PCMs to microclimate cooling around the body for the general population and occupational groups are needed. In order to increase cooling effectiveness, factors (e.g. melting temperature, the amount of material, covering area) that affect the cooling efficiency and duration of the PCMs should be taken into consideration (Gao 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
