<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A large number of previous studies across alpine or tundra ecosystems indicated that climate change resulted in an approximately 30% species disappearance (Klein et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34799-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Post &amp; Pedersen, 
 <xref rid="ece34799-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). In our study, however, we found that the seedling species richness and density in the alpine meadow were significantly increased by warming. The results were consistent with a meta‐analysis of 13 study areas in alpine or tundra ecosystems, which showed that warming had positive effects on plant reproduction and growth (Arft et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34799-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). One possible reason is that climate change increases the soil and air temperature, which is a key environmental factor that may promote plant growth, development, and senescence (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34799-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In addition, the germination rates of the seeds and organs and soil mineralization increase with increasing temperatures in alpine areas. Seedlings can greatly contribute to the species diversity of grassland communities (Rees, Condit, Crawley, Pacala, &amp; Tilman, 
 <xref rid="ece34799-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). Our study revealed that seedling density did not determine species richness in the alpine meadow dominated by asexual reproduction, and seedling sexual recruitment determines the floristic diversity in alpine meadows. In regard to this result, Parolo and Rossi (
 <xref rid="ece34799-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) thought that sexual spread and reproduction are mostly important for plant colonization at new higher elevation sites; alpine species tend to colonize upwards gradually responding to global climate change mainly through sexual reproduction, which could have a significant influence on the vegetation community structure and species diversity in frigid alpine regions.
</p>
