<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Factors affecting overlap</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Scotia Sea, sea-ice dynamics broadly define the suitability of fishing grounds. Krill-fishing locations change within and between years, driven by changing sea ice conditions that can alter access to preferred fishing grounds [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref037">37</a>]. Historically, as winter advanced and sea ice covered southern areas, the fishery moved north and east from the Antarctic Peninsula region toward South Georgia. In recent years, reductions in sea ice extent in the Bransfield Strait during autumn and winter have allowed fishing vessels to remain in southern areas for longer periods of time [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref037">37</a>], resulting in the concentration of effort and a large increase in catches taken from Subarea 48.1 relative to earlier decades [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref038">38</a>]. Despite the strong dependence on sea ice for access to some fishing areas, however, it is notable that current management may be relatively more restrictive; catches near the 155,000 ton catch limit in Subarea 48.1 have been reached in 4 of the last 6 years [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref008">8</a>], prompting closure of the fishery despite conditions that remained favorable to continued fishing operations. As climate change is expected to further reduce the duration of the sea-ice season in the Antarctic Peninsula region [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref054">54</a>], longer fishing seasons may be expected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extent of spatial overlap we observed was also limited by available tracking data. Our data derive mostly from summer deployments on breeding animals with relatively restricted foraging ranges at two monitoring sites in the South Shetland Islands. Thus, our estimates of overlap with the fishery, while representative of the tracked population, under-represent true overlap given numerous other breeding locations of krill dependent penguins throughout the Scotia Arc [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref040">40</a>], untracked demographic groups (e.g., male Antarctic fur seals and juvenile penguins), and the proximity of fishing activity to coastal areas. It is important to note that increasing sample sizes from our study sites may not greatly increase estimates of overlap. Individuals from breeding colonies often exhibit preference for particular, local foraging areas [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref055">55</a>] potentially as a means to minimize inter- and intra-specific competition with neighboring populations of central place foragers. While adding more individuals from our tagging sites may increase the frequency of overlap in some grid cells, it is less certain that new areas of overlap would be identified. However, tracking individuals from neighboring colonies throughout the Antarctic Peninsula region or different demographic groups would almost certainly identify more areas of overlap. For example, predator-specific overlap with the fishery differs by species (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0170132.s004" href="#pone.0170132.s004">S1 Appendix</a>), owing to different foraging habitat preferences throughout the year (e.g., 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0170132.g002" href="#pone.0170132.g002">Fig 2</a>). However, combining those species-specific overlap maps builds the mosaic of overlap that increases the frequency of overlap in certain places and expands the total area of overlap in general. Additionally, male fur seals are known to occur in the vicinity of the South Shetland Islands throughout the winter [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref056">56</a>] and tracking data from geolocators suggests Adélie penguins may forage extensively in areas around the South Orkney Islands during winter [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref027">27</a>]. Thus, the spatial extent of overlap observed from our two study colonies, particularly at the smallest spatiotemporal scale, was unexpected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the broad scale, the risks to predators in areas of overlap may also be sensitive to movement of krill, whereby variability in the supply of krill from upstream areas dictates the risk of fishing in downstream areas [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref057">57</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref058">58</a>]. At finer spatial scales however, heterogeneity in circulation that can arise from interactions between complex bathymetry and time-varying flows may interact with krill behavior (e.g., diel vertical migration), altering the residence time of krill within specific areas relative to the background flux of krill [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref059">59</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref060">60</a>]. In such areas, a process of continuous replenishment may misrepresent true dynamics. For example, preliminary analysis of small-scale surface currents from drifter data and circulation modeling (Reiss, unpublished manuscript) suggest that areas with concurrent predator-fishery overlap in the southern Bransfield Strait are characterized by relatively low flows. While large-scale flux is critical for transport of krill from spawning areas in the western Antarctic Peninsula to the eastern Scotia Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref057">57</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref058">58</a>], the small scale rates of import and export, and hence any putative benefits of replenishment, in areas of overlap identified here remain unresolved.
 </p>
</sec>
