<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigating direct and indirect interactions between fisheries and marine predators is a motivating factor for ecosystem-based fisheries management (EBFM) worldwide [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref001">1</a>]. This is particularly true for the management of fisheries that target low- and mid-trophic level organisms that are major energy pathways from primary production to upper trophic levels [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref002">2</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref004">4</a>]. In such cases, removal or displacement of potential prey items by a fishery may impact predators by altering, 
  <span class="italic">inter alia</span>, their foraging behaviors, reproductive success, and survival. However, assigning causation of predator responses to changes in prey availability, including indices such as biomass, recruitment, total catch by a fishery, and harvest rates, remains difficult in many instances [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref005">5</a>], but see [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref006">6</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref007">7</a>]. Such uncertainty limits the implementation of EBFM.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recognition of potential competition between predators and fisheries and the desire to minimize the risks that fishing will irreversibly change marine ecosystems, however, lay at the heart of EBFM as implemented by the Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources (CCAMLR). In the Atlantic sector of the Southern Ocean, a mid-water trawl fishery for Antarctic krill (
  <span class="italic">Euphausia superba</span>) currently catches about 300,000 metric tons of krill in coastal waters of the northern Antarctic Peninsula and island archipelagos of the Scotia Arc [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref008">8</a>]. Throughout this region, breeding populations of Adélie (
  <span class="italic">Pygoscelis adeliae</span>), gentoo (
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">papua</span>), and chinstrap (
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">antarctica</span>) penguins and Antarctic fur seals (
  <span class="italic">Arctocephalus gazella</span>) forage on krill [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref009">9</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref011">11</a>]. These four species, hereafter “predators”, are studied annually as part of the CCAMLR Ecosystem Monitoring Program (CEMP). The CEMP, implemented in 1985, is a circumpolar research effort designed to detect changes in predator populations and distinguish between changes attributable to fisheries and environmental variation [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref012">12</a>]. In particular, the CEMP includes measurements intended to provide information across a range of spatiotemporal scales, from short-term and local-scale impacts (i.e., assessments of foraging effort, diet, chick growth, and reproductive success during the breeding season) to longer-term and larger-scale impacts that integrate over the non-breeding period in habitats remote from local breeding areas (e.g., trends in population size and survival rates) [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref012">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The predators were chosen because they are central-place foragers (they must forage close to breeding colonies to provision their offspring on regular intervals) whose diets typically contain high proportions of Antarctic krill [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref009">9</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref011">11</a>]. The restricted foraging space and dietary preference of these predators during the breeding season suggest that fishing activity near breeding colonies may have measurable impacts on the predators. For example, endangered African penguins exhibited a reduction in foraging effort [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref006">6</a>] and an increase in chick survival [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref007">7</a>] after a no-take marine protected area was established around their breeding colonies, demonstrating that predator performance can be sensitive to the spatial distribution of fishing. Similarly, the predators studied within the CEMP are considered useful indicators for developing fisheries management advice.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the long tenure of the CEMP, however, parameterization of the functional responses of krill-dependent predators to variations in krill biomass and krill catches remains difficult [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref013">13</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref015">15</a>]. This difficulty likely arises for myriad reasons, including: 1) massive inter-annual variations in krill standing stock due to recruitment [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref016">16</a>], advection [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref017">17</a>], and changes in krill assessment methodology [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref018">18</a>]; 2) strong climate signals in predator reproductive performance and demography [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref019">19</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref020">20</a>]; 3) oceanographic and bathymetric conditions that appear to aggregate krill locally [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref021">21</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref023">23</a>]; and 4) temporary catch quotas intended to minimize local depletion of prey [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref024">24</a>]. Additionally, the predators are highly mobile and often disperse widely throughout the Southern Ocean during the austral winter [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref025">25</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref027">27</a>]. Such dependence on distant foraging habitats may dilute an assessment of local fishing impacts. Nonetheless, krill-dependent predators and the fishery ultimately have a functional overlap; both are dependent on krill. If predators and the fishery use the same population of krill, it follows that removal of krill by one group may limit availability to the other. In the absence of clear functional responses, other metrics of predator-fishery interactions may be useful for informing management decisions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In systems with resource competition, actors typically minimize competition by partitioning their use of available resources in space and time [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref028">28</a>]. Therefore, quantitative descriptions of spatiotemporal overlap between predators and the fishery provide an index of the risk of potential competition for a shared resource. Locations with high overlap might be considered locations where the risks of negative impacts by the fishery are highest. In the Scotia Sea, the extent of concurrent overlap between predator foraging areas and fishing locations is unknown, but potentially widespread throughout coastal regions [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref029">29</a>], especially near breeding areas. Bycatches of penguins and seals in krill fishing nets are rare, but have been recorded [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref030">30</a>], indicating that overlap can occur at the finest possible scale. We posit, however, that indices of overlap integrated over tens to hundreds of kilometers, and from daily to annual time steps, are relevant to decisions regarding the spatial and temporal distributions of catch.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The krill fishery in United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization Statistical Area 48 is currently managed based on a biomass estimate from an acoustic survey of the Scotia Sea that was conducted in the year 2000 [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref031">31</a>]. From this survey, a precautionary catch limit of 5.61 million tons was agreed in 2010 [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref032">32</a>]. However, uncertainty regarding the risks to krill-dependent predators that could arise from a spatial concentration of catches has long been the chief concern of fisheries management for Antarctic krill. In 1991, the CCAMLR agreed to an arbitrary interim catch limit (known as the trigger level) of 620,000 tons [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref033">33</a>]. This trigger level supersedes the precautionary catch limit until such time that a small-scale spatial allocation of catches above the trigger level can be agreed. Concerned that even catches of 620,000 tons, if concentrated sufficiently, could adversely impact predators, the CCAMLR further agreed to subdivide the trigger level among FAO Statistical Subareas 48.1 through 48.4 [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref024">24</a>]. As such, the current catch limit in the Antarctic Peninsula region (Subarea 48.1) is set at an arbitrary 155,000 tons, representing roughly 2.75% of the precautionary catch limit. Thus, current catches are generally regarded as precautionary despite an obsolescing biomass estimate that was distributed primarily in open ocean areas outside the main fishing grounds [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref034">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Allowing an expansion of the catch up to the precautionary catch limit remains a long-term goal within CCAMLR [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref035">35</a>]. Such an expansion will require advice on appropriate spatial allocations of the catch limit and the provision of such advice is an ongoing research focus of the CCAMLR and its working groups [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref034">34</a>]. Given the relatively concentrated distribution of krill in the Scotia Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref036">36</a>] and a fishery that currently operates exclusively in the Scotia Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0170132.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170132.ref037">37</a>], we assume that large increases of krill catch limits imply that existing fishing areas will experience increased fishing pressure. Thus, to identify areas where increased catches may present risk to krill-dependent predators, we assess here the contemporaneous activities of predators and fishing vessels to identify the mosaic of current spatial overlap. We suggest that identifying the areas of concurrent overlap provide information necessary to consider where the risks of increased catches may exist. For example, is risk only present near breeding aggregations or is risk more broadly distributed? We first analyze six years of telemetry data to describe broad patterns of predator movements during summer and winter seasons. We then estimate concurrent overlap of predators with recent fishing activity in time, space, and depth to determine the extent and locations of overlap. We note that these estimates of overlap are not intended to infer negative impacts of current catches on predators. Rather, we identify the multi-species mosaic of overlap with the fishery to identify areas where subsequent increases in catch may increase risks to predator performance.
 </p>
</sec>
