<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The United Kingdom has seen a 20% increase in annual rainfall, fewer ground thaws, and warmer winters compared with 50 years ago, and there is a concern that these climate characteristics are beginning to negatively affect the sheep farming industry.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr99-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>
 </sup> Unpredicted parasitic disease outbreaks caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Haemonchus contortus, Nematodirus battus, Teladorsagia circumcincta</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Fasciola hepatica</italic> have been occurring in the United Kingdom.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr84-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr99-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr101-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr102-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>
 </sup> Such outbreaks have indicated that these parasites are able to exploit the changing climate, and models have shown that Wales and Scotland are at particular risk with outbreaks occurring earlier in the year.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr99-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr100-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr103-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic class="italic">Haemonchus contortus</italic> is now able to complete its life cycle and expand farther north, exerting infection pressure in a bimodal fashion.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr102-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr104-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>
 </sup> It has been estimated that climate change could extend the season of 
 <italic class="italic">F hepatica</italic> development by up to 4 months in northwestern regions of the United Kingdom and allow fascioliasis transmission to occur during winter months in southern regions.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr100-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr101-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>
 </sup> Although some areas may experience above optimal temperatures and droughts, it is unfortunately those areas predicted to have changes favorable to parasite development that overlap with high densities of cattle and sheep.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr101-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>
 </sup> Growing degree-day modeling for New Zealand showed risk of infection in some regions may rise over 100% by 2090.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr105-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>
 </sup> Although some regions had little change, it was again regions with sheep and cattle that typically saw risk increases.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr105-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
