<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">We used modelled species distribution data for 14,172 marine species (28 phyla, 1256 families) derived from AquaMaps, an online species distribution modelling tool that produces standardized digital range maps of aquatic species www.aquamaps.org
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. This is the most comprehensive and highest resolution data available on the distribution of marine biodiversity globally. The species distribution maps represent predicted relative probabilities of species occurrence at 0.5 degree latitude-by-longitude cell resolution. AquaMaps is an environmental envelope model that generates predictions about relative environmental suitability/species occurrence by relating species habitat preferences to local environmental conditions within a GIS framework. Species-specific habitat preferences with respect to five environmental parameters (depth, temperature, salinity, primary production and sea ice concentration) are derived from occurrence records available from online databases such as GBIF (www.gbif.org), supplemented by expert knowledge
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. The subsequently calculated relative probability of occurrence of a species for each cell represents the product of probabilities for different environmental parameters based on the preferred and tolerated habitat preferences (environmental envelopes) of each species. It is assumed that the preferred range is where probability is 1, outside the range limits is where probability is 0, and between these two thresholds the relative environmental suitability decreases linearly. We used a probability threshold value of 0.5 or greater to define actual species presence (or the realized niche), as per Klein 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies using AquaMaps data have found species distributions to be relatively robust across a range of thresholds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. A higher probability of occurrence restricts species presence to species-specific areas of high environmental suitability, which corresponds to what may be considered the core range for most species, and thus a threshold of 0.5 represents a relatively conservative threshold of probability.
</p>
