<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, experiments have been overly simplistic, which hampers the predictions of future community dynamics. With few exceptions, levels of experimental treatments have been static rather than naturally dynamic. Experiments will benefit from incorporating the interactive effects of two or more stressors, each with a minimum of three levels. Ideally, choice of levels for each stressor will be informed by information on species’ stressor-specific reaction norms for performance as this will enhance interpretation. While studies are becoming increasingly complex, researchers are yet to incorporate parental effects into studies of the interactive effects of climate stressors on escape performance. The way parents respond to their environment can shape offspring phenotypes, and these may help or hinder escape performance. Trans-generational experiments examining various traits including growth and metabolism have shown how parental exposure to high CO
 <sub>2</sub> (
 <xref rid="ref117" ref-type="bibr">Miller 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Allan 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref192" ref-type="bibr">Welch 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref114" ref-type="bibr">McMahon 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>) and temperature (
 <xref rid="ref157" ref-type="bibr">Salinas and Munch, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Donelson 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref166" ref-type="bibr">Shama 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Bernal 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>) affect offspring performance in isolation, but it is not known how interactions between these stressors may modify parental effects and offspring responses. Clearly, experiments that span multiple generations and incorporate two or more stressors are needed to provide an understanding of the role of parental inputs on fishes under climate change. We need to understand the mechanisms whereby performance is actually being affected by the stressors and their interactions if we are to understand the species capacity to adapt or acclimate to these conditions.
</p>
