<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-tropicalmed-03-00117" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Meteorological Model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modelling future temperatures builds on four representative concentration pathways (RCPs) representing four greenhouse gas concentration (not emission) trajectories, which were adopted by the IPCC for its 5th assessment report (AR5) in 2014 [
  <a rid="B22-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-tropicalmed-03-00117">22</a>]. These RCPs superseded the Special Report on Emissions Scenarios (SRES) projections published in 2000 and were previously used for this purpose. Unlike simpler models which make mixing assumptions regarding processes internal to a presumed cell, while other functions govern the interface between such cells, the GCMs describe four possible climate futures, which are all considered possible depending on how much greenhouse gases (GHGs) are emitted in the years to come (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="tropicalmed-03-00117-f001" href="#tropicalmed-03-00117-f001">Figure 1</a>). The four RCPs, i.e., RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6 and RCP8.5 are named after a possible range of ‘radiative’ forcing relative to pre-industrial values (+2.6, +4.5, +6.0, and +8.5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively) [
  <a rid="B23-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-tropicalmed-03-00117">23</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The IPCC relies also on Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) experiments, a collaborative series of experiments designed to improve our knowledge of the GCMs and their interactions. The most recently completed phase of the project is CMIP5, which includes more metadata describing model simulations than previous phases. The findings are summarized in AR5 (
  <span xlink:href="https://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/index.html" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/index.html</span>). In this study, all models were based on CMIP5 with RCP4.5, which represented a medium GHG emission increase. The temperature prediction data used were derived from GCMs created in a grid format of 0.5 × 0.5 degrees latitude and longitude by five well-known research centers representing the most generally accepted view of the world’s major climate systems (
  <a rid="tropicalmed-03-00117-t001" ref-type="table" href="#tropicalmed-03-00117-t001">Table 1</a>). The datasets we used consisted of a baseline temperature based on the 1961–1990 period and predicted periods 2021–2050 and 2071–2100. These were based on an ensemble of the five predicted climate scenarios between 2006 and 2100 with special reference to the monthly mean temperature (T
  <sub>mean</sub>), the maximum temperature of the warmest months (T
  <sub>max</sub>) and the minimum temperature of the coldest months (T
  <sub>min</sub>), which are reminiscent of the BIO
  <sub>1</sub>, BIO
  <sub>5</sub> and BIO
  <sub>6</sub> variables of the ‘WorldClim’ dataset [
  <a rid="B24-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-tropicalmed-03-00117">24</a>]. Thirty years of averaged monthly temperatures (T
  <sub>mean</sub>, T
  <sub>max</sub> and T
  <sub>min</sub>) spanning the periods 2021–2050 and 2071–2100 were extracted.
 </p>
</sec>
