<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-tropicalmed-03-00117" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Change of Transmission Region and PTI for Schistosomiasis due to Climate Change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average temperatures predicted by the IPCC for the two time periods 2021–2050 and 2071–2100, based on the average of the five GCM results, seemed increasingly likely in the event that efforts to curb the GHG emissions were not stepped up more than they were so far. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="tropicalmed-03-00117-f002" href="#tropicalmed-03-00117-f002">Figure 2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="tropicalmed-03-00117-f003" href="#tropicalmed-03-00117-f003">Figure 3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="tropicalmed-03-00117-f004" href="#tropicalmed-03-00117-f004">Figure 4</a> use IPCC’S predicted temperatures for the two future time periods 2021–2050 and 2071–2100 but rather than comparing with a preindustrial average, we used the 1961–1990 period for which we had available PTI data as a baseline. The blue color shown in the figures designated the ocean, while the background of each plot was based on the PTI baseline. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 
  <span class="italic">S. japonicum</span>, we only applied the low temperature constraints. The global warming displayed heterogeneous patterns with respect to snail survival. For example, the current areas endemic for 
  <span class="italic">S. japonicum</span> in the Sichuan Province were predicted to become unsuitable for snail habitats. On the other hand, the downstream regions between the Sichuan and Hunan/Hubei provinces corresponding to the area above the Three Gorges Dam, which is currently non-endemic, might well present a potential endemic risk in the future. The predicted potential transmission areas of 
  <span class="italic">S. japonicum</span> moving northward was not so obvious in 2021–2050 as it might have become in the 2071–2100 period.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 
  <span class="italic">S. mansoni</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. haematobium</span>, in both timeframes forecast, the potential transmission areas could retreat from the Saharan areas as the desert might encroach on this part of the continent due to diminishing or discontinued rainfall. The future transmission areas of 
  <span class="italic">S. mansoni</span> might shrink more than those of 
  <span class="italic">S. haematobium</span>, while schistosomiasis in Ethiopia and other highlands in Africa could reach higher with warmer temperatures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Suitability varies from 0 over the spectrum to the most likely (red). Grey areas signify areas that might potentially shrink as the temperature would become less suited to the specific snails for the different schistosomal species.</p>
</sec>
