<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The model results indicated that the range shifts of the two main regions of 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> distribution have different features. In northeastern China, the suitable habitat of 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> continues to decrease in are and move north, and marginal habitat is gradually increased, with the boundary shifted northward. In southwestern China, both the suitable and highly suitable habitat of 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> decreases extensively, although the northern boundary does not show obvious northward movement. The reasons for his lack of northward movement are as follows. First, the northern boundary of the 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> distribution in this area is along the edge of the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, and new suitable habitat cannot form due to the dramatic elevation changes, complicated topography and variable climate. Second, in contrast to plant species, fungal species such as 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> will not grow in the absence of suitable vegetation and soil conditions, even if climate and topography are favorable. Thus, soil type and vegetation type variables should be considered limiting factors during the modeling process. As global warming increases, the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> theoretically shifts poleward and to higher elevations. However, vegetation succession and the formation of suitable soil occur slowly in these areas under natural conditions, hindering the ability of fungal species to shift their ranges. Third, the shift of 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> habitat might be constrained by the movement of its hosts. Using the MaxEnt method, we simulated the future distributions of 
 <italic class="italic">T. matsutake</italic> host trees (
 <italic class="italic">Pinus densata, Pinus yunnanensis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus densiflora</italic>) in the 2050s and 2070s. The results showed that the northern boundary of the distribution of host trees also show no obvious trend of northward movement (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary materials</xref>).
</p>
