<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6374466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">38333</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-38333-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The potential role of temperate Japanese regions as refugia for the coral <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> in the face of climate change</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>Aki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5451-1231</contrib-id><name><surname>Yamakita</surname><given-names>Takehisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aizawa</surname><given-names>Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kitano</surname><given-names>Yuko F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iguchi</surname><given-names>Akira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yamano</surname><given-names>Hiroya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>Satoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agostini</surname><given-names>Sylvain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4854-1060</contrib-id><name><surname>Teshima</surname><given-names>Kosuke M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name><address><email>ninayausda@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0657 3887</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410849.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Marine Biology and Environmental Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Miyazaki, Faculty of Agriculture, </institution></institution-wrap>Gakuen- kibanadai-nishi-1-1, Miyazaki, 889-2192 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2191 0132</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410588.0</institution-id><institution>R&#x00026;D Center for Submarine Resource, Japan Agency for Marine-Earth Science and Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>2-15, Natsushima-cho, Yokosuka-city, Kanagawa 237-0061 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2179 2105</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.32197.3e</institution-id><institution>Department of Transdisciplinary Science and Engineering, </institution><institution>School of Environment and Society, Tokyo Institute of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>O-okayama 2-12-1-W8-5, Meguro-ku, Tokyo 152-8552 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0657 3887</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410849.0</institution-id><institution>Organization for Promotion of Tenure Track, </institution><institution>University of Miyazaki, Faculty of Agriculture, </institution></institution-wrap>Gakuen- kibanadai-nishi-1-1, Miyazaki, 889-2192 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0685 5104</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.267625.2</institution-id><institution>Iriomote station, Tropical Biosphere Research Center, </institution><institution>University of Ryukyus, </institution></institution-wrap>870 Uehara, Taketomi, Okinawa 907-1541 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0746 5933</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.140139.e</institution-id><institution>National Institute for Environmental Studies, </institution></institution-wrap>16-2 Onogawa, Tsukuba-shi, Ibaraki 305-8506 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4672 6261</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.471922.b</institution-id><institution>Department of Bioresources Engineering, </institution><institution>National Institute of Technology, Okinawa College, </institution></institution-wrap>905 Henoko, Nago-City, Okinawa 905-2192 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2230 7538</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.208504.b</institution-id><institution>Institute of Geology and Geoinformation, </institution><institution>National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST), </institution></institution-wrap>1-1-1 Higashi, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8567 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1764 1824</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410851.9</institution-id><institution>Research Center for Aquatic Genomics, National Research Institute of Fisheries Science, </institution></institution-wrap>2-12-4 Fukuura, Kanazawa-ku, Yokohama, Kanagawa 236-8648 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2369 4728</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.20515.33</institution-id><institution>Shimoda Marine Research Center, </institution><institution>University of Tsukuba, </institution></institution-wrap>Shimoda 5-10-1, Shizuoka, 415-0025 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff11"><label>11</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2242 4849</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.177174.3</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>Kyushu University 744 Motooka, </institution></institution-wrap>Nishi-ku, Fukuoka, 819-0395 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1892</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">As corals in tropical regions are threatened by increasing water temperatures, poleward range expansion of reef-building corals has been observed, and temperate regions are expected to serve as refugia in the face of climate change. To elucidate the important indicators of the sustainability of coral populations, we examined the genetic diversity and connectivity of the common reef-building coral <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> along the Kuroshio Current, including recently expanded (&#x0003c;50 years) populations. Among the three cryptic lineages found, only one was distributed in temperate regions, which could indicate the presence of Kuroshio-associated larval dispersal barriers between temperate and subtropical regions, as shown by oceanographic simulations as well as differences in environmental factors. The level of genetic diversity gradually decreased towards the edge of the species distribution. This study provides an example of the reduced genetic diversity in recently expanded marginal populations, thus indicating the possible vulnerability of these populations to environmental changes. This finding underpins the importance of assessing the genetic diversity of newly colonized populations associated with climate change for conservation purposes. In addition, this study highlights the importance of pre-existing temperate regions as coral refugia, which has been rather underappreciated in local coastal management.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Climate Change Adaptation Research Program of National Institute for Environmental Studies,</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>MEXT | Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>17H04996</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>the Global Environment Research Fund of the Ministry of the Environment of Japan and the Environment Research and Technology Development Fund (4RF-1501) and (4-1304) of the Ministry of the Environment, Japan the Program to Disseminate Tenure Tracking System from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT)</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Coral reef ecosystems harbour high biodiversity, supporting almost 30% of marine coastal species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. However, reef-building corals have a relatively narrow range of temperature tolerance and are considered especially vulnerable to climate change. The most well-known impact of warming oceans on corals is the increase in mass coral bleaching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In addition, climate change exacerbates local stresses by reducing water quality, which further threatens coral reefs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In contrast to tropical and subtropical regions where coral abundance is declining due to increasing water temperatures, rapid poleward expansions of the ranges of hermatypic corals have been reported in temperate Japanese regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> and the Mediterranean Sea<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Given that all of the range-expanding coral species are classified as Near Threatened or Vulnerable on the IUCN Red List, temperate regions may serve as refugia for hermatypic coral species in the near future<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> if the coral species can overcome the seasonal fluctuations in temperature and reduced light intensities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Among the multiple definitions of refugia, we use the term as defined by Keppel and Wardell-Johnson<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. In this paper, authors noted that &#x0201c;Refugia are habitats that components of biodiversity retreat to, persist in and can potentially expand from under changing environmental conditions and facilitates the persistence of species under anthropogenic climate change.&#x0201d; Population connectivity and relatively high genetic diversity are crucial for a population to expand and persist under climate change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>; thus, these characteristics are important for the populations in potential refugia.</p><p id="Par3">Winter water temperature has risen by 1.45&#x02009;&#x000b0;C over the last 100 years in the temperate Kuroshio Current region in Japan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.data.jma.go.jp/gmd/kaiyou/data/shindan/a_1/japan_warm/japan_warm.html">http://www.data.jma.go.jp/gmd/kaiyou/data/shindan/a_1/japan_warm/japan_warm.html</ext-link>), causing coral expansion and producing potential coral refugia at the edges of their distribution ranges<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. While such temperate region can be potential coral refugia, temperate peripheral populations may suffer from reduced genetic diversity due to small population sizes and isolation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. However, no studies have assessed the genetic diversity or structures of such coral populations, including the recently colonized temperate populations that expanded within the last 50 years as a result of climate change along the Kuroshio Current. In addition, there is a lack of knowledge of the oceanographic larval dispersal processes that shape the genetic variations and population structures of corals in the high-latitude regions of Japan.</p><p id="Par4">This study aimed to assess the genetic structures of recently expanded populations and examine the potential role of temperate regions as coral refugia in Japan. We thus examined the genetic diversity and meta-population structures of the subtropical to northernmost temperate populations of the reef-building coral <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic>, and the results were further compared with contemporary larval dispersal simulations in an oceanographic model.</p><p id="Par5">Our target species, <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> (Dana, 1846), is widely distributed in the tropical, subtropical, and some part of temperate regions of the Indo-Pacific<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Northward range expansion of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> has been observed in the temperate regions of Japan for the last 50 years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Previous studies that included some temperate populations found cryptic lineages (species) of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> species complex is a hermaphroditic, broadcast-spawning species whose fertilization takes place in the water column. More than 70% of the larvae settle within one week<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> but can survive in the water column for up to 5&#x02013;6 weeks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> is categorized as Near Threatened on the IUCN red list. <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> is one of the key reef-building species on tropical reefs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and can represent as much as 36% of the coral coverage in some high-latitude areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. These ecological features of this species are suitable for comparing the genetic diversity and connectivity of populations among temperate and subtropical regions. We defined the region south of the Watase Line<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> as subtropical and the region north of the Watase Line as temperate (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The region was split along this line because the biogeography of this region is often split between Yakushima and the Amami Islands, and the Kuroshio Current passes through this region.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Sampling sites in this study. The thickest grey curve indicates the Kuroshio Current. The circles represent pre-existing populations, and the stars indicate recently expanded populations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e633"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>The <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> lineage used in this study</title><p id="Par6">Only 10366m5 has possible null alleles, and we thus excluded this locus from the genetic analysis of the population. A previous study indicated that there are cryptic species (lineages) in <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> that are morphologically indistinguishable<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Thus, we identified the cryptic lineages in our dataset using STRUCTURE analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> to determine the lineage associated with the recently expanded populations in temperate regions. After removing 44 possible clones, our STRUCTURE analyses based on 645 multilocus genotypes (MLGs) indicated that the most likely number of clusters was <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, followed by 3 (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">1</xref>). At <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, temperate populations and some of the subtropical individuals were assigned to the same cluster (green lineage in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), and the other lineage was restricted to south of Miyazaki. At <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, the subtropical specific cluster at <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 (red in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) was further split into two different clusters (red and blue in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) results also supported different lineages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Moreover, populations with two or three different genetic lineages belonged to different clades in the neighbour-joining (NJ) phylogenetic trees (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). These results, as well as those of a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, indicated that these populations are possibly different species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Because we are interested in the genetic connectivity and diversity of the lineages that have recently expanded in temperate regions, we focused on one lineage (green lineage in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) found in both temperate and subtropical regions. Individuals assigned to the green lineage with probabilities &#x02265;70% in both the <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 and <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 results were used for the following analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). A relatively low value &#x02265;70% was chosen because that lineage was rather rare in the subtropical region and many individuals found in the subtropical area are partially admixed with other lineages. Populations with &#x02265;9 MLGs were used for subsequent analysis because smaller sample sizes are not suitable for population genetic analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. The final dataset included 240 individuals from 13 populations (shown in bold in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Initially, significant linkage disequilibrium was found in two pairs of loci (11401m4 and Amil2-23; 11401m4 and Amil2-2). However, linkages disappeared in the final dataset, which included only one lineage and no clones.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Bar plot data from STRUCTURE analysis (above <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, below <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) across all collected samples (above). The X-axis indicates individuals from different populations, and the Y-axis indicates the estimated proportions of different clusters shown in different colours. The PCoA plots are based on the populations separated into cryptic lineages revealed by STRUCTURE analysis at <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 and 3 (below). (<bold>Left</bold>) The first two coordinates explain 55.8% (x-axis) and 12.6% ((y-axis) of the data (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2); (<bold>Right</bold>) the first two coordinates explain 46.7% (x-axis) and 13.4% ((y-axis) of the data (<italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e746"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Details of the samples used in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Region</th><th>Sampling site</th><th>Code</th><th>N</th><th>Depth (m)</th><th colspan="2">Coordinates</th><th>MLG</th><th>1-MLG/N (%) Percentage of shared MLGs among samples</th><th>N. of Green lineage</th><th>N. of blue/red lineage (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">recently colonized in temperate area</td><td rowspan="2">Goto Islands</td><td>Oushima</td><td>GAHo</td><td>19</td><td>0.3~6.0</td><td>32&#x000b0;33&#x02032; 55.47&#x02033; N</td><td>128&#x000b0;53&#x02032; 56.57&#x02033; E</td><td>9</td><td>0.526</td><td>
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Kuroshima</td><td>GAHk</td><td>13</td><td>4.1~5.6</td><td>32&#x000b0;35&#x02032; 56.18&#x02033; N</td><td>128&#x000b0;50&#x02032; 04.05&#x02033; E</td><td>10</td><td>0.231</td><td>
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Kumamoto</td><td>Amakusa</td><td>AMK</td><td>25</td><td>N.A.</td><td>32&#x000b0;33&#x02032; 16.16&#x02033; N</td><td>129&#x000b0;59&#x02032; 59.91&#x02033; E</td><td>23</td><td>0.080</td><td>
<bold>23</bold>
</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Izu Islands</td><td>Shikinejima</td><td>ZAH</td><td>18</td><td>0.8~6.6</td><td>34&#x000b0;21&#x02032; 36.44&#x02033; N</td><td>139&#x000b0;12&#x02032; 02.39&#x02033; E</td><td>18</td><td>0.000</td><td>
<bold>17</bold>
</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7">pre-existing temperate area</td><td rowspan="2">Wakayama</td><td>Kushimoto</td><td>WAHk</td><td>34</td><td>2.4~5.5</td><td>33&#x000b0;28&#x02032; 27.36&#x02033; N</td><td>135&#x000b0;44&#x02032; 26.92&#x02033; E</td><td>29</td><td>0.147</td><td>
<bold>29</bold>
</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Shirahama</td><td>WAHs</td><td>18</td><td>0.7~9.4</td><td>33&#x000b0;40&#x02032; 59.81&#x02033; N</td><td>135&#x000b0;20&#x02032; 11.41&#x02033; E</td><td>18</td><td>0.000</td><td>
<bold>18</bold>
</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Kochi</td><td>Tatsukushi</td><td>KOC</td><td>32</td><td>1.0~6.0</td><td>32&#x000b0;45&#x02032; 49.33&#x02033; N</td><td>132&#x000b0;51&#x02032; 38.39&#x02033; E</td><td>31</td><td>0.031</td><td>
<bold>30</bold>
</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Miyazaki</td><td>Tsukijima</td><td>TUK</td><td>46</td><td>N.A.</td><td>31&#x000b0;28&#x02032; 39.18&#x02033; N</td><td>131&#x000b0;23&#x02032; 14.67&#x02033; E</td><td>30</td><td>0.348</td><td>
<bold>23</bold>
</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>Toimisaki</td><td>TOI</td><td>29</td><td>N.A.</td><td>31&#x000b0;21&#x02032; 00.47&#x02033; N</td><td>131&#x000b0;16&#x02032; 59.92&#x02033; E</td><td>28</td><td>0.034</td><td>
<bold>25</bold>
</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Yakushima</td><td>Tsukasaki</td><td>KAHyn</td><td>30</td><td>4.4~6.3</td><td>30&#x000b0;25&#x02032; 55.50&#x02033; N</td><td>130&#x000b0;34&#x02032; 34.46&#x02033; E</td><td>29</td><td>0.033</td><td>
<bold>24</bold>
</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Nanase</td><td>KAHys</td><td>13</td><td>5.6~7.7</td><td>30&#x000b0;14&#x02032; 42.24&#x02033; N</td><td>130&#x000b0;25&#x02032; 31.24&#x02033; E</td><td>9</td><td>0.357</td><td>8</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="11">subtropical area</td><td rowspan="2">Amami Islands</td><td>Saneku</td><td>KAHaw</td><td>22</td><td>1.5~4.8</td><td>28&#x000b0;11&#x02032; 33.24&#x02033; N</td><td>129&#x000b0;11&#x02032; 30.78&#x02033; E</td><td>22</td><td>0.000</td><td>0</td><td>22</td></tr><tr><td>Sakibaru</td><td>KAHae</td><td>16</td><td>N.A.</td><td>28&#x000b0;19&#x02032; 54.83&#x02033; N</td><td>129&#x000b0;33&#x02032; 19.76&#x02033; E</td><td>16</td><td>0.000</td><td>
<bold>14</bold>
</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Okinawa Island</td><td>Sesokojima</td><td>SSK</td><td>35</td><td>N.A.</td><td>26&#x000b0;37&#x02032; 51.43&#x02033; N</td><td>127&#x000b0;51&#x02032; 23.57&#x02033; E</td><td>35</td><td>0.000</td><td>0</td><td>35</td></tr><tr><td>Oura</td><td>OAH</td><td>42</td><td>N.A.</td><td>26&#x000b0;30&#x02032; 21.70&#x02033; N</td><td>128&#x000b0;02&#x02032; 28.84&#x02033; E</td><td>42</td><td>0.000</td><td>
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td>33</td></tr><tr><td>Miyakojima</td><td>Yoshino</td><td>MYK</td><td>47</td><td>N.A.</td><td>24&#x000b0;47&#x02032; 57.72&#x02033; N</td><td>125&#x000b0;20&#x02032; 59.22&#x02033; E</td><td>47</td><td>0.000</td><td>
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td>38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Sekisei Lagoon</td><td>Uro</td><td>SAHaaf</td><td>36</td><td>1.8~4.2</td><td>24&#x000b0;15&#x02032; 28.63&#x02033; N</td><td>124&#x000b0;10&#x02032; 39.49&#x02033; E</td><td>36</td><td>0.000</td><td>0</td><td>36</td></tr><tr><td>Hanari East</td><td>SAHd</td><td>49</td><td>1.0~6.6</td><td>24&#x000b0;13&#x02032; 20.22&#x02033; N</td><td>123&#x000b0;56&#x02032; 16.41&#x02033; E</td><td>48</td><td>0.020</td><td>1</td><td>47</td></tr><tr><td>Yonara Chanel</td><td>SAHfqy</td><td>65</td><td>1.0~3.8</td><td>24&#x000b0;22&#x02032; 00.32&#x02033; N</td><td>123&#x000b0;57&#x02032; 03.14&#x02033; E</td><td>65</td><td>0.000</td><td>0</td><td>65</td></tr><tr><td>Kohamajima East</td><td>SAHk</td><td>44</td><td>0.5~2.8</td><td>24&#x000b0;21&#x02032; 06.98&#x02033; N</td><td>124&#x000b0;00&#x02032; 41.96&#x02033; E</td><td>44</td><td>0.000</td><td>0</td><td>44</td></tr><tr><td>Haimi South</td><td>SAHt</td><td>28</td><td>2.2~4.8</td><td>24&#x000b0;16&#x02032; 06.23&#x02033; N</td><td>123&#x000b0;50&#x02032; 06.66&#x02033; E</td><td>28</td><td>0.000</td><td>1</td><td>27</td></tr><tr><td>Aragusuku East</td><td>SAHae</td><td>28</td><td>2.8~4.7</td><td>24&#x000b0;15&#x02032; 07.03&#x02033; N</td><td>123&#x000b0;58&#x02032; 25.77&#x02033; E</td><td>28</td><td>0.000</td><td>2</td><td>26</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The numbers of samples used in the population genetic analysis are shown in bold. N, total number of samples collected from each site. MLG, number of multilocus genotypes. N. of green lineage, number of green lineage samples; N. of blue/red lineage, number of blue/red lineage samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p>N.A. not available because of the lack of depth data</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Genetic diversity</title><p id="Par7">Possible clones with a probability of identity of <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 were more frequently found in the temperate region than in the subtropical region (9 out of the 11 populations in the temperate region but none in the subtropical region), which indicated that asexual reproduction (such as fragmentation) likely occurred more frequently in the temperate region than in the subtropical region (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). High clonal rates (23.1% for GAHk and 52.6% for GAHo) were found in two Goto Island populations, both of which are recently expanded populations.</p><p id="Par8">After removing possible clones, the north peripheral populations had reduced genetic diversity, which was observed in particular in the recently expanded populations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Genetic diversity metrics (allelic richness and heterozygosity) were more significantly reduced in the recently expanded populations than in the rest of the pre-existing temperate populations (Wilcoxon test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.010 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.038 for allelic richness and expected heterozygosity, respectively) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Similarly, the genetic diversity metrics were significantly higher in subtropical populations than temperate ones (Wilcoxon test, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007 and <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.028 for allelic richness and expected heterozygosity, respectively). Notably, all temperate populations, except for one north Yakushima population (KAHyn), had more than one fixed (monomorphic) locus. All the recently expanded populations had 2 to 4 fixed loci out of 8 loci (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">3</xref>). In total, 24 individuals had private alleles. Eight out of the 32 individuals (25.0%) examined in the subtropical populations had private alleles, and 11 out of the 149 (7.4%) individuals in the pre-existing temperate populations had private alleles. Two out of 59 individuals (3.4%) were found to have private alleles in the recently expanded populations (One from Goto Island, GAHo, and another from Amakusa, AMK). These results suggest that subtropical populations have more private alleles than temperate populations, and recently expanded populations possibly originated from a small number of individuals with low genetic diversity.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Plots of genetic diversity along central-to-peripheral populations. Circles indicate <italic>H</italic><sub><italic>E</italic></sub>, expected heterozygosity, diamonds indicate <italic>H</italic><sub><italic>O</italic></sub>, observed heterozygosity, and triangles indicate allelic richness.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1638"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Isolation by distance (IBD) pattern and genetic connectivity</title><p id="Par9">Significant IBD patterns within the green lineage were detected only when regressed onto oceanographic distance (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">4</xref>). A weak IBD tendency was detected using straight-line distance (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.085) only when the recently expanded populations were excluded, which possibly occurred because the recently expanded populations are not in genetic equilibrium.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>IBD patterns based on oceanographic distances using different sample sets ((<bold>a</bold>) all populations; (<bold>b</bold>) excluding recently colonized populations).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1670"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">The analysis of molecular variance (AMOVA) results suggested overall significant genetic structuring within the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> lineage that was examined in this study (global <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.108, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Significant genetic differentiation between the temperate and subtropical populations was not found, either including (all temperate vs subtropical, <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.042, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.064) or excluding (pre-existing temperate vs subtropical, <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.024, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.163) the recently expanded populations. The AMOVA results revealed non-significant genetic differentiation between the recently expanded populations and the pre-existing temperate populations (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.002, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.424) and between the populations along the main stream of the Kuroshio Current vs the Tsushima Current (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.275) in the temperate region (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This result suggests that populations in temperate regions were generally genetically close to each other. Pairwise tests showed almost no genetic differentiation among the recently expanded populations, whereas there were some significantly differentiated pairs among the pre-existing populations (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The Tsukijima population in Miyazaki (TUK) was one of the most isolated populations in the temperate region, most likely because the artificial structure surrounding this population (N. Yasuda pers. obs.) hindered larval exchange.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Results of AMOVA with different scenarios using only the green lineage in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 are shown in bold.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Scenario</th><th>Source of variation</th><th>df</th><th>%var</th><th colspan="2">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th>
<italic>P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Global test</td><td>Among populations</td><td>12</td><td>10.8</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.108</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Within populations</td><td>467</td><td>89.2</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Temperate vs subtropical</td><td>Among groups</td><td>1</td><td>4.2</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.042</td><td>0.064</td></tr><tr><td>Among populations within groups</td><td>11</td><td>9.4</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>SC</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.098</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Within populations</td><td>467</td><td>86.4</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.136</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Pre-existing temperate vs subtropical</td><td>Among groups</td><td>1</td><td>2.4</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.024</td><td>0.163</td></tr><tr><td>Among populations within groups</td><td>7</td><td>9.9</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>SC</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.102</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Within populations</td><td>353</td><td>87.7</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.123</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Recently vs pre-existing in temperate</td><td>Among groups</td><td>1</td><td>0.07</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.416</td></tr><tr><td>Among populations within groups</td><td>8</td><td>10.5</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>SC</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.105</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Within populations</td><td>406</td><td>89.46</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.105</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Kuroshio vs Tsushima Current in temperate</td><td>Among groups</td><td>1</td><td>0.07</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>CT</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.420</td></tr><tr><td>Among populations within groups</td><td>8</td><td>10.47</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>SC</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.105</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Within populations</td><td>406</td><td>89.5</td><td>
<italic>F</italic>
<sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>
</td><td>0.105</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, <italic>P</italic> values for <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>EST</italic></sub> and <italic>P</italic> values for Fisher&#x02019;s exact test. Significant tests after sequential Bonferroni correction are shown in bold.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="2"/><th colspan="4">Recently colonized in temperate area</th><th colspan="4">Pre-existing in temperate area</th><th colspan="5">Subtropical area</th></tr><tr><th>GAHo</th><th>GAHk</th><th>AMK</th><th>ZAH</th><th>WAHk</th><th>WAHs</th><th>KOC</th><th>TUK</th><th>TOI</th><th>KAHyn</th><th>KAHae</th><th>OAH</th><th>MYK</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="15">
<bold><italic>F</italic></bold>
<sub><bold><italic>ST</italic></bold></sub>
<bold>(above)</bold>
<bold><italic>P</italic></bold>
<bold>value (below)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Recently colonized<break/>in temperate</td><td>GAHo</td><td/><td>0.073</td><td>0.056</td><td>0.050</td><td>0.060</td><td>0.054</td><td>0.048</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>102</bold></td><td>0.031</td><td>0.041</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>084</bold></td><td>0.085</td><td>0.065</td></tr><tr><td>GAHk</td><td>0.010</td><td/><td>0.050</td><td>0.050</td><td>0.054</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>067</bold></td><td>0.026</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>169</bold></td><td>0.042</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>060</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>117</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>107</bold></td><td>0.086</td></tr><tr><td>AMK</td><td>0.016</td><td>0.001</td><td/><td>0.031</td><td>0.027</td><td>0.028</td><td>0.016</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>128</bold></td><td>0.023</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>041</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>094</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>072</bold></td><td>0.049</td></tr><tr><td>ZAH</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.012</td><td/><td>0.032</td><td>0.019</td><td>0.022</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>108</bold></td><td>0.030</td><td>0.028</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>069</bold></td><td>0.067</td><td>0.053</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Pre-existing<break/>in temperate</td><td>WAHk</td><td>0.013</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.041</td><td>0.003</td><td/><td>0.023</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>022</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>118</bold></td><td>0.028</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>038</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>087</bold></td><td>0.068</td><td>0.047</td></tr><tr><td>WAHs</td><td>0.012</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.047</td><td>0.257</td><td>0.097</td><td/><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>028</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>099</bold></td><td>0.027</td><td>0.023</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>065</bold></td><td>0.049</td><td>0.042</td></tr><tr><td>KOC</td><td>0.002</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.039</td><td>0.002</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td/><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>105</bold></td><td>0.014</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>032</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>079</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>068</bold></td><td>0.041</td></tr><tr><td>TUK</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td/><td>0.068</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>062</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>087</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>087</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>100</bold></td></tr><tr><td>TOI</td><td>0.313</td><td>0.008</td><td>0.034</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.092</td><td>0.000</td><td/><td>0.024</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>066</bold></td><td>0.055</td><td>0.043</td></tr><tr><td>KAHyn</td><td>0.006</td><td>0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.030</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.052</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.002</td><td/><td>0.027</td><td>0.030</td><td>0.043</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Subtropical area</td><td>KAHae</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.008</td><td/><td>0.042</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>074</bold></td></tr><tr><td>OAH</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.006</td><td>0.002</td><td>0.079</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.002</td><td>0.162</td><td>0.025</td><td/><td>0.046</td></tr><tr><td>MYK</td><td>0.024</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.041</td><td>0.019</td><td>0.059</td><td>0.065</td><td>0.014</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.028</td><td>0.015</td><td>&#x0003c;0.001</td><td>0.167</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="15">
<bold><italic>DEST</italic></bold>
<bold>Fisher&#x02019;s exact test</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Recently colonized<break/>in temperate</td><td>GAHo</td><td/><td>0.022</td><td>0.024</td><td>0.040</td><td>0.022</td><td>0.039</td><td>0.030</td><td>0.046</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.038</td><td>0.079</td><td>0.054</td><td>0.034</td></tr><tr><td>GAHk</td><td>0.061</td><td/><td>0.025</td><td>0.021</td><td>0.023</td><td>0.025</td><td>0.004</td><td>0.045</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.014</td><td>0.062</td><td>0.039</td><td>0.042</td></tr><tr><td>AMK</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.011</td><td/><td>0.013</td><td>0.004</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.012</td><td>0.012</td><td>0.010</td><td>0.030</td><td>0.064</td><td>0.050</td><td>0.013</td></tr><tr><td>ZAH</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.024</td><td>0.032</td><td/><td>0.011</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.012</td><td>0.032</td><td>0.022</td><td>0.005</td><td>0.029</td><td>0.026</td><td>0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Pre-existing<break/>in temperate</td><td>WAHk</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.050</td><td>0.018</td><td>0.082</td><td/><td>0.000</td><td>0.016</td><td>0.016</td><td>0.016</td><td>0.026</td><td>0.056</td><td>0.032</td><td>0.004</td></tr><tr><td>WAHs</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.002</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.485</td><td>0.127</td><td/><td>0.011</td><td>0.021</td><td>0.012</td><td>0.007</td><td>0.021</td><td>0.017</td><td>0.000</td></tr><tr><td>KOC</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.271</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.030</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td/><td>0.024</td><td>0.000</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.044</td><td>0.031</td><td>0.019</td></tr><tr><td>TUK</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td/><td>0.011</td><td>0.035</td><td>0.044</td><td>0.041</td><td>0.025</td></tr><tr><td>TOI</td><td>0.025</td><td>0.141</td><td>0.026</td><td>0.004</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.209</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td/><td>0.013</td><td>0.039</td><td>0.024</td><td>0.022</td></tr><tr><td>KAHyn</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.009</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.016</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.002</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td/><td>0.009</td><td>0.009</td><td>0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Subtropical area</td><td>KAHae</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.024</td><td/><td>0.022</td><td>0.014</td></tr><tr><td>OAH</td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.003</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.006</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.126</td><td>0.056</td><td/><td>0.011</td></tr><tr><td>MYK</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.005</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.003</td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td><bold>&#x0003c;0</bold>.<bold>001</bold></td><td>0.154</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par11">STRUCTURE analysis was again performed within the green lineage with and without prior information (subtropical vs temperate). The results indicated that <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 best explained the data (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">5a,b</xref>), which suggests admixture and no clear genetic divergence between the temperate and subtropical regions, and these findings are consistent with the AMOVA results. However, when using the LOCPRIOR model, different proportions of assigned lineages were found between temperate and subtropical regions at <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) with a small <italic>r</italic> value (0.869), which implies that very small genetic differences exist between the two regions.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Bar plot at <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2 using the LOCPRIOR model (temperate vs subtropical, green lineage only).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e3793"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">The estimation of recent gene flow based on the assignment method using GeneClass2 showed that 95 out of 240 individuals were successfully assigned to one of the populations. Most of the successfully assigned individuals (15 out of 16) in the recently expanded populations suggested self-seeding. Only one out of 76 (1.3%) temperate individuals were possible recent immigrants from subtropical populations (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Particle tracking simulation</title><p id="Par13">Larval dispersal generally occurred northward along the Kuroshio Current (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b,c</xref>). Larval dispersal from temperate to subtropical areas seemed uncommon within a single generation because larval dispersal is physically limited to the path of the Kuroshio Current (here called the Kuroshio-associated barrier), although dispersal could be achieved through multiple generations or occasional long dispersals (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>). The Kuroshio-associated barrier corresponds to the biogeographic boundary called the Watase Line (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Unidirectional dispersal was observed from the western Kyushu region (E in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>) along the Tsushima Current to the temperate region along the southern Japanese coast (B in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>) along the main stream of the Kuroshio Current (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Sites of simulated larvae release. The region codes A~F correspond to A~F in (<bold>b, c</bold>) and (<bold>b</bold>) connectivity matrix based on the calculation of 23 years of larval dispersal simulations. (<bold>c</bold>) Connectivity matrix after iterating dispersal over 1000 generations. The colour contours on the right indicate the probability of a larva arriving at a sink site from a source site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e3843"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par14">Cryptic lineages were found in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic>, while only one lineage is dominant in the temperate region and is apparently expanding to the north. The Kuroshio-associated barrier found in the numerical simulation and/or the lack of adaptability to the temperate environment could hinder northward migration of the blue/red lineages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The Kuroshio-associated barrier also matched the Watase Line, which is the biogeographic barrier that separates terrestrial fauna and was caused by land bridges and sea barriers in past climates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Larval dispersal simulations using particle tracking averaged over 24 years indicated discontinuous patterns of connectivity between Yakushima and the Amami Islands (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). This discontinuity is possibly due to the Kuroshio path crossing between Yakushima and the Amami Islands, which prevents direct dispersal of single generations from the subtropics to areas further north (referred to as the Kuroshio-associated dispersal barrier). This study demonstrates that the Watase Line can be found in marine species due to the existence of the Kuroshio-associated dispersal barrier. The limited larval transport from subtropical to temperate regions within a single generation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) suggested that the probability of future poleward migration of the other lineages (red/blue in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> would depend on whether the larvae of these lineages could pass through this barrier via long or multi-generation dispersal. Further regular monitoring of the distributions of all cryptic lineages using genetic markers is necessary to assess the poleward migration of the species.</p><p id="Par15">Reduced genetic diversity (heterozygosity, allelic richness, and clonal rate) was observed in the recently expanded <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> populations distributed near the edge of the species&#x02019; range. One historical interpretation is that reduced genetic diversity near the edge of a species&#x02019; range is the result of greater isolation in peripheral populations than in core populations where species are more abundant than along the periphery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. However, this study did not detect a gradual increase in genetic isolation towards peripheral populations (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Alternatively, IBD patterns produced by a simple linear stepping-stone model explains the reduced genetic diversity near the edge. If a population structure is assumed to exhibit linearly uniform distribution over a large distance with limited migration in a simple linear stepping-stone model, then IBD genetic structure can theoretically be observed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Under such a situation, Tajima<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> demonstrated that the level of DNA polymorphism is highest in the central populations and gradually decreases towards peripheral populations. Our data relatively fit this linear stepping-stone model because significant IBD patterns were observed when oceanographic distance was used. Although more data are needed, a linear stepping-stone model can at least partially explain the observed patterns. Lastly, it is also possible that genetic diversity will decrease towards the edge of a species&#x02019; range in response to different selection pressures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, although there is an opposing view that a stressful peripheral environment can increase the number of genotypes in some cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Environmental factors, such as low sea water temperature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, high concentration of chlorophyll a, particulate organic carbon (POC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, reduced aragonite saturation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, light intensity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, and high turbidity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> around northern populations (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">7</xref>), could affect the suitability of reef-building corals habitats<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and subsequently erode genetic diversity. On the other hand, the larger genetic diversity in the subtropical populations can be partly explained by possible hybridization between closely related lineages (as found in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">Some previous studies have also provided evidence for reduced genetic diversity in peripheral coral populations. For example, both brooder and broadcaster coral species in the southernmost reef in the Pacific showed lowered genetic diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. In the Atlantic, another coral species, <italic>Montastraea cavernosa</italic>, showed lower genetic diversity in peripheral populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. These studies suggested that a small founding population, small effective population size of genetic drift, or inbreeding depression caused reduced genetic diversity in peripheral coral populations. However, expanding coral populations do not always follow this trend of reduced genetic diversity, as was demonstrated in the Mediterranean coral <italic>Oculina patagonica</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par17">The clonal rates were higher in temperate regions than in subtropical regions. Although the mechanism is unclear, different habitat characteristics (i.e., reef structure in subtropical regions and non-reef structure in temperate regions) potentially caused different rates of sexual reproduction success in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic>. In <italic>Acropora palmata</italic>, different rates of asexual reproduction are known to be related to different habitat characteristics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par18">While the historical gene flow analysis (e.g., <italic>F</italic>-statistics; Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">5</xref>) showed overall genetic similarities among temperate populations, contemporary gene flow analysis (assignment tests) indicated that all studied populations, including those in the peripheral temperate regions, are basically self-seeding (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">6</xref>). This result concords with the fact that peripheral temperate coral populations are mostly self-sustained by local spawning<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Recently expanded populations were therefore possibly seeded from other temperate populations by occasional long dispersal and then sustained themselves by self-seeding.</p><p id="Par19">Although the recently expanded Goto populations (GAHo) had low genetic diversity and a small number of samples was analysed (MGL&#x02009;=&#x02009;9), one individual had a private allele. One possible explanation is that harsh environments around GAH (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">7</xref>) caused some strong directional selective pressures on the coral populations, which reduced the genetic diversity and changed the allele frequencies, as was discussed above (selective pressure increased the frequency of rare alleles, and a private allele was found). Alternatively, the Goto population was colonized by other genetically diverged populations, such as those from Taiwan through the Taiwan-Tsushima warm current system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, that were not analysed in this study. Previous study has claimed that peripheral populations with low genetic diversity are some of the most active regions of speciation because of such genetically distinct features<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Further genetic analysis of Goto will be interesting to examine potential speciation in such a peripheral region.</p><p id="Par20">Significant IBD patterns were detected only when oceanographic distance was used (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), which indicates that pairwise genetic distances (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>) significantly increased with geographic distance. This result indicates that overall, the effect of genetic drift is stronger than the effect of gene flow between distant populations.</p><p id="Par21">We expected that the larval dispersal model rather than oceanographic distance would have significant IBD patterns because genetic structure is considered to be most associated with larval dispersal. However, the IBD patterns that were derived using the number of larvae between sites based on numerical simulations did not improve in comparison to those using Euclidean distances and oceanographic distances (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">4</xref>). This result might be because the genetic markers used in this study captured historical events rather than contemporary gene flow, especially in the <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> calculations, which assume equilibrium. Similarly, the genetic distance of sea stars across the Indo-Pacific region was best explained by Euclidean distance and not modelled larval distance in a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> in which the authors considered that the estimated <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> reflected historical gene flow rather than contemporary gene flow. Another explanation for the weak correlation with IBD patterns is the lack of biological characteristics (i.e., larval behaviour) in the larval dispersal models used in this study. A more sophisticated model that includes the biological aspects of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> would improve the correlation with genetic distance, as in a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Although corals in subtropical regions are threatened due to climate change, they are expanding and propagating into temperate regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Many climate change predictions of the species distributions of corals show a general loss of reef habitats in many areas except for the relatively robust eastern marginal Pacific region, including temperate Japan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Given the moderate levels of neutral genetic diversity and the persistence and increase in coral cover before and after the rise in sea water temperatures in pre-existing temperate coral populations, we propose that some of the pre-existing temperate regions in Japan would be good refugia for at least one of the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> lineages. Pre-existing temperate regions are indeed the potential habitats that &#x0201c;part of biodiversity retreat to, persist in and can potentially expand&#x0201d; under climate change conditions. In temperate regions, seaweed beds have been replaced by temperate corals, including <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic>, and the coral cover is currently expanding in these regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Although a direct association between neutral genetic diversity and resilience of coral populations against environmental change is partly under debate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, some coral genotypes are known to be associated with stress tolerances such as disease and higher water temperature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Thus, moderate genetic diversity in pre-existing temperate populations may indicate stability and higher tolerance against unexpected extreme environmental changes such as local anthropogenic stress. Nonetheless, much less attention has been paid to coral assemblages and their conservation in temperate regions than in subtropical regions. Unlike in subtropical regions, where tourism, recreation, and fisheries are directly associated with the abundance of corals, temperate corals are sometimes regarded as a nuisance by local fishermen in temperate regions because subtropical fishes are of low economic value in these areas. In addition, expensive fishing nets become entangled on and broken by hard corals, causing pecuniary damage to fishermen (N. Yasuda personal communication with local fishermen in Miyazaki). Because reef-building corals help to increase overall biodiversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> by providing food and habitats with complex structures in coastal ecosystems, there is a need to review the value of temperate corals for conservation.</p><p id="Par23">The importance of conserving the pre-existing temperate corals discussed in this study does not dismiss or discourage the conservation of subtropical corals. Rather, two out of the three <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> lineages were found in only the subtropical region, and the highest genetic diversity was found in the subtropical region, indicating that these areas are nonetheless important.</p><p id="Par24">This study indicated that recently expanded marginal populations could have low genetic diversity and are possibly more vulnerable to environmental changes than pre-existing populations. This finding underpins the importance of assessing the genetic diversity of populations that have recently expanded due to climate change for conservation purposes, in particular when anticipating the roles of these areas as refugia under climate change.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Coral sampling and genotyping</title><p id="Par25">In total, 689<italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> samples were collected using SCUBA from 22 populations along the Kuroshio and Tsushima Currents (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This study included four temperate populations that have recently expanded possibly due to climate change: two populations from Goto Island and the Amakusa and Shikine populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. No records of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> were found in Goto and Amakusa in a 1965&#x02013;1977 survey. There was no existing record of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> in Shikine in a 1986 survey<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, but we discovered large colonies in 2016 in this study. Each sample was photographed except for the AMK, KOC, MYK, SSK, TUK, TOI, and OAH specimens (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Wherever possible about 5&#x02009;cm of skeleton specimens were collected and deposited at the University of Miyazaki (MUFS-Acr101&#x02013;310, 371&#x02013;428, 500&#x02013;531, 569&#x02013;717, 768&#x02013;801). Species identification was further confirmed by Dr. Hironobu Fukami based on morphological information.</p><p id="Par26">Genomic DNA was extracted using a modification of a previously published method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Genotypes of the corals were determined by 8 microsatellite loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Eight loci were amplified in 2 multiplex PCR sets using different dyes and non-overlapping loci (Plex1 includes 8346m3, 11401m4, 8499m4, and 10366m5; Plex2 included Amil2-2h, Amil2-23h, Amil2-10, and Amil2-12). For Amil2-2h and Amil2-23h, we used modified primers to increase PCR efficiency for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> (Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">8</xref>). We used an 8&#x02009;&#x003bc;l reaction containing 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of template DNA, 0.03&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of each primer (50&#x02009;&#x003bc;M), 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Type It (Microsatellite Kit, Qiagen), and 2.94&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of water. The thermal cycler profile that was used had an initial denaturation step at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min followed by 30 cycles of 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/30&#x02009;s, 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/30&#x02009;s, 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/30&#x02009;s, with a final extension step at 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min.</p><p id="Par27">The multiplexed PCR product was diluted by 100, and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the diluted PCR product was added to 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of highly deionized formamide containing 0.15&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the GeneScan-600 (LIZ) size standard (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) for genotyping on an ABI 3730xl automated sequencer (GeneMapper&#x000ae; ver. 5, Applied Biosystems), which was used to determine the fragment sizes (alleles) of all samples. All genotyping was manually checked. Whenever we found ambiguous patterns or no peak, we re-extracted the genomic DNA and re-amplified it or removed the sample from the analysis. We tested for the presence of null alleles using MICRO-CHECKER ver. 2.2.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, and the locus positive for null alleles was excluded from the genetic analysis of the population.</p><p id="Par28">The clonal structure of each coral population was examined by identifying the same MLGs based on 8 microsatellite loci; these were identified as possible clones (asexually reproduced by fragmentation), and all except one were excluded from subsequent analyses. The inbreeding coefficient of a population (<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>IS</italic></sub>), was evaluated with GenAlEx ver. 6.502<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Genotypic linkage disequilibrium across 8 loci was examined using GENEPOP on the web (ver. 4.0.10)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> by estimating exact <italic>P</italic> values using the Markov chain method with 10,000 dememorization steps, 1,000 batches, and 10,000 iterations per batch.</p><p id="Par29">Different measures of genetic diversity were estimated for each population, including the number of alleles per locus (Na), the observed (H<sub>O</sub>) and expected (H<sub>E</sub>) heterozygosity using GenAlEx ver. 6.502<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, and allelic richness (A) using FSTAT ver. 2.932<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Identifying cryptic lineages distributed in both temperate and subtropical regions</title><p id="Par30">We first identified the cryptic lineages of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic> found in a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. STRUCTURE analysis was conducted using the admixture model without prior information. The Markov chain Mote Carlo (MCMC) chains used a burn-in of 500,000 chains followed by 500,000 MCMC replications. Ten independent chains were run for each <italic>K</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 to 10 to confirm convergence. The coefficient of ancestry was calculated and visualized for each individual across 10 runs for the most likely values of <italic>K</italic> (Delta <italic>K</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>), in CLUMPAK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> Among the lineages identified in the STRUCTURE analysis above, we used only the lineage distributed in both temperate and subtropical regions in subsequent analyses (green lineage in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). PCoA was conducted to confirm the different lineages found in the STRUCTURE analysis using GenAlEx ver. 6.502<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. A NJ phylogenetic tree was reconstructed using Nei&#x02019;s genetic distance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> as implemented in POPULATIONS ver. 1.2.32<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> with 1000 bootstrap values and visualized this tree using TreeViewX ver. 0.5.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">STRUCTURE was again run to examine the intra-green-lineage genetic structure. First, we analysed STRUCTURE without any prior information and then used prior information about different regions (temperate or subtropical) using the LOCPRIOR model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. All other STRUCTURE run settings were the same as described above.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Genetic connectivity</title><p id="Par32">To examine the degree of genetic connectivity between temperate and subtropical populations, population genetic structure was examined by AMOVA using Arlequin ver. 3.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. After calculating global <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub>, we evaluated the genetic structure using the following prior groupings: (1) all temperate populations vs subtropical populations, (2) recently expanded populations vs pre-existing temperate populations, and (3) populations along the temperate main stream of the Kuroshio Current (ZAH, WAHk, WAHs, KOC, TUK TOI, and KAH) vs populations along the Tsushima Current (AMK, GAHo, and GAHk). Pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> and pairwise <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>EST</italic></sub> (Jost&#x02019;s direct measure of differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>) values across populations were calculated to estimate relatively isolated populations using GenAlEx 6.503<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. The significance of population differentiation was also determined based on Fisher&#x02019;s exact test using Genepop on the web ver. 4.0.10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup> with Markov chain parameters with 10,000 dememorization steps, 1,000 batches, and 10,000 iterations per batch. Sequential Bonferroni correction was applied to determine statistical significance for all pairs of populations (&#x003b1;&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p id="Par33">GeneClass2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> was used to estimate recent gene flow between temperate and subtropical populations using the criteria and the computational algorithm of Rannala and Mountain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> with default settings. Individuals were assigned to a source population when an individual had the highest assigned probability &#x0003e;70%, and others were regarded as unassigned. Because the two geographically close Wakayama populations (WAHs and WAHk) and the two Goto populations (GAHo and GAHk) were not significantly differentiated (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), we combined these populations for only the GeneClass2 analysis.</p><sec id="Sec12"><title>IBD</title><p id="Par34">To examine whether neighbouring populations have stronger gene flow than distant populations, the IBD patterns based on pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>ST</italic></sub> values were regressed onto (1) Euclidean distances between sites, (2) oceanographic distances avoiding physically impossible routes (e.g., passing on land) that were manually estimated using Google Earth and (3) simulated number of accumulated larvae based on a particle tracking model with iterations after 1000 generations (see below, Suppl.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">10</xref>). We used two different datasets, one including all green lineage populations and the other excluding four recently expanded populations. Significance was tested using the Mantel permutation test (10,000 randomizations) using R ver. 3.4.2. Because the TUK population was surrounded by artificial structures that prevented larval dispersal, this population was excluded from the IBD analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Lagrangian particle tracking simulation</title><p id="Par35">To estimate the probability of larval dispersal between different sites based on ocean current systems, we conducted Lagrangian particle tracking simulation using the Connectivity Modelling System (CMS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup> with Global HYCOM (Hybrid Coordinate Ocean Modelling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>) ocean-current analysis/reanalysis products (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://hycom.org">https://hycom.org</ext-link>). CMS can evaluate a full range of transport and fate variabilities at high computational efficiency. In the particle tracking model, larvae are treated as passive particles transported on the surface by horizontal current velocities. The particles regarded as larvae were totally released from 111 habitat zones of 1/12&#x000b0;&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1/12&#x000b0; rectangles (~10 km<sup>2</sup>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). The timings of spawning (particle release) from each site were assumed to have begun on the first full moon before the integrated water temperature anomaly from 13&#x02009;&#x000b0;C from February 1st exceeded 1000&#x02009;&#x000b0;C day (&#x0222b;max(T-13, 0)dt). The parameters for estimating the spawning dates (1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, February 1<sup>st</sup>, and 1000&#x02009;&#x000b0;C&#x000b7;day) were determined by trial-and-error adjustment using previous records of <italic>Acropora</italic> spawning timing in Japan. The estimated spawning dates were in general agreement with the records of previous spawning timing (Aizawa <italic>et al</italic>. unpub. data). The time-series dataset of sea surface temperature used to estimate spawning timing at each site was obtained by extraction from the Global HYCOM analysis/reanalysis products. Spawning events were assumed to take place 3 days before the spawning full moon and to continue for 10 days. From each site, 50 particles were released each day, and a total of 500 particles were released in one year. The maximum larval dispersal period was set for 42 days, which is the maximum length of pelagic larval duration of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hyacinthus</italic>. It was assumed that larvae could begin settling on coral habitats three days after particle release. When the particles passed by the coral habitats, the particles were counted as successful recruitments (the number of larvae dispersed from one place). Finally, a connectivity matrix was obtained by conducting the particle tracking simulation for a total of 24 years from 1993 to 2016. Using the average of the 24-year connectivity matrix, we iterated particle dispersal to simulate the long-term accumulation of dispersed larvae and consider the stepping-stone-like connectivity. This calculation was repeated until the number of the accumulated particle stabilized over time (1000 generations).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec14"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Suppl. 9</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_38333_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Suppl. material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-38333-5.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful for the assistance and helpful advice on this manuscript from Dr. Hironobu Fukami and Dr. Go Suzuki and Mr. Keichi Nomura and Mr. Mitsuhiro Ueno for their help with coral sampling. We also thank Mr. Akifumi Shimura, Ms. Yumi Yamamoto, Ms. Eriko Nagahiro and Ms. Ritsuko Kubota for their help with the experiments. This study was supported by the Environment Research and Technology Development Fund (4RF-1501 and 4-1304) of the Ministry of the Environment, Japan, Grant-in-aid for young scientists (A) (17H04996) and the Program to Disseminate Tenure Tracking System from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT), and the Climate Change Adaptation Research Program of National Institute for Environmental Studies. Sampling was conducted under Okinawa Prefectural Government Permits (No. 27-81, 27-29, 26-10, 25-44, 24-36), a Tokyo Prefectural Government Permit (No. 28-11), a Kochi Prefectural Government Permit (No. 530), and Ministry of the Environment permits (No. 1602252 and 1407181). Elsewhere, we submitted notifications to local governments and worked in agreement with local fishing corporations. We are grateful for the two anonymous reviewers who provided significant comments to improve this manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>A.N., Y.F.K., A.I., H.Y., S.A. and N.Y. conducted field surveys and sampling, and A.N. and S.N. carried out molecular experiments. T.N., T.Y., and H.A. conducted the numerical simulation analysis. A.N., K.M.T., and N.Y. analysed and interpreted the data. N.Y. designed the work and drafted the manuscript. All authors approved and revised the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets generated during and/or analysed during the current study are available in the Dryad repository (10.5061/dryad.5ps117g).</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wilkinson, C. <italic>Status of coral reefs of the world: 2008</italic> (GCRMN, 2004).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coral reefs under rapidclimate change and ocean acidification</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>1737</fpage><lpage>1742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1152509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18079392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yamano, H., Sugihara, K. &#x00026; Nomura, K. Rapid poleward range expansion of tropical reef corals in response to rising sea surface temperatures. <italic>Geophys</italic>. <italic>Res</italic>. <italic>Lett</italic>. <bold>38</bold>, 10.1029/2010GL046474 (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid Northward spread of a Zooxanthellate coral enhanced by artificial structures and sea warming in the Western Mediterranean</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e52739</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0052739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23341904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Done</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coral reefs. Limited scope for latitudinal extension of reef corals</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>1138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1259911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26045436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keppel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardell-Johnson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Refugia: keys to climate change management</article-title><source>Glob. Change Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2389</fpage><lpage>2391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2012.02729.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schierenbeck</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population-level genetic variation andclimate change in a biodiversity hotspot</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><year>2017</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcw214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28069633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Samis</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lougheed</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation across species&#x02019; geographical ranges: the central-marginal hypothesis and beyond</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1170</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03659.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18302683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Veron, J. &#x00026; Stafford-Smith, M. <italic>Corals of the world</italic> (Australian Institute of Marine Science, 2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ladner</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Palumbi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensive sympatry, cryptic diversity and introgression throughout the geographic distribution of two coral species complexes</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2224</fpage><lpage>2238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05528.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22439812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic evidence of peripheral isolation and low diversity in marginal populations of the <italic>Acropora hyacinthus</italic> complex</article-title><source>Coral Reefs</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1419</fpage><lpage>1432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00338-016-1484-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coral larval rearing in Singapore: observations of spawning timing, larval development and settlement of two common Scleractinian coral species</article-title><source>Contrib. Marine Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nozawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Okubo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival dynamics of reef coral larvae with special consideration of larval size and the genus</article-title><source>Acropora. Biol. Bull.</source><year>2011</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/BBLv220n1p15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21385953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hongo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayanne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Key species of Hermatypic coral for reef formation in the Northwest Pacific during Holocene sea-level change</article-title><source>Marine Geol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.margeo.2010.10.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Coverage, diversity, and functionality of a high-latitude coral community (Tatsukushi, Shikoku Island, Japan)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e54330</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0054330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23342135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Komaki, S. &#x00026; Igawa, T. The widespread misconception about the Japanese major biogeographic boundary, the Watase line (Tokara gap), revealed by bibliographic and beta diversity analyses. <italic>bioRxiv</italic>, 10.1101/186775 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pritchard, J. K., Stephens, M. &#x00026; Donnely, P. Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data. <italic>Genetics</italic><bold>155</bold>, 945&#x02013;959 (2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Burg</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Steeves</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sampling for microsatellite-based population genetic studies: 25 to 30 individuals per population is enough to accurately estimate allele frequencies</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e45170</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22984627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical analysis of DNA polymorphism</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Genet.</source><year>1993</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1266/jjg.68.567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8031577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L-Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lowered diversity and increased inbreeding depression within peripheral populations of wild rice <italic>Oryza rufipogon</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0150468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0150468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26963913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Parsons, P. A. Evolutionary rates under environmental stress. In <italic>Evolutionary biology: Volume 21</italic> (eds Hecht, M. K., Wallace, B. &#x00026; Prance, G. T.) 311&#x02013;347 (Springer US, 1987).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Agostini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Casareto</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuyama</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Northern limit of corals of the genus <italic>Acropora</italic> in temperate zones is determined by their resilience to cold bleaching</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>18467</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep18467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26680690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NASA Goddard Space Flight Center. <italic>Ocean Ecology Laboratory Ocean Biology Processing Group</italic>. <italic>Moderate-resolution imaging spectroradiometer (MODIS) Terra Ocean Color Data</italic> (NASA, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ocean acidification limits temperature-induced poleward expansion of coral habitats around Japan</article-title><source>Biogeosciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4955</fpage><lpage>4968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/bg-9-4955-2012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleypas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Menez</surname><given-names>LAB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental limits to coral reef development: where do we draw the line?</article-title><source>Am. Zoolog.</source><year>1999</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/39.1.146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleypas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coral reef development under naturally turbid conditions: fringing reefs near Broad Sound, Australia</article-title><source>Coral Reefs</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01145886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayre</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change, genotypic diversity and gene flow in reef-building corals</article-title><source>Ecol. Lett.</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2004.00585.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Knowlton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implications of isolation and low genetic diversity in peripheral populations of an amphi-Atlantic coral</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>4283</fpage><lpage>4297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04347.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19765228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leydet</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grupstra</surname><given-names>CGB</given-names></name><name><surname>Coma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host&#x02010;targeted RAD&#x02010;Seq reveals genetic changes in the coral <italic>Oculina patagonica</italic> associated with range expansion along the Spanish Mediterranean coast</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2529</fpage><lpage>2543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.14702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29693297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baums</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic variation in clonal structure in a reef&#x02010;building <italic>Caribbean coral</italic>, <italic>Acropora palmata</italic></article-title><source>Ecol. Monogr.</source><year>2006</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9615(2006)076[0503:GVICSI]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Woesik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coral communities at high latitude are not pseudopopulations: evidence of spawning at 32&#x000b0;N, Japan</article-title><source>Coral Reefs</source><year>1995</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00303433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the origin of the Tsushima warm current and its seasonality</article-title><source>Continent. Shelf Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0278-4343(98)00065-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesica</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Allendorf</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When are peripheral populations valuable for conservation? &#x000bf;Cu&#x000e1;ndo resultan las poblaciones perif&#x000e9;ricas valiosas para la conservaci&#x000f3;n?</article-title><source>Conserv. Biol.</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1523-1739.1995.09040753.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Return of the ghosts of dispersal past: historical spread and contemporary gene flow in the blue sea star <italic>Linckia</italic> laevigata</article-title><source>Bull. Marine Sci.</source><year>2014</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5343/bms.2013.1052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ocean currents help explain population genetic structure</article-title><source>Proc. Royal Soc. B Biol. Sci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>1685</fpage><lpage>1694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2009.2214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust performance of marginal Pacific coral reef habitats in future climate scenarios</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0128875</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26053439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verg&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The tropicalization of temperate marine ecosystems: climate-mediated changes in herbivory and community phase shifts</article-title><source>Proc. Royal Soc. B Biol. Sci.</source><year>2014</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>20140846</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2014.0846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baker, A. C. Symbiont diversity on coral reefs and its relationship to bleaching resistance and resilience. In <italic>Coral health and disease</italic> (eds Rosenberg, E. &#x00026; Loya, Y.) 177&#x02013;194 (Springer, 2004).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komyakova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Munday</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative Importance of coral cover, habitat complexity and diversity in determining the structure of reef fish communities</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e83178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0083178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24349455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meeker</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trede</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Method for isolation of PCR-ready genomic DNA from zebrafish tissues</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><issue>610</issue><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>614</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Oppen</surname><given-names>MJH</given-names></name><name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Muirhead</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Peplow</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ten microsatellite loci for the reef-building coral <italic>Acropora millepora</italic> (Cnidaria, Scleractinia) from the Great Barrier Reef, Australia</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol. Notes</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2006.01610.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shinzato, C. <italic>et al</italic>. Development of novel, cross-species microsatellite markers for <italic>Acropora</italic> corals using next-generation sequencing technology. <italic>Front</italic>. <italic>Marine Sci</italic>. <bold>1</bold>, 10.3389/fmars.2014.00011 (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Oosterhout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micro-checker: software for identifying and correcting genotyping errors in microsatellite data</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol. Notes</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-8286.2004.00684.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peakall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smouse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GenAlEx 6.5: genetic analysis in excel. Population genetic software for teaching and research &#x02013; an update</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2537</fpage><lpage>2539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GENEPOP: population genetics software for exact tests and ecumenicism</article-title><source>J. Heredity</source><year>1995</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a111573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FSTAT (Version 1.2): a computer program to calculate F-statistics</article-title><source>J. Heredity</source><year>1995</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a111627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evanno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Regnaut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2611</fpage><lpage>2620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2005.02553.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopelman</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayrose</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUMPAK: a program for identifying clustering modes and packaging population structure inferences across K</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol. Resour.</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1755-0998.12387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25684545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy of estimated phylogenetic trees from molecular data. II</article-title><source>Gene frequency data. J. Mol. Evol.</source><year>1983</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02300753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6571220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">POPULATIONS. <italic>Population genetic software (individuals or populations distances</italic>, <italic>phylogenetic trees</italic>) (2002).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>RDM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TREEVIEW: An application to display phylogenetic trees on personal computers</article-title><source>Comput. Appl. Biosci.</source><year>1996</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8902363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8902363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubisz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Falush</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring weak population structure with the assistance of sample group information</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol. Resour.</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1322</fpage><lpage>1332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02591.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21564903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Excoffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lischer</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arlequin suite ver 3.5: a new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and Windows</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol. Resour.</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02847.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21565059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>LOU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GST and its relatives do not measure differentiation</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4015</fpage><lpage>4026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03887.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19238703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GENECLASS2: a software for genetic assignment and first-generation migrant detection</article-title><source>J. Hered.</source><year>2004</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/esh074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15475402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rannala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mountain</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting immigration by using multilocus&#x02009;genotypes</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>9197</fpage><lpage>9201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.17.9197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9256459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Helgers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Sebille</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Connectivity modeling system: a probabilistic modeling tool for the multi-scale tracking of biotic and abiotic variability in the ocean</article-title><source>Environ. Modell. Softw.</source><year>2013</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envsoft.2012.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chassignet</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The HYCOM (HYbrid Coordinate Ocean Model) data assimilative system</article-title><source>J. Marine Syst.</source><year>2007</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmarsys.2005.09.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>