<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background &amp; Summary</div>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human activities have caused substantial changes to the global climate. In addition to the effects of greenhouse gases, aerosols, and land use/cover change, anthropogenic heat released from energy consumption can affect climatic changes at various scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. For example, Zhang 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> found that energy consumption could lead to increases in winter and autumn temperatures of up to 1 °C in the mid- and high latitudes across North America and Eurasia. Ichinose 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> found that the maximum anthropogenic heat flux (AHF) in central Tokyo, Japan, was as high as 1,590 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> in winter, resulting in warming to a maximum of 2.5 °C. Moreover, anthropogenic heat can affect wind speed because it reduces the stability of the boundary layer and enhances vertical mixing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. In view of the effects of anthropogenic heat on climate at local and continental scales and the increasing consumption of energy worldwide, the potential significance of anthropogenic heat as it relates to global climate change over a long-term period should be further studied using techniques such as global climate models.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The diversity of regional energy consumption and limited data availability make it difficult to produce high quality global AHF datasets when considering the accuracy
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, resolution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, and length of time series
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> of the data. For example, Allen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> developed a widely accepted AHF dataset at 2.5 × 2.5 arc-minute resolution based on the Large Scale Urban Consumption of Energy model; however, it still cannot satisfy the demand of high-resolution regional modelling because of the relatively rough spatial resolution. Additionally, acquiring all of the necessary data (e.g., population, temperature, and different types of the energy sources) has proved to be impossible for many countries such as island countries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Moreover, Chen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> and Yang 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> estimated global AHFs based on the Defence Meteorological Satellite Program/Operational Linescan System (DMSP/OLS) night-time light data, but the night-time light data were normally limited by the short time series (1992–2013) available, “light diffusion” phenomena in densely populated areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, and the differences in culture and day-length among different regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. All of these limitations remained in producing AHF data and hindered simulation studies of anthropogenic heat at local, regional, or global scales. Remarkably, the time series of previous AHF datasets generally is not long enough to be used for simulation studies of long-term climate change (e.g., the dramatic global warming period since the 1980s).
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Levels of energy consumption are expected to increase in the future because of the rapid development of the global economy and increased living standard. Therefore, it makes sense to study the variations and climatic effects of global AHF in the future. So far, only Flanner has projected the distribution of global AHFs in the future
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Flanner’s AHF dataset which was developed at 2009 included the global gridded AHF during 2005–2040 and in 2100; nevertheless, all of the data, except data for 2005, were projected data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. That is, Flanner’s AHF data during 2006–2040 were calculated based on the 2008 energy-use projection (high economic growth case) from the U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA); his data for 2100 were calculated based on the assumption that energy consumption will grow by 2% per year for each country after 2040
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Evidently, Flanner’s data from 2006 to 2040 and the EIA energy-use projection in 2008 have been out of date; his assumption on energy consumption after 2040 should be improved due to the varied energy demands of each country
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Recently, a report of the McKinsey Global Energy Perspective (GEP) was proposed (https://gep.mckinseyenergyinsights.com/), which takes into account both macro- and micro-economic developments. A unique aspect of the GEP is that most insights on future energy demand are local (i.e., projecting the evolution of energy systems by country). This provides an opportunity to re-estimate the distribution of future global AHF.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inventory-based approach is widely used to estimate anthropogenic heat release, including for both bottom-up and top-down approaches
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The bottom-up approach relies on detailed datasets of local land use and statistics on the hourly variation in energy consumption; this type of data is mostly used for local-scale studies such as a single city because of limited data availability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. In contrast, a top-down approach is often used for large-scale studies through allocating total energy consumption (e.g., energy consumption at country-level) into specific regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. However, some detailed information about local energy consumption (e.g., industrial scale and distribution) is difficult to capture. Therefore, when using the top-down approach, some spatial data closely associated with energy consumption intensity such as population density and/or night-time light data are normally used as a proxy for the redistribute the total energy consumption
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. The basic assumption of the top-down approach is that all energy consumed by human activities in a specified region is directly converted to anthropogenic heat in that region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. This assumption is somewhat insufficient because the transformation and storage of energy are ignored. However, detailed processes involved in heat emissions are not easily tracked in large-scale studies because transformation and storage can vary widely with the technology employed for each activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, AHF can be spatially estimated based on the concept of energy budget closure
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. This method employs measurements of net radiation along with sensible, latent, and ground heat using remotely sensed meteorological data, which is suitable for local-scale studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Recently, several studies have combined multiple approaches to estimate AHF for large regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. For example, Lee 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> built a regression model that used AHF calculated by an inventory-based approach and pollutant emission data to estimate AHF over the entire US. However, generalizing this method to a global scale has proved difficult, because such simulations of AHF are subject to the availability of data from multiple sources. Given the features and limitations of existing approaches, a top-down approach should currently be the most efficient for estimating the distribution of global AHF.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, the objective of this study is to develop a new long-term (1970–2050) global gridded AHF dataset with fine resolution using a top-down approach based on population density data. The new dataset, including past and future global gridded AHF (PF-AHF), was compared with previous estimates at multiple scales (from the city to global level) for validation.</p>
</sec>
