<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical energy consumption data</div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual primary energy consumption data from 1965 to 2016 were obtained from the British Petroleum (BP) Statistical Review of World Energy (hereinafter, BP Review) (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bp.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.bp.com/</span>). Primary energy sources comprise coal, hydroelectricity, nuclear energy, natural gas, oil, and modern renewables used to generate electricity. The BP Review classified the entire earth into six sub-regions, which include 65 countries and five other regions (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Based on the BP energy consumption data in 2015, the total energy consumption of the above-mentioned 65 countries counted about 95.8% of the global amount, indicating that these 65 countries are the most significant places for energy consumption and anthropogenic heat release. The energy statistics reported by BP with relatively high reliability have been used in many previous studies
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
   </span>. In addition, future energy demands reported by the 2018 Reference Case of McKinsey GEP were used to estimate annual growth rates in future energy demand (https://gep.mckinseyenergyinsights.com/).
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>List of the countries and regions in six sub-regions as listed in the British Petroleum Statistical Review of World Energy.</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>Sub-regions in the world</th>
       <th>Countries or regions</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>North America</td>
       <td>United States of America, Canada, Mexico</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>South and Central America</td>
       <td>Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, Republic of Trinidad and Tobago, Venezuela, other regions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Europe and Eurasia</td>
       <td>Austria, Azerbaijan, Belarus, Belgium, Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Kazakhstan, Lithuania, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Russian Federation, Slovakia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Turkey, Turkmenistan, Ukraine, United Kingdom, Uzbekistan, other regions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Middle East</td>
       <td>Iran, Israel, Kuwait, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, other regions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Africa</td>
       <td>Algeria, Egypt, South Africa, other regions</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Asia Pacific</td>
       <td>Australia, Bangladesh, China, India, Indonesia, Japan, Malaysia, New Zealand, Pakistan, Philippines, Singapore, Republic of Korea, Thailand, Vietnam, other regions</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global population data</div>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global gridded population density data representing conditions in 1970, 1980, and 1990 were obtained from the Global Population Density Grid Time Series Estimates, Version 1, while the data for 2000, 2005, 2010, and 2015 were obtained from the Gridded Population of the World, Version 4, Revision 10 Data Sets
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
   </span>. The two above-mentioned datasets were downloaded from the Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center in NASA’s Earth Observing System Data and Information System (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/data/sets/browse" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/data/sets/browse</span>). These two datasets have a spatial resolution of 30 arc-seconds (approximately 1 km at the equator) and are used to redistribute the total energy consumption within a country or region. The population size data were obtained from the Wittgenstein Centre Data Explorer Version 1.2 that includes the global population projections from 1970 to 2100 for 195 countries worldwide (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wittgensteincentre.org/dataexplorer" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.wittgensteincentre.org/dataexplorer</span>). The future population sizes during 2020–2050 used in this study were generated according to the medium level scenario of the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways scenarios. The assumptions about future trends in fertility, mortality, and migration are authoritative and were based on scientific input from more than 500 population experts worldwide who responded to an online questionnaire and assessed the validity of alternative arguments as well as the conclusions of intensive discussions at five meta-expert meetings
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. We re-counted the population sizes for the 65 countries and five other regions in the six sub-regions mentioned above to maintain data consistency (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other data used for validation</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DMSP/OLS night-time stable light (NSL) data in 2010 with a spatial resolution of 1 km were collected by the US Air Force Weather Agency and obtained from the NOAA’s National Geophysical Data Center (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ngdc.noaa.gov/eog/download.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://ngdc.noaa.gov/eog/download.html</span>). The values of NSL data ranging from 0–63 indicate the night-time light intensities. In general, developed areas with a high gross domestic product (GDP) consume more energy than do developing areas with low GDP. It has been demonstrated that night-time light intensity is positively correlated with GDP, population size, and energy consumption
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>. Therefore, the night-time light data could be used as a proxy of AHF to validate our PF-AHF dataset
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global Man-made Impervious Surface (GMIS) data in 2010 with a spatial resolution of 1 km were used to extract the spatial extent of urban area; GMIS data were obtained from the Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center in NASA’s Earth Observing System Data and Information System (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/data/sets/browse" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/data/sets/browse</span>). The values of pixels in the GMIS data ranging from 0 to 100% show the percentage of impervious surface. Examples of impervious surface include roads, parking lots, buildings, driveways, sidewalks, and other manmade surfaces
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. As an important indicator used to assess the urban environment, impervious surface has been frequently used to reflect the land use/cover change associated with urbanization
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. Based on the study of Voorde 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>, we extracted the regions with pixels having a GMIS value larger than 10%, and delineated them as urban areas.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
