<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global population data</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global gridded population density data representing conditions in 1970, 1980, and 1990 were obtained from the Global Population Density Grid Time Series Estimates, Version 1, while the data for 2000, 2005, 2010, and 2015 were obtained from the Gridded Population of the World, Version 4, Revision 10 Data Sets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. The two above-mentioned datasets were downloaded from the Socioeconomic Data and Applications Center in NASA’s Earth Observing System Data and Information System (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/data/sets/browse" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/data/sets/browse</span>). These two datasets have a spatial resolution of 30 arc-seconds (approximately 1 km at the equator) and are used to redistribute the total energy consumption within a country or region. The population size data were obtained from the Wittgenstein Centre Data Explorer Version 1.2 that includes the global population projections from 1970 to 2100 for 195 countries worldwide (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wittgensteincentre.org/dataexplorer" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.wittgensteincentre.org/dataexplorer</span>). The future population sizes during 2020–2050 used in this study were generated according to the medium level scenario of the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways scenarios. The assumptions about future trends in fertility, mortality, and migration are authoritative and were based on scientific input from more than 500 population experts worldwide who responded to an online questionnaire and assessed the validity of alternative arguments as well as the conclusions of intensive discussions at five meta-expert meetings
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. We re-counted the population sizes for the 65 countries and five other regions in the six sub-regions mentioned above to maintain data consistency (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
