<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For both crops, increasing production is an important goal—not only through expansion of plantation area, but also through increased productivity. This would enable the Nepali coffee and banana sectors to both meet growing demand and to improve the economic condition of smallholder farmers and entrepreneurs engaged in these two value chains. At the same time, there is a need to deal with issues related to land security issues and climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Climate change will have greatly impact subsistence or smallholder farmers and the poor [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], while large-scale commercial plantations and associated agribusiness will be similarly affected [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Climate change is expected to affect agriculture crop production throughout the greater Himalayan region including Nepal. Climate variability has affected livelihoods and food security in Nepal in the past [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], and these impacts are predicted to increase in the future. The Coupled Model Inter-comparison Project Phase-5 (CMIP5) simulations and its scenarios indicate that by the mid-21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century, mean annual temperatures will exceed 1.6–2.5°C above the late-20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup>-century baseline in Nepal [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Precipitation projections correspond to observed historical trends, which suggest decreases in post-monsoon rainfall in the winter months, potentially leading to drought conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. These changes are expected to have significant impacts on crop production with varying impacts depending on elevation, crop type, and growing season [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. For example, climate change is likely to drive geographic shifts in crop and land suitability, result in changes in the occurrence of crop diseases and pests [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], and directly impact yields of the main crop species [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] and varieties. These impacts may pose a major threat to different cash crops in the near future. Commodities like banana and coffee are not an exception to the potential impacts of climate change; it is probable that climate change impacts may be significant in monoculture plantations, which could be more susceptible to climatic and biological hazards [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. If the potential effects of climate change are not addressed through appropriate changes in farming practices and techniques then decreasing yields will impact both local and national food security [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] and trade relations. Adaptations to climate change in terms of farming practice and techniques could include measures such as moving cultivation to different areas and elevations, taking advantage of advances in agricultural technology such as abiotic-stress resilient crops [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], or other improved management practices such as agroforestry and integrated pest management [
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0163916.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>].
</p>
