<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">As the individual attribute components can be compiled into a composite indicator by multi-attribute utility functions to effectively represent multidimensional complicated issues
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>, the vulnerability to climate change has been generally measured by a composite indicator. A prominent framework for vulnerability assessment to climate change comprises the three attribute components of exposure, sensitivity, and coping, as presented in the IPCC TAR
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. There has been a variety of aggregation methods for the constituent components into a composite indicator to measure the overall vulnerability to climate change. The conventional frameworks commonly used for aggregating the IPCC’s assessment components can be classified as: 1) an additive form 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and a multiplicative form 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> for the three individual components as originally, 2) an additive form 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> and a multiplicative form 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> for the three individual components by replacing coping with lack of coping, and 3) an additive form 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>3</sub> and a multiplicative form 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>3</sub> for a composite indicator combining the two components, as well as the other one. However, it has not been explicitly interpreted how the construction frameworks and aggregation methods influence the vulnerability composite indicator outcomes. This study has therefore evaluated the robustness and sensitivity of the vulnerability composite indicators aggregated by the conventional additive and multiplicative multi-attribute utility functions from the vulnerability assessment components. The analysis is especially focused on the vulnerability ranking alteration across the six composite indicators by the conventional aggregation frameworks and processes. The effects on the vulnerability outcomes across different construction frameworks are first examined by a design of the possible reference cases of the vulnerability assessment components, and then demonstrated through a case study on the coastal flood vulnerability assessment from actual data to climate change.
</p>
