<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9" class="p">Apart from uncertainties in MBS and TECs, the coefficient of determination with TECs from ref.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> predicts that 61% of the spatial difference in glacier behaviour is due to different MBS, i.e. glacier responses. Furthermore, trends in summer temperature and annual precipitation, which were analysed in terms of climatic forcing, have lower determination coefficients with TECs throughout the calculated period (1979–2007, Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S3</xref>). The maximum determination coefficients are found for the trends from 1993 to 2007 for summer temperature (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.32) and from 1997 to 2007 for annual precipitation (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.20); the distributions of trends (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S4</xref>) are significantly different from those of MBS (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1c</xref>). Furthermore, periods exhibiting high correlations are different between the datasets from refs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> for trends in both summer temperature and annual precipitation. This suggests that the spatial heterogeneity of climate change is not a major contributor to the spatial heterogeneity in glacier mass change. TECs were obtained from 2003–2008 data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>, and the highest correlations between TECs and trends in summer temperature and annual precipitation are found between the 1990s and 2007 suggesting temporal gaps between climate forcing and TECs. We find no significant correlation between TECs and trends in temperature or precipitation during the TEC analysis period. There might have been step-like fluctuations in temperature and/or precipitation before 2003, and then glaciers have responded with some delay.
</p>
