<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">We classified the MBS-TEC scatter plot (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>) into 10 sub-regions following ref.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>, as shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5</xref>. In Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5b</xref>, variability in TEC (vertical variability in the figure) with the same order of MBS could imply a local variability in climatic forcing. For instance, glaciers in East Nyainquentanglha Shan have dominantly large absolute MBS and TEC values compared to other regions. East Nyainquentanglha Shan receives high precipitation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>, and thus, the error in MBS might be large, as described previously. The difference in TECs between Karakoram and West Nepal can be explained with the difference in MBS (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5b</xref>). However, MBS values for the Everest region in Nepal, Pamir, and Hindu Kush are similar to those in Karakoram but the absolute values of TECs in the former regions are clearly greater than those in the latter. This difference may be due to the Karakoram glaciers having a relatively less negative mass change under favourable climate forcing that maintains the glaciers, such as cooling summer temperatures and/or increasing winter precipitation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>. Glaciers in the former regions show relatively rapid mass loss due to warming temperatures and/or decreasing summer precipitation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. The ‘Karakoram anomaly’ has drawn attention in the recent decade because glaciers in the Karakoram Range do not appear to follow general global warming trends. The MBS-TEC plot (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5b</xref>), however, shows that the Karakoram glaciers are not outliers. Therefore, we conclude that the Karakoram glaciers are not behaving anomalously; they have an insensitive MBS, and thus change their mass slightly due to local climatic forcing. Glaciers in the West Kunlun Shan-Tarim region also have less negative MBS values while their TECs are relatively less negative, even positive, compared to those in other regions with similar MBS values (e. g. the Everest region, East Pamir, and north-east margin of Spiti Lahaul). These results suggest that cooling temperatures and/or increasing precipitation might contribute to the slight mass gain in the West Kunlun Shan-Tarim region.
</p>
