<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Our multiple regression analysis reveals that the variance in MBS can be reduced by 69% with three explanatory variables: summer temperature, annual range of monthly temperature (temperature range), and ratio of summer precipitation (June-July-August) to annual (termed the summer precipitation ratio) (Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>). Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6</xref> and the determination coefficient with MBS (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>) clearly show the impact of each explanatory variable on MBS values. Summer temperature shows a relatively simple and higher correlation with MBS (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6b</xref>) while the summer precipitation ratio has a largely varying relationship with MBS (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6c</xref>). In Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6c</xref>, winter accumulation type glaciers (summer precipitation ratio &lt;50%) have no strong sensitivity (MBS) while summer accumulation type glaciers (summer precipitation ratio &gt;50%) have large variations in MBS. This difference is likely due to summer accumulation type glaciers having large variability in summer temperature (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3d</xref>), which has the strongest impact on MBS. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3a–c</xref> show the area of each explanatory factor that corresponds to weaker (less negative) MBS; the relationships between MBS and explanatory factors are depicted in Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6</xref>. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3d</xref> shows that these overlapping areas with weak MBS tend to coincide with regions with small TEC, such as Karakoram and West Kunlun Shan (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a and b</xref>). Conversely, regions with little or no overlap between the areas of weak MBS tend to show larger TEC, such as the Hengduan Shan, Bhutan, and western Nepal Himalayas (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3d</xref>). We conclude that climatic settings represented by the three factors, summer temperature, temperature range, and summer precipitation ratio, are the dominant control on heterogeneous mass balance sensitivity (MBS) and, consequently, the spatially contrasting mass change in Asian glaciers. 
</p>
