<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The indirect exposure and sensitivity factors were combined and weighted by direct exposure to generate a continuous climate change vulnerability index value for each species (for full detail see: [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]). For this purpose scores of each factor (those comprising indirect exposure and sensitivity) were translated into a numerical value (DV = -2, SDV = -1, N = 0, SIV = 1, IV = 2, GIV = 3), where multiple categories were scored as an average of the two categories used. The numerical value for each factor was then multiplied by an index of direct exposure to climate change based on the proportion of the species’ geographic distribution exposed to different magnitudes of changing mean annual temperature and mean annual moisture index ([
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], 
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>). The values for each factor were then summed to produce the overall index value. The NatureServe approach assigns the final numerical score to a category of climate change vulnerability (eg. moderately vulnerable). However, we here used the underlying continuous values to allow a finer grained analysis. The final index value therefore integrates information on (i) sensitivity, as estimated from biological traits, (ii) indirect exposure to climate change, as estimated from the spatial overlap between the species’ distribution and three indirect exposure factors (natural barriers, anthropogenic barriers and sea-level rise), and (iii) direct exposure to climate change as estimated from climate projections within the geographic distribution of the species. Species that have both high sensitivity and high exposure to rapid climate change ultimately score as the most climate change vulnerable. Sparse information often limited the number of factors that we could assess, but a minimum of 13 out of the 20 sensitivity and indirect exposure factors is required by the NatureServe index to estimate overall vulnerability ([
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]; the factors we used are listed in 
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Sufficient information was available for 213 out of the 232 species initially selected (
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2 Dataset</xref>). The NatureServe approach focuses on the intrinsic traits and physiological characteristics of a species and does not include geographic range size or anthropogenic threats to the species. This renders the index comparable among species with differing conservation status or geographic range size.
</p>
