<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CMIP5 model-projected changes</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CMIP5 model-simulated Arctic warming and sea-ice loss vary greatly with month in the 21st and 22nd centuries, but not in the 23rd century when most of the sea ice is melted away (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). During the 21st century, large sea-ice loss (&gt;20% of the Arctic area) occurs from June to January, but large AA exists only from October to April, peaking in November–December (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). Reduced SIC allows the Arctic Ocean to absorb more sunlight from April to August (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>), but this extra energy is stored in the upper Arctic Ocean without increasing the surface temperatures substantially due to the large heat capacity of the ocean mixed layer. This results in small changes in LW_up and SH + LH fluxes and negligible AA for the summer months, consistent with the recent changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). This result suggests that when the Arctic Ocean is a heat sink from May to August (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5a</a>), all the surface and atmospheric changes (including increased LW heating from increased water vapor and clouds, Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>) cannot produce AA during those months. However, from October to March when the Arctic Ocean becomes a heat source to the atmosphere (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5a</a>), the extra energy stored in the ocean is released through surface upward LW radiation, LH and SH fluxes to heat the lower troposphere, thereby enhancing the Arctic warming during these months (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>), as LW radiation and SH directly warm the lower troposphere while LH increases water vapor and thus its greenhouse warming effect on the surface. This key role by surface LW, LH, and SH fluxes is consistent with that seen during the recent decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Clearly, whether an area is covered by sea ice during the cold season makes a huge difference for these surface fluxes, and this is why sea-ice loss can greatly enhance the warming induced by CO
  <sub>2</sub> and water vapor increases.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Centennial changes as a function of month from CMIP5 models. For Arctic (67°−90°N) sea-ice concerntraion (SIC, in % of Arctic area, shading, multiplied by −1), Arctic-to-global ratio of the Tas change (AA, black line, multiplied by 10 in order to use the left y-axis), and Arctic surface energy fluxes (in W m
     <span class="sup">−2</span>). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> 2070–2099 minus 1970–1999, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> 2170–2199 minus 2070–2099, and 
     <span class="bold">c</span> 2270–2299 minus 2170–2199 under the historical and RCP85 scenarios from the ensemble mean of nine model runs from the nine CMIP5 models. Net SW = net shortwave radiation (positive downard), upward LW = upward longwave radiation, SH = sensible heat, LH = latent heat. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Time-dependent warming and sea-ice loss from CMIP5 models. Time series of the difference between the 20 year periods separated by the plotted year in annual Arctic (67°−90°N, red solid) and global-mean (red dashed) surface air temperature (Tas), annual Arctic SIC (blue), and the difference between the red solid and red dashed lines (black) based on the ensemble mean of nine simulations from nine CMIP5 models. The correlation coefficient between the lines are: r (SIC, Tas_Arctic) = −0.97, r (sic,Tas_global) = −0.90, r (sic,Tas_diff) = −0.95, and r (sic, AA) = −0.80, where AA = the ratio of the Arctic to global Tas change (data before 2000 were not used for AA). These correlations have a 
     <span class="italic">p</span>-value well below 0.01
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7954_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e629" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Dependence of Arctic warming and amplification on sea-ice loss among 38 CMIP5 models. Scatter plot of 2070–2099 minus 1970–1999 difference under the RCP85 scenario between annual Arctic SIC loss and Arctic surface warming (red), Arctic-minus-global warming difference (blue), or the Arctic-to-global warming ratio (i.e., the Arctic amplification, or AA, black). Each dot is for one CMIP5 model. Correlation coefficients: r(SIC, dTas_Arctic) = 0.87 (
     <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.00), r(SIC, Tas_diff) = 0.84 (=0.00), and r (SIC, AA) = 0.54 (
     <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.01)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7954_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e644" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By the end of the 21st century, Arctic sea ice is largely gone from July to October (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5b</a>). As a result, the largest sea-ice loss in the 22nd century occurs from December to June, and the largest increases in the absorbed SW radiation are from April to June (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). Again, this extra energy is stored in the Arctic Ocean with negligible amplification of surface warming during these months (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). As the Arctic sea ice continues to decline during the cold season (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>), more ocean surfaces are ice-free and open to the atmosphere. Because the newly exposed ocean water is much warmer than the cold sea-ice surface existed previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, this allows the ocean to release more LH and SH fluxes and LW radiation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>) to warm the lower troposphere from November to March, when the ocean is still a seasonal heat source to the atmosphere (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5b</a>). The largest release of the extra LW, LH, and SH is delayed to January–February by the end of 22nd century from November to December in the 21st century as the maximum sea-ice loss moves to latter months (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a, b</a>). This results in elevated Arctic warming and thus large AA from November to March, whereas the AA is small for the other months (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the 23rd century, sea ice forms only over a small area (&lt;20%) of the Arctic Ocean even during the cold season (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5c, d</a>). Thus, there is no significant sea-ice loss for most of the months except for January–May when small (3–10%) losses still occur (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>). Because of this, absorbed solar radiation changes little, as do the surface LH and SH fluxes; while the upward LW increases uniformly throughout the year due to the overall surface warming (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>). Without the extra heating from the ocean (on top of the mean seasonal cycle, Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5c, d</a>), the Arctic warming during the 23rd century shows little seasonal variation, and it is only about 40–50% higher than the global warming rate for all the months (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>), which is comparable to the AA during the summer in previous centuries (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a, b</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We further calculated the local change between two moving 20-yr periods for Arctic annual SIC, Arctic and global-mean annual Tas, and the Arctic-minus-global warming difference (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>). Clearly, the elevated warming over the Arctic is strongly correlated with sea-ice loss (r = 0.95) for all the 40-yr periods within 1900–2300. As the Arctic sea-ice loss increases from the 1950s to the 2060 s, the Arctic-minus-global warming difference also increases; thereafter, the warming difference decreases as the sea-ice loss slows down due to reduced SIC (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>). After year 2200, there is little sea-ice left to melt, and the warming difference is small between the Arctic and the globe. In contrast, from 1980–2020 when the global warming rate is similar to that of 2200–2280, the Arctic warms much faster than the global-mean as the sea-ice loss is much larger during 1980–2020 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also found a strong correlation (r = 0.84) between the Arctic sea-ice loss and Arctic-minus-global warming difference from 1979 to 1999 and from 2070 to 2099 among the 38 CMIP5 models we analyzed (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>); that is, models with a larger sea-ice loss tend to produce larger AA in the 21st century under the RCP8.5 scenario. Since the current SIC determines how much sea ice is available for future melting, this result suggests that the magnitude of a model-simulated Arctic warming and AA will depend on its mean bias in SIC (and thus also Tas) for the current climate, consistent with previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strong spatial pattern correlations were also found between Arctic sea-ice loss and surface warming and changes in surface energy fluxes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>), consistent with recent observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). For example, large surface warming and large increases in LH and SH (and LW_up) fluxes in December are collocated with large sea-ice loss in both the 21st and 22nd centuries (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>), while the enhanced warming largely disappears in the 23rd century when the sea ice is gone (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). Without a central role of sea-ice loss, it would be difficult to think of any mechanism for reduced LW cooling due to a stable temperature profile
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>, increased LW heating from increased water vapor and clouds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, increased poleward heat transport
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, or other processes to generate such a spatial pattern of surface warming that resembles that of sea-ice loss and then their effects disappear in the 23rd century when there is little sea-ice loss. While enhanced local warming can increase sea-ice loss and thus cause a negative correlation between the SIC and Tas change, the warming pattern itself cannot be easily explained by the LW- and heat transport-related mechanisms without a key role of the sea-ice loss. This is because the large-scale downward LW forcing (from increased CO
  <sub>2</sub>, water vapor, or clouds) should not be correlated spatially with SIC loss unless there exists a major role by the sea-ice loss to alter the surface warming and water vapor (and thus LW) change patterns. In other words, if SIC does not play a major role, then the warming pattern should be fairly uniform (as CO
  <sub>2</sub> and water vapor in the Arctic would be well mixed zonally by the large-scale circulation if local processes played a minimal role), or spatially correlated with cloudiness changes rather than with SIC loss. Thus, while increased downward LW radiation associated with increased CO
  <sub>2</sub> and water vapor may play a large role for overall Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span> and global
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> warming, it cannot produce the enhanced warming collocated with sea-ice loss and existed primarily only during the cold season that leads to large AA only in the cold season. However, a general Arctic warming, either due to increased CO
  <sub>2</sub>, water vapor, or clouds, can indirectly contribute to AA through melting of sea ice.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Centennial changes from CMIP5 models. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> from 1970–1999 to 2070–2099 and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> from 2070–2099 to 2170–2199. Shown are changes in December sea-ice concentration (SIC, %, color shading), air temperature (Tas, °C, red contours, interval = 2), and latent and sensible heat fluxes (LH + SH, W m
     <span class="sup">−2</span>, yellow contours, interval = 10). Dashed contours are for negative values. Based on the ensemble mean of nine simulations from nine CMIP5 models under the historical and RCP85 scenarios. The spatial pattern correlations are: r (SIC, Tas) = −0.79, r (SIC, LH + SH) = −0.68, r (Tas, LH + SH) = 0.62 in 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, and r(SIC, Tas) = −0.85, r (SIC,LH + SH) = −0.65, r (Tas, LH + SH) = 0.60 in 
     <span class="bold">b</span>. Surface net energy flux change (not shown) is similarly correlated with the SIC and Tas changes, while the upward LW flux change (not shown) is highly correlated (r≈0.90) with the Tas change. These correlations have a 
     <span class="italic">p</span>-value well below 0.01
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7954_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e823" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, the increased LW_up, SH, and LH heating by the newly opened Arctic waters (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>) should increase lower tropospheric temperature and water vapor, and possibly cloud cover as well (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>) over and around the areas with sea-ice loss. These atmospheric changes, triggered by the extra surface heating induced by sea-ice loss and enhanced by the local positive water vapor feedback, result in increased downward LW radiation (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>) as noticed previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, which in turn helps maintain and enhance an elevated surface temperature over the newly opened waters. In turn, the enhanced warming should accelerate the sea-ice loss, leading to a positive feedback loop. The stable Arctic atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> may also allow the extra surface heating to generate large warming in the lower troposphere by reducing LW cooling to space
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. However, the fact that the AA becomes much smaller in the 23rd century (October–April mean Arctic to global warming ratio = 1.47) than that in the 21st (2.97) and 22nd (2.40) century (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) suggests that the LW, latent and sensible heating due to sea-ice loss is essential for large AA to occur, while all the other processes can only modulate the sea-ice loss-induced amplification or indirectly contribute to AA by causing sea-ice melting, but they cannot cause large AA without sea-ice loss.
 </p>
</sec>
