<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CMIP5 simulations</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The monthly model data were obtained from 38 historical (1900 to 2005) and RCP8.5 (2006 to 2100) simulations from 38 CMIP5 models
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span> (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cmip-pcmdi.llnl.gov/cmip5/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cmip-pcmdi.llnl.gov/cmip5/index.html</span>). Only nine of the models had simulations extended to 2300 under the extended RCP8.5 scenario
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span>. These are bcc-csm1-1, CCSM4, CNRM-CM5, CSIRO-Mk3-6-0, GISS-E2-H, GISS-E2-R, HadGEM2-ES, IPSL-CM5A-LR, and MPI-ESM-LR. The surface warming pattern and magnitude from 1970 to 1999 and from 2070 to 2099 are comparable between the 38-model ensemble mean and the 9-model ensemble mean, suggesting that the 9-model ensemble is a reasonable representation of the larger CMIP5 model ensemble. The recent mean annual cycles of the SIC and surface energy fluxes from the 9-model ensemble (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5a</a>) are comparable with the 38 CMIP5 models (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1b</a>) and ERA-40 reanalysis data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span> (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1a</a>). The SIC data were remapped onto a 1° grid, and all the other fields were remapped onto a 2.5° grid using a conservative mapping scheme. They were then averaged over the models (one simulation for each model) with equal weighting to create the ensemble mean, whose long-term changes were analyzed here to represent the response to future external forcing under the RCP8.5 scenario. Thus, the analyses presented here focus on the GHG-forced long-term response, not the short-term variations and decadal changes caused by internal climate variability that is a major component in recent observed changes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. Also, we did not examine the causes of sea-ice loss; but for the ensemble mean, the sea-ice retreat is primarily associated with GHG-induced surface warming: as the near-surface temperature increases to above the freezing point for a given month, sea ice starts to melt away (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>). Thus, the warming triggered by the increasing GHGs and enhanced by water vapor and other feedbacks (including the warming due to sea-ice loss) is the main cause of the sea-ice loss.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CESM1 simulations</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the Community Earth System Model version 1 (CESM1) from NCAR
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span> with the CAM4 option for its atmospheric component to make two multi-century simulations plus a 150-year pre-industrial control run. The CESM1 is a widely used fully coupled climate model that simulates the Arctic SIC and climate realistically (Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1c</a> and 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2c, d</a>). The CESM1 was run with grid spacing of 2.5° lon × ~2.0° lat for the atmospheric model, and ~1.0° lon × ~0.5° lat for the sea-ice and ocean models. The three simulations include a pre-industrial control (CTL) run with CO
   <sub>2</sub> fixed at 284.7 ppmv for 150 years, a standard 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run with fully coupled dynamic sea ice and a 1%-per-year increase in atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> for 235 years reaching 10.36 times of the pre-industrial CO
   <sub>2</sub> level, and a fixed sea-ice (FixedIce) run. The FixedIce run is the same as the standard 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run except that all the internally calculated ice–atmosphere, ice–ocean, and ocean–atmosphere fluxes north of 30°N were applied to the sea-ice fractional areas temporally interpolated from the monthly climatology of the CTL run, in contrast to the standard 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run in which these fluxes were applied only to the ice faction existed at the time in the model. Over a small fraction of the Arctic sea-ice area north of 30°N (mainly along the sea-ice margins at lower latitudes, Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>), where sea ice melted away completely (mainly in the latter part of the simulation) and thus the ice model did not calculate these fluxes, the monthly climatology of these fluxes from the CTL run was temporally interpolated and applied to the CTL SIC fraction of these small areas, except for surface absorbed shortwave (SW) radiation which was calculated using the CTL albedo values and model-internally calculated downward SW radiation. The CTL ice-atmosphere fluxes (including LH, SH, evaporation, upward LW radiation, and surface stress) and ice-ocean fluxes (including heat, salt, freshwater, SW radiation, and stress fluxes) did not account for internal changes in surface temperatures and other fields, and therefore they could potentially suppress long-term changes in the Arctic if applied widely. For example, the upward LW radiation from the CTL run lacked the increasing trend associated with surface warming and therefore could weaken the Arctic warming in the lower troposphere. However, because the use of the CTL fluxes occurred only over a very small fraction of the total sea-ice area along the initial ice margins where SIC was low to start with (i.e., SIC was low in the CTL run for the small number of grid cells where the CTL fluxes were applied to the low SIC fraction; Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>), the effect of this deficiency is likely to be small. The difference between the standard 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> and FixedIce runs comes mainly from the application of the internally calculated fluxes over a fixed sea-ice cover from the control run in the FixedIce experiment.
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the FixedIce run, the coupler and the atmospheric and ocean components in the CESM1 only saw the fixed sea-ice cover interpolated from the CTL run north of the 30°N; the sea-ice fraction inside the sea-ice model was allowed to evolve dynamically with the fluxes returned from the coupler. Thus, the above changes made in the FixedIce run would also affect the rate of sea-ice loss through the modification to the surface fluxes.</p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our main intervention of the fully coupled system in the FixedIce run is the application of the internally calculated fluxes over a fixed sea-ice cover from the CTL run (instead of only over the ice cover existed at the time inside the sea-ice model). A secondary intervention was the use of CTL surface fluxes (instead of letting the coupler to calculate them for a water surface) over the low SIC fraction in a small number of the grid cells that initially contained sea-ice but the sea ice melted away completely. This use of the CTL fluxes was not ideal but necessary because (1) the sea-ice model did not calculate surface fluxes for grid cells without any ice, (2) the internally calculated surface temperature over these grid cells is for water surfaces and thus can’t be used directly as the surface temperature for ice surfaces; and (3) the calculations of surface fluxes over sea-ice were complicated.</p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CTL fluxes contained only an annual cycle and were seen by the atmosphere and ocean component models; they along should not cause any long-term trends and are balanced out on an annual mean sense when applied to the small areas where ice was melted away completely (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>). That is, they should not violate the internal water and energy balance on an annual-mean basis, although they may slightly alter these balances on shorter time scales over the small number of grid cells (north of 30°N) where sea ice had melted away completely. This is much better than re-setting the ice cover to the CTL climatology after each time step, since that would provide an infinite source of ice for melting, leading to an infinite heat sink and freshwater source for the oceans. Our approach here focused on the effects on the climate (including sea ice itself) of a fixed sea-ice cover through its impact on surface fluxes; it differs from Deser et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>, who used an artificial LW forcing to maintain a constant sea-ice cover in a warming experiment, and Blackport and Kushner
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
   </span>, who modified ice–albedo to study the impact of sea-ice loss on the climate system.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Top-of-atmosphere (TOA) and surface energy fluxes in the CESM1 runs</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To verify that the imposed sea-ice and flux changes to the FixedIce run did not cause major artifacts in this simulation, here we examine and compare the TOA and surface energy flux changes in the CESM1 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> and FixedIce runs.
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a> shows the time series of the global-mean and Arctic-mean changes in the TOA and surface net energy fluxes from the two simulations. Over the Arctic (67°–90°N), the TOA fluxes are very similar for the two runs, while the net surface flux into the Arctic Ocean is substantially smaller in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run than in the FixedIce run (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10b</a>). This is expected because the use of the fixed sea-ice concentration (SIC) in the FixedIce run reduces the upward longwave (LW) radiation and sensible and latent heat fluxes (Figs. 
   <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7,</a>
   <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a> and Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">18</a>, 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">19</a>) and therefore should lead to a larger downward net flux in the FixedIce run. Thus, the Arctic surface flux difference shown in Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10b</a> is what we should expect physically from the change we imposed, whose impact on the Arctic TOA flux is negligible. Because of this, the small difference in the global-mean TOA flux between the two runs after year ~100 (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10a</a>) is likely due to other changes outside the Arctic region, rather than the direct effect of the imposed SIC change in the Arctic. Noticeable differences exist only after about year 100 in the global-mean fluxes between the two runs, and the TOA-minus-surface flux difference is similar between the two runs throughout the whole simulations (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10a</a>). Thus, the global-mean and Arctic-mean TOA and surface net fluxes from the two runs are reasonable.
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the spatial patterns, we compare the change patterns between the two runs for the TOA and surface net energy fluxes in Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a> and 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>, respectively. Again, the TOA flux changes are similar in the two runs, with noticeably higher downward TOA net fluxes over most of the Arctic Ocean in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11e</a>) than in the FixedIce run (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11f</a>) at the time of the 3rd CO
   <sub>2</sub> doubling (mainly due to increased absorption of solar radiation in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run), except over the areas with large SIC decreases in the FixedIce run by the 3rd CO
   <sub>2</sub> doubling (see Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11,</a>
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13</a>). Examination of the changes in the outgoing longwave radiation (OLR) and TOA net shortwave (SW) radiation (not shown) revealed that the increase in the Arctic TOA net flux is mainly due to the large increase in the absorbed SW radiation that exceeds the increase in OLR in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run, while it is mainly due to the reduced OLR (as surface upward LW radiation is reduced) as the albedo and thus SW changes are small in the FixedIce run. Thus, these TOA flux changes are expected physically based on the imposed the changes.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the surface net energy flux (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>), the broad change patterns are similar between the two runs over most of the globe, except the Arctic where the fixed SIC in the FixedIce run is expected to reduce the absorbed SW radiation, upward LW radiation, and surface sensible (SH) and latent (LH) heat fluxes in comparison with the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run (see Figs. 
   <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>, 
   <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a> and Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">18</a>, 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">19</a>). These reductions in upward fluxes lead to higher downward net energy fluxes in the FiexedIce run than in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> over the Arctic Ocean (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>). Further examination revealed that surface downward SW radiation is reduced over the Arctic due to increased cloudiness in both simulations (Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">14,</a>
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">15</a>); however, due to reduced sea-ice cover in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13</a>), surface absorbed SW radiation is actually increased despite the decreased downward SW radiation in this run (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">16a, b, e</a>). Because of the use of ice–albedo from fixed SIC in calculating the SW flux, the reduced downward SW radiation leads to decreased absorbed SW radiation in the FixedIce run (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">16b, d, f</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the fixed sea-ice cover reduces upward LW radiation, surface net LW radiative heating increases more in the FixedIce run than in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run in the Arctic (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17</a>). On the other hand, the surface LH (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">18</a>) and SH (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">19</a>) heat fluxes increase substantially only in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run over the Arctic, and they partially offset the large increases in the absorbed SW radiation (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">16e</a>) and the moderate increase in the net LW radiative heating (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17e</a>) over the Arctic in the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run, which results in only moderate changes in the net surface energy flux (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12e</a>). This differs from the FixedIce run, in which the changes in the LH and SH fluxes are small (Supplementary Figures 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17f</a>, 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S18f</a>), and the net surface energy flux change (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12f</a>) results mainly from the reduced net SW (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">16f</a>) and greatly increased net LW (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17f</a>) fluxes. These changes in the FixedIce run happened over most of the Arctic, not just over the sea-ice margins (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>) where the control-run fluxes might be used. Thus, these changes are mainly due to the use of the fixed SIC in calculating the surface fluxes, rather than due to the use of the control-run fluxes over a few areas around the original sea-ice margins. This further demonstrates that the use of the fixed SIC, rather than the use of the control-run fluxes, is the main reason behind these differences between the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> and FixedIce runs. These analyses of the TOA and surface fluxes also suggest that there are no major artifacts resulting from the imposed changes in the FixedIce run.
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Please note that we have provided several lines of evidence, besides using the 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> minus FixedIce difference, to support our conclusion that sea-ice loss is necessary for large AA to occur. These include the diminishing AA in the 23rd century in the CMIP5 models (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) and in the CESM1 standard 1% CO
   <sub>2</sub> run (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7d</a>) when Arctic sea-ice melting becomes small. Another evidence is the strong correlation between Arctic sea-ice loss and the AA among the 38 CMIP5 models during the 21st century (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), and the spatial and seasonal relationship between Arctic warming and sea-ice loss (and the associated surface energy flux changes). Thus, while the results from the FixedIce experiment provide a strong confirmation of the essential role of sea-ice loss, they represent only one of the several lines of evidence presented in the paper.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ERA-Interim reanalysis data</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the historical changes from 1979 to 2016 (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a, b</a>), we used the 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ecmwf.int/en/forecasts/datasets/archive-datasets/reanalysis-datasets/era-interim" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ERA-Interim reanalysis data</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>, which capture the historical SIC seasonal cycle and changes fairly realistically, although the mean SIC is somewhat lower than satellite observations from NOAA (Supplementary Figure 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). The ERA-Interim data have been used to study Arctic climate and SIC change in many previous studies;
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span> they arguably represent one of our best datasets available for the Arctic region.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Code availability</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The code of the CESM1 model used here is available from 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.2/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/models/cesm1.2/</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
