<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Prairie Pothole Region (PPR) is an extensive freshwater wetland ecoregion in North America that hosts numerous breeding wetland‐dependent bird species, including waterfowl species that have made the region a focus for conservation and management efforts (Doherty, Ryba, Stemler, Niemuth, &amp; Meeks, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Ringelman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Steen, Skagen, &amp; Melcher, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). This region is characterized by high climatic variability across years, and periods of drought or excessive precipitation may extend over multiyear periods. We obtained species occurrence (presence and absence) data from the North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS; Sauer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) for our focal species for the U.S. portion of the PPR in North Dakota, South Dakota, and Minnesota (See Fig. 
 <xref rid="ece33403-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="ece33403-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref> in Supporting Information). We included land cover covariates to associate with BBS routes that described wetland and upland coverages. We estimated models based on observed climatic conditions (Maurer, Brekke, Pruitt, &amp; Duffy, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). To assess climate change impacts we compared future distributions under forecasted climate to distributions under simulated past climate (“hindcast”), an approach that avoids conflating climate model biases with the impacts of climate change (Sofaer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Climate forecasts and hindcasts were obtained from 10 randomly selected CMIP5 GCMs under Representative Concentration Pathway 8.5 (See Fig. 
 <xref rid="ece33403-sup-0004" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref> in Supporting Information). Hydrological data were output from a macroscale hydrologic model (Liang, Lettenmaier, Wood, &amp; Burges, 
 <xref rid="ece33403-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>). Additional information on the Prairie Pothole ecosystem, the study area, and BBS, land cover and climate data sources are in Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece33403-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref> in Supporting Information.
</p>
