<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
 <p class="p">We thank Dr. Yuanyuan Fang, Department of Global Ecology, Carnegie Institution For Science, Stanford University for her advice in key areas. All authors acknowledge the UK research councils Living with Environmental Change (LWEC) program for funding and Dr. Sari Kovats, Faculty of Public Health and Policy, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine and LWEC fellow, for guidance and advice. RMD and MRH also acknowledge the cross UK-research councils Environmental Exposure and Human Health Initiative grant NE/I008063/1. FMO’C is also supported by the Joint UK DECC/Defra Met Office Hadley Centre Climate Programme (GA01101).</p>
 <p class="p">This paper is an updated and reduced version of a technical paper provided in support of a Health Report Card produced for the UK Living With Environmental Change (LWEC) Network.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Funding</title>
  <p id="Par42" class="p">Publication of this article was funded by the UK Living With Environmental Change (LWEC) Network. LWEC was succeeded in 2016 by the Research and Innovation for our Dynamic Environment (RIDE) Forum (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nerc.ac.uk/research/partnerships/ride" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nerc.ac.uk/research/partnerships/ride/</ext-link>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="Par43" class="p">Not Applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
  <title class="title">About this supplement</title>
  <p id="Par44" class="p">This article has been published as part of Environmental Health Volume 16 Supplement 1, 2017: Special Issue on the impact of climate change on health in the UK. The full contents of the supplement are available online at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ehjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/supplements/volume-16-supplement-1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://ehjournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/supplements/volume-16-supplement-1</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</ack>
