<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative Genetic Analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenotypic trait variances can be separated into genetic and environmental causes of variation using an “animal model” 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Charmantier3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Charmantier3">[44]</a>–
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Kruuk3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Kruuk3">[46]</a>. By maximizing the information available in an extensive multi-generational pedigree, the “animal model” minimizes upward inflation of estimates of additive genetic variance (V
  <sub>A</sub>) due to shared environmental effects between relatives; this approach has been shown in simulation studies to perform well in partitioning environmental and genetic components of variance 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Kruuk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Kruuk1">[29]</a>. There are several additional reasons to believe that the genetic and environmental components have been well separated here. First, a previous study found no indication that common environment effects in the form of maternal effects are important for laying date in this population (V
  <sub>M</sub>/V
  <sub>P</sub>  = 0.0023 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Henderson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Henderson1">[47]</a>). Second, although common environmental effects frequently play a major role in inflating covariances between relatives in nestling traits 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Postma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Postma1">[48]</a>, this is rarely the case for traits that are only expressed as adults, like laying date which we study here. Third, we explicitly take common environmental effects into account by fitting a permanent environmental effect 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Lynch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Lynch1">[45]</a>. In summary, therefore, we believe that our estimates of V
  <sub>A</sub> and h
  <span class="sup">2</span> are accurate and unbiased by inflation of common environment effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rather than only estimating the amount of genetic and environmental variance in laying date, we are interested here in whether the variance components changed with environmental conditions, and we therefore used a “random regression animal model” 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Meril3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Meril3">[49]</a>. Random regression models use covariance functions 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Meyer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Meyer1">[50]</a> to explicitly fit variance components as a function of the environment and hence allow a detailed examination of how environmental heterogeneity—in this case, spring temperature—influences genetic architecture. Thus our model was:
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="pbio.1000585.e001.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <span class="label">(1)</span>
  </div>where 
  <span class="bold">LD</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span> is the vector of the individual (
  <span class="italic">i</span>) laying dates and 
  <span class="bold">X, Z
   <sub>1</sub>, Z
   <sub>2</sub>
  </span>, and 
  <span class="bold">Z
   <sub>3</sub>
  </span> are the design and incidence matrices relating to the fixed and random effects of the additive genetic (
  <span class="bold">a</span>
  <sub>i</sub>), permanent environment (
  <span class="bold">pe</span>
  <sub>i</sub>), and year (
  <span class="bold">yr</span>
  <sub>i</sub>) observations, respectively. T is the spring temperature each year standardized to a (−1, 1) interval (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1000585.s002" href="#pbio.1000585.s002">Table S2</a>). Fixed effects (
  <span class="bold">b</span>
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span>
  </span> vector) included age as a two-level factor (first year breeder or older), to correct for the fact that laying date is generally later in young birds compared to older birds in great tits 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Kirkpatrick1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Kirkpatrick1">[51]</a>, and spring temperature to account for the population-level response in mean trait value. Year (
  <span class="bold">yr</span> vector) was included as a random effect in order to model variation between years not explained by spring temperature and a permanent environment effect (
  <span class="bold">pe</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span> vector) was fitted because of the repeated sampling of the same individuals; this also reduces inflation of estimates of the additive genetic variance due to environmental factors 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Kruuk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Kruuk1">[29]</a>. The error term (
  <span class="bold">e</span> vector) was partitioned into three decade–specific (1973–1984, 1985–1996, 1997–2007) groups, thus allowing residual errors to vary between decades. ϕ(
  <span class="bold">a</span>
  <sub>i</sub>,n
  <sub>1</sub>,T) is the random regression function of order n
  <sub>1</sub> of the additive genetic effect of individual 
  <span class="italic">i</span>, which varies as a function of the temperature T in a given year, and similarly, ϕ(
  <span class="bold">pe</span>
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span>,n
  <sub>2</sub>,T), is the random regression function of order n
  <sub>2</sub> of the permanent environment effect varying as a function of T.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because we were only interested in whether the two variance components (and particularly V
  <sub>A</sub>) changed with the environment, we only fitted two models. The first model was a zero order function (n
  <sub>1</sub> = n
  <sub>2</sub> = 0) for both V
  <sub>A</sub> and V
  <sub>PE</sub> in which variance components are constant across the environment. In the second model, we fitted a first order polynomial (n
  <sub>1</sub> = n
  <sub>2</sub> = 1) for both V
  <sub>A</sub> and V
  <sub>PE</sub>, thus allowing both additive genetic effects and permanent environment effects, and hence their corresponding variance components, to vary across the environment T. These two models were then compared using a likelihood-ratio test by calculating twice the difference in log likelihood, which is chi-squared distributed with degrees of freedom equal to the difference in degrees of freedom between the two models 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Wilkin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Wilkin1">[52]</a>, which is here equal to 4 (variance in slopes and covariance between elevation and slope for both V
  <sub>A</sub> and V
  <sub>PE</sub>). As the model where both variance components were allowed to vary was significantly better than a model in which they were assumed to be constant (see 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s2" href="#s2">Results</a>) we used the estimates from the first order polynomial model to generate predictions of annual values of V
  <sub>A</sub> (and V
  <sub>PE</sub>) across varying temperatures. The environment-specific additive genetic covariance matrix, 
  <span class="bold">G</span>, was then obtained as 
  <span class="bold">G</span>  =  
  <span class="bold">zQz</span>
  <span class="sup">T</span>, where 
  <span class="bold">z</span> is the vector of orthogonal polynomials evaluated at standardized temperature values and 
  <span class="bold">Q</span> is the additive genetic variance-covariance matrix of the random regression parameters. Approximate standard errors for the (co)variance components of 
  <span class="bold">G</span> as a function of the temperature values were calculated according to Fischer et al. 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Gienapp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Gienapp1">[22]</a>, with confidence intervals defined as twice the standard errors. Finally, environment-specific heritability estimates were calculated as the environment-specific V
  <sub>A</sub> estimate divided by the environment-specific V
  <sub>P</sub> estimate from the model in which both V
  <sub>A</sub> and V
  <sub>PE</sub> varied with the environment. Because it has been found that random regression models can be sensitive to “edge effects” 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Gienapp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Gienapp1">[22]</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Pinheiro1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Pinheiro1">[53]</a>, we repeated our analyses where we look at the association between strength of selection and expression of genetic variance to be conservative. For more information about the use of random regression animal models in natural populations, see 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Husby1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Husby1">[18]</a> and 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-Wilson2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-Wilson2">[54]</a>. All animal models were fitted using REML methods implemented in ASReml v 2.0 
  <a rid="pbio.1000585-vanBalen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1000585-vanBalen1">[38]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
