<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The control sections were situated upstream of the manipulated sections with buffer areas in‐between (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33973-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Flooding was created by constructing dams in the streams to obstruct the water flow in the main channels. In Denmark, a lateral dam made of sandbags was established across the stream channel (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33973-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>a), while in Germany and the Netherlands, longitudinal dams were built within the channel, which together with a lateral dam across the channel obstructed the water flow in the main channel (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33973-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b). The constructed dams were used to create a 6‐week flooding of the adjacent riparian areas (from March to mid‐April) in 2011, 2012, and 2013, where the strongest responses were expected to occur in the final year of sampling given that the areas have been subject to manipulation for several years. However, in 2013, flooding was delayed in Denmark due to ice cover and lasted from the end of April to mid‐June. In Denmark, summer droughts were created by digging a ditch, which together with a lateral dam in the main channel diverted part of the water flow from the main channel, resulting in a lowered water table within the experimental areas (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33973-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>a). In Germany and the Netherlands, a longitudinal dam was constructed across the stream channel, which together with a lateral dam across the channel obstructed the water flow adjacent to the experimental area, thereby lowering the water table (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33973-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b). The drought experiment was conducted in 2011, 2012, and 2013 from the end of June to September (approximately 10 weeks) at all sites except Boye where strong groundwater seepage prevented reduction in the water table in the drought section.
</p>
