<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39" class="p">The ITCZ is narrower than the neighboring subsiding regions of the Hadley circulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>] and is a region of widespread moist convection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" class="xref">116</xref>]. Consequently, theories for the area fraction of moist convection have potential relevance for the ITCZ width. Bjerknes (1938) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>] used a thermodynamic argument based on dry and saturated moist adiabatic lapse rates to argue that moist convection tends to occupy an updraft region that is narrow relative to the downdraft region, although he neglected temperature tendencies due to radiative and surface fluxes. Later, analytical and idealized-modeling studies of the Walker circulation found that the area of ascending motion depends upon the SST gradient, the gross moist stability,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2" class="xref">2</xref> cloud-radiative feedbacks and atmosphere-ocean coupling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" class="xref">119</xref>]. Following these studies that considered the convective area fraction quite generally, various idealized-modeling studies noted a dependence of ITCZ width on the dynamical core and model resolution [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" class="xref">120</xref>], the convective parameterization [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>], the strength of horizontal diffusion of moisture [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>], the radiative effects of clouds and water vapor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" class="xref">121</xref>], and the longwave optical thickness [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. It is clear from these idealized models, and indeed from observations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>] and comprehensive models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>], that the ITCZ width is influenced by a variety of climate processes.
</p>
