<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 3</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Projection of decreased response to a diabatic equatorial Atlantic heating.</title>
  <p class="p">Multimodel (the 17 selected models) average of boreal summer (JJA0) regression of equatorial (10°S to 10°N) vertical atmospheric velocity (pascals per second; color) and equatorial atmospheric flow vectors (zonal wind and vertical velocity scaled by a factor of 300) onto the Atl-EOF index of the present-day (1900–1999) (
   <bold class="bold">A</bold>) and future (2000–2099) (
   <bold class="bold">B</bold>) 100-year periods. Values exceeding 1 SD are shown in shaded contour and black vectors. The color map and reference vector are labeled in the middle of (A) and (B). (
   <bold class="bold">C</bold>) Comparison of vertical velocity response to the Atl-EOF index over the present-day (blue bars) and future (orange bars) 100-year periods in the 17 selected models. The three models that simulate an increase in response are marked in gray. Error bars in the multimodel mean are calculated as 2 SDs (the 95% confidence interval based on normal distribution) of the 10,000 inter-realizations of a bootstrap method (see “Bootstrap test” section in Materials and Methods). The vertical velocity response is measured by the regression coefficients (pascals per second per SD) of the JJA0 vertical velocity anomalies at 600 hPa averaged over the equatorial Atlantic (5°S to 5°N and 45°W to 20°E) and the respective Atl-EOF index. (
   <bold class="bold">D</bold>) Responses of JJA0 vertical velocity anomalies at 600 hPa averaged over the equatorial Atlantic (5°S to 5°N and 45°W to 20°E) (pascals per second) to JJA0 Atl-EOF index using all samples of 17 selected models. The vertical velocity anomalies are binned in 0.1 SD. Atl-EOF index intervals and the median vertical velocity anomaly and index are identified for each bin (dots). Blue and red dots indicate values in the present-day and future 100-year periods, respectively. The corresponding linear fitting lines (with the values of the slopes plus and minus the 95% confidence values from the Student’s 
   <italic class="italic">t</italic> test) are also shown.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="aax4111-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
