<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is a naturally occurring event, but human activities have significantly contributed to changes in atmospheric conditions, resulting in an accelerated change in this process, and the current precarious state.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr1-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr2-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> Climate change is increasingly threatening as we continue to realize its potential impacts on global health and security. Global climate experts agree that anthropogenic activities have significantly contributed to the increasing concentration of atmospheric greenhouse gases and destruction of ecosystems.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr3-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr4-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr5-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr6-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup> Direct consequences of climate change are not difficult to notice through the occurrence of extreme weather events or changes in temperature and precipitation,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr7-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup> but indirect consequences are not as easily seen. An increase or change in the endemic range of parasitic diseases as a result of climate change will have very serious repercussions. Now, it is not only our physical footprints prompting the spread of disease through habitat destruction and ecological disruption
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr8-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup> but possibly our carbon footprints as well. Climate change directly causes increases in temperature and affects weather patterns, which indirectly can change spatial patterns of disease vectors and human populations.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr9-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr10-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup> Increases in temperature facilitate the development of arthropod vectors that carry many parasitic organisms and the parasites themselves.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr11-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> A warm climate also increases the range of reservoir hosts, vector abundance, biting rates and overall survival, and parasitic transmission rates of vectors such as mosquitoes, ticks, and tsetse flies.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr12-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
