<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Biogeochemical processes, including sorption/desorption, complexation, dissolution/precipitation, and uptake/release by biota, control the mobility of heavy metals and thus the residence time in soils and water (Carillo-Gonzáles et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2006</xref>; Reeder et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2006</xref>). When introduced into the environment, heavy metals tend to accumulate in soils and sediments (Foster and Charlesworth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">1996</xref>) because of their affinity for sorption processes. Therefore, it may take decades to centuries or longer before heavy metals leach to groundwater (Seuntjens 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">2002</xref>; Degryse and Smolders 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2006</xref>; Bonten et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2012</xref>; Joris et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2014</xref>). The solid-solution partitioning in soils is controlled by pH, redox potential, clay and soil organic matter (SOM) content, and the concentration of complex organic or inorganic ligands and competing cations (Elliott 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">1986</xref>; Hornburg and Brümmer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">1993</xref>; Sauvé et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2000</xref>; Römkens et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">2004</xref>; Pédrot et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2008</xref>; Unamuno et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">2009</xref>; Degryse et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2009</xref>; Acosta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2011</xref>; Groenenberg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2012</xref>). Dissolved heavy metals are transported to surface waters via several hydrological pathways. Metals are transported downward through the unsaturated zone to groundwater. In groundwater, the transport rate of metals depends on the groundwater recharge rate, drainage density, hydraulic conductivity, porosity, and physiochemical conditions (McNab et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2006</xref>). Heavy metals may also take shortcut pathways to surface waters via quickflow routes including overland flow and tube drain flow. This happens in particular when the precipitation intensity exceeds the infiltration capacity of soils or when soils are saturated (Smith and Goodrich 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2006</xref>). Due to large accumulation of metals present in upper soil layers, metal concentrations are generally higher in water discharging to surface waters under quickflow conditions (Rozemeijer and Broers 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2007</xref>; Bonten et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
