<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">In this paper, we present the results of an ethnobotanical inventory in the 
 <italic class="italic">Sierra Nevada del Cocuy-Güicán</italic> (from now on “the SN Cocuy-Güicán”) and discuss the possible effects of climate and land use change on the future availability of useful plants for local farmer communities. The 
 <italic class="italic">SN Cocuy-Güicán</italic> rises in the northern range of the Eastern Cordillera of the Colombian Andes. Since 1977, this region is protected within a National Natural Park (NNP-Cocuy) because of its fragile páramos, extraordinary biodiversity and endemism, and its function as a corridor for migratory species under conditions of climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. Páramos and Andean forests provide drinking water to Colombia’s large cities, like Bogotá, Medellín, and Bucaramanga. With the largest extension of glaciers in Colombia, the SN-Cocuy-Güicán is a valuable freshwater reservoir that supplies the Orinoco and the Magdalena River basins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. The local population consists of indigenous U’wa people, who occupy the eastern flanks of the SN Cocuy-Güicán, and more recent settlers (“colonos” or “campesinos”). The latter are farmers who inhabit the western flanks and were the focus group of our ethnobotanical research. The vascular flora of the páramo of SN Cocuy-Güicán is well documented [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>], but the few ethnobotanical studies in this area focused on few medicinal plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>], potatoes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>] or specific plant families such as Ericaceae [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. Previous ethnobotanical research among farmers in the same Boyacá department (in Guacamayas at 32 km downslope from El Cocuy and in Villa de Leyva at 300 km distance) highlights the relevance of the useful flora for preserving their cultural heritage and biodiversity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>].
</p>
