<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The outputs of these analyses are often explicitly intended to inform the development of adaptation strategies and plans. However, there is little evidence that climate change projections are used to inform practical adaptation decisions [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Climate change projections typically target the future several decades ahead, or even at the end of the century. Yet the most pressing issues faced by people and institutions often necessitate a focus on the present and near-term future, particularly in developing countries where there is less capacity to act [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Heat waves, for example, are an increasing risk to human health in a warming climate, but many of the most effective strategies to reduce this risk concern the development of seasonal adaptation plans and early warning systems [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. These programs allow a range of preparedness measures to reduce vulnerability and exposure, from training and awareness-raising activities at the start of the summer season to emergency interventions that could include public alerts, opening cooling centres, and distributing drinking water. In India, for example, moving the neonatal ward from the top to the bottom floor of a hospital had a significant protective effect and required no forecast information at all [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Even when the long term is relevant, as, for example, in the case of large infrastructure developments, the uncertainties involved in climate prediction on local scales are so large that they can exceed the magnitude of the projected change [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Moreover, with many relevant non-climate factors, it is difficult to disentangle the role that climate change projections may have played in the development of an adaptation plan.
</p>
