<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted mixed effects models (R package: nlme) to examine the difference in 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> values between the topsoil and the subsoil. In the model, site and soil depth were set as fixed factors, and depth nested in replicate was treated as a random factor. Having detected no interaction effect between site and soil depth (table S1), we used paired 
  <span class="italic">t</span> tests to compare the means of physicochemical properties between the topsoil and the subsoil. Linear regression models were then performed to identify the relationships of 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> with aggregate protection and microbial communities. Before the analyses, the variance inflation factor (VIF) was calculated to assess the collinearity of the variables (acceptable collinearity VIF ≤ 2) (
  <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">
   <span class="italic">58</span>
  </a>). On the basis of this criterion, the collinearity between SOC distribution in macroaggregates and microaggregates could be partly omitted (VIF = 1.6), whereas the relative abundance of fungal PLFAs was closely correlated with F/B (VIF = 4.4), and thus, only the former was included in the model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To further analyze the relative importance of different variables, we conducted variation partitioning analysis (R package: vegan) to partition the effects of aggregate protection and microbial communities on 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> in various C pools. △
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> (
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10 topsoil</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10 subsoil</sub>, the difference in 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> between the topsoil and the subsoil) for the two manipulative experiments was then calculated to test the role of aggregate protection and microbial communities. A positive value of △
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> represents larger 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> in the topsoil, while a negative value represents larger 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> in the subsoil. The means of △
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> between control and crush/inoculation treatments were compared using paired 
  <span class="italic">t</span> tests. The decrease in △
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> compared with the control indicates that crush/inoculation treatment reduces the difference in 
  <span class="italic">Q</span>
  <sub>10</sub> between the topsoil and the subsoil and vice versa. All of the statistical analyses were conducted with R version 3.2.1 (
  <a rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" href="#R59">
   <span class="italic">59</span>
  </a>), with a significance level of 0.05.
 </p>
</sec>
