<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mapping</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hydrodynamic and hydrogeologic models needed to be run on a high-resolution, seamless topographic and bathymetric (TB) digital elevation model (DEM) of the study area. To create the TB-DEM, topographic data from Global Positioning System (GPS) and terrestrial lidar scanning (TLS) collected on the island were combined with bathymetry derived from satellite imagery. The topographic surveys of Roi were conducted using static Topcon GRS1 dual-frequency GPS and GPS rovers. TLS surveys were conducted using a Riegl VZ-1000 tripod-based lidar scanner placed at 31 locations on the island. Data point cloud cleaning and filtering were performed on the registered point clouds to produce a subset of ground measurements suitable for constructing a bare-earth DEM. Because of the lack of high-resolution bathymetric data for the study area, WorldView-2 and WorldView-3 multispectral satellite imagery were used to derive bathymetry (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>). Depths on the ocean side were a combination of depths generated from the model down to 22.5 m; past that, depths were taken from an interpolated surface from fathometer measurements. A 3 × 3 low-pass convolution filter was used on the final product to eliminate single-pixel anomalies. To create the seamless TB-DEM of Roi-Namur, TLS, GPS, and satellite-derived bathymetry were combined into a 0.5-m grid. For the island and intertidal reef flat areas, TLS and GPS data were combined into a triangulated irregular network model. Because of the higher data density, TLS data were used preferentially over GPS and satellite-derived bathymetry wherever it was available. To produce the final seamless 0.5-m resolution TB-DEM, the onshore and offshore grids were combined.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrodynamic modeling uses a variety of equations with different coefficients to describe interactions between waves, current, and the seabed. Benthic habitats were mapped using spectral classification with the Iterative Self-Organizing Data Analysis Technique (ISODATA) unsupervised clustering algorithm, in combination with on-screen, heads-up digitizing (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>). The minimum mapping unit (MMU) in the areas where ISODATA was used to depths of 10 m was at the pixel level (4 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>); the MMU in the deeper areas where on-screen digitizing was used was 30 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>. The benthic habitat map was produced using a nonhierarchical classification system similar to the scheme used on adjacent Majuro Atoll (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>). The resulting habitat map was converted to a spatially varying friction coefficient map, using published values for coral reef habitats from the literature (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Land-cover data were needed to determine how much of any given land cover class would be inundated for a given future wave and sea-level scenario. Half-meter true-color and three-band color infrared satellite imagery were used as base layers to develop the terrestrial land-cover map. The ArcGIS Interactive Supervised Classification tool was used to delineate 15 distinct land-cover classes, and a majority filter was applied using eight closest cells. The result of the majority filter was a raster that was converted to polygons that were grouped by land-cover classification.</p>
</sec>
