<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">Trapping is an activity that requires knowledge of the biology and ecology of furbearers. This knowledge develops with experience over the years. The use of land and natural resources thus fuels trappers’ knowledge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>]. To ensure the sustainability of their harvests, trappers must pay particular attention to the sampling effort that they deploy under changing environmental conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>]. Traplines are thus considered to be integral ecosystems that must be managed responsibly [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>]. Trappers are recognized as “land custodians,” who are particularly interested in documenting changes in the distribution and harvesting of fur-bearing animals and the effects of habitat disturbances on forest operations and climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>]. We sought to meet with experts, both Indigenous and non-Indigenous, who were the most recognized by their peers because of their experience in trapping and their knowledge of the forest in general, and the habitats of marten and fisher in particular. We have created four groups: i) marten trappers who were active on the same territory for several years (active trappers, AT); ii) trappers who were recognized as experts by their peers, but who are no longer able to carry out their activities on a full-time basis because of their age (recommended trappers, RT); iii) experts who were involved in the management of trapping areas or in fur sale (experts, Ex); iv) elders (Elders, E). Inclusion of elders has been justified, given their important role in the transmission of forest-related knowledge over the generations, and which has increased the temporal depth of information. We used the “snowball sampling method,” whereby people in the communities identified the most experienced trappers, who in turn were able to suggest other trappers, and so on [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>]. This identification of local experts by peers ensures the recruitment of the best-informed individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>].
</p>
