<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The giant panda (
 <italic class="italic">Ailuropoda melanoleuca</italic>) is probably one of the world's most treasured endangered species (Wei et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Its habitat is currently restricted to six isolated mountain ranges in Sichuan, Shaanxi, and Gansu provinces in south‐central China (State Forestry Administration, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). The giant panda was listed as an endangered species by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) in 1996 (IUCN, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>) due to their limited geographic range, the risk of small and isolated populations, low reproductive rates, habitat loss, and diet specialization (Swaisgood, Wang, &amp; Wei, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Wang, Ye, Skidmore, &amp; Toxopeus, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Wei et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). A narrow geographic distribution makes them highly susceptible to climate change (Liu, Guang, Dai, Li, &amp; Gong, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Songer, Delion, Biggs, &amp; Huang, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Over the past decades, the Chinese government implemented many conservation programs to protect giant panda, such as establishment of reserves (State Forestry Administration, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), the panda monitoring project (Wei et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), and the Grain‐to‐Green program (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). From 1988 to 2015, the population of giant panda grew from 1,114 to 1,864 (State Forestry Administration, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), and the species has been downlisted from “Endangered” to “Vulnerable” in the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species (Swaisgood et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The Chinese government announced that giant panda conservation programs will continue and will establish national parks in the giant panda's range to specifically strengthen further conservation of giant panda (State Forestry Administration, 
 <xref rid="ece32981-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016a</xref>). Therefore, a major motivation for assessing the vulnerability of giant panda is to provide adaptive strategies for conservation programs and development of national parks to reduce effectively potential climate‐related threats to the species.
</p>
