<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6657677</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7218</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Soil Science</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Climate Change Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Natural Resource Management</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biogeochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Impacts</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Differences in biomass and silica content in typical plant communities with ecotones in the Min River estuary of southeast China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Shuijing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><email>s2008shuijing@163.com</email></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Zhigao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref><email>liujuan@gzhu.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Chuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label><institution>School of Geographical Sciences, Key Laboratory of Humid Subtropical Eco-geographical Process, Ministry of Education, Fujian Normal University</institution>, <addr-line>Fuzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label><institution>Innovation Center and Key Laboratory of Water Quality and Reservation in the Pearl River Delta, Institute of Environmental Research At Greater Bay, School of Environmental Science and Engineering, Guangzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jianhua</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2019-07-22"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e7218</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2019-01-07"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-05-31"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 Gao et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gao et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/7218"/><abstract><p>Silica (Si) is a basic nutrient requirement for many aquatic organisms and its biogeochemical cycle plays an important role in estuarine coastal ecosystems. However, little is known about the role Si plays during plant&#x02013;plant interactive processes in the marsh ecosystems. Here, variations in biomass, biogenic silica (BSi) content, and available Si content of <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic>-dominated marshes, <italic>Phragmites australis</italic>-dominated marshes, and their ecotonal marshes were studied in the Shanyutan marsh in the Min River estuary, China. Results showed that <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> biomass in ecotones was lower than those in typical communities by 46.4% and 46.3%, respectively. BSi content in aboveground organs of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and culms and roots of <italic>P. australis</italic> was lower in ecotones than in typical communities, whereas BSi content in other organs showed the opposite trend. Biomass allocation in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> roots in ecotones was higher by 56.9% and 19.5%, respectively, and BSi stock in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> roots was higher than that in typical communities by 120.9% and 18.9%, respectively. Available Si content in ecotonal marsh soils was 12.6% greater than that in typical communities. Thus, the two plant species may use different strategies for Si accumulation and allocation in ecotones to adapt to the competitive environment. <italic>P. australis</italic> may expand primarily via occupation of wider aboveground space, thereby increasing the Si accumulation capacity in aboveground organs. Meanwhile, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> may increase the Si allocation capacity of its roots to withstand the pressure from <italic>P. australis</italic>. This study will provide new insights into marsh plant competition from the perspective of Si, which can also benefit plant management in marsh ecosystems.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Variation</kwd><kwd>Silica</kwd><kwd>Ecotone</kwd><kwd>Competition</kwd><kwd>Marsh</kwd><kwd>Min River estuary</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Natural Science Foundation of China</funding-source><award-id>41401114, 41573008, 41873015 and U1612442</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Guangzhou University&#x02019;s 2017 training program for young top-notch personnel</funding-source><award-id>BJ201709</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 41401114, 41573008, 41873015 and U1612442) and the Guangzhou University&#x02019;s 2017 training program for young top-notch personnel (BJ201709). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Silica (Si) is considered as a beneficial element for plants (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Ma &#x00026; Yamaji, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Klotzb&#x000fc;cher et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Coskun et al., 2019</xref>). Many terrestrial and aquatic plants accumulate high amounts of Si in their tissues (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Struyf et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Ma &#x00026; Yamaji, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Carey et al., 2017</xref>). Si is still not recognized as an essential element for plant growth; however, its beneficial effects on the development, yield, mineral nutrition, health, and survival have been observed in a variety of plant species for decades in agricultural ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Datnoff, Deren &#x00026; Snyder, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Savant et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Datnoff, Snyder &#x00026; Kornd&#x000f6;rfer, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Ma &#x00026; Yamaji, 2006</xref>). During the last decade, Si has received increased attention in natural ecosystems owing to its importance in plant growth, nutrient content (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et al., 2012b</xref>, <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Brackhage et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Coskun et al., 2016</xref>), stoichiometry (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Schaller &#x00026; Struyf, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Schaller, Hines &#x00026; Brackhage, 2017</xref>), providing rigidity to plant structures, and enhancing resistance to abiotic and biotic stresses (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 1994</xref>, <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Quern&#x000e9;, Ragueneau &#x00026; Poupart, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck et al., 2014</xref>). Si availability has a great influence on other nutrient content and the stoichiometry of marsh grasses during plant growth (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et al., 2012b</xref>; <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Brackhage et al., 2013</xref>), and can influence element cycling during litter decomposition (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Schaller, Hines &#x00026; Brackhage, 2017</xref>). Furthermore, Si may affect the nutrient element turnover via altered plant nutrient and litter decomposition, and the trade-off between resource efficiency and plant stabilization/defense (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Schaller, Brackhage &#x00026; Dudel, 2012a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Schaller &#x00026; Struyf, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et al., 2016</xref>). Si could play a significant role in vegetation dynamics, and the processing and functioning of ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Struyf &#x00026; Conley, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Schaller et al., 2012b</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Struyf et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Carey et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Coskun et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Estuarine marshes, located in the land&#x02013;ocean transition zone, are some of the most sensitive ecosystems to global climate change (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Simas, Nunes &#x00026; Ferreira, 2001</xref>), and are considered as important areas for studying Si transport and processing (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Struyf et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Struyf &#x00026; Conley, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Carey &#x00026; Fulweiler, 2013</xref>). The efficient use of Si by different plant species potentially influences competitiveness in dynamic environments (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Struyf &#x00026; Conley, 2009</xref>). Plants that are able to utilize Si to their benefit are favored under changing environmental conditions in estuaries at the community level (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Quern&#x000e9;, Ragueneau &#x00026; Poupart, 2012</xref>). Si is important for plant decomposition processes, plant competitiveness, and stress tolerance (<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck et al., 2014</xref>). Previous studies have been conducted to explore Si content variations of typical plant communities in estuarine marsh ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Struyf et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Hou et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Quern&#x000e9;, Ragueneau &#x00026; Poupart, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Jacobs et al., 2013</xref>), whereas those in ecotones (i.e., the transitional zone between two plant species) remain neglected. The competition among different plant species and the ecological edge effect in ecotones are clearly obvious (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Cadenasso et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Theriot et al., 2013</xref>). However, Si cycling in ecotones and its role for plant competition in estuarine marshes has not been explained in recent studies (<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck et al., 2014</xref>). As a beneficial nutrient, Si content might show more variability in ecotones compared to typical communities, and thus may provide new insight into marsh plant competition.</p><p>The Shanyutan marsh is the largest wetland in the Min River estuary in the transitional subtropical zone of southeast China. The main vegetation includes native species <italic>Cyperus malaccensis, Phragmites australis</italic>, and <italic>C. compressus</italic>, and invasive species <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>, which started to invade this marsh in 2002 (<xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Tong et al., 2011</xref>). Different types of typical plant communities are distributed zonally from land to sea. The ecotones of two plant communities, that is, the transition regions gradually formed during the process of plant expansion, are clearly distinct in this zone. <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones grow as vigorously as those in typical communities. Therefore, this provides a suitable area to study the differences between ecotones and typical community zones in the Min River estuary. Studies regarding Si in the Min River estuary marshes have mainly focused on soil and porewater in typical vegetation areas (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Zhai &#x00026; Xue, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Hou et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2018</xref>), whereas Si cycling in transitional systems has been neglected. Previous studies have shown that biomass allocation and biogenic silica (BSi) stock in roots was higher in ecotones than in typical communities (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2017</xref>). This has important implications for understanding the mechanisms behind habitat competition of different plant species. However, the accumulation and allocation of biomass and Si content among different plant species in ecotones of plant&#x02013;plant interactive processes have been overlooked.</p><p>In the present study, the differences in biomass and BSi content of <italic>P. australis</italic> and <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> during their competition were investigated, as was the available Si content of soils in the Shanyutan marsh. The objectives were to: (i) compare the variation in Si content and biomass of typical communities with that of ecotones; and (ii) discuss Si allocation variations among plant organs and between typical communities and ecotones. This would not only enhance the knowledge regarding the variations in Si content, but also help understand the potential competitiveness mechanism of native plant species from Si cycling in the estuarine marsh ecosystems.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study area</title><p>The present study was undertaken in the Shanyutan marsh (119&#x000b0;34&#x02032;12&#x02033;&#x02013;119&#x000b0;40&#x02032;40&#x02033;E, 26&#x000b0;00&#x02032;36&#x02033;&#x02013;26&#x000b0;03&#x02032;42&#x02033;N), which is the largest wetland (approximately 3,120 ha) in the Min River estuary, southeast China (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Liu, Zeng &#x00026; Chen, 2006</xref>). The climate is relatively warm and wet, with a mean annual temperature of 19.6 &#x000b0;C and a mean annual precipitation of 1,300 mm. This area is featured by typical semi-diurnal tide with a mean tidal range of 4.37&#x02013;4.46 m (<xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Zhang, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Dai, 2004</xref>). The marsh sediment is dominated by saline soil with low pH. The width of the Shanyutan coastal marsh (gradient 1&#x02013;2&#x000b0;) is generally larger than one km (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Liu, Zeng &#x00026; Chen, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Chen, Tang &#x00026; Li, 2015</xref>). The main marsh vegetation includes three native species (<italic>P. australis</italic>, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>, and <italic>C. compressus</italic>) and one invasive species <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Tong et al., 2010</xref>). In the western Shanyutan marsh, there are five typical plant communities distributed in a belt-like pattern from land to sea (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>): <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community, <italic>P. australis</italic> community, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community, <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> community, and <italic>C. compressus</italic> community, with the latter two communities excluded from the present study. In this region, <italic>P. australis</italic> and <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> coexist without other species in the transitional zone, and are distributed from both <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community to <italic>P. australis</italic> community and also from <italic>P. australis</italic> community to <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community, with a width of approximately 50&#x02013;100 m. Therefore, there were three typical communities and two distinct ecotones in our study.</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>The study area and location of the sampling sites.</title><p>W1, <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> marsh; W2, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>-<italic>Phragmites australis</italic> marsh; W3, <italic>P. australis</italic> marsh; W4, <italic>P. australis</italic>-<italic>C. malaccensis</italic> marsh; W5, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> marsh.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Sample collection and pretreatment</title><p>In July 2015, two parallel transects perpendicular to the coastline were laid from land to sea in the high-middle flat tidal zone of the western Shanyutan marsh. The distance between the two transects was approximately 100 m, and on each transect five sampling sites were selected that included three typical community marshes and two ecotonal marshes, that is, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community (closed to land and more than 50 m away from the dam, W1), <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>P. australis</italic> community (<italic>C. malaccensis</italic> was dominant with a relative culms density of 82.7% per square meter, W2), <italic>P. australis</italic> community (W3), <italic>P. australis</italic>&#x02013;<italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community (<italic>C. malaccensis</italic> was dominant with a relative culms density of 66.1% per square meter, W4), and <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> community (closed to sea, W5). To better distinguish the same plant species among the two ecotones, we recorded <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in W2 as W2-C and <italic>P. australis</italic> as W2-P whereas <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in W4 was recorded as W4-C and <italic>P. australis</italic> was W4-P.</p><p>Three replicate plots (50 &#x000d7; 50 cm) were randomly chosen from each of the five sites for the collection of soil and plant samples. Soil profiles (0&#x02013;40 cm) were taken with a columnar sampler (diameter 10 cm and height 80 cm) and samples were collected at 10 cm intervals (0&#x02013;10, 10&#x02013;20, 20&#x02013;30, and 30&#x02013;40 cm) from each plot. Soil electrical conductivity and pH were measured simultaneously in situ using a portable instrument (Spectrum Technologies Inc., Chicago, IL, USA, and HACH-sensION3, Loveland, CO, USA, respectively). A total of 120 soil samples were collected and air-dried, ground, and sieved through an 80-mesh nylon sieve. Aboveground parts were clipped at the soil surface and separated into culms, leaves, and litter (withered parts). Underground parts were also collected. Plant samples of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> or <italic>P. australis</italic> collected from typical communities or ecotones were wholly divided and pretreated based on the different organs of plant species in the ecotones. All plant organs were washed thoroughly with deionized water and dried in an oven (GZX-9140; MBE, Beijing, China) at 65 &#x000b0;C until a constant weight. Then, the samples were ground into a fine powder (&#x0003c;0.25 mm) for Si analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample analysis</title><p>To extract BSi, 30 mg of plant powder was digested for 5 h with Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (0.1 mol/L) at 85 &#x000b0;C (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Demaster, 1981</xref>; <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Struyf et al., 2005</xref>). BSi and available Si content of the soil were extracted with alkaline Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Demaster, 1981</xref>) and citric acid (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Acquaye &#x00026; Tinsley, 1965</xref>; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Lu, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Narayanaswamy &#x00026; Prakash, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Babu et al., 2016</xref>), respectively. The dissolved Si content in the extractions was measured using the molybdate blue spectrophotometric method. Total carbon and total nitrogen in soil were determined with a Vario EL Elemental Analyser (Elementar Scientific Instruments, Langenselbold, Germany). Soil grain size was measured with a Master Sizer 2000 Laser Particle Size Analyzer (Master Scientific Instruments, Malvern, UK). Soil organic matter (SOM) was analyzed by the K<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> oxidation method. Soil bulk density (BD) was measured using the cutting ring method. Soil moisture content was the weight difference between fresh soils before and after drying in an oven at 105 &#x000b0;C for 24 h. The physical and chemical properties of soil profiles from the five sampling sites are shown in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Physical and chemical properties of soil profiles from five sampling sites.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sites</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EC (mS/cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moisture (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOM (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BD (g/cm<sup>3</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TN (mg/g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC (mg/g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21 &#x000b1; 0.86<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.43 &#x000b1; 0.28<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.78 &#x000b1; 4.37<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38 &#x000b1; 1.37<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 &#x000b1; 0.11<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#x000b1; 1.06<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.28 &#x000b1; 11.63<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 &#x000b1; 0.85<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28 &#x000b1; 0.38<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.23 &#x000b1; 8.53<sup>ac</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89 &#x000b1; 0.92<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 &#x000b1; 0.16<sup>ac</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 &#x000b1; 0.70<sup>ac</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.12 &#x000b1; 7.95<sup>ac</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 &#x000b1; 1.29<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.17 &#x000b1; 0.27<sup>ac</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.98 &#x000b1; 4.41<sup>bd</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52 &#x000b1; 1.03<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 &#x000b1; 0.08<sup>bd</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 &#x000b1; 0.64<sup>ac</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.46 &#x000b1; 7.37<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29 &#x000b1; 0.90<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.96 &#x000b1; 0.15<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.39 &#x000b1; 3.15<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 &#x000b1; 1.33<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 &#x000b1; 0.09<sup>ac</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.12 &#x000b1; 1.29<sup>ac</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77 &#x000b1; 0.95<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.17 &#x000b1; 0.32<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.99 &#x000b1; 1.83<sup>cd</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 &#x000b1; 1.09<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 &#x000b1; 0.03<sup>cd</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 &#x000b1; 0.24<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.88 &#x000b1; 2.67<sup>bc</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p><bold>Notes:</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Values are means &#x000b1; S.E. Different lowercase letters indicate statistical significant differences between sampling sites within the same column at the level of <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn2" fn-type="other"><p>EC, electrical conductivity; Moisture, soil moisture; SOM, soil organic matter; BD, bulk density; TN, total nitrogen; TC, total carbon.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Calculations</title><p>The biomass or BSi stock allocation proportions (AP, %) in different plant tissues were calculated by the following equation:<disp-formula id="eqn-1"><label>(1)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-e001.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$${\rm{AP}}\,{\rm{ = }}\,{{{\rm{Bi}}} \over {{\rm{Bn}}}}\, \times \,100\% $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn001"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>AP&#x02009;=&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Bi</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Bn</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi>%</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>where, Bi (g/m<sup>2</sup>) is the biomass or BSi stock in different plant organs (including roots, culms, leaves, and litter); and Bn (g/m<sup>2</sup>) is the total biomass or total BSi stock. BSi stock is BSi content multiplied by relevant biomass (mg/m<sup>2</sup>).</p><p>The relative competition coefficient of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> to <italic>P. australis</italic> (Rcp) was calculated based on <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">De Wit&#x02019;s (1960)</xref> model of resource competition to represent the interspecific competition ability as follows:<disp-formula id="eqn-2"><label>(2)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-e002.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$${\rm{Rcp}}\,{\rm{ = }}\,{{{\rm{Yce/Ype}}} \over {{\rm{Yct/Ypt}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn002"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Rcp&#x02009;=&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Yce/Ype</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Yct/Ypt</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>where, Yce (g/m<sup>2</sup>) and Yct (g/m<sup>2</sup>) are the biomass of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in ecotones and typical communities, respectively; and Ype (g/m<sup>2</sup>) and Ypt (g/m<sup>2</sup>) are the biomass of <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones and typical communities, respectively. Rcp &#x0003e; 1 means that <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> has a greater competition ability than that of <italic>P. australis</italic>.</p><p>For each plant species, we used the data regarding BSi content to calculate the values of roots/culms (<italic>B<sub>R</sub>/B<sub>C</sub></italic>), roots/leaves (<italic>B<sub>R</sub>/B<sub>L</sub></italic>), culms/leaves (<italic>B<sub>C</sub>/B<sub>L</sub></italic>), and shoots/roots (<italic>B<sub>S</sub>/B<sub>R</sub></italic>), which could represent the ability of relative transportation or immobilization of BSi under different situations, according to the methodology described by <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Dahmani-Muller et al. (2000)</xref>. For example, if the value of <italic>B<sub>R</sub>/B<sub>C</sub></italic> was lower, especially less than 1, more BSi was transported from roots to culms or more BSi was immobilized in culms.</p><p>Accumulation factors (AF) in different organs were calculated using the ratio of (Element)<sub>plant</sub> to (Element)<sub>soil</sub> (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Duman, Cicek &#x00026; Sezen, 2007</xref>) (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eqn-3">Eq. (3)</xref>) to evaluate the ability of plants to absorb Si from marsh soils:<disp-formula id="eqn-3"><label>(3)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-e003.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$${\rm(AF)_{plant}} = {{{C_{{\rm{plant}}}}} \over {{C_{{\rm{soil}}}}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-eqn003"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>AF</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>plant</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>plant</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>soil</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>where, <italic>C</italic><sub>plant</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>soil</sub> (mg/g) were the average BSi content in different plant organs (including roots, culms, leaves, and litter) and in surface soils, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Statistical analyses were performed with the SPSS Version 19.0 Statistical Software Package (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). One-way analysis of variance was used to analyze significant differences in Si content of marsh plants and soils between typical communities and ecotones. Correlations between available Si content and physical and chemical properties were evaluated using Pearson correlation coefficients with a significance level of <italic>p</italic> = 0.05. Principal component analysis and stepwise linear regression analysis were used to test the major influencing factors of available Si content in marsh soils.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Variation of biomass allocation of marsh plants in typical communities and ecotones</title><p>Biomass allocation was widely different in typical communities compared to ecotones for the same plant species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2A</xref>; <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2A</xref>). Each organ biomass of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in typical communities was higher than that in ecotones. The total biomass of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in typical communities was higher by 46.4% (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) and 46.3% (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) than those in ecotones, respectively.</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Biomass (A) and allocation proportion of biomass (B) to different organs of <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> and <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> in typical communities and ecotones.</title><p>The species <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in W2 were recorded as W2-C and W2-P while those in W4 were recorded as W4-C and W4-P respectively. Error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Biomass (A) and allocation proportion (B) to different organs of <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> and <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> in typical communities and ecotones.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Locations</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Biomass (g/m<sup>2</sup>, A)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Allocation proportion (%, B)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Litter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Litter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cyperus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,023.90 &#x000b1; 97.89<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.58 &#x000b1; 6.17<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.37 &#x000b1; 1.55<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">796.58 &#x000b1; 32.52<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,886.42 &#x000b1; 73.10<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.16<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.36<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>malaccensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecotone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">317.97 &#x000b1; 11.69<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.44 &#x000b1; 1.05<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74 &#x000b1; 0.07<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">672.88 &#x000b1; 47.17<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,011.02 &#x000b1; 34.36<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.53<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.47<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phragmites</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">684.83 &#x000b1; 46.08<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218.5 &#x000b1; 70.64<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">376.51 &#x000b1; 39.78<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,034.77 &#x000b1; 168.95<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,311.63 &#x000b1; 219.01<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.50<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.45<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.29<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.76<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>australis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecotone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346.49 &#x000b1; 14.14<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.39 &#x000b1; 4.07<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.23 &#x000b1; 17.93<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">663.58 &#x000b1; 37.50<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,240.69 &#x000b1; 65.50<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.95<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.05<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.53<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.47<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Note:</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Asterisks indicate significant differences between typical communities and ecotones within <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> or <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> communities.</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn2" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn3" fn-type="other"><label>**</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="table-2fn4" fn-type="other"><label>***</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Generally, the allocation proportion to <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> root biomass was similar to that of <italic>P. australis</italic> in typical communities (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05); however, it was obviously higher in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> than that in <italic>P. australis</italic> in the ecotones (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2B</xref>; <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>). For the same plant species, root biomass allocation proportions in ecotones were higher than those in typical communities by 56.9% (<italic>C. malaccensis</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) and 19.5% (<italic>P. australis</italic>, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). However, biomass allocation proportions of culms (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) and litter (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in ecotones were lower than those in typical communities by 41.8% and 43.1%, respectively, with no obvious discrepancy with <italic>P. australis</italic> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). The leaf biomass allocation proportion of <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones was significantly lower than that in typical communities (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) by 35.4%, whereas no difference was observed for <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>BSi variation of marsh plants in typical communities and ecotones variation in BSi content</title><p>BSi content in different organs of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in typical communities and ecotones was lower than that of <italic>P. australis</italic> (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3A</xref>; <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3A</xref>). For <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>, the mean BSi content of different organs in W1, W2, W4, and W5 was 12.64, 9.90, 6.35, and 7.41 mg/g, respectively. The mean BSi content in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> culms (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05), litter (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05), and leaves (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) in ecotones was lower than that in typical communities, whereas the mean BSi content in roots was greater (by 2.27%, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3A</xref>). The average BSi content of different organs in <italic>P. australis</italic> was highest in W2, followed by W3, and was lowest in W4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The average BSi content of <italic>P. australis</italic> culms and roots in ecotones was lower than that in typical communities (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05), whereas the average BSi content in litter and leaves showed the opposite trend (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3A</xref>). Thus, the same plant species had approximately more BSi near the shore and less BSi near the sea, except for <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in W4.</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>BSi content (A) and allocation proportion of BSi stock (B) of <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> and <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> in typical communities and ecotones.</title><p>The species <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in W2 were recorded as W2-C and W2-P while those in W4 were recorded as W4-C and W4-P respectively. Error bars represent standard error of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>BSi content (A) and stock allocation proportion (B) to different organs of <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> and <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> in typical communities and ecotones.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Locations</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">BSi content (mg/g, A)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Allocation proportion (%, B)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Litter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Litter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cyperus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.06 &#x000b1; 3.12<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.40 &#x000b1; 2.15<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.55 &#x000b1; 3.85<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84 &#x000b1; 1.09<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.54<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.86<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>malaccensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecotone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.35 &#x000b1; 2.38<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.44 &#x000b1; 1.87<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.21 &#x000b1; 1.50<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn3"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.95 &#x000b1; 0.21<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.71<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn4"><sup>***</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.71<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phragmites</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.86 &#x000b1; 1.89<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.43 &#x000b1; 1.52<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.19 &#x000b1; 1.89<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.98 &#x000b1; 0.79<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.54<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.94<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.33<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.19<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>australis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecotone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.17 &#x000b1; 4.45<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.95 &#x000b1; 2.53<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.43 &#x000b1; 0.99<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.87 &#x000b1; 3.09<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.56<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.70<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.49<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.26<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-3fn2"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fn"><p><bold>Note:</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-3fn1" fn-type="other"><p>Asterisks indicate significant differences between typical communities and ecotones within <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> or <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> communities.</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn2" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn3" fn-type="other"><label>**</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></fn><fn id="table-3fn4" fn-type="other"><label>***</label><p><italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Allocation proportion of BSi stock</title><p>In ecotones, the allocation proportion of <italic>P. australis</italic> BSi stock was higher in roots and litter, and lower in leaves and culms than those in typical communities. The allocation proportion of BSi stock in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> roots was higher in ecotones than in typical communities, whereas other organs showed the opposite trend (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3B</xref>). In contrast to BSi stocks in culms and leaves, the average allocation proportion in the roots of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones was higher than that in typical communities by 120.9% and 18.9%, respectively (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3B</xref>). For the different plant species, the allocation proportion of BSi stock in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> roots (23.9%) was lower than that of <italic>P. australis</italic> (32.2%) in typical communities; however, it was higher in ecotones, with an allocation of 52.7% in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and 38.3% in <italic>P. australis</italic> (<xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3B</xref>). Therefore, both species might regulate BSi allocation in culms and leaves to be habituated to the homogeneous environment in typical communities while increasing the root BSi allocation to adapt to the competitive environmental conditions.</p><p>Variation in BSi transport was observed in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> as well as in typical communities and ecotones (<xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4A</xref>). The values of <italic>B<sub>R</sub>/B<sub>C</sub>, B<sub>R</sub>/B<sub>L</sub></italic>, and <italic>B<sub>C</sub>/B<sub>L</sub></italic> of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones were higher than those in typical communities, whereas <italic>B<sub>S</sub>/B<sub>R</sub></italic> ratios showed the opposite trend. Therefore, the mobility of BSi from roots to aboveground parts in ecotones was relatively weaker than that of typical communities.</p><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>BSi transfer coefficients (A) and accumulation factors (B) in <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> and <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> of typical communities and ecotones.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g008"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" content-type="text"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Species</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Locations</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Transfer coefficients (A)</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Accumulation factors (B)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B<sub>R</sub>/B<sub>C</sub></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B<sub>R</sub>/</italic>B<sub><italic>L</italic></sub></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B<sub>C</sub>/B<sub>L</sub></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>B<sub>S</sub>/B<sub>R</sub></italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Litter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cyperus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>malaccensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecotone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Phragmites</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Typical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>australis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecotone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The accumulation of BSi in different organs of the two plant species is shown in <xref rid="table-4" ref-type="table">Table 4B</xref>. Apart from the roots, the AF of other organs of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> in typical communities was generally higher than those in the ecotones. However, the AF in the roots of <italic>P. australis</italic> in the ecotones was lower than that in the typical communities by 16.2%.</p></sec><sec><title>Variation in available Si content of marsh soils in typical communities and ecotones</title><p>Generally, available Si content of marsh soils gradually increased from land to sea except for W5, and the mean value of available Si content in ecotones was significantly higher than that in typical communities by 12.6% (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>). Significant differences were observed in available Si content of soil layers from 0 to 30 cm (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) in the five sampling sites, with no significant difference in the 30&#x02013;40 cm soil layer (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). In general, available Si content decreased with increasing depth in different marshes (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01). Therefore, the available Si content in surface soil may be influenced by plant rooting, tides, and other factors, whereas the available Si content in deeper soils was relatively stable.</p><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Available Si content of marsh soils in typical communities and ecotones.</title><p>Error bars represent standard error of the mean. Uppercase letters represent significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) in available Si content in the same soil layer between different sampling sites. Lowercase letters represent significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) between different soil depths in the same site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Biomass allocation of marsh plants in ecotones and its implications for plant competition</title><p>Plasticity in biomass allocation determines the ability of plants to obtain resources in heterogeneous environments (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Poorter, Remkes &#x00026; Lambers, 1990</xref>), thereby influencing their competitiveness in different plant communities. Plants may improve their competitive ability by increasing biomass (such as roots, culms, etc.) and by allocating more resources to root systems under low nutrient conditions (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Weiner, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Wu, Chen &#x00026; Du, 2010</xref>). In the Shanyutan marsh, the biomass of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones was lower than that in typical communities (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2A</xref>), indicating that competition might exist between <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones, and plant growth was inhibited to some extent. Additionally, biomass allocation to <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> roots in ecotones was higher than that in typical communities (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>). In ecotones, the biomass allocation of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> culms and <italic>P. australis</italic> leaves was significantly decreased. Therefore, plants might allocate more resources to roots, thus promoting root growth. To improve survival ability and competitiveness, plants may take different strategies for biomass allocation to make better use of resources under different environmental conditions (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Lloret, Casanovas &#x00026; Penuelas, 2010</xref>). In this region, both plant species might increase their ability to absorb soil nutrients, resulting in lower average C and N content of soils in ecotonal marshes (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Under this condition, plants in ecotones may increase the biomass allocation proportion of roots to improve their competitiveness and resist nutrient stress.</p><p>In ecotones, <italic>P. australis</italic> occupied more aboveground space with greater density and higher height, whereas the density of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> was greatly reduced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">Table S1</xref>). Thus, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> had to promote a high biomass allocation proportion of roots to absorb more nutrients from subsurface layers and better withstand competition from <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones. In addition, the relative competitive stress of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> was higher than that of <italic>P. australis</italic> (Rcp &#x0003e; 1), especially for underground resources (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-3">Table S2</xref>), which also showed that the underground parts of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> had a stronger competition advantage in ecotones.</p></sec><sec><title>Changed BSi stock allocation of marsh plants in ecotones and its implications for plant competition</title><p>Biomass of each organ in plants determines the amount of accumulated nutrients and the distribution of nutrients within plants (<xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Zeng, Zhang &#x00026; Tong, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Li, 2013</xref>). Several studies have indicated that the differences of plant BSi storage were attributable to the discrepancies of biomass (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Struyf et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Carey et al., 2017</xref>). In the present study, BSi stock allocation in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> roots was obviously higher in ecotones than that in typical communities, principally owing to the increased biomass allocation proportion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2B</xref>; <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>). Especially for <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>, BSi allocation proportion of roots in ecotones almost doubled in typical communities, whereas the BSi allocation proportions in leaves and culms were nearly decreased by half. However, BSi allocation proportion in <italic>P. australis</italic> roots only increased by 18.9% in ecotones. Therefore, this might illustrate that <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> roots reserving more BSi may help it to compete with <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones.</p><p>Usually plants allocate more resources to roots to obtain more nutrients to improve their competitiveness under low nutrient conditions (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Weiner, 2004</xref>). Regarding Si, active plant Si uptake has been suggested for native species exhibiting strong environmental stress conditions (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck &#x00026; Struyf, 2016</xref>). The level of BSi accumulation in marsh plants could be automatically adaptive, that is, Si accumulation in the vegetation would be increased under stressful conditions (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Schoelynck &#x00026; Struyf, 2016</xref>). In the Shanyutan marsh, <italic>P. australis</italic> flourished easier to gain light and space on the ground than <italic>C. malaccensis</italic>. Therefore, <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> had to promote the Si enrichment ability of its roots to resist the spread of <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones, and adjust the absorption and allocation of Si to adapt to this competitive environment (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2017</xref>). In the present study, the allocation proportion of BSi stock in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> was different among ecotones, compared with that in the typical communities. In ecotones, BSi allocation proportion of each organ in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> decreased except for the roots, whereas the increased value of BSi allocation proportion in <italic>P. australis</italic> was focused on the leaves and litter. Generally, Si has distinct effects in Si-accumulators (such as marsh plants) that are exposed to abiotic and biotic stresses (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Ma &#x00026; Yamaji, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Coskun et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, for superficial estimates, more BSi was focused on the roots in <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> rather than on the leaves in <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones to resist biotic pressure.</p><p>These results might indicate that the two plant species use different strategies for Si accumulation and allocation in ecotones to adapt to the competitive environment. <italic>P. australis</italic> expanded primarily by occupying a wider aboveground space and by increasing its Si accumulation capacity of aboveground organs, whereas <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> was able to resist the competitive pressure of <italic>P. australis</italic> by expanding the Si allocation of its roots.</p></sec><sec><title>Differences of available Si content in marsh soils between typical communities and ecotones</title><p>Available Si content is important for measuring soil nutrient supply to plants (<xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Babu et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Klotzb&#x000fc;cher et al., 2018</xref>). Pearson correlation analyses showed that significantly positive correlations occurred between available Si content and soil moisture and SOM (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 or <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-4">Table S3</xref>). Available Si content was relatively higher in soils with more water content (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2015</xref>), which might be the reason for higher available Si content in ecotones (W2 and W4, <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, a previous study demonstrated that the decomposition of SOM could release Si, and soil organic acids and reductive conditions formed by organic matter degradation may damage iron-Si complexes, which are also conducive to Si dissolution (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Ma, Chen &#x00026; Chu, 2016</xref>). The higher available Si content observed in ecotonal marsh soils might also be related to the higher SOM (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) compared to typical communities. Thus, soil moisture and SOM had important effects on the distribution of soil available Si in the Shanyutan marsh.</p><p>Principal component analyses showed that the major factors influencing available Si content were soil BD, grain composition, pH, and organic components (a variance contribution rate of 81.0%; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-5">Table S4</xref>). Furthermore, stepwise linear regression analysis revealed that soil BD was the crucial factor influencing available Si content (available Si = &#x02212;301.691 &#x000d7; BD + 793.286, <italic>p</italic> = 0.006). In the present study, available Si content was relatively higher in ecotones than in typical communities and had a significantly negative correlation with BD (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-4">Table S3</xref>), which might be due to the root systems of the vegetation. Previous studies indicated that root growth was limited because of the hardness and lack of oxygen supply in soils with higher BD, thus decreasing root dry weight (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Grzesiak, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Singh, Salaria &#x00026; Kaul, 2015</xref>). In the present study, the mean biomass allocation to root systems in ecotones (60.0%) was higher than that in typical communities (43.56%, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>), whereas soil BD showed the opposite trend in ecotones (0.98 g/cm<sup>3</sup>) and typical communities (1.02 g/cm<sup>3</sup>, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). Therefore, this might result in the higher available Si content in the marsh soils of ecotones.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The biomass and BSi stock allocation proportion of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> and <italic>P. australis</italic> roots were higher in ecotones than those in typical communities in the Shanyutan marsh. In ecotones, <italic>P. australis</italic> might expand primarily by occupying a wider aboveground space and increasing the Si accumulation capacity of aboveground organs, whereas <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> might resist the competition pressure of <italic>P. australis</italic> by increasing the Si allocation capacity of its roots. Available Si content in ecotone soils was also higher than that in typical community soils. Soil moisture, SOM, BD, and plant assimilation were the major factors influencing available Si content in the Shanyutan marsh.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title>Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Raw data applied for data analyses and preparation for all Figures and Tables.</title><p>Biogenic Si content, biomass, density and height, available Si content, and soil properties.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-s001.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Mean values of height and density of marsh plants in typical communities and ecotones.</title><p>Note: Asterisks indicate significant differences between typical communities and ecotones within <italic>Cyperus malaccensis</italic> or <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> communities (<sup>*</sup> means <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05, <sup>**</sup> means <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, and <sup>***</sup> means <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>Relative competition coefficient of <italic>C. malaccensis</italic> to <italic>P. australis</italic> in ecotones.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-s003.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/supp-4</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 4</label><caption><title>Correlation coefficients between available Si contents and physical and chemical properties in marsh soils.</title><p>Note: Asterisks indicate significant correlations between available Si contents and physical and chemical properties in marsh soils (<sup>*</sup> means <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>**</sup> means <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01).</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-s004.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.7218/supp-5</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 5</label><caption><title>Eigenvalues and rotated component matrix of available Si content in soils of the Shanyutan marsh.</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-07-7218-s005.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank Tao He, Jiabing Li, Peng Ren and He Zhu for their assistance with field sampling and thank Guanyun Hou for her help with the data analysis. We sincerely thank the reviewers and editor for their valuable comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conflict-1"><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-1"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Hui Gao</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-2"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Shuijing Zhai</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-3"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Zhigao Sun</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-4"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Juan Liu</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contribution-5"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-5">Chuan Tong</xref> performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>Data are available as a <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplemental-information">Supplemental File</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Acquaye &#x00026; Tinsley (1965)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acquaye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinsley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hallsworth</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soluble silica in soils</article-title><source>Experimental Pedology</source><year>1965</year><conf-name>Proceedings of the Eleventh Easter School in Agricultural Science</conf-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Butterworths</publisher-name><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>148</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Babu et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tubana</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Datnoff</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupree</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survey of the plant-available silicon status of agricultural soils in Louisiana</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Nutrition</source><year>2016</year><volume>41</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01904167.2017.1346668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Brackhage et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brackhage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ucker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon availability affects the stoichiometry and content of calcium and micro nutrients in the leaves of common reed</article-title><source>Silicon</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12633-013-9145-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Cadenasso et al. (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cadenasso</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>STA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weathers</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A framework for a theory of ecological boundaries</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/0006-3568(2003)053[0750:affato]2.0.co;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Carey &#x00026; Fulweiler (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulweiler</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen enrichment increases net silica accumulation in a temperate salt marsh</article-title><source>Limnology and Oceanography</source><year>2013</year><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4319/lo.2013.58.1.0099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Carey et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetcher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogenic silica accumulation varies across tussock tundra plant functional type</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2177</fpage><lpage>2187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2435.12912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Chen, Tang &#x00026; Li (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group><source>Influence of outflows from the Minjiang River on the estuary and adjacent coastal areas</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Coskun et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coskun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Britto</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronzucker</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of silicon in higher plants under salinity and drought stress</article-title><source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27486474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Coskun et al. (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coskun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronzucker</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;langer</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The controversies of silicon&#x02019;s role in plant biology</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2019</year><volume>221</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.15343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30007071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Dahmani-Muller et al. (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahmani-Muller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Oort</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000e9;lie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Balabane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies of heavy metal uptake by three plant species growing near a metal smelter</article-title><source>Environmental Pollution</source><year>2000</year><volume>109</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0269-7491(99)00262-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15092894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Dai (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of hydrologic features in the Fuzhou district</article-title><source>Hydraulic Science and Technology</source><year>2004</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Datnoff, Deren &#x00026; Snyder (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datnoff</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Deren</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon fertilization for disease management of rice in Florida</article-title><source>Crop Protection</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0261-2194(97)00033-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Datnoff, Snyder &#x00026; Kornd&#x000f6;rfer (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Datnoff</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornd&#x000f6;rfer</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Silica in agriculture</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>De Wit (1960)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Wit</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On competition</article-title><source>Versl Landbouwk Onde</source><year>1960</year><volume>66</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Demaster (1981)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demaster</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The supply and accumulation of silica in the marine environment</article-title><source>Geochimica Et Cosmochimica Acta</source><year>1981</year><volume>45</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1715</fpage><lpage>1732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0016-7037(81)90006-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Duman, Cicek &#x00026; Sezen (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal changes of metal accumulation and distribution in common club rush (<italic>Schoenoplectus lacustris</italic>) and common reed (<italic>Phragmites australis</italic>)</article-title><source>Ecotoxicology</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>457</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10646-007-0150-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17577664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Epstein (1994)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anomaly of silicon in plant biology</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.1.11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11607449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Epstein (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon: its manifold roles in plants</article-title><source>Annals of Applied Biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>155</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7348.2009.00343.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Gao et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal and spatial variation of available soil silicon and its influence on the formation of phytoliths in <italic>Phragmites communis</italic> in Northeast China</article-title><source>Quaternary Sciences</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>976</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Gao et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silica distribution characteristics in plant-soil systems of typical vegetation communities and ecotones in Min River estuary wetland</article-title><source>Journal of Soil and Water Conservation</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Gao et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal variations of available silica content in marsh soils under the <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion in the Min River estuary</article-title><source>Acta Ecologica Sinica</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>6136</fpage><lpage>6142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5846/stxb201709041593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Grzesiak (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grzesiak</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of soil compaction on root architecture, leaf water status, gas exchange and growth of maize and triticale seedlings</article-title><source>Plant Root</source><year>2009</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3117/plantroot.3.10</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Hou et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogenic silica in intertidal marsh plants and associated sediments of the Yangtze Estuary</article-title><source>Journal of Environmental Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1001-0742(09)60118-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Hou et al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of salinity on silicon, carbon, and nitrogen during decomposition of <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> litter</article-title><source>Acta Ecologica Sinica</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5846/stxb201607261527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Jacobs et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teuchies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oosterlee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The vegetation silica pool in a developing tidal freshwater marsh</article-title><source>Silicon</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12633-012-9136-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Klotzb&#x000fc;cher et al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klotzb&#x000fc;cher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Klotzb&#x000fc;cher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Merbach</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikutta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of agricultural practices on plant-available silicon</article-title><source>Geoderma</source><year>2018</year><volume>331</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geoderma.2018.06.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Li (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on the biomass, nutrient content and C, N reserves of <italic>Betula alnoides</italic> plantation</article-title><year>2013</year><comment>Master Degree.</comment><publisher-name>Guangxi University</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Liu, Zeng &#x00026; Chen (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source>Research of Minjiang River estuary wetland</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Lloret, Casanovas &#x00026; Penuelas (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lloret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanovas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Penuelas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seedling survival of Mediterranean shrubland species in relation to root: shoot ratio, seed size and water and nitrogen use</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2435.1999.00309.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Lu (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methods of soil science and agricultural chemistry analysis</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Agriculture Science and Technology Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Ma, Chen &#x00026; Chu (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial distribution and affecting factors of soil available Si in Shihezi region</article-title><source>Acat Agriculturae Boreali-Occidentalis Sinica</source><year>2016</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Ma &#x00026; Yamaji (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon uptake and accumulation in higher plants</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2006.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Ma &#x00026; Yamaji (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cooperative system of silicon transport in plants</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2015.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25983205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Narayanaswamy &#x00026; Prakash (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayanaswamy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of selected extractants for plant-available silicon in rice soils of southern India</article-title><source>Communications in Soil Science and Plant Analysis</source><year>2010</year><volume>41</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00103621003646063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Poorter, Remkes &#x00026; Lambers (1990)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poorter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Remkes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon and nitrogen economy of 24 wild species differing in relative growth rate</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1990</year><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.94.2.621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16667757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Quern&#x000e9;, Ragueneau &#x00026; Poupart (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quern&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragueneau</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Poupart</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In situ biogenic silica variations in the invasive salt marsh plant, <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>: a possible link with environmental stress</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><year>2012</year><volume>352</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-011-0986-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Savant et al. (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savant</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornd&#x000f6;rfer</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Datnoff</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon nutrition and sugarcane production: a review</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Nutrition</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1853</fpage><lpage>1903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01904169909365761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Schaller, Brackhage &#x00026; Dudel (2012a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackhage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon availability changes structural carbon ratio and phenol content of grasses</article-title><source>Environmental and Experimental Botany</source><year>2012a</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envexpbot.2011.12.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Schaller et al. (2012b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackhage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gessner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ucker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon supply modifies C:N:P stoichiometry and growth of <italic>Phragmites australis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Biology</source><year>2012b</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1438-8677.2011.00537.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22136652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Schaller et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackhage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paasch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ucker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudel</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silica uptake from nanoparticles and silica condensation state in different tissues of <italic>Phragmites australis</italic></article-title><source>Science of the Total Environment</source><year>2013</year><volume>442</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2012.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23178503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Schaller, Hines &#x00026; Brackhage (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackhage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is initial Si concentration determining the influence of warming and N-supply on stoichiometric changes during litter decomposition?</article-title><source>Aquatic Botany</source><year>2017</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquabot.2016.11.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Schaller et al. (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoelynck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon affects nutrient content and ratios of wetland plants</article-title><source>Silicon</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12633-015-9302-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Schaller &#x00026; Struyf (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon controls microbial decay and nutrient release of grass litter during aquatic decomposition</article-title><source>Hydrobiologia</source><year>2013</year><volume>709</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10750-013-1449-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Schoelynck et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoelynck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Backx</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okruszko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silica uptake in aquatic and wetland macrophytes: a strategic choice between silica, lignin and cellulose?</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2010</year><volume>186</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03176.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20136720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Schoelynck et al. (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoelynck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandevenne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Opdekamp</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon-vegetation interaction in multiple ecosystems: a review</article-title><source>Journal of Vegetation Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvs.12055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Schoelynck &#x00026; Struyf (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoelynck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicon in aquatic vegetation</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2435.12614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Simas, Nunes &#x00026; Ferreira (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of global climate change on coastal salt marshes</article-title><source>Ecological Modelling</source><year>2001</year><volume>139</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0304-3800(01)00226-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Singh, Salaria &#x00026; Kaul (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Salaria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of soil compaction on soil physical properties and root growth: a review</article-title><source>International Journal of Food, Agriculture and Veterinary Sciences</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Struyf &#x00026; Conley (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silica: an essential nutrient in wetland biogeochemistry</article-title><source>Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/070126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Struyf et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosimane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Pelt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray-Hudson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Frings</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gondwe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoelynck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of vegetation in the Okavango Delta silica sink</article-title><source>Wetlands</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13157-014-0607-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Struyf et al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribsholt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Middelburg</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Phragmites australis</italic> and silica cycling in tidal wetlands</article-title><source>Aquatic Botany</source><year>2007</year><volume>87</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquabot.2007.05.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Struyf et al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Struyf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribsholt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Middelbulg</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogenic silica in tidal freshwater marsh sediments and vegetation (Schelde estuary, Belgium)</article-title><source>Marine Ecology Progress Series</source><year>2005</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps303051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Theriot et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Conkle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezeshki</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaune</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Will hydrologic restoration of Mississippi River riparian wetlands improve their critical biogeochemical functions?</article-title><source>Ecological Engineering</source><year>2013</year><volume>60</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoleng.2013.07.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Tong et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial variations of carbon, nitrogen and phosphorous in tidal salt marsh soils of the Minjiang River estuary</article-title><source>Geographical Research</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1203</fpage><lpage>1213</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Tong et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting nutrient stocks and litter decomposition in stands of native and invasive species in a sub-tropical estuarine marsh</article-title><source>Environmental Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>111</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2011.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21704985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Weiner (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allocation, plasticity and allometry in plants</article-title><source>Perspectives in Plant Ecology Evolution and Systematics</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1078/1433-8319-00083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Wu, Chen &#x00026; Du (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>GZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of biomass allocation and morphological characteristics to light and nutrient resources for seedlings of three alpine species</article-title><source>Acta Ecologica Sinica</source><year>2010</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Zeng, Zhang &#x00026; Tong (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal dynamics of nitrogen and phosphorus in <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> and <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> in the wetlands of Min River estuary</article-title><source>Wetland Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>Zhai &#x00026; Xue (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the distribution of silica in the porewaters and sediments of the intertidal zone with different plant communities in the Min River estuary</article-title><source>Acta Ecologica Sinica</source><year>2016</year><volume>36</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>6766</fpage><lpage>6776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5846/stxb201501140109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>Zhang (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The analysis of the developments and evolution of the shoal patch outer Minjiang estuary</article-title><source>Journal of Fujian Normal University (Natural Science Edition)</source><year>1991</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>