<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When asked for their perceptions of the impacts climate change has had on tap yield in recent decades, almost half (49%) of the respondents reported no impacts, 32% reported positive or mostly positive impacts, and 19% reported negative or mostly negative impacts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215511.g006" class="xref">Fig 6a</xref>). However, the proportion of producers reporting negative impacts was significantly higher for respondents from lower latitudes (i.e. ≤ 40°) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215511.g006" class="xref">Fig 6b</xref>). This result suggests that maple syrup production in the southern portion of the study area in the U.S. has already been impacted by global warming in recent years, potentially revealing the first manifestation of the expected northward shift of the climatic envelope favorable to sap flow [
 <xref rid="pone.0215511.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. For the next 30 years, a higher proportion (45%) of the respondents are anticipating negative or mostly negative impacts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215511.g006" class="xref">Fig 6a</xref>), with respondents from the left to the center of the political spectrum being more likely to anticipate negative impacts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215511.g006" class="xref">Fig 6c</xref>). These results are somewhat surprising since political view appears to be a stronger predictor of producers’ beliefs about future climate change impacts than personal experience due to past exposure to climate change effects. In other words, while maple syrup producers recognize impacts of climate change based on their personal experience, political ideology is more important in shaping their beliefs about future impacts. Interestingly, a similar result has been found among Idaho’ farmers: while many are noticing changes in precipitations, winter temperatures and growing season lengths, only a few connect these with anthropogenic climate change, indicating that direct experience of climate change manifestations is not sufficient to overcome the influence of political views [
 <xref rid="pone.0215511.ref092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>].
</p>
