<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para530" class="p">
 <boxed-text id="cetextbox10" class="boxed-text">
  <caption class="caption">
   <title class="title">Research in context</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="para540" class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Evidence before this study</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para550" class="p">An important feature of global climate change is increasing air temperatures across most areas of the world. Extremes of atmospheric temperature are a known health hazard, since good health relies on maintaining the core body temperature within a narrow range (36·5–37·5°C) under different external environmental conditions. If core body temperature increases to more than 38–39°C, there is a risk of heat exhaustion. At core body temperatures of more than 40°C, serious heat stroke can cause death. Evaporation of sweat is a key mechanism for cooling the body when the external temperature is above 35°C. In high-humidity environments, evaporation of sweat is inhibited, so this important natural heat loss mechanism is undermined. Many tropical and subtropical areas can already experience high levels of heat stress annually for several months of the year. Ongoing climate change is projected to substantially increase temperatures in many densely populated areas. In assessments of the health risks associated with increasing global temperature, it is essential to consider temperature, humidity, and the heat generated from physical activity. Acclimatisation to high temperature does occur, but there is a limit, and combinations of high temperature and high humidity can lead core temperature to reach problematic levels.</p>
  <p id="para560" class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Added value of this study</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para570" class="p">Most epidemiological studies and impact assessments have analysed the effects of high temperatures on mortality during heat waves and have focused on older people. In this study, we analysed the effects of temperature, humidity, and work rate on adults in their daily activities (workability) and on their physiological ability to cope with heat (survivability). By use of bias-corrected climate model data to calculate the wet-bulb globe temperature, the most widely used heat-stress index used to assess health risks in physical work situations, we found that risks to workability and survivability increase with modelled global temperature changes, particularly in tropical or subtropical regions. To our knowledge, no previous peer-reviewed publication has presented such an analysis, which projects changes in heat exposure risk based on thresholds for work and survival, and which contributes to the accumulating evidence of the serious planetary health threats of climate change.</p>
  <p id="para580" class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Implications of all the available evidence</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para590" class="p">In combination with previous reports, our assessment of health effects highlights the importance of environmental heat for global population health. The heat stress that we have evaluated affects the active adult population in many countries during the hot season, and it is not just restricted to those experiencing extreme heat waves. During the hot season, people are already physically acclimatised and adaptation via air conditioning in residences and workplaces can reduce heat exposure risk. However, it is unlikely that people receiving low incomes will be able to afford efficient cooling systems and many work situations cannot always be protected with such systems. In many cases, those affected by extreme heat will receive greatly reduced income for at least 1 month a year, which will increase the risk of impoverishment. This new evidence on the effects of climate change should inform future policies for the protection of planetary health via mitigation of climate change, highlighting the importance of limiting global temperature increases in line with Paris Agreement targets.</p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
