<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study can inform future assessments in several ways. First, while species level or ecoregion analyses may be of ecological interest, spatial distribution analyses intended to inform stock assessment or management should be based on spatial boundaries consistent with those used in the stock assessment. All stocks in this analysis had at least one spatial indicator that was different in terms of magnitude or direction than previous analyses that did not use stock boundaries. This is a general principle that extends beyond stock assessment and management of groundfish under United States jurisdiction in the Northwest Atlantic. Second, very few of the stock assessment packages currently used in the United States can represent spatial structure explicitly [
  <a rid="pone.0196583.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196583.ref053">53</a>]. Should future advancements enable the incorporation of spatial indicators as data inputs, such indices must be based on stock boundaries, just as the survey indices that are used to tune catch data are. Finally, future spatial distribution analyses for a particular stock should be age-based, as ontogenetic changes may be masked when the data are not disaggregated by age [
  <a rid="pone.0196583.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196583.ref027">27</a>]. This was not done in the present study because the goal was to examine trends across multiple stocks, rather than the spatiotemporal distribution of one stock in detail.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study shows that fishing pressure, in addition to the previously established role of climate [
  <a rid="pone.0196583.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196583.ref006">6</a>], influences the spatial distribution of groundfish in the Northwest Atlantic. More broadly, this study is one of a small but growing body of literature to demonstrate that fishing pressure, in addition to climate, has an effect on the spatial distribution of marine resources. It has recently been shown that fishing pressure can cause synchronous changes in stock abundance at spatial and temporal scales comparable to those attributed to climate forcing [
  <a rid="pone.0196583.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196583.ref054">54</a>]. Altogether this mounting body of evidence necessitates that future work must consider both fishing pressure and climate when examining mechanisms underlying fish distribution shifts.
 </p>
</sec>
