<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33405-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="ece33405-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and climate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field work was carried out in the suburbs of Ji'An (27°06′N, 115°02′E), Jiangxi Province, China, from 2010 to 2016. The study area is bounded by Tianyu‐Qingyuan Mountain with an average altitude 300 m to the east and Ganjiang River in the other three directions (Figures 
   <a rid="ece33405-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0001">1</a> and 
   <a rid="ece33405-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0002">2</a>). Residential areas were interlaced with hilly grounds, water bodies, and paddy fields with an average altitude of 75 m in the whole study area. The forest environments where Masked Laughingthrushes lived were broken into pieces, unevenly and discretely distributed in the whole study area (Ke et al., 
   <a rid="ece33405-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0032">2011</a>). Climatic data were collected at a weather station (no. 57799) at the southwest of the study area. A subtropical monsoon climate is the typical climate, and the long‐term (1980–2016) average annual temperature was 19.0°C, with a minimum of 6.5°C in January and a maximum of 30.5°C in July. Annual total precipitation was 1504 mm, 80% of which fell between January and August.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33405-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The distribution of suitable habitats (red circles) of the population distribution of Masked laughingthrushes in a geographical map</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-7-8719-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33405-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>A sketch map of the population distribution of Masked laughingthrushes showing the fragmentation of suitable habitats and the relative isolation by surrounding environments. Black areas indicate the fragmented suitable habitats, which are interlaced with small villages, paddy fields and lower hills and surrounded by Tianyu‐Qingyuan Mountain, Ganjiang River and residential area of Ji'An city. Dashed boxes illustrate the division of the 12 subpopulations and subareas. Lines with numbers show the topographic contour line of 150 m, 300 m, and 450 m of the two mountains</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-7-8719-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33405-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Group size counting</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Masked laughingthrushes initiate reproduction in February and end in August of each year. During each breeding season, we surveyed the whole study area territory by territory and observed all social groups by conducting song playback. The songs were collected from populations out of the study area. In this study, it is difficult to color‐band all the birds, especially the adults, and there was also no DNA analysis for member relationships. While some birds were marked during nestling stage, they were observed staying at home with their parents in the next year. This suggested that group members are families. These family groups showed strong adherence to their territories and actively defended them. When we played the songs of the birds, Masked laughingthrushes shyly responded in the early breeding season (March to May) but reacted strongly in the other stages. When there was only one group in the censusing area, we enticed them to a relatively open area for easy bird counting. In some situations, there could be more than one group appeared after the playback, these groups reacted not only to the songs we played but also strongly to the each other. They flew to their territory boundaries and defended it by active singing. If there was no actual invasion, they would gradually return to a normal state and retreat from the boundaries. Hence, it is not difficult for us to distinguish the territory boundaries of each family group and the individual affiliations.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Group size was the maximum number of birds in each group territory among all the visual observations in a same season (which could have included repeated observations of the same group of birds on different days). The group sizes based on more observations were considered to be more reliable (in single observations, some individuals could have been missed). Group sizes of the birds may fluctuate in different seasons, and different groups may initiate their reproduction asynchronously. The birds behaved in a strongly skulking manner due to nest protection in the early breeding season (February to May), which led to difficulty in counting group size for all the groups. In this study, we use the data of group sizes in the latter breeding season (June to August), in which season the birds respond more actively to playback, and the data of group sizes were more complete than those in the early breeding season. In this study, fledglings born in the current season were excluded in the group sizes, because they did not participate in territory defense or group formation at the start of the breeding season. These fledglings can be easily distinguished by the traits of lighter feather color and timid behavior in their early fledging stage.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33405-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat suitability and measurement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to characteristics of vegetation composition and spatial structure, the habitat in our study area can be roughly distinguished into three types of compartmental patches with relatively distinct boundaries: (1) dense living grasses or bushes on the ground with dense or sparse trees; (2) bared grounds with sparse trees; and (3) sufficient ground litter under sparse trees. Masked laughingthrushes were usually foraging and breeding in those habitats characterized by sparse trees and a small amount of litter. All these types of patches in which we observed the behaviors of foraging and breeding of the birds (bird presence) more than three times were considered suitable habitats for the birds. The territory was defined as the area used for living and breeding (Maher &amp; Lott, 
   <a rid="ece33405-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0045">1995</a>). Territories of different social groups were distinguished by territory defense behavior and the natural boundaries of the patches where there were no neighboring groups. Based on field observations of the natural boundary of habitat patches and territory defensive behaviors, we finally delineated the distribution map of the birds (Figures 
   <a rid="ece33405-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0001">1</a> and 
   <a rid="ece33405-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0002">2</a>). We were then able to measure the areas of all the patches of suitable habitats. All the areas were measured using Google Earth Pro software.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33405-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subarea/subpopulation division</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For territorial bird species, spatially closed social groups may be close relatives due to limited dispersal. They breed independently in summer but may amalgamate during a harsh winter, while communications between those spatially distant social groups may be limited due to territorial defense or the long distance between territories (Ke, 
   <a rid="ece33405-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0029">2009</a>). Intraspecific competition for resources, one of the main density‐dependent processes, will work mainly on a local scale in territorial species (Newton, 
   <a rid="ece33405-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0049">1992</a>). Hence, for a territorial bird species living in strongly fragmented habitats, distant habitat patches can be seen as relatively independent land islands, in which the utilization of ecological resources is relatively exclusive. Similarly, distant groups or territories can be considered relatively independent. In contrast, neighboring habitat patches may be shared by neighboring groups across different seasons through group amalgamation or generational replacement. Although the members of the social groups may change across years or seasons, these neighboring habitat patches can be looked as a whole, which is shared by the continuum of family generations of these neighboring social groups. Correspondingly, the continuum can be looked as a subpopulation. Hence, the perspective can be changed as to how a subarea of the suitable habitat supports the social groups in the subpopulation across the years, regardless of who the group members are and where they are from.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Masked laughingthrushes live year‐round in territories within social groups, and their suitable habitats are partitioned by large areas of paddy field, water bodies, and higher mountains (Ke et al., 
   <a rid="ece33405-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0032">2011</a>; Figures 
   <a rid="ece33405-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0001">1</a> and 
   <a rid="ece33405-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0002">2</a>). Among these fragmented patches of suitable habitats, one family may occupy several patches, and one patch may also sometimes include several territories. In total, there were approximately 50 family groups scattered among these patches each year with an average nearest distance of 600 m (ranging from 230 m to 1,200 m) between territories (Ke et al., 
   <a rid="ece33405-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0032">2011</a>). Their territories may vary across the years because of new territory foundation, old territory shifting, territory budding, disappearing, and amalgamation. We recorded the geographic coordinates of the central points of all the territories over the six‐year period. Based on the location information, we clustered the contiguous habitat patches into subareas using the centroid linkage and clustered corresponding social groups across years into subpopulations. The total area of all the patches in a subarea is considered to be the area of suitable habitats for the subpopulation in the subarea.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33405-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MGS and MGD averaged for different time durations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean group size and mean group density for the subpopulations in certain subareas were calculated by the data combined for each year or two to five consecutive years. The MGDs were calculated as the mean number of social groups divided by the total area of suitable habitats in each subarea. We marked the MGS as 
   <span class="italic">Gx</span> (G0, G2… and G23, G34…, etc. represented the MGS data of the year 2010, 2012… and 2012‐2013, 2013‐2014…, etc.), and MGD as 
   <span class="italic">Dx</span> (similarly, D0, D2… D23, D34 …D023456 to represent the MGD for corresponding time durations). Because the data in the year 2011 were not included, the data of 2010 were only used to calculate G0, D0 for 1 year, but G023456 and D023456 were used for all 6 years in this study.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33405-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using MGD as independent variables and MGS as the dependent variable, the response curves of MGS to MGD are fitted by a quadratic function and modeled by quadratic regression. First, we explore the correlations between 
   <span class="italic">Gx</span> and D023456 to show how MGS varied with long‐term MGD. Second, we explore the correlation between 
   <span class="italic">Gx</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Dx</span> with same time durations (
   <span class="italic">x</span>) and try to find a lower limit of years for the stable correlation that can be tested. Finally, we made a 
   <span class="italic">p</span>‐value matrix for the correlations between 
   <span class="italic">Gx</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Dx</span> (related combination by changing the time duration (
   <span class="italic">x</span>) for both parameters) to show how MGS varied with MGD. When the correlations between MGS and MGD for all combinations of a certain time duration (from one to six years) were significant, the correlation was considered to be stable, and the time duration was considered that required for a stable correlation that can be tested. The smallest of these time durations is considered to be the lower limit of the time duration for the “long term.”
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in group sizes among subpopulations or across years were examined using one‐way ANOVAs. All statistics were performed using SPSS software 20.0 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> values of all correlations are provided. Probabilities are two tailed, and the significance level is set at α = 0.05. All values given were mean ± 1
   <span class="italic">SD</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
