<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33405-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Group size counting</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Masked laughingthrushes initiate reproduction in February and end in August of each year. During each breeding season, we surveyed the whole study area territory by territory and observed all social groups by conducting song playback. The songs were collected from populations out of the study area. In this study, it is difficult to color‐band all the birds, especially the adults, and there was also no DNA analysis for member relationships. While some birds were marked during nestling stage, they were observed staying at home with their parents in the next year. This suggested that group members are families. These family groups showed strong adherence to their territories and actively defended them. When we played the songs of the birds, Masked laughingthrushes shyly responded in the early breeding season (March to May) but reacted strongly in the other stages. When there was only one group in the censusing area, we enticed them to a relatively open area for easy bird counting. In some situations, there could be more than one group appeared after the playback, these groups reacted not only to the songs we played but also strongly to the each other. They flew to their territory boundaries and defended it by active singing. If there was no actual invasion, they would gradually return to a normal state and retreat from the boundaries. Hence, it is not difficult for us to distinguish the territory boundaries of each family group and the individual affiliations.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Group size was the maximum number of birds in each group territory among all the visual observations in a same season (which could have included repeated observations of the same group of birds on different days). The group sizes based on more observations were considered to be more reliable (in single observations, some individuals could have been missed). Group sizes of the birds may fluctuate in different seasons, and different groups may initiate their reproduction asynchronously. The birds behaved in a strongly skulking manner due to nest protection in the early breeding season (February to May), which led to difficulty in counting group size for all the groups. In this study, we use the data of group sizes in the latter breeding season (June to August), in which season the birds respond more actively to playback, and the data of group sizes were more complete than those in the early breeding season. In this study, fledglings born in the current season were excluded in the group sizes, because they did not participate in territory defense or group formation at the start of the breeding season. These fledglings can be easily distinguished by the traits of lighter feather color and timid behavior in their early fledging stage.</p>
</sec>
