<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33405-sec-0017" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long‐term MGD: a better index for habitat quality</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is often difficult to find a good measure of habitat quality for most species or populations. Some researchers have used time budgets to reveal favored habitat types (Brown &amp; Balda, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0008">1977</a>), vegetation structure (Brown &amp; Brown, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0009">1981</a>), or a measure of the available food resources (Macroberts &amp; Macroberts, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0043">1976</a>; Trail, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0069">1980</a>) as potential indices of territory quality in different species. None of the above indices can be generally used to measure the habitat quality for all species. However, we can expect the long‐term MGD to be a better index for habitat quality in populations of territorial species, due to following reasons.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long‐term MGD is the synthesized results of all ecological factors across years. Many studies suggested that long‐term mean territory size is inversely related to food abundance per unit area (Holmes, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0028">1970</a>; Myers et al., 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0048">1979</a>; Seastedt &amp; MacLean, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0060">1979</a>; Simon, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0061">1975</a>; Smith &amp; Shugart, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0065">1987</a>; Stenger, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0067">1958</a>), and thus, it is inversely related to long‐term MGD. Because the food abundance per unit area is one important indicator of habitat quality (Emlen, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0019">1982</a>), both long‐term mean territory size and long‐term MGD can also be used as indicators of habitat quality. And in fact, the long‐term MGD is a synthesized result of food distribution, forage investment, nest site selection, habitat saturation, and population dynamics in the wild populations of territorial species, which are the components of overall habitat quality (Franzblau &amp; Collins, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0021">1980</a>; Fretwell &amp; Lucas, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0022">1969</a>; Orians, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0052">1971</a>). Carrying capacity of certain area of habitats is affected by the abundance and distribution of resources and by how individuals compete for these limiting resources (Ayllon, Almodovar, Nicola, Parra, &amp; Elvira, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0002">2012</a>; Rees, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0055">1992</a>). The stable quadratic correlation between long‐term MGS and MGD in this study also supports the hypothesis that long‐term MGD can be used as an indicator of the long‐term habitat quality, and the period of the “long term” is a time duration of three or four years in Masked laughingthrushes. In addition, MGD is an indicator that is more easily to be recorded and estimated compared with other detailed ecological factors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The long‐term MGD has reflected that the natural resources in certain area of suitable habitats are utilized together by all social groups and their generations. For one certain social group, all the members exclusively utilize the resources in their territory in certain seasons. For different social groups, neighboring ones may breed independently in summer but amalgamate in winter; new groups may bud from territories of their parents, and one group may expand their territory to neighboring territories after the original “owners” disappeared (Ke, 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0029">2009</a>). While those distant social groups have very limited influences on natural resources in the other's habitats. Hence, all the natural resources across years in the certain area of habitats were utilized together by those social groups and their generations living in the habitat. The long‐term MGD reflects the upper limit of carrying capacity at group level.
 </p>
</sec>
