<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33405-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and climate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field work was carried out in the suburbs of Ji'An (27°06′N, 115°02′E), Jiangxi Province, China, from 2010 to 2016. The study area is bounded by Tianyu‐Qingyuan Mountain with an average altitude 300 m to the east and Ganjiang River in the other three directions (Figures 
  <a rid="ece33405-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0001">1</a> and 
  <a rid="ece33405-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33405-fig-0002">2</a>). Residential areas were interlaced with hilly grounds, water bodies, and paddy fields with an average altitude of 75 m in the whole study area. The forest environments where Masked Laughingthrushes lived were broken into pieces, unevenly and discretely distributed in the whole study area (Ke et al., 
  <a rid="ece33405-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33405-bib-0032">2011</a>). Climatic data were collected at a weather station (no. 57799) at the southwest of the study area. A subtropical monsoon climate is the typical climate, and the long‐term (1980–2016) average annual temperature was 19.0°C, with a minimum of 6.5°C in January and a maximum of 30.5°C in July. Annual total precipitation was 1504 mm, 80% of which fell between January and August.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33405-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The distribution of suitable habitats (red circles) of the population distribution of Masked laughingthrushes in a geographical map</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-7-8719-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33405-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>A sketch map of the population distribution of Masked laughingthrushes showing the fragmentation of suitable habitats and the relative isolation by surrounding environments. Black areas indicate the fragmented suitable habitats, which are interlaced with small villages, paddy fields and lower hills and surrounded by Tianyu‐Qingyuan Mountain, Ganjiang River and residential area of Ji'An city. Dashed boxes illustrate the division of the 12 subpopulations and subareas. Lines with numbers show the topographic contour line of 150 m, 300 m, and 450 m of the two mountains</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-7-8719-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
