<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we used an updated
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup> version of a meta-database recently used
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> to evaluate the global imprint of climate change on distributional changes in marine life that accounts for a total of 270 range shifts reported in the literature where climate change was proposed as a driver of the shift (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>). The dataset spans multiple taxonomic groups and types of responses (i.e., shifts in population centroid and leading and trailing edges). Using generalized linear models, we employed a model selection approach
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> to predict observed distribution shifts resulting from (see Methods, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1)</xref> (i) the changes in local climate conditions using the velocity of climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>, (ii) the taxonomic identity of the species involved, (iii) the directional agreement between spatial gradients in sea surface temperature (SST) and ocean currents, and (iv) the location of a given shift within a species range. To define local directional agreement between spatial thermal gradients and ocean currents, we propose the use of the cosine of the difference in angles associated with both parameters (see Methods). This new, simple metric generates an index that ranges from −1 (for ocean currents in the opposite direction to spatial thermal gradients) to 1 (for currents and gradients in the same direction) (Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Both the questions being addressed and the processes involved are directly transferable to freshwater species and all terrestrial organisms relying on aerial dispersal processes, including many plants, insects, and birds. 
</p>
