<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aim 1: what to conserve?</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social learning can create behavioural variants that form valuable units of biodiversity. When information consistently travels from parents to offspring, social learning can act as a form of non-genetic inheritance (Laland et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2001</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">2009</a>), which can drive population differences in behaviour. When social learning leads to the adoption of fitness relevant behaviours or drives reproductive isolation in sympatric groups, socially learned behavioural variants can shrink effective population sizes, thereby magnifying threats that would otherwise be considered over a geographical area (Whitehead et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" href="#CR134">2004</a>; Ryan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">2006</a>). Additionally, culturally derived behaviours and the conformity they promote can put certain populations at greater risk than others. For example, even though orcas (
  <span class="italic">Orcinus orca</span>) are capable of capturing a variety of prey, southern resident populations (a socially and culturally distinct group) mainly hunt chinook salmon (
  <span class="italic">Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</span>) (Ford and Ellis 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2006</a>) and are therefore more vulnerable than other groups of orcas if salmon populations decline (Whitehead 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">2010</a>). Finally, it has been argued that some group-specific, socially learned behaviours are worthy of conserving in their own right because their loss would result in unwanted homogenization of species’ behaviours (Slabbekoorn and Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">2002</a>; Whitehead 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">2010</a>). For example, the diversity of song in Dupont’s lark (
  <span class="italic">Chersophilus duponti</span>) declines as habitat fragmentation increases (Laiolo 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2008</a>), a type of loss akin to the disappearance of human languages (Laiolo and Jovani 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2007</a>). Thus, quantifying stable, socially learned behaviours can inform conservation management about population vulnerability and behavioural variation worth saving (Whitehead 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">2010</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
