<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aim 2: what threatens biodiversity?</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social learning can benefit animals where it helps them adjust to human induced changes in the environment, but it can also prove detrimental where it spreads behaviours that lead to human-wildlife conflict. Therefore, predicting where social learning occurs can be important for assessing threats posed by human activities. In species that rely on the social transfer of information for survival, identifying where human activities could disrupt information transfer is essential for accurate threat forecasting. For example, chemical pollutants such as heavy metals can blunt fishes’ responses to conspecific alarm cues (Mirza et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">2009</a>), which would reduce their ability to learn socially about predators. Meanwhile, anthropogenic noise can distract attention and mask auditory communication channels (Shannon et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2015</a>), such that individuals would be less likely to pick up on alarm vocalizations that could lead to learning about predators (Grade and Sieving 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2016</a>). In this way, identifying where survival mostly rely on social learning can help prioritize which species or populations most need protection from processes that interfere with information transfer, such as chemical pollution or anthropogenic noise.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As well as disrupting learning channels, human activity can also reduce the diversity of information carried socially in populations. The loss of socially learned information as a result of population decline can have long-term consequences that threat forecasting should strive to evaluate. For example, it has been suggested that the failure of the North Atlantic right whale (
  <span class="italic">Eubalaena glacialis</span>) population to rebound after whaling was banned might be due to the their loss of socially retained information about feeding habitats (Whitehead et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" href="#CR134">2004</a>). Thus, accurate assessments of species recovery rates may need to consider the social learned information that populations carry when determining their relevant Allee effects (i.e. inverse density dependence; fitness-driving processes that are magnified as population size decreases; Stephens et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">1999</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a more positive sense, the occurrence of social learning amid human-induced habitat changes can also have net benefits for species survival where it allows animals to flexibly respond to threats. Social learning can help spread novel behavioural variants that facilitate animals’ ability to adjust to environmental changes (van der Post and Hogeweg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2009</a>; Brown 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2012</a>; Rubenstein 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">2016</a>), such as the uptake of innovations (entirely novel behaviours) that allow for the adoption of new foods or foraging techniques (Ramsey et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">2007</a>). For example, black rats (
  <span class="italic">Rattus rattus</span>) in Israel created a new foraging niche and expanded their range into nearby forests by adopting a socially learned foraging technique that allowed them to eat pine cones (Terkel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">1996</a>). More generally, foraging innovations have been linked to invasion success, at least in birds (Sol and Lefebvre 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">2000</a>; Sol et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">2002</a>). Meanwhile in primates, species-level measures of foraging innovations are correlated with social learning (Reader and Laland 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">2002</a>). Thus, social learning of novel foraging techniques could more widely accelerate behavioural adjustments to changing habitats, and those species which are most innovative might be most likely to spread novel behaviour. Models that aim to predict the spread of invasive species or the resilience of species to shifting climate could benefit from incorporating this information (Keith and Bull 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The acquisition of novel behaviour and the expansion of niches via social learning may equally serve as a threat to biodiversity when innovations put species in conflict with people. There have been documented cases where social learning has been implicated in aiding the spread of conflict or problematic behaviours, such as the depredation of fishing catches by sperm whales (
  <span class="italic">Physeter macrocephalus</span>) (Schakner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">2014a</a>), crop raiding behaviours by African elephants (
  <span class="italic">Loxodonta Africana</span>) (Chiyo et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2012</a>) and spreading bears’ and dolphins’ reliance on anthropogenic foods (Mazur and Seher 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2008</a>; Donaldson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2012</a>). These types of conflict can foster negative attitudes towards wildlife, can reduce support for local conservation programs and lead to persecution or culling of conflict species (Mpanduji et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">2004</a>; Thirgood et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" href="#CR117">2005</a>). Additionally, since social learning does not always spread the most efficient or rewarding behaviour (Boyd and Richerson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1985</a>; Laland and Williams 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1998</a>; Giraldeau et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2002</a>), animals may socially learn conflict behaviours despite other, equally beneficial options being available. For example, in the case of black bears (
  <span class="italic">Ursus americanus</span>), Mazur and Seher (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2008</a>) found that cubs obtain preferences for human-developed or natural habitat from their mother, regardless of the presence of both habitat types in the area. Moreover, the bears in developed habitats were 45 times more likely to feed on human-produced food, even though a third of these bears would not survive past their first year due to conflict-related deaths. Therefore, conflict behaviours that spread via social learning can persist even if they reduce fitness. Overall, the likelihood that species will acquire and spread either adaptive or maladaptive behaviours is vitally important to predicting future resilience or conflict with humans.
 </p>
</sec>
