<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation applications that target social learning biases</div>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given how many biases can influence social learning, is it wise to advise conservation managers to simply expose individuals to conspecifics if they want to increase a behaviour and limit their exposure if they want to prevent a behaviour from spreading? This is the tactic often employed or suggested (Shier 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" href="#CR107">2016</a>), but crucial details about the species, context and cues could obfuscate the outcomes, even if their social system allowed such manipulations. By accruing many examples of biases and highlighting places for future development, this paper is not meant to imply that social learning is too variable to be used. It does mean, however, that there are dangers with relying on studies from a single species or context to guide the development of novel management protocols in other species or contexts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the field is a long way from developing relevant and useful guidelines for all species and situations, there has been progress in the development of techniques in some areas, such as species translocations that train animals socially about appropriate behaviours prior to release (e.g. Walters et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" href="#CR130">2010</a>). Augmenting these existing practices with insights generated from research on social learning biases will only strengthen their effectiveness. Additionally, there are areas where social learning biases are known, but techniques targeting them have not yet been employed in conservation practice, for instance, in mitigating social learning interference of chemical or auditory alarm cues in areas where noise or chemical pollution is known to interfere with learning channels. These areas represent fertile opportunities for experts in social learning to use their knowledge to shape research and consult with conservationists in cases where they could help solve specific problems. Despite these promising developments, however, there are also high priority areas where more fundamental research is still needed before conservationists can broadly use social learning to predict and mitigate threats, such as the spread of human-wildlife conflict behaviours.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One way of identifying such holes in the literature is by conducting systematic reviews and maps of social learning in conservation practice. Evidence-based systematic reviews bridge the gap between academics and managers by presenting a weighted overview of all studies relating to a topic, including information from the “grey” literature where conservation management outcomes often are reported (Pullin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">2007</a>). Systematic maps operate on a similar premise but aim to outline existing knowledge gaps (Haddaway et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2016</a>). These types of evidence-based reviews are gaining momentum (Sutherland et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">2004</a>; Pullin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">2007</a>; Walsh et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129" href="#CR129">2014</a>) and deserve to be employed with behavioural interventions in mind (Greggor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2014a</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2016a</a>; Schakner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">2014b</a>). Not only will such reviews direct managers in the use of existing social learning interventions but also will help prioritize areas where future studies of social learning could be most influential in management contexts. Conservationists are only likely to adopt animal social learning tactics when managers can be provided with evidence that it improves outcomes over existing methods.
 </p>
</sec>
