<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cue-based biases</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Certain cue-response pairings are easier to learn than others. Stimuli will be more easily learned the more they (a) are conspicuous, (b) reliably precede an outcome and (c) are evolutionarily relevant (Shettleworth 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">2010</a>). Social learning will occur more quickly and strongly with increasingly salient cues because they are more likely to attract the attention and emotional reaction of an observer. For example, exposure to a conspecific reacting fearfully is more effective than just broadcasting alarm calls alone (Curio 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1988</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Learning is also based on contingency. If two cues do not reliably coincide, animals are not likely to learn socially about them. For example, even in species that can learn socially, social learning may not occur in the wild if animals never observe the behaviour they are expected to learn. For example, the planigale (
  <span class="italic">Planigale maculate</span>) is a small Australian mammal that is threatened because it consumes a toxic, invasive predator, the cane toad (
  <span class="italic">Rhinella marina</span>). Although planigales are capable of avoiding toads through taste aversion learning, and are likely capable of learning socially, there is no evidence that they socially learn to avoid toads (Box and Gibson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2006</a>; Webb et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" href="#CR131">2008</a>; Llewelyn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">2010</a>). Presumably, all knowledgeable individuals that individually learn to avoid the toads do not produce social information about toads because they avoid interacting with them. So, unless species commonly forage in groups where they could observe “disgust” responses (e.g. Mason 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">1988</a>), they are not likely to learn socially in the wild about novel, poisonous food. Predicting the frequency of social information that individuals are likely to encounter is, therefore, an integral part of predicting the spread of socially learned behaviour.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the ecological relevance of stimuli is crucial for determining whether it will spread socially. In the case of socially acquired predator avoidance, fear-relevant stimuli are more likely to be learned than fear-irrelevant stimuli because the process is adaptively biased to facilitate escape from danger but to limit the amount of time wasted on false alarms (Griffin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2004</a>). Therefore, the information gathered during fear conditioning tends to be content, not context specific, such that animals respond any time they encounter that fear stimulus, irrespective of location (although some species do generalize their socially learned threat responses if they occupy risky environments; Ferrari et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2009</a>). It is not always easy to predict what types of stimuli can be associated with predatory threats, since individuals have been shown to socially acquire fears of inanimate objects, such as a coloured plastic bottle, or of non-predatory species, such as goldfish, although not always as strongly as natural fear stimuli (Curio 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1988</a>; Chivers and Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">1994</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
