<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Learning is biased</div>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animals perceive, remember and act on information from the environment in a biased way. All animals, including ourselves, filter irrelevant details from the information that we perceive and learn about. This filtering process is shaped by natural and sexual selection, such that each species is primed to attend to and learn about the types of information that it most needs to survive and reproduce (Shettleworth 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">2010</a>). For example, since it has been evolutionarily advantageous for a generalist scavenger like a rat to avoid food that causes illness, rats rapidly associate taste cues with feeling ill, even after a single encounter (Garcia et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">1974</a>), a process called conditioned taste aversion. However, rats fail to make the same association when a light instead of the taste of food precedes the feeling of illness (i.e. the Garcia effect). In contrast, other species that consume a single food type, such as vampire bats (
  <span class="italic">Desmodus rotundus</span>), fail to show taste aversion learning (Ratcliffe et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">2003</a>). Therefore, not all stimuli are equally likely to cause learning and not all species are equally likely to learn from the same stimuli. The guiding principles of learning predict that stimuli which are more perceptually salient, predictable and biologically relevant are more likely to be learned (Shettleworth 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">2010</a>). Such learning biases are widespread in the animal kingdom.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many of these same biases apply when considering social learning because it involves similar associative learning mechanisms, but with attention drawn towards social cues (Heyes 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">1994</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2012</a>; Dawson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2013</a>; Leadbeater 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2015</a>). For example, rhesus monkeys (
  <span class="italic">Macaca mulatta</span>) will learn socially to fear snakes, an evolutionarily relevant predator, but will not learn to fear flowers, even if they see demonstrators reacting fearfully towards them (Mineka and Cook 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">1988</a>; Cook and Mineka 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">1989</a>). Despite the similarities between social and asocial learning, predicting whether individuals will use social information relies on understanding on an additional layer of biases that guide attention towards the demonstrator. Both vertebrates and invertebrates exhibit social learning biases or “strategies” that can sometimes offer conflicting predictions about “when”, “where”, and “from whom” animals copy information, depending on the species, the context and time of year (Kendal et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2005</a>; Rendell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2011</a>; Grüter and Leadbeater 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2014</a>; Greggor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2016b</a>). For example, female guppies (
  <span class="italic">Poecilia reticulata</span>) only copy older females (Dugatkin and Godin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">1993</a>), whereas squirrel monkeys (
  <span class="italic">Saimiri</span>) will copy individuals of either sex (Hopper et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2013</a>). How then should a manager predict which sex will spread information in a different species?
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When scrutinized in this way, certain gaps in our knowledge about social learning highlight how difficult predictions about the social spread of novel behaviour can be. For example, there is lots of evidence that animals learn socially about what, where and how they should eat, especially during development (Galef and Giraldeau 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2001</a>; Visalberghi and Addessi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127" href="#CR127">2003</a>; Thornton and McAuliffe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122" href="#CR122">2006</a>; Thornton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" href="#CR118">2008</a>; Thornton and Clutton-Brock 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">2011</a>). In contrast, there is less research about how wild animals socially learn about what not to eat when encountering novel foods in adulthood (Galef and Giraldeau 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2001</a>), although there is evidence that some species may socially acquire food avoidance (Mason and Reidinger 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">1982</a>; Snowdon and Boe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">2003</a>). Predicting the occurrence of social learning is complicated because biases can differ at several levels: between habitats, between species, between individuals and between the cues that individuals encounter. Each of these types of biases is discussed separately below, but in reality, they are overlapping processes in which several might apply in a given situation. Every case discussed where current theory fails to predict the outcome of these biases offers a prime opportunity for future research that advances both social learning knowledge and conservation aims.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat driven biases</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In theory, social learning should be favoured over individual learning when animals are uncertain or acquiring information individually is costly (Rendell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2011</a>), and should be favoured in environments that are variable enough to promote learning as opposed to genetic adaptation, but not too variable such that learned information is quickly outdated (Laland and Kendal 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2003</a>). Additionally, the value and variability of resources have also been suggested to influence greater use of social information when competition is high (Smolla et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">2015</a>). Even though theories about what conditions should favour social learning have been well explored (see list in Fragaszy and Perry 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2003</a>; pg. 34), predicting where social learning will actually occur is challenging (Rendell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2011</a>), especially in the wild. Empirical validation is needed for a range of these theories. As a first step, the theory and modelling about what optimal level of environmental variability most encourages social learning need to be mapped onto the real-world conditions of change that animals currently experience because of human influences.
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There have been but a handful of empirical field tests of the hypotheses that social learning should be favoured in conditions of mid-level environmental variability. Wilkinson and Boughman (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">1999</a>) looked at whether the rate at which feeding patches disappeared—a proxy for environmental variability—predicted species’ use of social information at several communal roosts in three bat species that differed in foraging ecology. They found that they could predict the relative amount that each species followed conspecifics out of the roost based on how often bats foraged unsuccessfully on their own. However, their prediction that sufficiently high patch variability would select against social learning in one of their study species was not supported with the data. Such experiments in other wild systems are central to predicting whether social learning propensities will increase or decrease as conditions change. Tests of the propensity for social learning across urban and rural habitats, for instance, where variability is proposed to differ, would be hugely informative. Such tests will help inform predictions about which environments impacted by humans are most likely to interfere with or generate social learning.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species-based biases</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species differ in their propensity to learn. However, species ranging from bumblebees (
   <span class="italic">Bombus terrestris</span>) (Worden and Papaj 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139" href="#CR139">2005</a>) to chimpanzees (
   <span class="italic">Pan troglodytes</span>) (Whiten et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" href="#CR135">1999</a>) are routine social learners. Therefore, social learning is perhaps better predicted by the circumstance in question, rather than by assumptions about the learning capacities of the species involved (Laland and Kendal 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2003</a>). Species do not have to be social to learn socially (Wilkinson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" href="#CR136">2010</a>), but social species may have more opportunities for social learning. Thus, social learning is expected to be more common in social as opposed to solitary species (Roper 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">1986</a>; Lee 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">1991</a>; Lefebvre et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">1996</a>; Lefebvre and Giraldeau 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">1996</a>; Reader and Lefebvre 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">2001</a>). However, a species’ social system alone cannot predict the occurrence of social learning (Thornton and McAuliffe 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" href="#CR121">2015</a>; Thornton et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123" href="#CR123">2016</a>). There are species that may seem like good candidates for social learning, such as spotted hyenas (
   <span class="italic">Crocuta crocuta</span>), that live in social groups and are opportunistic foragers, but for which social learning does not influence the uptake of novel behaviours in foraging tasks (Benson-Amram et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2014</a>). Such exceptions are not only interesting from an academic standpoint, but explaining why such exceptions exist is crucial to predicting the use of social learning in lesser studied species of conservation concern.
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In some cases, there are easily identifiable reasons why a species may not learn socially. For example, alarm behaviour is less likely to lead to social learning in species where alarms do not reliably predict a high threat of predators (Griffin, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2004</a>). For instance, alarm calling in birds can be triggered by the presence of a predator, but can also result from false alarms about non-predatory intruders or be given by deceptive individuals that gain from distracting conspecifics (Møller 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">1988</a>). Thus, learning immediately and irreversibly about whatever stimulus is paired with conspecific alarm calling could be detrimental. In contrast, for many fish species, where alarm signals are derived from the chemicals released by injured conspecifics, the alarm always indicates the presences of predators and thus should be more robust to extinction (Griffin 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2004</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if a species learns socially in one context, it does not mean that it will learn socially in all contexts. For example, Norway rats (
   <span class="italic">Rattus norvegicus</span>) learn socially about novel foods (Galef 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">1982</a>). However, these rats do not learn socially about a novel foraging technique in which individuals dive for molluscs on river beds (Galef 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">1982</a>), perhaps because the behaviour is harder to observe underwater. Meanwhile, the same is true for vervet monkeys (
   <span class="italic">Chlorocebus pygerythrus</span>) that appear not to use social information when learning about a new deterrent, such as recently installed electric fencing (Weingrill et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">2005</a>), even though they learn socially in novel food contexts (e.g. van de Waal et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128" href="#CR128">2013</a>). Investigating what separates the contexts in which a species does and does not learn socially would clearly be important in facilitating or preventing social learning.
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species-level biases are also fundamental to predicting threats and advising conservation policy. Migrating species differ in whether they socially learn their travel route; many baleen whales and bird species do, but sea turtles do not (Scott et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">2014</a>). Several conservation considerations hinge on whether or not a migratory species learns its route socially, such as: do migration routes represent a cultural variant that needs to be maintained, should the loss of migratory knowledge be included in threat forecasting, and should social learning should be encouraged in reintroductions to aid first migrations (e.g. Urbanek et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125" href="#CR125">2005</a>)? Meanwhile, differences in species’ social learning propensities can influence the extent to which a management action persists over time. For example, the effectiveness of an intervention designed to prevent waterfowl from taking handouts from park visitors differed by species, potentially because of differences in social learning between them (Conover 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">1999</a>). Geese (
   <span class="italic">Branta canadensis</span>) and swans (
   <span class="italic">Cygnus olor</span>) were conditioned to avoid bread through the application of distasteful chemicals. Even though both showed similar levels of initial avoidance, the geese lost their avoidance faster than the swans once regular bread was available because they forage in larger groups where a greater number of social cues were available to indicate food palatability (Conover 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">1999</a>). Overall, determining which species are most likely to learn socially in a given context is essential to determining if social learning should be used in its conservation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual-based biases</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another source of bias in social learning stems from who is observing the socially produced information. Some individuals can have preferences for asocially acquired information, even if the information is outdated or suboptimal (Leadbeater and Florent 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2014</a>). The developmental stage, sex or personal experience of the observer can all influence how likely an individual is to copy a demonstrator (Nottebohm 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">1970</a>; Reader and Laland 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">2000</a>; van Bergen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2004</a>; Thornton and Malapert 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">2009</a>). Of these observer-driven biases, those that are dependent on the stage of development are best studied. Such biases influence social learning during critical periods, often to help in the development of evolutionarily appropriate behaviour. The acquisitions of birdsong and mate preference are classic examples where information is learned socially during a sensitive period of development (Nottebohm 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">1970</a>; Clayton 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">1989</a>). This means, for example, that birds which do not have social exposure to song or the appropriate parent will develop suboptimal song and mate preferences that can reduce their reproductive prospects. While sensitive periods are utilized in many captive breeding programs, such as encouraging socially mediated migration and habitat choices (Urbanek et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125" href="#CR125">2005</a>), the mitigation of social learning interference during critical periods has not often been attempted in the wild. Such efforts are limited by the fact that we lack understanding of what happens after interference is removed (e.g. in the case of anthropogenic noise, Shannon et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding where learning is biased towards certain age groups, for instance, could be crucial to accurately assessing where natural channels of information flow might be disrupted by human activities. For example, older female matriarchs carry social knowledge in elephants (
   <span class="italic">L. africana</span>), such that groups with older females have higher fitness and respond better towards predators (McComb et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2001</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2011</a>). Since older elephants (including females) have larger tusks, they are preferentially targeted by poachers (Dobson and Poole 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1998</a>). Similar social learning biases towards older females have also been found in orca social groups (Brent et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2015</a>). Therefore, assessing the impact of this social learning bias is crucial to accurately predicting the threats posed by poachers and the demographic costs that the removal of such individuals from the population would have (Whitehead 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">2010</a>). Also important to such assessments is whether individuals are flexible in employing different social learning strategies that enable them to learn when to switch to a different demonstrator if their demonstrator becomes unreliable or ceases to exist (discussed in Heyes 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2016</a>; Mesoudi et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other factors during development can also influence the probability of a given individual attending to and learning about social information. For instance, the level and timing of developmental stress that quail (
   <span class="italic">Coturnix japonica</span>) experience influences their use of social information (Boogert et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2013</a>). Developmental stress can be triggered by inadequate food provisioning (Pravosudov and Kitaysky 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2006</a>), and areas with high human impact, such as urban habitat, appear to have lesser quality food as evidenced by the stunted development seen in urban populations (e.g. great tits 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span> and blue tits 
   <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>; Bailly et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2016</a>). Therefore, researching whether suboptimal habitat influences individual social learning tendencies may help explain natural individual variation in social information use and could be an important component of predicting the impact of urbanization on animal populations.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether an animal has previous experience with a stimulus can also influence whether they learn socially about it. Short-term habituation to non-threatening stimuli, on the order of ∼5 presentations, does not hamper fear conditioning, but long-term habituation, such as lifetime experience with a non-threatening stimulus (e.g. a heterospecific), does (Curio 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1988</a>). Other types of experiences can also influence whether individuals use social information. Early life experience with conspecifics can influence individuals’ tendency to learn socially in later life (Chapman et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2008</a>). Moreover, the type of social experience an individual has with a stimulus can determine whether learning occurs, although the direction of this effect can depend on the species. For example, individual pigeons do not learn a new feeding technique if they scrounged from others who learned the method (Lefebvre and Helder 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">1997</a>). In contrast, in some other species, such as meerkats (
   <span class="italic">Suricata suricatta</span>) and common marmosets (
   <span class="italic">Callithrix jacchus</span>), scrounging experience has been shown to promote social learning (Caldwell and Whiten 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2003</a>; Thornton and Malapert 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">2009</a>). These differences in the effects of scrounging on social learning may be linked both to species-level variation in social tolerance (Caldwell and Whiten 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2003</a>) and the extent to which the act of scrounging exposes individuals to the instrumental contingencies of a task (Thornton and Malapert 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">2009</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another type of bias driven by individuals stems from who is producing information. Demonstrator bias (otherwise known as “indirect” or “model-based” bias; Rendell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2011</a>) can differ depending on the species. For example, nine-spine sticklebacks, chimpanzees and meerkats are more likely to copy older individuals (Dugatkin and Godin 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">1993</a>; Thornton and Malapert 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">2009</a>; Horner et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2010</a>), while rats (
   <span class="italic">R. norvegicus</span>) do not show copying biases relating to demonstrator’s age (Galef 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2009</a>). Moreover, a given species can exhibit multiple demonstrator biases, such as copying older and more knowledgeable conspecifics (Kendal et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2015</a>). To complicate matters further, the rules about who to copy can vary depending on an individual’s early life experience. Zebra finches (
   <span class="italic">Taeniopygia guttata</span>) that experienced higher levels of developmental stress are less likely to copy their parents than unaffected offspring are (Farine et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a>). Current research has not revealed general rules that determine these individual copying biases between species. Indeed, simple rules are unlikely to exist, given the number of biases that can apply. However, the better we can predict where similar assumptions about biases hold across related species or social systems, the better management techniques that target social learning will generalize across contexts.
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An understanding of individual-based biases that influence how information spreads socially within wild populations is of great importance in several mitigation settings. Selective removal practices that target an individual after they have committed “problem behaviour” are often ineffective in the long term (Treves and Naughton-Treves 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124" href="#CR124">2005</a>). Such practices would be more effective, and considerable time and money saved, if managers could determine ahead of time the probability that problem behaviour would spread, and under what timeframe it might do so. Additionally, management solutions that do not have the capacity to target all individuals in a population could benefit from insight into which individuals tend to spread information in a population. It has been proposed, for example, that road collisions could be reduced by installing invisible fences near roads and fitting shock collars on a subset of the population, in the hopes that avoidance will spread socially (Proppe et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">2016</a>). Again, much time, energy and investment could be saved if collared individuals could be chosen based on their location in the social network and their likelihood of acting as a “demonstrator” for others.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cue-based biases</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Certain cue-response pairings are easier to learn than others. Stimuli will be more easily learned the more they (a) are conspicuous, (b) reliably precede an outcome and (c) are evolutionarily relevant (Shettleworth 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">2010</a>). Social learning will occur more quickly and strongly with increasingly salient cues because they are more likely to attract the attention and emotional reaction of an observer. For example, exposure to a conspecific reacting fearfully is more effective than just broadcasting alarm calls alone (Curio 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1988</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Learning is also based on contingency. If two cues do not reliably coincide, animals are not likely to learn socially about them. For example, even in species that can learn socially, social learning may not occur in the wild if animals never observe the behaviour they are expected to learn. For example, the planigale (
   <span class="italic">Planigale maculate</span>) is a small Australian mammal that is threatened because it consumes a toxic, invasive predator, the cane toad (
   <span class="italic">Rhinella marina</span>). Although planigales are capable of avoiding toads through taste aversion learning, and are likely capable of learning socially, there is no evidence that they socially learn to avoid toads (Box and Gibson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2006</a>; Webb et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" href="#CR131">2008</a>; Llewelyn et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">2010</a>). Presumably, all knowledgeable individuals that individually learn to avoid the toads do not produce social information about toads because they avoid interacting with them. So, unless species commonly forage in groups where they could observe “disgust” responses (e.g. Mason 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">1988</a>), they are not likely to learn socially in the wild about novel, poisonous food. Predicting the frequency of social information that individuals are likely to encounter is, therefore, an integral part of predicting the spread of socially learned behaviour.
  </p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the ecological relevance of stimuli is crucial for determining whether it will spread socially. In the case of socially acquired predator avoidance, fear-relevant stimuli are more likely to be learned than fear-irrelevant stimuli because the process is adaptively biased to facilitate escape from danger but to limit the amount of time wasted on false alarms (Griffin 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2004</a>). Therefore, the information gathered during fear conditioning tends to be content, not context specific, such that animals respond any time they encounter that fear stimulus, irrespective of location (although some species do generalize their socially learned threat responses if they occupy risky environments; Ferrari et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2009</a>). It is not always easy to predict what types of stimuli can be associated with predatory threats, since individuals have been shown to socially acquire fears of inanimate objects, such as a coloured plastic bottle, or of non-predatory species, such as goldfish, although not always as strongly as natural fear stimuli (Curio 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1988</a>; Chivers and Smith 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">1994</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
