<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ece32846-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">Two ecologically and economically important, and threatened Dipterocarp trees Sal (
  <italic class="italic">Shorea robusta</italic>) and Garjan (
  <italic class="italic">Dipterocarpus turbinatus</italic>) form mono‐specific canopies in dry deciduous, moist deciduous, evergreen, and semievergreen forests across South Asia and continental parts of Southeast Asia. They provide valuable timber and play an important role in the economy of many Asian countries. However, both Dipterocarp trees are threatened by continuing forest clearing, habitat alteration, and global climate change. While climatic regimes in the Asian tropics are changing, research on climate change‐driven shifts in the distribution of tropical Asian trees is limited. We applied a bioclimatic modeling approach to these two Dipterocarp trees Sal and Garjan. We used presence‐only records for the tree species, five bioclimatic variables, and selected two climatic scenarios (
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">RCP</styled-content>4.5: an optimistic scenario and 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">RCP</styled-content>8.5: a pessimistic scenario) and three global climate models (
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">GCM</styled-content>s) to encompass the full range of variation in the models. We modeled climate space suitability for both species, projected to 2070, using a climate envelope modeling tool “MaxEnt” (the maximum entropy algorithm). Annual precipitation was the key bioclimatic variable in all 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">GCM</styled-content>s for explaining the current and future distributions of Sal and Garjan (Sal: 49.97 ± 1.33; Garjan: 37.63 ± 1.19). Our models predict that suitable climate space for Sal will decline by 24% and 34% (the mean of the three 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">GCM</styled-content>s) by 2070 under 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">RCP</styled-content>4.5 and 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">RCP</styled-content>8.5, respectively. In contrast, the consequences of imminent climate change appear less severe for Garjan, with a decline of 17% and 27% under 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">RCP</styled-content>4.5 and 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">RCP</styled-content>8.5, respectively. The findings of this study can be used to set conservation guidelines for Sal and Garjan by identifying vulnerable habitats in the region. In addition, the natural habitats of Sal and Garjan can be categorized as low to high risk under changing climates where artificial regeneration should be undertaken for forest restoration.
 </p>
</abstract>
