<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Annual mean temperature is projected to affect the habitat suitability of threatened tree, herb, and fern species most, while precipitation seasonality is the driving factor in changing habitat suitability for threatened shrub species. This indicates the importance of monitoring threatened plant species according to factors such as plant type. This is consistent with previous studies that found that annual mean temperature was the most important bioclimatic variable for the distribution and growth of trees, herbs, and ferns (
 <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yu et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). The annual mean temperature is projected to increase dramatically in the 2080s. Hence, annual mean temperature may dramatically alter the distribution of plant species. 
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dilts et al.</xref> (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) showed that the water balance influenced by precipitation seasonality is related to the geographic distribution of most shrub species. By the 2080s, precipitation seasonality may also change substantially with increasing greenhouse gas concentrations. Hence, we also focused on the role of precipitation seasonality on habitat suitability or threatened plant species. Moreover, the impact of soil pH on habitat suitability for tree, shrub, and fern species was substantial (
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ervin &amp; Holly</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Marschner, Crowley &amp; Yang</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>). Soil pH affects nutrient availability, which dramatically impacts habitat suitability (
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ervin &amp; Holly</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Marschner, Crowley &amp; Yang</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>). To address the practical conservation issues, we must consider the impact of future climate change coupled with factors such as soil pH on habitat suitability for threatened plant species, particularly, tree, shrub, and fern species.
</p>
