<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on the Global Strategy for Plant Conservation (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbd.int/gspc/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cbd.int/gspc/</ext-link>), at least 75% of known threatened plant species are protected. Projected climate changes caused by high greenhouse gas emissions are projected to damage suitable habitats for plant species within Chinese nature reserves. The large shift in potential habitat distributions and decreases in habitats with suitable climates could leave potentially viable populations of threatened plant species vulnerable to extinction (
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fordham et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Costion et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Andel et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Hence, we compiled a list of important plants for conservation within China including more than 60 threatened plant species (over 73.2% of all 82 species), for example, 
 <italic class="italic">T. koraiensis</italic>, which is particularly endangered by trends of climate suitability under the high concentration scenario. In particular, extreme climate events and rapid changes in climate can cause physiological stress and damage to plants (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bastos et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zinta et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Threatened plant species are already in danger and thus are vulnerable to extreme climate events like the 2003 summer heatwave, showing that inappropriate land management can threaten the existence of plant species (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bastos et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zinta et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wujeska-Klause, Bossinger &amp; Tausz</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Furthermore, we found that the threatened tree species within nature reserves would be strongly affected by climate change, particularly under the high concentration scenario by the 2080s. The distributions of suitable habitats for tree species may shift as a consequence of climate change. 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Alberto et al.</xref> (
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) has shown that evolutionary responses are required for tree populations to track climate change. Hence, we must assess the impact of climate change on habitat suitability for tree species when managing the conservation of threatened plant species. Although fern species may be affected less by climate change, we still must pay attention to the response of fern species like 
 <italic class="italic">Alsophila denticulate</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cibotium barometz</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Alsophila metteniana</italic> because their suitable habitats decrease substantially under the high concentration scenario. Hence, we must monitor the changing dynamics of potential distributions of threatened plants under climate change and prevent habitat degeneration in order to stabilize plant populations (
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thuiller et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Araújo et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
