<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="evo13660-sec-0110" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We studied whether the optimal reaction norm of great tit laying date against temperature changed over three consecutive time periods in a long‐term study population and whether this resulted in intensified directional selection on—and an evolutionary response in—its two components (elevation and slope, i.e., the sensitivity to the environmental variable). We found that, whereas the optimal laying date (as predicted by spring temperatures and determined by the timing of the caterpillar peak) across the temperature range (the elevation of the optimal reaction norm) advanced over the past decades, the sensitivity of the optimal laying date to temperature (the slope of the optimal reaction norm) did not change. In agreement with this, there was selection on the great tit reaction norm elevation, but not on the slope, in the second third of our time series, but this selection waned in the third period, potentially due to the increased variability in phenotypic optima (Fig. 
  <a rid="evo13660-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#evo13660-fig-0001">1</a>A). Despite directional selection, we predicted quantitatively that the elevation of the reaction norm would shift only marginally over time (a maximum of a few days), simply because of the low heritability, the generation time of about two years (Garant et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0025">2004</a>; Kvist et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0047">2007</a>) and the sex limitation of laying date (Caro et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0011">2009</a>). Indeed, the actual (observed) reaction norm did not change over time, neither in slope nor elevation. Our results suggest that, despite the apparent lack of an evolutionary response in our population, adaptation of timing of breeding to climate change can only occur through evolution of the elevation of the reaction norm, as evolution of increased (or decreased) phenotypic plasticity is not possible.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection on plasticity in our study population was limited because the slope of the optimal reaction norm did not change over time. However, even if there had been substantial directional selection on the slope, the response to selection would have been weak as there was very little variation in individual reaction norm slopes, both phenotypically and additive genetically (Tables 
  <a rid="evo13660-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#evo13660-tbl-0002">2</a> and 
  <a rid="evo13660-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" href="#evo13660-tbl-0003">3</a>). This qualitative statement can be quantified by comparing the variances in environment‐specific expected values of laying date attributable separately to variation in reaction norm elevations (i.e., the estimates from Table 
  <a rid="evo13660-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" href="#evo13660-tbl-0003">3</a>) and slopes (i.e., estimated variance multiplied by the variance in centred temperatures; see Appendix 7 in Morrissey and Liefting 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0056">2016</a>). This was 3.24 [0.88, 5.68] and 4.38 [1.98, 6.70] for the phenotypic and additive genetic intercepts, respectively, whereas it was only 0.05 [0.00, 0.34] and 0.04 [0.00, 0.34] for the respective slopes. Thus, the contribution of variance in slopes to variance in expected laying dates in a given environment was negligible.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lack of variation in (phenotypic) plasticity slopes (I × E) contradicts previous work on our study population (Nussey et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0062">2005b</a>; Husby et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0041">2010</a>, 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0042">2011</a>). The source of this discrepancy lies in the residual variance structure of the random regression models. Besides the problems inherent to using BLUPs in this context, Nussey et al. (
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0062">2005b</a>) fitted homogeneous residual variance, thereby forcing any heterogeneity in residual variance caused by the environment (i.e., temperature) to be estimated by the phenotypic covariance matrix and hence inflating estimates of I × E. Husby et al. (
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0041">2010</a>, 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0042">2011</a>), on the other hand, fitted a heterogeneous residual structure but grouped years by decade, assuming that variance in laying date increased over the years because temperature increased over time. This assumption does not hold up, however, as we found that the variance in laying date in HV correlated very weakly with year (slope = 0.001 [–0.22, 0.22]; 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.00 [0.00, 0.001]), whereas it correlated reasonably well with temperature (2.40 [0.70, 4.49]; 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.13 [0.01, 0.36]). In general, it would make more sense to partition residual variance based on years with similar environments rather than based on decades. Indeed, when we fitted the model of equation 
  <a rid="evo13660-disp-0008" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#evo13660-disp-0008">(6)</a> (but dropping the G × E term for efficiency) on the same data subset (1973–2006) as in Husby et al. (
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0041">2010</a>, 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0042">2011</a>) and partitioned residual variance into three groups by decade, we found substantial individual variation in slopes (posterior median slope variance and 95% HPDI: 0.91 [0.36, 1.53]). When we refitted the model on the same data subset (1973–2006) with residual variance partitioned into three groups based on temperature, however, the slope variance decreased substantially (0.25 [0.00, 0.87]). These results were confirmed by simulations; when we simulated a population with a small slope variance, specifying the incorrect residual structure in the random regression model led to upward bias in the variance estimate and a high false‐positive rate (Supplementary Info 2, Fig. 
  <a rid="evo13660-supl-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#evo13660-supl-0001">S1</a>). Thus, we conclude that variation in plasticity in HV really is limited, reinforcing the notion that, despite previous studies (Nussey et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0062">2005b</a>), there can be only limited response to selection on plasticity in this population (cf. e.g., Brommer et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0008">2012</a>; Hayward et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0037">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we can only speculate about the reasons for an apparent lack of I × E and G × E in our population, previous simulation studies suggest it is unlikely that we had limited statistical power (or precision in our case) to detect either (Martin et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0052">2011</a>; Van de Pol 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0089">2012</a>). Illustrative in this respect are the narrow 95% HPDIs for slope variances (Table 
  <a rid="evo13660-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" href="#evo13660-tbl-0003">3</a>), which seem to indicate that the RRAM was able to estimate I × E (strictly speaking PE × E and G × E) with a fair amount of precision. To put this in perspective, when we applied a version of the model of equation 
  <a rid="evo13660-disp-0008" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#evo13660-disp-0008">(6)</a> (that included individual‐mean‐centred temperatures) to another of our long‐term great tit study populations on the Dutch island of Vlieland (VL), we found substantial evidence for I × E in laying date (posterior median slope variance and 95% HPDI: 1.32 [0.53, 1.89]), but not G × E (0.10 [0.00, 0.67]; unpublished results), both estimated with substantially lower precision (the zero constraint of the estimates notwithstanding). The HV and VL datasets are quite similar in terms of the number of individuals and observations and we should therefore have been able to detect I × E in HV if it was really there. Since the pedigree in VL is more informative (“deeper”) than the one in HV because of limited immigration from the mainland (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0032">2013b</a>; Postma and Van Noordwijk 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0065">2005</a>), the VL data may be better suited to test for G × E, but even there G × E appeared to be limited. (No caterpillar biomass data are available for that population, making it an unsuitable dataset for the purpose of this article.) This apparent absence of G × E is consistent with the notion that G × E in general is hard to detect in wild populations when not in an experimental setting (Gienapp and Brommer 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0026">2014</a>; Wood and Brodie III 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0108">2016</a>; Hayward et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0038">2018</a>; Ramakers et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0067">2018</a>). Nevertheless, since I × E is the upper limit of G × E (Gienapp and Brommer 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0026">2014</a>), the absence of I × E in our study system in HV suggests that G × E is absent. The reason for this absence may be that early‐spring temperatures have historically been highly predictive of the food peak and selection for being well matched with this peak has been strong (Reed et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0071">2013b</a>; Visser et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0103">2006</a>), possibly eroding (genetic) variation in plasticity in laying date over time (cf. Tomkins et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0085">2004</a>; Turelli and Barton 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0086">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite selection on, and ample additive genetic variation in, the elevation of the reaction norm (Tables 
  <a rid="evo13660-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" href="#evo13660-tbl-0001">1</a> and 
  <a rid="evo13660-supl-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#evo13660-supl-0001">S1</a>), the observed, period‐specific reaction norms changed only marginally over the course of time, as was also predicted from the quantitative genetic model (eq. 
  <a rid="evo13660-disp-0007" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#evo13660-disp-0007">(5b)</a>). A close look at Figure 
  <a rid="evo13660-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#evo13660-fig-0001">1</a>C reveals that the population is “sliding” up and down the same reaction norm; that is, the observed temperature range has become wider and individuals are still using these temperatures to time the onset of reproduction (see also Visser et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0103">2006</a>). Clearly, given the increase in mismatch with the caterpillar peak in this population, this is not an adaptive strategy (Reed et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0071">2013b</a>; Thomas et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0084">2001</a>); the population needs to evolve a lower elevation to become better matched with the caterpillar peak. The apparent lack of such a shift is most likely explained by the low heritability of elevation, the generation time and the sex limitation of laying date, as shown by our quantitative genetic model (eq. 
  <a rid="evo13660-disp-0007" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#evo13660-disp-0007">(5b)</a>). Additionally, increased variability in phenotypic optima in the last third of the study period may further hamper adaptation as early‐breeding genotypes no longer consistently have a reproductive advantage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the quantitative genetic model, we used annual phenotypic selection gradients to predict the change in the reaction norm from one year to the next. One concern with using phenotypic (annual) selection gradients is that estimates of selection in reality reflect an environmental covariance between the trait and fitness or selection on a correlated trait (Lande and Arnold 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0050">1983</a>; Price et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0066">1988</a>; Hadfield 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0033">2008</a>). In our population, however, we know that such environmental bias in selection is limited and that estimates of selection at the phenotypic and genetic level are very similar (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0030">2006</a>; Reed et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0069">2016</a>). Thus, the necessary ingredients for genetic adaptation—genetic variation and selection—are real and present in HV, but evolutionary change is simply too small to be detected due to the large environmental variation in laying date among years (see also discussion in Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0030">2006</a>). Such small rates of adaptation can put a strain on population persistence in the longer run as adaptation continues to be outpaced by climate change (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0029">2013a</a>; Carlson et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0010">2014</a>; Visser and Gienapp, unpubl. ms.; but see Reed et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0070">2013a</a>,
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0071">b</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many populations have thus far responded to the increased mismatch with the phenology of their food through phenotypic plasticity (Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0013">2014</a>; Merilä and Hendry 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0053">2014</a>), but it has been predicted that this cannot be sufficient in the long run as climate change continues to disrupt synchrony between trophic levels (Visser et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0099">2004</a>; Visser 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0097">2008</a>; Thackeray et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0083">2010</a>; Carlson et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0010">2014</a>; Thackeray et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0082">2016</a>; Visser and Gienapp, unpubl. ms.). Consequently, we need to know whether an absence of G × E in phenology as reported here is the general case or an exception. As pointed out above, such studies in natural populations are rare (but see Ramakers et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0067">2018</a>), which is likely due to the logistical challenges of obtaining the necessary pedigree, so far constraining these studies to mainly birds and mammals. Replacing the observational, social pedigree by relatedness estimated from genetic markers has earlier been suggested (Moore and Kukuk 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0055">2002</a>; Ritland 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0074">1996</a>), but applications of this approach remained unsuccessful (Coltman 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0017">2005</a>; Garant and Kruuk 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0024">2005</a>; Csilléry et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0018">2006</a>). However, with the advent of high‐throughput, high‐density genotyping to “nonmodel” species, “genomic” relatedness estimates should have become sufficiently reliable to replace pedigrees (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0027">2017</a>) and thereby allow us to study genetic variation in and selection on phenotypic plasticity both in labile and fixed traits in a broader range of taxa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, evidence for successful evolutionary rescue through a genetic shift in the reaction norm remains rare (Merilä and Hendry 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0053">2014</a>). One textbook example of successful evolutionary rescue is that of the great tit's most important food source, caterpillars of the winter moth (
  <span class="italic">O. brumata</span>); three Dutch populations have now restored the match of their hatching date with oak (
  <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span>) bud burst through a genetic shift in the elevation of the reaction norm (Van Asch et al. 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0087">2013</a>). It remains unclear whether such a change will be also observable in vertebrate populations, as the methods thus far deployed have been largely insufficient to infer evolutionary change (Merilä and Hendry 
  <a rid="evo13660-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#evo13660-bib-0053">2014</a>). We provide an important step to this discussion by using rigorous statistical tools to reveal the evolutionary potential of a key life‐history trait in a reaction norm context.
 </p>
</sec>
