<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results demonstrate conclusively the benefits of Si supplementation for root nodulation: root nodule abundance was always increased in plants growing in Si+ soil and other factors, whether CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, temperature and aphid presence no longer had significant impacts on nodule abundance. The mechanisms by which Si is so effective at promoting nodulation are not well-understood, but could include changes in soil conditions, increased root growth (and potential invasion sites), higher abundance of bacteroids and symbiosomes, together with the synthesis of compounds that upregulate nodulation genes (as discussed by 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Johnson et al., 2017</xref>). The increased nodule density reported in the present study tentatively suggests that greater nodule abundance was not merely a function of increased root growth. Further work is needed, but Si could provide a useful tool for mitigating some of the negative impacts of climate change on crop production – in this instance maintaining nodulation rates of 
 <italic class="italic">M. sativa</italic> in warmer climates. Moreover, other studies suggest Si could redress negative effects of eCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> on plant–herbivore interactions. For example, herbivore damage to roots of sugarcane was exacerbated under eCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> conditions, but application of Si reversed these effects and stimulated crop growth (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Frew et al., 2017</xref>). Intervention strategies could include targeted application of Si (e.g., furnace slag), selection of plant lines that naturally take up large amounts of Si (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McLarnon et al., 2017</xref>) and remediation of soils deficient in bioavailable Si (silicic acid) (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guntzer et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Johnson et al., 2016a</xref>).
</p>
