<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-plants-08-00065" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Vascular Cambium and Plant Growth</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When active, vascular cambium undergoes cell division to contribute to secondary growth of xylem and phloem, representing the largest carbon sink in vascular plants [
  <a rid="B3-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-plants-08-00065">3</a>,
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00065">11</a>]. The cambial zone refers to all layers of meristematic cells and their derivatives between the xylem and phloem. Increased cambial division leads to increased production of xylem biomass [
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00065">11</a>]. Developing cells have different stages of primary and secondary cell wall formation and lignification [
  <a rid="B43-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-plants-08-00065">43</a>]. During primary growth, procambial cells promote upward growth of vascular tissue [
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00065">11</a>]. Patterns of radial growth are positively correlated with the width of the cambial zone [
  <a rid="B44-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-plants-08-00065">44</a>], which varies among individuals of a species [
  <a rid="B43-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-plants-08-00065">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cambial development can also be controlled by interactions of phytohormones, such as auxins, gibberellins, cytokinins, and ethylene [
  <a rid="B9-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-plants-08-00065">9</a>,
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00065">11</a>,
  <a rid="B44-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-plants-08-00065">44</a>]. For example, a low concentration of ethylene can have a stimulatory effect on cambial cell division in young shoot of white leadtree (
  <span class="italic">Leucaena leucocephala</span> (Lam.) de Wit.) [
  <a rid="B45-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-plants-08-00065">45</a>]. However, a low concentration of cytokinin signaling is the primary basis for the impaired cambial growth of poplar (
  <span class="italic">Populus trichocarpa</span> Torr. and A. Gray ex. Hook.) [
  <a rid="B46-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-plants-08-00065">46</a>]. Since environmental factors can influence hormone levels and transport [
  <a rid="B47-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-plants-08-00065">47</a>,
  <a rid="B48-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-plants-08-00065">48</a>], cambial development may be indirectly affected; for example, drought reduces transport of cytokinins from root to shoot but increases transport of an ethylene precursor [
  <a rid="B48-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-plants-08-00065">48</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
