<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot3-plants-08-00065" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Plant Responses to Carbon Dioxide and Drought</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been suggested that increased atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> may lead to improved drought tolerance in plants [
  <a rid="B117-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B117-plants-08-00065">117</a>]. However, other studies have suggested that drought may limit the positive effects of elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, regardless of increased WUE [
  <a rid="B118-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B118-plants-08-00065">118</a>]. In C
  <sub>3</sub> plants, elevated atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> could enhance carbon gain while decreasing stomatal conductance [
  <a rid="B17-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-08-00065">17</a>]. Elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> may directly increase photosynthetic activities, which would contribute to increased growth without water status improvements [
  <a rid="B85-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-plants-08-00065">85</a>]. Increased photosynthetic rates at elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> have also been shown to be most prominent under drought, and this indicates that elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> could mitigate the negative effects of drought stress. Many of these measurements, however, have been conducted at the leaf level instead of the whole-plant level, which yields less clear-cut results [
  <a rid="B17-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-08-00065">17</a>]. In a study, elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> increased biomass by 15% in the water-stressed plants [
  <a rid="B85-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-plants-08-00065">85</a>]. Elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> also increased WUE, but did not increase biomass any more under drought conditions than it did under normal conditions in several riparian tree species [
  <a rid="B85-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-plants-08-00065">85</a>]; this may be indicative of species variation in response to elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>. In many plants, elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> decreases stomatal conductance but increases WUE, and these effects are increased under drier conditions, which may lead to a reduction in plant water demand. In semi-arid environments, transpiration is reduced under elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>; this can increase plant growth under dry periods and counteract the negative effects of warming on the supply of available water to plant roots [
  <a rid="B85-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-plants-08-00065">85</a>]. Under both drought stress and elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, there can be a partial closure of stomata due to increased sub-stomatal CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration [
  <a rid="B86-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B86-plants-08-00065">86</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In woody plants (e.g., lemon tree), drought stress combined with elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> decreased both stomatal conductance and transpiration, but had no significant effects on plant biomass [
  <a rid="B107-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B107-plants-08-00065">107</a>]. Also, drought stress reduces suberin by up to 70% [
  <a rid="B19-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-plants-08-00065">19</a>], and the effects of CO
  <sub>2</sub> on suberin content has yet to be studied. If CO
  <sub>2</sub> does not increase suberin biosynthesis, plants may suffer significant water loss. Since beneficial effects of CO
  <sub>2</sub> have been shown to vanish under severe drought stress, CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization may be unable to compensate for the negative effects of drought stress [
  <a rid="B18-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-plants-08-00065">18</a>]. In herbaceous plants (e.g., soybean), elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> with drought stress decreased net CO
  <sub>2</sub> assimilation, stomatal conductance, transpiration and biomass, but increased WUE [
  <a rid="B112-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112-plants-08-00065">112</a>] (see 
  <a rid="plants-08-00065-t002" ref-type="table" href="#plants-08-00065-t002">Table 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="plants-08-00065-f001" href="#plants-08-00065-f001">Figure 1</a>). In a study, the common bean (
  <span class="italic">Phaseolus vulgaris</span> L.) plants that were grown under pre-industrial CO
  <sub>2</sub> had a higher transpiration rate under moderate drought, and maintained normal net photosynthesis more than plants that were grown under ambient or elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, which had increased WUE and no change in water potential [
  <a rid="B17-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-08-00065">17</a>]. At elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, the bean plants had a decreased capacity of xylem water transport to meet water demand, and there were stronger drought-induced transpiration limitations [
  <a rid="B17-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-08-00065">17</a>]. Elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> also increased xylem vessel diameter in bean plants, but drought and the interaction between CO
  <sub>2</sub> and drought had no significant effect. Moreover, elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> increases the chance of embolism due to increased vessel diameter [
  <a rid="B17-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-08-00065">17</a>]. It has been shown that drought-tolerant rice plants, grown at elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, were able to maintain their stomatal conductance under drought conditions by having reduced stomatal density [
  <a rid="B119-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119-plants-08-00065">119</a>]. It remains unknown how CO
  <sub>2</sub> affects aspects of vascular cambium initiation and tissue differentiation.
 </p>
</sec>
