<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5-plants-08-00065" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Conclusions and Future Directions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to predict how plant hydraulics will respond to a changing climate, both structural and functional components, such as plant metabolism, xylem properties, vascular architecture, and leaf size are needed for incorporation into a functional model [
  <a rid="B35-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-plants-08-00065">35</a>]. Responses to climatic conditions are species-dependent and, therefore, there may be a genetic component to climatic responses, with plant species having differential physiological responses to similar stimuli. Also, studies have shown that the formation of xylem is more sensitive to environmental factors than the formation of phloem [
  <a rid="B29-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-plants-08-00065">29</a>]. This emphasizes the need for research into the development of vascular tissues, including xylem, phloem, parenchyma and fibers, from the base of plant to shoot apex.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, a current challenge in plant physiology is to associate particular structural characteristics of the vascular bundle to specific functions regarding efficiency of water transport [
  <a rid="B35-plants-08-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-plants-08-00065">35</a>]. Studies that examine vascular tissue differentiation are rare, and the majority of existing studies look at woody species. More work is needed in determining the effects of environmental factors on vascular development, especially in herbaceous plants. Our lack of understanding makes it difficult to predict how climate change will affect vascular development and the transpiration stream in plants; however, decreased shoot biomass under stress conditions may be indicative of a reduction in vascular tissue. It is essential to understand how plant forms (e.g., vascular tissues) and functions (e.g., photosynthesis and transpiration) will respond to climate change. Optimization of hydraulic efficiency is the first step in ensuring that plants may be better equipped to cope with future climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
