<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Expert elicitation</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the expert elicitation, thirty-six top experts on China’s energy and climate policies were asked to complete a written survey and a follow-up interview was offered to all experts. They were selected because of their capacity to understand the big picture, and their ability to answer our questions regarding which policies are relatively more important than others. We did not target experts who are famous for any niche issue within China’s climate change policy, such as issue experts on transportation, building efficiency or afforestation. Eighteen responses were received, thirteen of which were from Chinese experts, and five from foreign experts. Background information about these experts, including institutions and expertise are provided in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. The survey was semi-structured and we provided experts with the freedom to identify climate policies that they determined were important through 2016, rather than requiring them to stick to the predetermined list of policies provided in the Appendix attached to the survey protocol. Some experts identified policies that were not included in our policy inventory. We uploaded the survey protocol (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) as on-line Supplementary information via figshare.com [
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://figshare.com/s/483d43b02d6110c8ea24" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://figshare.com/s/483d43b02d6110c8ea24</span>], so the survey is now available for review. The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB) at Tufts University since the expert elicitation method involved human participants. We obtained consent from all participants during the fieldwork.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Background information on experts surveyed</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Expert</th>
      <th>Institutions</th>
      <th>Expertise</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>1</td>
      <td>Tsinghua University</td>
      <td>Energy and climate change modeling, energy, and climate change policy</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>2</td>
      <td>Tsinghua University</td>
      <td>Climate change, energy, and climate change policy</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>3</td>
      <td>Tsinghua University</td>
      <td>Climate change, energy, and sustainable development</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>4</td>
      <td>Renmin University</td>
      <td>Energy and environment modeling, energy, and climate change policy, international climate institutions</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>5</td>
      <td>Chinese Academy of Science</td>
      <td>Sustainable development, climate change, energy package, environment governance and policy</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>6</td>
      <td>Chinese Academy of Social Science</td>
      <td>International climate governance, energy, and climate policy</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>7</td>
      <td>Energy Foundation, China</td>
      <td>Climate change modeling, climate change policy, technology innovation and transfer</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>8</td>
      <td>Energy Foundation, China</td>
      <td>Climate change, clean energy, and clean transportation</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>9</td>
      <td>National Center for Climate Change Strategy and International Cooperation</td>
      <td>Energy and renewable energy policy and strategy</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>10</td>
      <td>National Center for Climate Change Strategy and International Cooperation</td>
      <td>Climate change strategy and policy, low carbon development</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>11</td>
      <td>Development Research Center of the State Council</td>
      <td>Industrial economics, climate change</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>12</td>
      <td>Former Ministry of Environment</td>
      <td>Climate change governance</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>13</td>
      <td>Former Ministry of Finance</td>
      <td>Green finance and climate change</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>14</td>
      <td>Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT)</td>
      <td>Air quality &amp; health, energy, climate policy, regional analysis</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>15</td>
      <td>Syracuse University</td>
      <td>Environment economics, economics of technological change</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</td>
      <td>Low-carbon development modeling, building energy efficiencies, appliance efficiency standards</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>17</td>
      <td>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</td>
      <td>Energy and environment modeling, energy, and climate change policy, international climate institutions</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>18</td>
      <td>Georgetown University</td>
      <td>Environmental policy, technology transfer</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most Chinese experts preferred to respond to the questions orally, and their responses were recorded by hand. Gallagher and Zhang conducted these interviews in either Chinese or English (or a mixture of both). All the foreign experts chose to respond with written responses to the survey and declined the follow-up interview.</p>
</sec>
