<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Expert elicitation</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine which policies were likely the most important in reducing greenhouse gas emissions to date and in the future (and which were not) we conducted a qualitative survey of Chinese and foreign climate policy experts. The qualitative survey was conducted during June/July 2017, and in October 2018. Two-thirds of the respondents were Chinese experts and one-third were foreign experts. All of the experts believed that China would peak in advance of 2030, but three-quarters of them believed it would be difficult or relatively difficult to peak well in advance of 2030. The non-fossil fuel target was perceived to be more challenging from the experts’ perspective and three-quarters of them thought it would be difficult or impossible for China to achieve the 20% non-fossil fuel target. Regarding the existence of a climate policy gap, all experts believed that a policy gap currently exists, but that the gap is not large and can be fixed with modest efforts to reform existing policies or to implement new ones.</p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These experts identified 17 policies that they believed were the most influential in limiting CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions to date. The six policies that were most frequently cited were: feed-in tariffs for renewable energy, energy efficiency standards for power plants and motor vehicles, non-fossil energy targets, mandated caps on coal consumption, energy efficiency standards for buildings and equipment, and the key enterprise program for energy efficiency. The full list of influential emission-reducing policies generated by the survey is provided in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Most important climate policies through 2016. As we gave experts the freedom to list the climate policies that they thought were important through 2016 (rather than sticking to the list selected policies provided in the appendix), some experts introduced new policies that are not included in the appendix and the system dynamics model, including the coal cap policy, energy intensity targets, green bonds, air pollution standards, and phasing out old and inefficient power plants</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9159_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e396" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of policies were also identified by individual experts as either no longer necessary or in need of reform as summarized in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>: the national emission trading system (ETS), power sector reform (incomplete), electric vehicle subsidies (too high), resource tax (too low and not covering CO
  <sub>2</sub>), feed-in tariff (replace with ETS or carbon tax), manufacturer subsidies, and CCS promotion policies. There was no consensus among experts about which policies were no longer necessary or in need of revision.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Policies that are most in need of reform. SOE refers to state-owned enterprises. ETS refers to the national emission trading system for the power sector. As we gave experts the freedom to list the climate policies that they thought were most in need of reform, some experts introduced new policies that are not included in the appendix and the system dynamics model. The results show that power sector reform, ETS and the feed-in-tariff for renewables are the top three policies that are most in need of reform</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9159_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e413" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experts were also asked which new policies were needed most to achieve the NDC targets, and the three most frequently mentioned responses were: policies to reduce non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> gases, a carbon tax for sectors not covered under the new national ETS, and entrepreneurship incentives for low-carbon firms as indicated in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. China’s NDC only covers CO
  <sub>2</sub>, however, so the first policy recommendation would not, in fact, help China to achieve its NDC even though it would limit overall GHG emissions. Experts expressed mixed views about China’s emerging ETS, with some being skeptical that it would produce a CO
  <sub>2</sub> price that would incentivize behavioral change, and others feeling more confident about its eventual success over time. Few experts identified innovation policies, economic reform policies, or industrial policies as influential in emissions reductions, but the authors of this paper believe that these policies are, in fact, key to the ability of China to limit future emissions. Innovation policies, although indirect and difficult to model, are likely to become even more important in the future. Innovation policies include investments in energy research, development, and demonstration; investments in human capital; and creation of market-pull incentives for creating new products and processes that will contribute to GHG emission reductions.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>New policies needed to close the climate policy gap in China. GHG refers to greenhouse gas. Carbon tax for non-covered sectors and non-carbon GHG (e.g., CH4) are recognized as the two most important new policies needed. Notably, there is little consensus on the magnitude of other kinds of new policies that are needed to close the climate policy gap in China</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9159_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e436" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
