<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">Two newly-developed, data-driven models were used to simulate long-term cliff retreat
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup> and sandy beach evolution
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup> at ~5000 cross-shore transects spaced every 100 m along the southern California coast. Coastal cliff retreat is projected using a multi-model ensemble that includes vertically-discretized cross-shore models
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>, as well as empirical and statistical models that scale wave forcing and SLR to time-averaged cliff edge retreat rates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">83</xref>
 </sup>. At each transect, the ensemble gives preference to models that show less sensitivity to variations in model parameters based on the standard deviation during Monte Carlo simulations, and then weights projection uncertainty proportionally with the difference between individual model results (i.e. how well the ensemble reaches a consensus)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. The CoSMoS-COAST shoreline change model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup> combines three process-based models to compute sandy beach change: (1) wave-driven longshore transport
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>, (2) cross-shore transport due to waves
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">84</xref>
 </sup>, and (3) cross-shore transport due to SLR
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>
 </sup>. Both the cliff and sandy shoreline change models use historical shoreline positions, hindcast nearshore wave conditions (wave height, period, and direction), and an adaptive data assimilation scheme to calibrate a suite of equations and develop relationships between wave forcing parameters and geomorphic change at each model location. To drive both cliff retreat and shoreline model projections, continuous time-series of projected nearshore waves
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup> and water levels
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> through the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century, combined with different sea-level rise rates, are used through the year 2100. This is the same total water level proxy that is used to identify storm events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>. The two models provide time-varying sandy shoreline (mean high water [MHW] line) and cliff positions (cliff edge) that are subsequently used to evolve cross-shore profiles
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup> extracted from the originating high-resolution DEM; evolved profiles are used in scenarios that incorporate future SLR and storms using full model physics of the CoSMoS flood model described above. A summary of the coastal change results is shown in Supplementary Data and Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">3</xref>.
</p>
