<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extremes, Outliers, Black Swans and Tipping Points</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The codimension 
  <span class="italic">c</span>(γ) quantifies the 
  <span class="italic">rate</span> at which – due to the clustering - the spike levels λ
  <span class="sup">γ</span> build up as a function of the range of scales over which the dynamical processes act (eq. 
  <a rid="Equ3" ref-type="" href="#Equ3">3</a>). 
  <span class="italic">c</span>(γ) is nonlinear, requiring at least two parameters: the codimension near the mean (
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>1</sub>) and the multifractal index α that determines its curvature near the mean (eq. 
  <a rid="Equ8" ref-type="" href="#Equ8">M3</a>). However, it generally requires an additional third parameter 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> that characterizes the large γ behaviour, i.e. the tails of the probability distributions (eq. 
  <a rid="Equ13" ref-type="" href="#Equ13">M8</a>). This is because scaling in space and/or time generically gives rise to power law probability distributions (also known as “Pareto” or “fat-tailed” distributions). Specifically, the probability of a random temperature fluctuation Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span> exceeding a fixed threshold 
  <span class="italic">s</span> is:
  <div id="Equ5" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">5</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M39" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{array}{cc}{\rm{\Pr }}({\rm{\Delta }}T &gt; s)\approx {s}^{{q}_{D}}; &amp; s\gg 1\end{array}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M40" display="block" class="math">
     <div class="mtable">
      <div class="mtr">
       <div class="mtd">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Pr</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span stretchy="true" class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
           <span class="mi">T</span>
           <span class="mo">&gt;</span>
           <span class="mi">s</span>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="true" class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">≈</span>
         <div class="msup">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">s</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">q</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">D</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">;</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mtd">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">s</span>
         <span class="mo">≫</span>
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2018_30829_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>where 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> is a different exponent, this time characterizing the extremes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To get an idea of how extreme the extremes can be, consider an example with 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> = 5 (as has been estimated for the wind or temperature going back to ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> and Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). With this exponent, temperature fluctuations 10 times larger than typical fluctuations occur only 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> times less frequently. In comparison, for a Gaussian, they would be ≈10
  <span class="sup">23</span> times less likely; they would never be observed. Understanding the nature of the extremes is fundamental since it determines our interpretation of large events as either extreme - but nevertheless within the expected range, and hence “normal” - or outside this range, hence an “outlier” or perhaps even a “tipping point”.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) (top panel): The probability distribution for absolute changes in the time series of Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a> are shown. For clarity, they have been shifted to the right by factors left to right, respectively: 10, 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32). As discussed in Methods, reference lines give estimates of −
     <span class="italic">q</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">D</span>
     </sub> indicated in the figure and in Table 
     <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>. Also shown for reference (dashed curves) are the Gaussian distributions that give the same mean and standard deviations. (b) (bottom panel): The same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) but for the transects used in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>. Note that there plausible arguments that numerical model outputs and reanalyses (the two middle curves) tend to be too smooth and to underestimate extremes; this might explain some of the larger 
     <span class="italic">q</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">D</span>
     </sub> values (for weather and macroweather).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_30829_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2640" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A relevant example is global warming. Over about a century, there has been 1 °C warming of the globally averaged temperature - a roughly a 5 standard deviation event (with Gaussian probability ≈3 × 10
  <span class="sup">−6</span>). In spite of this, climate skeptics claim that it is no more than a Giant Natural Fluctuation (GNF) i.e. a change that might nevertheless be normal - albeit extreme. The relevant extreme centennial changes are indeed non-Gaussian, and bounding the probability tail between power laws with 4 &lt; 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> &lt; 6, ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> showed that the probability of extremes were enhanced by a factor of as much a factor of 1000. Yet the GNF hypothesis could nevertheless be statistically rejected with more than 99.9% confidence.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the log-log plots shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, we see that - as expected from eq. 
  <a rid="Equ5" ref-type="" href="#Equ5">5</a> - most of the distributions show evidence of log-log linearity near the extremes. When judging possible deviations, it could be recalled that due to inadequate instrumental response times, post-processing noise reduction procedures (e.g. smoothing) or via “outlier” elimination algorithms, that extremes can easily be underestimated. Also, several of the distributions in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> are from reanalyses which are numerical model outputs. Since physically, the extremes are consequences of variability building up over a wide range of spatial scales, the models’ small hyperviscous scale range (truncated at ≈10
  <span class="sup">5</span> m rather than at the viscous scale of ≈10
  <span class="sup">−3</span> m), effectively truncates the extreme tails. Any of these effects could explain deviations from perfect power law tails or might explain some of the larger (i.e. less extreme) 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> values in Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>. Finally, while power law probabilities arise naturally in scaling systems, the distributions are not 
  <span class="italic">necessarily</span> power laws; non-power law (curved tails in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>) may simply correspond to the special cases where 
  <div id="IEq16" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M41" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${q}_{D}\to \infty $$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M42" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">q</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">D</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">→</span>
     <span class="mi">∞</span>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41598_2018_30829_Article_IEq16.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In any event, for each empirical distribution, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> shows the Gaussian with the same mean and standard deviation (dashed). We see that the empirical distributions are generally quite far from Gaussian.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The power law fluctuations in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a,b</a> are so large that according to classical assumptions, they would be outliers. While Gaussians are mathematically convenient and can be justified when dealing with measurement errors, in atmospheric science thanks to the scaling, very few 
  <span class="italic">processes</span> are Gaussian. Extremes occur much too frequently, a fact that colleagues and I regularly underscored starting in the 1980’s (for a review see Table 5.1a,b. in ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At best, Gaussians can be justified for additive processes, with the added restriction that the variance is finite. However, once this restriction is dropped, we obtain “Levy distributions” with power law extremes, but with exponents 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> &lt; 2. The Gaussian assumption also fails for the additive but scaling 
  <span class="italic">H</span> model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Most importantly, Gaussians are irrelevant for multiplicative 
  <span class="italic">processes</span>: these generally lead to power law extremes but without any restriction on the value of 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Related models include Self-Organized Criticality
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> and Correlated Additive and Multiplicative noise
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Note that purely multiplicative random 
  <span class="italic">variables</span> lead to somewhat less extreme log Levy and lognormal distributions (i.e. the logarithms are Levy or Gaussian; for the latter, see
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> for an early review: their tails are “long” but not “fat”). The enhanced variability of multiplicative processes when compared to multiplicative variables is due to the singular small scale limit of the former; it has been theorized in the framework of multifractal phase transitions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. We could also mention that power law distributions also appear as the special (Frechet) case of Generalized Extreme Value Distributions although due to long range statistical dependencies, standard Extreme Value theory does not generally apply to scaling processes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To underscore the importance of nonclassical extremes, Taleb
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> introduced the terms “grey and black swans”. Originally, the former designated Levy extremes, and the latter was reserved for extremes that were so strong that they were outliers with respect to any existing theory. However, the term “grey swan” never stuck, and the better-known expression “black swan” is increasingly used for any power law extremes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of this is important in climate science where extreme events are often associated with tipping points. The existence of black swan extremes leads to a conundrum: since black swans already lead to exceptionally big extremes, how can we distinguish “mere” black swans from true tipping points?</p>
</sec>
