<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quasi-oscillatory model of atmospheric variability was first clearly articulated at the dawn of the paleo climate revolution by M. Mitchell
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> who admitted that it was largely “an educated guess”. In spite of weak empirical support, it survived because even sophisticated analysis techniques were only applied over narrow ranges of scale so that the bigger picture was obscured. In addition, analyses were not sufficiently 
  <span class="italic">simple</span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> spanning over 17 orders of magnitude in time (updated from
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>), clearly and simply shows how temperature and paleo temperatures vary with time scale; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a> shows examples of corresponding spatial statistics which are also scaling over large ranges.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) (top panel): A wide scale range composite of temporal Root Mean Square (RMS) Haar temperature fluctuations with the data described in Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> in thick lines (from left to right, the solid curves are data set #1, bottom, #2, top #3), #4, #5, #7, #8). The dashed lines are reproduced from ref.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
     </span> left to right, datasets #2, #6, #7, #8. Here as in b, the fluctuations were multiplied by the canonical calibration constant of 2 so that when the slopes are positive, the fluctuations are close to difference fluctuations. The various scaling regimes are indicated at the bottom. (b) (bottom panel): Same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) but for spatial transects. The bottom aircraft (data set #9) and top (daily resolution, data set #10) data are in the weather regime (“W”), the line labelled “M” is in the macroweather regime (data set #11), and the one labelled (“C”), the climate regime (data set #12, see Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> for details). At scales &gt;≈2500 km, the aircraft fluctuations from a single flight, have a dip caused by poor statistics. The breaks in the other (weather, macroweather and climate) transects only occur at scales of about 10,000 km (upper right).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_30829_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e220" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">New clarity was possible thanks to the rejuvenation of a fluctuation definition first proposed over a century ago
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. For a time series 
  <span class="italic">T</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>), the Haar fluctuation Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>(Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span>) over a time scale Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span>, is simply the difference between the average of the first and second halves of the interval Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span>. Although technically, the Haar fluctuation is a wavelet, one doesn’t need any knowledge of wavelets to use them. The utility of the Haar fluctuation is not only that it is easy to define and implement numerically - even on series with missing data - but rather that its 
  <span class="italic">interpretation</span> is simple. In regimes where the average fluctuations Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>(Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span>) increase with scale Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span>, it is nearly the same as the difference 
  <span class="italic">T</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) − 
  <span class="italic">T</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span> − Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span>), in regimes where the average fluctuation decreases with scale, it is nearly the same as the anomaly – the average value of segments of length Δ
  <span class="italic">t</span> of a series whose mean has been removed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. The Haar fluctuations are adequate as long as the fluctuation exponent 
  <span class="italic">H</span> is in the range −1 to 1 and this includes nearly all geophysical series (time) and transects (space; see below). With Haar fluctuations, wide scale range composites are both easy to produce and to interpret.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yet, this is more than just new picture for classifying atmospheric variability. In this paper, we explore some of its consequences: extremes, sparseness, spurious spectral spikes, oscillations, outliers and tipping points.</p>
</sec>
