<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spectra</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows that superficially routine series and transects can hide enormous nonclassical statistical variability. Until revealed by the spike plots, these fluctuations are virtually invisible yet they do not hide from spectral analysis which is highly sensitive to jumps. To explore this, we made a sample of 5000 realizations of a mildly intermittent multifractal process with parameters similar to those of the spiky regimes in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, see Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> and Methods; here 
  <span class="italic">H</span> = 0.33, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.05, α = 1.6 and each realization had 2048 points. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> (bottom left) shows one of the simulations and the corresponding spike plot (top left) confirming that while the process itself is apparently only weakly variable (bottom left), it is nevertheless highly spiky and non-Gaussian with two of the spikes having Gaussian 
  <span class="italic">p</span> ≪ 10
  <span class="sup">−9</span>. The spikiness is well detected by the spectral analysis which itself has spikes. The spectrum (the black curve) is of a single realization, it is a “periodogram” obtained with a standard Hanning window. The right panel of Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> reveals that with respect to the ensemble averaged spectrum (over 5000 periodograms from the same process, smooth, blue), nearly a dozen spectral spikes exceeded the conventional 2 standard deviation significance level (the arrows), with some exceeding the 4 standard deviation level (
  <span class="italic">p</span> ≈ 10
  <span class="sup">−5</span>). Although to make our point, we subjectively chose one of the more extreme of the first 50 simulations, this mild selection effect cannot explain the numerous strong spectral spikes. However, these spikes were to be expected since for each frequency, the tail of the probability distribution of the Fourier components was found to be a power law (here with exponent 
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </sub> ≈ 5, see below).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>A multifractal simulation of a 2048 point series (lower left) with spike plot (upper left), and the corresponding spectrum (black, right). In the spike plot, the lower horizontal line corresponds to the maximum expected for a Gaussian process, the top dashed line indicates the 10
     <span class="sup">−10</span> probability level. This realization was one of 5000 that were made with multifractal parameters 
     <span class="italic">H</span> = 1/3, C
     <sub>1</sub> = 0.05, α = 1.8 (see Methods and Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The smooth blue curve is the ensemble average of the process (with theory and numerics superposed: they cannot be distinguished). Above the blue curve, is an orange 2 standard deviation curve, and (red), 3, 4 standard deviation curves (probabilities 0.1%, 0.003% respectively). The arrows indicate spikes with Gaussian 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_30829_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2105" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Imagine that we performed a spectral analysis, but didn’t know what to expect; e.g. an early analysis of ice core paleo temperatures. Encouraged by the idea that variability is synonymous with oscillations (e.g. the NOAA paleo-data website states that “because a particular phenomenon is called an oscillation, it does not necessarily mean there is a particular oscillator causing the pattern. Some prefer to refer to such processes as variability”, cited in ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>), we might attempt to find a physical interpretation for some of the stronger spectral spikes. This temptation would be strengthened by the finding that some spikes are broad whereas (Gaussian) theory leads us to expect nearly independent Fourier components. Using sophisticated statistical methods such as multi-taper analysis (MTA) or singular spectral analysis (SSA), we could estimate the precise positions of the spectral spikes (see e.g. ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>). With this, we could judge their statistical significance. The conventional null hypothesis is that the background residuals are autoregressive order 1 Gaussian processes. For many of the spikes in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, we could reject this null hypothesis with very highly levels of confidence. For example, out the 100 lowest Fourier components shown, 10 would be significant at the 95% level (the arrows) and one would have a probability of less than 10
  <span class="sup">−6</span>. With a confidence level exceeding 99.9999%, we would be sorely tempted to postulate that we had uncovered strong evidence for the presence of a new quasi-periodic process.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is tempting to conclude that many ephemeral (and presumably spurious) claims of oscillatory atmospheric (and other) processes might have been consequences of fast computers, Fast Fourier Transforms, combined with inappropriate null hypotheses.</p>
</sec>
