<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic sea ice</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been hypothesized whether global warming can cause abrupt and irreversible sea-ice loss in the Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. The most important argument for this idea is the positive feedback between surface albedo and sea-ice loss (ice-albedo feedback). It has been found that the existence of bifurcations in sea ice models depends on the description of spatial differences and the seasonal cycle
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. While future ice loss is reversible in comprehensive models, these models also indicate that Arctic winter sea ice can be very sensitive to warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. Moreover, a comprehensive model shows three alternative stable sea-ice states on a completely land-free Earth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. One of these states is a globally ice-covered planet, resembling the “snowball” conditions that occurred during the Neoproterozoic. This state also occurs in at least one other complex model under present-day boundary conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, it is plausible that tipping points in sea ice have occurred in the Earth’s past, triggered by changes in the continental configuration, Milankovitch forcing, or the seasonal insolation cycle. In this regard, Eisenman
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span> provides an insightful parameter analysis of a simple Arctic sea ice model that is driven by the annual cycle of solar and terrestrial radiation. Small variations in these fluxes can lead to abrupt changes in the annual cycle of sea ice. Compared to the previous systems, Arctic sea ice and the surface ocean constitute a slow system that is not in equilibrium with the annual cycle of insolation. This can be seen from the fact that the annual cycle of Arctic sea ice volume lags the insolation cycle by approx. three months. The analysis by Eisenman
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span> was performed with a model that already included the annual cycle of short- and long-wave insolation. The concept of tipping points in periodically forced systems suggests that the bifurcations in the model originate from multiple states under certain fixed values of insolation, as the following model results show.
 </p>
</sec>
