<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toward a more general view on tipping points</div>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the sake of simplicity, our example models are a very idealized representation of reality. For example, alternative equilibria are arguably less likely or at least harder to find in more complex models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>
  </span>. Also, low-order models can often be misleading when spatial dimensions come into play. Taking space into account can often suppress multiple equilibria, but can also lead to new critical phenomena like pattern formation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Despite the relevance of abrupt shifts in the Earth system, the connection between regime transitions in spatially extended systems (like the onset of turbulence in fluids)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> and bifurcations in ordinary differential equations is not straightforward
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, and neither is such theoretical knowledge well applied to the specific physical systems mentioned above. Nonetheless, nonlinearities and critical thresholds are arguably present in all Earth system components, providing a basis for abrupt shifts. At the same time, other yet unrecognized tipping points could exist in the Earth system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In more realistic systems the drivers also have a more continuous spectrum. In models, the fast time scales in such spectra are often described by stochastic terms. The amplitude and period of the periodic oscillations we assumed above can be seen as an analogy for the typical magnitude and duration of random external fluctuations. Small changes in these statistical properties can lead to large and sometimes counter-intuitive changes in the distribution of a system’s state
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>
  </span>. In this regard, the concept of tipping points triggered by changes in periodic forcings is one representation of the fundamental question how vulnerable components of the Earth system are to environmental change. Theoretical progress has been made in recent decades to generalise concepts from bifurcation theory, for example by defining pullback attractors for deterministic non-autonomous systems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
  </span>, and random attractors for stochastic systems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>. Unfortunately, such theoretical insights do not always feed back to our knowledge on tipping points in the Earth system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One particular challenge in this regard is to investigate the applicability of statistical stability indicators that could provide an early warning of abrupt change. In climate research, this concept has mostly been explored in the static context of classical tipping points
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
  </span>. In the case of the systems above, classical indicators like rising variance and autocorrelation are not necessarily the most useful approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>
  </span>. It is therefore important to explore alternative approaches to early warnings of abrupt change. Although conceptual models cannot replace studies based on observations and process-based modelling, they can help raise questions for future research. For example, it may be beneficial to compare abrupt monsoon changes on different time scales and in different regions: Are there common mechanisms behind the abrupt onsets in different monsoon systems on the planet? Are these mechanisms also responsible for abrupt monsoon shifts in palaeorecords? Is the expectation to see early warning signals before the occurrence of a certain shift supported by current process understanding? Will stronger El Niño events have irreversible consequences for tropical forest and savannah ecosystems? Was sea ice involved in a tipping point in the Earth’s history, and what was the role of periodic forcings? To explore such questions, it would be beneficial to further develop models of low to intermediate complexity in addition to existing Earth system models. Such a model hierarchy is most established in the case of sea ice models, but patchy in the case of ecosystems, and lacking in the case of monsoons. A suite of models that are easy to use would also better connect research attempts to understand different monsoon systems.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On top of that, studies on isolated tipping elements may even not be sufficient, as different Earth system components are linked in their stability behaviour and thus do not act in isolation. For example, sea-ice loss and the meridional ocean circulation affect each other
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>
  </span>, and transitions between vegetation states depend on the global background climate involving the ice sheets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>
  </span> and the Atlantic overturning circulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>
  </span>. In light of the large uncertainties, the candidates and suspected mechanisms of tipping points will certainly evolve with new knowledge. As the Earth system is interspersed with feedbacks and natural thresholds, and features oscillations and environmental fluctuations on a vast range of time scales, it seems plausible that non-equilibrium tipping points have already occurred in the past and could occur again in the future.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data availability</div>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analysed data can be produced with the simple models as explained in the Supplementary Information, and can also be obtained from the lead author (S.B.).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
