<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The encountered deficiencies appear to be tightly connected with the total lack of capacity building strategies for protected area staff with regard to research abilities and methodological training for climate change adaptation across all evaluated plans. The wish and perceived need to increase the knowledge base before acting prevails. This issue was also encountered in 57 climate change adaptation plans in developed countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. Because of uncertainty and the lack of a culture dealing with non-knowledge and mistakes, managers seem to feel not strong enough and legitimated to ground management decisions on projections or scenarios. In conversations (in Brandenburg) they often insist in the judgement that current threats to biodiversity are more pressing than future changes. They seem to be more comfortable with reactive management, which is easier to justify, even when it is clearly coming too late and likely to fail. From many discussions we know that the reason could be even more trivial, but still alarming: Managers are simply overwhelmed by day-to-day management and have no resources for thinking about a more complex and future-oriented management. However, this greatly inhibits climate change adaptation. Also Geyer et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] identified a serious lack of confidence in proactive and future-oriented thinking. Other obstacles associated with the most deficient principles identified in other studies include a lack of resources and manpower, established management habits that conflict with a systematic learning process, static and incoherent legislation as well as restrictive policies and terms of reference for certain protected areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Not questioning the changeability of such barriers (however difficult they might appear to overcome) may itself be considered an obstacle to the adaptation process [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref088" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>].
</p>
