<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">All reviewed active transport articles concluded that their scenarios would reduce GHGE and increase physical activity resulting in net positive health outcomes. The degree to which GHGE were reduced or health was improved depended largely on the scale of the transportation modification, the range of health outcomes considered, and the assumptions of the model. In all reviewed articles physical activity was the largest determinant of health outcomes and was always positive. However, assumptions regarding the effects of traffic injury and air pollution varied between articles, resulting in a range of positive and negative health outcome predictions. Woodcock et al. [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] found that traffic injuries (modeled using risk (i.e., cycling injury data), distance and vehicle speed assumptions) decreased in all scenarios. Conversely, Macmillan et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] found that serious injuries and fatalities increase for cyclists (modeled using cycling injury data with a safety-in-numbers effect), causing a net increase in traffic fatalities despite decreased fatalities for car occupants. Such outcomes depend greatly on the assumptions made concerning the effect of increased cycling on the fatality and injury rate of cyclists. Countries where cycling is common, like the Netherlands, have much lower fatality rates than countries with little cycling, like the United States. It is not clear how or when fatality rates decrease with increased rates of cycling, though cycle friendly infrastructure and a “safety in numbers” effect almost certainly contributes. The net health benefit from reduced air pollution was positive for all articles, though Rojas-Reuda et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] and Rabl and De Nazelle [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] identified that not all individuals will be affected equally. In these articles, individuals engaging in active transport had increased fatalities from exposure to air pollutants, while the net effect on the population health was favorable. However, recent findings indicate that the health benefits from physical activity outweigh any ill effects of pollution for individuals engaging in physical activity in urban areas [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Notably, some transportation scenarios elected to combine elements of “greener” transportation (including cleaner operating vehicles, increased public transportation and active transport) for the greatest effect (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-14-00468-t003" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). This combined approach may provide more realistic transportation alternatives for a larger portion of the population.
</p>
