<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measures</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The primary outcome was the effect of the performance feedback dashboard on physicians’ motivation to make a quick disposition decision (i.e. the moment the physician decides whether the patients will be admitted to the hospital or discharged from the ED). To measure motivation, we used a set of measures derived from Self-Determination Theory which posits that perceived value/usefulness, competence, and autonomy support are important factors for motivation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. We used the Value/Usefulness and Competence subscales of the Intrinsic Motivation Inventory and the six-question version of the Work Climate Questionnaire for Perceived Autonomy Support [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>], which have been used and validated in a variety of settings including educational settings, sports psychology, and the workplace environment [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. All questions were rated on a seven-point Likert scale ranging from “Not at all true” to “Very true”. These questions were included in both the pre- and post-survey.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate changes in physicians’ practice patterns, we focused on test-ordering, which is a known predictor of LOS and is directly influenced by physicians’ decisions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. To assess physicians’ likelihood of ordering diagnostics tests, we included a vignette adapted from Kool et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>] in which the need for imaging is purposefully ambiguous. After reviewing the vignette, physicians were asked whether they would order diagnostic imaging, and if so, what type of diagnostic order. The vignette was included in both the pre- and post-survey.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate the design of the prototype performance dashboard in the post-survey, we assessed the perceived usefulness and ease of use based on the Technology Acceptance Model [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. The Technology Acceptance Model has been used extensively to evaluate physician acceptance of health technology [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. Questions such as “I believe that the performance feedback tool is flexible to interact with” were scored on a seven-point Likert-scale ranging from “Disagree strongly” and “Agree strongly”. We also assessed physicians’ perception of the importance of the metrics included in the dashboard and physicians’ perceptions of their ability to affect these measures on the same seven-point Likert-scale. Lastly, we asked physicians a Net Promotor Score question, which is widely used in various industries to understand the quality of the product or service: 
  <span class="italic">“How likely are you to recommend this performance feedback tool to your colleagues and peers to visualize and improve their performance as ED physicians?”</span> with an eleven-point response scale ranging from “Not likely at all” to “Extremely likely.” We also asked for suggestions to improve the tool and inquired about additional physician comments.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the ED culture, we asked physicians about their perceptions of the social, technical, and environmental aspects of their workplace in the pre-survey. We used the first thirteen questions of the Safety Attitudes and Safety Climate Questionnaire, which has been extensively psychometrically validated [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. These thirteen questions specifically address the teamwork and safety climate. All questions were scored on a five-point Likert scale ranging from “Disagree strongly” to “Agree strongly”, with an N/A option for each question. To describe the underlying social network, we included the question “
  <span class="italic">Who do you discuss problems with at work?</span>” which returns social network data indicating specifically who communicates with whom in the organization [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. Understanding this network is important if there are cultural barriers that limit the adoption of an intervention [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. Up to seven names could be selected from a pre-specified list of ED provider-names, including those in leadership roles. See Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a> for the complete surveys.
 </p>
</sec>
