<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the importance of end-user involvement in the development process, respondents were categorized as (1) directly involved in the dashboard development (interviewees, co-author MM), (2) not directly involved in the development but ≥30% of their network was involved, or (3) not directly involved and &lt; 30% of their network was involved. The social network question was used to create a model that assessed the level of exposure that each participant had to people who were involved in the development of the dashboard. Exposure was defined as the percentage of nominated people who were involved in the development [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Centrality measures for the social network analysis (in-degree, out-degree, closeness, and betweenness) were calculated using the igraph library [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. Out-degree is the number of people someone selected in the network question; in-degree is the number of times a person was selected by someone else; closeness measures the average distance someone has to everyone else in the network; and betweenness is a measure of how often each person lies on the shortest paths connecting others [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. People with high betweenness scores are thought to be key in the early adoption of innovation, people with a high in-degree are ‘popular’ figures in the network that are important for the innovation to spread to the early majority, and people with a high closeness score are thought to be important for an innovation to spread to a large amount of people [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Descriptive statistics were used to describe the sample and survey results. Pre- and post-survey data were compared using a Wilcoxon Ranked Sum test for continuous measures and the McNemar’s Test for categorical variables. The Kruskal-Wallis Test was used to compare change-scores between groups. A Spearman correlation coefficient was used to describe relations between continuous data. Rho correlations coefficients of &gt; 0.7 were considered strong correlations, coefficients between 0.5–0.7 were considered moderate, and coefficients between 0.3 and 0.5 were considered weak. A 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-value of &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. Analyses were performed in SAS 9.4 (Cary, NC).
 </p>
</sec>
