<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the Indian Gangetic plains, the combined pressures of population growth and climate change are likely to have significant impacts on agriculture and social dynamics in the years to come (Ministry of Home Affairs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">2011</xref>). In the specific context of Bihar, climate change is expected to impact due to heat stress (IPCC 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">2014</xref>), erratic monsoon events, with repetitive drought and unexpected floods (Sehgal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">2013</xref>; Kishore et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2014</xref>). Additional environmental hazards can result in the degradation of the quality and quantity of water, as well as being related to soil erosion (Mall et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2006</xref>; Sinha 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" class="xref">2011</xref>). Since 2009, Bihar has experimented four major droughts. In response, numerous external interventions involving women have sought to provide training and external support for implementing smart agriculture practices along with technological practices to mitigate the effects of climate change (Mehar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2016</xref>). For instance, at the Vaishali site, a formal women’s organization was created as part of the CGIAR Research Program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS). In Muzzafarpur, researchers from Rajendra Agricultural University, among others, have been working with local farmers on agro-biodiversity management programmes. However, the Bihar Action Plan for Climate change (Government of Bihar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2014</xref>) makes little mention of the statutory and customary rules that restrict women’s access to land, information and services. These constitute barriers to engage in environmental restoration and management programmes and are a cause of major vulnerability to climate change hazards.
</p>
