<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">We used modelled species distribution data, which represent predicted relative probabilities of species occurrence (from 0.0 to 1.0) at 0.5 degree latitude-by-longitude cell resolution, and are the best data available on the distribution of marine biodiversity globally. We used a probability threshold value of 0.5 or greater to define actual species presence (or the realized niche) to improve the robustness of our findings
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Using a 0.5 probability reduced the chance of capturing marginal or edge habitat of species and reduced the likelihood of overestimating species range representations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies have found a 0.5 threshold to be appropriate, with species distributions relatively robust across a range of thresholds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. We determined the proportion of LMPA in each 0.5 degree cell, and because the exact distribution of species within each cell in unknown, we assumed that the area of a species range represented in LMPAs was equal to the area of LMPA coverage for grid cells where the species were present in. But where the actual species’ range is only a portion of the cell and does not overlap with the MPA the representation will be overestimated. However, we found that in 73% of the cells containing MPAs, the MPA covered more than 90% of the cell’s ocean area meaning that such overestimation is likely to be minimal. Future analyses with actual – rather than modeled – species distributions and finer resolution will be able to provide better estimates of species’ representation by LMPAs. Given the limitations of the data we used, our results can only be interpreted at the resolution of the input data, 0.5 degree cells
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. We used one future climate scenario to model the future distributions of species, because although multiple climate scenarios exist, modeled species distribution data were only available for one scenario. We used all LMPAs that were officially designated as of December 2015 (defined as having a legal boundary; n = 53, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref> and Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>). We do not differentiate between varying levels of implementation, management, or enforcement because this information was not readily available. When improved data (species distributions, climate projections, management effectiveness) become available in the future, the analysis should be repeated. Additionally, as improved data becomes available it would be useful to evaluate the size and location of LMPAs for the optimal representation of biodiversity.
</p>
