<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BRT models construction and performance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One hundred bootstraps, each with 10-fold cross-validation, were applied to compute the mean, SD, and confidence intervals (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>) of (i) the mean reconstructed abundance of eastern bluefin tuna and (ii) the relative influence of each of the four hydroclimatic indices. Two BRT models were used to reconstruct bluefin tuna abundance for years 1634–1929, i.e., before the first industrial fishery and rapid north Atlantic warming (
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>), to assess the patterns of abundance while omitting the main components of human disturbances (i.e., the overfishing mortality and the rapid elevation of temperature with the increasing emissions of greenhouse gases). First, we considered the index of bluefin tuna abundance without a lag, and then, we incorporated a one-generation lag (i.e., 16-year lag selected by cross-correlation and taking into account the temporal autocorrelation of the time series). This enabled us to assess both the direct effects of hydroclimatic variability on adult distribution and the indirect effects on recruitment occurring one generation later. The performance of the two models in reconstructing eastern bluefin tuna abundances over 1634–2011 was assessed with the training data correlation (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>adj</sub>) (fig. S2).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our BRT models reproduced well the temporal autocorrelation that was detected in the observed bluefin tuna abundance index. It slowly decreases until a 27-year lag in the historical time series and to a 29-year lag in the predicted time series, which is in line with the maximum life-span of bluefin tuna.</p>
</sec>
