<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Elaboration of the Atlantic bluefin tuna abundance index</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Atlantic bluefin tuna is currently managed by the ICCAT as western and eastern stocks (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>), although these two stocks undertake annual migrations between the main spawning (i.e., the Gulf of Mexico and the Mediterranean Sea) and feeding (northwest, central, and NE Atlantic) regions (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>). While current changes in abundance occurring in the eastern region may relate to ~90% of Atlantic bluefin tuna populations (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>), the two stocks were assumed to be approximately the same order of magnitude in the 1970s until the western stock collapsed (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). However, the actual long-term fluctuations in the Atlantic-wide distribution of Atlantic bluefin tuna remain unknown. We focused our analyses on eastern bluefin tuna because historical data are available since the 16th century for this stock only (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>), assuming that it represented the baseline variability of about half of bluefin tuna populations over the past four centuries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the relative fluctuations in eastern Atlantic bluefin tuna from the mid-17th century onward, we used an index of abundance based on two databases: (i) the historical catches in traps located in and around the Mediterranean Sea during the period 1634–1959 that targeted large, mature individuals during their spawning migrations (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>) and (ii) the last ICCAT spawning stock biomass (SSB) estimation for the period 1950–2011 (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). While the consideration of young stages in the SSB might have slightly diminished the explanatory power of analyses after the 1960s, both datasets remained the most relevant to assess the major long-term changes in eastern bluefin tuna abundance (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>). We scaled the SSB index to the historical index over the common period 1950–1959 and evaluated their adequacy by applying a Wilcoxon test, which revealed no significant difference (
  <span class="italic">W</span> = 23, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.14). Both indices were then combined in a single abundance index spanning from 1634 to 2011, with relative abundance being averaged for the common period.
 </p>
</sec>
