<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Large-scale hydroclimatic indices</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigated the relative influence of four large-scale hydroclimatic indices used in the reconstruction of the Atlantic bluefin tuna abundance index for the period 1634–2011.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1) NHT anomalies were used as a proxy of the potential effect of climate change in the Northern Hemisphere. We used the dataset developed by the Tree-ring Network for the period 918–2011 (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.st-andrews.ac.uk/~rjsw/N-TREND/N-TREND2015.xlsx" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.st-andrews.ac.uk/~rjsw/N-TREND/N-TREND2015.xlsx</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2) The TSI index (the total spectrally integrated energy input to the top of the Earth’s atmosphere at a standard distance of one astronomical unit from the Sun) is assumed to be a good proxy of particularly cold periods (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>) around the end of the Little Ice Age (14th to mid-19th century; fig. S3). Data for the period 1610–2011 were provided by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.noaa.gov/dataset/dataset/noaa-climate-data-record-cdr-of-total-solar-irradiance-tsi-nrltsi-version-2" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://data.noaa.gov/dataset/dataset/noaa-climate-data-record-cdr-of-total-solar-irradiance-tsi-nrltsi-version-2</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3) The winter NAO index describes the basin-scale gradient of atmospheric pressures over the North Atlantic between the high pressures centered on the subtropical Atlantic and the low pressures over Iceland in winter (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>). We used (i) a millennium-long (1049–1969) tree-ring–based reconstruction of the NAO (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www1.ncdc.noaa.gov/pub/data/paleo/contributions_by_author/ortega2015/ortega2015nao.txt" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www1.ncdc.noaa.gov/pub/data/paleo/contributions_by_author/ortega2015/ortega2015nao.txt</span>) and (ii) the NAO index based on a rotated PCA performed on monthly standardized 500-mbar height anomalies over the North Atlantic sector for the period 1950–2011 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/precip/CWlink/pna/nao.shtml" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products/precip/CWlink/pna/nao.shtml</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4) The AMO index characterizes the multidecadal ocean/atmosphere natural variability in temperatures, in a range of 0.4°C, in many oceanic regions of the North Atlantic, with a periodicity ranging from 60 to 100 years (
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>). Here, we combined (i) a tree-ring–based reconstruction of the AMO for the period 1567–1990 (ftp://ftp.ncdc.noaa.gov/pub/data/paleo/treering/reconstructions/amo-gray2004.txt) and (ii) the index constructed from extended reconstructed SST data for the period 1856 onward and averaged in the area of 25° to 60°N and 7° to 75°W, minus regression on global mean temperature (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/timeseries/AMO/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/timeseries/AMO/</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We combined two hydroclimatic versions of the AMO and NAO indices to cover the whole time period 1634–2011. For each version, the oldest was rescaled (range and offset) to be comparable with the recent one. Variances were then homogenized by applying a moving mean of the larger window applied in the index reconstruction [i.e., 10 years for the AMO (
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>) and 3 years for both NAO indices. For each index, we calculated and tested the correlation between the reconstructions based on tree-ring data and contemporary indices, which proved to be highly significant in each case (for AMO indices: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,104</sub> = 268.6, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>adj</sub> = 0.72, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001; for NAO indices: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,15</sub> = 70.0, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>adj</sub> = 0.81, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001); old and recent indices were therefore averaged per year over common periods and combined into a single index.
 </p>
</sec>
