<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Occurrence data of the Atlantic bluefin tuna (T. thynnus, Linnaeus 1758)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The information on Atlantic bluefin tuna distribution was compiled from georeferenced (i.e., longitude and latitude) and time-referenced data (year, month, and day) available in public databases provided by the Ocean Biogeographic Information System (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 9288; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iobis.org/explore/#/taxon/519492" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://iobis.org/explore/#/taxon/519492</span>), the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 597; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.15468/dl.ndf0hz" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://doi.org/10.15468/dl.ndf0hz</span>), the International Commission for the Conservation of Atlantic Tunas (ICCAT) Task I (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 165,050), and the ICCAT conventional tagging (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 87,466; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iccat.int/en/accesingdb.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://iccat.int/en/accesingdb.html</span>). Duplicates were discarded on the basis of year, month, day, longitude, and latitude. A checking procedure was applied on ICCAT data to remove occurrences with a spatial resolution lower than 1° longitude by 1° latitude and a temporal resolution lower than 1 month (i.e., the resolution of the gridded climatic data described in the “Environmental data” section). Occurrences located outside the Atlantic Ocean or south of 12°S (i.e., outside the natural distribution range of Atlantic bluefin tuna) (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>) were also excluded. A total of 27,617 occurrences were retained to estimate the bluefin tuna’s habitat suitability. Distribution maps of occurrence records are presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a> (red dots).
 </p>
</sec>
