<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agglutination and lysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the effect of carotenoid supplementation on immune system performance in juvenile chameleons, we used a modified version of the agglutination and lysis assay described by Matson et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>], which is a highly repeatable and informative way to measure the strength of the humoral components of the constitutive innate immune system (specifically, antibodies and complement enzymes; [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>]). We made two modifications to the procedure described by Matson et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>] based on pilot work to maximize our ability to detect inter-individual variation: 1) we reduced the concentration of the SRBC suspensions in this assay from 1% to 0.5% and 2) the incubation temperature was decreased from 37°C to 26.5°C. This temperature change allowed the assay incubation to more accurately reflect the ambient temperature in which study animals were housed (range 25.0 - 27.2°C), as has been done previously with ectotherms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B51" href="#B51">51</a>] and which is important because incubation temperature plays a significant role in agglutination and lysis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B52" href="#B52">52</a>]. After incubation for 90 min, the plates were tilted for 20 min at 45° to permit visualization of the agglutination response, then digitally scanned at a resolution of 600 dpi. After scanning, the plates were laid out on a flat surface for 70 min before scanning a second time to record the lysis response. This assay thus identifies the plasma dilution at which agglutination (clumping of sRBC) and lysis (destruction of sRBC) occur due to innate immune mechanisms. The assessments of two independent investigators, blind to treatment, family, and individual, were significantly repeatable [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>] for both agglutination (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.990
  <span class="italic">, P</span> &lt; 0.0001) and lysis (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.989
  <span class="italic">, P</span> &lt; 0.0001), so we used the average of these scores for all subsequent statistical analyses. Because agglutination and lysis were highly positively correlated and are at least partially mechanistically linked [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>], we performed principal components analyses (PCA) to collapse agglutination and lysis scores into a single metric (with two metrics, this is the covariation between the two). The agglutination and lysis scores for chameleons during development reduced to a single principal component that explained 98% of the variation among these variables (agglutination loading, 0.71, lysis loading, 0.71). Therefore, individuals with high positive PC1 scores exhibited strong agglutination and lysis responses.
 </p>
</sec>
