<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blood collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess circulating carotenoid levels and some aspects of immunity, we drew blood five times during the study – once prior to carotenoid supplementation (Week 4) and at four other times during the supplementation period (Weeks 11, 14, 17, and 20; Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>). At each collection point, we collected up to 0.1% of each chameleon’s body mass of blood from the caudal vein with a 0.3 cc heparinized syringe and kept this blood on ice until centrifugation (5 min at 10,000 rpm). After centrifugation, we drew off plasma and stored it at -80°C for subsequent analyses (see below).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Timeline of carotenoid supplementation, blood collection, and dermal biopsies during our study.</span> During Week 4 of the study, blood was collected from all individuals to establish initial values for circulating carotenoid, agglutination, and lysis titers prior to supplementation (
    <span class="italic">Blood Collection 1</span>). Additionally, biopsy X
    <sub>0</sub> was performed during Week 4 of the study to determine the post-wounding time points with the greatest variation in wound area (to focus subsequent wound healing analyses). In Week 8 of the study, carotenoid supplementation commenced. Every three weeks during the supplementation period, blood was collected to measure circulating carotenoid levels and agglutination and lysis titers (
    <span class="italic">Blood Collections 2-5</span>). At weeks 14 and 20 of the study, we biopsied (X
    <sub>1</sub>, X
    <sub>2</sub>) the chameleons to evaluate wound healing. Wound healing rates were determined by measuring wound area from photographs taken immediately after biopsies, and on days 6 and 10 after wounding. Furthermore, we evaluated circulating nitric oxide levels by collecting blood samples immediately before, and again two days, after each biopsy.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1742-9994-11-26-2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
