<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual chameleons supplemented with the carotenoid lutein circulated significantly higher total carotenoid concentrations compared to control animals; however, this treatment did not influence any measured aspect of chameleon immune function. Specifically, there were no effects of lutein supplementation on the agglutination or lysis of SRBCs or on wound healing rate. Additionally, in marked contrast to the general predictions made by Alonso-Alvarez et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>] about carotenoids and their ameliorating effects on oxidative stress (such as that due to NO production), we found no effect of lutein supplementation on baseline NO levels or NO burst after wounding. While we uncovered several interesting relationships in this study (e.g., among growth, immunity, and post-wounding NO levels, discussed below), our findings demonstrate that lutein supplementation does not provide any significant immunostimulatory benefit in this species (at least for the immune system attributes we measured).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection should favor the evolution of carotenoid-dependent immune function in organisms with regular access to these biomolecules. For example, granivorous, frugivorous, and herbivorous animals that can selectively forage for carotenoid-rich food items (e.g., house finches 
  <span class="italic">Haemorhous mexicanus</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B58" href="#B58">58</a>]; parsnip webworms 
  <span class="italic">Depressaria pastinacella,</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B59" href="#B59">59</a>]; European blackcaps 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span>, [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">60</a>]) seem ideal candidates for the regular use and incorporation of carotenoid molecules into various aspects of the immune response. In contrast, predatory organisms that do not regularly ingest carotenoids directly from plants may be less likely to exhibit strict carotenoid-dependence for essential processes (e.g. immune function; [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B61" href="#B61">61</a>]), including ornamental coloration (
  <span class="italic">cf</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B48" href="#B48">48</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">63</a>]). The lack of any significant effects of lutein supplementation on immune responses of growing veiled chameleons should therefore be cautiously interpreted in a phylogenetic and life-history framework. Specifically, because most chameleons are arthropod generalists [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>] and may therefore be limited with respect to how much control they have over the carotenoid content of their food, selection may never have favored evolution of the mechanisms required for carotenoid-based immunoregulation. Carotenoid molecules appear to play an important role in the display colors used by veiled chameleons (authors’ unpublished data); however, our data suggest that incorporation and utilization of carotenoids by veiled chameleons is not required for immune system regulation in this species.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Family-level influences</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During development, family A became significantly more massive than family B in Week 12, a relationship that continued throughout the duration of the study. Unfortunately, this difference resulted in the nesting of body mass within family as well as housing arrangement (all family A cages were positioned higher than family B cages), which confounded our interpretations of all significant family effects that we uncovered. As such, differences between family groups could have arisen due to genetic or early developmental differences (e.g., in growth rate [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B64" href="#B64">64</a>]), effects of differing height on microenvironment conditions (e.g., lighting, temperature, humidity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>]), body mass-mediated differences [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>], or some interaction among these factors.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the primary differences we found between families was that supplemented members of family B always circulated significantly higher carotenoid levels than supplemented members of family A, and this can reasonably be explained by the phenomenon of dose-dilution as a function of body mass [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B57" href="#B57">57</a>]. Specifically, a given volume of carotenoids will be more diluted in larger-bodied animals than in those with smaller bodies. That differences between supplemented individuals arose as a result of differences in body mass is further supported by the fact that there were no differences in carotenoid circulation between families before supplementation (at the time when there was no family-based difference in mass) but that such differences existed during three of the four sampling periods after family masses became significantly different (with the fourth sampling period exhibiting the same, albeit non-significant, trend).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine performance of the developing humoral arm of the innate immune system, we recorded agglutination and lysis titers at multiple time points during development. We found that agglutination and lysis performance increased as the chameleons aged, but family A’s agglutination and lysis scores were generally higher than family B’s. However, differences in body mass between families did not likely drive the pattern for agglutination, as 
   <span class="italic">post hoc</span> analyses did not reveal any intrafamilial relationships between agglutination and lysis titers and mass. Given that the proteins that constitute the humoral branch of the innate immune system (i.e., antibodies and the complement system [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B67" href="#B67">67</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>]) are encoded by germ-line genes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>], it is possible that genetic differences drove the observed family difference in these aspects of innate immunity. However, we are unable to test if these family-level differences arose as a result of genetic effects or differences in cage height.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Families A and B had nearly equivalent agglutination and lysis scores by the end of the study (Week 20; Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">5</a>), a convergence that began in Week 14. Though these chameleons may not have reached full adult size by the end of this study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>], it is possible that, as they progressed into advanced developmental stages, Family A’s immune system was down-regulated, as they approached sexual maturity and began investing in reproductive characters (
   <span class="italic">cf.</span> the trade-off model described by [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">70</a>]). Similar trade-offs between reproduction and immune system activity have been documented in great tits 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>], crickets 
   <span class="italic">Gryllus texensis</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B72" href="#B72">72</a>], ruffs 
   <span class="italic">Philomachus pugnax</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B73" href="#B73">73</a>], tree lizards 
   <span class="italic">Urosaurus ornatus</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>], and black guillemots 
   <span class="italic">Cepphus grylle</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B74" href="#B74">74</a>]. However, because other variables were correlated with family, a convergence in lysis/agglutination scores due to sexual maturation is just one possibility, and interactions between age and genetic effects or rearing environment may have also influenced the changes in agglutination and lysis scores over time.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental wounding is a biologically relevant immune challenge, and multiple aspects of the immune response can be quantified following the biopsy, making this procedure a valuable tool in investigations of immune system function [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>]. Although carotenoid supplementation had no effect on wound-healing in our study, the family of origin had a significant effect on wound size at biopsy X
   <sub>2</sub>. Specifically, members of family A had consistently smaller wound areas in response to biopsy X
   <sub>2</sub> than those of family B, though no differences between families were detected for biopsies X
   <sub>0</sub> or X
   <sub>1</sub>. Oddly, for biopsy X
   <sub>2</sub>, wound size differed between the two families at all time points, including D
   <sub>0</sub>. Thus, the intial difference in wound size likely contributed to the observed differences at D
   <sub>6</sub> and D
   <sub>10</sub> (i.e. healing rate between the two families was similar). Because we used a standardized biopsy procedure with all chameleons, differences in wound area at D
   <sub>0</sub> are paradoxical, but might represent a difference in the acute response to trauma (e.g. tissue contractility). Independent of the wound size differences seen in response to biopsy X
   <sub>2</sub>, it is interesting to note that the pattern of wound healing changed from a linear reduction in wound area over time for biopsy X
   <sub>0</sub> (prior to supplementation) to a more biphasic healing trajectory in the subsequent (X
   <sub>1</sub> and X
   <sub>2</sub>) biopsies where healing rate was slower between D
   <sub>6</sub> and D
   <sub>10</sub> than it was between D
   <sub>0</sub> and D
   <sub>6</sub>. Furthermore, the initial reduction in wound area size was greater (steeper, more negative slope) for biopsies X
   <sub>1</sub> and X
   <sub>2</sub>. Because there were no effects of carotenoid supplementation on wound healing rate, these changes in healing rate may reflect an increased ability to deal with a wound of a given size as the chameleons grow, perhaps because the size of the wound relative to the size of the chameleons was less as the chameleons aged and grew. Additional work is required to determine whether these changes in healing trajectory are linked to age, size, sexual maturation, or some combination of these factors.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interpreting long- and short-term changes in NO</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on previous studies of NO, a key regulator of immune function and a non-specific pathogen destroyer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B75" href="#B75">75</a>], we anticipated that (i) NO levels before wounding would be low and approximately equivalent, representing a baseline circulating NO titer, and (ii) that higher levels would be observed after wounding, reflecting the NO burst triggered by an immune challenge ([
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>]; reviewed in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]). However, neither of these predictions was met. Instead, we recorded an overall decrease in NO levels in most individuals from pre- to post-wound, regardless of treatment or family group, which is in direct opposition to previous studies in mammals documenting a post-immune challenge increase in NO levels ([
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>]; reviewed in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]). Unfortunately, because we did not have a non-wounded control group to control for variability in NO related to age or time, our methodological limitations restrict the interpretation of these findings. It is possible that we mistimed our post-biopsy blood collection (though missing peak NO levels does not explain the observed reduction in NO levels from pre- to post-wounding) or that some aspect of the procedure itself caused the unexpected drop in NO. As such, additional work is required to determine the appropriate time course over which to measure NO burst in squamates and the underlying causes of the observed post-wounding decreases in plasma NO levels.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
