<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resource availability, assimilation, and allocation can affect the development and function of multiple physiological processes, including those of the immune system [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B1" href="#B1">1</a>]. While the capability to eliminate pathogens and recover from an immune challenge is critical to survival throughout life, robust immune function is particularly important to juveniles. Juveniles must survive the energetically demanding developmental phase to reach sexual maturity, and do so in sufficient health to reproduce [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>]. Additionally, exposure to pathogens during development can enhance immune function in adulthood (e.g., through acquired immunity; [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">3</a>]). Because of the costs associated with immune responses, however, the immune system is likely to consume resources at the expense of other costly physiological processes, such as growth and development [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>], ornamentation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>], and reproduction [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>]. Though numerous studies (e.g. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>]; reviewed in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B9" href="#B9">9</a>]) have documented trade-offs between growth and immune system development in juveniles, the limiting resources (e.g. energy, nutrients) and their influence on development are likely to vary among taxa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One well-studied physiological trade-off occurs with carotenoids, which, for vertebrates, can only be acquired through the diet [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B10" href="#B10">10</a>]. Carotenoids are a class of organic compounds that have bright red, orange, and yellow hues [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B11" href="#B11">11</a>] and can produce colorful ornamental structures [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B16" href="#B16">16</a>], but are simultaneously used for vital physiological processes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B17" href="#B17">17</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>]. Significantly, carotenoid molecules can play an important role in both the activation and regulation of the immune system (reviewed in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]), though these relationships are not universal [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>]. For example, carotenoids can enhance antibody production [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>] and activation of the plasma complement cascade (a set of proteolytic enzymes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>]) that promote inflammation, as well as the agglutination and marking of invasive microbes for destruction by lysis or phagocytosis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>]. Additionally, immune responses are frequently linked to increased oxidative stress [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">25</a>], illustrating the potential for a mechanistic link between antioxidants (such as carotenoids) and immunity. For example, the antioxidant activity of carotenoids has been implicated in ameliorating damage caused by free radicals, such as nitric oxide (NO), produced by immune cells when responding to pathogenic threats (reviewed in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>]). Carotenoids can also stimulate attacks on foreign cells after the skin has been breached (by activating an unidentified feature of the acquired immune system [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]), and may facilitate rapid recovery of wounds, as has been shown for other antioxidants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">28</a>]. Recovery from physical wounds is vital, because animals that heal wounds more quickly can minimize time spent in a vulnerable state [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B29" href="#B29">29</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>], yet this aspect of immune response is rarely considered. After wounding, carotenoids (in their role as antioxidants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B31" href="#B31">31</a>]) may even shield important host cells and structures from circulating NO [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">32</a>] which is released as a defense against pathogens in response to inflammation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>], yet is indiscriminately destructive to foreign microbes and host cells alike [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B36" href="#B36">36</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of literature on carotenoid physiology in animals has focused on the antioxidant functions and immunoregulatory roles of these compounds in birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>], despite their demonstrable physiological role in other taxa (e.g., mammals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B38" href="#B38">38</a>], reptiles [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B39" href="#B39">39</a>], fish [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>]). Given the relative lack of taxonomic diversity in carotenoid physiology research and the idea that dietary access to these nutrients during development (including embryonic stages [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">40</a>]) may be particularly important for developing immune systems (e.g. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B41" href="#B41">41</a>]), we tested the hypothesis that carotenoid supplementation during a period of rapid growth and development would improve immune system performance of captive juvenile male veiled chameleons (
  <span class="italic">Chamaeleo calyptratus</span>; Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a>). Veiled chameleons are a reptile species that uses carotenoids in their dynamic and colorful displays as adults (authors’ unpublished data), though the pigmentary content of the predominantly green coloration of juveniles is unknown. Additionally, veiled chameleons demonstrate intense intrasexual aggression and combat as adults [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B42" href="#B42">42</a>] and as juveniles (pers. obs.). This agonistic behavior occasionally results in open wounds (authors’ unpublished data), which could provide additional selective pressure for the ability to quickly heal injuries (which can also be obtained in a number of other ways, for instance via predation attempts). Therefore, we used a standardized biopsy procedure to quantify wound healing, a biologically relevant measure of multiple phases of the immune response [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>], during development. The biopsy simultaneously provided an immune-challenge to our chameleons that could be used to monitor other metrics of immune function in blood samples. Blood was measured for circulating plasma NO and carotenoid levels, as well as the agglutination ability of antibodies and the lytic capacity of complement (quantified by a sheep red blood cell (SRBC) assay). We predicted that dietary carotenoid supplementation would result in elevated levels of circulating carotenoids, which in turn would positively affect various aspects of immunity and wound healing. Specifically, both within and between treatment groups, we predicted that higher carotenoid levels would be associated with a greater ability of circulating antibodies and complement to agglutinate and lyse SRBCs [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>]. We also predicted that higher levels of circulating carotenoids would have a two-pronged effect on NO levels and wounding healing: (i) in their role as immunostimulants (reviewed in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]), carotenoids should initiate and accelerate the NO burst following wounding, and (ii) by serving as antioxidants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>], carotenoids should counteract the indiscriminately destructive pro-oxidant activity of NO, allowing carotenoid-supplemented individuals to avoid self-damage associated with NO and lead to faster rates of wound healing [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Juvenile veiled chameleons (</span>
    <span class="bold">
     <span class="italic">Chamaeleo calyptratus</span>
    </span>
    <span class="bold">) during (a) Week 1 (approximately 8 weeks of age) and (b) Week 17 of the study.</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1742-9994-11-26-1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
