<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study design</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We purchased two groups of 10, eight-week old male veiled chameleon siblings through a private breeder (FL Chams, Florida, USA) in July 2011. Chameleons were initially housed in groups of five brothers in four identical cages (89 × 56 × 53 cm) with screen roofs and doors, feeding cups, and automated misters (which misted for three minutes, four times per day). All chameleons experienced a 12:12 light:dark cycle, and we provided each cage with a heat lamp (Zoo Med Repti-Basking Spot Lamp, 50 watt, Zoo Med laboratories Inc., San Luis Obispo, CA, USA) and a UV light source (Zoo Med Reptisun 5.0 UVB Fluorescent Bulbs, Zoo Med laboratories Inc., San Luis Obispo, CA, USA). Individual cage lamps were set to turn on 15 min after the room lights to simulate dawn and turn off 15 min before room lights to simulate dusk. We housed the chameleons in an indoor, climate-controlled room with the daily temperature range set to 25.0-27.2°C and an average humidity of 25-35%.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All cages were furnished with grape vines (
  <span class="italic">Vitis</span> spp.), yellow palo verde (
  <span class="italic">Parkinsonia microphylla</span>) branches, and faux vines to provide perches at various heights for thermoregulation under the heat lamps [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>]. Space limitations necessitated that we place chameleon cages in two tiers, with one group of 10 brothers (hereafter, family A) occupying the upper cages of our stacked racks and the remaining group of brothers (family B) occupying the lower cages. All members of each family were kept at the same relative height throughout the duration of the study to minimize within-family differences in housing conditions and maximize our ability to detect any effects of carotenoid supplementation. After an eight week acclimation period, we moved all chameleons into individual cages to prevent excessive aggression [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>]. During both the acclimation and experimental periods, we fed the chameleons crickets dusted with calcium (
  <span class="italic">Rep-Cal</span> Phosphorus-free Calcium, 0% D3, Rep-Cal Research Labs, Los Gatos, CA, USA) and vitamins (Zoo Med Reptivite Reptile Vitamins, Zoo Med Laboratories Inc., San Luis Obispo, CA, USA) throughout the study. Wild chameleons have access to a broader array of dietary items, so the limited diversity of commercially available food items necessitates dietary supplements such as these [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>]. Reptivite vitamins contained no measurable quantities of any carotenoid.
 </p>
</sec>
