<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wound healing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We took dermal biopsies from each chameleon at three time points during the study and recorded changes in wound area using digital photography [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] and image processing and analysis freeware (ImageJ64, NIH [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">54</a>]). We collected dermal biopsies using a standardized procedure based on a previous wound healing study [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>], though we modified biopsy placement to better suit chameleon morphology. Immediately after blood collection, we anesthetized each chameleon using isoflurane, then disinfected the biopsy site with isopropyl alcohol and removed a circular section of the epidermis and dermis near the hip using a 3.5 mm biopsy punch. After wounding, pressure was applied for three minutes or until bleeding was stopped before the wound was photographed. We conducted the first biopsy (X
  <sub>0</sub>) and all associated wound photography (Weeks 4-7) before carotenoid supplementation began. We performed two other biopsies adjacent to, but not at, the location of previous biopsies during the supplementation period at predetermined time points corresponding to the middle (Biopsy 1 = X
  <sub>1</sub>; Week 14) and end (Biopsy 2 = X
  <sub>2</sub>; Week 20) of the study. The second biopsy (X
  <sub>1</sub>) was conducted on the opposite side of the body as the first biopsy (X
  <sub>0</sub>), and the third biopsy (X
  <sub>2</sub>) was on the same side as biopsy X
  <sub>0</sub>, separated by approximately 8 mm.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All wounds were photographed in a standardized fashion to control for angle and distance, as well as to improve repeatability. Chameleons were manually restrained during photography sessions and all photographs were taken with a digital camera (Panasonic HDC-TM700P/PC, Panasonic Corporation, Kadoma, Osaka, Japan) on a small tripod. We positioned light sources to best illuminate the wound area and elevated a ruler to be level with the wound for setting scale in later image analysis. A minimum of four photographs were taken of each wound, ensuring at least two were zoomed in as close as possible without compromising focus.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After X
  <sub>0</sub>, we monitored and photographed all wounds every other day, beginning on the day of biopsy (D
  <sub>0</sub>), until at least one chameleon’s wound was fully healed (i.e., biopsy site was completely covered in smooth, gray scar tissue or new colorful epidermis). From a subset of these photographs, we determined two time-points (Day 6 = D
  <sub>6</sub> and Day 10 = D
  <sub>10</sub>) during the healing process that yielded the greatest variation in wound size, suggesting that wound measurements taken on these days during future biopsies would be most likely to capture inter-individual variation in wound healing rate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All wound photographs were viewed in ImageJ64 to assess the size of the wound (mm
  <span class="sup">2</span>), with the investigator blind to sampling date, treatment, and chameleon identity (ImageJ64, NIH [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">54</a>]). Based on French et al.’s [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] study in tree lizards (
  <span class="italic">Urosaurus ornatus</span>), we used the area of the wound as a measure of wound healing (where area was the most reliable metric because wounds healed in a non-uniform manner and irregular closure of wounds was common). Specifically, the area of any portion of the biopsy site that was considered unhealed “wound” (i.e., textured or deep red) was measured (Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3" href="#S3">3</a>: Figure S1). On every occasion of wound measurement, at least two photos with both a well-focused ruler and wound were analyzed and the wound areas averaged. We calculated the repeatability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>] of wound sizes during one round of wound healing and found that wound size (mm
  <span class="sup">2</span>) was significantly repeatable for all chameleons (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.97, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001).
 </p>
</sec>
