<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees at the global scale
 </div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To ascertain how important the climate impacts of N-fixing trees could be, we estimated the net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees at the global scale. Although N-fixing trees play a crucial role in forests, the global distribution of N fixation strategies is not well established
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Accordingly, we made estimates of the global net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees first by examining three basic scenarios: all N-fixing trees are obligate, all N-fixing trees are facultative, and all N-fixing trees are incomplete regulators. Because forests around the globe include an assemblage of these three N fixation strategies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, the maximum and minimum of these three basic scenarios provide bounds to the global net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees. We ran each basic scenario under future N deposition rates (for the SRES A2 scenario). Our model suggests that if all N-fixing trees are facultative, they will have an insignificant influence on estimates of the net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of global forests (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). At the opposite extreme, if all N-fixing trees are obligate, N-fixing trees will decrease estimates of the net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of global forests by the radiative equivalent of 0.77 Pg C yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modeled global net CO
     <sub>2</sub>–N
     <sub>2</sub>O effect of forests and of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees under future N deposition rates (2030 for the SRES A2 scenario)
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Global forest composition</th>
      <th>Global net CO
       <sub>2</sub>–N
       <sub>2</sub>O effect of forests (Pg C yr
       <span class="sup">−1</span>)
      </th>
      <th>Global net CO
       <sub>2</sub>–N
       <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees (Pg C yr
       <span class="sup">−1</span>)
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Obligate N-fixer and non-fixer</td>
      <td>−2.98</td>
      <td>+0.77</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Facultative N-fixer and non-fixer</td>
      <td>−3.72</td>
      <td>+0.03</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Incomplete regulator N-fixer and non-fixer</td>
      <td>−3.40</td>
      <td>+0.36</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Non-fixer</td>
      <td>−3.76</td>
      <td>Not applicable</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Scenarios displayed are: all N-fixing trees are obligate, all N-fixing trees are facultative, and all N-fixing trees are incomplete regulators. Units are C radiative equivalents, which balance the greenhouse effects of CO
     <sub>2</sub> and N
     <sub>2</sub>O using the global warming potential of N
     <sub>2</sub>O. Negative values in the centre column indicate a net cooling CO
     <sub>2</sub>–N
     <sub>2</sub>O effect of forests. Positive values in the right-hand column, which are the differences from the non-fixer row in the centre column, indicate that N-fixing trees have a net warming CO
     <sub>2</sub>–N
     <sub>2</sub>O effect relative to non-fixing trees
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="italic">NA</span> not applicable
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a further analysis, we determined the global net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effects of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees for a range of relative abundances of ecosystems containing obligate N-fixing trees and ecosystems containing facultative N-fixing trees under a range of N deposition rates (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). Under recent N deposition rates, our assumptions of the relative abundances of ecosystems containing obligate and facultative N-fixing trees have a negligible influence on the global net CO
  <sub>2</sub>–N
  <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>, Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), whereas under future N deposition rates these assumptions can change this global scale estimate by up to 0.77 Pg C yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>, Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modeled global CO
     <sub>2</sub> and N
     <sub>2</sub>O effects of nitrogen-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Global net CO
     <sub>2</sub>–N
     <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees for a range of relative abundances of ecosystems containing obligate N-fixing trees and ecosystems containing facultative N-fixing trees under a range of N deposition rates. Global forest composition ranges from the scenario in which all N-fixing trees are facultative to the scenario in which all N-fixing trees are obligate, i.e. the relative abundances of ecosystems containing obligate N-fixing trees and ecosystems containing facultative N-fixing trees range from 0 to 100% and 100 to 0% respectively. Red represents a warming effect and blue represents a cooling effect relative to non-fixing trees. Global N deposition rate ranges from the minimum recent N deposition rate derived from Vet et al.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span> or Dentener et al.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
     </span>, to the future N deposition rate derived from Dentener et al.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
     </span>. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Global net CO
     <sub>2</sub>–N
     <sub>2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees under recent and future N deposition rates. The curves in 
     <span class="bold">b</span> are cross sections of the extremes of the surface displayed in 
     <span class="bold">a</span>. The dotted line is at zero, representing the transition between a cooling effect and a warming effect relative to non-fixing trees. Fac. represents ecosystems containing facultative N-fixing trees and Ob. represents ecosystems containing obligate N-fixing trees
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9424_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1159" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
