<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Table 2</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Additional parameter plane regions.</p>
 </div>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Region</th>
    <th>Behaviour</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>A</td>
    <td>Bistable regime, converging to either a coral death equilibrium with sustainable parrotfish density or the unassisted macroalgae-free equilibrium.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>B</td>
    <td>Behaviour stabilizes to either a limit cycle or the assisted macroalgae-free equilibrium.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>Tristable regime, stabilizing to either: (
     <span class="bold">1</span>) a coral death equilibrium with parrotfish survival and full conservation cooperation, (
     <span class="bold">2</span>) a catastrophic equilibrium with parrotfish extinction with full conservation cooperation or (
     <span class="bold">3</span>) the assisted macroalgae-free equilibrium.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>D</td>
    <td>Bistable regime, stabilizing to either the assisted macroalgae-free equilibrium or a state of coral and macroalgal decimation, with human-assisted parrotfish survival.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>E</td>
    <td>Tristable regime, stabilizing to either: (
     <span class="bold">1</span>) the unassisted macroalgae-free equilibrium, (
     <span class="bold">2</span>) the assisted macroalgae-free equilibrium, or (
     <span class="bold">3</span>) a state governed by a human-unassisted coral death equilibrium, with sustainable parrotfish density.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>F</td>
    <td>Bistable regime, stabilizing to either the unassisted macroalgae-free equilibrium or a state governed by the human-unassisted coral death equilibrium, with sustainable parrotfish density.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>G</td>
    <td>Tristable regime, with behaviour converging to either behaviour of (
     <span class="bold">D</span>), or a state governed by the human-unassisted coral death equilibrium, solely governed by macroalgae.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>H</td>
    <td>Convergence to limit cycles.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</div>
