<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Giant kelp populations are naturally quite variable, so changes in kelp forests can easily be misinterpreted unless viewed in the context of long-term data
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>. Longer and more spatially comprehensive records of giant kelp and sea surface temperature (SST) obtained from satellite imagery confirm the patterns documented by divers and moored sensors at our study sites. Large seasonal and interannual fluctuations in giant kelp biomass characterized all of southern California from 1984–2015 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4a</xref>). However, negative-kelp anomalies during 2014–2015 from Santa Barbara to the Mexican border in San Diego were within the range observed during the 32-year time series despite unprecedented positive anomalies in ocean temperatures during this period (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4b</xref>). This result is quite surprising given giant kelp's reported sensitivity to such conditions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref> and stands in contrast to reports from other kelp systems showing sharp declines in response to warming conditions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>. The location of our study within giant kelp's range offers one possible explanation for the difference; southern California, and Santa Barbara in particular, does not represent either the geographical or thermal limit for the species in the northeast Pacific
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref> although San Diego is on average 1–4 °C warmer than Santa Barbara and closer to giant kelp's thermal limit (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). Nevertheless, giant kelp populations are highly adapted to local nutrient conditions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref> and the potential for rapid dispersal from distant populations that are better adapted to sudden changes in local conditions is limited
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>. Thus, similar to that shown for other habitat forming seaweeds
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref>, we would expect giant kelp populations far from the range edge to be equally sensitive to large and sustained anomalies in temperature and nutrients such as those associated with the recent warming event.
</p>
