<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The same tendencies in temperature, precipitation and climate extremes are projected in the twenty-first century, in all the moderate-to-high emission scenarios, with the amplitude of the climate change signal growing proportionally with the projected global warming. The intensification of the hydrological cycle in the recent decades and in future projections has also been detected in in the world's dry and wet regions, leading to an increased risk of flooding in dry regions as the climate warms (Donat et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). However, the future projections of the West African climate are affected by large uncertainties, especially regarding the monsoonal precipitation. Indeed, although around 50% of the CMIP5 GCMs agrees on the future positive trend, around 25% of the models project the opposite situation, weakening the prevision (Biasutti, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). The origin of this uncertainties is two-fold. On the one hand, the biases characterizing the SST simulated by the atmosphere-ocean climate models, which affect the mechanisms driving the multidecadal variability of the WAM system (Roehrig et al., 
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Rowell, 
 <xref rid="B165" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). On the other hand, the diverse sensitivity of climate models to the effect of the projected increase in CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration, which induces wet anomalies through the direct radiative warming of the surface at the regional scale, but at the same time inhibits the precipitation when the radiative forcing is mediated by the global SST warming (Bony et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Gaetani et al., 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Climate modeling of West Africa at the regional scale shows promising improvements of the GCM performances, although large uncertainties still persist. Firstly, RCMs are inevitably affected by the biases of the driving GCMs (Dosio et al., 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Secondly, RCMs experiments show high sensitivity to the physical parametrization, especially regarding convection (Klutse et al., 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), which is crucial for the simulation of the monsoonal rainfall. Therefore, the climate modeling community is pushed for a further effort to improve the modeling of West African climate, in the direction of both understanding the physical mechanisms and reducing the climate model shortcomings.
</p>
