<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the analysis of STRUCTURE, two clusters (K = 2), representing a southern and a northern group, may be the most parsimonious explanation for the structure present in the data, yet we consider it not to offer the most biologically meaningful explanation. This is because three clusters (K = 3) better reflect the structure in the data, showing groups of populations that are geographically coherent. Moreover, the three genetic clusters, as revealed by nSSRs were further fully supported by the analysis of cpDNA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0194726.g003" class="xref">Fig 3</xref>). Here, the green cluster matched haplotype H2, and the brown and orange clusters matched the closely related haplotypes H5 and H4. Although dispersal via pollen in 
 <italic class="italic">Senegalia senegal</italic> might be effective within its natural landscapes coupled with the fact that open low density forest facilitates longer pollen dispersal distances [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], human-mediated dispersal through decades of economic usage might have also influenced the disjunct pattern of populations of cluster 1 observed in the dataset. Because of its agroforestry importance and high quality gum production, 
 <italic class="italic">Senegalia</italic> seeds have been traded among nomads, pastorialists and traders of various agricultural products across the region for centuries [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Various animals such as cattle, sheep, goat, donkey and camels that graze on the fields for pasture across the entire region play a role in the dispersal of seeds among population. These human-mediated seed transfer is usually along specific routes of similar arid environmental condition, such as MDG, ZUR, and BKG. Frequent gene flow is propagated among those populations without severe interference with populations aside those routes, such as BRN, JAK, and HAD. In addition, sharp environmental transition due to climate change and land use has been shown to be responsible for the increasing aridity from north to south, hence the progressive expansion of 
 <italic class="italic">Senegalia</italic> species from the driest to the wettest zones in the SSZ [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Consequently, this gradient rather than geographic distance accounts for gene flow among the populations making up cluster 2 and 3 (K = 3), and thus the divergence of populations.
</p>
