<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The major drivers of the socioeconomics of the industry are economic development, specifically per capita disposable income (PCDI, which impacts scallop pricing and demand) and fuel costs (which impacts industry operating costs and crew incomes). To develop trajectories for future socioeconomic scenarios, we used the output from the GCAM integrated assessment model which developed the RCP4.5 scenario [
 <xref rid="pone.0203536.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0203536.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Each official RCP scenario has been generated using a different integrated assessment model with separate underlying drivers and assumptions. In order to maintain consistency between model assumptions for the future scenarios, we used projections of economic development and carbon taxes from GCAM’s estimates of the other RCP scenarios. We converted US GDP and population projections to PCDI by correcting GDP per capita data to PCDI through a derived correlation using historical data from US Bureau of Economic Analysis of US population (pop), GDP, and PCDI data corrected to 2011 USD (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0203536.e001" class="xref">Eq 1</xref>): 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0203536.e001" class="disp-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0203536.e001.jpg" id="pone.0203536.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M1" class="math">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">P</mi>
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
      <mi class="mi">D</mi>
      <mi class="mi">I</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mn class="mn">2011</mn>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo class="mo">=</mo>
    <mi class="mi">A</mi>
    <mi class="mi">*</mi>
    <mo class="mo">(</mo>
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mi class="mi">G</mi>
         <mi class="mi">D</mi>
         <mi class="mi">P</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mn class="mn">2011</mn>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">p</mi>
       <mi class="mi">o</mi>
       <mi class="mi">p</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
    <mo class="mo">)</mo>
    <mo class="mo">-</mo>
    <mi class="mi">B</mi>
    <mo class="mo">,</mo>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
 </disp-formula> where PCDI
 <sub class="sub">2011</sub> is the historical per capita disposable income corrected to 2011 USD, GDP
 <sub class="sub">2011</sub> is the historical US GDP corrected to 2011 USD, and pop is the historical population. A and B are constants derived as 0.8025 ± 0.0286 and 2383 ± 1089 (r
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.984, p &lt; 0.0001), respectively. Future PCDI, corrected to 2011 USD, is expected to increase by a factor of 2.5–3 by the end of century under all four climate scenarios analyzed in this study (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0203536.g002" class="xref">Fig 2C</xref>). There is considerable uncertainty in projections of energy use, emissions scenarios, and economic development that has begun to be recently explored in greater detail using the future Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs) [
 <xref rid="pone.0203536.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Given that our temperature and atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> projections were based upon the RCP scenarios, we chose to the use the RCP projections of GDP and population to generate our PCDI projection. The impacts of different economic development narratives could be explored in more detail using the new SSPs but would be beyond the scope of this study.
</p>
