<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Studies have argued that some or all the negative global warming impacts on wheat yields might be compensated for by the increasing atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration in combination with adaptation strategies (
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">32</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">34</italic>
 </xref>). In semiarid environments, wheat growth will be enhanced by the higher water use efficiency under elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">35</italic>
 </xref>). However, the authors of the corresponding study stated that “supplemental irrigation was applied to the entire experiment on occasion during excessively dry periods to prevent crop loss,” indicating that the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> transpiration effect has limitations under extreme drought, as has been confirmed experimentally by Medina 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">36</italic>
 </xref>). Although water use is reduced under elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">37</italic>
 </xref>) and may alleviate moderate dry spells, recent studies have found that drought stress mediated by severe heat cannot be compensated for by elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">38</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">39</italic>
 </xref>). Long-term studies with elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> revealed that intensifying drought for some crops resulted in diminished yield stimulation under an elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration (
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">40</italic>
 </xref>). In addition, Dai 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">41</italic>
 </xref>) compared the future drying in a model simulation with and without considering the plant physiology in response to increasing CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. They found that the plant physiological response to increasing GHGs is secondary, suggesting that the impact of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization on future drought is small. As explained in Materials and Methods, we calculated the potential evapotranspiration (PET) through the Penman-Monteith method using an approach based on the surface energy budget, and therefore, the ambient CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> effects on plant transpiration, vegetation growth, and feed feedback are implicitly considered. Therefore, we postulate that the effects of SWS will likely not be alleviated by enhanced CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and that SWS implementing PET based on the surface energy budget approach represents a reliable indicator of drought irrespective of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> levels.
</p>
