<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate score variance across wards was significant for the factors Safety climate, Working conditions, and Perceptions of management. All three factors had noticeable ICCs and sufficient between-ward heterogeneity to be considered organizational climates [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref019">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control for responder sociodemographic background characteristics eliminated ward level factor score variation for Safety Climate, but not for Working conditions and Perceptions of management. For Working conditions and Perceptions of management ward level variance even increased, indicating that actual ward differences were hidden in the empty models, in which staff age, gender, mother tongue and job experience were not taken into account. The significant clustering of the factor scores Safety climate, Working conditions, and Perceptions of management indicates that leaders can address patient safety at organizational level by using climate survey scores to identify nursing home wards with high and low climate scores. This is important for clinicians and patients in wards with lower scores, where the SAQ-A may identify potentials for and perhaps lead to improvement.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, 42 000 people with and without dementia are residing in one of the 955 nursing homes in Norway, most of them—about 31 000—in long-term care units [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref035">35</a>]. The average nursing home has 44 residents (range 8–200). The usual nursing home unit has 8 to 14 residents, usually in single-bed rooms (98%). Almost 90% of all institutions are owned and run by the municipalities, and more than 145 000 registered nurses and lisenced practical nurses are responsible for care and treatment. Nursing home care in Norway is a standardized service, available in all municipalities. It is paid for by the Government, which requires homogeneous provision of care for the frailest old. The included nursing homes in Tønsberg are comparable to usual nursing home standard, staffing and education level at baseline. However, individual variations for instance in connection with leader awareness and engagement are possible.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a previous paper we already found that considerable parts of the patient safety climate factor score variations in hospitals were at ward and department levels [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref026">26</a>]. More variation was seen at ward level than at department level. We concluded that patient safety culture improvement efforts in hospitals should not be limited to all-hospital interventions or interventions aimed at entire departments, but also include involvement at the ward level, selectively aimed at low scoring wards. In the present study, we have found that the same principle applies to nursing homes. Improvement tools to help discuss measurement results are developed and have been shown effective in dealing with ward-specific patient safety problems [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref036">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A strength of the study is that besides studying between-ward variance, we also evaluated the climate strength by calculating within-groups agreement, thereby quantifying the degree to which patient safety is a shared concern within organizational units. It is relevant when applying the tool in practical improvement work; the stronger the climate, the more it predicts care processes and outcome [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref019">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Stress recognition factor lacked variance between wards. In a previous patient safety climate study in departments of non-psychiatric care in a Norwegian hospital no between-site variation in staff perceptions of Stress recognition was found [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref037">37</a>]. An explanation may be that the items reflect individual level attitudes and not a group phenomenon. Therefore, the factor is probably not useful for organizational climate measurements.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Staff perception of Teamwork climate and Job satisfaction were good in most wards, with little variation between wards. The variance at ward level for Teamwork climate and Job satisfaction was low and insignificant, indicating low between-ward heterogeneity. The results means that the Teamwork climate and Job satisfaction factors are less useful for identifying wards with improvement opportunities in nursing homes. This stands in contrast to a hospital study where the Teamwork climate and Job satisfaction factors produced significant between-ward variance [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref037">37</a>]. The small ICCs produced by these two factors in nursing homes may be due to differences, e.g., in the presence or absence of medical doctors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hospital studies have found that medical doctors have significantly more positive Teamwork climate perceptions than do nurses [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref039">39</a>]. The difference in Teamwork climate factor and Job satisfaction factor variance between wards in hospitals and nursing homes may therefore perhaps be related to differences in the composition of professions. The extent to which doctors and nurses expect that voicing patient safety concerns will be met with respect within their team may for example have an impact [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref040">40</a>]. That will naturally depend on interpersonal relations and support across professional boundaries to make patients safe. Positive experiences may create positive perceptions of the two factors as well as good relationships and trust between doctors and nurses. Bad experiences may, on the contrary, create distrust and negative perceptions of the same factors. In this way, measurements of Teamwork climate and Job satisfaction may expose how relationships between and within professions vary across hospital wards. In nursing homes, where differences in professional background are smaller, relationships between staff members vary less, which is reflected in little variance in the measurements.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we did not measure the nursing home care process, or its outcome. We therefore cannot validate whether variation in climate scores produces variation in care processes and outcome. This relationship has, however, been established in other studies [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref012">12</a>]. It would also have been useful to have data on leadership practices regarding dialogue meetings with staff and the extent of patient safety issues on board meeting agendas [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref041">41</a>]. With such data we could have studied if the variation was related to leadership activities [
  <a rid="pone.0218244.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218244.ref022">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results in this study were fed back to each of the participating nursing home wards with five or more respondents. Each ward was shown its own scores and compared with the scores of all the other participating wards, the latter presented anonymously, so no accidental reader could identify the other wards. The healthcare providers and supervisors were encouraged to focus on specific factors related to patient safety in their own wards and to discuss possible strategies for improvement.</p>
</sec>
