<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have developed a model of satellite-based environmental data-fishing performance relationship to explore and map out the spatial distribution pattern and persistence of pelagic hotspots for skipjack tuna. The fishing performance data represented by CPUE and fishing frequency are low-cost fish distribution datasets commonly available to fishery scientists. CPUE data provide a good proxy as an index of fish abundance [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref036">36</a>], whereas fishing frequency data act as an index of fish occurrence or fish availability [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref037">37</a>]. The fishing data describe fisher’s experience-based knowledge and provide invaluable supplement data to a better habitat prediction [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref038">38</a>], while satellite data are mostly available at no cost to the user monitoring oceanographic features over a wide area [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref039">39</a>]. Therefore, the strong correlation between the fishery data with the satellite oceanographic information provides an important means to identify habitat hotspots for pelagic species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In principle, our model extracts the optimum combination of three environmental factors (SST, Chl-a and SSHA) from the areas of high fishing performance to produce pelagic habitat hotspots. Several studies supported that a combination of these factors plays a pivotal role in explaining and exposing a pelagic tuna habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref008">8</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref040">40</a>]. Our results found that Chl-a is an important variable for identifying tuna forage habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref009">9</a>]. SST was selected to be another important variable for detecting the habitat hotspot since skipjack tuna are sensitive to the changes of temperature on their distribution [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref015">15</a>], while SSHA is related to the changes in the depth of the thermocline and mesoscale variability [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref041">41</a>]. We combined these variables to improve detection of potential pelagic hotspots for skipjack tuna.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results show that skipjack tuna habitat is associated with the areas of warm SST, specific Chl-a concentrations and positive SSHA, favoring fishing operations (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g002" href="#pone.0185601.g002">2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g003" href="#pone.0185601.g003">3</a>). The surface temperature preference for skipjack is relatively warmer than reported from the other areas around the world [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref027">27</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref037">37</a>]. The highest catches consistently occur in May when SST gradually decrease to about 30.5°C after reaching a peak in November-December and back to the lowest SST in July and August [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref034">34</a>]. At the same time, the skipjack tuna fishery tends to occur within the areas of positive SSHA anomalies suggesting that food aggregates mainly at the surface when the thermocline depth moves in the opposite direction of sea surface height [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref041">41</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref042">42</a>]. We found that predominantly positive SSHA had an effect on both skipjack CPUE and number of fishing set (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g003" href="#pone.0185601.g003">Fig 3C</a>), reflecting preference for areas closely associated with the warm mixed layer above the thermocline. The positive SSHA values are preferred for the skipjack tuna habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref027">27</a>], indicating the important anticyclonic eddy fields [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref044">44</a>] where skipjack catches increase significantly [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref045">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is interesting to note that our finding shows Chl-a as a key oceanographic indicator of locating hotspots for skipjack tuna within the southwestern Coral Triangle tuna. Satellite derived Chl-a concentration is an index of phytoplankton biomass which provides valuable information about trophic interactions, forage habitat and dynamic movement of pelagic species [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref046">46</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref047">47</a>]. Skipjack feed on both the small epipelagic fish and zooplankton which all of them graze on phytoplankton [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref046">46</a>]. The Chl-a concentrations control the skipjack abundance (CPUE) in the food web system through the linkages between phytoplankton and, zooplankton and small pelagic fish. Therefore skipjack tuna enable to take advantage of a short food-web which is probably efficient from the energetic point of view [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref048">48</a>]. We show that favorable Chl-a for skipjack has more specific range than the previous study [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref022">22</a>] and clearly indicates frontal areas at the level of 0.2 mg m
  <span class="sup">-3</span> Chl-a isopleth (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g004" href="#pone.0185601.g004">Fig 4</a>). Skipjack tuna fishing sets assembled in waters along Chl-a front (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g002" href="#pone.0185601.g002">2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g004" href="#pone.0185601.g004">4</a>), implying that this oceanographic feature plays a role for detecting skipjack habitat hotspot along study area (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g005" href="#pone.0185601.g005">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g008" href="#pone.0185601.g008">8</a>). Preference for 0.2 mg m
  <span class="sup">-3</span> Chl-a has important biophysical, physiological and trophic implications. Skipjack tuna locate and forage along the frontal zones within the preferred temperatures and SSHAs [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref049">49</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present paper, we explore the performance of skipjack hotspots based on the three main points: (1) high PHI; (2) the area of potentially suitable habitat and (3) persistence of the most suitable habitat. For the period of 5 years, our findings show that the areas of the most potential skipjack habitat hotspot consistently peak in May corresponding to the highest PHI (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g005" href="#pone.0185601.g005">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g006" href="#pone.0185601.g006">6</a>). These areas may relate strongly with enhanced feeding opportunities for skipjack. Several investigations found that the distribution and abundance of tuna are strongly linked with the forage availability [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref050">50</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref051">51</a>]. Skipjack tuna move and exploit primarily high densities of food organisms, which could be tracked by the high PHI. The skipjack forage on species such as anchovy, cephalopods and crustacean [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref048">48</a>], which are more abundant in the areas of increased probability index. Anchovy (
  <span class="italic">Stolephorus spp</span>.) represent more than 80% of skipjack stomach content when caught in the western Coral Triangle tuna [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref052">52</a>]. We propose that the PHI provides a reasonable proxy detecting forage abundance, and thus skipjack tuna spatial distribution and abundance. The key skipjack habitats in the peak season (May) may have a good association with enhanced feeding opportunity for skipjack which is probably stimulated by the Chl-a front (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g004" href="#pone.0185601.g004">4</a>,
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g008" href="#pone.0185601.g008">8</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g010" href="#pone.0185601.g010">10</a>), upwelling zone [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref031">31</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref043">43</a>], ocean current and eddy fields [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref053">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the formations of habitat hotspot varied spatially (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g005" href="#pone.0185601.g005">Fig 5</a>), however, the spatial mean position of the pelagic hotspots did not substantially change (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g010" href="#pone.0185601.g010">Fig 10</a>). Habitat hotspots in the Gulf of Bone such as in 2007 appear more pronounced than in the Flores Sea reflecting that the enhanced forage habitat supporting high tuna concentration cover a wide area. In the subsequent years, the biologically rich habitats mainly perform along the Chl-a of 0.2 mg m
  <span class="sup">-3</span> (Chl-a front). Several explanations for the association of tunas with fronts include: (1) the availability of appropriate food; (2) confinement to a physiologically optimum temperature range; (3) use of frontal gradients for thermoregulation; (4) limitation of visual hunting efficiency owing to water clarity [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref049">49</a>]; and (5) forage habitat and migration route [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref054">54</a>]. The Chl-a front appears to coincide with the shelfbreak position (approximately 350 m isobath) of both Flores Sea and Bone Gulf (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g001" href="#pone.0185601.g001">1</a>,
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g005" href="#pone.0185601.g005">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g010" href="#pone.0185601.g010">10</a>). Highest skipjack CPUEs are concentrated near the shelfbreak location [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref017">17</a>] during the daytime [
  <a rid="pone.0185601.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0185601.ref055">55</a>]. Our empirical fishing data (2007–2011) confirm that fishermen consistently exploit the forage habitat during the daytime and, using the fishing data in 2012, we showed that our prediction models have been substantially verified (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g005" href="#pone.0185601.g005">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g008" href="#pone.0185601.g008">8</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g009" href="#pone.0185601.g009">9</a>). To improve the model performance, we suggest that the effect of upwelling and current systems should be added to the analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to note that at the peak season for 5-years (May 2007–2011), less than 2% of the study area exhibits a persistent concentration of habitat hotpots (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g010" href="#pone.0185601.g010">Fig 10</a>: left). We suggest that these areas play a pivotal role since skipjack CPUEs increase significantly with increasing the habitat persistence (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0185601.g010" href="#pone.0185601.g010">Fig 10</a>: right) and thereby provide potential targets for marine conservation and fishing management strategies. As a result, our findings could be as preliminary nature of results in providing new insight into detection of skipjack tuna distribution and abundance in either the Coral Triangle tuna region or the western tropical Pacific Ocean.
 </p>
</sec>
