<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
 <p class="p">This work is part of the ICE-ARC project funded by the European Union’s 7th Framework Programme, (grant 603887, contribution 006). D.Y. received additional funding from ERIM, Erasmus University Rotterdam, and Paul Ekins at the ISR, University College London. K.S. was funded by NSF (grant 1503559) and NASA (grants NNX14A154G, NNX17AC59A). E.J. was funded by the NGEE Arctic project supported by the BER Office of Science at the U.S. DOE. Y.E. was funded by the NSF (grant 1900795). E.B. was supported by the UK Met Office Hadley Centre Climate Programme funded by BEIS and DEFRA. Publication of this article was funded by Lancaster Environment Centre, the University of South Florida St. Petersburg’s Open Access Publication Fund, NSF (grant 1900795) and NASA (grants NNX14A154G, NNX17AC59A). We thank the five anonymous referees for providing wide-ranging critical comments that helped improve the paper considerably. We are also grateful to multiple colleagues from the ICE-ARC consortium and beyond for a number of useful discussions that contributed to shaping this study, including Jeremy Wilkinson, Peter Wadhams, Michael Karcher, Frank Kauker, Rüdiger Gerdes and Andy Jarvis. Special thanks go to Michael Winton for providing the original ALL/CLR script. We also acknowledge the World Climate Research Programme’s Working Group on Coupled Modelling, which is responsible for CMIP, and we thank the climate modelling groups (listed in Supplementary Tables 
  <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">18</xref> and 
  <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">19</xref>) for producing and making available their model output. For CMIP the U.S. DOE’s Program for Climate Model Diagnosis and Inter-comparison provides coordinating support and led development of software infrastructure in partnership with the Global Organization for Earth System Science Portals.
 </p>
</ack>
