<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is significantly altering the structure and function of ecosystems, compromising their ability to provide goods and services to human populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. Some projections indicate that water availability, thermal regimes and biogeochemical processes will be strongly affected in some geographic regions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Consequently, freshwater biodiversity, the structure and dynamic of the aquatic food webs, as well as the quality, abundance and distribution of habitats will be altered [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Freshwater fisheries could also be affected by changes in water temperature that will influence habitat quality, and by changes in water volume that will affect habitat quality and availability, habitat connectivity, and lifecycle events [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. This will happen while freshwater fishes are threatened by other anthropogenic impacts, including the degradation of the riparian habitat, imposition of migration barriers, the introduction of exotic species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>], and overfishing [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. Such impacts are global and are even apparent in the largest rivers of the world such as the Amazon [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Finally, environmental change and globalization are impacting social-ecological systems, as the collapse of fish stocks can lead to social reorganization [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interaction and connection between ecological and social subsystems is an important mediator of the influence of environmental change on natural resources. In fisheries context, the fishers’ ecological knowledge (EK) represents a substantial information base and is frequently used to evaluate fisheries resource levels [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], plan fisheries conservation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>], and to support basic research on local fish populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Such knowledge is increasingly being applied to the study of climate change through ethno-climatological approaches [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>], which can be utilized to determine the potential consequences of climate change on exploited populations across different spatial and temporal scales. Information from such studies can be used for participative management [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>] and to guide future research [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. Moreover, the integration of scientific and traditional knowledge facilitates and supports social negotiation during the development and implementation of resource management measures [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Artisanal fishing communities in the Amazon have historically been subjected to the impacts of climatic variabilities, such as El-Niño and La Niña and they have developed strategies to deal with extreme phenomena. However, new challenges in the form of current climate change may affect their economy and food security [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Climate change may, therefore, increase fishers’ dependence on having sound knowledge of climate and its effects to develop effective decision-making. In Brazil, studies on ethnoichthyology have mostly been applied in coastal areas with less attention given to the large fishing communities of the Amazon [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], characterized by high levels of subsistence consumption [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>] and commercial activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aims of this study were to: 1) assess how commercial riverine fishers recall extreme climatic events affecting the local aquatic environments (drought and flood); 2) identify how fishers respond to the consequences of extreme events on fish availability; 3) determine the sources of information about extreme events (drought and flood) used by fishers, considering their education and experience, and; 4) assess fishers’ knowledge of extreme event years. To do that, we adopted two approaches: 1) Cultural response analysis based on “cultural consensus theory”; 2) integrative fishers/hydrological analysis: comparing empirical measurements of water levels with fishers’ identification of years of extreme events.</p>
</sec>
