<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sources of knowledge of extreme climatic events were classified as familiar (grandparents, parents, brothers and cousins) and non-familiar (magazines and personal experience). Differences between sources of knowledge for each experience category (experienced/novice) were assessed. Fishers’ educational level was classified as literate (basic, primary/new fundamental education) or illiterate (“did not study”). Differences between educational level and Fisher categories (experienced/novice) were assessed.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two methodologies were used to evaluate the fishers’ knowledge of past extreme climate events: a consensus analysis and an integrative fishers/meteorological analysis. The consensus analysis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>] was performed and validated using anthropological theory [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. In this approach, the cultural consensus is defined as the “pattern or agreement or consensus among informants that permit to make inferences about their differential competence in knowledge of the shared information pool constituting the culture. It is assumed that the correspondence between the answers of any two informants is a function of the extent to which each is correlated with the truth” [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. To support this analysis we estimated and plotted the annual distribution frequency of quotes by drought events and by flood events.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The integrative fishers/meteorological analysis was based on hydrological records of water levels were retrieved from the Manaus harbour website [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. Extreme flood/drought events were classified as those causing a water level of above 28 m or lower than 17 m, respectively, according to the criteria of Bittencourt and Amadio [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. Fishers’ memories of extreme events were classified as being “in Accordance with the Hydrological Records” (AHR) or “Not in Accordance with the Hydrological Records” (NAHR).
 </p>
</sec>
