<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data was collected between June and October 2013 through interviews with commercial fishers that use the Panair fishery harbor in Manaus, Central Amazon (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). This is the main fishery landing and commercial center of central Amazonia, receiving 25 % of the fish 
  <span class="italic">in nature</span> commercialized in the Region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>].
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Map of Central Amazonia. Legend: 
     <span class="italic">Black Star</span> - Panair’ fishery harbor, located in Manaus
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13002_2016_123_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Semi-structured questionnaires (see 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="Sec12" href="#Sec12">Appendix</a>) were applied to 91 artisanal commercial fishers. A stratified random sample was applied by separating the population into strata based on fishermen’s experience (“novice fishers”- less than 15 years of experience; and “experienced fishers”- fishers with 15 plus years of experience) to assure the representativeness of the sample and the perception of the error [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. The interviews followed standard recommendations for ethnoecological research [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. They lasted for about 30 min and were given in Portuguese. Participant observation and historical timelines were applied to the questionnaires [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. Questions dealt with various social and cultural themes, e.g., time of fishery experience, education, sources of information and ecological knowledge related to fish, fishing and climate, including perceived impacts of extreme weather impacts on local fishery resources. All research was conformed to the ethical and legal obligations of the author’s institution and the Federal government (license number: 13813613.9.0000.0006).
 </p>
</sec>
