<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgements</div>
 <p>We are very grateful for the contribution of all fishers to this study, including the Panair fishers’ colony president, Miguel Oliveira Falcão. We are also thankful for the cultural experience that we have seen at Manaus, as all of that contributed to better understanding the dynamics of this fishery sector. We are also grateful to the reviewers for all their useful suggestions and contributions.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Funding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was funded by Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel (CAPES) (AICG grant), the Brazilian Innovation Agency (FINEP) and the Ministry of Fisheries and Aquaculture (MPA) (grant # 01.10.0770.00). VSB grant has been provided by the National Research Council of Brazil (CNPq) (grant # 303469/2013-7).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Availability of data and materials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All data analyzed during the current study are available on figshare website (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://figshare.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://figshare.com/</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Authors’ contributions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AICG conceived the study and its design, carried out the interviews, performed the statistical analysis and drafted and revised the manuscript. RJL suggested research narrative, and revised the manuscript. VSB participated in its design, the statistical analysis and helped to draft the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Authors’ information</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AICG studied fisheries sciences, and she is specialized in Ecology and conservation. Her master thesis was about sport fishing catches. She has worked in a freshwater biology management study in a city council, and in a fishery study in the Basque country (AZTI). Since 2013, that she is a doctorate student in BADPI (freshwater biology and continental fisheries graduate program) at INPA (National Institute of Amazonian Research). She is working with climate influence on commercial fisheries.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RJL is Titular Professor of Conservation Biogeography at the Federal University of Alagoas in northeast Brazil. His interests span conservation science, biogeography, evolutionary theory, and ecology, public understanding of science, sustainable development and sustainable tourism.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">VSB graduated in Oceanography, Master’s degree in Biological Oceanography and a PhD in Freshwater Biology and Inland Fisheries. In 2013, he was a visiting professor at Bournemouth University, UK. He worked during 16 years at the Federal University of Amazonas and currently is Titular Professor at the Federal University of Alagoas. He has experience in Fisheries Resources and Ecology, with an emphasis on Applied Ecology.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Competing interests</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consent for publication</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each of the participants has signed a permission reporting that its information can be used in any publication.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics approval and consent to participate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was cleared by the Research Ethics Committee (CEP/CONEP) (CAE number: 13813613.9.0000.0006), and all signed an Informed Consent Form.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
