<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Extreme population responses were observed in all years, and in at least 1 year for the majority of species: moths, butterflies and birds. Furthermore, in the majority of years, one or more species showed extreme positive population growth (explosions) while others simultaneously showed rapid declines (crashes). These findings show that extreme population changes are individualistic among species; an extreme year for one species is not necessarily an extreme year for another. Individualism can be expressed not only in the particular climate variables (or other drivers) that a species responds to, but also in the time delays between an event and the population response. The observed effects can be direct (e.g. population growth within a warm year), delayed by a year (e.g. drought-induced mortality of Lepidoptera that is not recorded until adults fail to emerge the next year), or delayed by 2 or more years via community interactions (e.g. through altered natural enemy or food abundances) [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Delayed density dependence (population crash following a good year, or vice versa) may add further lags to the system. Across all 238 species, a combination of delayed community and density-dependent effects could mean that extreme population responses are more evenly spread across years than the ECEs that may trigger these changes. The longer generation times, larger body size, higher trophic level (on average) and homeothermic biology of birds, compared with Lepidoptera, may tend to spread their observed responses more evenly across the years, as we observed. The (weak) negative correlation between the responses of birds and Lepidoptera (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160144F2" class="xref">figure 2</xref>
 <italic class="italic">d</italic>) may stem from different lag times, differences in which aspects of environmental variation they respond to, and different overall sensitivities to the climate.
</p>
