<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Indian summer monsoon rainfall during June to September contributes more than 80% of the total annual rainfall over India, and its interannual variation of around 10% can have substantial impacts on agriculture and the economy in general (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">10</italic>
 </xref>). Skillful prediction of this variation months in advance would allow improved agricultural planning, drought mitigation, and flood warning (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">11</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>). Numerous observational (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>) and modeling studies (
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">19</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>) have shown that positive Eurasian snow cover anomalies during winter and spring tend to be followed by an anomalous deficit of rainfall over the Indian subcontinent in the subsequent summer monsoon season, while negative snow cover anomalies tend to be followed by abundant rainfall. However, there are studies noting that this negative snow-monsoon teleconnection only holds true when the snow cover in particular regions, such as western Eurasia, is considered (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">26</italic>
 </xref>) or when the effect of the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO) is excluded (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">27</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">28</italic>
 </xref>). After years of extensive research, exactly which part of the Eurasian region is primarily responsible for the inverse correlation between snow cover and the following Indian summer monsoon rainfall and how robust the relationship is in a changing climate remain unclear. This uncertainty is probably partly due to the use of different period lengths and different snow proxies in different studies (
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">17</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
