<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045" class="p">Categories were decided based on the following rationale. We recorded the professional specialty of each lead author, hypothesizing that the climate change policy purview of different health professionals would be influenced by their training and practice. For instance, we anticipated public health professionals would frame climate change in adaptive terms. We predicted that author location would prove influential, noting the extensive geographic variety in climate change beliefs and attitudes across the US (
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Howe et al., 2015</xref>). We categorized each article by broad motive for engagement with climate change, hypothesizing that health threats and economics would most likely incite action. We extracted any disease or health threat and placed it into eight health trend categories. This assessed what medical professionals expect to respond to in their practice as result of climate change, and whether this correlates with expected epidemiology. For example, we predicted that extreme weather events would be mentioned frequently, given their dramatic and visible character. Each article was examined for evidence of adaptation and/or mitigation approaches to the problem. We expected mitigation responses to be dominant, in light of widespread conceptualization that climate change is abstract and discountable in the immediate (
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Trope and Liberman, 2003</xref>). We recorded the sectors that an article proposed to intervene upon, anticipating a high frequency of suggested changes to energy sourcing and transportation. Following this, we ascertained 
 <italic class="italic">how</italic> an article proposed to intervene, expecting the medical community to favor educational and technological strategies, as these are already great strengths of US medicine. Given the mosaic of institutions and entities that piece together US health care, we recorded any suggested collaborations and partnerships. These were broken up into the following categories - for-profit private entities, non-profit private entities, and public entities, predicting that public sector partnerships would be favored in accordance with US governments recently dominant voice on the issue. Finally, we evaluated the overall disposition of an article, observing how inactive, reactive or proactive their suggestions were, in order to get a high-level view of how much US health care is responsible for climate change.
</p>
