<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change researchers and communication practitioners are becoming increasingly interested in applying social marketing principles, including audience segmentation, to better understand their audiences. Much of this climate change segmentation research has focused on identifying groups that share similar beliefs, attitudes, and behaviours related to climate change within large national samples. The “Climate Change in the American Mind” collaboration between researchers at the Yale Program on Climate Change Communication and the George Mason Center for Climate Change Communication, is the most influential and well-established of such programs. Data for its initial segmentation study were collected from a large nationally representative sample of US residents in 2008 [
 <xref rid="pone.0197988.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Segmentation based on 36 variables assessing climate change beliefs, issue involvement, policy preference and behaviours revealed six distinctive segments: 
 <italic class="italic">Alarmed</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Concerned</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cautious</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Disengaged</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Doubtful</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Dismissive</italic>. Collectively labeled the 
 <italic class="italic">Six Americas</italic>, the segments reflect quantitative shifts from generally high to generally low levels of concern, and degree of certainty that global warming is occurring, with engagement having a curvilinear relationship such that it is highest among those who are in segments at either end of this continuum–that is 
 <italic class="italic">Alarmed</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Concerned</italic>, or 
 <italic class="italic">Doubtful</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Dismissive</italic>–but lowest among the 
 <italic class="italic">Cautious</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Disengaged</italic> (see also [
 <xref rid="pone.0197988.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]).
</p>
