<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several studies have incorporated a broader range of psychological variables, some of which are not explicitly related to climate change, in their segmentation analyses. For example, in another Australian study, Hine et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0197988.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] used a broad set of profiling variables including environmental values, trust, emotional responses and spatial and temporal discounting, in addition to the more standard climate change belief variables used in other studies. They identified five segments (
 <italic class="italic">Dismissive</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Doubtful</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Uncertain</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Concerned and Alarmed</italic>) and found significant differences across segments on a range of validation dimensions, including climate change mitigation behaviours and energy policy preferences. In their study, the 
 <italic class="italic">Uncertain</italic> segment shared characteristics of the 
 <italic class="italic">Disengaged</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Cautious</italic> segments identified in other studies in the US and Australia, but it is difficult to make meaningful comparisons across the studies because this study used a different set of measure to define segments. In the UK, the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (DEFRA) segmented 3600 English residents based on their attitudes, beliefs and behaviours about environmental issues, including (but not restricted to) climate change. Seven segments were identified (
 <italic class="italic">Positive Greens</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Waste Watchers</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Concerned Consumers</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Sideline Supporters</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cautious Participants</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Stalled Starters</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Honestly Disengaged)</italic>, which varied in terms of unique motivations and barriers, and also in the degree to which they engaged in climate change mitigation behaviours [
 <xref rid="pone.0197988.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
