<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To measure population density change, we use the SEDAC CIESIN Gridded Population of the World (GPW) [
 <xref rid="pone.0170615.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] dataset. We used a combination of the Gridded Population of the World, Version 3 (GPWv3) population density grid for the years 1990, 1995 and 2000 and the GPWv3 population density grid future estimates for the years 2005, 2010 and 2015 available from the Columbia University Center for International Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN) in collaboration with Centro Internacional de Agricultura Tropical (CIAT) [
 <xref rid="pone.0170615.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. GPW gridded population data consists of estimates of human population for different years (1990, 1995, and 2000) at 2.5 arc-minute grid cells and uses a proportional allocation gridding algorithm based on more than 300,000 national and sub-national administrative units to assign population values to grid cells. We used the population density grids that are derived by dividing the population count grids by the land area grid and represent persons per square kilometer. The Future Estimates population data consists of estimates of human population for the years 2005, 2010, and 2015 by 2.5 arc-minute grid cells with population values that are extrapolated based on a combination of sub-national growth rates from census dates and national growth rates from United Nations statistics. All of the grids have been adjusted to match United Nations national level population estimates. We calculated zonal statistics for ecoregions and hotspots to estimate percent change in population density as the difference between 1990 and 2015 population density divided by 1990 population density. We estimated population density change as the difference between 1990 and 2015 population density divided by the area of the zone of interest. Both percent change and density change provide relevant information on potential pressures on natural resources.
</p>
