<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30" class="p">We used four conceptually and statistically different ENMs based on presence data (i.e., only occurrences of snakes species are known, absences are unknown). The models included in the analyses were Bioclim – BIOC
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" class="xref">107</xref>
 </sup> based on bioclimatic envelope logic, Gower Distance – GOWD
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">108</xref>
 </sup> based on environmental distance approach, Maximum Entropy – MAXE
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" class="xref">109</xref>
 </sup> based on machine learning technique and Ecological Niche Factor Analysis – ENFA
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" class="xref">110</xref>
 </sup> based on multivariate analysis. Given the particularities of each model, different predictions are provided, generating estimates of uncertainty about which model is more appropriate to represent the geographical distribution of species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" class="xref">111</xref>
 </sup>. To overcome this uncertainty and minimize errors, we employed the ensemble forecasting approach, which provides a consensus of multiple models
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">89</xref>
 </sup>. The main idea of ensemble forecasting is that different sources of errors will affect each niche model in different ways and, by obtaining a consensus result of these models, errors will tend to cancel each other out and produce a trustworthy and more conservative solution
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">86</xref>
 </sup>. Assuming that the consensus model (CONS) reduces uncertainty and error associated with alternative ENMs, only the range sizes from the CONS model were interpreted. To obtain the CONS model we first adjust for each species the individual models as follows.
</p>
