<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Future soil degradation and its impacts on crop production are unknown and uncertain by nature since it will depend on intensity of hazardous processes, exposure, vulnerability, and cropland management. In this study we quantify vulnerability (Oppenheimer et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) as a “predisposition” of calorie yields to be adversely affected by soil degradation. From a variety of degradation processes (e.g., Louwagie et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) we address the decline in fertility due to nutrient and soil organic matter depletion and soil erosion. Other degradation processes, such as soil structure decline, salinization, or acidification, are not represented here (see also Text S3 in 
 <xref rid="eft2292-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supporting Information S1</xref>). As expected, fertilization is the dominant factor controlling yield vulnerability in this study since it determines the capacity to offset the degradation‐induced nutrient losses. Fertilization intensity, which is a fraction of BAU fertilization over fertilization needed for crop yields without nutrient stress (scenario P1), explains more than 50% of variability in the Vs values (Figure S3a in 
 <xref rid="eft2292-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supporting Information S1</xref>). On the contrary, irrigation intensity has only a small effect on yield vulnerability (Figure S3b in 
 <xref rid="eft2292-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supporting Information S1</xref>), suggesting that the soil's ability to supply water is affected less at our scale of analysis. Changes in hydro‐physical soil properties (wilting point and field water capacity) as simulated by pan‐EU EPIC are of inferior importance compared to the changes in soil organic matter pool (Figure S11 in 
 <xref rid="eft2292-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supporting Information S1</xref>). More detailed description and discussion with this respect is provided in Text S3 in 
 <xref rid="eft2292-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supporting Information S1</xref>. It should be noted that our concept does not account for processes of organic carbon and nutrient redistribution, which contribute additional uncertainty on soil vulnerability (e.g., Paustian et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
