<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Intensive fertilization may indeed overcome limitations due to soil degradation by soil organic matter loss so that crop yields are not affected (Holland, 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>), but it may also lead to environmental pollution (Sutton, 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and adverse trends in soil health hampering future production (Squire et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Therefore, soil conservation has been recognized as a prominent adaptation strategy when coping with soil degradation (Bindraban et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Montanarella, 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Given the diversity of practices in conservation agriculture and a lack of consolidated data in Europe (e.g., Merante et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), conservation practices are not explicitly included in our vulnerability assessment in Section 3.3. We examine possible implications of avoiding conservation practices for our analysis in Section 3.4 by analyzing the calorie yields simulated under assumptions of (1) low intensity of soil disturbance, (2) high crop residue return, (3) mulching, (4) manure fertilization, and (5) high erosion control (see Table 
 <xref rid="eft2292-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">3</xref>), that is, measures known to enhance soil quality (Lal, 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). First, the effects of conservation practices generated by pan‐EU EPIC are in general accordance with expectations: our historical yields under conservation practices are on average 85%–95% of conventional yields (de Ponti et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Soane et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), and the relative loss is higher in cooler regions (Lithuania), while almost equal though less variable calorie yields are estimated in Portugal. Indeed, conservation practices are particularly appropriate in semi‐arid regions where they allow for better water management and erosion control (Pittelkow et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Soane et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Second, avoiding conservation practices does not undermine the robustness of our vulnerability analysis (see Section 3.3).
</p>
