<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">Geography—Large scale, geographic data on tidal restrictions are rare, but a large number of examples and case studies of restriction and restoration occur within the literature. As an indication of scale, approximately 50% of pre-development tidal saltmarsh area in the U.S. has been destroyed by human activities, with impoundment and drainage as prominent causes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, and a quarter of remaining coastal wetlands in the state of Massachusetts, for example, is landward of nearly 600 transportation-related tidal restrictions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. To estimate the scale of tidally restricted wetlands area and the proportion of existing wetlands that are restricted, we compiled published information on the occurrence along the U.S. Atlantic coast of managed wetland impoundments and incidental, full or partial impoundments caused by transportation infrastructure (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). In the northeast U.S., wetland and impoundment areas landward of primarily transportation-related restrictions comprise 29% of total tidal wetland. In the southeast U.S. 10% of total tidal wetland area is diked and impounded for waterfowl and mosquito management. The tidal wetlands in the regions and states represented in the analysis comprise 55% of the total tidal wetland on the U.S. Atlantic coast, and thus are expected to be approximations of the entire coast and may be similar to many developed coastal regions elsewhere. Based on the assumption that similar levels of transportation-related and diked restrictions occur throughout the U.S. east coast, we estimate that 39% of total tidal wetland area on the U.S. Atlantic coast, ~3,800 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, is above tidal restrictions or blockages. Montague 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, reported that 87% of the southeast U.S. mosquito and waterfowl impoundments included in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref> had salinity less than 16 psu. Thus, they are expected to be significant methane sources. It is not known what proportions of restricted wetlands related to transportation infrastructure are in freshened, drained, or relatively unaltered condition. In Massachusetts 70% of tidally restricted wetland area is described as freshwater marsh or fresh shrub, with 52% of the vegetated area colonized by invasive 
 <italic class="italic">Phragmites australis</italic>, while the remainder remains brackish to saline marsh
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. In general, where purposeful actions have not been taken to drain tidally-restricted wetlands, such as is the case with incidental restrictions caused by transportation infrastructure, flooding and freshening are the most likely result. Thus, we can approximate that 70% of restricted wetland area compiled here, or 2,650 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, is in a flooded/freshened condition. To calculate minimum and maximum estimates of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission from those wetlands, we multiplied the area by the minimum and maximum annual emissions rates of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> from impounded wetlands (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>, Scenario 1, EF1 and EF3 pre-restoration minus post-restoration). For context, the annual emission rates from 2,650 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of freshened wetlands were compared to average annual tailpipe emissions from a U.S. automobile
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>, at 4,690 kg CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> y
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, with the comparison calculated as cumulative RF over a 20-y period of continuous emissions at those rates. The resulting anthropogenic wetland emission estimate was 28,000 to 145,000 tonnes CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> y
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, with RF equivalent to 20 years of continuous emissions from 0.6 to 3.1 million automobiles (not shown).
</p>
