<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The field of invasion science has recognized many of these challenges and research directions are clearly changing to meet them (McGeoch et al. 
 <xref rid="b190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Ricciardi et al. 
 <xref rid="b235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Simberloff et al. 
 <xref rid="b267" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Much of this new work remains ecological in nature (at the organismal, population, species or ecosystem levels), including work that aims to guide management interventions to address the impacts of biological invasions (Richardson and Pyšek 
 <xref rid="b239" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Blackburn et al. 
 <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Nonetheless, from early on in the development of the field, several other approaches have been considered. Among these, the utility of genetics and the significance of evolutionary processes have long been recognized (e.g. Baker 
 <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1974</xref>). However, it is only recently that they have seen a resurgence of interest (Huey et al. 
 <xref rid="b143" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Callaway and Maron 
 <xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Dormontt et al. 
 <xref rid="b89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Lawson Handley et al. 
 <xref rid="b166" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Indeed, the significance of genetic approaches and an evolutionary perspective are now recognized as important not only for understanding the ability of species to progress along the stages of invasion (e.g. Pandit et al. 
 <xref rid="b212" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Richardson and Pyšek 
 <xref rid="b239" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>), but also for improving management interventions that might reduce the rates and impacts of invasions (Lawson Handley et al. 
 <xref rid="b166" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Prentis and Pavasovic 
 <xref rid="b224" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Examples include better genotypic matching of biocontrol agents and their hosts, and understanding the coevolutionary dynamics of invasive species and those with which they interact (Phillips and Shine 
 <xref rid="b217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; McDonald et al. 
 <xref rid="b189" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Gaskin et al. 
 <xref rid="b117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Nonetheless, additional scope exists for modern genetic approaches, and notably genomics, to contribute to the understanding and forecasting that is required to limit the rates and impacts of biological invasions, especially given the expectation of interactions with other global change drivers.
</p>
