<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0070" class="p">In the present study, a crop ideotype was defined as a subset of Sirius cultivar parameters that would deliver high yield performance in a target environment when optimized (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). A cultivar, which is based on an ideotype and utilizes its optimal combination of trait values, would deliver optimal yields for the environment in question. 
 <italic class="italic">Claire</italic> is a popular winter wheat variety in Europe, including the UK, and in NZ for its soft milling, early sowing, lodging and disease-resistant characteristics, and consistent high yield performance (
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Limagrain, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Powell et al., 2013</xref>). For the same reasons, 
 <italic class="italic">Claire</italic> has been used extensively as a parent in many wheat breeding programmes (Powell et al., 2013). In the present study, the local winter wheat 
 <italic class="italic">cv</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">Claire</italic> was used as a parent for designing wheat ideotypes. The Sirius model was calibrated for 
 <italic class="italic">Claire</italic> as being heat- and drought-sensitive during reproductive development. A list of the 22 Sirius cultivar parameters as calibrated for 
 <italic class="italic">Claire</italic> is presented in 
 <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>. In our study, only eight cultivar parameters were selected from the above list for optimization (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). As winter wheat is mostly grown under rainfed condition in the UK and NZ, we designed a wheat ideotype for the water-limited condition (rainfed) under 2050-climate (
 <italic class="italic">IW
  <sub class="sub">2050</sub>
 </italic>). Additionally, as irrigation is also available in NZ at present and will probably be available in the future, we designed a wheat ideotype for the potential condition (irrigated or no-water limitation) under 2050-climate (
 <italic class="italic">IP
  <sub class="sub">2050</sub>
 </italic>). Both the ideotypes, 
 <italic class="italic">viz</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">IW
  <sub class="sub">2050</sub>
 </italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">IP
  <sub class="sub">2050</sub>
 </italic>, were optimized to raise the genetic yield potential under 2050-climate in the UK and NZ.
</p>
