<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiment 1: novel object experiment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental arena was made of plastic-coated wood and measured 76.5 × 73 × 19 cm. Black meshing was placed over the top to ensure that the animals could not escape. The box was marked so that it was visually split into four quadrants (38.25 × 36.5 cm) one of which contained the novel item. Four objects, all novel to the lizards and all of which were a similar size (average ± SD; 13.62 ± 2.43 cm), were used in this experiment. The objects were a plastic toy police van, a china garden fairy, a pottery wellington boot, and a small plastic blue lamp. All four objects varied in color and were chosen so as not to be ecologically relevant (Greggor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2015</a>). All objects were sprayed with disinfectant to reduce potential olfactory cues, and the arena was cleaned between trials. The objects were always placed in the same quadrant in the arena, 54 cm from the starting position of the lizards (which remained the same throughout the experiment). The room was maintained at 28.5 ± 1 °C throughout testing. A digital camera (Sony HDR-CX22OE) was placed on a tripod above the arena so that the whole area was recorded during the experiment. The experimenter left the room for the duration of the trial.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habituation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All animals were habituated to the testing arena prior to testing. During habituation, a lizard was placed into the arena for 15 min. After each 15-min period, a mealworm was placed on the opposite side of the enclosure. If the lizard ate the mealworm within 5 min on 3 consecutive days, then it was considered habituated. If the lizard failed to eat the mealworm within 5 min, the habituation procedure was repeated until the lizard met the criterion.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Testing</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the start of each trial, a lizard was placed on a marker on the diagonally opposite side of the arena to the object, facing toward it. In each Phase, lizards received two novel object trials (order of presentation counterbalanced across objects). Trials were separated by 4 or 5 days. Phase 1 trials were conducted when the animals were 10 months old, and the Phase 2 trials were a repeat of the experiment but using different novel objects 5 months after Phase 1.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
