<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Anthropogenic release of fossil fuels has caused an increase in the concentration of carbon dioxide (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) in the atmosphere from pre-Industrial Revolution levels of approximately 280 ppm [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Since 1990, the Intergovermental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) has been using models of climate processes to predict future changes in climate on a global scale [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Global Climate Models (GCMs) incorporate appropriate fluid dynamics of the ocean and atmosphere with other climate system processes including the carbon cycle, dynamic vegetation, atmospheric chemistry and land ice. Atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is expected to continue increasing through the end of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century due to the continued burning of fossil fuels [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Due to the greenhouse effect, this increase in CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> has and will continue to cause an increase in atmospheric and, consequently, ocean temperatures, which are projected to warm by 2.6–4.8°C by the year 2100 [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] under the Representative Concentration Pathway 8.5 (RCP8.5) greenhouse gas scenario. Considering the ecological and economic value of nearshore and coastal ecosystems [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], determining the effects of predicted increases in global temperatures on marine species life histories in these systems is important to the understanding of the future of these critically important systems. Such questions regarding the effects of climate change require forecasts at regional, rather than global scales. Downscaling GCM projections to higher spatial resolution in specific regions addresses this issue by helping us understand how global change may play out in specific environments [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
