<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When transferred to the greenhouse on 2 May 2012 for acclimatization, the plantlets were potted up with 70% commercial peat (Kekkilä Oy, Lapinneva, Finland) and 30% vermiculite (AO Vermipu Oy, Lapinjärvi, Finland). The relative air humidity was set at 70%. High‐pressure sodium lamps (GE Lighting, Cleveland, OH, USA) of 400 W were used for enriching the light conditions. The temperature was set to 20 ± 3
 <sup class="sup">°</sup>C, and the photoperiod was 18 hr. Due to the additional heat production from the lamps, the temperatures fluctuated between 20 and 23
 <sup class="sup">°</sup>C, depending on the time of day. The plantlets were transferred to the field site in Joensuu, Finland (62
 <sup class="sup">°</sup>60′N, 29
 <sup class="sup">°</sup>75′E), on 7 June 2012 and planted in soil on 11 June. We followed the same individuals for bud phenology as in Strømme et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Some mortality occurred during the study period occurred due to 
 <italic class="italic">Venturia</italic> shoot blight, and also as a result of some mechanical and herbivore damages. All the plants in the experimental field were scored for bud break and bud set. As a consequence of 
 <italic class="italic">Venturia</italic> infections on the apical meristems, numerous buds remained dead or fell off during scoring, and only the plants that successfully in completed their growth stages were taken into consideration for the data and statistical analyses. The reduction in the number of individuals in 2014 was due to severe 
 <italic class="italic">Venturia</italic> infection, while there was an increase in the number in 2015 owing to new growth during the subsequent spring season. The number of plants recorded for bud set in 2013 was 289 females and 319 males and in 2014, 203 females and 197 males. The number of plants recorded for bud break in 2014 was 261 females and 291 males and in 2015, 413 females and 405 males.
</p>
