<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Glacial response of the Indian monsoon</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To further explore the mechanisms by which the Northern Hemisphere (NH) ice sheets influence IPWP climate, we performed a hierarchy of simulations with varying degrees of ocean-atmosphere coupling. The hierarchy consists of uncoupled (atmosphere only), thermally coupled (atmosphere coupled through heat fluxes to a mixed layer ocean), and fully coupled simulations. All uncoupled simulations were run with SSTs from the preindustrial control (see section S7.1 for further details). All three types of simulations show a large-scale weakening of the Afro-Asian summer monsoon system with drying stretching from the Sahel to northwest India (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, top, and also fig. S9). The fact that widespread continental drying occurs in the uncoupled case (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5A</a> and also fig. S9C) indicates that SST changes do not play a role in linking ice sheet cooling with the large-scale monsoon weakening. We characterize this large-scale response as a monsoonal retreat, with the exception of south India, which shows increased rainfall in the uncoupled case (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5A</a>). Inclusion of air-sea coupling causes drying over south India (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, B and C), suggesting that SST changes play a role on this regional aspect of the response. The large-scale pattern of drying from Africa to central Asia can be attributed to enhanced “ventilation” of mid-latitude air as follows. Cold and dry air generated over the Laurentide ice sheet (LIS) is advected by the westerly winds around the NH, particularly over northern Africa and central Asia. This air is mixed equatorward, making the environment less conducive to deep convection. This limits the summertime advance of the monsoon rain belts seen as reductions in summertime rainfall (see section S7.1 for further details).
 </p>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Boreal summer climate response to ice sheet albedo as a function of ocean-atmosphere coupling.</div>
   <p>Rainfall (
    <span class="bold">A</span> to 
    <span class="bold">C</span>) and surface temperature (
    <span class="bold">D</span> to 
    <span class="bold">F</span>) change during July-August-September (JAS) simulated by CESM1 in response to ice sheet albedo. Surface wind stress changes (vectors) (D to F) are June-July-August (JJA) to highlight their role initiating the cooling of the Arabian Sea. Climate responses under varying degrees of ocean-atmosphere coupling are shown. Left to right: CESM1 with fixed SSTs, with a mixed-layer ocean model, and with a fully interactive ocean model.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aat9658-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The retreat of the monsoon rainbelts leads to reductions in cloud cover and relative humidity, causing massive changes in the energy balance of the land surface (fig. S10). Increased radiation and decreased evaporative cooling cause pronounced warming over a swath of land stretching from the Sahel to northwest India (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, bottom, and fig. S9, top). This warming results in a large land-sea temperature contrast between the Arabian Peninsula and the Arabian Sea that drives anomalous southwesterly winds along the shore (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, bottom, vectors). These wind changes are present in the uncoupled case (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5D</a>), showing that they are directly driven by the large-scale monsoonal retreat. Thermal air-sea coupling plays a key role in enhancing the land-sea temperature contrast, as the increased wind speed cools the ocean surface over the Arabian Sea (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5E</a>). Interactive ocean dynamics do not change the pattern and amplitude of this response (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5F</a>), demonstrating that evaporative cooling is the essential mechanism cooling the Arabian Sea. Furthermore, this response explains the drying over the core Indian monsoon region (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, B and C), especially in southern India, confirming that cooling of the Arabian Sea is the key feedback contributing to the glacial drying over India. Note that this thermodynamic effect overwhelms the effect of stronger winds, which would otherwise increase rainfall, as seen in the uncoupled response (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5A</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
