<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">QTL analysis in cowpea led to the identification of five genomic regions accounting for 11.5–18.1% of phenotypic variation for heat tolerance (Lucas et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) as well as three loci associated with heat‐induced browning of seed coats (Pottorff et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). QTL mapping accompanied by synteny analysis revealed candidate genes for resistance to 
 <italic class="italic">Macrophomina phaseolina</italic>, a fungal pathogen of cowpea (Muchero, Ehlers, Close, &amp; Roberts, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). A recent study in pigeonpea used three different mapping populations and genotyping by sequencing to construct dense genetic maps that revealed 14 significant QTLs for resistance to fusarium wilt (Saxena, Singh, et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0124" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Similarly, QTLs have been identified for sterility mosaic disease in pigeonpea (Saxena, Kale, et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). In addition, a QTL‐Seq approach has been used to map Fusarium wilt and sterility mosaic disease in pigeonpea (Singh, Khan, Saxena, et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). In wild lentil (
 <italic class="italic">Lens ervoides</italic>), a recent study by Bhadauria, Ramsay, Bett, and Banniza (
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) identified a total of 14 QTLs for resistance to 
 <italic class="italic">Colletotrichum lentis</italic> (race 0 and 1) and 
 <italic class="italic">Stemphylium botryosum</italic>. Several studies in common bean identified QTLs for resistance to different fungal (e.g., white mold, angular leaf spot, anthracnose, rust), bacterial (e.g., common bacterial blight, halo blight), and viral (e.g., bean common mosaic virus, bean common mosaic necrosis virus, beet curly top virus) pathogens (see Bitocchi, Rau, Rodriguez, &amp; Murgia, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>, as a review).
</p>
