<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="grl58008-sec-0010" class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>The authors are grateful to Johannes Mohrmann and Robert Wood (University of Washington) for thoughtful insights on our preliminary results and to Nick Burkhart (UCLA), Robert Fofrich (UCI), Helen He (NERSC), Evan Lyons (Stanford University), David Rigby (UCLA), Peter Schuetz (Det Norske Veritas), Jan Solski (University of Tromsø), and Jin‐Ho Yoon (Gwangju Institute of Science and Technology) for answering questions related to experiment design, model setup, and data processing. This work was supported by NASA ACCESS (NNX14AH55A), NASA AIST (80NSSC17K0540), NASA IDS (80NSSC17K0416), and the U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) Office of Science, Biological and Environmental Research as part of the Earth System Modeling program (DE‐SC0012998) and the Regional and Global Climate Modeling program. The Pacific Northwest National Laboratory is operated for DOE by Battelle Memorial Institute under contract DE‐AC05‐76RLO1830. This research used resources of the National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center, a DOE Office of Science User Facility supported by the Office of Science of the DOE under Contract No. DE‐AC02‐05CH11231. GCM sea ice concentration and thickness data can be accessed from the CMIP5 archive at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://esgf-node.llnl.gov/projects/cmip5/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://esgf-node.llnl.gov/projects/cmip5/</span>. UN Comtrade data are available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://comtrade.un.org/data/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://comtrade.un.org/data/</span>. CESM Large Ensemble Project (LENS) simulations are available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/projects/community-projects/LENS/data-sets.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cesm.ucar.edu/projects/community-projects/LENS/data-sets.html</span>. Data for results presented in this paper are available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1StLozrLMUmbdwwsQfsvAI4xBWP0sCEsV" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1StLozrLMUmbdwwsQfsvAI4xBWP0sCEsV</span>.
 </p>
</div>
