<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58008-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Younger, thinner, and less‐extensive sea ice (Lindsay &amp; Schweiger, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0032">2015</a>; Stroeve et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0059">2012</a>) is altering the Arctic climate system (Cohen et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0010">2012</a>; Dall'Osto et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0015">2017</a>; Semenov et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0051">2015</a>; Stroeve et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0060">2014</a>; Tang et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0062">2013</a>) and enabling human access to more of the Arctic Ocean than ever before (Stephenson, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0053">2017</a>; Stephenson &amp; Pincus, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0055">2018</a>). In particular, the prospect of trans‐Arctic shipping is supported by shipping simulations that show robust increases in trans‐Arctic access by midcentury under multimodel climate projections (Aksenov et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0002">2017</a>; Khon et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0028">2017</a>; Melia et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0036">2016</a>; Stephenson &amp; Smith, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0056">2015</a>). Of particular geopolitical interest is the so‐called 
  <span class="italic">trans‐polar route</span> over the North Pole, the shortest theoretical crossing between the North Atlantic and the Bering Strait that circumvents central Arctic state territorial waters and Exclusive Economic Zones (Clarke‐Sather et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0009">2017</a>). Although the economic viability of transit shipping along such Arctic routes is still debated (Brigham, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0003">2010</a>; Lasserre, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0031">2015</a>; Meng et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0037">2016</a>), ship traffic appears likely to increase in the coming decades due to increasing resource extraction, resupply of growing communities, and tourism (Farré et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0018">2014</a>; Yumashev et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0070">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because warming favors increased shipping traffic, previous studies have focused on the potential for ship emissions of black carbon (BC) and other particulates to enhance warming by lowering the otherwise high albedo of ice and snow (Browse et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0005">2013</a>; Corbett et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0013">2010</a>; Ødemark et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0040">2012</a>; Sand et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0047">2016</a>). The source of emissions is an important factor in determining the magnitude of this feedback and their ultimate climatic impact. Unlike BC transported to the Arctic from these midlatitude sources in Russia and Asia (Winiger et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0067">2017</a>; Wobus et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0068">2016</a>), strong surface inversions in the Arctic boundary layer make it more likely that BC emitted in the Arctic will be deposited on ice and snow, thereby maximizing its impact on surface temperature. However, previous studies demonstrated significant warming signals from reduced albedo only after scaling BC emissions more than 100 times above the current average ambient BC levels in the Arctic (Sand et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0046">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other mechanisms of radiative forcing are also important to Arctic temperatures. The insulating effect of longwave absorption by clouds may amplify Arctic warming (Cox et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0014">2015</a>), and Arctic clouds are particularly sensitive to increases in cloud condensation nuclei (CCN) from pollution due to the stability of Arctic air masses (Coopman et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0012">2018</a>). In opposition, emissions of sulfur oxides (SO
  <sub>2</sub>) and resulting sulfate (SO
  <sub>4</sub>) generate a direct negative radiative forcing by scattering incoming sunlight (Charlson et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0007">1992</a>), which may offset a significant part of the BC heating effect in the Arctic (Yang et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0069">2018</a>). Lastly, an increase in atmospheric particulates that serve as CCN will tend to increase cloud albedo by encouraging formation of smaller and more numerous cloud droplets (Twomey, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0064">1977</a>), particularly in liquid clouds (Christensen et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0008">2014</a>; Morrison et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0038">2012</a>). Although the influence of particulate emissions in the Arctic has historically been small and localized relative to more populous lower latitudes (Gong et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0021">2018</a>; Peters et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0042">2011</a>), increases in shipping emissions could substantially raise CCN, enhance cloud formation, and induce a climatic response (Mueller, 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0039">2018</a>; Wang et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0066">2013</a>; Yang et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0069">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have investigated the interacting effects of short‐lived pollutants from Arctic shipping scenarios with mixed and contrasting results. Using chemical transport and radiative forcing models, Dalsøren et al. (
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0016">2013</a>) found warming under two spatially explicit emission scenarios (Peters et al., 
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0042">2011</a>) between 2004 and 2030, while Fuglestvedt et al. (
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0019">2014</a>) used a simple 2‐box climate model to demonstrate enhanced Arctic warming from short‐lived shipping pollutants until 2160. In contrast, Gilgen et al. (
  <a rid="grl58008-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58008-bib-0020">2017</a>) found net cooling by 2050 using a global aerosol‐climate model, driven by enhanced cloud droplet number and optical thickness of clouds over the Arctic Ocean. Although highly relevant to environmental impacts of future shipping, the methods and emission projections used previously are not capable of evaluating dynamic feedbacks in the physical climate and human activities. We build on these earlier studies by using a fully coupled Earth system model (ESM) forced by spatially and temporally explicit projections of trans‐Arctic shipping emissions between 2006 and 2099. Unlike previous studies, this ESM simulates the physical interactions of albedo, clouds, oceans, and sea ice, and the emission projections employed allow specific shipping routes to vary with seasonal and decadal changes in sea ice so that shipping routes span multiple marine pathways (e.g., the coastal Northern Sea Route and direct transits over the North Pole). Our results thus represent a more realistic and robust estimate of climate responses to future trans‐Arctic shipping.
 </p>
</sec>
