<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To ensure proper model performance in our study, we evaluated the climate suitability for threatened plant species with occurrence localities based on previous field work (
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pineda &amp; Lobo</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Andel et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Walsh &amp; Haseeb</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). We used ArcGIS 10.2 (Esri; Redlands, CA, USA) to extract the current and future climate suitability for threatened plant species based on occurrence localities from the maps of climate suitability generated by our Maxent models. Occurrence localities were derived from field data coded as presence and absence within nature reserves. We then used two indices: (1) changes in climate suitability in order to identify climate suitability of threatened plant species and (2) the overlap between current and future climatically suitable habitats under the low, medium and high concentration scenarios. The species with substantially decreasing climate suitability and large overlaps between current and future climatically suitable habitats indicate highly negative effects of climate change on habitat suitability (
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thuiller et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). The projected changes in climate suitability may indicate variability in the potential locations of suitable climate conditions for threatened plant species in China, and the overlap between current and future climatically suitable habitats may indicate the potential movement of suitable climate conditions for threatened plant species (
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Warren, Glor &amp; Turelli</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Groom</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guisan et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
