<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation to Climate Change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protected area network is part of a climate adaptation strategy to preserve biodiversity in a changing climate 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Mawdsley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Mawdsley1">[6]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Hannah1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Hannah1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Heller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Heller1">[101]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Wiens1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Wiens1">[102]</a>. In general, climate adaptation strategies to preserve biodiversity can be divided into resistance and resilience strategies. Resistance strategies attempt to maintain the status quo of biodiversity in the face of climate change, and resilience strategies to enhance species and ecosystems to accommodate disturbances caused by changing climate 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Heller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Heller1">[101]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Poiani1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Poiani1">[103]</a>. Restoring degraded habitats (see also 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Mawdsley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Mawdsley1">[6]</a>) can be included in resistance strategy, whereas resilience strategies might include translocating species beyond current range limits or actively creating new corridors to allow species movement.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protected area network in Finnish mires, marshlands or Arctic mountain habitats is not situated at suboptimal sites in relation to predicted climate change, as measured by the probabilities of occurrences of bird species’ conservation concern and the hotspots of the most suitable areas for several species. In the future, protected areas seem to cover a fairly high or high proportion of occurrences of bird species, on average, in these habitats according to all scenarios, with only some slight decreases in the hotspots of predicted species occurrences. However, protected areas cannot ultimately prevent the predicted decrease in the northern species of mires, forests and Arctic mountain habitats 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Kujala1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Kujala1">[20]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala3">[49]</a> if the climate space for these species disappears. Both degraded mire habitats and forest habitats in terms of biodiversity have been restored in Finnish protected areas in a large programme 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Aapala1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Aapala1">[104]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Simil1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Simil1">[105]</a>, which also benefits the future survival of bird species in these habitats.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the forests of the southern and middle boreal zones, the proportion of habitat protected and the predicted habitat suitabilities of bird species in the 5% hotspots are so low that protected areas are likely to have only a limited impact on the species’ resistance to climate change. Our suitability hotspots results for forest birds suggest that the protected area network would benefit from its enlargement, particularly in the north-eastern part of the southern boreal zone and in the south-eastern and north-western part of the middle boreal zone.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the northern boreal zone the extent of protected areas is much higher, but due to the concentrated location of the areas, the significance of protected areas to preserve forest bird species of conservation concern only seems to come up in more advanced climate warming, particularly according to scenario A2. The concentrated forest protection in the northern boreal zone seems to raise an interesting question: in a mild climate change scenario, the protected area network is clearly inefficient, while in a strong climate change scenario it preserves, on average, species occurrences much more effectively (see, however, the disappearance of northern species, above). Thus, there is no single solution to preserving biodiversity in a changing climate – several future pathways should be considered (see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Wiens1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Wiens1">[102]</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the location of future protected areas should be planned in detail in relation to predicted climate change, although in the boreal zone, species have fairly large ranges and therefore species might not be so susceptible to the smaller-scale spatial variation of protected areas (see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala5" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala5">[60]</a>). A good example of the effects of the location of protected areas under climate change is the northern boreal zone in Finland, where forests have not been adequately protected, although almost a quarter of the forests are protected.
 </p>
</sec>
