<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species Atlas Data and Climate Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the European Bird Atlas, the EBCC Atlas for European Breeding Birds 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Hagemeijer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Hagemeijer1">[46]</a>, in developing the bioclimatic envelope models for the 100 bird species studied. We focused on present-absent data from all the European Bird Atlas 50-km grid squares where data covered at least 75% of expected breeding species (see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Hagemeijer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Hagemeijer1">[46]</a>). A species was considered to be breeding in a grid cell when the record for it fell under one of these categories: possible, probable and confirmed breeding.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following earlier studies 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Heikkinen2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Heikkinen2">[27]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Huntley4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Huntley4">[48]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala3">[49]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Forsman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Forsman1">[62]</a>, we selected five climate variables as potential explanatory variables for BEMs: mean temperature in April–June (TEMP
  <sub>AMJ</sub> ), mean temperature of the coldest month (MTCO), annual daily temperature sum above 5°C (growing degree days, GDD5), mean precipitation in April–June (PREC
  <sub>AMJ</sub>), and mean annual precipitation (PREC).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An observed Eurasian-wide climate dataset of monthly mean temperatures and precipitation at 10′×10′ spatial resolution averaged for the period 1971–2000 was constructed by combining two gridded databases: the CRU_TS_3.1 dataset at 30′×30′ grid resolution with monthly data during the period 1961–2000 (updated from Mitchell and Jones 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Mitchell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Mitchell1">[63]</a>), and monthly climatologies for the period 1961–1990 at 10′×10′ grid resolution from the CRU_CL_2.0 dataset 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-New1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-New1">[64]</a>. Data were extracted for Eurasia for the window 12°W to 70°E longitude and 34°N to 72°N latitude consisting of 73,670 grid cells at 10′ resolution and 9,167 grid cells at 30′ resolution (for more details, see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala2">[36]</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data in 10′ resolution were related to the 50×50 km grid system used in the EBCC Atlas for European Breeding Birds by calculating the mean, minimum and maximum for TMP
  <sub>AMJ,</sub> MTCO and GDD5 of all 10′ grid cells whose centre point was located within a given 50×50 km cell. The minimum and maximum values were applied so that our bioclimatic envelope models would include the preferences of bird species favouring lowland or upland climate conditions. Overall, 11 individual climate variables were considered in the model building.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three climate scenarios representing a wide range of possible climatic conditions for 2051–2080 were constructed for our climate variables on a 10×10 km grid covering Finland. Climate data for an ensemble of 19 General Circulation Models employed in the IPCC’s Fourth Assessment Report 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-IPCC1">[65]</a> (GCMs; for the selected models, see Virkkala et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala2">[36]</a>) were downloaded from the archive of the Third Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP3; 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Meehl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Meehl1">[66]</a>). In addition to the central ensemble scenario, two individual GCM simulations representing low and high changes were selected. Thus, we included: (i) the 19-model ensemble mean for the SRES A1B emission scenario representing average changes; (ii) a simulation of the Australian CSIRO-MK3.0 GCM for the SRES B1 (from now on B1) scenario, which shows relatively low annual temperature and precipitation changes across Finland throughout the 21st century; and (iii) a simulation of the Japanese MIROC3.2/medres GCM for the SRES A2 (from now on A2) scenario, which is among those simulations giving higher annual temperature and precipitation increases. We calculated simulated changes in temperature and precipitation from these scenarios between the baseline and scenario periods and applied these to an observed monthly climatology on a 10 km×10 km grid for Finland.
 </p>
</sec>
