<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The European-wide climate and bird data were employed to calibrate the bioclimatic models. The mean, maximum and minimum values for TMP
  <sub>AMJ</sub>, MTCO and GGD5 were highly intercorrelated. Thus, we first selected either the mean, maximum or minimum value for each study species and each of the three variables. This was done using generalized additive models (GAM) via the GRASP user-interface and the measures of predictor variables importance therein, see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala2">[36]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Lehmann1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Lehmann1">[67]</a>. Next, a second GRASP run was conducted where we included the remaining five climate variables, and in if high (&gt;0.9) correlations between the five predictor variables appeared, a variable with lower importance was excluded. However, for the precipitation variables we used only the mean values of the 10′×10′ grid cells. Moreover, because the correlation between precipitation variables and the other variables was always below &lt;0.8 (cf. 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Denol1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Denol1">[68]</a>) we included these two variables in all our BEMs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calibrated bioclimatic envelope models with the European climate (1971–2000) and bird data (50×50 km) were first projected for the climate data for Finland averaged over the period 1971–2000 in the 10×10 km grid scale. This provided the baseline estimate of the climatic suitability (i.e., predicted probability of occurrence) of each 10×10 km grid cell for each bird species. Next, we fitted the derived models to the three climate scenario datasets for the time period 2051–2080, which provided estimates of the future climatic suitability for each species.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bioclimatic envelope models were generated using the BIOMOD framework (the version described in 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Thuiller3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Thuiller3">[69]</a> in the R environment version 2.12., and the three modelling techniques, generalized linear models (GLM), generalized additive models (GAM) and generalized boosting method (GBM). For each of the 100 bird species, polynomial GLMs were computed using an automatic forward stepwise procedure together with the Akaike information criterion (AIC) model selection criteria. To produce GAMs, we used a cubic spline smoother with three degrees of freedom, and the step forward variable selection of GAM in BIOMOD based on AIC was employed 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Thuiller4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Thuiller4">[70]</a>. GBM was implemented into R (R Development Core Team, 2011) 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-R1">[71]</a> using the library GBM (Generalized Boosted Regression Modelling). The maximum number of trees was fixed at 2,000, and a four-fold cross-validation procedure was employed. For more details on the modelling methods used here, see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Lehmann1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Lehmann1">[67]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-McCullagh1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-McCullagh1">[72]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Marmion1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Marmion1">[78]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assessed the predictive power of the derived models using a four-fold cross validation with a random split into 20% validation and 80% calibration datasets. The discrimination ability of the predictive models was determined using three commonly used measures, which were: 1) the area under the curve (AUC) of a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) plot 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Fielding1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Fielding1">[79]</a>, 2) the kappa statistic 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Congalton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Congalton1">[80]</a>, and 3) the true skill statistic (TSS; Allouche et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Allouche1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Allouche1">[81]</a>). The predictive performance of all our BEMs (three modelling techniques times 100 species) was generally good or excellent, as only two species showed AUC values lower than 0.80, see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala2">[36]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the probability of occurrence of species generated by the three modelling methods, the arithmetic mean probability value was calculated for each species in each 10-km square for the periods 1971–2000 and 2051–2080. In calculating the joint habitat suitability index (joined species-specific and joined overall habitat suitability index), the amount of focal habitat (forest, mire, marshland and Arctic mountain habitats) in each square was first standardised to vary between 0 and 1 by dividing it by the largest amount of habitat per square in the corresponding zone. This was done because the amount of different habitats varies considerably in Finland (see 
  <a rid="pone.0063376-Virkkala2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0063376-Virkkala2">[36]</a>): the total land area of forests is 184,854 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (60.7% of total land area of 304,474 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in Finland) and that of marshlands 963 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (0.3%). Then this rescaled habitat amount was multiplied by the species probability of occurrence (values 0–1) to produce the joined species-specific habitat suitability index in each square for each species separately. Thus, in this procedure each species was related to its species-specific habitat, i.e. forest species to forest habitat, mire species to mire habitat etc., so that the species probability of occurrence was multiplied by the species-specific, standardised habitat amount (values 0–1) in each square. In the final step of the process, the joined overall habitat suitability index was calculated for each of our four species groups (i.e. the mean of the forest species joined habitat suitability indices, and so forth for all species groups) in each square. The degree of matching between most optimal areas for species and the reserve network was tested using Spearman rank correlation, where the habitat suitability index of species and species groups was related to the amount of protected habitat (hereafter “proportion protected”) in each square. Because of large sample sizes (452–1539) in these correlation analyses, only very low probability values (p&lt;0.001) can be regarded as “significant”. In comparing the overall habitat suitability index of the four species groups in 1971–2000 and in scenarios in the period 2051–2080, we used 5% hotspots, that is 5% of squares with the highest values of this index, separately for each species group in each boreal zone.
 </p>
</sec>
