<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To quantify a measure of population at risk, comparable between current and future climate scenarios, we used population count data from the Gridded Population of the World, version 4 (GPW4)[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], predicted for the year 2015. We selected this particular population product as it is minimally modeled 
 <italic class="italic">a priori</italic>, ensuring that the distribution of population on the earth’s surface has not been predicted by modeled covariates that would also influence our mechanistic vector-borne disease model predictions. These data are derived from most recent census data, globally, at the smallest administrative unit available, then interpolated to produce continuous surface models for the globe for 5-year intervals from 2000–2020. These are then rendered as globally gridded data at 30 arc-seconds; we aggregated these in R to match the climate scenario grids at 5 minute resolution (approximately 10 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> at the equator). We used 2015 population count as our proxy for the current population, and explored future risk relative to the current population counts. This prevents arbitrary demographic model-imposed patterns emerging, possibly obscuring climate-generated change. We note that these count data reflect the disparities in urban and rural patterns appropriately for this type of analysis, highlighting population-dense parts of the globe. Increasing urbanization would likely amplify the patterns we see, as populations increase overall; however, the lack of appropriate population projections at this scale for 30–50 years in the future limits the precision of the forecasts we provide. We thus opted for a most conservative approach. We finally subdivide global populations into geographic and socioeconomic regions as used by the Global Burden of Disease studies (
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0007213.s001" class="xref">S1 Fig</xref>
 </bold>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. We used the ‘fasterize’ R package [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007213.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>] to convert these regions into rasters with percent (out of 100) coverage at polygon edges. To calculate population at risk on a regional basis, those partial-coverage rasters were multiplied by total population grids.
</p>
