<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The interaction of climatic and anthropogenic factors influence the persistence of coastal ecosystems [
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>], together with their intrinsic vulnerability. In this study, hammocks persistence was defined by the interaction between exposure and sensitivity criteria. To assess hammocks persistence, each indicator of both criteria was weighted to express its importance relative to the other indicators, based on the pairwise comparison method [
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. A priority vector (weights) was estimated from the pairwise comparison matrix. The relative importance was based on the influence of each indicator in the flooding of hammocks, derived from the opinion of experts and published research. The relative importance ranges from 1 (equally important) to 9 (extremely more important). In the pairwise comparison matrix, relative importance values are allocated for the more important indicators against less important indicators, while the reciprocal values are allocated for the less important indicators against more important indicators (Tables 
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref> and 
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.t005" ref-type="table" class="xref">5</xref>). Since this study assumes that it is likely that SLR due to climate change will directly contribute to the increase in hammocks’ exposure, the assessment of the “sea flooding due to SLR scenarios” exposure indicator was assigned the highest value of relative importance, compared to the other exposure indicators. Conversely, the “hurricanes impact” exposure indicator was assigned the lowest value, based on the fact that even when a hurricane could affect both terrestrial and coastal margins, particularly increasing the mortality of trees with small diameters (3.3–10 cm) [
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>], a recent study states that other factors such as anthropic disturbances may have a larger and more permanent impact on hammocks in this area [
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. “Coastal flooding”, “proximity to streams”, and “land cover change” indicators were assigned the same relative importance because although LCC may have more permanent adverse effects on the persistence of hammocks, the other two indicators have a more extensive effect. In the case of sensitivity, the “type of hammock” indicator was rated with the highest value of relative importance, compared to the other two sensitivity indicators, since trees in the coastline are most sensitive to processes such as submergence, coastal flooding, and coastal erosion [
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0162637.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>].
</p>
