<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Jamba</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAMBA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>J&#x000e0;mb&#x000e1; : Journal of Disaster Risk Studies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2072-845X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1996-1421</issn><publisher><publisher-name>AOSIS</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6676940</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JAMBA-11-739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/jamba.v11i1.739</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Application of livelihood vulnerability index to assess risks for farmers in the Sukoharjo Regency and Klaten Regency, Indonesia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3763-9639</contrib-id><name><surname>Suryanto</surname><given-names>Suryanto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5839-8259</contrib-id><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>Aulia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Department of Economics Development, Faculty of Economics and Business, Sebelas Maret University, Surakarta, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Suryanto Suryanto, <email xlink:href="suryanto_feb@staff.uns.ac.id">suryanto_feb@staff.uns.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>739</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019. The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>Licensee: AOSIS. This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This research tried to compare the level of farmers&#x02019; livelihood vulnerability to flooding in Sukoharjo and Klaten. Farmers are the most susceptible caused by climate change. The data used in this research are primary data, collected by interviewing 61 respondents who are farmers in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo Regency and 72 respondents in the Jiwo Wetan Village, Klaten Regency. This data obtained by using non-probability sampling technique with purposive methods. Meanwhile mapping for hazard level was analysed by using Geographic Information System (GIS). Descriptive statistic was used for the livelihood vulnerability index&#x02019;s (LVI) and the LVI-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&#x02019;s (IPCC) index calculation. The results show that the farmers&#x02019; livelihood vulnerability in the Sonorejo Village is medium level because of climate change based on the LVI index value at 0.363 and LVI-IPCC index value at 0.044. Meanwhile, the Jiwo Wetan Village has a lower index in LVI at 0.344 and LVI-IPCC index value at 0.038. Areas with similar physical characteristic and most of its community have a dependence on agriculture tend relatively the same level of vulnerability.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>poverty</kwd><kwd>food security</kwd><kwd>livelihood vulnerability index</kwd><kwd>flood</kwd><kwd>climate change</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The increase in emissions of greenhouse gases (GHG) leads to an increase in temperature of the earth and causes global climate change. This is one of the key elements in the system of metabolism and physiology of plants; the global climate change has a major impact on the agricultural sector. According to the Agricultural Research and Development Agency (BBSDLP <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), the agricultural sector is one of the most threatened sectors that is suffering and vulnerable to climate change. Salinger (<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) and Karim, Jahan and Islam (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) stated three main factors in the agricultural sector based on global climate change, that is, (1) changes in the patterns of rainfall, (2) the rise of extreme climate events (floods and droughts) and (3) an increase in air temperature.</p><p>An extreme climate change causes a great impact on the agricultural sector. The climate change severely leads to changes in pattern, and the level of precipitation affects the initial time of planting and growing period. The alteration in level of precipitation affects the time and seasons, cropping patterns, land degradation, destruction of crops and productivity, planted and harvested acreage, and the damage to biodiversity, especially crops that is relatively sensitive to water availability (Runtunuwu &#x00026; Syahbuddin <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Flooding on rice fields causes a reduction in harvest area and a decline in rice production significantly. High rainfall causes losses to farmers in the United States. The US EPA (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) reported losses in 2010&#x02013;2011, which reached $220 million. Mall, Gupta and Sungkar (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) said that farmers must be given guidance to adapt because climate change has a negative effect.</p><p>Central Java Province is the second largest province of East Java with total area of wetland that is prone to flood or inundation (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Even so, Central Java Province remains one of Indonesia&#x02019;s largest rice suppliers. Sukoharjo sub-district is one of the regions that largest suppliers of rice and food buffer in Central Java. Rice is the main agricultural product in Sukoharjo sub-district. According to report from the Minister of Agriculture and the Central Bureau of Statistics in Sukoharjo 2015, rice production in the Sukoharjo sub-district ranks third after the Polokarto sub-district and Mojolaban sub-district. Sukoharjo sub-district consists of 14 villages, where most of the land is used as a wetland. The use of paddy fields in the sub-district of Sukoharjo in 2013 amounted to 2.363 hectares (ha) or 53% of the total area of its territory. Sonorejo is the largest area with land use for rice fields; proportion is reached to 68% (302 ha) of the total area (444 ha). However, at some point the fields contained in the Sonorejo Village is prone to floods. However, Klaten is also a producer of rice in Central Java. Rice production in Klaten reaches 350 000 tons per year, while local demand is only 207 500 tons per year. Unfortunately, some areas become prone to flood because of overflow of the Dengkeng River. One of the worst impacted areas is the Jiwo Wetan Village in Klaten Regency, where, in 2017, there was a crop failure of 35.2 ha which was suffered by 123 farmers.</p><table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Summary of research methods.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research purposes</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis tools</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mapping of flood-prone wetland in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo Sub-district</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GIS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary data<break/>Secondary data</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Map of flood vulnerability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Livelihood vulnerability index of farmers in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo sub-district</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Descriptive statistics</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primary data</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vulnerability index (livelihood vulnerability index)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>GIS, Geographic Information System.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on the results of the mapping with Geographic Information System (GIS) and interview conducted with the Head of Village and the Head of Sonorejo&#x02019;s Farmers Group Association (Gapoktan), wetland that is mostly prone to flood is located in the eastern part of the Sonorejo Village, namely, Langsur and Ngiser, that is directly adjacent to the Bulakrejo and Sukoharjo Village. The land altitude in those areas is lower than the surrounding areas, and the water drains (drainage) are not functioning properly, resulting to the flooding in the field.</p><p>The research area in Klaten Regency also has characteristics similar to the sample area in Sukoharjo Regency. The altitude of the Jiwo Wetan Region is lower than other areas around it. When the Dengkeng River overflows, the overflow leads in the terrain in the south of the village. If the inundation does not pass, then the water goes to the rice fields and settlements of the Jiwo Wetan Village.</p><p>The majority of the population in the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages rely on agriculture, especially crops and paddy rice. This condition causes the vulnerability on the livelihoods of farmers and their households. This study aims to deepen the understanding of the vulnerability of people&#x02019;s livelihoods in flood-prone areas in paddy field in the Sonorejo Village and Jiwo Wetan Village, which are based on the results of the mapping with GIS and livelihood vulnerability index (LVI). The benefit of this research is to find out whether areas that have the same level of hazard and the same dependence on agriculture will have the same level of vulnerability.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Methods and data analysis</title><p>Geographic Information System is used as a tool to find the area that is prone to flood. Thereafter, the analysis of the vulnerability of households&#x02019; farming based on flood occurrence will be conducted by using LVI calculations, which is based on the primary data obtained. Furthermore, the results are described as follows.</p><sec id="s20003"><title>Analysis by Geographic Information System</title><p>The utilisation of GIS has been done to identify areas of potential disasters. Wood and Good (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) identify vulnerability at airports and seaports as catastrophic earthquake and tsunami. Saptutyningsih and Suryanto (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), measure the environmental and social impact caused by natural disasters (ND). This research used the GIS to map the flood-prone areas in the Sonorejo Village and Jiwo Wetan Village by taking some variables into account, such as flood event data, curvature of the river, slope and land use.</p></sec><sec id="s20004"><title>Livelihood vulnerability index approach</title><p>Vulnerability is one of the factors that determines whether people have risks to their livelihoods or not. According to IPPC (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), the vulnerability assessment measures the ability of the community to respond to hazard and or secure their livelihood. Therefore, the index is used for comparison among the communities. Vulnerability Index or LVI was developed by Hahn, Riederer and Foster (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), Madhuri, Thewari, and Bhowmick (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), Simane, Zaitchik and Foltz (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and Richardson et al. (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). This study wants to measure the vulnerability of households living in areas classified as flood-prone in Sukoharjo Regency and Klaten Regency. Most of the LVI studies were conducted to see differences in the level of vulnerability in different regional characteristics. Some examples of studies, Hahn et al. (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) use LVI for coastal and inland populations, Simane et al. (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) see differences in the characteristics of highland and lowland ecosystems and Richardson et al. (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) further see LVI as a basis for predicting food security in a region. Nevertheless, the LVI calculations by Hahn et al. (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) is applied in this study, which consists of the following seven main components:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Socio-demographic profile (SDP)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Livelihood strategies (LS)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Health (H)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Food (F)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Water (W)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Social networks (SN)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Natural disasters (ND) and climate variability</p></list-item></list><p>According to Hahn et al. (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), LVI component consists of several sub-components or indicators. These sub-components are developed based on a literature study of each major component. <xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows how each of these sub-components is taken into account and limits the ability or potential bias.</p><table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Design of the livelihood vulnerability index.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major component</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sub-components</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explanation of sub-components</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potential limitations</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Socio-demographic profile</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependency ratio</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ratio of population &#x0003c; 15 and &#x0003e; 65 years of age to the population between 19 and 65 years of age</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large extended families, confusion about who is a member of the household, the absence of birth certificates</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of female-headed households</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Household percentage of adult female. If the head of her family had no home &#x0003e; 6 months a year</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unable to determine the head of the family at home because there is more than one family living together without husband</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households where head of household did not attend school</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of heads of households who do not attended schools</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households with members needing dependent care</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of members of the house for at least a person who needs daily care, for instance, old age person, physical or mental condition and disability</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Livelihood strategy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households with family member working in a different city</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households whose members at least one person working outside the city for their primary work activity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion about who the members of his family, did not count how many family members who have previously worked out of the city</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that the main income depends on natural resources or agriculture</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that report the main income source only from agricultural sector</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Only three main sources included</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average Agricultural Livelihood Diversification Index (range: 0.20&#x02013;1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The opposite of (amount of agricultural activity +1), for example, household farming, gardening and farming, will have a livelihood classification index = 1/(3 + 1) = 0:25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three main sources of family income in the agricultural sector. Outside the agricultural sector were not included</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Health</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average time to health facility (min)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average time required to reach the members of the house nearest health facility</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective estimation of travel time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Households percentage with family member having chronic illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Households percentage report with at least one family member having chronic illness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjectively defined by respondent</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Food</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households dependent on family farm for food</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that have food primarily from their personal farms</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjectively defined by respondent</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of months households struggle to find food (range: 0&#x02013;12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of months households struggle to obtain food for their family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective definition of &#x02018;struggle&#x02019;; believe in self-reported</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households without crops savings</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households without crops savings from each harvest</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Families that sell crops and save money are not counted</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Water</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that are using the source of natural water</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that report their primary source of water is from river, lake or hole</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion regarding when families have more than one water source</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average time to source of water (min)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average time of households taken to travel to their primary source of water everyday</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective estimates of travel time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households without a consistent water supply</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that report water is not available at their primary source everyday</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recall bias (more likely to remember several consecutive days of water shortage)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The inverse of the average number of litres of water stored per household (range: &#x0003e; 0&#x02013;1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The inverse of (the average number of litres of water stored by each household +1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of information about the size of containers</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Social networks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average receive: Given ratio (range: 0&#x02013;15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ratio of (how much help received by household in the past month +1) to (the number of types of help given by a household to someone else in the past month +1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion who is the family (immediate) and who is a relative (extended), reliance on self-reported types of help</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average borrowed: Lend money ratio (range: 0.5&#x02013;2.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ratio of household borrowing money in the past month to a household lending money in the same month, for example, if a household borrowed money but did not lend money, the ratio = 2:1 or 2 and if they lent money but did not borrow any, the ratio = 1:2 or 0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reliance on self-reported money exchanges, does not consider exchange of non-monetary goods</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that does not seek for assistance to their local government in the past 12 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that reported they did not ask their local government for any assistance in the past 12 months</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion of believe in self-reported about the frequency of visits local government in past 12 months</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Natural disaster and climate variability</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of floods, in the past 5 years (0&#x02013;7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of floods incident that was reported by households in the past 5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not remember about small flood event</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that did not receive warning about the pending natural disasters</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that did not receive a warning about the most severe flood event in the past 5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjectively defined</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households with an injury or death as a result of the most severe natural disaster in the past 5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that reported either an injury or death of any of their family member as a result of the severe flood in the past 5 years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not remember small injures</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation average mean of the daily maximum temperature by month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation average of daily maximum temperature by month between 2009 and 2013 for its province</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short period of time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation average mean of the daily minimum temperature by month</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation average of the daily minimum temperature by month between 2009 and 2013 for its province</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short period of time</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Source</italic>: Hahn, M.B., Riederer, A.M. &#x00026; Foster, S.O., 2009, &#x02018;The livelihood vulnerability index: A pragmatic approach to assessing risks from climate variability and change: A case study in Mozambique&#x02019;, <italic>Journal of Global Environmental Change</italic> 19(1), 74&#x02013;88. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.11.002/">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.11.002/</ext-link>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Each of these sub-components is calculated with different scales; therefore, an index is needed to calculate all the components as a whole. Accordingly, the composite index approach was used to convert the scale of each sub-component derived from <italic>The Life Expectancy Index</italic> (UNDP <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), which is calculated as follows:
<disp-formula id="FD1"><alternatives><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 1]</label></disp-formula>
where, S<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> is the value of the sub-components of the area <italic>d</italic>, and <italic>S</italic><sub>min</sub> and <italic>S</italic><sub>max</sub> indicate the minimum and maximum values of each sub-components that is determined by the data from the study area. Once standardised, the sub-components are averaged by using the following formula, and then calculate the value of its main components.
<disp-formula id="FD2"><alternatives><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 2]</label></disp-formula></p><p>The value of <italic>M</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub> is equal to one of the main components in the area <italic>d</italic> (SDP, LS, H, F, W, SN and ND). The <italic>d</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> index reflects the value of the sub-components that are indexed by <italic>i</italic>. Based on these equations, the LVI grades can be obtained by using the following equation:
<disp-formula id="FD3"><alternatives><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>LVI</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 3]</label></disp-formula>
or
<disp-formula id="FD4"><alternatives><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>LVI</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e004.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 4]</label></disp-formula>
where, LVI<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> represents the index value for the susceptibility in area, <italic>d</italic>, measured by seven major components. WM<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> represents the number of sub-components that reflect to the main component, which is equally contributed to the overall LVI (Sullivan, Meigh &#x00026; Fediw <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). The scale of LVI grades ranged from 1 to 3, where:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>0 to 0.2 = not vulnerable</p></list-item><list-item><p>12:21 to 0.4 = vulnerable</p></list-item><list-item><p>0:41 to 0.5 = very vulnerable.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="s20005"><title>Livelihood Vulnerability Index approach-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</title><p>Livelihood Vulnerability Index-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) index is an alternative method used when calculating LVI according to the IPCC definition of vulnerability. <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the composition of seven key components of LVI-IPCC approach. The population exposure in this research is measured based on the number of floods that occurred in the last 5 years, while climate variability is measured by the average standard deviation of monthly maximum and minimum temperature and a monthly precipitation over a period of 5 years. Adaptive capacity is measured by the demographic profile of the area (headed by women), occupation of LS and SN (the percentage of households who helped neighbours). Then, sensitivity is measured by determining the present food status, water assurance and the health status of a region. The index showed in <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> is also used to calculate LVI-IPCC. The calculation of LVI-IPCC is different from the main components of LVI combined. Firstly, all components will be combined by category plan in <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> by using the following equation:
<disp-formula id="FD5"><alternatives><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CF</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 5]</label></disp-formula>
where, CF<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> represents the contributing factors according to IPCC (exposure, sensitivity or adaptive capacity) for area <italic>d</italic> (Sonorejo Village); <italic>M</italic><sub><italic>di</italic></sub> represents a main component for area <italic>d</italic>, which is indexed by <italic>I</italic>; WM<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> represents the quality of the main component; <italic>n</italic> represents the number of the main components of each contributing factor. The combination of these three contributing factors is calculated using the following equation:
<disp-formula id="FD6"><alternatives><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>LVI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>IPCC</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 6]</label></disp-formula>
where LVI-IPPC<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> represents the LVI index in area <italic>d</italic> expressed by using the framework of the vulnerability of the IPCC; <italic>e</italic> represents the score of area <italic>d</italic> (equal as the main component of ND and climate variability); <italic>a</italic> represents adaptive capacity score of area <italic>d</italic> (weighted by the average of the main component, i.e. LS, socio-demographic and SN) and <italic>s</italic> represents sensitive score of area <italic>d</italic> (weighted by the average of the major components, i.e. health, food and water). The scale of LVI-IPCC range between (&#x02212;1) and (&#x02212;0.4) is not vulnerable; (&#x02212;0.41) and (0.3) is vulnerable or moderate and (0.31) and (1) is very vulnerable.</p><table-wrap id="T0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Categories of major components contributing factors by the definition of vulnerability according to Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change for the calculation of the Livelihood Vulnerability Index-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contributing factors to vulnerability</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major components</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural disaster and climate variability</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Adaptive capacity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socio-demographic profile</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Livelihood strategies</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Sensitivity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social networks</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Source</italic>: Hahn, M.B., Riederer, A.M. &#x00026; Foster, S.O., 2009, &#x02018;The livelihood vulnerability index: A pragmatic approach to assessing risks from climate variability and change: A case study in Mozambique&#x02019;, <italic>Journal of Global Environmental Change</italic> 19(1), 74&#x02013;88. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.11.002">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.11.002</ext-link>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s20006"><title>Ethical considerations</title><p>Respect for the dignity of research participants was prioritised. Anonymity of individuals and organisations participating in the research were ensured.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Result</title><sec id="s20008"><title>Results prone to flood mapping with Geographical Information Systems</title><sec id="s30009"><title>Flood</title><p>The high intensity of rainfall in the Sonorejo Village causes the rice fields in the area vulnerable to flooding. Based on the mapping of flood-prone rice fields in the Sonorejo Village, the areas most prone to flooding in lowland rice fields are Langsur and Ngiser. Meanwhile, the region that has the same characteristic with the Sonorejo Village is the Jiwo Wetan Village in Klaten Regency. The Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages have an annual flood risk; the frequency of flooding is 4 to 6 times each year. In 2017, farmers in the Jiwo Wetan Village have accepted agricultural insurance claims because their agricultural land was damaged by floods (i.e. 75%).</p></sec><sec id="s30010"><title>The curvature of the river</title><p>The curvature of the river is the ratio between the valleys and the length of the river. The river in the eastern of Sonorejo Village is a meandering river that flows over gently sloping ground that begins to curve back and forth across the landscape. Meandering river has asymmetric channels. The deepest part of the channel is found outside of each bend. The water flows faster in these deeper fragments and grinds down material from the riverbank. The water flows more gently in the shallow areas near the inside of each bend. The slower flow of water cannot carry much residue and deposits its load on a series of point bars. Meandering rivers erode residue from the outer curve of each meander bend and deposit it on an inner curve further downstream.</p><p>The characteristics in the Jiwo Wetan Village area have similarity with the Sonorejo Village. Although the meandering is not like in Sonorejo, yet Jiwo Wetan is potentially flooding because the south of the village is the terrain of the Pegunungan Seribu, Yogyakarta. When rainfall is high, rainwater flows into the Dengkeng River and has the potential to increase the vulnerability of the area in Jiwo Wetan Klaten.</p></sec><sec id="s30011"><title>Slope</title><p>Slope in the Sonorejo Village, Sukoharjo sub-district, shows that most areas in the Sonorejo Village are flat with slope level ranging between 2% and 6%, which leads to the conclusion theoretically that the Sonorejo Village is highly susceptible to flooding. Slope in the Jiwo Wetan Village, Klaten Regency, is approximately 2% &#x02013; 7%.</p></sec><sec id="s30012"><title>Land use</title><p>Land use index is determined by a map of land use and land use information on RBI topographic maps. The data collected are then contributed to the mapping of land use. The result shows that the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages are classified into three categories of land use, that is housing, irrigated fields and farming.</p></sec><sec id="s30013"><title>Potential flooding</title><p>Flood is a condition of overflowing of a large amount of water. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref> shows the mapping of flood-prone area in the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages.</p><fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Mapping of flood-prone area in the Sonorejo Village.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-g001"/></fig><p>Based on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>, the areas marked with dark red are the area mostly prone to flooding in the Sonorejo Village. Based on the results of the mapping using GIS with the consideration of a variable number of flood events, local curvature of the river, slope and land use, it can be seen that Langsur and Ngiser in the Sonorejo Village are two areas prone to catastrophic flooding in lowland rice fields compared with other areas.</p><p>Based on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>, the results of the mapping using GIS with the consideration of a variable number of flood events, local curvature of the river, slope and land use, it can be seen that most areas in Jiwo Wetan are marked dark red. The Jiwo Wetan Village is passed by a river which can overflow at any time if the intensity of the rain increases. Based on reports from the Local Disaster Board (Badan Penanggulangan Bencana Daerah [BPBD]), standing water can reach 1 m.</p><fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Mapping of flood-prone area in the Jiwo Wetan Village.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-g002"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s20014"><title>Analysis of livelihoods vulnerability</title><p>Livelihood vulnerability index consists of seven main components, namely, SDP, LS, H, F, W, SN and ND and climate variability, and each consists of several indicators or sub-components. Each sub-component is measured by different scales that should be standardised to convert it into an index and combine it as a whole with the composite index.</p><p>The result of the standardisation of each sub-component, which is obtained by a survey of 61 families in the Sonorejo Village and 72 respondents in the Jiwo Wetan Village, is presented in <xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>Livelihood vulnerability index results for the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sub-components</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Composite index<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Main component</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Major component index<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sonorejo</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jiwo Wetan</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sonorejo</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jiwo Wetan</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent ratio</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Socio-demographic profile</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of female-headed households</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.368</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average age of female head of household</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.432</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of household head has not attended school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.262</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households with members seeking dependent care</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.213</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households with family member working in different community</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.456</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Livelihood strategy</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.392</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households where the main source of income depends on agriculture</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average Agricultural Livelihood Diversification Index (range: 0.20&#x02013;1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average time to health facility (min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households&#x02019; family members with chronic illness</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households dependent on family farm for food</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.443</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.445</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of months that households struggle to find food (range: 0&#x02013;12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households without crops savings</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.557</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households using source of natural water</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.787</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average time to source of water (min)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households without a consistent water supply</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The inverse of average number of litres of water stored per household (range: &#x0003e;0&#x02013;1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average received: Given ratio (range: 0&#x02013;15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.217</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social network</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.482</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.203</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average borrowed: Lend money ratio (range: 0.5&#x02013;2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.234</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that do not seek for assistance from their local government in the past 12 months</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.656</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number of floods, in the past 5 years (0&#x02013;7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.177</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Natural disasters and climate variability</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.495</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households that did not receive warming about pending natural disaster</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.852</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.445</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of households with injury or death as a result of the severe natural disaster in the past 5 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation mean average of daily maximum temperature by month</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation mean average of daily minimum temperature per month</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.705</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard deviation mean average of precipitation by month</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Overall LVI</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.355</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.275</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>LVI, livelihood vulnerability index.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on the level of vulnerability classification conducted by Hahn et al. (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), it is known that the scale of the LVI value is set between 0 and 0.2 (not vulnerable), 0.21 and 0.40 (vulnerable or moderate) and 0.41 and 0.5 (very vulnerable). The results of the calculations in <xref rid="T0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> can be interpreted as measured variables including the following.</p><sec id="s30015"><title>Socio-demographic profile</title><p>The socio-demographic index of the Sonorejo Village is 0.235 and the Jiwo Wetan Village is 0.145. The proportion of the population of non-productive age, education pursued by the head of the family and the limitations of family members are still at a moderate level. The percentation of women as family heads is 0.115, while in the Jiwo Wetan Village it is higher at 0.368. This index shows that families led by a woman will be more vulnerable than households led by a man.</p></sec><sec id="s30016"><title>Livelihood strategy</title><p>The livelihood strategy index from the Sonorejo Village is 0.392, while in the Jiwo Wetan Village it is 0.499. The index of household sub-components that are based on the agricultural sector in Sonorejo sub-district is 0.607, while in the Jiwo Wetan Village it is 0.645. This shows that family dependence on the agricultural sector is more susceptible to climate change than families who do not only rely on the agricultural sector. Besides farming they also work outside the city and other economic sectors.</p></sec><sec id="s30017"><title>Health</title><p>The comparison of the health index numbers shown by the Sonorejo Village is 0.263, while in the Jiwo Wetan Village it is 0.245. In the health sub-component, the distance between health facilities and the number of families who have members with chronic diseases shows a moderate number. Based on the health degree vulnerability index, it can be concluded that the residents in the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages are not very vulnerable to climate change. Geographically, the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages are not isolated from health service centres.</p></sec><sec id="s30018"><title>Food</title><p>Based on the survey results, several families in the Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages have the same characteristics in terms of food components. If the level of vulnerability in the Sonorejo Village is 0.426, then in Jiwo Wetan Village it is not significantly different at 0.445. This is because of changes in rainfall patterns and high rainfall as a result of climate change that causes flooding or inundation in the paddy fields of Sonorejo and Jiwo Wetan villages, resulting in crop failure and a decrease in rice productivity. As a result, farm households that get the main food source from their own crops become vulnerable to climate change. Based on the food sub-component index, households whose main source of food comes from their own crops do not store it for use when unpredictable conditions are the most vulnerable to climate change.</p></sec><sec id="s30019"><title>Water</title><p>Households in the Sonorejo Village in the water component showed a relatively moderate level of vulnerability with an index number of 0.274. As many as 78.7% of families in the Sonorejo Village use natural water sources to meet their daily water needs with consistent water availability (always available), while 8.19% or five families are recorded as not having a consistent water source. This is because their water sources sometimes have a salty or cloudy taste, so they have to find other water sources to meet their family&#x02019;s water needs. The level of vulnerability in water resources in the Sonorejo Village is higher than in the Jiwo Wetan Village. Water problems in the Jiwo Wetan Village will appear during the dry season, but not significantly.</p></sec><sec id="s30020"><title>Social networks</title><p>The Social Network Indicator in the Sonorejo Village shows that most of the people in the Sonorejo Village did not request assistance from the local or local government during the past year (as many as 65.57% or 40 households). While in the Jiwo Wetan Village, the majority of the population also did not ask for government assistance except because of the agricultural insurance premium subsidy programme. Based on the results of the survey conducted, in Sonorejo Village the agricultural insurance programmes are still at the socialisation stage, while in the village area Jiwo Wetan has implemented the programme. The agricultural insurance programme in the Jiwo Wetan Village has given claims to farmers who have experienced crop failure.</p></sec><sec id="s30021"><title>Natural disasters and climate variability</title><p>The index number of ND and climate variability in the Sonorejo Village is 0.495; this figure shows that farmers in Sonorejo sub-district are very vulnerable to floods because of their location adjacent to Langsur River and lower terrain than other regions in Sonorejo sub-district. Based on the average number of floods reported in the past 6 years, as many as 85% of families did not get a warning or notification that there would be heavy rain or flooding. However, for the Jiwo Wetan region 0.445 is lower than in Sonorejo. This information is important considering the population of Jiwo Wetan when the rainy season almost always suffers from flooding because it is topographically bordered by the Dengkeng River and Pegunungan Seribu.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s20022"><title>Livelihood Vulnerability Index-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change approach</title><p>Livelihood vulnerability index/LVI-IPCC is a measure of vulnerability of farmer households in disaster-prone areas with three measurement indicators, namely, exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity. The formula LVI calculation formula based on the IPCC is:
<disp-formula id="FD7"><alternatives><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>LVI</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>IPCC</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Sd</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="JAMBA-11-739-e007.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></alternatives><label>[Eqn 7]</label></disp-formula>
where, LVI-IPCC<sub><italic>d</italic></sub> is a formula to measure the level of vulnerability of a community or community using the IPCC framework; <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub> is a score calculation from community or community exposure; <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub> is the calculation of the score from the capacity of a community or community and <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub> is the calculation of the sensitivity of a community or community.</p><p>Livelihood Vulnerability Index-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change is an alternative method for making the alleged vulnerabilities of communities relative to the effect of climate change developed from LVI. The Final IPCC weighted LVI scores range between (&#x02212;1) and (&#x02212;0.4) is not vulnerable, (&#x02212;0.41) and (0.3) is vulnerable or moderate and (0.31) and (1) is the most vulnerable (<xref rid="T0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>Calculation of Livelihood Vulnerability Index-Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change contributing factors in the Sonorejo Village and Jiwo Wetan Village.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">IPCC contributing factors to vulnerability</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Major components index<hr/></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Major components scores<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sonorejo</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jiwo Wetan</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sonorejo</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jiwo Wetan</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.495</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.208</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.495</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.208</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adaptive capacity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.797</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.762</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.345</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.342</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Socio-demographic</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Livelihood vulnerability</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.392</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Social network</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.482</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.657</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.105</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.295</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.234</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Health</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.263</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Food</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Water</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.145</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final IPCC weighted LVI scores</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>-</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.044</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;0.032</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: Bold values indicate the results of IPPC factors that contribute to vulnerability.</p></fn><fn><p>IPCC, Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change; LVI, livelihood vulnerability index.</p></fn><fn><p><italic>Source</italic>: Adapted from IPCC, 2001, <italic>Climate change 2001: Impacts, adaptation, and vulnerability, contribution of working group II to the third assessment report</italic>, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The overall value of LVI-IPCC indicated that the vulnerability of farmers&#x02019; livelihoods to flood in the Sonorejo Village goes in the category of vulnerable or moderate by 0.044 on index figure. Although Jiwo Wetan has a lower LVI than Sonorejo, LVI Jiwo Wetan is still classified as vulnerable. LVI Score in Jiwo Wetan is &#x02212;0.032. The agricultural insurance programme is proven to reduce losses for farmers in Jiwo Wetan. If the social network score in Sonorejo reaches 0.482, then in Jiwo Wetan it is at the level of 0.245.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0023"><title>Conclusion</title><p>According to the mapping result using GIS, rice field in the Sonorejo Village, especially in Langsur and Ngiser, has high level of vulnerability to flood because of its lower altitude than other areas.</p><p>The results of the research show that farmers in the Sonorejo Village is vulnerable to climate change by 0.363 and 0.044 index calculated by using the LVI and LVI-IPCC approach, respectively. In Jiwo Wetan, LVI is lower than in Sonorejo Village (0.275) and LVI-IPCC is also lower than in Sonorejo Village (&#x02212;0.032).</p><p>The LVI index measurement results show that two regions that have the same characteristics also have different levels of vulnerability. Strengthening population capacity can be done by expanding the agricultural insurance network. Although agricultural insurance still depends on government subsidies, this policy eases the burden on farmers who experience crop failure.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Board of Disaster Management of Karanganyar Regency for their help.</p><sec id="s20024" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no financial or personal relationships that may have inappropriately influenced them in writing this article.</p></sec><sec id="s20025"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>S.S. has shared the idea and methodology and reviewed the article. A.R. has conducted the data analysis and coordinated the field survey.</p></sec><sec id="s20026"><title>Funding information</title><p>This research has been funded by the Higher Education (Dikti) Grant, Ministry of Research and Higher Education of Indonesia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s20027"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>Data sharing is not applicable to this article as no new data were created or analysed in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s20028"><title>Disclaimer</title><p>The views and opinions expressed in this article are those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of any affiliated agency of the authors.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>How to cite this article:</bold> Suryanto, S. &#x00026; Rahman, A., 2019, &#x02018;Application of livelihood vulnerability index to assess risks for farmers in the Sukoharjo Regency and Klaten Regency, Indonesia&#x02019;, <italic>J&#x000e0;mb&#x000e1;: Journal of Disaster Risk Studies</italic> 11(1), a739. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4102/jamba.v11i1.739">https://doi.org/10.4102/jamba.v11i1.739</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list id="references"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>BBSDLP</collab></person-group>, <year>2011</year>, <source><italic toggle="yes">Indonesia Peat Lands Map Scale of 1: 250,000</italic></source>, <comment>Agricultural Research and Development Agency</comment>, <publisher-name>Ministry of Agriculture</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Jakarta</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Etwire</surname><given-names>P.M</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Hassan</surname><given-names>R.M</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwornu</surname><given-names>J.K.M</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Osei-Owusu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2013</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Application of livelihood vulnerability index assessing vulnerability to climate change and variability in Nothern Ghana</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Environment and Earth Science</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>M.B</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>S.O</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2009</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>The livelihood vulnerability index: A pragmatic approach to assessing risks from climate variability and change: A case study in Mozambique</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Global Environmental Change</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPCC</collab></person-group>, <year>2001</year>, <source><italic toggle="yes">Climate change 2001: Impacts, adaptation, and vulnerability, contribution of working group II to the third assessment report</italic></source>, <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IPCC</collab></person-group>, <year>2007</year>, in <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Canziani</surname><given-names>O.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palutikof</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Linden</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name> (eds.)</person-group>, <source><italic toggle="yes">Climate change 2007: Impacts, adaptation and vulnerability, contribution of working group II to the fourth assessment report of the intergovernmental panel on climate change (IPCC)</italic></source>, pp. <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>, <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Jahan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2014</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Impacts of climate change on agriculture in the flood plain area of Chauhali Upazila, Sirajgonj, Bangladesh</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Science, Technology &#x00026; Environment Informatics</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>(<issue>01</issue>), <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>, <comment>viewed 25 January 2019, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/267626585_Impact_of_Climate_Change_on_Agriculture_in_the_Flood_Plain_Area_of_Chauhali_Upazila_Sirajgonj_Bangladesh">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/267626585_Impact_of_Climate_Change_on_Agriculture_in_the_Flood_Plain_Area_of_Chauhali_Upazila_Sirajgonj_Bangladesh</ext-link>.</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mall</surname><given-names>R.K</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Sungkar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2017</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Effect of climate change on agricultural crops</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal Current Developments in Biotechnology and Bioengineering</italic></source>
<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-444-63661-4.00002-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madhuri, Tewari</surname><given-names>H.R</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhowmick</surname><given-names>P.K</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2014</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Livelihood vulnerability index analysis: An approach to study vulnerability in the context of Bihar</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">J&#x000e0;mb&#x000e1;: Journal of Disaster Risk Studies</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <comment>Art. #127</comment>, <fpage>13</fpage> pages. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/jamba.v6i1.127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>K.J</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>K.H</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname><given-names>P.K</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Wiltshire</surname><given-names>A.J</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2018</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Food security outcomes under a changing climate: Impacts of mitigation and adaptation on vulnerability to food insecurity</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Climatic Change</italic></source>
<volume>147</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>), <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-018-2137-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Runtunuwu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Syahbuddin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2007</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>The alteration of precipitation and its impact on planting period</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Land and Climate</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salinger</surname><given-names>M.J</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2005</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Climate variability and change: Past, present, and future over view</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Climate Change</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>), <fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-005-5936-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saptutiningsih</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Suryanto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2011</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Hedonic price of flood effect on agricultural land</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Economics Journal of Emerging Markets</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <comment>viewed 23 March 2019, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://journal.uii.ac.id/JEP/article/view/2322/2121">https://journal.uii.ac.id/JEP/article/view/2322/2121</ext-link>.</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaitchik</surname><given-names>B.F</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Foltz</surname><given-names>J.D</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2016</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Agroecosystem specific climate vulnerability analysis: Application of the livelihood vulnerability index to a tropical highland region</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Mitigation and Adaptation Strategies for Global Change</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>39</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11027-014-9568-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30197559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>., <name name-style="western"><surname>Meigh</surname><given-names>J.R</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Fediw</surname><given-names>T.S</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2002</year>, &#x02018;<chapter-title>Derivation and testing of the water poverty index phase 1</chapter-title>&#x02019;, <comment>Final report</comment>, <publisher-name>Department for International Development</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UNDP</collab></person-group>, <year>2007</year>, <source><italic toggle="yes">Human development report 2007/2008: Climate change and development</italic></source>, <publisher-name>UNDP</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>US EPA</collab></person-group>, <year>2015</year>, <source><italic toggle="yes">Climate impacts on agriculture and food supply</italic></source>, <comment>viewed 17 April 2019, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://19january2017snapshot.epa.gov/climate-impacts/snapshot-help.html">https://19january2017snapshot.epa.gov/climate-impacts/snapshot-help.html</ext-link>.</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>N.J</given-names></name>. &#x00026; <name name-style="western"><surname>Good</surname><given-names>J.W</given-names></name>.</person-group>, <year>2004</year>, &#x02018;<article-title>Vulnerability of port and harbour communities to earthquake and tsunami hazards: The use of GIS in community hazard planning</article-title>&#x02019;, <source><italic toggle="yes">Article in Coastal Management</italic></source>
<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>269</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08920750490448622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>