<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate</div>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the variable importance rankings and partial dependence plots for individual predictors (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), WAH distribution during spring migration was largely predicted by 4 climatic variables (winter precipitation, PET, fall temperature, and snow-free date) all of which help to determine snow conditions across the region during migration. Winter precipitation and PET were important predictors in both spring and fall, and migrating caribou were predicted to occur in areas with low to moderate levels of winter precipitation and moderate PET. The importance of potential evapotranspiration in all of the seasonal models highlights a strong association between the WAH and broad-scale abiotic factors that determine PET across the region, including temperature, humidity, solar radiation, wind, and biomass. This association corresponds with other results that demonstrated increasing herd size during positive (warm) phases of the PDO and a decreasing population during periods of low (cool) PDO [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. Areas in Alaska with the lowest PET occur primarily north of the Brooks Range and on the Seward Peninsula, compared to the warmer, drier conditions more common to interior Alaska. Likewise, most of the WAH range coincides with an area of northwest Alaska that receives moderate winter precipitation (50–120 mm) as compared to the higher totals found at the highest elevations or in the ranges of other arctic caribou herds. Areas receiving moderate amounts of fall precipitation or cool mean annual ground temperatures were also associated with caribou distribution in fall, corresponding to a similar area encompassing the northern Seward Peninsula, western Brooks Range, and western coast where caribou occur during fall. At the local scale, when posed with a range of available conditions in the Brooks Range, caribou were predicted to occur in valleys or west-facing ridges, where PET was higher and snow cover was shallower than higher elevations and on east facing aspects.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier snow free dates were also highly predictive of caribou in spring, whereas a longer growing season was predictive of caribou in fall. In contrast to PET and winter precipitation trends which vary primarily across wider scales, the tight correspondence between early snow free date and areas predicted to have been repeatedly used by caribou in spring is apparent at a much finer local scale (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>]. Snow cover has previously been shown to affect the timing and habitat selection of migrating caribou as they seek out patches of emergent forage where snow has melted [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>]. Caribou have evolved exceptionally efficient locomotion such that the energy required to move is exceeded by the amount of forage they are able to obtain from new patches of high quality forage [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>]. However, sinking through deep or crusted snow increases energy expenditure exponentially, so encountering such conditions during migration could cause delays that result in phenological and geographic mismatches during calving that could ultimately lead to starvation. This may explain why caribou were not predicted to occur in areas of late snow melt (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>d) and were predicted to travel closer to the coast in spring (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>) on wind-packed snow or sea ice. To avoid poor snow conditions, spring migration is often constricted into areas where animals develop packed trails that tend to follow windswept terrain that hardens snow [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>] and aids locomotion or other areas with low snow accumulation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Caribou also selected areas of tussock tundra and areas with tall shrubs during migration (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>) but did not select forested habitats. Tall vegetation can impede movements, reduce visibility and increase snow depth, which may account for caribou selecting tussock tundra during spring migration. This explanation runs counterintuitive to the predicted selection for tall shrubs, however. Tall shrubs tend to occur in riparian valleys, where caribou were often predicted to occur, so selection for this tall cover type could be coincident with other suitable environmental conditions in Brooks Range valleys. The winter model also showed caribou using areas with less than complete or shallow snow cover (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>f). Caribou may be using areas which tend to be snow free longer in fall and spring, and which have lower relative snow depths in winter, providing them with better traveling conditions and more accessible forage. Our models predicted WAH caribou to occur in areas where moderate precipitation and relatively warmer temperatures lead to earlier snow melt, and we surmise that these combine to minimize thermodynamic and nutritional stress throughout the year.
 </p>
</sec>
