<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We posit that given the influence of climate variables in our models, that rapid changes in these processes will play outsized roles in determining the trajectory of caribou in the future. Increased climatic volatility and annual shifts in migratory patterns of the WAH underscore the need to allow caribou to select among a variety of habitats in order to find the most suitable conditions in a given year or season. Strong links between caribou distribution and interacting trends in snow, PET, growing season, and sea ice are apparent in our models. As the volatility in these and other climate effects (e.g., increased fire frequency and shrubification) grows, WAH caribou migration patterns are also likely to become more variable in the future. We surmise that this could result in changing phenologies (e.g., delayed migration, increased spatial variability in calving) as a means of coping with decreasing climatic reliability. As such, the success of harvesting caribou near any given rural community in a given year may correspondingly decrease in the future as well [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It remains unclear whether WAH caribou are capable of adapting to rapid climatic changes or whether future predictions of a distribution contraction will occur. Some potential changes, like longer growing seasons, may aid caribou by allowing for increased energetic intake, while others, like the loss of sea ice from Kotzebue Sound and deeper, crusted snow, could make travel costlier near the coast. As a species, caribou have thus far largely adapted to an evolving suite of highly variable and changing ecological conditions, including new predators [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>], changing habitat and forage quality [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>], and the development of portions of their range [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. It is possible that they may also be capable of adapting behaviorally to the threats of accelerating climate change and further limited development. However, the rates of environmental change in the Arctic are unprecedented and the ability of WAH caribou to adapt at these rapid rates should not be taken for granted.
 </p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we did not explicitly measure displacement, our models predicted the majority of WAH to occur in areas at least 20–100 km from roads and communities during all seasons except fall (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This could have important implications for the herd should any of the numerous proposed roads be constructed in northwest Alaska, especially those that would bisect the documented migratory areas in the Kobuk Valley (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>). Proposed roads extending from the communities of Ambler to Kotzebue, Noatak or the Red Dog Mine could have major consequences for caribou because these corridors would bisect all of the main migratory regions. While a proposed road to access the Ambler mining district stops short of much of the core WAH migratory area, it would cut directly through a core area used by caribou during the winter (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>f). In addition to potential disruptions to migration [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>] and the effects of windborne dust [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>] resulting from industrial traffic, an associated increase in hunter access to migratory areas could have far more detrimental effects on caribou populations, should this or other new roads be publically accessible (see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>]). Given the extensive climatic and anthropogenic disturbances threatening the Western Arctic Herd, we echo the call for comprehensive management planning that recognizes and conserves a variety of migratory areas to buffer caribou from environmental volatility as part of a long-term persistence strategy for caribou in the Arctic [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
