<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human infrastructure</div>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also showed that caribou were negatively associated with roads at distances less than 20–100 km away during the spring, calving, insect-avoidance, late summer, and winter seasons (although there was no correlation in fall), and distance to roads was among the top predictors in each of these models (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). These trends may reflect the tendency of the WAH to occur in the geographic space between the Delong Mountain Transportation System (also known as the Red Dog Mine road), the road north of the community of Kobuk, and roads emanating from Nome. However, during the insect relief season, some WAH caribou were predicted to use habitat near the coast, placing them in an area closer to the Red Dog Mine road, yet they were still not predicted to occur within 20 km of the road (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>e). This distance towards the upper end of previously reported zones of influence by roads that extended 14–23 km [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>]. Wilson et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] found that 30% of WAH caribou traveling within 15 km of the Red Dog Mine road were delayed by an average of 33 days during fall migration. Moreover, Leblond et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>] documented a road-displacement distance of 5 km and that a majority of their study population failed to cross a highway which lead to a loss of &gt; 50% of their range. Our models are consistent with this and other research that show caribou tending not to occur near human infrastructure, including roads, communities, and developed areas [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>]. For example, the density of females and calves in the CAH was shown to be low within 4–6 km of linear features within the herd’s calving area, although the herd did not avoid the area during other seasons [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our models indicated a dissociation between caribou and towns during the spring, calving, insect-relief, and winter (but not fall) seasons by 20–75 km (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), with distance to community ranked among the top 10 predictors of 37 in all models (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The predicted tendency for caribou to occur away from communities may be best exemplified by their absence around the community of Noatak, but is also visible in the immediate vicinities of Kobuk, Kiana, Noorvik, Selawik, and Kotzebue in models and telemetry records (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>). Their predicted lack of occurrence near Noatak could also be related to spruce forests found in the valley, as caribou were predicted in treeless land cover types in much greater proportion relative to their availability (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). However, the potential exists for caribou to be disturbed by noise from motorized equipment and airstrips that can be detected as far as 30 km of communities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>], and begs further investigation. In contrast, caribou were weakly associated with communities within 75 km distance during fall, suggesting either that caribou are either less concerned with disturbances during this season, or that following preferred habitat during the southward migration brings them closer to more communities. In other words, communities may have historically been intentionally placed within preferred fall migratory areas, but shifting migratory patterns may be altering this association. While the passage of caribou may still continue in the vicinity of anthropogenic disturbances, the timing and duration of migration can be delayed in developed areas, and broader effects on population health have not yet been demonstrated [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
