<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pooled seasonal models</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GPS collars recorded locations of WAH caribou from September 7, 2010 to November 30, 2017 resulting in a total of 465,807 occurrence records. Seasonal models, pooled across years, predicted regions of use by the WAH during the spring, calving, insect-relief, late summer, fall, and winter seasons. Based on AUC scores and overall percent correct, model accuracies ranged from ‘good’ to ‘excellent’ in their predictions of the spatio-temporal distribution of caribou in the WAH. Environmental predictors were ranked to show the most influential predictors in the model (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and partial dependence plots Figures 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) indicated ranges of each predictor that were associated and disassociated with the predicted distribution of caribou in the models (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Partial-dependence plots for the top 6 predictors, mean winter precipitation (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), potential evapotranspiration (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), mean fall temperature (
     <span class="bold">c</span>), mean snow-free date (
     <span class="bold">d</span>), distance to nearest road (
     <span class="bold">e</span>), and distance to mean maximum sea ice extent (
     <span class="bold">f</span>), for the pooled (2010–2017) spring caribou distribution model
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40462_2019_162_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Partial-dependence plots for the top 6 predictors, potential evapotranspiration (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), mean annual ground temperature (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), mean length of growing season (
     <span class="bold">c</span>), mean winter precipitation (
     <span class="bold">d</span>), mean fall precipitation (
     <span class="bold">e</span>), and distance to nearest road (
     <span class="bold">f</span>), for the pooled (2010–2017) fall caribou distribution model
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40462_2019_162_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modeled seasonal distributions of Western Arctic Herd caribou. Models were developed for the spring (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), calving (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), insect-relief (
     <span class="bold">c</span>), late-summer (
     <span class="bold">d</span>), fall (
     <span class="bold">e</span>), winter (
     <span class="bold">f</span>) seasons during 2010–2017. Warm colors indicate areas of high predicted Relative Index of Occurrence (RIO), cool colors indicate areas of low predicted RIO
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40462_2019_162_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spring model predicted the presence of caribou in a belt of land around the coast of Kotzebue Sound and a band extending northward across the Kobuk River between the communities of Noorvik and Kobuk (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>a). Three swaths of predicted presence diffused north over the Baird Mountains and across the breadth of Noatak National Preserve (NOAT). Areas of high RIO extended over the Brooks Range across numerous mountain passes before converging on the North Slope. The overall accuracy for the best pooled spring model was deemed ‘good’ (AUC = 0.95; Overall Accuracy
  <sub>test</sub> = 88.45%; Mean Residual
  <sub>2018</sub> = 0.39 ± 0.30) at a presence/absence threshold of 0.61. Winter precipitation was the most important predictor in the spring distribution model (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), which predicted caribou to occur in areas with more than 70 mm of winter precipitation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a). The mean precipitation in areas predicted as presences was 84.8 mm versus 66.8 mm in absence areas. PET (potential evapo-transpiration) was also highly predictive of the presence of caribou (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), especially in areas where the mean evaporative potential was 220–350 mm, but the 2 were negatively correlated when PET exceeded 350 mm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>b). The mean evaporative potential in predicted presence areas was 293.0 mm versus 360.0 mm across absence areas. Models also generally predicted caribou to occur in areas where mean decadal fall temperatures were above − 4 °C (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>c) and where average snow melt occurred between April 20 and May 10 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>d). Local snow melt timing varied by as much as 2 months across ridgelines in areas frequented by caribou. The model showed a tendency for caribou to be negatively associated with roads at distances within 40 km (mean = 89.7 km; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>e), and positively correlated when between 40 and 200 km from roads (mean = 128.8 km). Caribou were also predicted to occur within 100 km of the mean spring sea ice extent (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>f). Distance to community was ranked as the 8th-most important predictor (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and the model predicted caribou to occur beyond ~ 20 km from the nearest community (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S1). Mean distance to community was 77.7 km for predicted presences as compared to 58.9 km for predicted absences.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial projections predicted the majority of animals during the calving season to be concentrated in ~ 25,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> of land surrounding the upper Colville River (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>b). Areas of high RIO trailed to the south as far as western Kotzebue Sound but in decreasing breadth and intensity. The calving model accuracy was deemed ‘excellent’ (AUC = 0.98; Overall Accuracy
  <sub>test</sub> = 93.53%, Mean Residual
  <sub>2018</sub> = 0.05 ± 0.06) using a balanced presence/absence threshold of 0.62. During the calving season, the presence of caribou was most-closely associated with PET (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), especially in areas where PET was less than 260 mm (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S2). Caribou were predicted to occur at distances of 470–600 km from the mean September sea ice extent (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S2). Distance to roads was also influential in the calving model (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) with caribou tending to occur in areas 100–250 km from roads (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S2). Distance to communities was ranked 7th in relative importance (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and the model predicted caribou to be negatively associated with communities at distances less than 80 km (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the insect relief season, models predicted nearly all caribou to occur north of the Noatak River, with most concentrated in an area near the coast but east of Point Hope (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>c). Two ‘tails’ extended on either side of the Colville River; 1 running along the north side of the DeLong Mountains as far east as Gates of the Arctic National Park and Preserve (GAAR), and the other farther onto the North Slope. Model accuracy for the insect-season model was ‘excellent’ (AUC = 0.98; Overall Accuracy
  <sub>test</sub> = 93.84%, Mean Residual
  <sub>2018</sub> = 0.09 ± 0.06) at a balanced threshold of 0.75. The most important predictor of high RIO values in the model was PET (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), which was directly correlated with caribou in areas with an average evaporative potential of &lt; 225 mm (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S3). Precipitation was also important (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and directly related to high RIO in areas receiving an average of &gt; 85 mm in fall (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S3). There was also a disassociation between human infrastructure and caribou during the insect season, where caribou were not generally predicted to occur within 20 km of roads or within 53 km of communities (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>e, Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S3). Distance to the coast also influenced the model (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and indicated a roughly inverse linear relationship between caribou and the coast, with caribou predicted to occur in areas more than 70 km from the Bering Sea (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S3).
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the late-summer season, the model predicted caribou over a broad area extending from the DeLong Mountains to north of the Colville River (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>d). Longitudinally, the area reached from east of Point Hope nearly to the community of Anaktuvuk Pass in the central Brooks Range. Other areas predicted as presences included much of NOAT and the northwestern portion of GAAR. The best model for the late summer season (AUC = 0.97; Overall Accuracy
  <sub>test</sub> = 87.02%, Mean Residual
  <sub>2018</sub> = 0.11 ± .06) had ‘good’ accuracy using a balanced threshold of 0.75. The most important environmental variable in the late-summer model was fall snow-day fraction (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) with caribou tending to occur in areas where snow occurred on the ground more than 70% of days in fall (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S4). Winter precipitation was also influential in predicting caribou and was positively related to presences in areas averaging more than 55 mm in winter (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S4). PET was somewhat less predictive in this model but was correlated with caribou presence in areas where average annual PET was 200 mm – 300 mm (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S4). Caribou were also predicted to occur in areas at least 40 km from roads (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S4). Winter snow day fraction was somewhat important (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and corresponded with the presence of caribou where snow was typically on the ground more than 90% of winter (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S4). Distance to communities ranked 7th in relative importance (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and was positively correlated with predicted caribou occurrence from 12 to 144 km away (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S4).
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial distribution of the fall model shows wide geographic variation across predicted presence areas (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>e). The core distribution during this period was predicted to occur from near the community of Kobuk in the north, to the south and west around the margins of Kotzebue Sound, to Bering Land Bridge National Preserve (BELA). Other areas with high RIO included a swath along the western boundary of Kobuk Valley National Park (KOVA) to Kiana and to the east of Kotzebue Sound, a second band ran along the coast from Wainwright to Kotzebue, while other predicted presence areas were scattered across the eastern half of NOAT and the North Slope (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>e). The pooled fall model predicted the presence of caribou with ‘good’ accuracy (AUC = 0.91; Overall Accuracy
  <sub>test</sub> = 83.44%; Mean Residual
  <sub>2018</sub> = 0.30 ± 0.13) using a balanced threshold of 0.47. A combination of numerous predictors contributed to the model, but several climatic factors were most important (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The top variable, PET, was predictive of caribou in areas where average annual evaporative potential was 225–365 mm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>a). The mean evaporative potential in presence areas was 294.5 mm versus 368.9 mm in absence areas. The occurrence of caribou was also strongly associated in areas where mean annual ground temperatures were between − 2 °C and − 5.5 °C (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>b). Growing season length was also highly predictive of caribou in fall in areas with between 130 and 150 days (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>c). Fall and winter precipitation were both influential in the model, with caribou predicted to occur in areas with between 90 and 145 mm of precipitation in fall and between 44 and 125 in winter (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>d-e). Roads were ranked 6th (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and at distances less than 180 km away, there was no clear association with predicted caribou presence and roads in fall (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>f). The mean distance to roads in predicted presence areas was 116.6 km as compared to 88.0 km in absence areas. Distance to communities was somewhat positively associated with caribou at distances less than 75 km (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S5) and the mean distance from communities was 63.2 km for predicted presences versus 60.4 km for predicted absences. The geographic niche of WAH caribou in fall was also weakly associated with minimum September sea ice 450–660 km away (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S5).
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In winter, models indicated that the highest predicted RIO were concentrated in BELA and eastward across the Seward Peninsula (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>f). However, sporadic clusters of predicted presences also occurred throughout GAAR, NOAT, Cape Krusenstern National Monument (CAKR) and across the western North Slope. The winter model predicted presences with ‘excellent’ accuracy (AUC = 0.97; Overall Accuracy
  <sub>test</sub> = 92.40%; Mean Residual
  <sub>2018</sub> = 0.12 ± 0.09) using a balanced threshold of 0.65. Winter snow-day fraction was the dominant environmental predictor in the model (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and was negatively associated with the presence of caribou in areas where snow was typically on the ground more than 99% of days in winter (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S6). Other predictors including distance to roads, distance to mean minimum sea ice, PET also contributed to the model’s prediction of caribou (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Predicted RIO was higher when caribou were between 130 and 215 km from the coast (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S6), whereas caribou were not generally predicted to occur within 38 km of roads (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S6). Distance to community was ranked 6th in importance (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) by the model which predicted caribou to occur at distances between 45 and 108 km from communities, but the 2 were negatively associated outside of this range (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S6).
 </p>
</sec>
