<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0055" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transportation of seedlings</div>
 <p id="par0120" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The on-site GHG emissions of diesel consumption for seedling transport was calculated via the following formula Eq. 
  <a rid="eq0070" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#eq0070">(14)</a>.
  <div id="eq0070" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">(14)</span>NGTS
   <span class="italic">
    <sub>t</sub>
   </span> = EF
   <sub>D</sub> × QDTS
   <span class="italic">
    <sub>t</sub>
   </span> × 10
   <span class="sup">−3</span>
  </div>where NGTS
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>t</sub>
  </span> is the GHG emissions for seedling transportation in the 
  <span class="italic">t
   <span class="sup">th</span>
  </span> year (Gg C), and QDTS
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>t</sub>
  </span> is the diesel consumption for seedling transportation in the 
  <span class="italic">t
   <span class="sup">th</span>
  </span> year (t). The calculation for QDTS
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>t</sub>
  </span> is the same as that in Eq. 
  <a rid="eq0065" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#eq0065">(13)</a>, and the weight of the seedlings to be transported was determined using the following formula Eq. 
  <a rid="eq0075" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#eq0075">(15)</a>.
  <div id="eq0075" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">(15)</span>QS
   <span class="italic">
    <sub>t</sub>
   </span> = (SW
   <sub>1</sub> + SW
   <sub>2</sub>) × PD × SA
   <span class="italic">
    <sub>t</sub>
   </span> × 1/2 × 1.05 × 10
   <span class="sup">−6</span>
  </div>where QS
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>t</sub>
  </span> is the weight of the transported seedlings in the 
  <span class="italic">t
   <span class="sup">th</span>
  </span> year (t); SW
  <sub>1</sub> is the weight of the seedlings with bare roots (50 g·plant
  <span class="sup">−1</span>); SW
  <sub>2</sub> is the weight of the seedlings in containers, which is 200 g·plant
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (the weight factors of both types of seedlings were obtained by consulting Chengde Liyuan Garden Engineering Co., Ltd. and Beijing Sannong Agriculture Development Co., Ltd.); PD is planting density, plants·ha
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, which is obtained by reference to the technical regulations for afforestation and reforestation [
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">27</a>]; and SA
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>t</sub>
  </span> is the area of artificial afforestation and reforestation in the 
  <span class="italic">t
   <span class="sup">th</span>
  </span> year (ha). Our study assumes that seedlings with bare roots and seedlings in containers each account for 50% of the total afforestation and reforestation area. The damage rate of seedlings during transport, and thus the replanting rate, is assumed to be 5%, so a factor of 1.05 is applied.
 </p>
</sec>
