<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33319-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explore ecological and evolutionary relationships, a model‐based approach was used following phylogenetic reconstruction using the maximum‐likelihood analysis on 27 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> sequences isolated from western Himalayan birds as well as 46 reference sequences downloaded from MalAvi database (Bensch et al., 
  <a rid="ece33319-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33319-bib-0010">2009</a>). The 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> phylogeny included 12 sequences isolated from western Himalayan birds and 27 reference sequences downloaded from MalAvi database (Bensch et al., 
  <a rid="ece33319-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33319-bib-0010">2009</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon majoris</span> (GenBank accession number: 
  <span ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AY393804" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AY393804</span>) served as an outgroup in both phylogenies. The maximum‐likelihood tree was constructed using Bayesian phylogenetics as implemented in BEAST version 1.4.3 (Drummond &amp; Rambaut, 
  <a rid="ece33319-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33319-bib-0022">2007</a>) using the most appropriate substitution model (GTR + G) according to the Akaike Information Criterion implemented MEGA version 5.2 (Tamura et al., 
  <a rid="ece33319-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33319-bib-0057">2011</a>). We present a maximum clade credibility tree using a relaxed molecular clock approach (Drummond &amp; Rambaut, 
  <a rid="ece33319-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33319-bib-0022">2007</a>). Rates of substitution were drawn from a lognormal distribution, and Yule prior was used for branching rates. We conducted two runs of 20 million generations, each with sampling conducted every 1,000 generations. 
  <span class="italic">Tracer</span> (Rambaut &amp; Drummond, 
  <a rid="ece33319-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33319-bib-0045">2003</a>) was used to assess convergence, and whether two chains were mixing and whether the estimated sample size (ESS) for each parameter was sufficient (ESS &gt; 200) to obtain robust parameter estimates. Four million generations were discarded as burn‐in from each run, leaving a posterior distribution of 32,000 trees.
 </p>
</sec>
