<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the 1935–2011 period common to all TRW data, we compared climate, tree growth and the growth-climate relationship from the earliest, 1935–1964, to the most recent, 1982–2011 period. This was done to attempt to find a causal link between juniper growth and climate response to observed changes in climate during the 20
  <span class="sup">th</span> century. For the climate data, anomalies of temperature and precipitation from each CRU grid point were used to produce means for the most contrasting seasons: for winter (previous year December to current year February, pDJF) and summer (June–August, JJA). Changes in juniper growth were calculated by averaging the TRW indices over the two 30-year periods. We used Pearson correlation statistics to investigate the growth-climate relationships for the full 1935–2011 and the two shorter (1935–1964, 1982–2011) sub-periods. This was done using monthly climate values, as well as the seasonal temperature means and precipitation sums. Additionally, both TRW chronologies and climate data were high-pass filtered using a 10 year spline to investigate the growth-climate relationship during summer in the high-frequency domain.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine spatial and temporal changes in winter and summer climate, annual tree growth, and climate-growth responses to summer temperature and precipitation, the period differences were entered as point data in ArcMAP 10.1 [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref043">43</a>]. Areas with no data coverage were estimated by an inverse distance weighted (IDW) interpolation technique [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref044">44</a>]. This method fills missing cell values using a distance-weighted average of neighboring points. The power parameter 
  <span class="italic">p</span> defines the influence of the weights. We used twelve neighboring points and 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 2, to give higher weights to closer points and progressively decreasing weights to distant points.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of elevation on the climate data, the so-called lapse rate, was neglected in the study since we used interpolated grid point data. However, changes in tree growth and climate sensitivity were analyzed as a function of altitude.</p>
</sec>
