<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results of the present study were gained for beech seedlings, however also could have direct implications for adult beech stands, because the shallow soils and the shallow root system do not allow adult beech to tap much deeper water and nutrient resources than beech seedlings. Furthermore, the competitive performance and establishment of beech seedlings is of importance for the rejuvenation of the stands. By highlighting the relationships between drought, N cycling and beech N seedling nutrition, our work provides pointers to developing mitigation options to increase beech seedling resilience and adaptation potential in a changing climate. In intensively managed forests and plantations, nutritional limitations could be counteracted by fertilization to increase levels of bioavailable N in soil. However, trade-offs such as undesired rapid hydrological NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup> leaching in the joint aquifers of limestone karst systems would need to be quantified. The associated risk for nitrous oxide losses may remain small due to high nitrous oxide reductase activity in such soils, converting nitrous oxide into harmless dinitrogen [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Another option to promote beech seedling establishment and performance is silvicultural reduction of the stand density. This treatment increased soil water availability via increased throughfall and reduced competition for water in coniferous stands [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. A further alternative is mixing beech stands with deep-rooting trees such as oak. Such mixing approaches appear to improve water balance of soil and beech via hydraulic lift of water from deeper aquifers followed by water efflux from oak roots [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>], and thus may increase the resilience of beech seedlings to climate change in stands mixed with deep rooting tree species.
</p>
