<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43" class="p">The BASE-future and PHYS-future simulations use CLM4-CN to simulate the response of the global dust emission rate 
 <italic class="italic">Q</italic> to climate changes until the year 2100. We forced CLM4-CN with a preindustrial atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration (285 ppmv) until it reached equilibrium. Specifically, we cycled the first 25 years (1948–1972) of the Qian et al.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup> NCEP/NCAR reanalysis data set (temperature, precipitation, winds, etc.), and repeated this procedure until the 25-year average of the net ecosystem exchange fluxes fell below 0.05 PgC/year
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>. After CLM4-CN was spun up in this manner, we conducted model experiments from the year 1798 until 1972 following the procedure outlined in ref. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>. That is, we cycled the 1948–1972 Qian et al.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup> reanalysis data, combined with historical reconstructions of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>, nitrogen deposition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>, and land cover change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. From 1973 onward, we forced the model with the same 1948–1972 repeat cycle, but with climate anomalies added, and with the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration increasing following the SRES (Special Report on Emissions Scenarios) A1B scenario. These climate anomalies were taken as the average difference between the monthly mean of fully coupled simulations with the ECHAM5/MPI-OM model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup> and the 1948–1972 reanalysis, and are described in more detail in ref. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>. The 25-year cycling of reanalysis data was done to create realistic interannual variability in the simulated future climate, which is important because of the non-linear dependence of dust emissions on wind speed, soil moisture, and vegetation. We consequently report model results in terms of 25-year running averages. We used output from ECHAM5, because Mahowald
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup> showed that this model predicts changes in the global desert area that are characteristic of the mean of the models that participated in Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 3 (CMIP3). The ECHAM5 simulations were forced with the A1B scenario, as part of the CMIP3. Since the historical reconstructions of nitrogen deposition and land cover change only extend until 2005
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>, and since we desired to separate the response of the dust cycle to climate changes from other anthropogenic changes such as land use, we kept nitrogen deposition and land use from 2006 onward constant at 2005 levels. Note that human land use changes can also substantially impact dust emissions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. Since such changes are the direct result of human actions, they constitute an anthropogenic forcing, not a feedback, and are thus not included in our simulations. For both the BASE-future and PHYS-future simulations, the global tuning constant for dust emissions was set such that the global dust emission rate over the period of 1995–2011 equaled that for the same period for the BASE-AERONET and PHYS-AERONET simulations, respectively, for which the global tuning constant was calibrated to AERONET observations (see above and ref. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>).
</p>
