<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Other studies discover variability in farmer perceptions of climate change across regions, crops, and other factors, such as length of experience with farming. For instance, Diggs [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] found significant difference in belief that climate change is occurring between farmers surveyed in Colorado and North Dakota, with the former being more skeptical, but also that those with less farming experience are more likely to believe that negative events such as extreme drought were becoming more severe. Safi et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] discovered that over sixty percent of surveyed farmers in Nevada believe climate change is taking place, but less than thirty percent believe it is due to human activity or that it is having an effect on current adverse environmental conditions. Schattman et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] reported that Vermont farmers have some of the highest reported beliefs that climate change is occurring among studies conducted nationwide (eighty percent), whereas Marchant and Bosc [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] report some of the lowest levels of belief in Mississippi (under twenty-five percent). (For thorough reviews of these and more studies on farmer attitudes towards climate change, see [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]). Arbuckle et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0207237.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] state close to seventy percent of Iowa farmers believe in climate change, but less agree that it will have any sort of impact on their own farm operations (thirty-five percent). Such studies reveal the range in attitudes towards the reality of climatic change among farmers, as well as its impacts on their own production platforms.
</p>
