<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Proxy data and palaeoclimatic modelling shows that dry spells during HS 1 considerably increased the extension of dry areas from the South-East to the rest of Southern Iberia, only leaving small refugia of more favourable conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. During HS 1, the extent of drylands increased particularly during the summer months (June to August), turning the major part of Southern Iberia into devastating ultrahyperarid areas. We hypothesize that this process had a crucial impact on the settlement system in Southern Iberia, but only insignificant impact on Northern Iberia. Two major site clusters during the Solutrean in the South, which both represent core areas of human settlement, are located in the South-East and in Central Portugal. While the south-eastern cluster shrinks dramatically during HS1 going into the Magdalenian, the cluster in Portugal remains mostly intact. Higher humidity values from to the nearby Atlantic coast could be a reason for this. Although summed probability curves of radiocarbon dates show an increase of Magdalenian data in the South after HS1, this is not matched by site numbers, which still point to a low presence of human groups. We hypothesize that at least the eastern cluster and the large dry areas of the southern Meseta were considerably affected by dry climatic conditions during HS 1, preventing early colonization by Magdalenian groups due to shortage in water, prey, and natural vegetation for nutrition for both humans and animals. The most arid area of Southern Iberia is located in the South-East; as the coastal stretching of settlement areas is a major weakness for mating networks, strong dry spells during HS 1 could easily have interrupted these networks along the coast and have caused a breakdown of regional populations. In addition to this, we hypothesize that the significant increase of Magdalenian sites in the north-eastern regions of Iberia could have been caused not only by a spread of the settlement areas from the northern Atlantic coast to the East, but also by a retreat from the south-eastern areas along the Mediterranean coast to the North.
</p>
