<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58562-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combined Effects of SMP Feedbacks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58562-fig-0002">2</a> shows the fraction of land areas that feature combinations of the spatial and temporal SMP feedback metrics (top row) and heterogeneity feedback metric (bottom row) in observations and models. Results of the same analysis using different significant levels are presented in the 
  <a rid="grl58562-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supinf-0001">supporting information</a> (Figures 
  <a rid="grl58562-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supitem-0001">S4</a> and 
  <a rid="grl58562-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supitem-0001">S5</a>). Only 5° × 5° boxes of which more than a third are land areas were classified as land are considered, and the ratio of land area is calculated with area‐weighted composition. Analyzing Ys and Yt in a combined way allows for a more comprehensive comparison of the prerainfall morning soil moisture conditions between observations and models. Additionally, with the consideration of Yh, we discuss possible mechanisms behind the commonly found combinations of SMP feedback metrics in both observations and models and how they potentially contribute to the spatial and temporal structure of precipitation persistence.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="grl58562-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Fractions of land area with different combinations of the spatial and temporal soil moisture‐precipitation feedback metrics (top row) and the heterogeneity feedback metric (bottom row) in observations and models. Ys, Yt, and Yh indicate spatial, temporal, and heterogeneity metric, respectively. P stands for positive sign of the feedback metrics and N for negative. Subscripts in GLEAM
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">C</span>
    </sub>, GLEAM
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
    </sub>, and GLEAM
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">P</span>
    </sub> indicate the precipitation data set used to derive each of the soil moisture estimates.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="GRL-46-1861-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="alt-text">grl58562-fig-0002</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The combination of negative (hereafter, N) Ys and positive (hereafter, P) Yt occurs predominantly in the observations. While each observational estimate shows a similar fraction of land area, the regions where the combination appears vary across different observational data sets (Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supitem-0001">S2</a>, 
  <a rid="grl58562-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supinf-0001">supporting information</a>). An important implication of this combination (NYs‐PYt) is that the majority of the afternoon rainfall events occur when the whole event domain is anomalously wet, since the location of maximum afternoon precipitation occurs over a grid cell with positive soil moisture anomaly in the morning (PYt), while the surrounding grid cells have even higher soil moisture anomaly (NYs). Therefore, the dominant positive heterogeneity metric across all observed estimations (Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58562-fig-0002">2</a>, lower left) indicates high heterogeneity among positive soil moisture anomalies, which should be distinguished from high heterogeneity due to mixture of dry and wet soil moisture anomalies. The other dominant combination in observations is NYs‐NYt. This combination still reflects significantly more frequent afternoon rainfall occurrence over regions drier than their surroundings but also less precipitation persistence due to NYt. In addition, this combination does not reveal the large‐scale soil moisture condition in the entire event domain, unlike the former, and thus, there is larger uncertainty in how the positive Yh is driven. It should be noted that in Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58562-fig-0002">2</a>, the combination of positive spatial and positive temporal metrics (PYs‐PYt) also seems to appear relatively often. However, looking at the maps of the metrics (Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supitem-0001">S2</a>) reveals that this cooccurrence in fact stems from various, randomly distributed grid cells and does not cluster into consistent regions. Therefore, this signal appears not robust and should be interpreted with caution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In models, the combination of positive Ys and Yt (PYs‐PYt) appears as the most common and is, unlike in observations, also confirmed by the maps in Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supitem-0001">S3</a>. This combination indicates localized (grid scale) dry or wet persistence as it means that afternoon rainfall occurs more frequently over the temporally and spatially wetter regions. This is opposed to the observational estimates. PYs‐NYt is the second most common combination in the models. PYs‐NYt indicates that afternoon rainfall is more likely under dry soil condition and occurs over wetter regions in a given area. Thus, under this combination of feedbacks increase in precipitation likelihood might be only possible when there are sufficient drying down periods between the precipitation events, indicating a system with low precipitation persistence or high evaporative demands. The fraction of areas with different signs of Yh varies substantially across different models, but for each given model, the fractions of NYh and PYh are comparable. CNRM‐CM5 appears as the only model where fraction of land areas with negative Ys and significant Yt is larger than 10%. IPSL‐CM5A‐MR simulates dominantly positive signals in all three metrics.
 </p>
</sec>
