<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58562-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated spatial and temporal SMP feedbacks in nine GCMs stemming from the CMIP5 archive using three different metrics (Ys, Yt, and Yh), which quantify sensitivity of afternoon rainfall occurrence to morning soil moisture conditions compared to 12 observational estimates over the period of 1976–2011. We found dominantly positive spatial feedback metric (Ys) in all coupled climate models, contrasting to observations and consistent with the results of C. M. Taylor, de Jeu, et al. (
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0035">2012</a>), which were based on Atmospheric Model Intercomparison Project‐type simulations. The temporal feedback metric (Yt) in the models shows better agreement with observations, but with a larger intermodel spread. When interpreting Yt, one should keep in mind that the sign of the feedback metric might be partially caused by atmospheric persistence, which may induce spurious positive relationship between soil moisture and precipitation. The heterogeneity feedback metric (Yh) and Yt have similar spatial patterns in models, unlike in observations where Yh is dominantly positive. The combinations of spatial and temporal SMP feedbacks in models, mainly PYs‐PYt and PYs‐NYt, indicate that they might introduce more localized and stronger wet or dry persistence than the observations, where generally negative Ys is combined with positive Yh. The SMP feedback is an emergent property of climate models which is not parameterized and certainly influences simulated climate or weather phenomena. In particular, it reveals the spatiotemporal structure of precipitation persistence that could be favored in a given climate model. Thus, the results in this study may help to understand how land‐climate interaction in climate models contributes to errors in precipitation variability at different temporal scales that were identified in previous investigations (Langford et al., 
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0024">2014</a>; Moon et al., 
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0027">2018</a>), of which substantial parts are not explained by contributions from large‐scale variability.
 </p>
</sec>
