<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58562-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coupling Diagnostic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diagnostics to assess SMP coupling are mainly adopted from C. M. Taylor, de Jeu, et al. (
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0035">2012</a>) and Guillod et al. (
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0016">2015</a>). A set of three metrics, which assess the sensitivity of afternoon rainfall occurrence to morning soil moisture spatially, temporally and in terms of heterogeneity, are calculated for each afternoon precipitation event. In this section, we first provide a description of the methodology as applied to the observational data, and we then describe the differences introduced for the analysis of models at the end of this section.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each day, accumulated afternoon precipitation (12 p.m. to 12 a.m.) is analyzed. Locations of precipitation maxima (Lmax, more than 4 mm) are first identified. An event domain (Levt) is subsequently defined as 5 × 5 grid cells centered at the Lmax locations, and locations of minimum rainfall on that day within Levt are called Lmin. Grid cells with highly varying topography, water bodies or morning (6 a.m. to 12 p.m.) accumulated precipitation larger than 1 mm were masked out. The three metrics are then identified based on these locations as follows: The spatial metric Ys is defined as 
  <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">S</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mtext">Lmax</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">′</span>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="mo">−</span>
   <div class="msubsup">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">S</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mtext">Lmin</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">′</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, where S' is the morning (preevent) soil moisture anomaly obtained by subtracting the seasonal cycle .The subscript refers to the location where S' is taken. The seasonal cycle of soil moisture was calculated by applying 31‐day moving average filter to a multiyear daily climatology. In the case of multiple Lmins due to zero precipitation, 
  <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">S</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mtext">Lmin</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">′</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> was calculated as the average soil moisture anomaly at all corresponding grid cells. The temporal metric Yt is defined as 
  <div id="nlm-math-3" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">S</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mtext">Lmax</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">′</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>. The heterogeneity metric Yh is defined as standard deviation of the 25 values, 
  <div id="nlm-math-4" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">S</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mtext">Levt</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">′</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>. Only the convective seasons determined by latitude are considered for the analysis, which are May–September for the north of 23°N, November–March for the south of 23°S, and all months in the tropics.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to event samples that are metrics calculated for each event at the respective locations, we define a control sample as the same metrics at the same locations but from nonevent days from the same month of all years.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All events within 5° × 5° boxes are pooled together to assess the statistical strength of the mean metric value, which is determined by assessing whether the differences between the event and control samples are significantly larger (or smaller) than those generated by chance as follows: First, the climatology of the individual locations within the 5° boxes is removed by subtracting the long‐term mean of the values within the control and the event samples (pooled together from both samples for each location). Second, the difference between the averages of the event sample and the corresponding control sample (
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">δ</span>(
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</span>) = mean(
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</span>
  <sub>
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">e</span>
  </sub>) − mean(
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</span>
  <sub>
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">c</span>
  </sub>)) is computed, and its strength is determined by the corresponding quantile of the distribution of the same difference in each of 1,000 random samples. These samples consist of 
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">n</span> values (where 
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">n</span> is the size of the event sample) randomly selected from all values of the event and control samples pooled together (as a substitute for the event sample) and the remaining values within this pool (as a substitute for the control sample). Statistical significance of a positive (negative) feedback is claimed if the strength of 
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">δ</span>(
  <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</span>) is greater (smaller) than 0.9 (0.1). 5° boxes with less than 25 event samples were masked out as they cannot provide robust results.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The models and observations differ in terms of their spatial resolution. In addition, climate models consistently have an early initiation of afternoon rainfall compared to observations (Dai, 
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0005">2006</a>). To account for these mismatches, we follow previous assessments (C. M. Taylor, de Jeu, et al., 
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0035">2012</a>) and process observed and modeled data differently; time steps were used with a 3‐hr shift in models (9 a.m. to 9 p.m. for afternoon, 3 a.m. to 9 a.m. for morning precipitation, and 6 a.m. to 9 a.m. for morning soil moisture), and Levt consists of 3 × 3 grid cells around Lmax instead of 5 × 5.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As mentioned earlier, the comparatively coarse spatial resolution of climate models requires parameterization of convection and this might itself affect the SMP feedback. We note that in previous studies (C. M. Taylor, de Jeu, et al., 
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0035">2012</a>), the metrics chosen to assess the SMP feedback were additionally calculated at coarser resolutions from observations, which resulted in weaker but consistent sign of the metrics. We find similar results in the 
  <a rid="grl58562-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supinf-0001">supporting information</a> (Figure 
  <a rid="grl58562-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58562-supitem-0001">S1</a>), suggesting that the spatial resolution of the data on which the metrics are computed does not qualitatively affect the results. Nonetheless, the coarser spatial resolution of models compared to observations may cause the former to capture only the largest or most widespread events, while the observations capture many more smaller events. It should be noted that the metrics do not explicitly account for atmospheric preconditions (apart from the filter for morning rainfall, which ensures that rainfall was not already present in the morning), which might determine the preferred soil moisture condition or in some cases inhibit moist convection (Findell &amp; Eltahir, 
  <a rid="grl58562-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58562-bib-0012">2003</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
