<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Importantly, total body mass is typically greater in obese compared to lean children, resulting in a greater heat production and therefore evaporative requirement during similar absolute workloads. In addition, obese children typically possess a lower maximal aerobic capacity, and therefore, when exercising at the same intensity, obese children are achieving a higher absolute workload and heat production [
 <xref rid="B74-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Adipose tissue has a lower water content and lower specific heat compared to muscle (2.97 kJ·kg
 <sup>−1</sup>· °C
 <sup>−1</sup> versus 3.66 kJ·kg
 <sup>−1</sup>· °C
 <sup>−1</sup>), with less heat necessary to increase a specific mass of adipose tissue a given temperature. It is logical to assume that both children and adults with higher adiposity may therefore experience a greater 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> rise for a given heat production compared to lean individuals. Notably, the physiological impact of adiposity on thermoregulation and practical considerations for prescribing comparable workloads has recently been challenged [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. In adults, Dervis and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] eloquently demonstrated that during exercise in the heat, overweight or obese individuals experience a greater 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> increase versus those with lower body fat, independently of differences in mass and metabolic heat production [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. They further suggest that body fat percentage has a relatively small influence on 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic>, with independent influences on thermoregulatory function during exercise only with large differences (&gt;20%) between groups or individuals (e.g., obesity). Dervis and colleagues calculated (based on another authors data [
 <xref rid="B75-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]) that a 20% difference in body fat only elicits a ~3%–5% difference in whole-body mean specific heat, perhaps explaining the similarities between groups in some studies. Obese individuals pose a lower mean specific heat capacity compared to lean individuals, which, coupled with blunted sudomotor responses, may explain the greater 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> rise [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Prior studies have also suggested the insulative properties of adipose tissue may attenuate heat loss at the skin [
 <xref rid="B76-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], but this was not observed by Dervis et al. [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] and may only be relevant in cool conditions when SkBF is minimal and subcutaneous fat is of greater importance. Many of these biophysical principles may hold true in children but warrant further research to explore the independent effects of adiposity on thermoregulation, with appropriate physiological adult–child comparisons requiring workload adjustment for body mass and BSA to avoid systematic bias. 
</p>
