<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31" class="p">In conclusion, the fact that a certain comprehensive model does not show multiple solutions under the same external conditions does not automatically suggest that tipping points are not possible. This has two reasons: First, tipping points can remain hidden in a parameter range related to periodic forces that is not explored when varying one parameter (such as CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) alone. As Eisenman’s single column model above shows, the existence of multiple equilibria under fixed seasonal conditions in a model is a ‘smoking gun’ pointing to a strong positive feedback. Such a feedback indicates that the system is prone to tipping points even if the multistability is not apparent in the seasonally forced (non-autonomous) system. Changes in the insolation forcing (for instance due to changes in the annual cycle of cloud cover) can hence bring the system into a regime where abrupt changes are possible. The same can occur due to changes in the intrinsic relaxation time of the system, for instance related to the fact that the growth rate of sea ice depends on its thickness and hence the background climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>
 </sup>. Second, abrupt shifts can also occur in systems without multiple states. Specifically, the freezing point of water acts as a natural threshold for the formation of sea ice, making ice cover very sensitive on temperature in a certain regime and prone to reversible abrupt shifts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. The quasi-periodic changes in insolation related to Milankovitch forcing might therefore switch the Arctic back and forth between an ice-free and a seasonal ice regime (in analogy to the monsoon switches outlined above). A similar switch-mechanism determining the growth and melt of ice sheets has also been discussed as an explanation of ice ages during the Pleistocene
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">71</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
