<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">According to the IUCN Red List, the worldwide status of 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta</italic> is of least concern [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. However, in Japan, populations of the subspecies (
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic>) have already become extinct in some mountain areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. In the 1980s, the population of 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> was estimated at 3000 birds. In the northern part of Japan’s Southern Alps, the number of breeding pairs declined by ~ 50% from 1981 to 2004 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. In addition, there is concern that the grazing impacts of increasing Sika deer 
 <italic class="italic">Cervus nippon</italic> populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>], along with an increase in montane terrestrial predators, will negatively affect the flora and fauna of the alpine zone. As a consequence, the ranking of 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> was raised from vulnerable to endangered in the Japanese Red List revised in August 2012 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. On the basis of the law for the conservation of endangered wild fauna and flora species, the Ministry of the Environment introduced a program for the conservation of 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> in October 2012. In central Japan, the subspecies 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> inhabits the mountain alpine zone, which represents the southernmost limit of the global distribution of this species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> uses the Japanese stone pine (
 <italic class="italic">Pinus pumila</italic>), which is a dominant alpine zone shrub species, as nesting sites and shelters from predators. 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> mainly feeds in alpine fellfields and snowbed grasslands [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. Consequently, this species is highly dependent on alpine habitats, which are considered vulnerable to rapid climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Therefore, 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> is hypothesized to be influenced by changes to alpine vegetation due to global warming. Of particular concern in this regard is the prediction by Nakamura that most of the available habitat for 
 <italic class="italic">L. muta japonica</italic> would disappear if the annual mean temperature rises by 3 °C [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>].
</p>
