<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The impact of climate change on the world’s ecosystems and the cascading consequences for human societies is one of the grand challenges of our time (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>1</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>3</italic>
 </xref>). Agriculture and marine fisheries are key food production sectors that sustain global food security, human health, economic growth, and employment worldwide (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>4</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>), but are substantially and heterogeneously affected by climatic change (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>7</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>8</italic>
 </xref>), with these impacts being projected to accelerate as greenhouse gas emissions rise (
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>9</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>12</italic>
 </xref>). Policy decisions on mitigation and adaptation strategies require understanding, anticipating, and synthesizing these climate change impacts. Central to these decisions are assessments of (i) the extent to which impacts in different food production sectors can be compensated, (ii) the consequences for human societies, and (iii) the potential benefits of mitigation actions. In that regard, global vulnerability assessments that consider countries’ exposure of food production sectors to climate-induced changes in productivity, their socioeconomic sensitivity to affected productivity, as well as their adaptive capacity are certainly useful to define the opportunity space for climate policy, provided that food production sectors are analyzed together. Building on previous multisector assessments of exposure (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>13</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>14</italic>
 </xref>) and vulnerability (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>), our purpose is to move toward a global-scale analysis of human vulnerability to climate change on two major food sectors: agriculture and marine fisheries.
</p>
