<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mitigation potential of feeding legumes has been the subject of a substantial number of studies. Simulation results in one study showed that CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production is 28% lower with legume forage (alfalfa hay) as compared to grass (timothy hay) when expressed as a proportion of gross energy (GE) intake, and 21% lower when expressed relative to digestible energy (DE) [
 <xref rid="B176-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>]. These results are corroborated by multiple field studies, which also find lower CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> with pasture legumes for sheep [
 <xref rid="B177-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">177</xref>] and cattle [
 <xref rid="B178-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B179-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">179</xref>]. For example, Waghorn 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2002) found that when fed to sheep, a sulla/lucerne feed mixture produced just 19.0 g CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> per kg DMI compared to fresh pasture, which produced 25.7 g CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> per kg DMI. In a second trial, lotus produced just 11.5 g CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> per kg DMI, and by using polyethylene glycol binding to remove condensed tannins (CT), the researchers demonstrated that CT played an important role in this reduction [
 <xref rid="B177-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">177</xref>]. Condensed tannins not only lower CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production in sheep, but may also have other beneficial effects including improving wool growth and reducing intestinal worm burdens [
 <xref rid="B180-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>]. However, at least one study failed to find reduced methane production feeding white clover to sheep (Hammond 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011) [
 <xref rid="B181-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">181</xref>], and so more study is required.
</p>
