<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Inter- and intraspecific variation in body size with temperature (and latitude) that is generally consistent with patterns predicted by ecogeographical or biogeographical rules [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>], such as Bergmann’s Rule [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>], James’s Rule [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>], the Temperature-Size Rule [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>], and others, has been reported for a diversity of animal groups. These include vertebrates (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]), terrestrial invertebrates (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref081" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]), and marine invertebrates such as mollusks and crustaceans [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref082" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>] as well as two of the species studied here 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">analoga</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">braziliensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. However, few studies of marine invertebrates have examined macro-scale variability in body size of multiple species from the same coastal ecosystem that possess different feeding habits, microhabitats and life histories, as we have done here. Our finding that body sizes of a suite of ecologically important intertidal crustaceans are strongly correlated with sea-surface temperatures across latitudinal gradients, and for one species, across hemispheres, suggest that more general predictions of ecological responses to climatic variation for coastal ecosystems may be possible, with significant implications for conservation of these threatened ecosystems. In addition, the general lack of evidence supporting a strong role of biotic interactions, such as predation or competition, in structuring intertidal communities of sandy beach ecosystems reported to date [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], makes our results linking body size and life history patterns with environmental forcing more compelling.
</p>
