<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature-driven thermokarst lake dynamics</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rather than simulating individual lake life cycles of formation, expansion, drainage, and re-initiation of later generation lakes (e.g., ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>), AThaw quantifies the net effect of new lake formation and drainage in modelled lake areas (F
  <span class="sup">TKL</span>). We capture a wide range of uncertainty in net lake formation and drainage trajectories by varying two key model parameters: The maximum net lake area, F
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span>, and the optimum high latitude surface temperature increase, dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Model parameters for the maximum lake area extent (F
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span>) were chosen individually for the four AThaw soil classes to capture expected differences in the potential for future lake development (see Methane and CO
  <sub>2</sub> in newly-formed thermokarst lakes). However, the parameter that most strongly controls the dynamics of thermokarst lake formation and drainage is the temperature optimum, dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span>, the temperature at which the maximum lake area occurs. We prescribed a mean estimate of 5 °C for dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> (i.e., high latitude surface air warming above pre-industrial) and consider a full range of 4–6 °C in our model ensemble. This parameter choice is based on paleoenvironmental evidence of Early Holocene warming by a few degrees Celsius in Northern Hemisphere land areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span> which resulted in rapid and intensive thermokarst activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This range of dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> values was also chosen to capture the sensitivity of future surface ice-wedge melt to climate warming, since ice-wedge melt is a critical step in thermokarst lake formation and drainage. Increases in permafrost temperature, which typically mirror increases in air temperature, have been observed in many Arctic regions, with warming of up to 3 °C since the 1970’s in some of the coldest permafrost regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>. Permafrost warming is often accompanied by active layer deepening and increased ground-ice melt. Widespread surficial degradation of ice wedges and a significant increase in areas of water-filled polygonal troughs has been linked to climatic warming during the past few decades in northern Alaska, the Canadian Arctic Archipelago, and Siberia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Additional permafrost warming on the order of 2–3 °C anticipated by 2050 for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>, is expected to intensify permafrost and surface ice wedge degradation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, enhancing thermokarst. For RCP4.5, permafrost warming slows beyond 2050
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>, supporting AThaw ensembles of lower net thermokarst lake formation during the latter part of the century (Supplementary Figs 4 and 5). In contrast, extreme warming after 2050 for RCP8.5 is expected to heavily degrade permafrost, such that near-surface permafrost disappears entirely from many arctic regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. These conditions lend support to AThaw parameterization, which leads to net lake drainage in the later part of the century for RCP8.5.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In AThaw, warming above the temperature optimum in the 21st century is assumed to lead to a reduction in AThaw lake area due to increasing lake drainage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, until a prescribed minimum fraction F
  <span class="sup">TKLmin</span> remains. The minimum fraction of the landscape still covered by newly formed lakes, decreases from north to south
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. In northern, continuous permafrost regions, lakes in AThaw are prescribed to drain laterally as melting of the ice-wedge network in the surface surrounding lakes can create drainage pathways
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. Other mechanisms of lake drainage include bank overtopping, headward gully erosion towards a lake; and tapping of lakes by streams, rivers, or other water bodies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. Higher drainage potential in southern, discontinuous permafrost regions also encompasses internal drainage of lake water through open taliks that penetrate thin permafrost in groundwater recharge settings
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the 4–6 °C dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> range used in our modeling was prescribed based on paleoenvironmental evidence, historical observations, and modeling of future permafrost dynamics, we can consider the implications of using smaller or larger dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> values. Smaller dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> values would imply that the maximum area of thermokarst lake coverage would occur earlier in the century. This would result in a relatively larger AThaw increase to the PCF earlier in the 21st century and a lower AThaw contribution to PCF toward the end of the century due to more widespread drainage. If dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> aligned more closely with the range of simulated high latitude warming inferred from higher concentration pathways (e.g., dT′
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span> &gt; 6 °C), we would expect maximum thermokarst lake coverage (i.e., F
  <span class="sup">TKLmax</span>) to occur later in the century, less drainage of AThaw lakes during the 21st century, and a larger relative contribution of AThaw to end-of-the century PCF under stronger future warming.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is interesting to note that that while thermokarst-lake initiation and drainage rates are linked to climate, thermokarst-lake growth—the long process between initiation and drainage that results in most of the carbon release—has dynamics (e.g., talik growth, shore expansion) that once started become rather decoupled from climate due to strong linkage with local factors such as ground ice content and ice-layer thickness
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>
  </span>. Hence, thermokarst lakes are found across the entire range of Arctic climatic zones and permafrost temperatures as long as there is sufficient ground ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>
  </span>. A thermokarst lake on the New Siberian Islands has the same potential to release carbon as a thermokarst lake in Central Yakutia; the differences are largely not determined by climate (or RCP conditions) but by local conditions such as permafrost soil carbon and ground ice contents. Hence, either RCP scenario will result in more lakes (earlier or later) and both scenarios will have a similar emission magnitude linked to maximum lake areas, but relative to anthropogenic emissions, the thermokarst lake emissions from RCP4.5 will be more relevant.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Factors other than temperature that are not included in AThaw, but which can also affect thermokarst lake dynamics include natural and anthropogenic surface disturbance, precipitation changes, and local topography
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. However, since CMIP5 models consistently predict a moistening trend in the Arctic (i.e., an increase in precipitation relative to evapotranspiration)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>, an explicit accounting for predicted 21st-century precipitation and evaporation trends would reinforce rather than weaken the AThaw lake dynamics driven by temperature changes alone.
 </p>
</sec>
