<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The uncertainties regarding the alterations of the water‐saving strategies of plants exposed to high temperature go beyond the stomatal movements. In fact, the dynamic of 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>min</sub> rates in a scenario of increased temperature also represents an important gap in our knowledge. For most species, especially the nondesert ones, 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>min</sub> rates tend to show small variations at temperatures from 15 to 35°C, while temperatures above 35° induce a drastic increase in cuticle permeability and, consequently, in water loss (Schreiber, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0204" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Schuster et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0206" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). This abrupt increase in 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>min</sub> rates under a certain temperature threshold, also known as transition temperature (Schuster et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0205" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), can have a catastrophic effect on plants exposed to heat waves, especially under drought conditions, since the increase in water loss can significantly increase the tension in xylem vessels, which can result in a reduction in the time to HF (Cochard, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). However, despite the great impact that the increase in atmospheric temperature can have on 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>min</sub> rates (Bueno et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Schuster et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0205" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) and, thus, on plant survival (Cochard, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>), key questions regarding this topic remain. For example, we currently do not have enough information to answer to which extent plants acclimated to high temperatures can alter the physicochemical properties of their cuticle in order to increase the transition temperature. This kind of information is essential to improve the prediction about the impact that the increase in atmospheric temperature, especially in association with drought, will have on the composition of forest ecosystems worldwide (Cochard, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
