<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Projections of future climate change include higher mean temperatures, water deficit intensity, and more intense El Niño-Southern Oscillation events
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. How biological systems will respond to stress due to changes in temperature and moisture regimes is therefore paramount
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Forecasting the impact a changing climate will have on forest ecosystems is particularly important because they cover 30% of the land surface, support 80% of the world’s terrestrial biodiversity, and perform essential ecosystem functions and services such as carbon sequestration
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. These impacts may include reduced growth and increases in mortality
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Several recent studies in forests have investigated the stability of ecosystem functioning, such as growth or productivity, in response to drought
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span> and suggest that there may be a positive link to diversity.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we define stability as the ability of a community to defy change (i.e. resistance and resilience)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The basis for positive diversity-stability relationships is the insurance hypothesis. First proposed by
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> and refined by
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>, the insurance hypothesis posits that species richness can act as a buffer against fluctuations in the environment. A key mechanism underlying insurance is species asynchrony, i.e. that species may independently have different responses to similar environmental conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. How these species respond to environmental conditions may be driven by biological traits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> as well as demography
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, there may be more relevant aspects of diversity from which to discern diversity-stability relationships
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. In a recent study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, the authors found empirical evidence for decreased stability in certain functions from an analysis of species abundances in five different functional groups (i.e. decomposition, carbon sequestration, pollination, pest control, and cultural values) which they posit is due to a weakened insurance capacity. They claim that there is a higher risk of failure in these functions under future environmental perturbations, although they do not consider perturbations of higher frequency and magnitude. Incidentally, stress, defined as extreme environmental conditions which are detrimental to ecosystem functioning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, is largely ignored, both empirically and theoretically, in biodiversity-ecosystem functioning (BEF) research
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> although there are exceptions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multiple mechanisms may drive BEF relationships during stressful events
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Niche complementarity predicts that heterogenous environments lead to higher mortality in monocultures than in mixtures because resources are used more efficiently in mixtures than in monocultures thus mediating the community-level response to stress intensity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Complementary effects can also come from changes in the functional contribution of facilitative interactions among species. However, a stressful environment can also change the strength of per capita species interactions. Specifically, it is posited that the performance of more diverse communities improves relative to that of low diversity communities in stressful environments because of the emergence of interspecific facilitative interactions among individuals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Both species-specific (complementarity) and per capita (stress gradient hypothesis) mechanisms suggest a stronger impact of stress events on monocultures than on mixture communities.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Detection of community-level stress response has been inferred from measures of resistance and resilience to stress. Pimm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> defined resistance as the magnitude of change in a response variable during a perturbation and resilience as how fast recovery occurs following a perturbation. Subsequently, there have been many different mathematical interpretations of these measures. In particular, resistance and resilience have been interpreted as “components” of temporal stability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> (and references therein). A recent study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span> further proposes a bivariate framework for resilience in terms of normalized resistance and recovery metrics based on the undisturbed state in order to have a comparable measure of resilience between different systems. When introducing the concept of stress, including extreme climate events and tree stress response, individual variation becomes important and a new detection problem emerges. Therefore, separating the background variation in functioning from the signal due to stress means developing an approach to measure stability accounting for this variation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of trees to recover may be dampened by periods of stress such as drought or extreme heat
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. This loss of resilience or critical slowing down can push forests to the boundary of massive die-off
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Recently it has been shown using satellite data from evergreen tropical forests in South America, Africa, and Asia/Australia that slowing down may be driven by low levels of precipitation (i.e. mean annual precipitation values which are less than 1,500 mm ⋅ yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. There are many indicators which may infer slowing down
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Such indicators are related to the resilience, and in particular the shape of the basin of attraction, of the current state. As environmental drivers push the current state to a tipping point, the slope of the basin of attraction decreases and, consequently, resilience to small perturbations decreases
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. If one were to measure the temporal autocorrelation (TAC) at lag-1 of this state, it would approach 1 as consecutive states in time are closer to one another due to a flattened basin. However, lag-1 autocorrelation does not account for variation at higher lags; the power spectrum can show changes in the spectral properties of a time series before a transition. In other words, a power spectrum can determine how similar states are at higher lags by decomposing a time series into its component frequencies. Systems closer to a transition may exhibit spectral reddening (i.e. most of the variation in the series occurs at lower frequencies) because states tend to change slowly in time about this flattened basin. A particularly important question which, to the best of our knowledge, has not yet been explored in the literature is how diversity might impact slowing down. TAC and spectral reddening have the potential to provide novel insights to slowing down following extreme climate events.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we focus on the detection of stress response in forest communities. As our case study, we consider a long-running tropical tree diversity experiment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> and identify stressful events at the site from the standardised precipitation-evapotranspiration index
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> (SPEI). We study how growth and mortality along diversity gradients are impacted by extreme climate events based on bootstrapping of tree data to generate the statistics need to account for potentially large individual variability. We hypothesize that differences in growth along a gradient of species richness should manifest mostly during wet or dry extreme climate events. In other words, monocultures should have greater variability in their growth compared to higher richness mixtures during stress. We also predict that mortality will be higher in monocultures during intense spells of drought as a result of lower resilience than higher diversity treatments. To determine whether the hypothesized mortality for monocultures may indicate sudden massive die-off we compute the temporal autocorrelation at lag-1 and the spectral density of growth time series. To study the relationship between species richness and slowing down, we compare these indicators across diversity treatments. Specifically we expect monocultures to exhibit spectral reddening whereas the power spectrum should become more flat at higher richness. Our approach improves our understanding and our ability to quantify stability under stress for forest ecosystems, and gives momentum to the study of the relationship between diversity and slowing down.
 </p>
</sec>
