<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Studying Effects of Environmental Change in This System</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We study the effects of change of the environmental variables 
  <span class="italic">s</span> and 
  <span class="italic">r</span>. In general, environmental variables may undergo sudden shifts, gradual changes and stochastic fluctuations [
  <a rid="B31-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-biology-01-00639">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-biology-01-00639">32</a>]. For simplicity we here consider sudden shifts only, but by envisioning gradual or stochastic changes as a series of smaller shifts their qualitative effects can still be discerned from the results.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the environment changes, the population will no longer be at ecological and evolutionary equilibrium. In the short term, the population densities may increase or decrease, as may the fraction of young in the population. We record these two properties, along with the new selection gradient 
  <span class="italic">h</span>(
  <span class="italic">μ</span>) after the population density has settled on the new equilibrium. We assume however that evolutionary change, 
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, change in mean arrival time 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>, is slow compared to demographic responses, and therefore assume that it is not affected. 
 </p>
 <div id="biology-01-00639-f002" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Properties of the ecological and evolutionary equilibrium. The panels show how ESS timing of arrival (
    <span class="bold">A</span>–
    <span class="bold">D</span>) and the corresponding equilibrium population density (
    <span class="bold">E</span>–
    <span class="bold">H</span>) and fraction of young at equilibrium (
    <span class="bold">I</span>–
    <span class="bold">L</span>) depend on model parameters. When not varied as indicated by the graphs, the parameters under study are set to 
    <span class="italic">s</span> = −1, 
    <span class="italic">s
     <sub>A</sub>
    </span> = 0.5, 
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <sub>0</sub> = 3 and 
    <span class="italic">σ
     <sub>R</sub>
    </span> = 0.1. These values are indicated by the vertical line which thus represents the same parameter settings across panels. Remaining parameter values: 
    <span class="italic">r</span> = 1, 
    <span class="italic">S</span>
    <sub>0</sub> = 1, 
    <span class="italic">q
     <sub>c</sub>
    </span> = 1, 
    <span class="italic">v</span> = 0.5, 
    <span class="italic">σ
     <sub>S</sub>
    </span> = 0.4, 
    <span class="italic">k</span> = 0.5 (note that 
    <span class="italic">s
     <sub>J</sub>
    </span> = 
    <span class="italic">ks
     <sub>A</sub>
    </span>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="biology-01-00639-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
