<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Future Research on Eco-Evolutionary Dynamics in Phenological Shifts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conclude by highlighting some interesting avenues to continue studying phenological adaptation based on the eco-evolutionary approach presented here. While we above make some qualitative comparisons between the model and observed responses, logical next steps are to test the model predictions against a standardized data set for pied flycatchers in Europe and to parameterize the model using detailed data from a well studied population, as in e.g., 
  <span class="italic">Parus</span> spp. populations in the Netherlands [
  <a rid="B5-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-biology-01-00639">5</a>,
  <a rid="B36-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-biology-01-00639">36</a>] and in Britain [
  <a rid="B40-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-biology-01-00639">40</a>]. Most of the existing studies estimate changes in the food peak (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, estimations of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>) and it would be interesting to include estimations of changes in pre-breeding conditions (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, to estimations of 
  <span class="italic">S</span>) which has been done to a lesser extent (but see e.g., [
  <a rid="B39-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-biology-01-00639">39</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is also much scope for further enhancing the ecological realism of the model. One could for example include features from related annual routine models [
  <a rid="B16-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-biology-01-00639">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-biology-01-00639">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-biology-01-00639">18</a>], such as different stop over sites and more detailed physiology, into the framework. That would enable a more explicit modelling of the migration ecology and could shed light on how other factors than strong survival costs constrain evolution of early arrival. Many 
  <span class="italic">Parus</span> species and pied flycatchers compete for food and nestboxes [
  <a rid="B41-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-biology-01-00639">41</a>,
  <a rid="B42-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-biology-01-00639">42</a>] and this may affect phenological responses. It would therefore be interesting to include interspecific competition into the model. One shall also note that our model does not include breeding time as such. Our assumption of reproduction being a sigmoid function of arrival date means that only arrival in relation to the food resource peak determines reproductive success. In nature, breeding may be hampered by other factors than arrival time however, e.g., inappropriate cues [
  <a rid="B43-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-biology-01-00639">43</a>]. In other words, whereas suboptimal arrival necessarily confers suboptimal reproduction, optimal arrival does not guarantee optimal breeding. To address this question one could include breeding time as an additional trait into the model. Costs of early breeding relative to the arrival time, e.g., reduced resources or physiological costs for the female [
  <a rid="B23-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-biology-01-00639">23</a>], could then be represented in the model by reduced reproduction or survival.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our analysis we studied the ESS timing of arrival and changes in selection pressures following environmental changes. It is however possible to adapt the framework to create predictions on subsequent gradual evolutionary trajectories as well. One may then for example use the canonical equation of adaptive dynamics for mutation limited evolution [
  <a rid="B44-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-biology-01-00639">44</a>], or relax the assumption of a monomorphic resident population and include genetic variation, following a quantitative genetic approach [
  <a rid="B45-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-biology-01-00639">45</a>] or individual-based simulations [
  <a rid="B31-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-biology-01-00639">31</a>]. Note also the fitness function employed here by definition describe an adaptive landscape that can be studied to predict the likelihood of invasions of different traits following environmental changes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theories for the evolution of continuous traits under the influence of ecological feedback have developed rapidly over the last decades [
  <a rid="B28-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-biology-01-00639">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-biology-01-00639">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-biology-01-00639">30</a>,
  <a rid="B46-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-biology-01-00639">46</a>]. It has been argued that they are only just beginning to tap into their potential impact on ecology and evolution, and developing new and better applications is therefore the most important future direction [
  <a rid="B28-biology-01-00639" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-biology-01-00639">28</a>]. By developing a framework for studying demographic responses and phenological shifts in a changing climate we have not only taken a step in that direction, but also generalized and extended the theory for adaptation to changed seasonal environments.
 </p>
</sec>
