<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We here account for and compare the effects of temporal advancement of (i) the food peak 
  <span class="italic">r</span> only, (ii) the onset of spring 
  <span class="italic">s</span> only and (iii) the food peak 
  <span class="italic">r</span> together with the onset of spring 
  <span class="italic">s</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>). We consider, in turn, effects on selection pressures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>A–E), effects on population densities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>F–J) and effects on population structure (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>K–O). Each of these effects are studied for the range of populations with different historical baselines shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>. Each panel in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a> shows the effects of environmental changes on the property in the corresponding panel in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>. The relative sensitivity of the biological properties to the different types of environmental changes (i–iii) can be discerned by comparing the different effects (purple, blue and green lines in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>).
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Ensuing Selection Pressures after Seasonal Changes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An advanced onset of spring has a strong effect on selection compared to an advanced food peak when spring is already early (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>A), when winter survival is high (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>B), when productivity is high (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>C), when the resource peak is narrow (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>D) and with slow improvement of pre-breeding conditions (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>E). In these cases, the selection after only 
   <span class="italic">r</span> has changed is very small (solid lines are close to zero), and the effect of changing 
   <span class="italic">s</span> and 
   <span class="italic">r</span> jointly (green lines) is very similar to changing 
   <span class="italic">s</span> only (blue lines).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under most settings, advanced food peak leads to selection for earlier arrival (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>A–C,E). When the resource distribution is broad, however, advanced food peak can cause selection for a delayed arrival date (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>D). To understand this phenomenon, note that a changed resource peak affects the adaptive landscape not only by affecting the reproductive success of individuals for different arrival dates, but also by changing the reproductive success as such (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f001" href="#biology-01-00639-f001">Figure 1</a>A), which, via effects on population densities, can affect the competitive pressure. At evolutionary equilibrium there is a balance between selection for earlier arrival to increase reproduction and to avoid competition, and selection for later arrival dates to increase survival (cf. Equation 14). When the food peak advances, selection for earlier reproduction increases but population density decreases (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>I). Thereby also the competitive pressure decreases, which in turn weakens selection towards earlier arrival dates. The effect of a food peak shift on selection is relatively weak when the food distribution is wide, but the effect of population densities (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>I) and thereby on competition may still be substantial, which explains why later arrival can be favoured under these circumstances.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally we note that 
   <span class="italic">s</span> has the stronger influence on selection when the ESS is early (compare 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>A–E with 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>A–E). An early ESS can in turn occur either when spring is early or when competition is strong. An early spring leads to a large population, whereas strong competition occurs when the population density is large e.g., due to high winter survival, high productivity, narrow resource distribution or slow rate of improving pre-breeding conditions. Thus, strong influence of 
   <span class="italic">s</span> on selection is also predicted by large population size (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>F–J).
  </p>
  <div id="biology-01-00639-f003" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Selective and demographic responses to changed seasonal environments. The figure shows effects of shifts in the timing of the resource peak (
     <span class="italic">r</span>, purple), in the onset of spring (
     <span class="italic">s</span>, blue) and joint shifts in both these components of the seasonal environment (
     <span class="italic">s</span> and 
     <span class="italic">r</span>, green). The top row of panels (
     <span class="bold">A</span>–
     <span class="bold">E</span>) shows how selection gradients (from Equation 12) changes due to these environmental changes. Note that the selection gradient is equal to zero for the ESS prior to change. The middle row of panels (
     <span class="bold">F</span>–
     <span class="bold">J</span>) shows the relative population change, defined as 
     <span class="italic">n</span>
     <sub>2</sub>
     <span class="sup">*</span>/
     <span class="italic">n</span>
     <sub>1</sub>
     <span class="sup">*</span> where 
     <span class="italic">n</span>
     <sub>1</sub>
     <span class="sup">*</span> and 
     <span class="italic">n</span>
     <sub>2</sub>
     <span class="sup">*</span> denote the equilibrium density before and after the change, respectively. The bottom row of panels (
     <span class="bold">K</span>–
     <span class="bold">O</span>) shows the relative change in population structure, defined as 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>2</sub>/
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>1</sub> where 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>1</sub> and 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>2</sub> is the fraction of young at equilibrium before and after change, respectively. Absence of effect corresponds to selection gradients equal to zero, and the relative changes in population density and population structure equal to one. In cases where population density is zero after the change, the lines in corresponding panels are discontinued. The parameters 
     <span class="italic">s</span> and 
     <span class="italic">r</span> were reduced with 0.5 units in the scenarios in which they changed. Parameter values are otherwise as in 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>, and with the vertical solid line indicating the same parameter values across panels.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biology-01-00639-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Equilibrium Population Density after Seasonal Changes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The population grows when spring advances and declines when the food resource peak advances in all scenarios (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>F–J). The effect of changed resource peak is very small for many parameter settings investigated (purple lines are close to 1 in large parts of 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>F–J), however. In these cases, the model predicts a net increase when both factors advance, indicating that the positive effects on population density from the advanced spring overrides the small negative effects of an advanced food peak. More precisely, this occurs when the baseline ESS mean arrival time is early, which, as discussed above, is in turn predicted by large population densities. In cases where changes in 
   <span class="italic">r</span> have the larger effect, namely at low population densities in the baseline (cf. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>F–J), the changes in 
   <span class="italic">r</span> can be very strong however, and lead to strong reductions or even extinctions of the population (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>F–J).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Equilibrium Population Structure after Seasonal Changes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fraction of young in the population decreases both when the onset of spring advances and when the food peak advances. In many cases, the effect of changed resource peak is again very small, however (purple lines are close to 1 in large parts of 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f003" href="#biology-01-00639-f003">Figure 3</a>K–O). Effects of 
   <span class="italic">s</span> and 
   <span class="italic">r</span> on population structure follow the same pattern as the effects of 
   <span class="italic">s</span> and 
   <span class="italic">r</span> on selection and population density: high population densities (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="biology-01-00639-f002" href="#biology-01-00639-f002">Figure 2</a>F–J) predict more effect of 
   <span class="italic">s</span> than of 
   <span class="italic">r</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
