<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used the 
 <sc class="sc">biomod2</sc> platform (Thuiller, Lafourcade, Engler, &amp; Araujo, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) in R (R Core Team, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) to quantify species' climatic niches and subsequently project current and future spatial distributions. The following modelling algorithms were used: generalized linear model (GLM), general additive model (GAM), boosted regression tree (BRT) and random forest (RF). For applying these species distribution models (SDMs) with presence‐only data as provided by GBIF, we generated “pseudo‐absences” following recommendations of Barbet‐Massin, Jiguet, Albert, and Thuiller (
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>): for regression technique models (GLM and GAM), we used 10,000 randomly distributed absences, and for machine‐learning technique models (BRT and RF), we used a number of pseudo‐absences equal to the number of occurrences found in GBIF and selected outside a radius of 200 km around these occurrences. In the latter case, pseudo‐absence generation, and hence model calibration, was repeated 10 times per species to ensure that selected pseudo‐absences did not bias the final predictions. For all models, the weighted sum of presences equalled the weighted sum of pseudo‐absences. The predictive performance of the models was evaluated by means of the true skill statistic (TSS; Allouche, Tsoar, &amp; Kadmon, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>) based on a repeated (three times) split‐sampling approach in which models were calibrated with 80% of the data and evaluated over the remaining 20%. Evaluated models were then used for two different average projections of the spatial distribution of each of the 34 garden plants and their 173 native and naturalized congeners under current climatic conditions and the three climate change scenarios: one comprised the two regression‐based techniques and one comprised the two machine‐learning techniques. The probabilistic output of the two ensemble models was aggregated to a weighted mean, with weights determined by their respective TSS scores. Similarly, binary outputs of each of the two ensemble projections were generated based on a threshold that maximizes the TSS score (Liu, Berry, Dawson, &amp; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Liu, White, &amp; Newell, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and then aggregated to a conservative consensus ma; that is, 10′ resolution cells were only classed as climatically suitable to a species if both ensemble models agreed on the potential presence of the species in the cell.
</p>
