<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As the papers reviewed here are based on modeling techniques, they are subject to the general limitations of these techniques which have been extensively covered in the literature (Beaumont, Hughes, &amp; Pitman, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Senay, Worner, &amp; Ikeda, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Stoklosa, Daly, Foster, Ashcroft, &amp; Warton, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Wiens, Stralberg, Jongsomjit, Howell, &amp; Snyder, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). There are additional limitations specific to the application of these techniques to IAS in the face of climate change, which we describe here. A plethora of methods exist for modeling species distributions, and none of them is specific to IAS. Among the most used approaches, BioMod and MaxEnt are purely correlative models, and Climex also relies on the species distribution but has a more process‐based orientation (Elith, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Most studies in our dataset used correlative approaches rather than mechanistic models. We may expect that correlative approaches based on distribution only are more likely to overestimate the risk posed by IAS as they do not consider key processes like growth rate (reproductive strategy, phenology) that may limit the future distribution of species. Yet, we did not find differences between results from distribution only techniques and process and distribution techniques (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34098-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>B), although the number of studies based on process only is low. In this study, we focus on main trends regarding the predicted effect of climate change on IAS distributions, but further analyses to investigate how modeling choices (e.g., algorithm, resolution) may influenced those results are also needed. Therefore, the predicted species range changes is an estimation and do not exactly reflect the future realized distribution of the species. This would require also considering biotic interactions and potential resources.
</p>
