<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape scale</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape scale analyses included the four landscape structures and circular month variables (the cosinus and sinus of month values 1 to 12 scaled to the interval 0 to 2π) [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref058">58</a>] in relation to bird abundances (survey transect counts of all species pooled or summing only the Fringillidae or the 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> species separately), species richness and Shannon diversity (‘vegan’ R-package version 2.3–1. [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref059">59</a>]). Since sample sizes of single species were usually insufficient to model species-specific habitat selection separately, some species commonly visiting vineyards were pooled into the genus 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> (thrushes, 4 species: song thrush 
  <span class="italic">Turdus philomelos</span>, mistle thrush 
  <span class="italic">Turdus viscivorus</span>, fieldfare 
  <span class="italic">Turdus pilaris</span> and blackbird 
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>) and the family of Fringillidae (finches, 6 species: chaffinch 
  <span class="italic">Fringilla coelebs</span>, linnet 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis cannabina</span>, goldfinch 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis carduelis</span>, greenfinch 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis chloris</span>, citril finch 
  <span class="italic">Serinus citrinella</span> and serin 
  <span class="italic">Serinus serinus</span>). Species richness refers to the total number of species encountered per transect, also beyond the above two pooled taxonomic groups. Concerning landscape explanatory variables, proportions were arcsin-square root transformed and counts (densities) log transformed. We arcsin-square-root transformed proportions and log-transformed counts or other variables that were strongly right-skewed to improve model fit and to better comply with model assumptions. If the log works better than the untransformed variable, this indicates that the (biological) effect is rather multiplicative than additive, and vice versa. The arcsin-square-root-transformation stretches small proportion values. A difference of 1% grove between two transects A and B has not the same effect for birds if A: 50% to B: 51% or if A: 1% to B: 2%. In the first case, it represents a small, in the second case a large change. Our transects exhibited a grove cover between 0 to 11%. We used arcsin-sqrt instead of logit due to the zeros in our sample. Values were then standardized (mean = 0, standard deviation = 1) to improve convergence of the model fitting algorithms. In case of (continuous) explanatory variables showing a Spearman correlation coefficient |r
  <sub>s</sub>| &gt; 0.7, the biologically less meaningful variable was excluded from modelling. Because the number of potential models was large relative to our sample size due to various possible combinations of explanatory variables, the model selection procedure was conducted in two steps.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a first step, overall habitat preferences (complete data set from the whole year) were investigated using Generalized Linear Mixed Models (GLMMs) from the ‘lme4’ R-package (version 1.1–10, [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref060">60</a>]) with ‘transect’ and ‘date’ set as random effects to account for repeated visits per transect and per day. An observation level random factor was added to correct for overdispersion when necessary [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref061">61</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref062">62</a>]. Except for species richness and diversity, the log of the transect length was used as an offset [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref063">63</a>]. The potential influence of transect area on species richness was evaluated by including the linear, quadratic and cubic effects of the area in the models. Polynomial and linear terms were successively discarded when they met the following two criteria: their 95%-credible intervals included zero and the effect size of the squared effect was smaller than the one of the linear effect. In all cases, we ended up with species richness models without any area variables (note that the area of transects did not vary strongly). Time since sunrise (time as the transect visit started relative to the time between sunrise and sunset) was included as a covariate to correct for known variability in bird activity according to daytime [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref064">64</a>]. For abundance data and species richness, a Poisson model with a log-link function was used. For species diversity, a Gaussian error structure was assumed. In all full models, random slopes of the predictors were investigated but never improved the model fit according to the AICc (ΔAICc &gt; 20). Also, the additional variance explained by the model when random slopes were included was always near zero and maximally 0.2% (calculated by Δdeviance/null deviance). On the other hand, excluding transect as random intercept produced a much larger AICc value (Δ4.7 for the Shannon Index and &gt; 40 for the other outcome variables), hence transect was always retained as a random effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To generate the set of candidate models (differing only in the fixed effects), all possible combinations of the four landscape structure variables (
  <a rid="pone.0170176.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0170176.t001">Table 1A</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0170176.g001" href="#pone.0170176.g001">Fig 1A</a>) were fitted using the ‘dredge’ function of the ‘MuMIn’ R-package (version 1.15.6., [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref065">65</a>]). Model selection was based on Akaike’s Information Criterion corrected for small sample size (AICc; [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref066">66</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref067">67</a>]). Semi-variograms did not show substantial spatial autocorrelation in the data ('gstat' R-package version 1.1–3, [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref068">68</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a second step, each of the landscape variables figuring in the best model (with the lowest AICc; but always including the relative time since sunrise) of overall habitat preferences was used separately in combination with circular month variables to further investigate seasonal variation in habitat selection patterns [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref010">10</a>]. For this purpose, a set of candidate models including all possible combinations of the habitat variable and the cosinus and sinus of month (values 1 to 12 scaled to the interval 0 to 2π; hereafter “cosmonth” and “sinmonth”) were, again, fitted by means of the ‘dredge’ function and ranked according to AICc (possible combinations of predictors included models with interactions except for the interaction between cosmonth and sinmonth). A significant main effect of cosmonth can be interpreted as a difference in bird abundance between winter and summer (a positive coefficient estimate relates to a higher abundance in winter, a negative coefficient to a higher abundance in summer). Sinmonth analogously refers to increased numbers in spring (positive estimate) vs decreased numbers in autumn (negative estimate). A significant interaction between a habitat variable and cosmonth and sinmonth suggests a variation of the birds’ affinity for that habitat variable across seasons. Model assumptions were checked using residual plots (including autocorrelation among the residuals), overdispersion was assessed using the ‘dispersion_glmer’ function from the ‘blmeco’ R-package (version 1.1, [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref063">63</a>]). Semi-variograms did not show substantial spatial autocorrelation in the data ('gstat' R-package version 1.1–3, [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref068">68</a>]).
 </p>
</sec>
