<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Management recommendations and conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on these results, we first recommend to keep and rehabilitate hedges and patches of woody vegetation beyond the boundaries of the grape production area or between vine parcels, this in order to bolster avian biodiversity at the landscape scale. This is in line with the suggestion by Ceresa et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref066">66</a>] that even a slight increase in grove cover will benefit avian biodiversity. Although this measure is likely to be quite effective in intensively managed vineyard regions presently void of woody structures [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref051">51</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref082">82</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref083">83</a>], if the objective is to ensure the provision of a genuine pest control service by insectivorous birds, then more heterogeneous farmed matrices would be needed [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref084">84</a>]. When rehabilitating woody structures, a diverse species composition must be envisioned to provide a broader palette of resources [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref077">77</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another important beneficial measure, to be implemented within the vineyards themselves, is to allow ground vegetation to grow on roughly half of the ground surface, for instance within every second vine row or inter-row. This would represent the best option to sustain bird communities and populations the year-round. Whenever possible, another ideal option would of course be to remove grass mechanically instead of chemically from the «bare ground» row or inter-row, as requested by the organic and biodynamic cultivation protocols. This is because of the potential deleterious effects of herbicide application on plant and invertebrate communities [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref041">41</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref078">78</a>], with cascading effects upon avifauna [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref053">53</a>], as illustrated for birds in orchards [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref085">85</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref086">86</a>]. Yet, if half of the Valais vineyards would be half-covered by ground vegetation this would already represent an enormous change for biodiversity (currently 95% of the vineyards in the study area have a total mineral appearance due to extensive herbicide treatment [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref037">37</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Boosting biodiversity among vineyards will probably in the future represent an important asset of grape and wine production, notably in terms of ecosystem functioning and service provisioning (e.g. pest control, combatting soil erosion, enhancing soil fertility, etc.) [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref087">87</a>]. Thus, in addition to its intrinsic value for human recreation, the promotion of woody structures and grassy ground cover within and adjacent to vineyard parcels paves the way towards a more sustainable grape and wine industry. Similar issues and solutions might be valid for other agroecosystems, especially for other perennial crops such as orchards [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref006">6</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref071">71</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref085">85</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref086">86</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study confirms that multiple species and scales must be considered when dealing with the sheer complexity inherent to the conservation and restoration of farmland biodiversity. It also shows that the land sparing and land sharing concepts, rather than being mutually exclusive options, would greatly benefit from being applied as dual, complementary management schemes [
  <a rid="pone.0170176.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0170176.ref088">88</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
