<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results show that the potential impact of climatic change on European birds is a combination of: very rapid potential range displacements of large magnitude, generally in a northward direction; an average reduction in the extent of species' ranges; a limited mean overlap between species' potential future and present ranges; a general reduction in the number of species breeding in any area; and an increased extinction risk for some species, including a number of those endemic or near endemic to Europe.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">No comparable synthesis of modelling results for a large ensemble of species and at a continental scale, such as that presented here for the birds breeding in Europe, has previously been reported to our knowledge. Nonetheless, evidence from those studies that have been reported on other groups and in other regions 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Araujo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Araujo2">[41]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Midgley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Midgley1">[43]</a> suggests that our results can serve as a general model for other groups and continents. In terms of the development of adaptation strategies, the rate and magnitude of potential distribution shifts pose perhaps the most fundamental challenges. Conservation strategies have to-date relied heavily upon the identification and designation of protected areas (PAs); as others already have argued, however, climatic change is likely to result in some species being unable to persist in those PAs where they now occur 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Araujo3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Araujo3">[44]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Hannah1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Hannah1">[45]</a>, including in some cases perhaps the species whose conservation initially prompted the establishment of the PA. In addition, the rates of range-boundary adjustment required to track climatic change are, as we have shown, unlikely to be achieved except by a minority of species with ‘invasive’ characteristics. Furthermore, the majority of species will require relatively closely spaced habitat patches if they are to achieve even the relatively slow rates of range boundary adjustments that are more typical. Adaptation strategies thus must have at their core an extension of conservation measures and species' protection to the wider landscape. This is not to be taken as implying that PAs will be of any less value in future. Existing PAs, although they may lose some of the species for which they were designated, are likely to continue to protect important habitats from damage. Furthermore, their optimal management is likely to assist those species declining in a region because of climate change by delaying their disappearance and thus providing a continuing source of propagules/offspring for dispersal to areas with more favourable climate. For those species for which the climate of a region is becoming more suitable, existing PAs are likely to offer prime sites for colonisation and thus ‘bridgeheads’ for range extension. In these roles, among others, increases in the extent of existing PAs and the establishment of new PAs are likely to be beneficial in meeting future conservation targets, as Hannah 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Hannah1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Hannah1">[45]</a> have argued. However, whilst they will remain necessary, PAs will not of themselves be sufficient. If species are to achieve their potential range shifts then the wider landscape must provide ‘corridors’ 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Williams1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Williams1">[46]</a> or ‘stepping stones’ 
  <span class="italic">via</span> which species can cross the generally inhospitable matrix of heavily managed landscapes dominated by agriculture, intensive forestry and other human land-uses that are inimical to wildlife. Given the magnitude of potential distribution shifts, the individualism displayed by species with respect to the direction of their range shifts, and the inherent uncertainties in the projection both of future climatic conditions and of their impacts, ‘corridors’ will generally be a less viable option than ‘stepping stones’ because the latter, if appropriately implemented, can support range boundary shifts in any direction and of any magnitude across the landscape. Given, however, that in many parts of the world the magnitude of the range shifts not only will result in species complements of individual PAs potentially changing, but will result in species' distributions potentially shifting into countries where they are not currently present, the development of adaptation strategies must in most regions be undertaken as a collaborative international effort.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential reductions in the extent of species' ranges, and the consequent potential reductions in local species richness, represent a further challenge for biodiversity conservation. In this case, adaptation strategies must be designed to mitigate these potential changes as far as possible, principally through a combination of increases in the extent of PAs and the extension of species' protection measures to the wider landscape, including the ‘stepping stone’ habitat patches established therein. Projected climatic change during the present century also can be expected to increase extinction risk 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Thomas1">[13]</a>, especially for species with small range extents and those occupying climatic conditions that are unlikely to persist in the future. Identifying species at greatest risk and monitoring their distribution and population must form part of adaptation strategies, as must the implementation of management measures designed to reduce the negative impacts of climatic change where these are projected to occur. In the most extreme cases captive breeding programmes and/or deliberate translocations may offer the only hope for the most severely impacted species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ultimately, climatic change can be expected to cause massive re-arrangements of ecosystems comparable to those that characterised the transition from the last glacial to the post glacial 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Jacobson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Jacobson1">[47]</a>. Conserving biodiversity during such a period of ecological upheaval poses many new challenges and will require a considerable increase in the resources available, especially to achieve the increase in the area that is protected for wildlife that will be necessary in order to sustain species as they adjust their ranges in response to climatic change.
 </p>
</sec>
