<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The response to climatic change of species' distribution and abundance patterns arises from a combination of behavioural 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huppop1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huppop1">[1]</a>, genetic 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Davis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Davis1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Parmesan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Parmesan1">[3]</a> and spatial 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Parmesan2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Parmesan2">[4]</a> responses. However, evidence of species' responses to past climatic changes 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huntley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huntley1">[5]</a> leads to the expectation that the last of these responses – change in the form and/or location of the geographical range – will be of the greatest importance in relation to the rapid large-magnitude climatic changes predicted for the coming century 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Parmesan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Parmesan1">[3]</a>. In order to inform the development of adaptation strategies for biodiversity conservation, as well as to assess the potential consequences for ecosystem structure and function, quantitative estimates are required of the likely magnitude, direction and rates of these potential range changes. Such estimates can be made using models that relate species' distributions to present climate. To avoid reaching potentially spurious conclusions, however, estimates should be made as ‘ensemble forecasts’ obtained by modelling the potential future geographical ranges of a large number of species, preferably all of the members of one or more major taxonomic groups, under a variety of projected future climate scenarios. Because it is at extensive spatial scales that climate becomes more important than other factors, such as habitat availability, in determining species' patterns of occurrence, species' distributions also should be modelled at the scale of sub-continental or continental regions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to provide such a systematic, continent-wide assessment and quantification of the potential impacts of climatic change upon all species in a taxonomic group, we have applied a consistent approach to model the relationships between breeding distribution and climate for bird species breeding in Europe. Data recording breeding distributions of birds in Europe, as presence or absence in the cells of a 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 50×50 km grid, were obtained from the European Bird Census Council 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Hagemeijer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Hagemeijer1">[6]</a> and mean monthly climatic data for 1961–90 (‘present’) from a global dataset at 0·5°×0·5° resolution 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-New1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-New1">[7]</a>. Response surface models 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huntley2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huntley2">[8]</a> were fitted relating each species' distribution to three bioclimate variables, i.e. variables derived from the climatic data and known to be relevant to species' survival and/or performance. Robustness of the models was evaluated using a jack-knife approach, model performance being assessed using the area under the curve (AUC) of a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) plot 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Metz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Metz1">[9]</a>. Six climate scenarios for 2070–99 were developed from transient simulations made using three general circulation models (GCMs) for the IPCC SRES A2 and B2 emissions scenarios 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Nakicenovic1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Nakicenovic1">[10]</a>. Potential breeding range of each species for each future climate scenario was simulated using the response surface model. Our results are based upon 431 species for which useful models could be fitted (from a total of 496 species whose European breeding distributions have been mapped 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Hagemeijer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Hagemeijer1">[6]</a>; see Supplementary Material (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0001439.s001" href="#pone.0001439.s001">Table S1</a>) for a list of the 431 species included in the synthesis, and 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s2" href="#s2">Materials and Methods</a> for the criteria for selection of these species).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Centroids of potential future and simulated present ranges (the point about which the sum of the distances of all the grid squares in which the species is simulated as present is zero, i.e. the ‘centre of gravity’ or centre of mass of the species' simulated distribution; when calculating the sum, distances to the east and north are considered positive, those west and south negative), the geodesic distance (the length of the shortest path across the Earth's surface connecting two points) between and initial azimuth (the bearing relative to north (0°) at which the geodesic path departs from the initial point) from present to future centroid, the extent and overlap of potential future ranges relative to present ranges, and the magnitude and rate of range boundary shifts necessary to realise potential range changes were evaluated for each species. Using the results, we estimated the mean distance and direction of the potential spatial displacement of species' ranges, and also the mean rate of range boundary shift required to realise these potential range changes. We also estimated the mean potential change in range extent and the mean degree of overlap between present and potential future ranges. Because the extent to which species will achieve range changes depends upon the rate of climatic change relative to the rate at which species can extend their range boundaries 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Hill1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Hill1">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Warren1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Warren1">[12]</a>, potential future number of species per grid cell was estimated for ‘worst case’ and ‘best case’ alternatives 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Thomas1">[13]</a>, i.e. assuming either that species fail to disperse, persisting only where their potential future and present ranges overlap, or that species fully realise their potential future ranges. For species whose geographical ranges are restricted or almost restricted to Europe, we also explored the extent to which they may face an increased risk of future extinction as a consequence of climatic change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results provide quantitative evidence of the potential impacts of climatic change on European birds, but also have general relevance in relation to impacts of climatic change on European biodiversity as a whole. Such quantitative evidence can be used to inform the development of adaptation strategies for biodiversity conservation.</p>
</sec>
