<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data recording the breeding distribution of birds in Europe were obtained from the European Bird Census Council (EBCC) 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Hagemeijer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Hagemeijer1">[6]</a>. These data record the occurrence of breeding by each species in the 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 50×50 km squares of a Universal Transverse Mercator (UTM) grid, largely during the late 1980s. The data also distinguish between grid squares where evidence of breeding by a species was sought, but not obtained, and grid squares where such evidence was not sought. In our modelling, only the first of these were used as absences, the second category being considered as missing data and excluded from model fitting for that species. Data were available for all 496 species mapped by the EBCC. These include 17 introduced species, as well as a number of native species recorded from very small numbers of grid cells. An attempt was made to fit models for 453 of these species, including 10 introduced species; no attempt was made to fit models for species with very few (&lt;5) recorded occurrences or very sparsely scattered occurrences. For the synthesis we included the 430 native species, of the 443 that we attempted to model, that gave at least useful models, but excluded all but one of the introduced species; we included 
  <span class="italic">Phasianus colchicus</span> (Pheasant), however, because it was introduced to many parts of Europe at least several centuries ago and is likely to have extended its range throughout most or all of the climatically suitable areas of the continent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean monthly temperature, precipitation and cloudiness data for 1961–90 (‘present’) were interpolated for the mid point of each UTM grid cell from a 0·5×0·5° longitude×latitude global dataset 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-New1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-New1">[7]</a>. Using previously published methods 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huntley3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huntley3">[14]</a>, values for a variety of bioclimatic variables were calculated from these monthly meteorological data. Models were fitted using combinations of a range of variables representing each of the three principal climatic constraints upon the distributions of organisms in Europe, i.e. winter cold, growing season warmth and moisture availability. For the synthesis presented here we wished to ensure consistency of modelling approach; the three variables that most often gave the best fitting model across all species were therefore used to model all species. The resultant decrease in model fit for those species best fitted by a different variable combination was marginal in all cases. The three variables used were: mean temperature of the coldest month – as a measure of winter cold; annual temperature sum above 5°C – as a measure of thermal energy available during the ‘growing season’; and an estimate of the ratio of actual to potential evapotranspiration (Priestley-Taylor α) – as a measure of the extent of annual moisture deficiency. The latter variable was estimated using a ‘bucket model’ that takes as inputs daily values of precipitation, temperature and insolation; the first two were derived from the monthly mean values for the variables, whilst the latter was estimated from the latitude of the grid cell mid-point, the day of the year and the monthly mean cloudiness 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Cramer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Cramer1">[15]</a>. It should be noted that, in using these three variables, it is not assumed that they necessarily act upon the bird species directly, indeed in many cases it is clear that the causal paths 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Shipley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Shipley1">[16]</a> through which they operate must be indirect. Winter cold, for example, cannot have a direct effect upon migrant species that are not present in the region during that season, but nonetheless is often a strong constraint upon their distributions, probably as a result of its effect upon habitat or food availability. Similarly, it is unlikely that moisture availability acts directly upon many bird species, but by acting to determine the character of the vegetation it will in turn determine availability of habitats and suitable food items.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The modelling approach used was that of fitting species–climate response surfaces 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huntley4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huntley4">[17]</a>. For each species a response surface was fitted to the three selected bioclimatic variables; locally-weighted regression was used to fit the response surface 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Cleveland1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Cleveland1">[18]</a>. This approach was preferred for several reasons to the many alternatives, including the multiple model and ‘model ensemble’ approaches advocated by some 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Thuiller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Thuiller1">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Araujo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Araujo1">[20]</a>. In particular: the user makes an 
  <span class="italic">a priori</span> choice of the variables to be included, rather than the modelling method selecting variables from some larger set input by the user; no assumption is made about the general form of the relationship between a species' probability of occurrence and a bioclimatic variable; interactions between variables are readily accommodated and, because the fitting is local, can vary across the climatic domain as evidence from autecological studies indicates is often the case 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Pigott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Pigott1">[21]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Pigott4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Pigott4">[24]</a>. Any extrapolation of the fitted model is also made very conservatively, the species' probability of occurrence beyond the margin of the fitted response surface being rapidly asymptotic to the value at the margin of that surface. Because our aim was an overall synthesis using a large ensemble of species, rather than a focus upon individual species, the uncertainties arising with respect to individual species as a result of differences in future range predictions made by models fitted using different modelling approaches also are of minimal importance. Furthermore, in at least one case where such differences have been reported 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Pearson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Pearson1">[25]</a>, modelling was carried out at a spatial scale (1′×1′, i.e. 
  <span class="italic">ca</span>. 2×2 km) much finer than that which we are considering, and at which it is very likely that factors other than climate are playing a substantial role in determining the species' pattern of distribution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Models were fitted using all of the data (‘full’ models), and also using a very stringent jack-knife approach in which the data from all of the grid squares of each in turn of the 6° longitude×8° latitude ‘panels’ of the UTM grid system were excluded and the model fitted to the remaining data was then used to predict the species' occurrence in the omitted cells. Performance of both the ‘full’ and jack-knife models was assessed using the area under the curve (AUC) of a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) plot 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Metz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Metz1">[9]</a>. In order to express the probabilities of occurrence simulated by the models as simulations of presence or absence of the species, the threshold probability that maximised Cohen's κ 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Cohen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Cohen1">[26]</a> was determined 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huntley2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huntley2">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Huntley3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Huntley3">[14]</a>. Although it has been suggested, on the basis of tests with small artificial datasets (100 samples), that this is not the best approach for determining thresholds 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Liu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Liu1">[27]</a>, the results of that comparative study nonetheless led its authors to conclude that “
  <span class="italic">the best result will probably be obtained by any approach</span>” 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Liu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Liu1">[27, p. 392]</a>; furthermore, we are aware of no systematic study of alternative methods that has been performed for large datasets and across many species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AUC values for the ‘full’ and jack-knife models for all 453 species for which we attempted to fit models are illustrated in the Supplementary Material (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0001439.s003" href="#pone.0001439.s003">Figure S1</a>). Almost 89% of the ‘full’ models fitted gave AUC values &gt;0·9, indicating a ‘high’ model performance 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Swets1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Swets1">[28]</a>, whereas &lt;2% of the models gave AUC values ≤0·7. Of the jack-knife models, although only 28% gave AUC values &gt;0·9, a further 60% gave AUC values &gt;0·7, indicating that they were ‘useful’. The jack-knife model performance was most markedly reduced, compared to that of the ‘full’ model, for species with geographically restricted distributions; in such cases leaving out a ‘panel’ of grid cells often resulted in omitting a substantial proportion of the species' recorded presences. The synthesis presented here is based upon the ‘full’ models and includes the 430 native species that gave models with a ‘useful’ or ‘high’ performance and one introduced species (
  <span class="italic">Phasianus colchicus</span> – Pheasant), the model for which had a ‘high’ performance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The six potential future climate scenarios used were for the period 2070–99 and were developed from transient simulations made using three of the general circulation models (GCMs) included in the IPCC 2001 synthesis 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Cubasch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Cubasch1">[29]</a> and for two of the IPCC SRES emissions scenarios, the A2 and B2 scenarios 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Nakicenovic1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Nakicenovic1">[10]</a>. All three GCMs selected, GFDL_R30_c 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Knutson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Knutson1">[30]</a> (GFDL), HadCM3 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Gordon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Gordon1">[31]</a> and ECHAM4/OPYC3 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Roeckner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Roeckner1">[32]</a> (ECHAM4), have an equilibrium sensitivity for global mean temperature close to the mean for the nine models included in the IPCC synthesis 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Cubasch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Cubasch1">[29]</a>. With respect to their simulated precipitation, however, GFDL is relatively ‘wet’, the HadCM3 model is close to the mean for all nine models, and the ECHAM4 model is relatively ‘dry’. The A2 emissions scenario is one of continuing relatively rapid population growth and relatively high emissions, global CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions increasing to almost 5× 1990 values by 2100, whereas the B2 scenario is one of slower but continuing population growth and diverse technological change resulting in global CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions just over double their 1990 values by 2100. In each case the future climate scenario used to model the potential impacts was obtained by calculating the anomalies between the GCM simulated mean monthly temperature (additive anomaly) and precipitation (multiplicative anomaly) for 2070–99 and 1961–90 for the GCM grid cells, interpolating these to the UTM grid, applying them to the values interpolated for the UTM grid from the 1961–90 observed data, and finally calculating values for the three bioclimate variables.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential breeding range of each species for each future climate scenario was simulated using the species–climate response surface. Because this modelling approach does not attempt to simulate either the species' population dynamics or the dispersal of offspring, the two principal components of the process by which species' range shifts are achieved, the simulated range is not a ‘projection’; what is simulated is the species' ‘potential’ future range, i.e. the range it could occupy if it fully achieved the range shift necessary to occupy all of those areas with future climatic conditions equivalent to those in some part of its present range. In order to reduce any effects of model bias, future range extent (
  <span class="italic">R</span>) and overlap (
  <span class="italic">O</span>) were calculated relative to the species' range simulated in the same way for the present climate. The centroids of the potential future and simulated present ranges were calculated; geodesic distance (
  <span class="italic">D</span> – km) and initial azimuth (
  <span class="italic">θ</span>) from the present to the future centroid were computed using a Fortran program implementing the solution of Sodano and Robinson 
  <a rid="pone.0001439-Sodano1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0001439-Sodano1">[33]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each species and scenario, the range boundary shift necessary to realise the potential range displacement was estimated as the 90
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile of the distribution of geodesic distance between each grid cell simulated as newly suitable and the nearest grid cell simulated as suitable at the present. Given that this shift would need to be realised during the interval between 1961–90 and 2070–99, i.e. within 109 years, the rate of range boundary shift (
  <span class="italic">V</span> – km yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) was estimated by dividing the estimated range boundary shift by 109.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimates of the potential relative number of species per grid cell were made using only those grid cells for which presence or absence could be simulated for at least 395 of the species considered. Estimates were made for the ‘worst case’ (
  <span class="italic">N</span>′) and ‘best case’ (
  <span class="italic">N</span>) alternatives, i.e. assuming either that species failed to disperse and persisted only in the area of overlap between the potential future and present ranges or that species fully realised their potential future ranges.
 </p>
</sec>
