<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The higher numbers of both colonising and disappearing species (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b) and the stronger thermophilisation and aridisation signals (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>) at the uniform slope in the ecotone (block A) conform with the lowest elevation and closest connection to the alpine grassland zone. The different magnitudes of change among the four blocks reflect a gradient of increasing low‐temperature conditions and a thinning of species pools, and thus the importance of the particular position along the thermal gradient for the velocity of warming‐driven vegetation dynamics. This corresponds to recently observed effects over larger elevation ranges, where both species ranges and abundances changed more rapidly the lower a species was situated historically (Rumpf 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph15290-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). In the alpine–nival ecotone on Schrankogel, vascular plant species cover decreased in general (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph15290-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Interestingly, however, the cover remained stable in block A in the second decade, which could signal an early stage of infilling processes. Combined with the strong thermophilisation signal, this is likely to indicate an enhanced expansion of the more thermophilous species. By contrast, cover continued to decrease in the rugged blocks B and C, together with a significant thermophilisation (Table 
 <xref rid="nph15290-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S17</xref>), and thus was mainly driven by the dieback of subnival–nival species. Rugged terrain did not restrain the decline of cryophilic species, but may have provided a barrier to the expansion of potential competitors. We therefore suggest that factors other than competition, such as direct temperature effects on plant metabolism, have strongly contributed to the decrease in cover of the cold‐adapted, high‐elevation species.
</p>
