<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The DSSAT model has been widely used to simulate crop growth, soil water balance and soil C and N dynamics under different crop systems, management practices and various climatic conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. It has also been used to support crop management policy decisions and to simulate the effects of climate change on crop production [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. The DSSAT v4.6 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dssat.net/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://dssat.net/</ext-link>) is integrated with widely used Cropping System Models (CSM), a soil water balance module, and two soil nitrogen and organic matter modules (the CERES-based and CENTURY-based soil models) [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. The CSM can simulate the growth of 42 different crops as well as for fallow fields. The CENTURY-based soil module was found more suitable for long-term sequence simulations [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], and it was selected to simulate soil nitrogen and carbon dynamics in our research. The soil water balance module is based on the Ritchie equation to calculate daily soil water changes [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. In this study, the DSSAT Sequence program was used to simulate multi-year soil and water dynamics in addition to crop growth processes. This program is designed to analyze the long term effects of management practices or climate change on crop growth, soil water movement, soil carbon and nitrogen processes. Initial soil conditions are only required to be set up before the first year simulation, then soil water, carbon and nitrogen flows are transferred to the next season automatically [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. In this study, the calibrated DSSAT model was used to explore potential impacts of climate change on spring wheat and maize yields, soil water balance and nitrate leaching. Detailed model input parameters and calibration were introduced in SI (Tables A and B in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0207370.s001" class="xref">S1 File</xref>).
</p>
