<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The nineteen Worldclim (ver. 1.4) bioclimatic variables were chosen as candidate predictors (
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al., 2005</xref>), with 30 arc-seconds resolution, for both the current and the future scenarios (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2" class="xref">Supplement 2</xref>). We chose to use, for the model projections to 2050 and 2070, four different “Representative Concentration Pathways” (commonly known as RCPs) (
 <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meinshausen et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stocker, 2014</xref>), coded as 2.6, 4.5, 6.0 and 8.5. The RCP 2.6 predicts a low future increase in radiative forcing with respect to its current values, consequent on a constant decrease in greenhouse gases (GHG) emissions after a predicted peak in 2020, while, at the other extreme, the RCP 8.5 corresponds to the highest radiative forcing increase, with a non-stop GHG emission trajectory until 2100 (
 <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Riahi et al., 2011</xref>); 4.5 and 6.0 are intermediate RCPs, representing gradually-increasing values of radiative forcing. Even though the RCP 2.6 is by now acknowledged to be no more plausible (
 <xref rid="ref-78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sanford et al., 2014</xref>), it was implemented in the ensemble modeling framework as a “control scenario”, providing information on how more efficient measures against global warming could have influenced the future distribution of the target species. Since the variability in the future climate conditions inferred by different Global Climate Models (GCMs) is recognized as one of the most important sources of uncertainty in ENMs projections to future scenarios (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Garcia et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stralberg et al., 2015</xref>), we chose to perform model projections to 2050 and 2070 considering three different GCMs, namely BCC-CSM-1 (
 <xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wu et al., 2014</xref>), CCSM4 (
 <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gent et al., 2011</xref>) and MIROC-ESM (
 <xref rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Watanabe et al., 2011</xref>). Possible multicollinearity within the set of 19 candidate predictors was assessed through a correlation matrix (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-3" class="xref">Supplement 3</xref>) built in ArcMap 10.0 (Esri, Redlands, CA, USA); within pairs of variables with Pearson |
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>| &gt; 0.85, the one having less ecological importance to the species based on its autoecology (
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Di Cerbo, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lo Valvo et al., 2014</xref>) was discarded from model building (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Elith et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dormann et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brandt et al., 2017</xref>). Occurrences were spatially rarefied using the spThin R package, setting the thinning distance to 10 km (
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aiello-Lammens et al., 2015</xref>), and spatial autocorrelation among occurrence records was further tested through a Moran’s I test in ArcMap 10.0 (Esri, Redlands, CA, USA).
</p>
