<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">Local scale studies have noticed the effects of tree size (age) on RWI-climate relationship. For instance, older trees were found to be more sensitive to climate change than younger ones
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>, and large-DBH trees were more sensitive to drought than small trees
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Some authors also showed that the differences in RWI-climate relationships between DBH classes were greater than those between species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>. These evidences suggest that tree size or height may play a role in affecting RWI-climate relationship. As for the effect of stand density, forest thinning treatments have found that low density stands were less sensitive to droughts than high-density ones, because lower competition increases the resource availability of individual trees
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>. Based on these evidences, we had expected that forest height, maximum volume and stem density might play a stronger role in explaining RWI-climate relationship. However, our results showed that the importance of height, volume and density were low (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>). Studies that found clear effect of tree size (age) and density were generally conducted by comparing trees of a same species under a similar climate. Our results suggest that height and density are weaker modulators of RWI-climate relationship, when compared with the great gradients of climate and forest type. It should be noted that forest height and density entered most of the final models for the RWI-climate correlations, suggesting they still played a necessary role in addition to forest type and climate. Another possible reason for the weak effect of height and density found here may because our study area is a humid cold region without water deficit
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>. Existing evidences on the effect of tree size (age) and density were mostly found for the growth sensitivity to drought
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, we suggest that forest height and density may reveal a much stronger effect in arid regions, which need to be tested carefully in the future.
</p>
