<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36" class="p">Our method can be compared with a recent study
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Specifically, that work uses singular value decomposition (SVD) and multidimensional scaling (MDS) to map present-day CMIP5 spatial model output, and corresponding observations into a 2D parameter space. Associated with each point in this space is a prediction property of interest (in this case climate sensitivity CS, as well as future regional temperature and precipitation changes), interpolated between model points. The study then proceeds to sample randomly from all points in the space within the convex hull of the models, with denser sampling close to observations, to construct a cumulative distribution function for CS, and pdfs for temperature and precipitation changes. The work claims their pdfs are just “resampled histograms of model behavior”
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. However, we show using additional statistical analysis in Supplementary Note 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref> (for their “Gaussian” experiment), that their approach is similar, and also considers all model interactions under some limiting statistical assumptions. Specifically, by using deterministic interpolation they assume a degenerate conditional probability for CS given a value of parameters in the 2D space. In addition, convex hull of the models is clearly a crude approximation to the probability space. Even if questions remain about the justification for their statistical model, this means that Bayesian multi-model probabilistic projections accounting for all model interactions (2
 <sup class="sup">50</sup> − 1 ≈ 1.1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">15</sup> interactions) are already available to climate community. There are numerous differences between our work and that study. First, we consider dependence in both present-day and future model output. Second, we use time-series while that work uses spatial model output
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Third, we provide a statistical theory and method for finding non-exclusive hypothesis probabilities, and for prediction under such hypotheses that accounts for all hypothesis interactions.
</p>
