<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bayesian skyline plots</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our mitochondrial DNA analysis (see also 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Chakraborty2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Chakraborty2">[29]</a>) demonstrated that the three Arunachal macaque populations, Tawang, Upper Subansiri and West Siang, are geographically distinct. Macaque populations, being female philopatric, tend to exhibit such distinctive population genetic structure for maternally inherited mitochondrial DNA 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Modolo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Modolo1">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Kawamoto1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Kawamoto1">[20]</a>. Given this population structure, we treated each population separately for demographic analyses. Conducting a skyline plot with data from all three populations combined would result in a putatively incorrect signature of population expansion since these population show significant structure 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Chikhi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Chikhi1">[8]</a>. Of these three populations, the Upper Subansiri had the largest number of sampled individuals and was, therefore, taken up for further analysis. It must be noted, however, that we could not rule out the existence of local migrants and their influence on our results, as we could not sample all the populations in the intervening time periods.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Bayesian skyline plot for the Upper Subansiri population indicated a population expansion right after the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) at around 15,000 years before present (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097061-g002" href="#pone-0097061-g002">Fig. 2</a>). The population, however, appeared to have maintained a constant population size before this expansion. The plot also revealed a small reduction in effective population size in more recent times, right after the Middle Holocene (between 5,000 and 7,000 years before present; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097061-g002" href="#pone-0097061-g002">Fig. 2</a>), an indication that the distribution may have stabilised around the mean, given that there is no detectable change in trends for the upper bound. Finally, it must be noted that such horizontal distribution can also be drawn within the credibility interval and, as a result, the mean effect may represent a simple trend rather than true statistical evidence of actual demographic shifts.
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0097061-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0097061.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Bayesian skyline plot reconstruction of past population size trajectory for the Upper Subansiri population.</div>
   <p>The plot is the product of female effective population size (f
    <span class="italic">N
     <sub>e</sub>
    </span>) and mutation rate (
    <span class="italic">μ</span>) through time, assuming a substitution rate of 0.1643 substitutions per nucleotide per million years 
    <a rid="pone.0097061-Chakraborty2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Chakraborty2">[29]</a>. The lower and upper 95% confidence interval for the Upper Subansiri TMRCA is also shown. LGM, Last Glacial Maximum, approximately 18 to 20 thousand years before present.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0097061.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
