<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population demographic history</div>
 <sec id="s2d1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bayesian skyline plots</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used Bayesian skyline plots of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) to examine the past population dynamics of the study populations.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bayesian skyline plots allow for the estimation of effective population size, 
   <span class="italic">Ne</span>, through time without specifying population change models such as constant size or exponential growth. The age of ‘the most recent common ancestor' or TMRCA of each clade 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Chakraborty2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Chakraborty2">[29]</a> – Tawang: 0.12 mya (95% Highest Posterior Density or HPD 0.05 – 0.21), Upper Subansiri: 0.46 mya (95% HPD 0.27 – 0.68) and West Siang: 0.89 mya (95% HPD 0.53 – 1.3) – were employed as priors for the three populations. Furthermore, we selected the HKY+Γ+I mutation model for the analysis with a mean HVS1 substitution rate of 0.1643 substitutions per nucleotide per million year (Myr) for the mean rate prior 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Chakraborty2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Chakraborty2">[29]</a>. We used BEAST, version 1.7 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Drummond1">[30]</a> for constructing the Bayesian skyline plots. Two independent runs were conducted for 10
   <span class="sup">7</span> steps, with a sampling of the parameters once every 10
   <span class="sup">3</span> steps. Ten percent of the samples were discarded as burn-in. The estimated sample size (ESS) for all parameters was found to be above 200 at the end of each run, indicating good convergence of the Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulations. The independent runs were combined using LogCombiner, version 1.5.4 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Drummond1">[30]</a>, with resampling every 10
   <span class="sup">5</span> steps. After combining all the MCMC runs, the ESS for all parameters was observed to be more than 200.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The EWCL (Ewens, Watterson, Cornuet and Luikart) method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Demographic events such as recent population bottlenecks are known to leave distinct genetic signatures in the distributions of allele size, expected heterozygosity and in the genealogy of microsatellite loci 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Piry1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Piry1">[33]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Goossens1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Goossens1">[9]</a>. Here, we used the allelic frequency spectrum, namely the number of alleles 
   <span class="italic">(n
    <sub>A</sub>)
   </span> and the expected heterozygosity 
   <span class="italic">(H
    <sub>e</sub>)
   </span>, to determine the patterns of genetic diversity expected for a demographically stable population 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet1">[32]</a>. We performed simulations in Bottleneck, version 1.2.02 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Piry1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Piry1">[33]</a>, for both the species separately, to obtain the distribution of 
   <span class="italic">H
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span>, conditional on 
   <span class="italic">n
    <sub>A</sub>
   </span> and on the sample size for each population and locus. These 
   <span class="italic">H
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span> values were then compared to those obtained from the real dataset. Three mutation models were used: the infinite-allele model (IAM), the stepwise-mutation model (SMM) and the two-phase model (TPM), with various amounts (70% to 95%) of single-step mutations 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-DiRienzo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-DiRienzo1">[34]</a>. Any departures from the null hypothesis were explained as departures from the model, including selection, population expansion or decline. Consistency across independent loci, however, was unlikely to be caused by selection but rather by demographic events. This approach allowed us to detect population size changes and confirm that the signal was consistent across mutation models. The demographic event, however, could not be dated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Approximate Bayesian Computation approach</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We further inferred the demographic history of the Arunachal macaque, based on microsatellite data, using the approximate Bayesian computation (ABC) approach 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Beaumont2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Beaumont2">[35]</a>, implemented in the programme DIY-ABC, version 1.0.4.46b 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet2">[36]</a>. This approach allowed us to choose a demographic scenario among many that best fits the data and infer the posterior probability distributions for the parameters of interest under this preferred scenario. The different steps of the ABC parameter estimation procedure 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Beaumont3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Beaumont3">[37]</a> are briefly described here.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared three demographic scenarios, graphically depicted in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097061-g001" href="#pone-0097061-g001">Fig. 1</a>. Scenario 1 consisted of a null hypothesis that assumed a population whose effective size (
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span>) remained stable over time. Scenario 2 assumed a population of size 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>A</sub>
   </span> that declined instantaneously to its current effective size (
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span>), 
   <span class="italic">T
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span> generations ago. Conversely, Scenario 3 assumed a population of effective size 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>B</sub>
   </span> that increased instantaneously 
   <span class="italic">T
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span> generations ago to reach its current effective size (
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span>). For Scenarios 2 and 3, we considered 
   <span class="italic">T
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span> to be between 20 and 4000 generations, during which time these events could have occurred.
  </p>
  <div id="pone-0097061-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0097061.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Possible alternative scenarios of the demographic history of the Upper Subansiri population.</div>
    <p>When tested using the ABC approach, Scenario 2 was best fit with the data (
     <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0097061-t002" href="#pone-0097061-t002">Table 2</a>). The details of each scenario parameterisation have been given in the Methods. The time-scale is indicated by the arrow on the left. T
     <span class="italic">
      <sub>1</sub>
     </span> ranges between 20 and 4000 generations. Time has been measured backward in generations before the present. Gen: Generation.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0097061.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the three models, we simulated one million datasets based on a demographic history that described the model, using the programme DIY-ABC. Some or all parameters that defined each model (such as population sizes, timing of the demographic events or mutation rates) were considered as random variables for which some prior distributions were defined, as shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0097061-t001" href="#pone-0097061-t001">Table 1</a>. For each simulation, the parameter values were drawn from their prior distributions, defining a demographic history that was used to build a specific input file for the DIY-ABC programme. Coalescent-based simulations were run to generate a genetic diversity for each sample, with the same number of gene copies and loci as those originally observed. Summary statistics (S) were then computed for the simulated datasets for each of the observed dataset (S*). Following the method of 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Storz2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Storz2">[38]</a>, a Euclidean distance, δ, was calculated between the normalised S and S* for each simulated dataset.
  </p>
  <div id="pone-0097061-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0097061.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Model specifications and prior distributions for demographic parameters and locus-specific mutation model parameters.</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone-0097061-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0097061.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="center" span="1"/>
      <col align="center" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Priors for the Demographic Parameters</td>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
        <span class="italic">N
         <sub>1</sub>
        </span>
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UN ∼ [50, 5000]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
        <span class="italic">T
         <sub>1</sub>
        </span>
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UN ∼ [20, 4000]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
        <span class="italic">N
         <sub>A</sub>
        </span>
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UN ∼ [10000, 70000]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
        <span class="italic">N
         <sub>B</sub>
        </span>
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UN ∼ [10, 5000]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
        <span class="bold">Priors for the Mutation Model</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Autosomal microsatellites</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEAN – 
        <span class="italic">μ
         <sub>mic</sub>
        </span>
       </td>
       <td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">UN∼[1×10
        <span class="sup">−4</span>, 1×10
        <span class="sup">−3</span>]
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAM – 
        <span class="italic">μ
         <sub>mic</sub>
        </span>
       </td>
       <td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GA∼[1×10
        <span class="sup">−5</span>, 1×10
        <span class="sup">−2</span>, 2]
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEAN – 
        <span class="italic">P</span>
       </td>
       <td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">UN∼[0.10, 0.30]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAM – 
        <span class="italic">P</span>
       </td>
       <td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GA∼[0.01, 0.9, 2]</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MEAN – 
        <span class="italic">SNI</span>
       </td>
       <td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">LU∼[1×10
        <span class="sup">−8</span>, 1×10
        <span class="sup">−4</span>]
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAM – 
        <span class="italic">SNI</span>
       </td>
       <td colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GA∼[1×10
        <span class="sup">−9</span>, 1×10
        <span class="sup">−3</span>, 2]
       </td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="nt101" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UN: Uniform distribution, with two parameters – minimum and maximum values; GA: Gamma distribution with three parameters – minimum and maximum values and shape parameter value; LU: Log-Uniform distribution with two parameters – minimum and maximum values. See 
      <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0097061-g002" href="#pone-0097061-g002">Figure 2</a> for the demographic parameters of each model tested. The mutation model parameters for the microsatellite loci were the mutation rate (
      <span class="italic">μ
       <sub>mic</sub>
      </span>), the parameter determining the shape of the gamma distribution of individual loci mutation rate (
      <span class="italic">P</span>), and the Single Insertion Nucleotide rate (
      <span class="italic">SNI</span>).
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 22 microsatellite loci were assumed to follow a generalised stepwise mutation model 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Estoup1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Estoup1">[39]</a> with two parameters: the mean mutation rate (
   <span class="italic">μ
    <sub>mic</sub>
   </span>) and the mean parameter of the geometrical distribution assumed for the length in repeat numbers of mutation events (
   <span class="italic">P</span>) drawn from uniform prior distributions of 10
   <span class="sup">−4</span> to 10
   <span class="sup">−3</span> and 0.1 to 0.3, respectively. Each locus has a possible range of 40 contiguous allelic states, except Locus 12 (43 states) and was characterised by individual 
   <span class="italic">μ
    <sub>loc</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">P
    <sub>loc</sub>
   </span> values, drawn from gamma distributions with respective means of 
   <span class="italic">μ
    <sub>mic</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">P</span>, and shape parameter 2 in both cases 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Verdu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Verdu1">[40]</a>. Using this setting, we allowed for large mutation rate variance across loci (range of 10
   <span class="sup">−5</span> to 10
   <span class="sup">−2</span>). We also considered mutations that insert a single nucleotide into or delete one from the microsatellite sequence. We used default values for all other mutation model settings. The details on model parameterisation and prior settings have been provided in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0097061-t001" href="#pone-0097061-t001">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The summary statistics of genetic diversity for the microsatellite loci, calculated with the programme DIY-ABC, included: the mean number of alleles per locus (
   <span class="italic">A</span>), mean expected heterozygosity (
   <span class="italic">H
    <sub>e</sub>
   </span>), mean allele size variance (
   <span class="italic">V</span>), and mean GW Index across the loci 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Garza1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Garza1">[31]</a> (Garza and Williamson 2001).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The posterior probability of each competing scenario was estimated using a polytomous logistic regression 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet3">[41]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet2">[36]</a> on 1% of the simulated datasets closest to the observed dataset. We evaluated the ability of our ABC methodology to discriminate between scenarios by analysing simulated datasets with the same number of loci and individuals as in our real dataset. Following the method of Cornuet 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet2">[36]</a>, we estimated the Type I error probability as the proportion of instances where the selected scenario did not exhibit the highest posterior probability, as compared to the competing scenarios for 500 simulated datasets generated under the best-supported model. We similarly estimated the Type II error probability by simulating 100 datasets for each of two alternative scenarios and calculating the mean proportion of instances in which the best-supported model was incorrectly selected as the most probable model.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We estimated the posterior distributions of the demographic parameters under the best demographic model, using a local linear regression on the closest 1% of 10
   <span class="sup">6</span> simulated datasets, after the application of a logit transformation, the inverse of the logistic function, to the parameter values 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Beaumont2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Beaumont2">[35]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet3">[41]</a>. Finally, following the method of Gelman 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Gelman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Gelman1">[42]</a>, we evaluated whether, under the best model-posterior combination, we were able to reproduce the observed data using the model-checking procedure available in DIY-ABC 
   <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet2">[36]</a>. Model-checking computations were processed by simulating 1000 pseudo-observed datasets under each studied model-posterior combination, with sets of parameter values drawn with replacement among the 1000 sets of the posterior sample. This generated a posterior cumulative distribution function for each summary statistic, allowing us to estimate the 
   <span class="italic">P</span> values for the observed values of these summary statistics. In addition, a principal components analysis (PCA) was performed on the summary statistics. Principal components were computed from the 15,000 datasets simulated with parameter values drawn from the prior. The target (observed) dataset, as well as the 1,000 datasets simulated from the posterior distributions of parameters, was then added to each plane of the PCA.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
