<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Holocene population decline</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increase in effective female population size of the Arunachal macaque, as revealed by the Bayesian skyline plots, continues till approximately 5,000 years ago, after which it appears to have suffered a mild decline. Mitochondrial and nuclear autosomal microsatellite loci are known to be informative at different time scales, highlighting different episodes in the demographic history of a species 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Fontaine1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Fontaine1">[6]</a>. The mtDNA diversity tends to reflect comparatively older demographic events in a species' history. Conversely, microsatellite data are more informative about the contemporary demography of a species. Such a difference in demographic signals, captured by each type of genetic marker, may arise from the differences in their respective mutation rates 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet2">[36]</a>. The relatively fast mutation rate of microsatellite loci enables them to capture recent and almost contemporaneous events but also increases homoplasy at these loci, which thereby reduces the signal of older demographic events 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Estoup1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Estoup1">[39]</a>. These, more ancient, events can, however, still be detected using the slower evolving mtDNA sequences. That is why we employed our microsatellite data to validate the occurrence of a very recent population decline in the Arunachal macaque.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The classical heterozygosity excess test (the EWCL method) suggested a past population bottleneck in at least the Upper Subansiri population, as reflected in its microsatellite data although the statistical significance of this result was highly dependent on the underlying mutational model. A bottleneck was inferred for this population for two particular models – the infinite-allele (IAM) and two-phase (TPM) models – but not for a third one, the stepwise-mutation (SMM) model, despite the IAM being unrealistic for most microsatellites 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-DiRienzo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-DiRienzo1">[34]</a>. Several other microsatellite-based studies of species, thought to have experienced severe, but temporary, reductions in population size, had either failed altogether to detect a bottleneck or, as with our study, yielded results that depended on the mutational model 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Spong1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Spong1">[63]</a>. In at least some of these cases, a few specific markers may have disproportionately influenced the more conservative SMM model. However, in our study, we used 22 microsatellite loci, over twice the minimum number recommended 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Luikart1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Luikart1">[64]</a>. To circumvent this problem, we applied the ABC method that clearly supported the population decline model (Scenario 2) over the constant size and population expansion models.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We could also estimate the extent and time of the decline from the posterior probabilities. Our simulations suggest the population decline started approximately 3,500 years ago, which was climatically a warm period and this is surprising as such climatic conditions are normally conducive for population growth. Several authors have postulated that such idiosyncratic mid-Holocene population declines may have been accelerated and enhanced by major expansions in ancient human civilizations 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Stavrianos1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Stavrianos1">[65]</a> (ca. 1,500 BC), the rapid development of agriculture, and the resulting changes in landscapes in recent times. For example, it has been speculated that the expansion and migration of human populations into the erstwhile virgin mountains of the Sichuan region may have caused the decline of the giant panda population during the later part of the mid-Holocene 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Zhang2">[66]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Arunachal Pradesh too, anthropogenic factors may have significantly influenced the demographic history of the Arunachal macaque over the last few decades or centuries. One of the largest indigenous groups of people that inhabit the districts of Upper Subansiri and West Siang, two areas from which our study samples were derived, and which hunt wildlife extensively for food and sport, is represented by the collective animist Adi people 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Lego1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Lego1">[67]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Tabi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Tabi1">[68]</a>. Recent ethnographic and population genetic studies reveal that the Adi, alternatively referred to as the Luoba Tibetan in Tibet, trace their ancestral migration and settlement history from southern Tibet into Arunachal Pradesh to different time periods during the 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> to 7
  <span class="sup">th</span> century AD, or to the last 1,300 to 1,500 years before present 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Lego1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Lego1">[67]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Tabi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Tabi1">[68]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Krithika2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Krithika2">[69]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Kang1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Kang1">[70]</a>. Although these estimates do not reject the possibility of a peopling of this region in even earlier times, it is entirely possible that the Arunachal macaque population declines may have actually begun at the time that central Arunachal Pradesh was being peopled by the Adi and other animistic tribes that continue to hunt rampantly even today. It must be reiterated, however, that there is currently no evidence to conclusively establish the definitive contribution of either climatic or anthropogenic factors to this decline in Arunachal macaque populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that our investigation, which focuses on a rare, endangered, montane primate, has a smaller sample size than is typical for most population genetics studies. Although there appears to be little benefit in sampling more than 20 to 30 individuals per population for microsatellite-based studies that assess genetic diversity of populations 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Pruett1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Pruett1">[71]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Hale1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Hale1">[72]</a>, sample sizes that are even smaller, as is the case in the present study, may not precisely represent the populations and may yield large errors for descriptive statistical estimates such as allele frequencies and expected heterozygosity. It has, however, been suggested that where small sample sizes are unavoidable, as, for instance, in the case of rare and endangered species, the precision of the estimates can be significantly enhanced by increasing the number of genotyped microsatellite loci, which is precisely what we have done in our study 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Hale1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Hale1">[72]</a>. Moreover, we have used approximate Bayesian computations to test whether the population size changes that we observe using other analytical methods are noteworthy or not. The approximate Bayesian computation framework manages any sample size, which may often be as low as 8 – 12 samples per population 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Fagundes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Fagundes1">[73]</a>, by simulating the exactly observed sample sizes 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Beaumont4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Beaumont4">[74]</a>. Small sample sizes would simply lead to wider credible intervals than would larger sample sizes 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Beaumont4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Beaumont4">[74]</a>. We are aware of this limitation of our results but believe that the communication of our present study is of critical importance, in spite of its low sample size, for the conservation effort to save the species, particularly as the collection of more samples from the rare and heavily hunted macaque populations in Arunachal Pradesh is not currently feasible.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the Tibetan Plateau is an important region to study the population history of its native species for more than one reason. First of all, it is a highly variable region with its different regions – the flat central platform and the more variable mountainous edges based on altitude – differing significantly from one another in topography and climatic history. The edge regions of the plateau have had a tumultuous orogenic history and the species of these areas are, thus, also expected to show a more eventful evolutionary history. Our study of an edge primate species has, along with other studies from the region, hinted at a very complex image of how geographical features such as latitude and altitude, animal physiology, and climate change in the past may have together influenced its demographic history. Unlike in the tropics, where Pleistocene glacial fluctuations were less likely to have been extreme, this region seems to represent a balance between the tropics and the more severe, temperate arctic environments. This study also underscores the possibility that a cold-tolerant species like the Arunachal macaque, which could withstand historical climate change and grow once the climate became conducive, may actually be extremely vulnerable to anthropogenic exploitation, as is perhaps indicated by its more recent population decline. It is imperative that we understand the population dynamics of such a species at a much finer scale, which could be possible with sampling more populations, particularly those that may connect the study populations. What is of greater concern, however, is the clear genetic signature of a serious decline in the populations of the species, possibly mediated by the extensive hunting that it continues to face across its distribution range. While these threats to the affected populations are currently being documented by on-ground field studies, it is entirely possible that unless immediate action is taken, genetic drift caused by hunting, epidemics or other natural calamities can rapidly eliminate the remaining genetic diversity of this less-known endemic primate from an extremely important biodiversity hotspot in the remote Himalayan mountains of northeastern India.</p>
</sec>
