<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The EWCL (Ewens, Watterson, Cornuet and Luikart) method</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Demographic events such as recent population bottlenecks are known to leave distinct genetic signatures in the distributions of allele size, expected heterozygosity and in the genealogy of microsatellite loci 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Piry1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Piry1">[33]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Goossens1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Goossens1">[9]</a>. Here, we used the allelic frequency spectrum, namely the number of alleles 
  <span class="italic">(n
   <sub>A</sub>)
  </span> and the expected heterozygosity 
  <span class="italic">(H
   <sub>e</sub>)
  </span>, to determine the patterns of genetic diversity expected for a demographically stable population 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Cornuet1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Cornuet1">[32]</a>. We performed simulations in Bottleneck, version 1.2.02 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-Piry1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-Piry1">[33]</a>, for both the species separately, to obtain the distribution of 
  <span class="italic">H
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span>, conditional on 
  <span class="italic">n
   <sub>A</sub>
  </span> and on the sample size for each population and locus. These 
  <span class="italic">H
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> values were then compared to those obtained from the real dataset. Three mutation models were used: the infinite-allele model (IAM), the stepwise-mutation model (SMM) and the two-phase model (TPM), with various amounts (70% to 95%) of single-step mutations 
  <a rid="pone.0097061-DiRienzo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0097061-DiRienzo1">[34]</a>. Any departures from the null hypothesis were explained as departures from the model, including selection, population expansion or decline. Consistency across independent loci, however, was unlikely to be caused by selection but rather by demographic events. This approach allowed us to detect population size changes and confirm that the signal was consistent across mutation models. The demographic event, however, could not be dated.
 </p>
</sec>
