<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Scholars and climate policy makers alike are continuously grappling with how to integrate uncertainties into their decision-making processes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>. In this context, decision makers need tools that enable flexible and adaptive options
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref> for complying with their objectives, especially for climate change that is subjected to a diversity of uncertainties
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>. Such an adaptive approach yields a range of acceptable outcomes while avoiding irreversible negative effects, defined here by remaining within the planetary boundaries on climate change. There are a number of different approaches to generating adaptive policies and satisfying constraints (e.g. planetary boundaries) in order to stay within a given set (e.g. safe operating space). One example, the tolerable windows approach (TWA)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref> mathematically considers all possible options from a given initial state. Unlike TWA which works forward in time, we use a similar approach, viability theory
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>, that works backward in time. Viability theory considers all initial states and computes policy options according to each states of the system at each time step. The resulting policies are adaptive to the world’s states, which is relevant for defining climate policies where the future remains uncertain. Viability theory works backwards from specified constraints and enables us to mathematically find all policy options that comply with these constraints from a given set of initial conditions. That is, if we want to hit a target in 2050 starting from where we are today, what are all the feasible policy options that will get us there? This method provides traction for managing environmental systems within an acceptable range
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref> which, here, is based on the planetary boundaries
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>. The remainder of the paper focuses on using viability theory to provide some new insights regarding the trade-offs between policy lags and climate in terms of adaptive policies aimed at remaining within the climate change planetary boundary.
</p>
