<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">An important limit on adaptive potential in seasonal habitats is the lack of genetic variation for plasticity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Theoretical models of plasticity and population resilience generally assume such variation to be sufficiently present (e.g.,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>), but there is actually little empirical support for this assumption, as data on natural genetic variation for seasonal plasticity in natural populations is scarce (e.g.,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup> but see e.g.,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>). Of concern is the possibility that in predictable environments, selection against phenotype-environment mismatches will deplete variation in plasticity. In seasonally plastic organisms there is strong selection favouring a match between the expressed phenotype and what is needed to survive and/or reproduce in the prevailing seasonal environment. This requires predictability of seasonal transitions, and tuning of the phenotypic response for a particular trait (the reaction norm) to the reliability of environmental cues that predict the selective environment
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. If a cue is highly reliable, selection favours a trait reaction norm that is highly sensitive to the cue. Alternative reaction norms for that trait, that are less sensitive to the reliable cue, or tuned to a different, unreliable cue, will produce a maladaptive mismatch between phenotype and environment
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. Ongoing purifying selection against such mismatches will, under stable long-term climatic conditions, remove standing genetic variation for plasticity from the population.
</p>
