<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Under climate change, characterised by increased environmental stochasticity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>, the reliability of existing environmental cues as predictors for seasonal progression will likely diminish. As a consequence, the most common (i.e., previously adaptive) reaction norm is then more likely to produce mismatches between phenotype and environment. Such maladaptive phenological shifts are already being observed in many species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Under these conditions, selection will favour alternative reaction norms, for example with a different sensitivity to the environmental cue or bet-hedging strategies. Theoretical models predict that reduced environmental predictability places species with strong plasticity under increased extinction risk
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>, and a rapid response to selection for alternative reaction norms hinges on the presence of sufficient standing variation for plasticity. However, if past purifying selection has depleted this variation, the potential for evolutionary change is limited in the short term
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, reducing the probability of population persistence under rapid climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, rather than giving rise to adaptable generalists, phenotypic plasticity in seasonal habitats may generally result in specialists with reduced short-term adaptive potential that are particularly vulnerable to climate change. While selection on plasticity for timing of breeding has been documented in a wild-bird population in response to climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>, many other species or populations lack such adaptive potential
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>, raising unanswered questions about why such variation may be depleted.
</p>
