<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9" class="p">Here we quantify the potential for evolutionary change in plasticity, combining an RNA-Seq approach with a full-factorial split-brood design across 144 individual transcriptomes. Specifically, we (1) characterise the transcriptional architecture of the seasonal phenotypes, (2) quantify intra-population genetic variation for plasticity, (3) assess footprints of selection on plasticity in coding regions and (4) determine the role of stress in constraining or increasing adaptive potential. Our analysis uncovers high amounts of seasonal plasticity in the transcriptome, reflecting a genome-wide plasticity programme, consistent with the integrated suite of traits involved in the seasonal adaptation. Strikingly, intra-population genetic variation for this plastic response is largely absent, with low levels of gene-by-environment interaction and highly similar seasonal responses across families. We hypothesise that this reduction reflects strong purifying selection in the savannah habitat where temperature serves as a reliable cue for predicting seasonal transitions, and the fitness cost of a mismatched phenotype is high
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. Consistent with this, Tajima’s D, a measure of DNA sequence polymorphism, is reduced in genes differing in plasticity across families, while this gene set shows no such reduction in an outgroup species lacking strong polyphenism. Stressful conditions during development decrease the transcriptional divergence between the seasons, but this is not accompanied by increased genetic variance for plasticity. Our results show that lack of genetic variation for plasticity may critically limit evolutionary potential and population persistence under environmental change, providing empirical support for theoretical predictions that species with strong phenotypic plasticity may be at elevated extinction risk when environmental predictability breaks down.
</p>
