<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Catching and satellite tagging of cuckoos was permitted by Regional Environmental Centres in Ruokolahti (KASELY/353/07.01/2010) and Oulu (POPELY/166/07.01/2014) and by the Finnish Museum of Natural History (ringing permits 2784, 2836, 2973). Catching was carried out on private lands with permission from landowners. The study did not involve any endangered or protected species. Adults were caught with mist nets and young were taken in nest boxes. Blood sampling for sexing the cuckoos was permitted by the Finnish National Animal Experiment Board (permits ESAVI/2846/04.10.03/2012 and ESAVI/3221/04.10.07/2013). All sampling procedures and experimental manipulations were reviewed as part of obtaining the above-mentioned permits.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tracking data</div>
  <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Juvenile cuckoos</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We fitted satellite transmitters (PTT-100 5 gram Solar PTT, Microwave Telemetry Inc.) on 13 fledgling common cuckoos during 2013–2014 at two Finnish breeding sites (
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s004" href="#pone.0168940.s004">S2</a> and 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s005" href="#pone.0168940.s005">S3</a> Tables)–nine young near Oulu in 2014 (65°N 25°50'E; [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref014">14</a>]) and four young near Ruokolahti in 2013 (61°22'N 28°31'E; [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref015">15</a>]). The young cuckoos at both sites were raised in nest boxes allowing close monitoring of their growth rates. The host species were common redstart 
    <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</span> and in one case great tit 
    <span class="italic">Parus major</span>. The young cuckoos were tagged just before fledging and the harness size was the same as the one used in adults to account for further body growth [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>]).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of the 13 tagged nestlings, we consider 12 to have fledged successfully; for one, data was only received on the day of starting the transmitter indicating that fledging was not completed. Of the 12 successfully fledged juveniles, six transmitted positions for more than a month; four after 46 days and one the entire autumn migration, ceasing transmission after 12 days being stationary in the wintering grounds (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0168940.g001" href="#pone.0168940.g001">Fig 1</a>, 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s004" href="#pone.0168940.s004">S2 Table</a>). Satellite data rarely allows distinguishing death from tag failure [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref016">16</a>]. For one tag, transmissions indicated death and this tag was later recovered on the dead bird. No other tags allowed distinguishing the cause of the stopped transmission, but death is likely to be the most common cause. For the successfully fledged juveniles (N = 12), five (42%) transmitted until assumed independent (i.e. &gt;20 km from nest). Of those reaching independence (N = 5), one (20%) transmitted until completion of autumn migration.
   </p>
   <div id="pone.0168940.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0168940.g001</span>
    <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <div class="title">Autumn migration of common cuckoos.</div>
     <p>Tracks of juveniles from Finland (red), northern adults (N adults; North Sweden and Finland; blue) and southern adults (S adults; Denmark and South Sweden; grey) with tagging and wintering sites (green and white triangles, respectively), and end of transmission (white circles) indicated. (A) Migration from breeding to wintering grounds and (B) details of initial movements with different red tinge for each juvenile cuckoo. Best quality locations for each duty cycle (dots) connected with lines. Horizontal lines at 55°N and 50°N indicate the band used to define entering and leaving, respectively, the NC Europe stopover. The line at 7°N defines leaving the Sahel. (C) Initial travel directions from breeding sites after moving 100 km and (D) travel directions (N and S adults; black) after leaving the Sahel. Each dot indicates the direction of one individual. Lines are group mean directions with 95% confidence interval. Data on North Swedish adults from [
      <a rid="pone.0168940.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref012">12</a>] and Danish and South Swedish adults from [
      <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>].
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="pone.0168940.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Survival of young cuckoos varies depending on the host [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref017">17</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref018">18</a>] and survival of cuckoos fledged from redstart nests has not been estimated before. Assuming that all lost tags stopped transmitting because of death, our survival rates from fledging to independence were lower than those reported by Wyllie [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref019">19</a>], 42% versus 62%, but not significantly so (
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s006" href="#pone.0168940.s006">S4 Table</a>). Survival of juveniles during the first migration (20%) was lower than those reported for adult satellite-tagged birds (down to 53% for UK birds travelling via the western route [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref016">16</a>]), though not significantly lower (
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s006" href="#pone.0168940.s006">S4 Table</a>) presumably due to the low sample sizes. Survival during the first migration is expected to be lower than during later migrations; in satellite-tracked Egyptian vultures 
    <span class="italic">Neophron percnopterus</span>, survival during the first autumn migration was 47% compared to 95% in adults [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref020">20</a>]. In cuckoos, Wyllie [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref019">19</a>] reported 4 out of 60 (7%) tagged fledglings returning to their breeding site in the following year but the degree of natal dispersal in cuckoos is not known.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adult cuckoo data</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the data on juvenile cuckoos, we included tracks of adults from Finland and Scandinavia. Tracks of two adult cuckoos (two autumn migrations) from 2014, one caught near Oulu and one near Ruokolahti were included, as were published tracks of 11 adult birds (18 autumn migrations) from Scandinavia (Denmark: 10 tracks from four adults [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>]; South Sweden: four tracks from four adults [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>]; North Sweden: four tracks from three adults [
    <a rid="pone.0168940.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref012">12</a>]). For comparison with juvenile birds, we lumped the adult tracks into two different groups–northern adults (North Swedish and Finnish) and southern adults (Danish and South Swedish). Transmission stopped in three birds before arrival south of the Sahara Desert (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0168940.g001" href="#pone.0168940.g001">Fig 1</a>, 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s004" href="#pone.0168940.s004">S2 Table</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For data analyses, we used the highest quality position for every duty cycle with a 10 hours on—48 hours off, constant transmission schedule obtained from ARGOS/CLS GPS [
   <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>] (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s007" href="#pone.0168940.s007">S5 Table</a>). We considered juveniles to be independent of their host parents and to have left the breeding area when they were &gt;20 km from the nest [
   <a rid="pone.0168940.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref019">19</a>]. Several birds moved back and forth for some time after independence with no consistent direction of movement. We termed this the pre-migration period and defined it as the period after reaching independence until movement was consistently southward (
   <a rid="pone.0168940.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0168940.t001">Table 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s004" href="#pone.0168940.s004">S2 Table</a>). Similar movements are only rarely observed in adults and only one adult in our data set, from the Oulu study site (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0168940.g001" href="#pone.0168940.g001">Fig 1B</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s004" href="#pone.0168940.s004">S2 Table</a>), performed such pre-migratory movements.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0168940.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0168940.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Timing and duration of autumn migration in common cuckoos.</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0168940.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0168940.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size (adult/juvenile)</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adults</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juveniles</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Departure from breeding site</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/5</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 Jul (±11)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 Jul (±13)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initiation of migration</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/5</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 Jul (±12)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 Aug (±24)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Departure NC Europe stopover</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 Aug (±16)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 Sep</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaving Europe</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 Sep (±14)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 Sep</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrival Sahel</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 Sep (±15)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 Oct</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrival winter area</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 Nov (±22)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 Dec</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migration duration</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (±22)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days from NC Europe stopover to winter ground</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (±23)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Days from Sahel to winter ground</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/1</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (±25)</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="t001fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing (mean date ± SD) and duration (days) of different stages during autumn migration of adult and juvenile cuckoos. NC = North Central. Data on North Swedish adults from [
      <a rid="pone.0168940.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref012">12</a>] and Danish and South Swedish adults from [
      <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>].
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We defined a stopover as when a bird interrupted migration for more than five days. Individual stopover sites were estimated as average locations within the stationary periods as described in [
   <a rid="pone.0168940.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref013">13</a>]. Due to non-daily transmissions, departure and arrival dates were rarely strictly identifiable, and we used last and first (respectively) days within the region/site. We defined arrival on the winter grounds as when the birds reached the southernmost stationary position.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We calculated initial migration directions using the mean flight directions after individuals crossed a distance of 100 km (Number of juveniles, N
   <sub>Y</sub> = 5; Number of adults, N
   <sub>A</sub> = 20) from breeding sites. For two juveniles and one adult from Finland, the initial movements were considered pre-migratory movements, but the general direction in which the birds left the breeding grounds was consistent from these movements. The directedness of sample orientations for the individuals of each group was tested with a Rayleigh test. The difference in initial direction between juveniles and adults was tested with a Watson-Williams test (tests based on distances 20–500 km led to similar results except that the directions of juveniles were more scattered at 20 km).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We judged sea-crossing behaviour directly from the maps. Because positions are spaced in time, proof of actual sea-crossings can be hard to obtain. We considered accurate positions over water or islands that connected positions over land on both sides of the Baltic Sea to be proof of a sea-crossing. We estimated potential individual sea-crossing distances as consecutive loxodromic distances between the last location before crossing, and the first location after crossing the Baltic. We subtracted the parts of these distances that occurred over continental land. We also compared the potential sea-crossing distances, irrespective of whether sea-crossing was considered proven or not, between adults and juveniles based on the shortest routes.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in the geometry of juvenile and adult tracks were also tested. First, longitudes of migration routes were compared between the juveniles (N
   <sub>Y</sub> = 3) and northern adult cuckoos (N
   <sub>NA</sub> = 6) at the southernmost latitude of migration where there were still three juvenile cuckoos migrating (55°N, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0168940.g001" href="#pone.0168940.g001">Fig 1A and 1B</a>). Second, for latitudes ranging from the North European stopovers to the southern edge of Sahel (7°N) where the adults followed a detoured route, we compared route deviations in the juvenile (N
   <sub>Y</sub> = 1) and the adults (N
   <sub>A</sub> = 10, only from year 2010). We calculated deviations from the direct loxodromic route from breeding to wintering grounds for each individual. Interpolated locations were calculated on the loxodromic routes using the latitudes of the location estimates of each track and the longitudes of the loxodromic routes at each of these latitudes. Route deviations were calculated as the horizontal distance from the location estimates of the tracks to the interpolated locations and tested using a Wilcoxon test. For the migration leg south of the Sahel (7°N), we only compared directions to the winter grounds of juvenile and adult cuckoos (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0168940.g001" href="#pone.0168940.g001">Fig 1D</a>) because there was no detour in adults and other differences could not be tested due to low sample size (N
   <sub>Y</sub> = 1; N
   <sub>A</sub> = 16).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluation of differences in total migration duration and timing of the different stages for juveniles and adult cuckoos was based on descriptive measures because of low sample sizes (
   <a rid="pone.0168940.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0168940.t001">Table 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s004" href="#pone.0168940.s004">S2 Table</a>). We estimated the mean difference and standard deviation in timing based on all pair-wise inter-age-class differences and compared observed mean difference by randomly resampling from pooled adult and juvenile timing (1,000 bootstrap replicates). Potential effects of wind during migration were considered for initial migration as well as for the migration from North-Central Europe to the sub-Sahel (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168940.s001" href="#pone.0168940.s001">S1 File</a>). We used R 3.1.2 [
   <a rid="pone.0168940.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref021">21</a>] for linear statistics, Oriana 3.0 [
   <a rid="pone.0168940.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref022">22</a>] for circular statistics and diagrams, and the RNCEP package [
   <a rid="pone.0168940.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0168940.ref023">23</a>] for wind analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
