<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While vegetation cover is generally sparse in the alpine belt of the cordillera (dominated by 
 <italic class="italic">Festuca dolichophylla</italic> J. Presl, 
 <italic class="italic">Agrostis tolucensis</italic> Kunth and various species of 
 <italic class="italic">Pycnophyllum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Deyeuxia</italic>) several deep valleys formed by the last ice ages shelter extended wetlands whose characteristics vary depending on water availability. In our study, the term “wetlands” defines a range of ecosystems from temporary wet grasslands to perennial peat bogs. Most of these wetlands are restricted to the alpine and sub-alpine belts at elevations between 3200 to 5000 m a.s.l., and appear as green oases in an overall arid landscape (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0175814.g002" class="xref">Fig 2C and 2D</xref>). Their vegetation contrasts sharply with surrounding terrestrial communities by having plant cover usually greater than 70% and high plant productivity [
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. These wetlands are characterized by the so-called cushion plants (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0175814.g001" class="xref">Fig 1C</xref>), some compact, low growing, mat forming plants commonly found in alpine and polar environments around the world. In Bolivia, above 4000 m a.s.l., cushion plants of the Juncaceae and Cyperaceae families (in decreasing order of abundance: 
 <italic class="italic">Oxychloe andina</italic> Phil., 
 <italic class="italic">Distichia muscoides</italic> Nees and Meyen, 
 <italic class="italic">Phylloscirpus deserticola</italic> (Phil.) Dhooge and Goetgh. and 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">filamentosa</italic> Buchenau dominate the lawn and hummock communities while aquatic macrophytes (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">Ranunculus uniflorus</italic> Phil. ex Reiche, 
 <italic class="italic">Lilaeopsis macloviana</italic> (Gand.) A.W. Hill, 
 <italic class="italic">Callitriche heteropoda</italic> Engelm. ex Hegelm. are found in open water pools [
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. High Andean wetlands in the Peruvian and Bolivian 
 <italic class="italic">puna</italic> are important staging grounds for migratory birds ([
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0175814.g001" class="xref">Fig 1D</xref>) and breeding grounds for invertebrates, amphibians, and fish [
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. The taxonomic diversity of this rich fauna is generally positively correlated with habitat area [
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Wetlands’ ability to promote vegetation growth lessens soil erosion and buffers water flow, providing a steady flow of water downstream while reducing the severity of floods and droughts [
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. They also support unique ecosystems and services that sustain the livelihoods of people by providing year-round water supply and forage for wild and domestic animals. A regional initiative for the conservation and wise use of high Andean wetlands was approved in November 2005 within the framework of the Intergovernmental Convention on Wetlands (RAMSAR, [
 <xref rid="pone.0175814.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]). While much of this vegetation is perennial, part of these wetlands can dry out or extend on the margins, depending on precipitation intensity. Moreover, when fed by rains, parts of the mineral landscape can become vegetated by pioneer herbaceous species forming new grasslands.
</p>
