<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ACCVI vulnerability models</div>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four vulnerability hazards (rain, snow, winter-summer temperatures, and sea level rise) included Type I model and a Multiplicative equation. The model was structured to identify existing spatial trends in vulnerability. Societal factors are emphasized over climate and physical features, and marine and airport sensitivity and adaptive capacity are calculated separately from exposure. This resulted in a quasi-weight of two-thirds weight on societal factors, while climate and physical features were allotted one-third of the weight. In this model, climate and physical features were coupled then added to airport or marine sensitivity (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>).
  <div id="Fig8" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 8</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Vulnerability model type I was calculated for all 50 communities for present, 2040, 2070, and 2100 timeframes under RCP 4.5 and 8.5 scenarios. Model was run using climate variables and extreme indices and for each sensitivity indices pairing (airport-disasters or marine-disasters). Under the Type I model, exposure projections and physical features were calculated together, then added to sensitivity (marine or airport)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10347_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e3161" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Outputs were assessed and verified by cross comparison with previous research and data from key informant interviews, indicating that Type I model was far more representative of the current vulnerabilities outlined in research and reports. Further, we found that the Type I model produced projections that were more congruent with some anticipated changes described by key informants and most in line with contextual vulnerability approach.</p>
 <p id="Par65" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More information on the calibration phase and the Type II model can be found in the Supplementary Notes 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">17, 19 and 20</a> (Type II results are not described in this article).
 </p>
</sec>
