<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Air and marine transportation systems play invaluable roles in the health, wellbeing, and economic vitality of the Canadian Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. These transportation systems are vulnerable to climate change due to persistent infrastructure inequities between the Canadian North and southern Canada
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, constrained emergency response capacities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, and increasing biophysical changes driven by climate change. Potential impacts are concerning and underpin the need for continued and enhanced investment in adaptation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Though developed in a Canadian Arctic context, ACCVI’s approach is highly adaptable and has broad relevance across circumpolar regions and other regions globally, being limited largely by environmental and socioeconomic data availability and projections. Using a new methodological approach to model vulnerability, we project the effects of various climate change scenarios on air and marine transportation systems across the Canadian Arctic. Based on the four hazards assessed we find that system vulnerability varies widely across the region and is projected to increase for at least the next 20 to 70 years. We also outline an iterative and transferable approach to model future climate change risks and delineate adaptation needs.</p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Developing complex and integrated vulnerability assessments comes with challenges and limitations. The authors acknowledge that several metrics available in the literature are absent of this analysis due to data availability or an inability to incorporate data into spatial assessments of aviation and marine sectors (Supplementary Discussion). Further, it was beyond the scope of this study to project potential socioeconomic pathways or changes to physical infrastructure. These limitations are highlighted as persistent scientific gaps in linked climate change socioeconomic and environmental modeling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Additional work is needed to address these gaps, with potential for continued advances in the vulnerability science and adaptation planning. In this context, community scale results are to be understood as relative and reflective only of variables and systems evaluated.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, it is important to note that vulnerability indexes are approximate methods of explaining how much a given system can be impacted by an external threat. In climate change science, the cause and effect between threats (exposure vector) and the end product (vulnerability) is a non-linearity. This non-linear relationship is produced by a condition that leads the system to a destabilizing threshold point which ultimately affects the entire system interrelationships. Such relationships between vulnerability drivers are so complex that is practically impossible to formulate indices that can unequivocally measure the vulnerability of a system (with progressive difficulty towards large areas)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. There are also indirect hazards, such as an oil spill’s impact on local food security, that were not specifically assessed or captured in the model. These indirect vulnerabilities are highly important, and while select variables, such as emergency response capacity and adaptive capacity, have wide implications, additional research is needed to more fully incorporate indirect scenarios accurately into models.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Projecting the vulnerability of social systems to biophysical changes is a necessary foundation to adaptation policies and building resilience across the Canadian Arctic, and more broadly in vulnerable regions around the world
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. This study is the first of its kind to assess Arctic climate change system vulnerability at such vast scale (over 2 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> land area) and resolution (∼25-km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) while promoting anticipatory adaptation through the identified vulnerabilities in air and marine transportation sectors. Based on our findings, we have outlined key areas needing adaptation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, under present conditions, air transportation systems are inhibiting timely access to definitive medical care, as well as reliable and regular access to many communities. To reduce sensitivity, weather observations and forecasts need to be reliably and regularly available, runways length needs to be appropriate for community needs and growing transport demand, and instrument approaches need to be improved and more widely available given that weather conditions and surrounding terrain often limit the ability of aircraft to safely land in communities across Inuit Nunangat
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, improvements in the coverage of detailed marine charting and navigational information is needed in vulnerable and heavy traffic regions to improve safety of shipping. Investments are specifically needed in the Arctic Archipelago, Hudson Bay, and Inuvialuit regions where vulnerability is projected to increase the most. Additionally, small ports have potential to reduce risks, especially in Inuvialuit
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Development of new ports should account for sea level decreases or rise.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third, there is a need for large investments in infrastructure across the region in order to meet formal Canadian Federal Agency Standards
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> as well to provide equity between south and north amenities and operational safety.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fourth, adaptive capacity is influenced by a variety of social, political, economic, technological, and institutional factors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Based on the adaptive capacity model (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a> and Supplementary Data 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">2</a>), we noted the majority of estimated highly adaptive communities are located in Nunatsiavut and Nunavik. Communities in Nunavik had high scores due to generally higher high school graduation and trade certificate attainment, as well as high presence of Inuktitut in households. For communities in Nunatsiavut, attainment of high school and trades certificates in the five communities increased relative scores. The lowest levels of adaptive capacity, as captured in the model, are distributed across the Central Arctic and Kivalliq region. This was due to lower levels of high school and trade certificate attainment and lower CWI scores.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are multiple opportunities for capacity building and adaptation across the Canadian Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. As highlighted by low estimated adaptation capacity in many communities, policies are needed to improve education, health, and income inequity, with many studies demonstrating the importance of Indigenous knowledge in building resilience
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Initiatives that address these social challenges will also likely improve a community’s ability to plan for and respond to climate change or disasters.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In such cases, first, it is essential that vulnerability assessments and adaptation plans look at various spatial scales to target at-risk populations. We highlight wide variation in exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity across Inuit Nunangat. While we did not assess intra-community variation, there is likely high variation between households. Adaptation planning should reflect various scales of needs and vulnerability. Second, emergency managers and public health officials should prepare for increasing probabilities of small and large disasters due to climate change, shifts in marine traffic, and changing demographics. Emergency and disaster response across the Canadian Arctic is limited by a lack of interagency training, a lack of community-based resources, knowledge, preparedness, and minimal resources beyond DND capacities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Capacity could be built through additional multi-agency training for both small (multi-day power plant failure) and large (airplane crash) incidents. Improvements in airport infrastructure where runways are too short for CC-130 or C17 to land and where instrument minimums frequently limit aeromedical access is essential to improving response.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additional methodological developments and the application of coupled social and biophysical vulnerability modeling is necessary to further our understanding of where, when, and how communities and populations are vulnerable to climate change, both in the Canadian Arctic and globally. Uncertainties related to the static geospatial datasets currently available (e.g., poor understanding of the distribution of ground ice and permafrost) and identifying other data (e.g., historical storm surge, flooding, erosion, permafrost, and landslide risk-classification products and/or future projections made by process-based models) would be useful for developing other vulnerability models and assessments such as this.</p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is essential that research to model vulnerability meaningfully incorporates local knowledge and/or Indigenous Knowledge and community perspectives
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Further, it is important that research teams are multidisciplinary and responsive to community experiences. Our approach was bolstered by using iterative steps to understand social and biophysical interactions, particularly a multiplex network analysis (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>; Supplementary Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>–
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>; Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Areas for future growth include linking dynamic social scenarios or pathways and analyzing additional livelihood sectors.
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Research has demonstrated that anticipatory adaptations are often more cost effective than reactive adaptation. It is essential that decision makers can anticipate future risks, can visualize where risks are highest, and understand how social and biophysical factors are interacting to create risk. The Arctic Climate Change Vulnerability Index approach developed in the paper helps to address these knowledge gaps for the transportation sector across Inuit Nunangat and outlines a method for future studies in other fields of vulnerability research.</p>
</sec>
