<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine transportation</div>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine transportation plays a critical role in the movement of goods to communities across the Canadian Arctic. For the majority of Inuit Nunangat communities, sealifts are the most cost-effective means of delivering non-perishable food, jet fuel, diesel for power production, gasoline, vehicles and construction equipment, and building supplies. Although the majority of communities rely on small docks and boat ramps, there are ongoing discussions of deep-sea ports in Pond Inlet and Iqaluit. A small craft harbor also exists in Pangnirtung. Though conventional shipping infrastructure is limited across much of the Canadian Arctic, navigational telex (provision of navigational and meteorological warnings and forecasts) are available along some of Baffin Island and the Hudson Bay. Additionally, electronic navigational charts are available around most communities. Canadian Coast Guard presence and icebreaking, oceanographic hazard mapping, satellite-based navigation systems, and Arctic shipping regulations are also key resources and systems that improve shipping safety across the region.</p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine access has historically been restricted by ice conditions to a window of one to three-month between July and September; however, shipping windows have become increasingly dynamic due to longer open-water season and the expanding presence of icebergs in some areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. Changes are also leading to increases in Arctic marine traffic regionally and through the Northwest Passage. Between 1990 and 2015, distance traveled by vessels in the Arctic increased by over 150%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
