<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The fate of Northern peatlands under climate change is important because of their contribution to global carbon (C) storage. Peatlands are maintained via greater plant productivity (especially of 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> species) than decomposition, and the processes involved are strongly mediated by climate. Although some studies predict that warming will relax constraints on decomposition, leading to decreased C sequestration, others predict increases in productivity and thus increases in C sequestration. We explored the lack of congruence between these predictions using single-species and integrated species distribution models as proxies for understanding the environmental correlates of North American 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatland occurrence and how projected changes to the environment might influence these peatlands under climate change. Using Maximum entropy and BIOMOD modelling platforms, we generated single and integrated species distribution models for four common 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> species in North America under current climate and a 2050 climate scenario projected by three general circulation models. We evaluated the environmental correlates of the models and explored the disparities in niche breadth, niche overlap, and climate suitability among current and future models. The models consistently show that 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatland distribution is influenced by the balance between soil moisture deficit and temperature of the driest quarter-year. The models identify the east and west coasts of North America as the core climate space for 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatland distribution. The models show that, at least in the immediate future, the area of suitable climate for 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatland could expand. This result suggests that projected warming would be balanced effectively by the anticipated increase in precipitation, which would increase 
  <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> productivity.
 </p>
</abstract>
