<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We performed all analyses in R software (version 3.4.3) [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref072">72</a>]. For calculating the circular mean (mean
  <sub>circular</sub>) and standard deviation (SD
  <sub>circular</sub>) of the entrance orientation and nest site orientation, we used the 
  <span class="italic">mean</span>.
  <span class="italic">circular</span> and 
  <span class="italic">sd</span>.
  <span class="italic">circular</span> functions from the 
  <span class="italic">circular</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref073">73</a>]. To correct for skewness of the data, we log-transformed nest entrance size, nest width and the TRI. We tested the difference between air temperature inside and outside the nest in the breeding season of 2018, using a two sample Student paired 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the effects of nest characteristics and weather conditions on the microclimate and breeding parameters, we modelled all relevant parameters and selected the best models based on the delta of the corrected Akaike’s Information Criterion (ΔAICc, calculated using the 
  <span class="italic">dredge</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">MuMIn</span> package) [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref074">74</a>]; the use of AICc instead of the regular AIC is recommended in the case of a small ratio between the sample size and the number of modelled parameters [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref075">75</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref076">76</a>]. A description of the starting models and the selected models is provided below. To estimate the goodness of fit of the models we calculated the likelihood-ratio based pseudo R
  <span class="sup">2</span> (R
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>p</sub>), [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref074">74</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref077">77</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If it was not possible to select the best model based on the ΔAICc, due to very similar ΔAIC values in high-ranked models, we performed model averaging of all models within 2 AICc units of the model with the lowest AICc to obtain weighted parameter estimates and the relative importance of each parameter, i.e. the sum of the Akaike weights of all the models with ΔAICc &lt; 2 containing this parameter [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref076">76</a>]. We only used significant models for model averaging, hence we determined the significance of the models with the Wald chi-square test, using the 
  <span class="italic">wald</span>.
  <span class="italic">test</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">aod</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref078">78</a>]. We calculated the weighted parameter estimates using full-model averaging (i.e. when calculating average parameter estimates, for models not containing the variable of interest the parameter estimate is set to 0), which is recommended in case of high model selection uncertainty [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref079">79</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To check for multicollinearity between variables in the starting models, we calculated the variance inflation factor (VIF) using the 
  <span class="italic">vif</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">car</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref080">80</a>]. High collinearity (high VIF) is especially problematic when ecological signals are weak, as high VIF may cause non-significant parameter estimates. Expecting the signal to be weak in our data set, but also aiming to minimize the risk of false positives, we selected VIF &lt; 5 as a threshold, which was enough to ensure a safe and flexible approach in regard to our data set [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref081">81</a>]. Subsequently, when VIF &gt; 5, we removed the variable from the model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As some nests were sampled &gt;1 in one year or sampled in both years (i.e. we possibly repeatedly recorded the same breeding pairs), we corrected for pseudoreplication by treating the nest label (hereafter nest ID) as a random effect. We tested the significance of the random effect by a likelihood ratio test (using the 
  <span class="italic">anova</span> function [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref072">72</a>]), which compared the linear mixed effect model with a similar linear model without the nest ID as a random effect. Comparing the output of the model with and without random effects is a way to test for significance of random factors [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref082">82</a>]. To enable this comparison, we fit both models using maximum likelihood.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For small sample sizes, we obtained the significance of the parameters by bootstrapping the model fitting of the specific model, including all averaged parameters (1000 iterations). We analysed the snow blocking and breeding output of both breeding seasons combined, to increase the sample size and enhance the power of the model. Parameters were considered significant if p ≤ 0.050, and considered a trend when p ≤ 0.100.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analysed the effects of weather conditions and nest characteristics on nest air temperature, snow blocking, hatching success and chick survival following a stepwise approach. In step 1 we aimed to investigate how weather conditions affected the nest air temperature during the breeding season of 2018 and the probability of the nest being blocked by snow in the breeding season of 2017 and 2018. Therefore, we first modelled the nest air temperature with the corresponding weather conditions by fitting a linear mixed effect model, using the 
  <span class="italic">lmer</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">lme4</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref083">83</a>] (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s002" href="#pone.0217708.s002">S2 Table</a>). Since the interval between the nest temperature measurements was 60 min and the interval between each of the other measurements was 10 min, we matched the nest air temperature at a specific moment with the corresponding weather conditions with an accuracy of ± 5 min. The averaged models predicting nest air temperature included the following predictors: air temperature, northern and eastern wind direction and wind speed (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s002" href="#pone.0217708.s002">S2 Table</a>). Similarly, we modelled the snow blocking status (1 = closed, 0 = open) with the mean environmental predictor variables calculated for the three days preceding the nest check and snow cover at the day of the nest check itself (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s003" href="#pone.0217708.s003">S3 Table</a>), using the 
  <span class="italic">glmer</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">lme4</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref083">83</a>]. Even though data from two years were included in this model, we decided that year should not be added as a predictor to this model. Since we expected that inter-annual differences in snow blocking the nest entrance are most likely the result of differences in weather conditions, the model already accounts for inter-annual differences by just testing the effects of weather conditions. The averaged models predicting the probability of snow blocking included the following predictors: air temperature, wind speed, northern and eastern wind direction, snow cover and precipitation. In none of the models, interactions between terms were tested, because we would lose too many degrees of freedom. We added nest ID as a random factor to both models. We obtained the significance of the parameters from the model averaging output (
  <span class="italic">MuMIn</span> package) [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref074">74</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In step 2 we quantified the nest effect on nest air temperature in the 2018 (hereafter the thermal microclimate) and snow blocking in 2017 and 2018 (hereafter the susceptibility to snow blocking), corrected for weather conditions. To quantify the thermal microclimate, we fit a linear mixed effect model to predict nest air temperature with all meterological parameters obtained from the model averaging described in step 1 (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s002" href="#pone.0217708.s002">S2 Table</a>) with nest ID as a random effect. From this model, we obtained the thermal microclimate as the conditional modes (i.e. best linear unbiased predictors [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref084">84</a>]) of the random nest ID effects, using the 
  <span class="italic">ranef</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">lme4</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref083">83</a>]. Simultaneously, we quantified the susceptibility to snow blocking as the conditional modes of the random nest ID effect from a binomial mixed effect model that predicted snow blocking of the nest. This model included all meteorological parameters obtained from the model averaging described in step 1 (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s003" href="#pone.0217708.s003">S3 Table</a>) with nest ID as a random effect. In both models, the random nest ID effect was significant (p &lt; 0.001).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In step 3 we examined how nest orientation, exposure and insulation (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s016" href="#pone.0217708.s016">S1 File</a> for more details on insulation) were related to the thermal microclimate and susceptibility to snow blocking, obtained in step 2. We modelled the thermal microclimate with nest characteristics using a linear model, starting with a model that included all possible nest characteristics (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s004" href="#pone.0217708.s004">S4 Table</a>). The parameters of the averaged models were: entrance size and northern nest entrance orientation, nest height, depth and width and insulation (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s004" href="#pone.0217708.s004">S4 Table</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s016" href="#pone.0217708.s016">S1</a> File). To examine snow blocking, we modelled the susceptibility to snow blocking using a linear model and started with a model that included all relevant nest characteristics (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s005" href="#pone.0217708.s005">S5 Table</a>). The parameters of averaged models were: entrance size, eastern entrance orientation, TRI, and WEI (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s005" href="#pone.0217708.s005">S5 Table</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In step 4 we modelled each breeding parameter (hatching success and chick survival) in relation to the thermal microclimate and the susceptibility to snow blocking, as quantified in step 2, using the 
  <span class="italic">glmer</span> function from the 
  <span class="italic">lme4</span> package [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref083">83</a>]. We included the breeding season in the model, to account for inter-annual differences. We considered hatching as successful (response variable = 1) if one egg hatched, and chick survival as successful (response variable = 1) if the hatched chick survived until fledging (i.e. when it reached the age of 50 days). We also investigated the relationship between the breeding parameters and the nest characteristics. To do so, we initially modelled each breeding output parameter (i.e. hatching success and chick survival) with the nest parameters that were associated with the thermal microclimate and snow blocking as obtained in step 3, and breeding season to account for inter-annual differences (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s006" href="#pone.0217708.s006">S6</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s007" href="#pone.0217708.s007">S7</a> Tables for the model selection of hatching success and chick survival, respectively). We added nest ID as a random effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We examined the relation between chick growth and the nest microclimate in both breeding seasons apart from the stepwise analyses described before. We modelled chick growth (i.e. the daily percentage body mass increase, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s017" href="#pone.0217708.s017">S2 File</a>) with the mean external weather conditions instead of the nest air temperature, as the nest air temperature measurements were limited to the breeding season 2018 (but see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s017" href="#pone.0217708.s017">S2 File</a> for additional analyses of chick growth). We used a linear mixed effect model and added nest ID as a random effect (model selection in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s008" href="#pone.0217708.s008">S8 Table</a>). We calculated the means of the explanatory variables based on records collected during the seven days preceding the nest check, so in general these intervals overlapped. We standardized all numerical parameters. We could not include the mean air temperature and the interaction between breeding season and snow cover in the model, due to multicolinearity (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s008" href="#pone.0217708.s008">S8 Table</a> for model selection and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s017" href="#pone.0217708.s017">S2 File</a> for additional analyses of chick growth).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Raw data is provided as supplementary material (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s009" href="#pone.0217708.s009">S9</a>–
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s015" href="#pone.0217708.s015">S15</a> Tables).
 </p>
</sec>
