<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The findings of our study support the hypothesis that under extreme weather conditions of the Antarctic summer, nest burrow characteristics—in particular the nest dimensions, entrance orientation and nest insulation—can provide shelter against the weather and thereby establish a thermally favourable microclimate and protection against snow blocking. In addition, the hypotheses that hatching success and chick survival are higher in nests with characteristics which improve the thermal microclimate and reduce the chance of snow blocking, was supported. However, it remains uncertain whether the observed effects on hatching success and chick survival were through nest air temperature or snow blocking, since the nest parameters that affected breeding output were associated with the thermal microclimate as well as the susceptibility to snow blocking. In addition, the hypotheses that chick growth was enhanced by a high nest air temperature was not supported, as we were unable to detect an unambiguous effect of weather conditions related to nest air temperature on chick growth. Since the effect of nest air temperature on chick growth remains indistinct, it is likely that also breeding output was less affected by the thermal microclimate and the susceptibility to snow blocking was possibly more important. Hence, despite some effects being statistically insignificant, apparent trends add some evidence to a growing awareness of the importance of nest shelter in establishing a thermally favourable microclimate and protection against snow blocking and thereby enhancing breeding success [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref011">11</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref046">46</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref085">85</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref087">87</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our hypothesis that hatching success and chick survival would be favoured in nests with nest characteristics which improve the thermal microclimate and reduce the chance of snow blocking, was supported, as hatching success as well as chick survival was positively affected by an eastern nest entrance orientation. However, it remains uncertain if the observed effect of nest characteristics originated from the thermal microclimate or from the susceptibility to snow blocking, since an eastern nest orientation (either of the nest site or the nest entrance, respectively) was associated with a more favourable nest specific microclimate as well as with a lower susceptibility to snow blocking. The positive effect of an eastern nest orientation regarding the thermal microclimate and the susceptibility to snow blocking, could be explained by the weather conditions at KGI. First of all, the predominant wind direction during the breeding seasons of 2017 and 2018 ranged from north to west to southwest [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref061">61</a>]. In addition, eastern wind was associated with higher air temperatures and less precipitation (i.e. snow or rain) [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref088">88</a>]. Therefore, it is likely that by selecting nests oriented towards the east, parents select nests sheltered in terms of the thermal microclimate and snow blocking. This is underlined by the mean orientation of the nest entrance (38.44° i.e. north-east) and nest site (67.15° i.e. east north-east) obtained in this study and our observation that the hourly mean nest air temperature was significantly higher than the hourly mean ambient air temperature during the breeding season of 2018. Although a difference of 0.9°C between the outside air temperature and nest air temperature might seem small, in the harsh climate of the sub-Antarctic and temperatures close to 0°C, such a small difference could be critical for breeding success. In addition, the importance of the thermal microclimate of the nest to hatching success and chick survival has also been reported in other studies, as it could hamper the embryonic development, increase the energetic demands of the incubating parents and reduce the immune response of chicks [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref022">22</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref089">89</a>]. However, the ambiguous effects of weather conditions related to nest air temperature on chick growth, do indicate that the thermal microclimate of the nest is not of major importance for the development of the Wilson’s storm-petrel chicks. Therefore, the observed effects of nest characteristics on the breeding output are possibly mainly through the susceptibility to snow blocking. Indeed, snow blocking of the nest has been reported in several studies as a major cause of egg and chick mortality in Wilson’s storm-petrels [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref053">53</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref057">57</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref058">58</a>]. Similar results have been obtained in a study at the Windmill Islands, East Antarctic, where Wilson’s storm-petrel nests were limited by the snow accumulation patterns during the breeding season [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref047">47</a>]. Hence, despite the absence of an observed direct effect of the thermal microclimate and susceptibility to snow blocking on the breeding success, the effect of an eastern nest orientation indicates that the thermal microclimate and the susceptibility to snow blocking could both be an important factor determining breeding success. Moreover, they could serve as an important driver of nest site selection, despite the highly variable and rather unpredictable nature of the Antarctic weather conditions and snow accumulation patterns in space and time [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref090">90</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref093">93</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of weather conditions on chick growth rate were complex, as both the effect of wind speed and wind direction depended on the breeding season. In 2017, wind speed and eastern wind direction negatively affected chick growth, while in 2018 chick growth was enhanced by higher wind speeds and an eastern wind direction. On the one hand, the negative effect of wind speed in 2017 and the positive effect of eastern wind direction in 2018 support our expectation that a higher nest air temperature favours chick growth. Firstly, due to the negative effect of wind speed on nest air temperature due to wind chilling effect, observed in this study. Secondly, due to the association of eastern wind with higher ambient air temperatures, reported in the study of Kejna and Laska [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref088">88</a>]. Hence, it appears that higher nest burrow air temperatures and ambient air temperatures favour chick growth, which is in accordance with the study of Wasilewski [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref057">57</a>] performed in the same area, in which nest burrow air temperature was positively related to chick growth rate. On the other hand, the opposite effects of eastern wind direction and wind speed in the two study periods might indicate that nest temperature is not a major driver of chick growth in Wilson’s storm-petrel chicks, especially, when also the results of the additional analyses of chick growth in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217708.s017" href="#pone.0217708.s017">S2 File</a> are considered (i.e. chick growth tends to be negatively affected by nest air temperature and the chick growth parameter is positively affected by nest height). Indeed, birds breeding at high latitudes or altitudes are typically resilient to the harsh climate of these areas [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref034">34</a>]. Also, Wilson’s storm-petrel chicks are known to have developed several strategies to cope with the harsh and unpredictable weather, such as a relatively high resting metabolism to maintain thermoregulation and the ability to survive and even induce facultative hypothermia during extreme circumstances (i.e. torpor) [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref044">44</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref051">51</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref052">52</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref057">57</a>]. Some of these adaptations are, however, energetically demanding and hence, food provisioning is thought to be one of the main limitations of chick growth and breeding success [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref051">51</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref063">63</a>]. Additionally, studies on common terns (
  <span class="italic">Sterna hirundo</span>) breeding in Europe, and Antarctic petrels (
  <span class="italic">Thalassoica antarctica</span>) have revealed that susceptibility of chicks to bad weather depends on their body condition [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref094">94</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref095">95</a>]. Therefore, the opposing effects of weather conditions in the two study years might be explained by differences in food availability between 2017 and 2018, and between periods with certain weather conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref058">58</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref096">96</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref099">99</a>]. The slower chick growth in 2017 may indicate a relatively low food availability, which could have reinforced the negative response of chick growth to the low nest air temperature caused by the wind chill effects of the strong winds. Higher food availability in 2018 could make the chicks more resilient to low nest air temperatures, and strong eastern winds could even have a positive impact on chick growth by enhancing food availability due to vertical mixing of Antarctic ocean water [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref096">96</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref099">99</a>] and due to higher air temperatures associated with eastern wind [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref088">88</a>]. Therefore, the effect of the thermal microclimate on chick growth is probably only apparent when food supply is limited.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to nest characteristics, parental effort and quality are likely to affect the breeding success and chick growth, however, we did not control for these variables. Therefore, it should be taken into account that the observed response of the breeding output to nest characteristics, could also be attributed to occupation of better quality nest burrows by higher quality parents. In that case, the observed effects are possibly not solely induced by the effects of the thermal microclimate or snow blocking, but could be (partly) ascribed to the quality of the parents. In fact, in common eiders breeding in the Arctic, the observed reduced breeding success at unfavourable nest sites was attributed to the lower quality of the parents occupying these nests, rather than to the unfavourable microclimate of these nests [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref048">48</a>]. Moreover, the effects of weather conditions on chick growth could also be attributed to the parental effort under certain weather conditions rather than directly onto the weather conditions. Indeed, unfavourable environmental circumstances are likely to reduce the parental effort in long living seabirds, although this response varies greatly between individuals [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref051">51</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref063">63</a>]. Nevertheless, despite the presumably complex effects of parental care and quality, we were able to detect some effects of nest characteristics and weather conditions that can, to a certain extent, be linked to the thermal microclimate and the susceptibility to snow blocking of the nest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, in the Antarctic, the effects of the expected increase in greenhouses gases over the next century, will be substantial because of the speed at which atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations rise, and because of polar amplification of the global warming signal [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref100">100</a>]. In the next 100 years, mean Antarctic surface temperatures are projected to increase 0.34°C per decade and annual snowfall will increase by 20% in total [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref100">100</a>]. Nest characteristics that determine the chance of snow blocking are therefore likely to become more important for breeding success. At a more regional scale, the natural highly variable climatic conditions of the Antarctic Peninsula resulted in a significant decrease in mean annual air surface temperature in the previous decade, which was especially apparent in the northwest of the Peninsula and on the South Shetland Islands [
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref101">101</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217708.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217708.ref102">102</a>]. Hence, it is likely that, despite global warming, such an unpredictable climate will keep demanding thermally favourable nest burrows, to support the breeding success.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study indicates the importance of nest characteristics like nest dimensions, insulation and orientation in establishing a thermally favourable microclimate and limiting snow blocking for the Wilson’s storm-petrel nests. However, the response of hatching success, chick growth and chick survival to the nest characteristics, was complex and probably greatly affected by other parameters, such as food availability, and parental effort and quality. This might explain why the effect of weather conditions through nest air temperature on chick growth remained indistinct. Nevertheless, nest characteristics that enhanced the thermal microclimate and reduced the risk of snow blocking positively affected both hatching success and chick survival. The projected increase in snowfall, due to climate change, will probably enhance the importance of nest characteristics that determine snow blocking. Additionally, the highly variable nature of the Antarctic climate will probably keep demanding for thermally favourable nest burrows. Thus, our study shows the importance of nest characteristics in enhancing the breeding output and chick growth of the burrow-nesting seabirds breeding in harsh polar conditions.</p>
</sec>
