<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Unfortunately, public and animal health surveillance systems often fail to communicate. For example, an outbreak of Rift Valley fever (RVF) in Mauritania was mistaken for yellow fever and detected only after communication with the veterinary services who observed abortions due to RVF in livestock (Digoutte 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>). Febrile illness in Bamako, Mali, is most often associated with malaria, ignoring the importance of zoonotic diseases like brucellosis or Q-fever (Steinmann 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). Similarly, the Dutch public health authorities complained that more than 3000 cases of human Q-fever could have been prevented if the veterinary services had communicated a large outbreak in goats (Enserink 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). It makes a lot of sense that the surveillance of vector-borne zoonoses is coupled between entomological, animal and human surveillance systems, e.g. for Japanese encephalitis virus in China (Baylis 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), borreliosis in Serbia (Savic 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) or West Nile Fever in Europe(Gossner 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Such iSRS should also include terrestrial wildlife (Singh and Gajadhar 
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) and marine animals (Stephen 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). The importance of including wildlife in iSRS is further demonstrated by the example of blood transcriptomes in lemurs that reveal novel parasitic zoonoses in Madacascar (Larsen 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). In South Korea, migration of wildlife, international human movement and illegal importation of wildlife were identified as the main risks for pathogen introduction into the country (Hwang 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Individual countries like Mongolia are currently developing One Health iSRS systems (Batsukh 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), while others are proposed (Cheng, Mantovani and Frazzoli 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
