<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Goats undoubtedly need to be the priority focus for livestock industries due to their advantages over other ruminant animals from a climate resilience point of view. Elevated ambient temperature during the summer months can have a significant influence on the basic physiology of rumen, thereby affecting the rumen fermentation pattern, VFA and other rumen metabolites production. Furthermore, growing evidence suggests that heat stress influences the rumen microbial population, resulting in alterations in ruminal digestion process in goats. In addition, heat stress has also been shown to increase the production of enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission resulting in dietary energy loss. Thus, the productive performances of the animals are compromised. Nutritional interventions and other management strategies are traditional ways by which enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission is reduced in goats. More recently, several researchers have targeted reducing enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> through advanced biotechnological tools such immunization therapy, using bacteriocins, etc. but without much success. Further refinements in these technologies are essential before these technologies are implemented at field level. In the near future, these technologies offer scope for identifying genetically superior animals with less CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production per unit feed intake. However, further research efforts are needed to elucidate the mechanisms associated with enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission during heat stress exposure by establishing the relationships among the rumen microbes through metagenomics approaches in goats in the changing climate scenario. Such efforts may help to develop more focussed mitigation strategies for reducing enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission in goats. This may help to sustain goat production in the changing climate scenario by preventing the dietary energy loss incurred during the process of enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission.
</p>
