<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dietary data from the FNFNES</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 21 FNs in British Columbia were surveyed between the Fall of 2008 and 2009. FNs were randomly selected using a combined ecozone/cultural area framework and residency information from on-reserve populations. An ecozone is a large geographical region identified by the distribution patterns of plants, animals, geographical characteristics and climate (ecozone.ca). The cultural area is a concept used to identify geographic areas within which Indigenous communities share a greater number of traits/cultural affinities than those outside the area [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref061">61</a>]. This study uses the data obtained from the six FNs communities in the Pacific Maritime ecozone, Subarctic/Northwest coast cultural area, including Kitsumkalum, Hagwilget, Skidegate, Nuxalk, Namgis, and Tla’amin (formerly Sliammon) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211473.g001" href="#pone.0211473.g001">Fig 1</a>). The Pacific Maritime ecozone comprises BC marine islands, the land along the Pacific Coast, and the border with Alaska. A total of 549 randomly selected households in the 6 randomly selected communities in the Pacific Maritime ecozone were invited to participate. The participation rate was 67%. In total, 369 individuals (one participant randomly selected from each household) who self-identify as FN adults living on-reserve were recruited to participate in this study. Pregnant and breastfeeding women (n = 13) were excluded from our analyses due to their different nutritional requirements and low sample size. The final sample included 356 individuals. All the data were weighted to obtain representative estimates of the total population by minimizing biases arising from differences between participating and non-participating persons using the Bootstrap method [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref030">30</a>]. Ethical approval was granted by the Ethical Review Boards at Health Canada, the University of Northern British Columbia, the University of Ottawa and the Université de Montréal.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data on age, sex, weight, height, physical activity level, smoking behaviour, educational attainment, household size, employment status, self-perceived health status, source of income, body mass index, and traditional food gathering activity were collected. Food security information was obtained using the income-related Household Food Security Survey Module (HFSSM) [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref062">62</a>] adapted from the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) Food Security Survey Module [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref063">63</a>]. The HFSSM was further adapted for FNs [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref064">64</a>]. Dietary information was collected by a 24-hour diet recall and a Traditional Food Frequency Questionnaire (FFQ) spanning the entire year and collecting information on the frequency of consumption of all traditional foods available for consumption. In total, the FFQ combined 208 traditional food items including 65 seafood species. Seafood species included fish (n = 41), shellfish (n = 16), seaweed (n = 4), and marine mammals (n = 4) reported in the survey.
 </p>
</sec>
