<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimation of nutrient intakes and nutrient requirements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each food item reported to be consumed in the dietary intake assessments were matched to the Canadian Nutrient File, a national food composition database [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref065">65</a>] taking into account the preparation method (i.e. baked or broiled, boiled or raw). Nutrients that are rich in seafood were selected to be included this study: protein, eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), vitamins (A, D, B12, and niacin), and minerals (zinc and selenium, and iron). See Supporting Information 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211473.s001" href="#pone.0211473.s001">S1 Table</a> for nutrient content of top 20 most consumed seafood species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the Dietary Reference Intake (DRI), in particular, the Recommended Dietary Allowance (RDA), to assess the contribution of seafood consumption to nutrient requirements [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref066">66</a>]. The DRIs are a comprehensive set of nutrient values for healthy populations used for assessing and planning diets. The RDA is the average daily dietary nutrient intake level that is sufficient to meet the nutrient requirements of nearly all (97.5%) healthy individuals in a particular life stage and gender group [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref067">67</a>]. The RDAs were available for all nutrients of interest except EPA and DHA. According to the Dietitians of Canada and the American Heart Association, consumption of 500mg/d EPA+DHA is recommended for the general adult population without cardio-heart diseases (CHD) which is considered to be sufficient to obtain protective effects for primary prevention of cardiovascular diseases [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref068">68</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref069">69</a>]. Thus, the contribution of EPA+DHA intake to the recommended intake (RI) was estimated. Nutrient requirements are the same for those aged 19 to 30 years and those aged 31 to 50 years; for this reason, these age groups were combined. Age groups containing those between 51 and 70 (inclusive) and those over 70 years of age were also combined due to the small sample size among the elderly.
 </p>
</sec>
