<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Projected effects of climate change on seafood abundance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used published projections of the effects of climate change on the relative abundance of 98 marine fish and invertebrate species of commercial and cultural importance to FNs in coastal BC [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref045">45</a>]. These projections were based on outputs from the dynamic bioclimate envelope model (DBEM), which is a mechanistic species distribution model that simulate changes in annual average abundance (relative to baseline time period) on a 0.5 ° latitude x 0.5° longitude grid of the world ocean [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref045">45</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref057">57</a>]. Briefly, the DBEM includes four different components: (1) temperature and oxygen-dependent size, growth and mortality [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref058">58</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref059">59</a>], (2) estimation of population carrying capacity in each grid cell based on environmental conditions and species’ habitat preferences, which can increase or decrease according to changes in environmental conditions and the species’ habitat preferences, (3) modelled ocean conditions dependent spatial population dynamics with adult movement and (4) larval dispersal modelled using an advection-diffusion-reaction model (see [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref057">57</a>] for detailed description of the model). Changes in seafood abundance were estimated under RCP 2.6 and RCP 8.5, representing “strong mitigation” and “business-as-usual” scenario. Changes in ocean conditions under climate change scenarios were projected from the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory Earth System Model 2M (GFDLESM 2M) [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref060">60</a>]. Projected changes in ocean conditions were regridded on a 0.5° latitude x 0.5° longitude grid of the global oceans on which the DBEM operates (see [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref057">57</a>] for details). Total annual average abundance in the Pacific Coast of Canada (within Canada’s Exclusive Economic Zone) were calculated for each species. The results for the 2050s period (average between 2041 to 2060) relative to the 2000s (average between 1991 to 2010) were then used in subsequent analysis. Despite the uncertainties associated with the coarse-scale (relative to the BC FN fisheries) projections, these represent one of the best available species-specific quantitative projections in the literature that cover a wide range of species that are important to BC FNs. We also discussed the implications of the uncertainties associated with the use of these projections for the conclusions of this study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In total, 98 species comprising marine and diadromous fish, shellfish, and invertebrates harvested by First Nations for food, social, and cultural purposes were selected. The list of species was identified from peer-reviewed literature, government and non-governmental organizations’ reports, treaty agreements, and First Nations’ reports. Marine mammals, seaweeds and birds were not included in the study [
  <a rid="pone.0211473.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211473.ref045">45</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
