<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for the total economic effect of climate change</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The NPV of the total economic effect of climate change, denoted as 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>NPV</sub>, consists of mitigation costs, adaptation costs and climate-related economic impacts aggregated until 2300 and discounted using equity weighting and a pure time preference rate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. We base the economic impacts due to changing temperatures on a recent macro-econometric analysis of historic temperature shocks on economic growth in multiple countries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. We project the economic impact function derived from this analysis onto the 8 global regions of the PAGE model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> using gridded population-weighted ERA-Interim reanalysis data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> for mean climatological temperatures in the base year, and adapt it to fit with the consumption-only approach for climate impacts in PAGE with no lasting effects on economic growth. Termed the level effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, this provides a likely lower end estimate for the economic impacts and also allows one to compare directly with the default PAGE09 impact functions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>, for which the original results for the PCF were derived
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. We also carry out updates to the sea level rise driver, discontinuity impacts and mitigation costs according to the latest literature (Methods, Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). The Zero Emissions scenario provides a hypothetical upper bound for the mitigation costs and includes residual impacts from historic emissions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we calculated 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>NPV</sub> for the global climate-economy system using the base PAGE-ICE model with the legacy Arctic feedbacks, and PAGE-ICE with the nonlinear PCF and SAF representations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>). In both settings, the mean total economic effects of the 1.5 °C, 2 °C and 2.5 °C scenarios are the lowest of the seven scenarios considered, while the NDC scenarios and, particularly, the BaU scenario have much higher mean total economic effects. All the distributions have long upper tails representing a possibility of large impacts relative to the means. The tails get elongated for higher emissions scenarios and when the nonlinear PCF and SAF representations are used.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Total economic effect of climate change with the nonlinear and legacy Arctic feedbacks. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> NPVs of the total economic effect of climate change (until 2300, equity-weighted, PTP-discounted), plotted for the legacy Arctic feedbacks (Base model) and with the nonlinear PCF &amp; SAF corrections included, and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> NPVs of the additional economic impact separately from the nonlinear PCF and SAF, calculated relative to their legacy values under the climate scenarios considered. Whiskers: 5–95% range; boxes: 25–75% range; horizontal lines: median; dots: mean. 100,000 Monte-Carlo runs of PAGE-ICE. The effect of the imaginary Zero Emissions scenario is higher compared to the 1.5 °C, 2 °C and 2.5 °C scenarios due to the large mitigation costs. Source data are provided as a Source Data file
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9863_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e855" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We then calculated the additional economic effect of the nonlinear PCF and SAF relative to the legacy values (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>). The nonlinear PCF leads to statistically significant increases in 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>NPV</sub> at the 5% significance level for all the scenarios considered, especially the NDC and BaU. The nonlinear correction to the SAF leads to small but statistically significant increases in 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>NPV</sub> for Zero Emissions and 1.5 °C, 2.0 °C and 2.5 °C target scenarios, statistically significant decreases in 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>NPV</sub> for NDCs Partial and BaU, and is not significant for NDCs (all at the 5% level).
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the nonlinear PCF and SAF representations are combined, the statistical mean of the economic effect of climate change increases relative to the base estimate with the legacy PCF and SAF by $16.1 trillion (1 trillion = 10
  <span class="sup">12</span>) for the counterfactual Zero Emissions scenario ($1288 trillion base estimate), $24.8 trillion for 1.5 °C target ($613 trillion base estimate), $33.8 trillion for 2.0 °C target ($613 trillion base estimate), $50.3 trillion for 2.5 °C target ($815 trillion base estimate), $66.9 trillion for NDCs ($1390 trillion base estimate), and by $59.8 trillion for NDCs Partial ($1702 trillion base estimate). These increases are statistically significant (5% level). We also found marginal but statistically insignificant increases for BaU ($2197 trillion base estimate), which remains the most expensive and least desirable scenario.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean economic impact of net additional warming from the nonlinear PCF &amp; SAF peaks at just under $70 trillion (NPV until 2300) for NDCs. To put this number into context, it exceeds the estimated long-term gains from economic development in the Arctic region through transit shipping routes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span> and mineral resource extraction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span> under high emissions scenarios by around 10 times, and could also dwarf pan-Arctic damages to infrastructure from thawing permafrost
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. The economic losses due to climate warming also tend to be higher in warmer poorer regions such as India and Africa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>, which are also less likely to benefit from the economic opportunities associated with a warmer Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
