<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current distribution of 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">harttii</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the current suitable distribution area for 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">harttii</span> (CPH) is south of the São Francisco river, where most published records are concentrated. Despite records in the coast of the Espírito Santo State (~ 19ºS) were not used in our analyses, that area is known as the southernmost distribution limit for the species [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref111" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref111">111</a>], with the highest percentage of CPH. That region coincides with a center of diversity within the Brazilian Province (20°S to 23°S), as indicated for benthic organisms, such as algae, invertebrates and fishes [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref121" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref121">121</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref122" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref122">122</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref123" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref123">123</a>]. That center is favored by the confluence of currents in the Brazilian coast, creating a transition zone between tropical and subtropical diversity [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>]. Despite a limited number of records of 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">harttii</span> and a smaller percentage of CPH to the north of the São Francisco River, the species is the main reef-builder northwards the São Francisco river [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref014">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most records of 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">harttii</span> are from shallow reefs, between 2 and 6 meters [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref120" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref120">120</a>] and consequently close to the coast. However, scattered records show this species occupying deeper reefs (up to 25 m) [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>] and even at mesophotic depths [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref020">20</a>]. Similarly, most of the CPH is concentrated in shallow waters (0–20 m), but with deeper suitable habitats commonly occurring, especially in the southern portion of species distribution. Most of current records of the species are within the Abrolhos Bank, in the East coast of Brazil (16°40′ – 19°40′S and 37°20′ – 39°10′ W), which harbour on of the most rich na extensive coral reef system in the South Atlantic [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref124" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref124">124</a>]. The area is composed by a mosaic of protected areas, as well as several distinct environments, such as biogenic reefs, euphotic and mesophotic reefs and rhodolith beds [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>]. The records are mainly concentrated in the shallow areas of the bank, but some came from southern deeper reefs, between 12 and 25 m (Espírito Santo State), a less studied area [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
