<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec011" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Visualization and Interpretation of ecological niche models</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predicting and mapping potential suitable habitats for threatened and endangered species is critical for monitoring and restoring their natural populations [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref091">91</a>]. In this sense, a modeling approach is an effective tool to predict the direction of contractions and expansions of species distribution [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref092">92</a>], producing probability maps for the presence or relative suitability of a species [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref093">93</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides elevated CPH validation indexes, literature data (not geo-referenced and therefore not used in the model) also record 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> in areas indicated by the model as suitable for the species, such as the southern portion of the Abrolhos bank (Espírito Santo State) [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>]. A model that fails to omit known points of presence is less accurate than those predicting unknown inhabited areas [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref095">95</a>]. These unknown areas provide a precise representation of the spatial extent of habitable conditions for the species [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref082">82</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the FPH of the species (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211171.g005" href="#pone.0211171.g005">Fig 5</a>) extends beyond the calibration area of the model (
   <span class="bold">M</span>), it was already expected an area of potential species habitat larger than the real distribution [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref065">65</a>]. Consequently, projections beyond the time interval of a training dataset (distribution in future dates) require cautious interpretations to avoid possible misinterpretations [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref096">96</a>]. Such caution is because AUC values tend to increase when the selected background area is larger than the observed current habitat of a species [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref097">97</a>]. Although the AUC values (close to 1) showed that the models performed very well with the results [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref090">90</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref091">91</a>] (better than any model generated with a set of random predictors [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref083">83</a>]), it was necessary to use a different approach to evaluate the models. In the AUC metric, the weight of commission errors is much lower than that of omission errors, which makes it an inappropriate performance measurement [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref098">98</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AUCratio also showed a good performance of the model, with values above 1 [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref082">82</a>] and close to 2. These results allowed us to evaluate the statistical significance of the AUC itself [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref098">98</a>]. In this way, it is more appropriate to evaluate the model performances [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref084">84</a>]. The thresholds used to generate the binary maps are best suited for applications in ecological niche templates [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref087">87</a>] [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref039">39</a>] by better predicting independent occurrence data [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref046">46</a>] [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref099">99</a>] [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref100">100</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental variables and 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii’s</span> habitat
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though the effects of each environmental variable on the population dynamics are unknown [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref101">101</a>], the variables chosen to model the habitat suitability for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> are in accordance with default conditions in previous studies on anthozoans [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref102">102</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current Potential Habitats for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> were mostly influenced by current velocity, bathymetry and temperature, respectively. Nutrient uptake in coral reefs is directly affected by current speeds [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref103">103</a>], which shape their distribution in both shallow and deep waters [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref104" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref104">104</a>]. The 
   <span class="bold">M</span> area is under the influence of the Brazilian and the North Brazilian Current [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref105" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref105">105</a>]. Studies on genetic connectivity with the genus 
   <span class="italic">Mussismilia</span> (
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">hispida</span>) showed that these currents may consist in a barrier to coral dispersal [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref106" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref106">106</a>]. In shallow reefs, currents cause constant sediment resuspension, which influences the coverage and composition of benthic organisms [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref107" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref107">107</a>], changing the visibility of water [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref108" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref108">108</a>], influencing the microbial community of corals [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref109" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref109">109</a>] and the behavior of the coral larvae during the nesting phase [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref110" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref110">110</a>]. Considering that most records of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> result from shallow reefs, it is expected that the species is rather influenced by sediment resuspension. Despite Brazilian corals as a whole are resistant to the input of terrigenous sediments and to relatively turbid waters 101], 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> has preference for clear waters, in which it is more abundant [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref111" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref111">111</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature, salinity and light have major effects on where reef-building corals grow [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref112" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref112">112</a>]. Despite the temperature showed the lowest contribution for the CPH, it is undoubtedly determinant for the future persistence of coral species, as 50% of these corals are threatened by climate changes [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref011">11</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref012">12</a>]. Our results also show the importance of temperature in the FPH for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span>. This species suffers thermal stress in temperatures higher than 31.0°C, leading to long-term damage or death [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref113" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref113">113</a>]. In fact, a recent study reported massive coral bleaching events in temperatures above 27° in Abrolhos reefs [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref114" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref114">114</a>], which concentrate most records of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> in the present study (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211171.g001" href="#pone.0211171.g001">Fig 1</a>). Climate change-related increase of temperature will affect wind regimes, ocean circulation and, consequently, precipitation and continental runoff, directly affecting the salinity in coastal waters [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref115" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref115">115</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref116" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref116">116</a>]. That may explain the spatial reduction in shallow waters projected in the FPH, and the increase in deeper zones. However, such habitat shifting can be related to several factors.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another important factor is the competition with algae (macroalgae and filamentous algae). These organisms dominate Brazilian benthic communities on reefs down to 15 m deep [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>]. Algae are favored by anthropic impacts, such as reduction of herbivorous/grazer fishes by overfishing, and increase of land nutrient discharges [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref118" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref118">118</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref119" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref119">119</a>]. Thus, in future scenarios, algae will likely continue to be favored, and its competition with corals tends to reduce coverage of the later in shallow waters. In contrast, besides less light availability, deeper areas would be less susceptible to the influence of runoff, temperature and salinity changes. Despite the lack of earlier baselines for Brazilian benthic communities, it is possible to affirm that the current scenario is result of a sum of anthropic impacts, as studies back in the 1960’s describe distinctive zonation and coverage in these communities [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref120" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref120">120</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec013" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current distribution of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the current suitable distribution area for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> (CPH) is south of the São Francisco river, where most published records are concentrated. Despite records in the coast of the Espírito Santo State (~ 19ºS) were not used in our analyses, that area is known as the southernmost distribution limit for the species [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref111" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref111">111</a>], with the highest percentage of CPH. That region coincides with a center of diversity within the Brazilian Province (20°S to 23°S), as indicated for benthic organisms, such as algae, invertebrates and fishes [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref121" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref121">121</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref122" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref122">122</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref123" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref123">123</a>]. That center is favored by the confluence of currents in the Brazilian coast, creating a transition zone between tropical and subtropical diversity [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>]. Despite a limited number of records of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> and a smaller percentage of CPH to the north of the São Francisco River, the species is the main reef-builder northwards the São Francisco river [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref014">14</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most records of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> are from shallow reefs, between 2 and 6 meters [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref120" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref120">120</a>] and consequently close to the coast. However, scattered records show this species occupying deeper reefs (up to 25 m) [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>] and even at mesophotic depths [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref020">20</a>]. Similarly, most of the CPH is concentrated in shallow waters (0–20 m), but with deeper suitable habitats commonly occurring, especially in the southern portion of species distribution. Most of current records of the species are within the Abrolhos Bank, in the East coast of Brazil (16°40′ – 19°40′S and 37°20′ – 39°10′ W), which harbour on of the most rich na extensive coral reef system in the South Atlantic [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref124" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref124">124</a>]. The area is composed by a mosaic of protected areas, as well as several distinct environments, such as biogenic reefs, euphotic and mesophotic reefs and rhodolith beds [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>]. The records are mainly concentrated in the shallow areas of the bank, but some came from southern deeper reefs, between 12 and 25 m (Espírito Santo State), a less studied area [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec014" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Mussismilia harttii</span>’s response to climate change by the end of the 21st century
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future distribution models (RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5) of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> showed expansion of suitable areas, towards deeper sites where there are few records of this species. Concomitantly, there was a reduction of suitable shallow water areas, especially at the northeast distribution limit, which suffered the greatest losses (Figs 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211171.g003" href="#pone.0211171.g003">3</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211171.g004" href="#pone.0211171.g004">4</a>). It is a more concerning fact if we consider that the species is the main reef-building coral in northeastern Brazilian reefs [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref014">14</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent study on 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref125" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref125">125</a>] estimates a decline of its populations in their current geographic range in shallow waters. Our results also indicate the same in a future scenario (RCP 8.5) with a loss of 98.5% of the current suitable area (~ 25480.7 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> in shallow waters (0–20 m), concentrated mainly in the northeast distribution of the species (
   <a rid="pone.0211171.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0211171.t003">Table 3</a>). Conversely, the results show a 1270% increase at deeper areas (50 m—75 m) in future scenario (RCP 4.5) (
   <a rid="pone.0211171.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0211171.t003">Table 3</a>). Thus, in a future scenario, the species would lose suitable habitats in coastal shallow sectors, followed by a gain of deeper habitats, which could serve as refugia in face of climate changes, if other environmental conditions such as luminosity, salinity and others are favorable [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref112" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref112">112</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Areas with potential habitat for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> outside the 
   <span class="bold">M</span> region in the two future scenarios, such as the northern coast of South America and the southern coast of Brazil, may be inaccessible due to geographic barriers for coral dispersion. These include colder water masses in the region of Cabo Frio (Rio de Janeiro), to the south [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref016">16</a>], and the plumes of São Francisco [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref126" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref126">126</a>] and the Amazon rivers [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref127" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref127">127</a>], to the north. In compensation, deeper potential habitats for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> within the 
   <span class="bold">M</span> region are mostly concentrated in the Abrolhos Bank, which might serve as refuge areas in future climate change scenarios.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec015" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deep sea refugia strategy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “deep reef refugia hypothesis” (DRRH) considers that coastal anthropic impacts and thermal stress effects are progressively reduced with depth [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref128" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref128">128</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref129" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref129">129</a>]. Therefore, mesophotic coral ecosystems, between 30 and 150 m, have been treated as important refugia for shallow reefs diversity [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref130" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref130">130</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref131" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref131">131</a>], temporarily supporting coral populations from shallow-reefs under stress conditions [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref132" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref132">132</a>]. Such areas would provide shelter in which these populations might persist in a long time [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref129" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref129">129</a>], and from which would subsequently expand [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref133" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref133">133</a>], recovering previously damaged areas [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref134" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref134">134</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reduction of shallow suitable areas and increase of deeper habitats suggest the potential of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> for using mesophotic reefs as refugia, ensuring its subsistence. However, the DRRH is more adequate for species with wide depth distribution ranges [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref117" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref117">117</a>] and presupposes larvae exchange between deep and shallow populations [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref135" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref135">135</a>], which have been demonstrated to be local and species-specific [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref136" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref136">136</a>]. Despite 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> is particularly representative in shallow waters (2–6 m), scattered records show this species occupying deeper reefs (up to 80 m) [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref020">20</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref094">94</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref137" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref137">137</a>] (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211171.s006" href="#pone.0211171.s006">S6 Appendix</a>), which reinforces the potential of the species to occupy deep mesophotic areas.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even showing wide depth ranges, connectivity between coral populations is not always continuous along bathymetric gradients [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref134" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref134">134</a>]. Consequently, it is still unknown if deeper populations of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> would serve as genetic stocks for shallow waters, as most of its deep records are sparse and rare [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref135" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref135">135</a>]. In any case, the expansion of deeper suitable areas may result in the expansion of deeper populations of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span>, regardless of the maintenance of coastal populations. In case of connectivity, such refugia would contribute for the recolonization of the coastal zone affected.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies using of global climate models mostly suggest that few shallow coral species will persist under a sea surface temperature increase of 2°C in the next one hundred years [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref138" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref138">138</a>]. Nevertheless, given the current slowness in mitigation measures, it is expected an increase of 3.1°C in the same period (RCP 8.5) [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref139" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref139">139</a>]. In such scenarios, identify and protect deep sea refugia must become priorities for species conservation [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref131" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref131">131</a>], considering the various factors defining a potentially true refuge [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref140" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref140">140</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Threats and perspectives for conservation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main global threats to coral species are related with greenhouse gas emissions (RCP), especially CO
   <sub>2</sub> [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref118" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref118">118</a>]. Effects of such impacts have lead to decline of biodiversity in reefs of Brazil and of the world, through increase of sea temperature and ocean acidification [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref011">11</a>]. Local impacts boost these effects through higher sedimentation, multiple biological invasions, bleaching, coral diseases and, consequently, loose of diversity on reef environments [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref011">11</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref141" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref141">141</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref142" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref142">142</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref143" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref143">143</a>]. Such impacts are frequently related to disorganized urban growth, pollution, messy tourism practices and overfishing [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref144" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref144">144</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref145" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref145">145</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref146" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref146">146</a>]. In the literature 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> used to be described as forming extensive bands on coastal reefs, showing colonies usually up to 1 m in diameter [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref120" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref120">120</a>]. Currently, this is a rare scenario for most of these reefs, which often have a low coral coverage, not corresponding the descriptions of the 1970’s.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental changes have triggered reorganizations in reef ecological relationships, zonation and dominance, in processes also called 
   <span class="italic">phase-shifts</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref147" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref147">147</a>]. In most reefs, for example, scleractinian dominance have been replaced mainly by macroalgae [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref119" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref119">119</a>], octocorals [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref148" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref148">148</a>], sponges [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref149" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref149">149</a>] and/or zoanthids [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref150" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref150">150</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref151" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref151">151</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref152" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref152">152</a>], the latter is the case of the Brazilian reefs [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref124" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref124">124</a>]. In these reefs, 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> is also threatened by the dominance of invasive species, such as 
   <span class="italic">Tubastraea</span> spp. [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref153" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref153">153</a>], which further compromises its resilience of shallow reefs.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The accelerated loss of biodiversity and habitats is one of the worst crisis of the present time, as evidenced by the ever increasing species red lists. All current and future scenarios showed herein alert for the relevance of the endemism and the role of 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> as a reef builder in Brazilian reefs. Currently, the species is classified as “in risk of extinction” [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref019">19</a>], and the perspective of reduction of suitable shallow areas highlight the urgency of priority conservation measures. Future environmental politics, therefore, must focus not only in the recovery of coastal populations, but also on the conservation of mesophotic coral ecosystems (MCE’s). Despite being less affected by climate changes, MCE’s are impacted by human activities, such as fisheries, mining and drilling [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref136" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref136">136</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref154" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref154">154</a>] and measures to protect deeper ecosystems should be prioritized in environmental policies for marine conservation, especially in Brazil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This research showed the efficiency of SDMs to predict areas with potential habitat to 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> in the present scenario and in two future scenarios for the end of the 21st century. The results showed a significant reduction of the area with potential habitat for the species. The largest area of the FPH for 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span> is concentrated in deeper waters, especially within the Abrolhos bank, one of the most important areas for biodiversity conservation in the South Atlantic [
   <a rid="pone.0211171.ref141" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref141">141</a>]. Despite having several protected areas, Abrolhos still suffers anthropic impacts, which tend to increase in the next decades, by activities such as port expansion, overfishing, mining and oil/gas extraction. Therefore, it is essential to ensure viable refuges not only for the endangered 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. 
   <span class="italic">harttii</span>, but for all Brazilian coral species, given the expected climate change scenarios. Thus, an expansion of protective measures focused on mesophotic reefs, especially in the Abrolhos Bank, is essential and urgent.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
