<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Occurrence records</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An extensive search was made in specialized literature (using the terms "Mussismilia", "harttii", "Brazil", and "Brasil"), with publications containing precise geographic information (latitude, longitude and/or georeferenced maps). Occurrence records with errors or lacking georeferenced were not used in the analyzes, resulting in a set of 147 records which were used to discuss the suitable areas provided by the models. The search focused on records of 
  <span class="italic">M</span>. 
  <span class="italic">harttii</span> from the last two decades, to reduce the loss of quality of data due to the action of time and dynamism in natural systems [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref045">45</a>]. Sometimes, these data may be influenced by drastic phenomena, such as the local extinction of species [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref046">46</a>] or changes in its distribution and abundance patterns [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref047">47</a>]. Sampling bias on occurrence data is also common in more accessible areas (more studied) because of regional interests [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref048">48</a>]. This may reduce the model's ability to predict independence of the spatial data [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref049">49</a>]. We used SDMtoolbox [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref050">50</a>] to filter occurrence data by environmental heterogeneity. This gradual filtering method is useful in studies with reduced numbers of occurrences and also avoids data with habitats with habitats other than the known occurrence of a species. [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref050">50</a>]. We calibrate the filter with radius of 5 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> for the raster of environmental heterogeneity, three numbers of heterogeneity of classes, maximum distance 25 km and minimum 5 km. At the end of the process, we obtained 102 (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211171.s001" href="#pone.0211171.s001">S1 Appendix</a>) occurrence records to calibration model (CPH) and projection (FPH). These filtered occurrence records were called modeling records (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211171.g001" href="#pone.0211171.g001">Fig 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species data collected 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span>, from reefs located in the States of Paraíba, Pernambuco, Alagoas, Bahia, as well as independent species presence data, were not used during the modeling process calibration model (CPH), but 
  <span class="italic">a posteriori</span> to evaluate the model. These occurrence records were filtered using the same procedure of the previous step. Finally, we obtained 33 filtered and independent records of the modeling records (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211171.s001" href="#pone.0211171.s001">S1 Appendix</a>). Validation with data independent from the model ensures greater robustness in its evaluation [
  <a rid="pone.0211171.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211171.ref051">51</a>]. These occurrence records are called evaluation records.
 </p>
</sec>
