<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Here we quantify changes in tree functional composition over the last century across a &gt;130,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> region in eastern Canada, at the ecotone between temperate and boreal forests (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a</xref>), and test the relative importance of climate change and anthropogenic disturbance as drivers of these changes. Over this time period, this region has experienced substantial changes in temperature and moisture (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b, c</xref>), and profound land-use changes linked to European settlement (i.e., rapid increase in disturbance rates due to the expansion of agriculture and industrial forestry
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>). We present a large dataset of early land survey observations (&gt;100,000 taxa lists recorded between 1790 and 1900; Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>) and modern forest inventories conducted during 1980–2010, both aggregated to a 25 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> grid (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref>). Under the hypothesis that climate change has been an important driver of forest dynamics, we test the prediction of a shift in forest composition toward more warm- and moisture-adapted tree species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>, and a positive correlation of the magnitude of such changes with the magnitude of change in temperature and moisture. Similarly, under the hypothesis that anthropogenic disturbance has driven forest change, we test the prediction of a shift toward more disturbance-adapted species, correlated with areas of more intense human influences. We quantified functional community composition using four indices (calculated using independent data) that represent the average affinities of co-occurring taxa with temperature (community temperature index (CTI)), drought (community drought tolerance index (CDTI)), light (community shade tolerance index (CSTI)) and disturbance (community disturbance index (CDI)). The latter two indices are expected to respond to disturbance negatively and positively, respectively. Changes in climate-related community indices were then tested for statistical relationships with changes from 1901 to 1980 in mean annual temperature (ΔTemperature, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref>) and in the standardized precipitation evapotranspiration index (ΔSPEI, a moisture index based on the balance between precipitation and potential evapotranspiration; Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1c</xref>). Changes in disturbance-related community indices were tested against changes in human population density since the early nineteenth century (ΔPopulation; Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1d</xref>), the latter being a good proxy for historical changes in land-use intensity. Overall, we show an overriding influence of anthropogenic disturbances compared to climate change in driving tree community dynamics since the nineteenth century, with disturbance-related changes potentially slowing or accelerating future community shifts in response to changes in temperature and precipitation.
</p>
