<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thawing and freezing of water bodies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between 2000 and 2014, the largest water bodies used by caribou went from mostly frozen to mostly thawed as early as May 13
  <span class="sup">th</span> (2010) and as late as June 13
  <span class="sup">th</span> (2004), with an average thawing date of May 28
  <span class="sup">th</span> (±8.8 days standard deviation, SD). Water bodies began freezing as early as November 9
  <span class="sup">th</span> (2002) and as late as November 26
  <span class="sup">th</span> (2005), with an average freezing date of November 19
  <span class="sup">th</span> (±5.1 days SD). Windows of opportunity during which ice was available for caribou ranged from a maximum of 201 days in 2009 to a minimum of 168 days in 2010. There was no statistically significant trend in thawing and freezing dates during this 15-year period (thawing: F = 0.50, df = 13, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.49; freezing: F = 0.13, df = 13, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.72; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Similarly, no statistically significant trend was observed for Lake Nichicun during the 1947–1985 period (see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>). Breakup dates of the largest lakes used by migratory caribou and Lake Nichicun were related to the NAO in May, whereas their freeze dates were related to the NAO in October and the AO in September (see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">4</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Trends in thawing and freezing dates for the largest water bodies used by migratory caribou. Thawing (
     <span class="italic">circles</span>) and freezing dates (
     <span class="italic">triangles</span>) were based on 8-day averaged MODIS values from 2000 to 2014. Values were truncated for the largest lakes, rivers, and reservoirs included in the range of the migratory Rivière-aux-Feuilles caribou herd (see list in Additional file 
     <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>). Regressions were: Thawing date = 930.4 ˗ 0.39(Year), and Freezing date = 94.9 + 0.11(Year)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40462_2016_79_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
