<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="tbl6" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Table 6</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Summary of statistical test results (Minitab v.15), using 2-tailed 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-tests (assuming normal distribution). The results of each duplicate analysis are included in order to provide a statistically significant sample size. Number in “Yes” column represents the number of amino acid (AA) fractions that enable discrimination between the two groups in question at a 95% confidence level. Number in “No” column represents the number of AA fractions that do not enable discrimination between the two sites at a 95% confidence level. For example, in the 2-tailed 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-tests, analysis of 
   <span class="italic">Bithynia</span> opercula results in ten out of ten AA fractions support the hypothesis that Cudmore Grove (CG) is distinguishable and younger than the sites correlated with MIS 11. The sites were selected because they have multiple lines of evidence that enable them to be correlated to a specific MIS. Full details of the statistical tests and further stratigraphical information and references associated with the sites are given in 
   <a rid="appseca1" ref-type="sec" href="#appseca1">Appendix 2</a>. EMR = East Mersea Restaurant Site.
  </p>
 </div>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th/>
    <th>Sites included in 2-tailed 
     <span class="italic">t</span>-test
    </th>
    <th>Yes</th>
    <th>No</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Is CG younger than sites correlated with MIS 11?</td>
    <td>Swanscombe, Clacton, Hoxne, Barnham, Elveden, Beeches Pit</td>
    <td align="char">10</td>
    <td align="char">0</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Is CG younger than sites correlated with MIS 9?</td>
    <td>Barling, Grays, Hackney, Purfleet</td>
    <td align="char">9</td>
    <td align="char">1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Is CG older than sites correlated with MIS 7?</td>
    <td>Lion Pit, Aveley</td>
    <td align="char">8</td>
    <td align="char">2</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Is EMR younger than sites correlated with MIS 7?</td>
    <td>Lion Pit, Aveley</td>
    <td align="char">10</td>
    <td align="char">0</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</div>
