<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measures</div>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implementation climate</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implementation climate was measured using the Implementation Climate Scale (ICS; 43). Providers reported about their team’s (i.e., their work group’s) implementation climate. Specifically, the referent for the respondent was the team, which was determined based on the service provider’s direct supervisor. The ICS is comprised of 18 items with and respondents are asked to respond regarding the degree to which they agree with each statement using response anchors from 0 (‘not at all’) to 4 (‘to a very great extent’). Items fall into six subscales: 1) Focus on EBP (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .90), 2) Educational support for EBP (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .84), 3) Recognition for EBP (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .78), 4) Rewards for EBP (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .81), 5) Selection for EBP (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .89), and 6) Selection for openness (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .85). The mean of the subscales was computed to create the ICS score (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .90). The complete ICS measure including scoring instructions can be found in the “additional files” accompanying the original measurement development study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://implementationscience.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13012-014-0157-1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://implementationscience.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13012-014-0157-1</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Service climate</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Service climate refers to employees’ perceptions of practices, procedures, and behaviors that are expected, rewarded, and supported with regard to customer service and customer service quality. To assess service climate, we used eight items adapted from Schneider and colleagues’ service climate measure (α = .91) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]. Items were modified to apply specifically to a SUD service setting. All service climate items were scored on a 0 (“poor”) to 4 (“excellent”) scale.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Organizational climate</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molar organizational climate was measuring using the Organizational Climate Measure (OCM; [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]). The OCM in its entirety consists of 17 scales capturing a broad range of molar organizational climate. Consistent with the original measurement development study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>], three of the 17 scales were used to examine construct-based validity. The three scales included in this study assessed climate for performance feedback (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .89, five items), involvement (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .88, six items), and efficiency (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .89, four items). OCM items were scored on a 0 (“not at all”) to 3 (“definitely true”) scale.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Organizational change</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Perceived Organizational Change (POC) measure [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>] was utilized to assess organizational change. The subscales planned change (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .80, three items) and psychological uncertainty (
   <span class="italic">α</span> = .91, four items) were used to examine construct-validity. POC items were scores on a 0 (“strongly disagree”) to 4 (“strongly agree”) scale.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
