<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We selected a set of ecologically relevant and minimally redundant environmental attributes as predictor variables in the SDMs (Table B in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0225128.s001">S1 File</xref>). The following bioclimatic predictors were used in the modeling process: annual mean temperature (TMEAN;°C), maximum temperature in the hottest month (TMAX;°C), minimum temperature in the coldest month (TMIN;°C), annual precipitation (PANN; mm), precipitation of wettest month (PMAX; mm) and precipitation of driest month (PMIN; mm). Temperature and precipitation have been chosen because they are the major climatic parameters determining the distribution of organisms on Earth [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. As ectotherms, temperature is one of the most fundamental variables influencing the physiology of fishes, influencing physiological condition, development, growth rates, reproduction and behavior [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Precipitation determines aquatic habitat availability and the seasonal variations of droughts and floods, synchronizing biological events of species, such as migration, spawning, home range shifts and growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. We also used the catchment topographic variable upstream flow path length (UFL) to represent variation in aquatic habitat availability [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and altitude (ALT). The bioclimatic variables representing current conditions were obtained from WORLDCLIM (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org</ext-link>) and for future times from CCAFS (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccafs-climate.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ccafs-climate.org</ext-link>; Research program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security), both with a spatial resolution of 30 arc-seconds (~1 km). Catchment topography and altitude were obtained from a 9 second digital elevation model (DEM; [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]). All variables were averaged according to the grid of 0.1° resolution for obtaining the environmental layers. Absolute Pearson’s correlation coefficients among predictor variables did not exceed 0.7.
</p>
