<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The complex societal challenges of climate change and sustainability are now key components of both national and international science strategies and are reflected in national and international funding mechanisms (The Royal Society 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2011</xref>). It has been widely recognised that tackling such global challenges will require collaboration across disciplines and between nations, to build research capacity, advance knowledge and generate potential solutions (Siedlok and Hibbert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2014</xref>; The Royal Society 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2011</xref>). Climate change is occurring against a backdrop of large scale and complex socio-economic change, including global population increases and dietary changes towards livestock products in the developing world (Thornton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">2010</xref>; Tilman and Clark 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2014</xref>). In this context, the agricultural sector is required to create and maintain sustainable production systems capable of ensuring food security in the long term while at the same time addressing the dual challenges of mitigating and adapting to a changing climate (Beddington 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2011</xref>; Lipper et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2014</xref>). Internationally, a wide range of initiatives are being developed to address these formidable challenges through coordination and collaboration between countries in research, policy and finance (Lipper et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2014</xref>). The Joint Programming Initiatives (JPI) of the European Commission are coordinating a European regional research agenda to increase the value of national research programmes (European Commission 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2015</xref>). Within this framework the JPI on Agriculture, Food Security and Climate Change (FACCE-JPI) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.faccejpi.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.faccejpi.com</ext-link>) has implemented the “knowledge hub” concept as a new instrument to facilitate and drive collaborative scientific research, in order to develop the coherence of purpose required to efficiently tackle urgent global and multi-sectorial problems such as climate change (Holzinger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2012</xref>; Soussana et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2012</xref>). Here, we aim to evaluate the potential of knowledge hubs to build community cohesion and hence facilitate interdisciplinary collaboration, by comparing the structure of the scientific community before and during the active period of MACSUR (Modelling European Agriculture with Climate Change for Food Security), the first FACCE-JPI Knowledge Hub.
</p>
