<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Female great tits expended more energy during egg laying under colder conditions and when their body mass was high. On average, earlier females will therefore spend more energy during egg laying due to the seasonal trend of increasing temperatures in spring. However, we found no difference in energy expenditure over a 24-h period during egg laying between early and late females measured on the same day, under the same weather conditions. The hypothesis that variation in laying date could be explained by differences in the relationship of temperature with energetic expenditure during egg laying between early and late birds was thus not confirmed.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To compare early with late females, we made use of the overlapping nature of egg laying periods. In our case, the difference in laying date between early and late laying females was 4 days. Although 4 days is a relatively short period compared to the total duration on which birds start egg laying (difference in laying date between the earliest bird vs. latest bird is ~30 days), the standard deviation of laying dates in 2008 was only 4.2 days. This means that 68.2% of all birds start egg laying in a period of 8.4 days only and thus that an interval of 4 days is biologically relevant.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though we found no intrinsic differences in energy expenditure between early and late breeding females, this does not mean that there are no differences in the fitness consequences of laying under cold conditions between early and late breeders. It is possible that variation in the fitness costs of energetic expenditure exists among females, potentially explaining variation in laying dates. Many examples exist in which an increased workload (for example by increasing the number of nestlings in a brood) negatively affects the survival of the parents (e.g. Dijkstra et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">1990</a>; Deerenberg and Overkamp 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1999</a>). However, to explain the maintenance in variation in laying dates from an optimality perspective, there have to be individual differences in fitness costs due to increased energetic expenditure. To our knowledge, this has never been demonstrated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results show that female great tits in Oosterhout expended more energy during egg laying than the Hoge Veluwe females. This difference could be caused by genetic differences between the populations [none of the 3,376 known breeding birds in Oosterhout were born in Hoge Veluwe and only two known breeding birds in Hoge Veluwe (out of 13,979 birds) were born in Oosterhout]. Alternatively, the between-site difference in energy expenditure could be due to differences in the timing of the caterpillar food peak. The Oosterhout population is situated on rich river clay soil compared to the sandy soil of the Hoge Veluwe. The difference in soil type is most likely why tree leafing is earlier in Oosterhout compared to the Hoge Veluwe, resulting in an earlier caterpillar food peak. This means that Oosterhout females have to lay eggs earlier (and under colder conditions; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) and thus expend more energy. Since great tits do not store large amounts of fat, maximum energy expenditure will directly depend on energy intake. From radio tracking data in both populations in the period before egg laying (L. te Marvelde and M.E. Visser, unpublished data), we know that females in Oosterhout often make use of the vast amount of supplementary bird food in the nearby village, whereas a food source like this is not available to the Hoge Veluwe population. The supplementary food in Oosterhout consists mainly of fat and peanuts; food full of energy but which does not contain the proteins needed for egg production. We have seen that females often visit the supplementary food for ~15 min after which they fly back to their territory to forage by hopping in the crown of the tree, most likely looking for (protein-rich) insects. The supplementary food then only serves as fuel that facilitates foraging for protein rich foods. As a consequence, they are able to work harder and therefore expend more energy compared to the Hoge Veluwe females.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A better understanding of the causes and consequences of variation in laying date among females is important as, due to climate warming, there is increased selection on laying date (Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2006</a>). Selection is influenced by, and potentially alters, the costs and benefits of the entire reproductive cycle, so we need to understand how females differ in their energetic costs (and in fitness consequences of these costs) not only during egg laying but also during other periods of the breeding cycle, such as chick feeding (te Marvelde et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2011b</a>). Understanding the proximate and ultimate factors maintaining variation among females will provide insight into patterns of phenotypic selection in natural populations.
 </p>
</sec>
