<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Doubly labelled water technique using eggs as samples</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The double labelled water technique enables us to measure DEE in free-living animals by measuring elimination rates of 
  <span class="sup">2</span>H and 
  <span class="sup">18</span>O which are enriched in the body water of the animal through injection (Speakman 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">1997</a>; see below). Instead of measuring elimination rates of 
  <span class="sup">2</span>H and 
  <span class="sup">18</span>O isotopes in blood samples (as is usually done), we measured elimination rates in the albumen of the eggs produced (as was done by Ward 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">1996</a>; Stevenson and Bryant 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2000</a>). This avoided recapture and handling stress in a period during which disturbance leads to high desertion rates (Kania 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">1989</a>). The period over which DEE is measured using this method depends on the exact timing after which water molecules can not freely move between the females’ body water pool and the water in the egg (i.e. the timing of which the egg shell is produced, separating the female body water pool from the water in the egg). Ward (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">1996</a>) studied the relationship between isotope concentrations in the albumen and blood for barn swallows (
  <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) and found that the average time of the day at which the water pools of female and egg separate was around 2245 hours. Although this timing is not known in great tits, it is the timing of separation 
  <span class="italic">within</span> a female over successive eggs which is important. No evidence exist that this timing differs between successive eggs 
  <span class="italic">within</span> a female’s laying sequence. Values of DEE found in this study are comparable to DEE values during egg laying found by Stevenson and Bryant (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2000</a>) and are about 2.5 times BMR, which was calculated with equation 5.1 in Kendeigh et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">1977</a>) for the average body mass of a female great tit of our dataset (19.6 g), which falls well within the range of DEE/BMR-ratios found for this and other species (King 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">1974</a>; Daan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1990</a>; Peterson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">1990</a>) in other parts of the breeding season.
 </p>
</sec>
