<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest boxes were checked twice a week from the beginning of April to monitor nest building. Once the bottom of the box was covered with nest material, nests were checked daily to determine exact laying dates. Eggs were numbered on the day they were laid. Female great tits were caught when leaving the nest box early in the morning, soon after egg laying using temporarily placed ‘box nets’ (te Marvelde et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2011a</a>). Immediately after catching, each female was injected intraperitoneally with 200 μl DLW using a 0.3-ml syringe with a 0.33 × 12 mm needle. After injecting, the female was weighed to the nearest 0.1 g and then released (usually within 10 min after catching). Early females were caught and injected with DLW on the morning they laid their sixth egg (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 25), whereas late females were injected in the morning they laid their second egg (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 18). The day after the injection, the third egg of a late and the seventh egg of an earlier female were collected. The next day, we collected the fourth and the eighth egg of those females. Because we can only capture the female the morning after we detect the first egg, the earliest measurement of DEE is the 24 h between the production of the third and the fourth egg. For the early females, we chose the eighth egg as a last sample since not all females produce more than eight eggs. All eggs taken as samples were replaced immediately by unbrooded eggs from a nearby study site to prevent the production of replacement eggs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">About 12 h after collection, the length, width and mass of the eggs were measured and the yolk and the albumen were separated and weighed to the nearest mg in the laboratory. The albumen was homogenised by hand and three samples of ~15 μl were transferred to non-heparinised 25-μl capillaries which were flame-sealed immediately.</p>
</sec>
