<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Adv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Adv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SciAdv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">advances</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Science Advances</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2375-2548</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6594768</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">aav0474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.aav0474</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>SciAdv r-articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>Applied Ecology</subject><subject>Oceanography</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Applied Ecology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Global ecosystem overfishing: Clear delineation within real limits to production</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2740-7161</contrib-id><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>Jason S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>Reg A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="award" rid="award416625"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, National Marine Fisheries Service, 166 Water Street, Woods Hole, MA 02543, USA.</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Institute for Marine and Antarctic Studies, University of Tasmania, Private Bag 129, Hobart, TAS 7001, Australia.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Corresponding author. Email: <email xlink:href="jason.link@noaa.gov">jason.link@noaa.gov</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>eaav0474</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 The Authors, some rights reserved; exclusive licensee American Association for the Advancement of Science. No claim to original U.S. Government Works. Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial License 4.0 (CC BY-NC).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" id="p-2"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial license</ext-link>, which permits use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, so long as the resultant use is <bold>not</bold> for commercial advantage and provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Newly derived thresholds show that about half the world&#x02019;s marine ecosystems are experiencing &#x0201c;ecosystem&#x0201d; overfishing.</p></abstract><abstract><p>The well-documented value of marine fisheries is threatened by overfishing. Management typically focuses on target populations but lacks effective tools to document or restrain overexploitation of marine ecosystems. Here, we present three indices and accompanying thresholds to detect and delineate ecosystem overfishing (EOF): the Fogarty, Friedland, and Ryther indices. These are based on widely available and readily interpreted catch and satellite data that link fisheries landings to primary production using known limits of trophic transfer efficiency. We propose theoretically and empirically based thresholds for each of those indices; with these criteria, several ecosystems are fished sustainably, but nearly 40 to 50% of tropical and temperate ecosystems exceed even extreme thresholds. Applying these criteria to global fisheries data results in strong evidence for two specific instances of EOF, increases in both pressure on tropical fish and a climate-mediated polar shift. Here, we show that these two patterns represent evidence for global EOF.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award416625"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000923</institution-id><institution>Australian Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>DP140101377</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Anne Suarez</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Fisheries are an important part of the global economy. The fisheries sector represents &#x0003e;15% of the blue economy sector, exports are valued at &#x0003e;150 US$ Billion, and contributes 57 million jobs globally (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). In addition to trade and jobs, fish provide the primary, consistent source of protein to more than 35% of the world&#x02019;s population and more than 50% in least developed countries and account for one-fifth of all global protein sources, 6.7% of all protein consumed, a daily per capita of 34 calories, and an annual average of 20 kg of food (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Approximately 30 to 35% of fish populations are fished unsustainably, with an additional 60% fully fished (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). The implications of unsustainable fisheries extend beyond simple status of fish populations and economic viability of fisheries to global food security, cultural survival, and even national security (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Not only are fish populations, fleets, and fishery systems affected by unstainable fishing (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>) but this also results in much broader impacts on marine ecosystems (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>). To address many of these challenges simultaneously, a broader, more systematic means of detecting and delineating overfishing, before it sequentially affects fish population after fish population, fishery after fishery, and marine ecosystem functioning, is warranted (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>).</p><p>Marine fishes and ecosystems experience overfishing. Most measures of overfishing address individual fish populations (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>); however, governance systems also need to address the wider aspect of ecosystem overfishing (EOF; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>). Clear definitions and demarcations of single stock (i.e., population) overfishing are well developed (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref> and fig. S1) (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>). Although there are attempts to quantitatively characterize the impacts of EOF (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>), few have clear thresholds and delineation of EOF (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>), and no definitions are widely used. In the less-developed world, the capacity to conduct monitoring, management, and enforcement of fisheries is notably lacking, thus some easily estimable EOF measures would be valuable. For developed countries, the question is whether emphasis on excessive population detail has resulted in eroding overall population and ecosystem condition, as well as missed opportunities (i.e., we miss the forest for the trees; e.g., even reasonable single species Total Allowable Catches can exceed system-level carrying capacity and lead to overfishing) (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>). It would be valuable to have a means whereby a nation or sector could assess whether it is experiencing EOF, in a way that other nations could also evaluate to readily determine whether there is compliance. A solid international definition of EOF, one that is not based on stock assessment models, assumptions of steady-state maximum sustainable yield (MSY), copious data, nor excessive monitoring requirements would be extremely valuable, especially as global ocean conditions continue to change. Here, we define EOF as an instance where the sum of all catches is flat or declining, total catch per unit effort (CPUE) is declining, and total landings relative to ecosystem production exceeds suitable limits.</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Schematic of stock and EOF.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of population overfishing. While a population is experiencing overfishing, the abundance and biomass (here as the number of fish icons) and fish size declines over time, along with many other facets related to population and fleet dynamics. (<bold>B</bold>) Schematic of EOF. Analogous to population overfishing, EOF is the result of continued fishing pressure on multiple populations, leading to sequential depletion across populations in an ecosystem over time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aav0474-F1"/></fig><p>Here, we propose three novel indicators to ascertain the occurrence of EOF, the Ryther index, Fogarty index, and Friedland index. These are based on the ecological principle of trophic transfer, with specific thresholds developed for each index to delineate whether EOF is actually occurring. The Ryther index is composed of total catch presented on a unit area basis for an ecosystem. The Fogarty index is the ratio of total catches to total primary productivity in an ecosystem. The Friedland index is the ratio of total catches to chlorophyll in an ecosystem. The proposed thresholds are based on facets of carrying capacity limits to production of communities of fish populations, limited by trophic transfer efficiencies (TEs) (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>). In essence, we are espousing the basic tenet of renewable natural resource management, such that any harvest meets the condition of <italic>R</italic><sub>removal</sub> &#x02264; <italic>R</italic><sub>renewal</sub> for each rate (<italic>R</italic>). Using known limits to ecosystem production (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>), we posit estimated limits to global and regional fishery production.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Indicator thresholds and geographically specific responses</title><p>Current observations coupled with simple, theoretical estimates of catches imply that the Ryther index should probably be on the order of 0.3 to 1.1 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> or practically not to exceed (NTE) ~1 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, with an extreme limit NTE 3 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Previously empirically derived tipping points typically occur in fished ecosystems with total catches greater than 3 to 5 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>), with expected system-wide MSYs on the order of 1 to 3 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>). For now, we propose a Ryther index threshold of ~1 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> to delineate EOF, consistent with this range of reported and derived results (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>The three novel indicators of ecosystem overfishing for major latitudinal bands.</title><p>Values of the potential measures to delineate EOF; the Ryther index (<bold>A</bold>), the Fogarty ratio index (<bold>B</bold>), and the Friedland ratio index (<bold>C</bold>) for all of the five latitudinal bands. The solid black line represents the proposed threshold (for the Friedland ratio; data are below the threshold for Ryther and Fogarty indices and thus is not shown). N Temp, northern temperate zone; S Temp, southern temperate zone.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aav0474-F2"/></fig><p>As expected, Fogarty ratio of 0.22 to 0.92 per mil (&#x02030;), or practically NTE ~1&#x02030;, with an extreme limit NTE of ~2.5&#x02030; emerges from theoretically based limits coupled with estimates of global catches. Previously modeled and empirical estimates suggested that catches relative to primary production (PP) exceeding 1 to 2&#x02030; resulted in a tipping point (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><italic>13</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>). For now, we propose a Fogarty index threshold of ~1&#x02030; to delineate EOF, consistent with this range of reported and derived results (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>). Using logic similar to the Fogarty ratio, we propose a threshold for the Friedland index NTE ~1 to delineate EOF (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>).</p><p>Examining these indices by latitudinal band (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>) reveals that no latitudes exceed the Ryther index threshold, although the Arctic and north temperate regions are within the range of what could possibly be considered fully fished or overfished if a lower threshold were used (i.e., &#x0003e;0.3 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Increasingly, the tropical band is approaching that level. Similar to the Ryther index, the Fogarty ratio indicates that no region is above the threshold (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B</xref>), with both the Arctic and north temperate regions well within the range of what could be considered fully fished (i.e., &#x0003e;0.25&#x02030;). The Friedland ratio indicates that the north temperate and tropical bands are above the threshold (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2C</xref>) potentially experiencing EOF. The Friedland ratio for the Arctic and south temperate regions are around 0.3 to 0.5, indicating that they are not likely experiencing EOF. The Antarctic region exhibits low values for all three indices, likely reflective of both limited data availability and difficult-to-access fisheries. From all three indices (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), the general picture for major latitudinal bands is that most places are not experiencing EOF, but the tropics and north temperate regions may be close to an EOF threshold depending upon the index examined (e.g., Friedland ratio) or level of threshold one uses.</p><p>Recognizing the absolute scale of global ocean areas, all portions of which may not be entirely fished (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><italic>22</italic></xref>), it is important to examine these three indicators at the more resolved large marine ecosystem (LME) scale. Presenting representative examples from each region (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, A to C</xref>), it is clear that many tropical and temperate LMEs are experiencing EOF according to the Ryther index, with many ecosystems experiencing catch rates of &#x0003e;5 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and many (especially in the tropics) are experiencing over 8 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Those are well above even the extreme threshold of 3 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The polar regions also have some LMEs potentially experiencing EOF; many have a Ryther index between 1 and 3 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The Ryther index threshold of 1 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> may be a low value for delineating EOF, and even 3 to 5 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> would indicate a high degree of EOF, nearing theoretically extreme values. Of the 65 LMEs, using the threshold of 1 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the Ryther index, 12 of 20 tropical regions (60.0%), 14 of 26 temperate regions (53.8%), and 5 of 17 polar regions (29.4%) are experiencing EOF.</p><fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>The three novel indicators of ecosystem overfishing, for example large marine ecosystems in the tropical, temperate, and polar regions.</title><p>Values of the potential measures to delineate EOF; the Ryther index (<bold>A</bold> to <bold>C</bold>), the Fogarty ratio index (<bold>D</bold> to <bold>F</bold>), and the Friedland ratio index (<bold>G</bold> to <bold>H</bold>) for representative examples of the 65 LMEs that had an index above one of the noted threshold values (black lines) at some point during the time series. Not all of the 65 LMEs are shown. The solid black line represents the proposed threshold.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aav0474-F3"/></fig><p>The Fogarty index (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, D to F</xref>) exhibits similar patterns to the Ryther index. Here, the number of ecosystems experiencing EOF is not as high as the Friedland ratio (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, G to I</xref>) or even the Ryther index (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, A to C</xref>) relative to their proposed thresholds. Yet, several LMEs exhibit Fogarty ratios of 2 to 3&#x02030;, an indication of probable EOF and approaching the extreme threshold. Of the 65 LMEs, using the threshold of 1&#x02030; for the Fogarty index, 6 of 20 tropical regions (30.0%), 10 of 26 temperate regions (38.5%), and 5 of 17 polar regions (29.4%) are experiencing EOF. The Friedland index confirms the results of the other indices, yet all example tropical and most temperate regions exhibit EOF according to this index (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, G to I</xref> ). Many polar regions also exhibit EOF according to the Friedland ratio. It may be because the Friedland threshold of 1 is too low, the index is too sensitive, or the catches overshadow chlorophyll values; however, even given these caveats, the potential for EOF appears much greater in the tropics, given the magnitude of this index there (~10 to 20) compared to the temperate (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>) and polar (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>) regions. Of the 65 LMEs, using a threshold of ~1 for the Friedland index, 15 of 20 in tropical regions (75.0%), 19 of 26 temperate regions (73.1%), and 4 of 17 polar regions (23.5%) are experiencing EOF.</p><p>The occurrence of EOF in LMEs is consistently detected across all indicators. Of particular note are some Southeast Asian LMEs, with values much higher than even the most extreme proposals for thresholds, aligning with what we know about these ecosystems (see the Supplementary Materials). Like all the data herein, these results are subject to the vagaries of misreporting, Illegal, Unreported, and Unregulated (IUU) catches, and the usual challenges of global databases (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>). Those LMEs and broader regions noted here as likely experiencing EOF are generally the same ones identified as being susceptible to higher fishing pressure in global studies using other proxies for fishing-induced ecosystem-level perturbation, including PP required (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>), the L index and probability of sustainability (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>), size spectra parameters (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>) or cumulative biomass, and trophic level (TL) and cumulative production curves (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>). They also correspond to those ecosystems with well-documented histories of sequential population overfishing (cf. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E3">Eq. 3</xref>). Here, we have an independent, readily estimable threshold to determine whether these LMEs are experiencing EOF.</p><p>The polar regions have experienced the least number of LMEs with EOF, but even then still exhibit several LMEs with indications of EOF occurring. The tropics consistently have the highest proportion of LMEs with EOF across these indices. More so, the tropics have seen the number of LME experiencing EOF increase over time (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, A, D, and G</xref>). The temperate regions also have a high number of LMEs experiencing EOF, with ~40 to 50% exhibiting such a pattern. Hence, the temperate regions have limited capability to absorb shifting fishing pressure from the tropics (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Evidence for global Ecosystem Overfishing: Two specific instances</title><p>Given the definitions of EOF, coupled with the three indicator thresholds for both latitudinal and LME-parsed catches, we examined the collective evidence to determine to what extent EOF may be occurring at a global level. First, we see that tropical pressure on fisheries is increasing. Unlike the polar regions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>) and temperate regions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>), total catches in the tropics have increased over time (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). The continual expansion of tropical fishing is such that fishing signatures are seen at every longitude (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). The longitudinal spread of catches in the tropics has and continues to expand (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>). The area fished is now greatest in the tropics (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>), although this region&#x02019;s fleets are composed primarily of smaller vessels (i.e., &#x0003c;20 m) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><italic>29</italic></xref>). The effort in the tropics is expanding (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>) (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>), such that the highest rate of increase in effort is seen in the tropics (Fig. 4F) (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). The collective CPUE in the tropics has decreased over time, declining by 50 to 80% from the 1950&#x02013;1960s to 2010s (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4G</xref>) (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). In addition, the mean size of individual fishes remains small in the tropics and is actually declining (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><italic>30</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><italic>31</italic></xref>). The valuation of fish caught in the tropics has slightly declined (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><italic>32</italic></xref>). In addition, fish food security has notably declined in the tropics (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). In tropical latitudes, this evidence collectively fits the pattern one would observe for EOF in any given ecosystem. Certainly, not all tropical ecosystems are experiencing EOF, but many are based on the three indices and ancillary information noted, consistent with EOF (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref> and fig. S1). The fraction of LMEs thought to be experiencing EOF is high in temperate regions but is highest in tropical regions (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3, A, D, and G</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Multiple characterizations of global fishing and fisheries catch demonstrating core criteria of EOF for different regions, with a particular demonstration of polar fishery stasis and increases in tropical fishing.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Total, global marine capture fisheries catch of all taxa over time. Total marine capture fisheries catch of all taxa over time, as integrated into major latitudinal bands; polar (<bold>B</bold>), temperate (<bold>C</bold>), and tropical (<bold>D</bold>). All latitudinal bands have data from both northern and southern hemispheres. (<bold>E</bold>) The width at each latitudinal band (four examples given) at which total average annual marine capture fisheries catch exceeded 60 t km<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. (<bold>F</bold>) Total fishing effort for exemplary latitudinal bands over time. (<bold>G</bold>) Total CPUE by latitudinal band over time. (<bold>H</bold>) The proportion of global fish catch in latitudinal bands over time. These are presented in approximate widths as degrees of longitude.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aav0474-F4"/></fig><fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Global patterns in total fisheries catches from over more than 50 years as seen in three example stanzas.</title><p>Total average annual marine capture fisheries catch (including estimates of illegal unreported and discards) of all taxa for 1950&#x02013;1959 (<bold>A</bold>), 1970&#x02013;1979 (<bold>B</bold>), and 2010&#x02013;2014 (<bold>C</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aav0474-F5"/></fig><p>Second, we see a polar shift occurring in fish populations, yet without an, as yet, concurrent shift in their associated fisheries. It is well documented that fish populations are shifting poleward (<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><italic>29</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><italic>33</italic></xref>), consistent with expectations from climate change impacts. Contrary to this well-documented shift in fish distribution, fisheries catches are not similarly shifting poleward (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4, B, C, and H</xref>; and <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>). The total polar (and temperate) catch is flat (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4, B and C</xref>), and the proportion of the total catch is shifting from the poles to the tropics (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4H</xref> and <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The effort in polar regions is also predominantly flat (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>) (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>) . Thus, CPUE in polar regions is decreasing by a factor of 20 to 40% from the 1960s&#x02013;1970s to 2010s (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4G</xref>) (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). The point is not that polar catches and effort are necessarily declining or projected to decline but rather that the tropical fleets that target tropical populations are not latitudinally following the generally poleward shift in tropical or temperate fish population distributions. Some LMEs in the polar regions are experiencing EOF (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3, C, F, and I</xref>), but the fraction of LMEs thought to be experiencing EOF is lowest in polar regions.</p><p>Combining both the polar shift and expanded tropical pressure, we can infer a global occurrence of EOF, with particular impact on the tropics. Fish populations (and productivity) are shifting out of the tropics at a time when effort there is increasing (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>). The proportion of catch in the tropics is increasing (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4H</xref>). Total CPUE is still notably lower there than in temperate or polar regions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4G</xref>) (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Although the total catch in the tropics is increasing (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4D</xref>), it is still not at the level as in temperate regions (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>). The expansion of the amount (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4F</xref>) and extent (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4E</xref>) of effort are greatest in the tropics (and may continue to grow) (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). This implies a notable increase in fishing pressure in the tropics that is not ameliorated via shifting fishing effort into other latitudinal bands. Thus, CPUE is declining both the most and the fastest in the tropics (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4G</xref>); the decline in CPUE in the polar and temperate regions over the past 60+ years has ranged from 20 to 40%, whereas in the tropics, it is 50 to 80% (Fig. 4G) (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Even if tropically oriented fleets were able to shift latitudes (crossing marine exclusive economic zone claims), it remains unclear whether temperate regions could absorb shifts from the tropics, given that many temperate regions are also experiencing EOF, and catches there have been flat for &#x0003e;30 years (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4C</xref>), with many of the fleets generating much of the fishing effort originating in those regions (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>). Both the latitudinal bands and LME examinations of EOF imply that the tropics are increasingly experiencing EOF.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Collectively, the three indices proposed here attempt to define and delineate thresholds of EOF. Hence, they are a potential international standard for tracking fisheries ecosystem status. Being able to clearly and consistently identify EOF is not insignificant. We assert that the approach proposed here would help in even (extremely) data poor situations. These indices are easily estimable, are based on widely repeated and available data, are readily interpretable, and are a pragmatic attempt to identify when an ecosystem would be experiencing EOF based on well-understood and well-accepted PP and food web limitations. These indices are able to accommodate a dynamic ocean, particularly as two of these indices link directly to measures of primary productivity. Detecting overfishing at an ecosystem level would also help to avoid many of the corollary impacts we have seen when managing fished taxa on a population-by-population basis (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>) and holds promise for detecting major signals more rapidly (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>) by establishing shifts in ecosystem and fisheries productivity much more quickly than piecing together any such shifts together in a meta-analysis from a population-by-population basis.</p><p>One could easily envision that if these catch values exceed the thresholds proposed here, or certainly the theoretically extreme thresholds, then the appropriate action to minimize EOF could be enacted in an ecosystem. There would obviously need to be a local policy choice regarding the level of EOF threshold (as proposed here, the theoretical maximum, something more precautionary, etc.) established in a given jurisdiction, but the estimates thereof would be relatively straightforward to delineate EOF. However, if an ecosystem is determined to be overfished, what specific action/s could be taken? At one level, the solution is simple&#x02014;that is, lower fishing pressure. Yet, at another level, the solution is complicated, with many social, economic, ecological, and even existence considerations. Enacting management to ultimately lower fishing pressure has many potential avenues (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>), and all should be explored given a local or regional context. The salient point here is that the value of having international standards would be that any party could obtain and calculate these estimates from readily available sources, and if the ratios exceeded the commonly noted threshold, then a clear agreement and obvious consensus on whether overfishing was occurring, or not, would then not be debatable. Rather, what appropriate actions to best mitigate EOF would be (specifically via particular management measures, beyond generally a lowering of fishing pressure) open for discussion and that would shift the burden of proof to one that would better emphasize sustainability.</p><p>Does this evidence for EOF have a solid theoretical underpinning? From the trophic transfer relationship (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E5">Eq. 5</xref>), catches increase when fish are targeted at lower TLs, TE is higher, or primary productivity (PP) is higher. What we see is that, in tropical regions, although TL of catches is declining (leading to &#x02191;<italic>C</italic>) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref>), the TE is declining (i.e., &#x02193;<italic>C</italic>) (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>) and PP is shifting (i.e., &#x02193;<italic>C</italic>) (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>). Thus, the theoretical net effect is less potential catch in tropical regions, confirming the trends observed. Conversely, in polar regions, we see that, although TL of catches is increasing (i.e., &#x02193;<italic>C</italic>) (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>), both TE is increasing (i.e., &#x02191;<italic>C</italic>) (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>) and PP is shifting to that region (i.e., &#x02191;<italic>C</italic>) (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>). Certainly, some taxa could obtain much of their energetic requirements in other ecosystems and migrate into a different ecosystem whereupon they would be caught; however, in these instances (e.g., straddling stocks and highly migratory species), it would be advisable to consult these indices in adjacent ecosystems. As a percentage of LMEs or taxa, and given the large areas of most LMEs, these would be exceptions to the general patterns of EOF detected herein. Given this caveat, the theoretical net effect is more potential catch in polar regions, again confirming observed trends. Furthermore, other potential measures of EOF using similar theoretical underpinnings (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>) and other criteria (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>) all generally confirm the results shown here, particularly in the tropical latitudinal band, even without the clear thresholds presented here. Thus, EOF is not expected to occur everywhere, but is expected to increase in prevalence at lower latitudes, and likely to exceed the proposed thresholds.</p><p>EOF is not occurring in every marine ecosystem, but it is widespread. Any instance of EOF has implications that collectively, and by definition, are not positive. In some instances, the ramifications of EOF are likely to be severe, potentially even leading to crisis. These instances are particularly acute in the tropics. The potential for strong impacts from EOF in the tropics, in terms of degraded economies, loss of stability and capacity of governance, food security, cultural identity, national security, and, in some instances, existence (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>) are clearly heightened by our results and clarified by the indices we propose. Conversely, this approach could perhaps identify specific regions with further potential fisheries production to ameliorate these tropical concerns.</p><p>The extent of EOF in many ecosystems and over a large proportion of the world&#x02019;s oceans is highly consequential and not trivial. Our proposed delineations provide an opportunity to establish international standards of what constitutes EOF and hence thresholds for action exceeded. Only when we can define and identify EOF can we begin to address it.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Defining (ecosystem) overfishing</title><p>The dynamics of single population overfishing are well chronicled; as catch (<italic>C</italic>) declines, effort (<italic>E</italic>) increases, which is then repeated<disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CPUE</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(1)</label></disp-formula></p><p>This is Graham&#x02019;s &#x0201c;Law of Overfishing&#x0201d; (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><italic>40</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><italic>41</italic></xref>) implying that as CPUE declines, an increasing amount of time is spent fishing in an increasingly larger area. For an individual population, as the fishing rate (<italic>F</italic>) increases mortality up to an unknown maxima, while numbers of fish (<italic>N</italic>), biomass of the population (<italic>B</italic> or <italic>B</italic> at MSY), mean size (usually length), mean weight at age, mean size and age at maturity, fecundity, recruitment (<italic>r</italic>), somatic and population growth (<italic>g</italic>), productivity, and ultimately yield (<italic>Y</italic>) all decrease (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>)<disp-formula id="E2"><mml:math id="m2"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>yields</mml:mtext></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="center" displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>MSY</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>size</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>mat</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>age</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>mat</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">wt</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">len</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="center" displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Area</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>fished</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mtext>MSY</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(2)</label></disp-formula></p><p>As this occurs, the area fished and effort to catch fish increase, resulting in a fishing rate that exceeds that for MSY (<italic>F</italic>/<italic>F</italic><sub>MSY</sub> &#x0003e; 1). There are various caveats to this regarding growth or recruitment overfishing (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>), but the general patterns hold based on population dynamic theory. This theory and practice of population overfishing have well-demarcated features (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>), which lead to relatively clear thresholds of overfishing and overfished population status, important decision criteria for fisheries management.</p><p>The typical yield curve (fig. S1) demonstrates that fishing effort has an optimal level of catches, with anything exceeding that resulting in overfishing. Several properties of this curve, or proxies thereof, are used to set fishing thresholds. Translating fishing effort into fishing rates has led to the relationship whereby <italic>F</italic>/<italic>F</italic><sub>MSY</sub> &#x0003e; 1 (or proxies of <italic>F</italic><sub>MSY</sub>; e.g., <italic>F</italic><sub>0.1</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>35%</sub>, etc.) is defined as overfishing, often used as a threshold in conjunction with estimates of biomass or productivity [biological reference point (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>)]. This implies a sustainable level of harvesting with biomass at ~50% of carrying capacity, with associated thresholds for <italic>B</italic>. In other words, the fishing effort should be at a rate that is less than the rate of fish production to maintain the population.</p><p>Most measures of overfishing have focused on individual fish populations (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref> and fig. S1), yet governance systems need to address the wider aspects of EOF (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>). There have been several attempts to quantitatively characterize the impacts of EOF (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><italic>13</italic></xref>). However, there are few, if any, with clear thresholds and delineation of EOF (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>) and no definitions that are widely used. By extending definitions of single-species overfishing, we posit that there is an analogous suite of overfishing dynamics for ecosystems (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>). As individual population <italic>C</italic> declines and <italic>E</italic> increases, such that CPUE ultimately declines beyond what is economically viable for a given population, <italic>C</italic> shifts toward a second, less preferred species, and the cycle then repeats itself ad infinitum<disp-formula id="E3"><mml:math id="m3"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CPUE</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>min</mml:mtext><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CPUE</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>CPUE</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>min</mml:mtext><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(3)</label></disp-formula></p><p>Overall, <italic>C</italic> in the ecosystem increases until CPUE declines, escalating to the point of systemic degradation. This is the Law of Sequential Depletion (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><italic>41</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>), a corollary to Graham&#x02019;s Law of Overfishing (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><italic>40</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><italic>41</italic></xref>). The cycle of CPUE implies an expansion of both geographic and taxonomic scopes as fleets pursue more and more distinct types of biomass in more and more distinct and distant habitats to maintain economically viable levels of CPUE (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><italic>22</italic></xref>). For the system of populations, as total <italic>C</italic> (or <italic>E</italic>) increases as integrated across all species, the mean size (usually some measure of length), total <italic>B</italic>, and total yield decline, whereas the size spectrum slope (&#x003b2;) increases (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>). Besides the facets noted above (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E2">Eq. 2</xref>), occurring across all species, other composite impacts are also observed. The species composition changes, and thus biodiversity may change, but not always in a predictable manner as, by definition, any particular diversity estimate can result from multiple responses to a range of changes in multiple configurations of species composition. These caveats aside, the principles of sequential depletion generally hold as based on theories from community ecology in a perturbation context (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>). For energy flow and food webs affected by fisheries, as overall <italic>C</italic> (or <italic>E</italic>, or <italic>F</italic>) increases, the L index, total system throughput, system ascendancy (<italic>A</italic>), <italic>B</italic> of apex predators of conservation significance, cumulative <italic>B</italic> inflection points, cumulative <italic>P</italic>, mean TL, and system redundancy (<italic>R</italic>) all decline (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>). Disruption in trophic linkages also typically occurs [e.g., forage fishes (<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>)]<disp-formula id="E4"><mml:math id="m4"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>system</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>yields</mml:mtext></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="center" displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mtext>apex</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">cumB</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>infl</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">cumP</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mtext>index</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TST</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">TL</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="center" displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Area</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>fished</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mtext>system</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mtext>system MSY</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(4)</label></disp-formula></p><p>Similar to the single population instance, as this occurs, the area fished and effort to catch all fish increase, resulting in a system-level fishing rate that exceeds that for MSY of the system (<italic>F</italic><sub>system</sub>/<italic>F</italic><sub>systemMSY</sub> &#x0003e; 1). In essence, one can extend the typical yield curve from an individual population to an entire system of fishes (fig. S1), with the same general properties and relationships. Doing so, links all fisheries removals to the nominal carrying capacity of the ecosystem. In other words, fishing effort should be at a rate that is less than the rate of ecosystem production required to maintain the aggregate of all fished taxa. Several example calculations have estimated these multispecies, aggregate, or system-wide MSYs (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>), but although extant, their use as thresholds has been quite limited in practice. We propose analogous thresholds but ones that are based on a more direct relationship to ecosystem productivity.</p><p>We acknowledge that there are many other potential facets of EOF relating to habitat, bycatch, biodiversity, apex predators, ecosystem functioning, etc. (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1B</xref>) (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>). Yet, we emphasized trophic transfer as a basis for determining the limits of fisheries production as that is intuitive, has had copious background studies establishing and describing these relationships (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>), and most population-oriented definitions of overfishing similarly focus on production of the population while acknowledging that other facets of population productivity do not typically use those other features (i.e., links to habitat, predation, etc.) to delineate population overfishing (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>).</p><p>To summarize, we define EOF as an instance where the sum of all catches are flat or declining, total CPUE is declining, and total landings relative to ecosystem production is excessive. The question is: At what point are landings deemed excessive?</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Real limits to global fisheries production</title><p>The productivity of the World Ocean is large but finite. The PP of the World Ocean is 40 to 50 Gt C year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, given mass-balance constraints of PP and nutrient recycling pathways (which converts to ~400 to 500 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> wet weight) (<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr"><italic>43</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr"><italic>44</italic></xref>). Climate change considerations predict that where that PP both occurs and is transferred to upper TL organisms of commercial importance will shift, vary in timing of major blooms, and change in species composition (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>), with tropical regions generally projected to be less productive (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>). Yet, no projections have PP globally increasing (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>). Thus, theoretically, there exists an overall, global cap on fish production as determined by lower TL production [sensu (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>46</italic></xref>)].</p><p>The limitations to fishery production by PP have been recognized for some time (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><italic>47</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><italic>49</italic></xref>). The PP required to support fishing ultimately limits the total amount of fish that can be caught in any given part of the world&#x02019;s ocean (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>). It is increasingly recognized that different pathways of production are important in increasing fisheries potential production (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>), but ultimately, PP can limit the dynamics and options of fishing fleets (<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><italic>50</italic></xref>).</p><p>Previous estimates of global marine capture fisheries production tend to be on the order of 0.1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (i.e., ~100 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Estimates of total, global fisheries yield ranges from 200 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><italic>49</italic></xref>), 140 to 180 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>), 150 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><italic>48</italic></xref>), 130 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>), 115 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><italic>47</italic></xref>), and 100 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>) to 68 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> [although this was just mean annual catch from 54 of 66 LMEs (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>)]. A few more recent estimates are closer to 1000 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (i.e., 1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), ranging from 790 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>) and 1.1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr"><italic>51</italic></xref>) to 2 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr"><italic>52</italic></xref>), but those are recognized as being at the higher end of the estimates when considered relative to total, global net primary production (NPP).</p><p>Recent official estimates of the total marine capture fishery yield remain on the order of 0.1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Debates as to the exact magnitude of total marine capture fisheries yield persist (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>46</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><italic>50</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>). These debates center around the actual magnitude of fishery production potential, whether the estimates are carrying capacity (<italic>K</italic>) or biomass at MSY (<italic>K</italic>/2), whether the estimates adequately capture IUU fishing, the methods for extrapolating data are appropriate, and other concerns over missing or misrepresented data. Regardless of these debated caveats as to the magnitude and source of the estimates, the total catch of global marine capture fisheries has been essentially flat for nearly 30 years (cf. <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>). Thus, the world is likely at some level of global fishery yield stasis.</p><p>The estimates and observed values of total, global catch are within expected ranges given assumptions of TE from PP of 40 to 50 Gt C year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Essentially, all one needs to estimate fish production is to simply convert PP to biomass and scale up three to four TLs where most caught species function (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). Given the first law of thermodynamics and constraints due to TEs up the food web (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr"><italic>54</italic></xref>), there are limits to how much fish any ecosystem can produce and, hence, can be (potentially) caught (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><italic>47</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><italic>49</italic></xref>). Biomass transfers up TLs with a notable inefficiency of energy transfer<disp-formula id="E5"><mml:math id="m5"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mtext>tot</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>PP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>TE</mml:mtext><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>where PP is often expressed NPP, &#x003b1; is a scalar for local conditions (set to ~15 to 20% for average availability of the TL in estimating total catch, a value that emerges when estimated from maintaining a global average catch that has been stable for the past 30 years) (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>), TE is usually between 10 and 16% (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>), and the relationship essentially bend or curve downward biomass by about two to three orders of magnitude at TLs 3 at 4, the TL at which most fish are captured (global averages at TL ~3.4) (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref>).</p><p>A sensitivity analysis was conducted on the trophic transfer relationship shown in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E5">Eq. 5</xref>. A surface of responses with PP ranging from 35 to 55 Gt C year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, TLs ranging from 2.8 to 4.2, and TE ranging from 6 to 16% was examined. Outputs were used to explore the range of probable thresholds for the indices noted below. The results of the sensitivity analysis reveal that catch decreases with an increase in TL, a decline in PP, and/or a decline in TE<disp-formula id="E6"><mml:math id="m6"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="center" displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02191;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TE</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02193;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>NPP</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(6)</label></disp-formula></p><p>Estimates of global catch are most sensitive to changes in TE, with order-of-magnitude effects transmuted through the exponential TL values. Assuming a NPP of ~45 &#x000b1; 5 Gt C year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (i.e., 450 &#x000b1; 50 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> wet weight), TE of 10 to 14%, &#x003b1; = 15 &#x000b1; 5%, and TL ~3.2 to 3.6, when used in these simple trophic transfer calculations results in an estimate of total fishery yield ranging from ~0.1 to 1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, consistent with other predictions and slightly higher than current observations.</p><p>To obtain higher catches from these calculations one would necessarily have to assume higher PP, which is not projected to occur (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>), or higher TEs at the extremely high end of observed ranges, which, although feasible, are not widely observed (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Thus, on average, it is likely in practice, given the relatively fixed primary production and observed flat fisheries catches, that the world&#x02019;s marine capture fisheries may only have limited potential to become more productive. Using centroid values of NPP of ~45 Gt C year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (i.e., ~450 Gt wet weight year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), TE of 12%, &#x003b1; = 15%, and TL ~3.4 results in estimates of marine capture fisheries yield of ~416 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> t year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, or potentially double or triple that of total catches typically observed, estimated, and reported. Thus, depending upon assumptions of TE (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>), and certainly in specific regions, the potential does exist for increased fisheries yield. A reasonable range of fisheries yield is thus, based on current estimates and this scoping exercise, likely on the order of 0.1 to 0.42 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Collectively, the global limits on PP, and hence fish production, imply that global fisheries yield may not yet be at a global carrying capacity but may be approaching these limits. The global consistency of catches for the past 30 years coupled with catches relative to PP of 0.1 to 3&#x02030; again implies some level of global fishery yield stasis.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Derivation of novel indices and delineation of EOF</title><p>Given the limits to fishery production in any given ecosystem forms a reasonable basis for delineating EOF. This can be expressed via three new indices proposed here. Using the centroid values of PP of ~45 Gt C year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, trophic TE of 12%, &#x003b1; = 15%, and TL ~3.4 again results in estimates of fisheries yield of ~0.42 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, with a reasonable range&#x02014;based on theory and observation&#x02014;of fisheries yield thus likely on the order of 0.1 to 0.42 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. This range of likely fishery yields can bracket the limits of fisheries production, can be used to bracket relationships of fisheries landings to other variables, and can provide an empirical basis for potential thresholds.</p><p>Scaling these production estimates by an area allows the calculation of the maximum sustainable yield for any part of the ocean. Given that the surface area of the world&#x02019;s ocean is approximately 363 M km<sup>2</sup>, one can estimate the areal values of catch, which can be reasonably expected. We call this the Ryther index (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>). Ryther&#x02019;s original work (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>) not only related landings to PP but also provided a global thinking and evaluation of fisheries catch. Thus, catches of 0.1 to 0.42 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> would result in a yield of 0.27 to 1.14 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, suggestive of a possible threshold NTE (~1). Even extreme estimates of global total catch around 1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> would result in a value of 2.7 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (~3 t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p><p>Another potential measure of EOF would be to contrast the ratio of fisheries catches to PP in an ecosystem. We call this the Fogarty ratio index (presented as per mil) (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). Fogarty <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>) have been estimating these values for some time and have proposed the use of this ratio as a means to manage fisheries. Simple calculations based on trophic transfer theory and an order of magnitude bracketing by a TL between 3 and 4 (based on <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E5">Eq. 5</xref>) suggest a range of possible catches relative to PP that would be feasible. That is<disp-formula id="E7"><mml:math id="m7"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="center" displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>For</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000a0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TE</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02030;</mml:mo><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TE</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0003</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02030;</mml:mo><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>15</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TE</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02030;</mml:mo><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TE</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>^</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>TL</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0001</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02030;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><label>(7)</label></disp-formula></p><p>Thus, on the basis of simple trophic transfer calculations, the Fogarty ratio of catches relative to PP ranges from 0.1 to 3&#x02030;. This again is suggestive of reasonable limits to catch potential and hence a possible threshold. Thus, given catches of 0.1 to 0.42 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> would imply an expected ratio of catch to PP of 0.22 to 0.92&#x02030;, suggesting a possible threshold NTE (~1). Even an extreme estimate of catches near 1 Gt year<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> would result in a value of 2.2&#x02030; (~2.5&#x02030;).</p><p>Acknowledging that estimates of PP are not always available but that satellite imagery able to produce estimates of chlorophyll a may be more so, we propose a proxy index. Coupling catch statistics with chlorophyll a estimates, and acknowledging all the important nuances of chlorophyll a and different pathways of production (<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>), we propose a unitless ratio of catch: Chlorophyll a to evaluate relative fishery productivity in those instances where PP estimates are not readily available. We call this the Friedland ratio index. Using logic similar to the Fogarty ratio, an empirical threshold NTE ~1 emerges.</p><p>To evaluate these proposed overfishing thresholds, we examined ecosystems with known instances of both population and ecosystem deterioration (see the Supplementary Materials). We acknowledge that copious further simulation testing of these thresholds would be advisable, but as a first-order proposal, here, we present these thresholds as empirically and theoretically based limits to fishing relative to ecosystem productivity. The threshold value of approximately 1 (for each index and their respective units) may be conservative from the perspective of some locales that are more productive or trophically efficient, but we wanted to establish these to not be too sensitive to these nuances; the range of values could be lower (i.e., more precautionary), and the theoretically and empirically estimated extreme values would be ~3&#x000d7; higher. For ecosystems with documented levels of negative impacts, and in some instances, recovery, where a clear history of the trajectory of population and ecosystem dynamics is captured, these thresholds perform well (see the Supplementary Materials).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Data sources and analysis</title><p>Marine capture fisheries data were obtained from Watson (<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>). This database represent a harmonized and mapped compilation of global catch from 1950 to 2014 sourced from the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization&#x02019;s (FAO) Capture Production 1950&#x02013;2014 dataset (release date: March 2016; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org">www.fao.org</ext-link>), International Committee for the Exploration of the Sea 1950&#x02013;2014 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ices.dk">www.ices.dk</ext-link>), Northwest Atlantic Fisheries Organisation Catch and Effort 1960&#x02013;2014 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nafo.int">www.nafo.int</ext-link>), Southeast Atlantic Capture Production 1975&#x02013;2014 (release date: June 2016) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.seafo.org">www.seafo.org</ext-link>), General Fisheries Commission for the Mediterranean Capture production 1970&#x02013;2014 (release date: April 2016) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gfcm.org">www.gfcm.org</ext-link>), Fishery Committee for the Eastern Central Atlantic Capture production 1970&#x02013;2014 (release date: May 2016) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/fishery/rfb/cecaf">www.fao.org/fishery/rfb/cecaf</ext-link>), Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources Statistical Bulletin 2016 Vol. 28 1970&#x02013;2014 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccamlr.org">www.ccamlr.org</ext-link>), and Sea Around Us project (SAUP) records for FAO area 18 (Arctic) v1 1950&#x02013;2010 (extrapolated to 2014) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.seaaroundus.org">www.seaaroundus.org</ext-link>). See previous descriptions [and references therein (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>)] for fuller details of data treatment.</p><p>For comparison, data were downloaded from FAO using the Fish-StatJ v2.12.2 software and database package. Data were also downloaded from the SAUP, by LME, using the online web interface to download CSV files. We explored these data across a range of taxa and taxa groups, across FAO statistical area, Regional Fisheries Management Organization, countries, exclusive economic zones (EEZs), and LME resolutions. Although there were differences among datasets in terms of magnitude, the same general trends and order of magnitude results were replicated (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>46</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><italic>50</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>). Thus, we used the compiled, composite set from Watson (<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>).</p><p>Upon examination of these data at multiple spatial scales, the clearest pattern in catches emerged from a half-degree by half-degree resolution of the data, as described previously (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>). Effort data were similarly tallied and presented at this resolution (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Catch data were analyzed using latitudinal assignments assigned to the various five (or three) broad latitudinal regions or LMEs (see below). As noted above, similar data were explored from FAO and SAU based on a country, an EEZ, LME, and statistical area assignation, but assignments to latitudinal cells were more resolved; hence, these other perspectives were not presented. We combined the Watson (<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>) data into latitudinal bands of 90&#x000b0;N to 55&#x000b0;N as Arctic, 55&#x000b0;N to 20&#x000b0;N as northern temperate, 20&#x000b0;N to 20&#x000b0;S as tropical, 20&#x000b0;S to 55&#x000b0;S as southern temperate, and 55&#x000b0;S to 90&#x000b0;S as Antarctic. The two temperate bands were combined into a global temperate band, as was the Arctic and Antarctic into a polar band. We also used the Watson (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>) data for each of the 65 LMEs. We acknowledged that aggregation across spatial scales could obfuscate some patterns among fisheries, but is the scale at which most fisheries operate (i.e., LME scale), the main patterns should be emergent. Estimates of PP (see below) were chosen at resolutions consistent with these scales. We also acknowledged that aggregating across taxa could also obfuscate some patterns among fisheries, but since our primary purpose was to explore total catches by ecosystem and this is a relatively simple integration, the total catch patterns would also emerge.</p><p>We present the FAO total capture fisheries catch en bloc as that is a familiar graphic to the discipline, as well as by the three main latitudinal bands. Decadal averages of effort and CPUE were also provided [adapted from Anticamara <italic>et al</italic>. (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>)], as well as proportions across latitudinal bands. Catch and CPUE were examined across example sequential stanzas (from 1950 to 1959, from 1970 to 1979, and from 2010 to 2014) and across longitudinal extent for several LMEs.</p><p>To highlight global shifts in distribution of catch across time, we present three stanzas spanning more than 50 years from the Watson data described above, one from 1950 to 1959, another from 1970 to 1979, and the most recent one from 2010 to 2014. Assignment of catches to 10&#x000b0; blocks was as described in Watson (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>). These data were captured on a global projection, and the spatial density of catches was scaled to maximal catch across all eras. Catches assigned to LME areas and to latitudinal bands, expressed as t km<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, are presented as the Ryther index.</p><p>Estimates of chlorophyll a and NPP were similarly estimated for all LMEs and latitudinal bands, from 1998 to 2014 using satellite imagery. These used a combined SeaWIFS and MODIS imagery set (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://oceancolor.gsfc.nasa.gov/">https://oceancolor.gsfc.nasa.gov/</ext-link>). Chlorophyll a was adapted from the merged time series data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hermes.acri.fr/">http://hermes.acri.fr/</ext-link>) at 25-km spatial resolution and annually integrated using monthly time steps. PP was estimated using the Behrenfeld method (<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr"><italic>55</italic></xref>), was annually integrated using daily values, and then summed for each LME or latitudinal band.</p><p>The spatial catch data were compared to chlorophyll a values to calculate the Friedland ratio index. The same catch data were compared to estimates of NPP to calculate the Fogarty ratio index (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). Both LME and latitudinal bands were evaluated. We also acknowledge the difference in latitudinal bands and LMEs, such that LME areas tend to exclude open ocean ecosystems and, hence, are areas where fish catches and PP tend to concentrate. Thus, global phenomena need to be interpreted within regional and even local contexts. In addition, within an LME, other sources of production may be occurring at the sub-LME scale that might not be as readily detectable via satellite (upwelling, estuarine, etc. inputs) and thus sporadically and locally alter production estimates. Thus, we recommend that the indices proposed here be used cognizant of other potential sources of productivity and that are relevant to the scale at which fisheries management mostly occurs.</p></sec></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/6/eaav0474/DC1</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_5_6_eaav0474__index.html"/>
</supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_2" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Download PDF</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="aav0474_SM.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank T. Miller, B. Fulton, S. Jennings, M. Barange, H. Browman, W. Cheung, D. Lipton, R. Hilborn, A. Pershing, C. Stock, G. Huse, M. Pinsky, and anonymous reviewers whose comments improved earlier versions of this manuscript. We thank K. Friedland and K. Hyde for providing estimates of chlorophyll a and PP. We thank M. Fogarty and C. Stock for ongoing discussions about global fisheries production. We acknowledge the FAO and the SAUP for their availability of supporting data. <bold>Funding:</bold> R.A.W. acknowledges support from the Australian Research Council (Discovery project DP140101377). <bold>Competing interests</bold>: The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <bold>Author contributions:</bold> J.S.L. conceived EOF and the conceptual framework. R.A.W. provided the data. J.S.L. conducted the analyses. Both authors contributed graphics and wrote and reviewed the manuscript. <bold>Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be accessed from (<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>) or requested from the authors.</p></ack><app-group><app><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><p>Supplementary material for this article is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/6/eaav0474/DC1">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/6/eaav0474/DC1</ext-link></p><p>Fig. S1. The classical fishery yield curve showing catch and CPUE compared to effort.</p><p>Fig. S2. Fishery yield curves for all fish (total) catches for example LMEs.</p><p>References (<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr"><italic>56</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr"><italic>57</italic></xref>)</p></supplementary-material></app></app-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES AND NOTES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FAO, <italic>The State of World Fisheries and Aquaculture 2016</italic>, Contributing to Food Security and Nutrition For All (FAO, 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bryndum-Buchholz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>B&#x000fc;chner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carozza</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>L. N. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dulvy</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maury</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tittensor</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Linked sustainability challenges and trade-offs among fisheries, aquaculture and agriculture</article-title>. <source>Nat. Ecol. Evol.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, 
<fpage>1240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1249</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29046559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stentiford</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leocadio</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katsiadaki</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auchterlonie</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mangi</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinnegar</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peeler</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luisetti</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baker-Austin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Catchpole</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clyne</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyder</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>O. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oidtmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posen</surname><given-names>P. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>N. G. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Townhill</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verner-Jeffreys</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Aquatic food security: Insights into challenges and solutions from an analysis of interactions between fisheries, aquaculture, food safety, human health, fish and human welfare, economy and environment</article-title>. <source>Fish Fish.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>938</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilborn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>When is a fishery sustainable?</article-title>
<source>Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci.</source>
<volume>72</volume>, 
<fpage>1433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1441</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>System-level optimal yield: increased value, less risk, improved stability, and better fisheries</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, 
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The Effects of Fishing on Marine Ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Adv. Mar. Biol.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, 
<fpage>201-212, 212e, 213-352</fpage> (<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>J. B. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>M. X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorndal</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Erlandson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estes</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>T. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenihan</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pandolfi</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steneck</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tegner</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Historical overfishing and the recent collapse of coastal ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>293</volume>, 
<fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>638</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11474098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botsford</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Castilla</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The management of fisheries and marine ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>277</volume>, 
<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Relationships between common biological reference points used as thresholds and targets of fisheries management strategies</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Fish. Aquat. Sci.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, 
<fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murawski</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Definitions of overfishing from an ecosystem perspective</article-title>. <source>ICES J. Mar. Sci.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, 
<fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>658</lpage> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Primary production required to sustain global fisheries</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>374</volume>, 
<fpage>255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Libralato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tudela</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palomera</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pranovi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Novel index for quantification of ecosystem effects of fishing as removal of secondary production</article-title>. <source>Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser.</source>
<volume>355</volume>, 
<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Large</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedland</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Critical points in ecosystem responses to fishing and environmental pressures</article-title>. <source>Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser.</source>
<volume>521</volume>, 
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pranovi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Libralato</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coll</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solidoro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Delineating marine ecosystem perturbation and recovery</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, 
<fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>661</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26456382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bundy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohaboy</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hjermann</surname><given-names>D. O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueter</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Common patterns, common drivers: Comparative analysis of aggregate systemic surplus production across ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser.</source>
<volume>459</volume>, 
<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rykaczewski</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asch</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedland</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>V. W. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Reconciling fisheries catch and ocean productivity</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>114</volume>, 
<fpage>E1441</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1449</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28115722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chassot</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonhommeau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dulvy</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000e9;lin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pape</surname><given-names>O. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Global marine primary production constrains fisheries catches</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Lett.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, 
<fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>505</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20141525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scardi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fisheries yield and primary productivity in large marine ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser.</source>
<volume>410</volume>, 
<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchingman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gelchu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Mapping global fisheries: sharpening our focus</article-title>. <source>Fish Fish.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>177</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nowara</surname><given-names>G. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Marine foods sourced from farther as their use of global ocean primary production increases</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>7365</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26079714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Link</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Large</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedland</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gove</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holsman</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karnauskas</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samhouri</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shuford</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tomilieri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zador</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comparing apples to oranges: Common trends and thresholds in anthropogenic and environmental pressures across multiple marine ecosystems. <italic>Front</italic></article-title>. <source>Mar. Sci.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, 
<fpage>282</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The spatial expansion and ecological footprint of fisheries (1950 to present)</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>e015143</fpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Systematic distortions in world fisheries catch trends</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>414</volume>, 
<fpage>534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>536</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dulvy</surname><given-names>N. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barange</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Potential consequences of climate change for primary production and fish production in large marine ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B</source>
<volume>367</volume>, 
<fpage>2979</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2989</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tickler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meeuwig</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Far from home: Distance patterns of global fishing fleets</article-title>. <source>Sci. Adv.</source>
<volume>4</volume>, 
<fpage>eaar3279</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30083601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anticamara</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sumaila</surname><given-names>R. U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Global marine yield halved as fishing intensity redoubles</article-title>. <source>Fish Fish.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, 
<fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dickey-Collas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>K. J. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kleisner</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minte-Vera</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mosqueira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osio</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ovando</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selig</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorson</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fishery production potential of large marine ecosystems: A prototype analysis</article-title>. <source>Environ. Dev.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, 
<fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anticamara</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gelchu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Global fishing effort (1950&#x02013;2010): Trends, gaps, and implications</article-title>. <source>Fish. Res.</source>
<volume>107</volume>, 
<fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinsky</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Worm</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fogarty</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Marine taxa track local climate velocities</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>341</volume>, 
<fpage>1239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1242</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fr&#x000f6;licher</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>V. W. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>M. L. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Shrinking of fishes exacerbates impacts of global ocean changes on marine ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Nat. Clim. Chang.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, 
<fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>258</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Denderen</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindegren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>K. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Global patterns in marine predatory fish</article-title>. <source>Nat. Ecol. Evol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, 
<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29180711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumaila</surname><given-names>U. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>V. W. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrick</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Climate change impacts on the biophysics and economics of world fisheries</article-title>. <source>Nat. Clim. Chang.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, 
<fpage>449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>V. W. Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Large-scale redistribution of maximum fisheries catch potential in the global ocean under climate change</article-title>. <source>Glob. Chang. Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, 
<fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Catch reconstructions reveal that global fisheries catches are higher than reported and declining</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, 
<fpage>10244</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26784963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>R. N. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buszowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>W. W. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Froese</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karpouzi</surname><given-names>V. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaschner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>M. L. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peters-Mason</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piroddi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steenbeek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sumaila</surname><given-names>U. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Database-driven models of the world&#x02019;s large marine ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Model. Theol.</source>
<volume>220</volume>, 
<fpage>1984</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1996</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dalsgaard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Froese</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Fishing down marine food webs</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>279</volume>, 
<fpage>860</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>863</lpage> (<year>1998</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9452385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polovina</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abecassis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The ocean&#x02019;s least productive waters are expanding</article-title>. <source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, 
<fpage>L03618</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwiatkowski</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bopp</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aumont</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ciais</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laufk&#x000f6;tter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>S&#x000e9;f&#x000e9;rian</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Emergent constraints on projections of declining primary production in the tropical oceans</article-title>. <source>Nat. Clim. Chang.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, 
<fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poloczanska</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burrows</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molinos</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kappel</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeman</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sydeman</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Responses of Marine Organisms to Climate Change across Oceans</article-title>. <source>Front. Mar. Sci.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, 
<fpage>62</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">M. Graham, <italic>The Fish Gate</italic>. (Faber, 1943).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">T. D. Smith, <italic>Scaling Fisheries: The Science of Measuring the Effects of Fishing, 1855&#x02013;1955</italic> (Cambridge Univ. Press, 1994).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A. D. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bulman</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>I. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano-Montes</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mackinson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marzloff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Impacts of fishing low&#x02013;trophic level species on marine ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>333</volume>, 
<fpage>1147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1150</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21778363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antoine</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Oceanic primary production: 2. Estimation at global scale from satellite (Coastal Zone Color Scanner) chlorophyll</article-title>. <source>Glob. Biogeochem. Cycles</source>
<volume>10</volume>, 
<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage> (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>M.-E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>M. A. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmeltz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noguchi Aita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Antoine</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arrigo</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asanuma</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aumont</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behrenfeld</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bidigare</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buitenhuis</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ciotti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dierssen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esaias</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gentili</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregg</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoepffner</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ishizaka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kameda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>le Qu&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohrenz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>M&#x000e9;lin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scardi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turpie</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tilstone</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A comparison of global estimates of marine primary production from ocean color</article-title>. <source>Deep Sea Res. Part II Top. Stud. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>53</volume>, 
<fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>770</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryther</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Photosynthesis and fish production from the sea</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>166</volume>, 
<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage> (<year>1969</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5817762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Branch</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGilliard</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pablico</surname><given-names>G. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ricard</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The trophic fingerprint of marine fisheries</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>468</volume>, 
<fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21085178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">H. W. Graham, R. L. Edwards, The world biomass of marine fishes, in <italic>Fish in Nutrition</italic>, E. Heen, R. Kreuzer, Eds. (Fishing New Books, 1962).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">W. E. Ricker, Food from the sea, in <italic>U.S. National Academy of Sciences Series-Resources and Man</italic> (W.H. Freeman, 1969).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The potential harvest of the sea</article-title>. <source>Trans. Am. Fish. Soc.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, 
<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage> (<year>1965</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Primary productivity demands of global fishing fleets</article-title>. <source>Fish Fish.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, 
<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Irigoien</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klevjer</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>R&#x000f8;stad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyra</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Acu&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Echevarria</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Gordillo</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Leon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agusti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aksnes</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kaartvedt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Large mesopelagic fishes biomass and trophic efficiency in the open ocan</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>327</fpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millero</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grosell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Contribution of fish to the marine inorganic carbon cycle</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>323</volume>, 
<fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19150840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A database of global marine commercial, small-scale, illegal and unreported fisheries catch 1950&#x02013;2014</article-title>. <source>Sci. Data</source>
<volume>4</volume>, 
<fpage>170039</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28398351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindeman</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The trophic-dynamic aspect of ecology</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>23</volume>, 
<fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage> (<year>1942</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrenfeld</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkowski</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Photosynthetic rates derived from satellite-based chlorophyll concentration</article-title>. <source>Limnol. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, 
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">G. Hempel, K. Sherman, <italic>Large Marine Ecosystems of the World: Trends in Exploitation, Protection and Research</italic> (Elsevier, 2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">K. Sherman, H. R. Skjoldah, <italic>Large Marine Ecosystems of the North Atlantic: Changing States and Sustainability</italic> (Elsevier, 2002).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>