<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although spontaneous adaptation is receiving some attention within these conceptual differentiations (e.g. Adger 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2001</xref>; Thorn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">2015</xref>), most scholars remain in the tradition of an intentional perspective on CCA and consequently focus on planned, impact-driven and anticipatory adaptation (e.g. Kates et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2012</xref>; Marshall et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2014</xref>; Moser 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">2009</xref>). Starting with Burton et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2002</xref>) several limitation of this “first generation” CCA have been discussed (Dessai and Hulme 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2004</xref>; O’Brien et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2004</xref>). One point of critique focuses on the belief that planned, anticipatory adaptation has to be created from scratch, fading out existing economic, social and/or political driving forces and constraints acting on a sector’s actors. Becoming more aware of this ‘polyrational context’ in which adaptation occurs, opens up the possibility, that also non-climatic driving forces can trigger interventions that directly or indirectly influence the coping capacities of actors to whatever changes the future might bring. Burton et al. referred to such interventions as adaptation policies that already exist, but are “rarely recognized by that name” (Burton et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2002</xref>). Thus, trying to ground adaptation in such polyrational contexts inspired the discussion about “second generation” adaptation assessments, reframing adaptation as managing for resilience, not impacts (Boyd and Cornforth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2013</xref>). As Darnhofer (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2010</xref>) pointed out, resilience thinking could be helpful in enhancing adaptive capacity. The resilience perspective is not yet reflected in the concepts presented in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>. 
</p>
