<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec6" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The butterfly effect: the importance of trophic cascades</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In common sense, 
  <span class="italic">chaos</span> denotes extreme confusion, disorder, a state in which behaviour and events are not controlled by anything, in sum, a pandemonium. For instance, I say very often these days to my wife: “The car traffic in Recife is becoming chaotic”. In Greek mythology, chaos (Greek χάος, 
  <span class="italic">khaos</span>) is the most ancient of gods, formless or void state preceding the creation of the universe. But only recently, I also came to understanding that, in mathematics, chaos theory is a field that studies the behaviour of dynamical systems (
  <a rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib89">Rickles et al., 2007</a>). The principle is that small changes in the initial conditions will result in different outcomes for such dynamical systems; this sensitive dependence on initial conditions is the so-called “butterfly effect”. The chaos theory has many potential applications, including in medicine (
  <a rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib81">Philippe, 1993</a>), ecology (
  <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">Hastings et al., 1993</a>) and evolution (
  <a rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib37">Ferrière and Fox, 1995</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The response of ticks to changes in climate and in densities of their hosts can be variable. For instance, manipulations of models (even deterministic ones) can produce different outcomes, including tick populations that either rise or fall under increasing host densities, depending on initial conditions (
  <a rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib25">Dobson, 2014a</a>). Tick-borne pathogen transmission systems are also difficult to predict (perhaps, unpredictable) in the long term, because of the possibility of chaotic behaviour (sensitive dependence on initial conditions). The existence of complex ecological processes (e.g., trophic cascades) and their possible influences on the tick-host-pathogen triad increase the complexity of models of multi-host transmission systems. For instance, a trophic cascade is ecological process that starts at the top of the food chain and fall down to the bottom (
  <a rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib77">Paine, 1980</a>). Food-webs may be influenced by top-down effects from carnivores to plants and by bottom-up effects that link plants to herbivores and higher trophic levels, and the importance of each in a given ecosystem is a subject of debate (
  <a rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib68">Muhly et al., 2013</a>). A classical example of a trophic cascade is what happened in the Yellowstone National Park in the United States, when grey wolves (
  <span class="italic">Canis lupus</span>) were reintroduced in 1995 (
  <a rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib8">Beyer et al., 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52">Kauffman et al., 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib90">Ripple and Beschta, 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib26">Dobson, 2014b</a>, 
  <a rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib91">Ripple et al., 2014</a>). In his talk “For more wonder, rewild the world” filmed July 2013 at TEDGlobal 2013, George Monbiot presented a very exciting description of what happened in this park, explaining how wolves transformed not just the local ecosystem, but also its physical geography (see video at: 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ted.com/talks/george_monbiot_for_more_wonder_rewild_the_world" id="intref0025" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ted.com/talks/george_monbiot_for_more_wonder_rewild_the_world</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if the relationship between grey wolf reintroduction and increased fruit availability and consumption by grizzly bears (
  <span class="italic">Ursus arctos</span>) in the Yellowstone National Park is an on-going debate (
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">Barber-Meyer, 2015</a>, 
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Ripple et al., 2015</a>), the occurrence of a wolf-inducted trophic cascade in this area is evident. The reintroduction of wolves triggered important changes in the local ecosystem, when they started preying on ungulates, particularly elk (
  <span class="italic">Cervus elaphus</span>) (
  <a rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib66">Metz et al., 2012</a>). The interactions between wolves, ungulates, coyotes (
  <span class="italic">Canis latrans</span>), red foxes (
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes</span>), and so on, resulted in important changes in terrestrial mammal and bird communities in the Yellowstone National Park.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trophic cascades may potentially affect the transmission dynamics of pathogens such as 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi</span>, through dilution and/or amplification effects. For example, 
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">Levi et al. (2012)</a> elaborated a theoretical model suggesting that changes in predator communities may have cascading impacts that facilitate the emergence of Lyme disease. They showed that increases in Lyme disease in the north-eastern and mid-western United States over the past three decades coincide with a range-wide decline of a key small-mammal predator, the red fox, likely due to expansion of coyote populations, being uncorrelated with deer abundance as usually thought.
 </p>
</sec>
