<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A growing body of literature has focused on understanding the impacts of such activities on regional climate processes. The climatic influences of land cover changes due to cropland conversion and expansion have been extensively studied (e.g., Douglas et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Findell et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Mahmood et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Pielke et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Several studies have demonstrated the mechanisms by which land cover changes influence regional climate by altering the Earth's radiation budget and by influencing both the partitioning of surface energy fluxes and the exchange of heat and moisture between the land surface and the atmosphere (e.g., Diffenbaugh, 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Douglas et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Halder et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Hirsch et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; McDermid et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Pielke et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Quesada et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Yamashima et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). These effects are particularly strong in regions of moderate to strong land‐atmosphere coupling including South Asia, the Great Plains of North America, the Sahel, and Central and East Asia (Koster, 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). Further, the impact of land cover changes depends on the a priori vegetation types (i.e., forests, shrublands, and deserts) and the local evapotranspiration regime (i.e., moisture or energy limited) and, therefore, can vary substantially across regions (Hirschi et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Myhre et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Despite the extensive research in this field, the timing and magnitude of the regional climate impacts of land cover changes are still uncertain (McDermid et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
