<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">An exception to increasing days exceeding critical temperatures occurs in the Nechako River in the northwest portion of the FRB. The Nechako River has been regulated by Alcan (now owned by Rio Tinto) since the construction of the Kenney Dam, the Skins Lake Spillway, and the Nechako Reservoir in the 1950s
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>. Summer flows in the Nechako River are further regulated in response to forecasted air temperatures owing to a 1980 court injunction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>. Following the court ruling, Rio Tinto implemented the STMP in 1981 to suppress river water temperatures to &lt;20 °C for the Nechako River at Finmoore (~40 km downstream from NVH) from 20 July to 20 August through controlled releases from Skins Lake Spillway for the benefit of migrating salmon. The Air2Stream model, forced with regulated discharge, simulates reasonably well the impact of the STMP on Nechako River water temperatures, including the NVH site. Model results suggest that the number of days when simulated water temperatures rise above T
 <sub>c20</sub> has not changed during the pre- and post-STMP time periods despite rising air temperatures, thereby revealing the effectiveness of the STMP in meeting temperature requirements near NVH. The warming trends in the Nechako River are likely not related to the impact of regulation, given that the varying summer water temperature response to climate change in its unregulated tributaries, i.e. strong warming summer trend at SFJ and insignificant summer trends at NFF and SGN. We tested the impact of regulation on water temperatures using Air2Stream sensitivity runs for NVH. Regulation decreases water temperatures especially during the STMP time window of 20 July to 20 August whereas the long-term trend abates due to regulation. This implies that overall water temperature increases in the Nechako River are mainly due to climate change rather than regulation.
</p>
