<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">We used nine climate simulations including projections from eight different general circulation models (GCMs) and one multi-model ensemble based on 15 different GCMs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>; see Supplemental Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref> for details of GCMs used. The multi-model ensemble includes some of the eight GCMs and so is not an independent case. However, it is included to represent the common usage of ensemble projections in conservation planning. These nine alternative climate projections allowed us to assess intermodel differences in climate process and parameterization schemes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, we used predictions from two representative concentration pathways (RCP) of greenhouse gasses (i.e., RCP 4.5 or medium-low emissions, and RCP 8.5 or high emissions) that represent uncertainty due to policy choices over the coming decades. Predictions from RCP 4.5 are based on a trajectory of greenhouse gas concentrations that stabilizes with a net positive (warming) energetic forcing to the atmosphere of 4.5 W m
 <sup class="sup">−2 </sup>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>, while predictions from RCP 8.5 are based on a higher trajectory of greenhouse gas emissions that produces a greenhouse gas radiative forcing that is nearly twice that of RCP 4.5
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. We pooled simulations representing the two RCP scenarios with the nine simulations from different GCMs, resulting in 18 different predictions for each of the three climate exposure metrics (Supplemental Figs 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">3</xref>). The purpose of producing these 18 different projections was to generate a range of reasonable climate predictions that represent alternatives available from the AdaptWest project for developing climate-informed conservation planning.
</p>
