<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">By employing the multi-model CMIP5 archive, we have demonstrated the varying rates at which regional heatwave characteristics increase relative to a universal temperature trajectory. While most heatwave changes are linear with respect to global warming (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>), the main exception is the number of discrete events per season. From 2 °C global warming onwards and particularly over tropical regions, the regional number of events may decrease. While this result is consistent with studies demonstrating the relatively rapid climatological shift of the tropics
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>, it potentially imposes adverse regional impacts, as a perpetual heatwave state will emerge each summer once 2 °C global warming is reached and exceeded. Indeed, impacts on local ecosystems could be devastating, as tropical climates will be pushed into uncharted territories. Regional changes in heatwave days are also quite striking. Increases in heatwave days may exceed 30 days per °C of global warming over tropical and arid regions. Changes of around 20 days per °C are anticipated over northern high latitudes, and 10–20 days per °C over southern high latitudes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a</xref>). Thus, if global warming is not capped at 2 °C or less, regional increases in heatwave days may span 60–120 
 <italic class="italic">extra</italic> days per summer by the end of this century, relative to a pre-industrial climate (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Generally speaking, the peak intensity of heatwaves scales reasonably close to the amount of global warming (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1d</xref>), with regional variations of 1–1.8 °C, per °C of global warming. The Mediterranean and Eurasian regions demonstrate the largest change, where peak heatwave intensity may exceed 8 °C by 2100 if global warming is not constrained. However, it is worth remembering that the occurrence of extremely intense heatwaves increases far more rapidly. By 1.5 °C global warming, almost all regions experience heatwaves every 4 years that occurred every 30 years when anthropogenic influence on the climate was negligible (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>).
</p>
