<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">Attention should also be drawn to the plethora of heatwave definitions that exist in both climate and impacts literature. There is no universal heatwave metric, nor will one likely ever exist, owing to the multiple physical characteristics
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup> heatwaves have and their vast array of impacts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, many impacts-based fields have their own specific definitions, directly relating to the impact at hand
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. This study employed the percentile-based definition against a baseline climate (see Methods) for multiple reasons – it is practical for different climates; it has been successfully used to derive changes in heatwaves from different types of climate data; and multiple heatwave characteristics can be derived for a range of such impacts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. However, all percentile-based definitions show very large changes in heatwave frequency and duration over tropical regions, due to the small temperature distributions of these areas. As a consequence of such increases, some studies suggest serious impacts to human health and productivity, especially if coupled with a rise in humidity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, Tropical ecosystems successfully function within a tight temperature range – small, yet regular deviations above this could result in disastrous ramifications. However there is and always will be a place for absolute-based heatwave definitions that do not require a baseline climate, for example to understand how particular species may cope with changes in frequency of certain future temperatures
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup> or potential changes of particular diseases that are directly correlated with certain temperature thresholds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
