<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theory states that the covariation in seasonal life-history traits such as clutch size and laying date arises from individual-specific fitness optima, suggesting that deviation from the reaction norm reduces fitness. Here, we advocate an approach based on random regression to first describe and test whether there is variation across individuals in the properties describing a trait–trait reaction norm and to further test for selection on these properties. We show that this approach indeed is effective in describing variation in Ural owl clutch size–laying date relationships and detects selection on the reaction-norm properties. Using a random regression mixed model to describe trait–trait reaction norms and selection on them avoids having to first extract information on reaction-norm properties from individual-specific regression and then regressing these estimates on fitness (e.g., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">Brommer et al. 2003</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">Nussey et al. 2005a</a>). Hence, uncertainties in the estimate of an individual's reaction-norm properties are incorporated and selection on the mean trait (i.e., elevation) is considered simultaneously to the within-individual covariation between traits as well as their codependency by considering the complete matrix of variances and covariances between the trait under investigation and fitness. The approach works especially well on data consisting of repeated measures of traits on a set of individuals, of which the seasonal life-history traits in the case scenario considered is but one example.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection acts on phenotypes, and, in case of phenotypic plasticity, the phenotype is an environment-specific realization of the genotype. Empirically measuring the fitness of the reaction norm requires integrating the fitness of all the phenotypes produced by a genotype over the entire environmental gradient (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">Weis and Gorman 1990</a>). However, in the case of labile traits, we consider trait expression by a set of individuals. Although each individual is a unique genotype, the variance between individuals in the properties describing the trait–trait reaction norms includes both the additive genetic variance and also other, nonheritable, consistent differences across individuals (so-called permanent environmental effects, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">Lynch and Walsh 1998</a>). In our example, environmental effect associated with individuals may arise because Ural owls are strongly territorial and essentially breed their entire career in the same territory (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">Saurola 1987</a>). Thus, variation across territories is confounded with variation across individuals and it is therefore possible that the variation in reaction-norm properties we here document is entirely caused by environmental differences across individuals. Nevertheless, provided sufficient pedigree information is available, a random regression animal model can be used to further partition the phenotypic properties into their additive genetic versus permanent environmental components (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">Nussey et al. 2007</a>). Such a random regression animal model would allow estimation of the additive genetic (co)variance matrix G for the reaction-norm properties.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nonlinear selection on reaction norm properties</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A major downside of the bivariate random regression approach in quantifying selection on plasticity is that it does not allow for nonlinear selection. For a single trait, nonlinear selection is estimated by calculating the covariance between the square of the trait and relative fitness (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">Falconer and MacKay 1996</a>). The reaction-norm slope is an emergent property determined by the within-individual covariance between the traits and cannot be directly measured. Selection on higher order polynomial terms, as we found in our example case for the second-order polynomial of the Ural owl clutch size–laying date relationship, refer to linear selection on specific curvature of the reaction norm itself rather than the shape of natural selection. Stabilizing selection on slope would be expected in case the reaction norm is maintained by selection. Nevertheless, there is generally a component of directional selection, except in the very restrictive case of completely symmetrical reductions in fitness if the slope deviates from the optimal reaction norm. Furthermore, comparative studies underline that directional selection is typically stronger than stabilizing selection (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">Kingsolver et al. 2001</a>; but see 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">Stinchcombe et al. 2008</a>). Investigation of the mapping of fitness to the BLUPs of the reaction-norm properties, as we did here, should reveal whether stabilizing selection on reaction norms may occur (although it does not allow a formal test). We advice that the estimates of selection on reaction-norm properties are considered with caution, but also emphasize that alternative approaches may lead to spurious findings, especially when the uncertainty of the slope estimate is ignored.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Applications of the random-regression approach in evolutionary ecology</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The approach used here to quantify selection on trait–trait reaction norms is equally useful for reaction norms of trait versus environment. The typical use of random regression mixed models is to model the covariance of a trait and an abiotic variable. For example, reaction norms in laying date and temperature have been explored in several studies in wild populations (e.g., 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">Brommer et al. 2005</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" href="#b50">2008</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">Nussey et al. 2005b</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">Charmantier et al. 2008</a>; 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">Husby et al. 2010</a>). Such random regression models can be readily extended to a bivariate form where fitness is also considered (Equation [6]) in order to analyze selection on the trait–environment reaction-norm properties. Understanding selection on trait–environment plasticity may be crucial, because under environmental change organisms may be selected to alter the plasticity in their trait–environment relationship, rather than merely their mean trait value. For example, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">Nussey et al. (2005b)</a> showed that selection on the BLUPs of the slope of laying date–temperature relationships of great tits 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span> in the Netherlands increased as the local spring climate warmed during the last decades.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies that consider repeated measures of different behaviors collected on a set of individuals may benefit from the approach outlines in this paper. The level of integration of several behaviors within an individual is increasingly receiving attention in ecology and evolutionary biology, because it captures “‘behavioural syndromes,” consistency in behaviors across different contexts (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" href="#b79">Sih et al. 2004</a>). Under this paradigm, correlated behaviors (e.g., between “boldness” and “aggression”) arise because individuals are relatively inflexible with respect to environmental conditions (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">Réale et al. 2007</a>). Hence, explicit consideration of “behavioural reaction norms” and understanding selection on their properties has been recently advocated as a potentially fruitful line of research for understanding how natural selection shapes behavioral syndromes (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">Dingemanse et al. 2010</a>). In particular, the notion that behavioral syndromes are maintained in the population because plasticity, that is, reaction-norm slope, is genetically constrained (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" href="#b79">Sih et al. 2004</a>) as opposed to being shaped by selection can be explicitly explored using the random regression approach advocated here.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
