<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interpretation of the findings</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We find that female Ural owls differ in the elevation, linear and quadratic slopes of their clutch size–laying date relationships. This variation across individuals is important, because it creates the potential for selection to shape the plasticity in clutch size as a function of laying date. We indeed show that selection operates on this plasticity, such that (1) females enjoy greater fitness when they have a larger elevation. That is, a larger clutch size at the mean value of observed laying dates, which is a close correlate of an individual's mean clutch size (cf. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">Brommer et al. 2003</a>), (2) females whose clutch size declines steeper with advancing laying date and who show a stronger nonlinear (concave) curvature in their clutch size–laying date relationship have higher fitness. Inspection of the interindividual clutch size–laying date relationship estimated by random regression (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>) shows that individuals with a concave curvature are those which have a relatively moderate clutch size at the early laying dates (before the median) and a relatively low clutch size during late laying dates (after the median). In the Ural owl, fledging success in brood sizes exceeding five offspring generally is poor, because hatching asynchrony increases rapidly with increasing clutch size (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">Kontiainen et al. 2010</a>). For example, in a brood of 5, the smallest offspring is already 4–6 days younger than its oldest sibling and mortality of the youngest nestling in such a large brood is likely (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">Kontiainen et al. 2010</a>). Therefore, the production of large clutch sizes adds little to lifetime fledgling production. In addition, late broods are typically found under poor environmental conditions (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">Pietiäinen 1989</a>) and it may be a good strategy to reproduce conservatively under those conditions. Thus, we believe that our selection analysis captures biologically plausible processes in this species. The main finding is, nevertheless, that there is selection on properties that describe the plasticity of seasonal adjustment in clutch size. Provided part of this latter variation across females in plasticity is heritable, selection has the potential to shape the clutch size–laying date relationship in this species.
 </p>
</sec>
