<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nonlinear selection on reaction norm properties</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A major downside of the bivariate random regression approach in quantifying selection on plasticity is that it does not allow for nonlinear selection. For a single trait, nonlinear selection is estimated by calculating the covariance between the square of the trait and relative fitness (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">Falconer and MacKay 1996</a>). The reaction-norm slope is an emergent property determined by the within-individual covariance between the traits and cannot be directly measured. Selection on higher order polynomial terms, as we found in our example case for the second-order polynomial of the Ural owl clutch size–laying date relationship, refer to linear selection on specific curvature of the reaction norm itself rather than the shape of natural selection. Stabilizing selection on slope would be expected in case the reaction norm is maintained by selection. Nevertheless, there is generally a component of directional selection, except in the very restrictive case of completely symmetrical reductions in fitness if the slope deviates from the optimal reaction norm. Furthermore, comparative studies underline that directional selection is typically stronger than stabilizing selection (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">Kingsolver et al. 2001</a>; but see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">Stinchcombe et al. 2008</a>). Investigation of the mapping of fitness to the BLUPs of the reaction-norm properties, as we did here, should reveal whether stabilizing selection on reaction norms may occur (although it does not allow a formal test). We advice that the estimates of selection on reaction-norm properties are considered with caution, but also emphasize that alternative approaches may lead to spurious findings, especially when the uncertainty of the slope estimate is ignored.
 </p>
</sec>
