<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We found overlapping key amphibian regions, such as important endemic amphibian regionalization (e.g. Sichuan and Guizhou provinces) and global biodiversity hotspots (e.g. Sichuan) (
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chen &amp; Bi, 2007</xref>). Nature reserves provide the most effective approach for biodiversity conservation, especially for the in situ conservation of wildlife and natural ecosystems (
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">D’Amen et al., 2011</xref>). Distribution shift, habitat loss and fragmentation caused by climatic change are the potential threats to amphibians in China, and the current network of natural reserves does not include some key regions for amphibians. In addition, many existing nature reserves have not sufficient to prevent amphibians from declining from threats of climatic change because their conservation objects and policies are not for amphibians, though they have a key role in protect amphibians. We should protect the amphibians under the climate change with the following strategies. First, we need to develop a conservation plan to estab1ish a network of national reserves covering populations of all threatened amphibian species in China. Second, we need to implement conservation action plans in all currently existing reserves to maintain viable populations and protect the habits for some vulnerable species with high habit loss (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Odorrana hainanensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Cynops cyanurus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Bombina fortinuptialis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhacophorus dennysi</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Rana amurensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Tylototriton asperrimus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pelophylax hubeiensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bufo melanostictus</italic>) and local extinction of certain amphibians for fragmentation (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Amolops ricketti</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pachytriton labiatus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Megophrys minor</italic>). Third, we need to develop some engineering strategies to increase shelters and canopy cover and install irrigation to maintain water potentials in wetland and upland habitats (
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li, Cohen &amp; Rohr, 2013</xref>).
</p>
