<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> distribution
 </div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> SDMs were similar in terms of their predictive performance and they outperformed the 
  <span class="italic">Fucus</span> SDMs (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). The joint effect of salinity and temperature explained more than half of the total variation in occurrence. However, most of the variation in this joint effect was attributable to salinity with its strongest effects in SDMs including distribution data. The response along temperature was negligible. The response along salinity was clearly positive in all 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> SDMs (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). In addition to direct abiotic forcing, distribution data showed that 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> was also sensitive to changes in the biomass of its host alga 
  <span class="italic">Fucus</span>. The probability of occurrence of 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> was significantly lower in the absence than in the presence of 
  <span class="italic">Fucus</span>. Moreover, with high credibility the probability of occurrence of 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> further increased with growing biomass of 
  <span class="italic">Fucus</span>, and at maximum biomass of host alga the effect of 
  <span class="italic">Fucus</span> on 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> was about one-third of the effect of salinity. The spatial random effect explained approximately 30% of the occurrence of 
  <span class="italic">Idotea</span> but there was no clear spatial pattern in the spatial random effect which indicates strong local variability in its occurrence beyond that explained by salinity, temperature and 
  <span class="italic">Fucus</span> biomass.
 </p>
</sec>
