<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon reservoir flux</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model calculates projected CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions based on representations of carbon emissions from the energy and land-use change sectors, as discussed above. These emissions accumulate in the atmosphere until they are absorbed into the biosphere, pedosphere or oceans based on C-ROADS, a Simple Climate Model, which has been used extensively for climate policy impact analysis and decision making by parties to the UNFCCC
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a>. Pathways and simplified equations for gross carbon flux among the reservoirs are illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f7" href="#f7">Fig. 7</a> and discussed below
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Figs 2 and 3</a> illustrates the ocean and land sink responses to increasing atmospheric carbon concentration. In 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 2</a>, cumulative uptake is plotted for both natural sinks relative to atmospheric carbon. In 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 3</a>, we plot the absolute (a) and fractional (b) responses of net sink flux to a range of constant emissions rates. For example, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 3b</a> indicates that a 100% increase in annual emissions generates a 150% increase in net atmospheric carbon flux, an 80% increase in net carbon uptake by the land sink, and only a 50% increase in oceanic carbon uptake. Conversely, a 50% decrease in anthropogenic emissions generates a 66% decrease in net atmospheric carbon flux and 50 and 35% decreases in net land sink and ocean fluxes, respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the nominal ECS value (3.0 °C/2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>), FeliX projects a transient climate sensitivity of 2.4 °C/2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>. For ECS=2.5 °C/2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>, the transient climate sensitivity is 2.1 °C/2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
</sec>
