<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CCS or utilization</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taken together, the Fossil Fuels, BAU, RE-Low and RE-High scenarios define a range of plausible energy-emissions pathways. As we have seen, however, even 5% annual growth in REs sustained through the twenty-first century fails to achieve critical benchmarks for both 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub> and Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>. Global transformations of the energy and LULUCF sectors need to be even more ambitious than in the RE-High scenario to achieve the COP targets, suggesting that additional socioeconomic and technological shifts must be considered.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CCS is implemented as a mitigation wedge within the RE-Low and RE-High scenarios to quantify the additional emissions mitigation necessary to achieve the COP targets. As variations on the energy and LULUCF sector transitions already discussed, we model the effects of CCS technologies scaled up after 2020 to 50% (
  <div id="d32e618" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e619" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>CCS) or 100% (CCS) of global energy infrastructures. Assuming an 80% capture efficiency, CCS systems capture and permanently sequester up to 40% of gross energy sector emissions in the RE-Low+
  <div id="d32e621" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e622" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m2.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>CCS and RE-High+
  <div id="d32e624" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e625" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m3.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>CCS variants and up to 80% of gross energy sector emissions in the RE-Low+CCS and RE-High+CCS variants.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To achieve these capture rates while keeping up with primary energy demand growth, the 
  <div id="d32e629" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e630" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m4.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>CCS and CCS pathways assume geometric growth (30% and 34% per year, respectively, from 2016 through 2040) in the amount of new carbon sequestered each year. Relative to the actual current value (7.3 MtC per year)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">10</a>, annual carbon capture expands by a factor of 630–720 by 2040 in 
  <div id="d32e634" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e635" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m5.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>CCS scenarios and by a factor of 1,310–1,490 by 2040 in the CCS scenarios. From 2040 through the end of the century, CCS capacity expands an additional 10–40% in both pathways to account for rising marginal costs of additional efficiency improvements and infrastructural expansion (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 1a</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the RE-Low scenario with 
  <div id="d32e645" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e646" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m6.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> CCS, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub>=1.6±0.6, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>A</sub>=524–535 p.p.m. and Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>=2.4–2.5 °C in 2100. For this energy profile, the 
  <div id="d32e662" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e663" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m7.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> CCS infrastructure avoids emissions up to 6.1 PgC per year and reaches a cumulative total of 383–429 PgC in 2100 (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3b</a>). In the RE-High scenario, the 
  <div id="d32e671" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e672" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m8.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> CCS infrastructure results in 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub>=0.7±0.9, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>A</sub>=443–449 p.p.m. and Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>=1.9–2.0 °C in 2100. The technology sequesters up to 5.3 PgC per year for a cumulative total of 305–403 PgC in 2100.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With CCS applied to the entire energy sector, the RE-Low+CCS scenario achieves 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub>=−4.1±5.4, where the outsized error is due to the vanishing denominator, representing natural sinks (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5b,c</a>). CCS infrastructures eliminate up to 12.6 PgC per year, with 776–981 PgC in storage by 2100. At the end of the century, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>A</sub>=393–405 p.p.m. and Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>=1.6–1.7 °C, making RE-Low+CCS an approximation of IPCC benchmark RCP 2.6 (refs 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub> rises again to 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub>=−2.1±1.0 in RE-High+CCS, as the removal of carbon from the atmosphere reverses the sign of the chemical coupling between the ocean and land reservoirs and the atmosphere, transforming them into net sources of carbon (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5b,c</a>). In this scenario, CCS eliminates up to 11.2 PgC per year and stores a cumulative total of 620–844 PgC by 2100 (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3b</a>). At the end of the century, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>A</sub>=328–363 p.p.m. and Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>=1.2–1.4 °C, making this scenario the only one consistent with global warming below 1.5 °C and beginning a return to pre-industrial atmospheric carbon concentration (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6" href="#f6">Fig. 6</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
