<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Land sink carbon flux and feedbacks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon flow from the atmosphere into the land sink begins from preindustrial net primary productivity (initial NPP=85.2 PgC per year). This initial carbon flux is coupled with atmospheric carbon concentration and global surface temperature via bio-stimulation (Λ
  <sub>C</sub>) and climate (Λ
  <sub>T</sub>) coefficients, respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bio-stimulation feedback mechanism introduces logarithmic NPP-carbon coupling as described in 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq12" href="#eq12">equation (1)</a> (
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>C</sub>=0.35). This mechanism increases land sink carbon uptake by 1.25 GtC p.p.m.
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t3" href="#t3">Table 3</a>) such that a doubling of the carbon content of the atmosphere (
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>A</sub>) relative to preindustrial 
  <div id="d32e1149" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e1150" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m11.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> generates a 24% increase in NPP before taking into account other feedbacks
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq12" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d32e1156" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m12.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within the land sink, the carbon stocks of the biosphere (plants) and pedosphere (soil) are modelled separately to account for distinct characteristic residence times. Gross carbon flow out of biomass is equal to biomass carbon stock (
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>B</sub>) divided by a constant residence time (
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>B</sub>=10.6 years). Treating this parameter as a constant neglects the impact of water and other nutrient availability in unmanaged ecosystems, which are not represented in the FeliX model
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. This flow is distributed between the pedosphere and the atmosphere according to the constant biomass humification fraction (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>H</sub>=0.428; 
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f7" href="#f7">Fig. 7</a> (2 and 3)). Gross carbon flow out of the pedosphere is equal to the carbon content of the reservoir (
  <span class="italic">C</span>
  <sub>P</sub>) divided by its residence time (
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>P</sub>). This residence time is coupled with climate, as discussed below.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon flux through the land sink is linked with global temperature change at two points in the model, providing feedback to both NPP and pedosphere residence time. NPP–climate coupling is included in the nominal land sink carbon flux through the climate coefficient (Λ
  <sub>T</sub> in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f7" href="#f7">Fig. 7</a> (4) and 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq13" href="#eq13">equation (2)</a> below), where the coefficient (
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>T</sub>=0.012 K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) is calibrated to match the average value in literature of the land sink-climate feedback mechanism
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">4</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">5</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq13" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d32e1217" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m13.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the average residence time of carbon in soil (
  <div id="d32e1220" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d32e1221" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m14.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>=27.8 per year for preindustrial climate; 
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f7" href="#f7">Fig. 7</a> (1)) is linearly coupled with climate, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq15" href="#eq15">equation (3)</a> below, where 
  <span class="italic">λ</span>
  <sub>P</sub>=0.5 year K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="eq15" class="disp-formula">
   <span id="d32e1243" xlink:href="ncomms14856-m15.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The net effect of the land sink-climate coupling reduces land sink carbon uptake by 66 PgC K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t3" href="#t3">Table 3</a>)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">4</a>. In year 2050 of the BAU scenario, this effect reduces global soil carbon reserves by 26 PgC (measured relative to BAU without the coupling. This figure is in line with the latest global estimates (30±30 PgC)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Net land sink carbon flux is plotted for all scenarios in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5c</a>. The cycling and availability of nutrients including N, P and water represent another important feedback to land sink carbon flow in general and NPP in particular
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. These considerations tend to limit NPP response to atmospheric carbon concentrations and should be included in subsequent iterations of this analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In deep decarbonization scenarios, net carbon flux into the ocean and lands reservoirs switches directions, turning these sinks into carbon sources. The simplest physical explanation for this effect is that rapid decarbonization reverses the sign, or direction, of the chemical coupling between the atmosphere, ocean and land sink. This coupling is responsible for increasing the net carbon flux into natural sinks as emissions rise; thus, it should also be expected to cause a net carbon flow out of these sinks if net-negative anthropogenic emissions are achieved and atmospheric carbon concentration begins to drop.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From another perspective, we could invoke Le Châtelier's principle to predict that the earth system will act to ‘resist' change. In deep decarbonization scenarios, the ‘change' is the reduction in atmospheric carbon concentration resulting from net-negative anthropogenic emissions and the natural ‘response' is the net flow of carbon out of the land and ocean sinks.</p>
</sec>
