<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature anomalies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HadCRUT4 data on global surface temperature anomaly are used for results validation, and represent observed temperature increases relative to the period (1850–1900) from the Met Office Hadley Center
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">38</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global surface temperature change is affected by radiative forcings, feedback cooling due to outbound longwave radiation, and heat transfer from the atmosphere and mixed ocean layer to the four deep ocean layers. Net radiative forcing is calculated from the concentration of carbon in atmosphere, a product of CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions from the energy and LULUCF sectors and other greenhouse gases, including CH
  <sub>4</sub>, N
  <sub>2</sub>O, halocarbons, and other gases and aerosols. Endogenous projections of atmospheric carbon concentration are used to model associated radiative forcing anomaly for carbon dioxide. Forcing anomalies associated with other greenhouse gases are modeled exogenously using RCP 4.5 (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>). Total greenhouse gas forcing is translated into temperature anomalies as in the C-ROADS model
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a> (
  <span class="italic">cf.</span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6" href="#f6">Fig. 6</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A negative feedback loop incorporates heat transfer from the atmosphere and the upper ocean into space via outbound longwave radiation. The magnitude of this feedback, or cooling, is determined by the ECS, a metric used to characterize the response of the global climate system to a given forcing. ECS is broadly defined as the equilibrium global mean surface temperature change following a doubling of atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration. In the FeliX model, ECS is nominally set equal to 3.0 °C/2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>. In 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 4a</a>, temperature anomaly projections are shown for the BAU scenario over the full range of probable values for ECS (1.5–4.5) as identified by the IPCC
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a>. In 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 5</a>, we plot 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>AF</sub> and Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span> projections based on ECS′=2.5 °C/2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>. This range of values is consistent with Coupled Climate Carbon Cycle Model Intercomparison Project results
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">4</a> and the latest estimates from IPCC
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">11</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
