<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The datasets consist of the observed and GCM-projected precipitation, T
 <sub class="sub">mean,</sub> T
 <sub class="sub">max</sub>, and T
 <sub class="sub">min</sub>. The observed daily data at 17 meteorological gauging stations of the HRB (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01706-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) were taken from the China Meteorological Data Service Center. The 17 different gauging stations are located in areas with different climactic conditions. Given the reliability and integrity, the observed data from 1961–2010 were selected in this study. Considering the spatial variability between stations, missing data accounting for approximate 2% of the total were generated by establishing the linear regression between the stations with missing data and their nearest stations, which were characterized by the same climate conditions. Monthly and daily data from 23 GCMs corresponding to the observed climate variables were obtained from the phase 5 of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5) archive (
 <uri xlink:href="http://cmip-pcmdi.llnl.gov/cmip5/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cmip-pcmdi.llnl.gov/cmip5/</uri>). The monthly data during 1961–2000 from 23 GCMs with different spatial resolutions were uniformly interpolated to the 2° × 2° spatial resolution to conduct the GCM performance evaluation, while the daily data were applied to generate the climate change scenarios by the statistical downscaling for the reference period (1976–2005) and the future period (2021–2050) under three RCPs (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, and RCP8.5) [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-16-01706" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. The RCPs are named depending on radiative forcing target level for 2100. RCP2.6 is defined that the peak in radiative forcing increased to 3 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> before 2100 and then declines to 2.6 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (around 490 ppm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> eq.) by 2100. The definition of the RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 are described as the stabilization without overshoot pathway to 4.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (around 650 ppm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> eq.) at stabilization after 2100 and the rising radiative forcing pathway leading to 8.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (around 1370 ppm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> eq) by 2100 [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01706" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Detailed information of the 23 GCMs referred to Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-16-01706" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>].
</p>
