<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Table 1</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Characteristics of contrails and contrail cirrus</p>
 </div>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>AIC</th>
    <th>Short-lived</th>
    <th colspan="2">Long-lived</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Ice cloud type</td>
    <td>Contrail</td>
    <td>Persistent contrail</td>
    <td>Contrail cirrus</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Morphology</td>
    <td>Line shaped</td>
    <td>Line shaped</td>
    <td>Irregularly shaped</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Meteorological condition</td>
    <td>Ice subsaturated</td>
    <td colspan="2">Ice supersaturated</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Duration</td>
    <td>0.1–10 min</td>
    <td colspan="2">10 min–10 h</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Depth</td>
    <td>100 m</td>
    <td colspan="2">100–1000 m</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Width</td>
    <td>10–100 m</td>
    <td>0.1–10 km</td>
    <td rowspan="1">&lt;100 km</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Length</td>
    <td>0.1–10 km</td>
    <td>0.1–10 km</td>
    <td rowspan="1">&lt;100 km</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>RF potential</td>
    <td>Negligible</td>
    <td>Small</td>
    <td>Large</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <div class="table-wrap-foot">
  <p>AIC subsume persistent contrails and contrail cirrus and potentially clouds either formed or modified by aircraft soot and sulphate particle emissions. In this review, the latter are not included in AIC due to lack of observational evidence of their existence. Contrails are line-shaped at formation and may attain irregular shapes due to non-uniform winds, turbulent (random) motions and humidity fluctuations at some point during their lifetime. Long-lived contrails spread out due to wind shear that is common at cruise altitudes. Those maintaining a linear shape are referred to as persistent contrails. Irregular-shaped contrail cirrus cannot be easily distinguished from natural cirrus hampering their observation. Dimensions of contrail cirrus clouds depend on poorly known morphologies and have not been studied systematically, but are likely highly variable. At northern middle latitudes, individual ice supersaturated regions may have lifetimes of several days
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143" href="#CR143">143</a>
   </span> and pathlengths exceeding 1000 km (ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144" href="#CR144">144</a>
   </span>), but such cases are rare and mean values are significantly lower. Ice supersaturated layer depths ranging between 300 and 1300 m have been estimated from corrected radiosonde soundings
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145" href="#CR145">145</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147" href="#CR147">147</a>
   </span>, often including many thin (few 100 m) layers
  </p>
 </div>
</div>
