<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To distinguish genetic groups of individuals in the AFLP dataset, a comparison was made by constructing a pairwise similarity matrix for all individuals: Dice’s coefficient was calculated and the resulting matrix was transformed using principal coordinates analysis (PCO) with Ntsys v.2.1
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b77" class="xref">77</xref>. Neighbour-nets of AFLP data were also calculated, both for individuals and populations, using the SplitsTree v.4.10 software
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b78" class="xref">78</xref>. To quantify the amount of genetic differentiation attributable to geographic and population subdivision, a hierarchical analysis of molecular variance was performed
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" class="xref">79</xref> in ARLEQUIN v.3.0 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2.4</xref>). For assessing the structure of populations, we used the Bayesian method implemented in STRUCTURE 2.2
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" class="xref">80</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81" class="xref">81</xref>, assuming admixture conditions and uncorrelated allele frequencies between groups, 500,000 generations (plus a burn-in of 100,000) were run for 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic> values of 1–10, with ten repetitions each. For each 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic> value, only the run with the highest maximum likelihood value was considered. The LnP (D) for the successive decomposition of groups was used in all STRUCTURE analyses
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b82" class="xref">82</xref>. To test the effect of the spatial distance on the genetic structure of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> populations, correlations between genetic (measured as F
 <sub class="sub">ST</sub>) and spatial distances between pairs of populations were determined using the Mantel permutation procedure in Ntsys. The genetic distance matrix used was based on the presence/absence matrix; the geographic distance matrix was based on absolute distances between the geographic coordinates for each collected population. In addition, the kinship multilocus coefficient (F
 <sub class="sub">IJ</sub>) was estimated using SPAGeDi
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" class="xref">83</xref> to determine the spatial structure of the examined populations, taking spatial distances into account in the analyses. BARRIER v.2.2
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" class="xref">84</xref> was used to identify possible geographic locations acting as major genetic barriers among 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> populations, based on genetic distances. The significance of these was examined with 1000 bootstrapped distance matrices obtained using AFLPsurv.
</p>
