<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Description of the study system</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The central Baltic Sea pelagic fish biomass is dominated by two clupeid stocks, Baltic sprat (
   <span class="italic">Sprattus sprattus</span>) and central Baltic herring (
   <span class="italic">Clupea harengus</span>). Both are important consumers in the pelagic food web [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref044">44</a>], serve as key food for the Eastern Baltic cod stock (
   <span class="italic">Gadus morhua</span>, [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref045">45</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref046">46</a>]) and form part of the diet of seals as well [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref047">47</a>]. They compete for food [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref048">48</a>], and herring growth is negatively affected by high sprat densities [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref049">49</a>]. Changes in the salinity, temperature and oxygen concentration affect food availability, recruitment conditions and growth of cod, herring and sprat [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref050">50</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref052">52</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cod, herring and sprat represent the main target species of the Baltic Sea harvest fisheries, making about 95% of the total catches [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref053">53</a>]. Demersal trawlers and gillnetters mainly target cod, while pelagic trawlers target herring and sprat [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref053">53</a>].The cod, herring and sprat fisheries in the Baltic are governed by the EU as guided by the Common Fisheries Policy (CFP). Annual total allowable catches (TAC) are set on the basis of a multiannual management plan which is based on ranges of F levels that provide yields not less than 95% of MSY [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref054">54</a>] F ranges are used in an attempt to consider ecosystem consequences of the fishery and management, e.g. a stock can be fished at higher F than F
   <sub>MSY</sub> (but below the upper F range) if it is necessary to avoid serious harm to the stock caused by intra- or interspecific stock dynamics.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystem models</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Major components and interactions represented in the three ecosystem models we used are shown on 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211320.g001" href="#pone.0211320.g001">Fig 1</a>. A more detailed description of the modelling approaches and their implementation for the Baltic Sea can be found in the 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211320.s001" href="#pone.0211320.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, chapters 1–4.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0211320.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0211320.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Model components and interactions in (A) EwE, (B) Gadget and (C) MSPM models of the Baltic Sea ecosystem.</div>
    <p>Grey shaded ovals represent the three fish stocks included in all models. Green ovals denote components unique to a model. Black arrows represent predation, the red arrow competition, and blue arrows abiotic environmental effects. Single-headed arrows represent one-way interactions and double-headed arrows dynamic predator-prey feedbacks. Fitting periods for the models were 2004–2013 (EwE), 1974–2013 (Gadget) and 1982–2013 (MSPM). EwE and MSPM have yearly, while Gadget quarterly time steps.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">Ecopath with Ecosim</span> (EwE; [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref006">6</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref031">31</a>] is a commonly used software and process-based modelling approach to study whole-ecosystem effects of fisheries. The EwE model of the open Baltic Sea [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref055">55</a>] includes charismatic species such as grey seals and offshore fish-feeding birds, four fish species (cod, herring, sprat and flounder), the benthic part of the food web, four zooplankton groups and one phytoplankton group. The Ecopath component represents biomass flows among organismal groups within the food web and to fisheries in the ‘model year’, 2004. Ecosim dynamically simulates the temporal development of biomasses and catches in the system 2004–2013 given certain fishing mortalities (defined as yearly harvest rate, catch/biomass) and environmental forcing. EwE model simulations have been carried out using the software Ecopath with Ecosim v. 6.5.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">Gadget</span> is a platform to run statistical models of marine ecosystems consisting of a limited number of species, accounting for biological processes, such as maturation, growth, predation, etc. [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref056">56</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref057">57</a>]. The Gadget implementation in the Baltic is a multispecies and multifleet model. Trophic interactions are represented by cod feeding on both herring and sprat, as well as on benthic prey. The model is age-length structured with quarterly time steps running from 1974 to 2013. The current implementation uses the package Rgadget v.0.5 [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref058">58</a>] under R v.3.4.1 [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref059">59</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">The MultiSpecies Production Model (MSPM,</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref034">34</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref035">35</a>] is a simplification of the age-structured multispecies model of [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref060">60</a>]. The model was applied to simulate stock dynamics in yearly time steps and interactions of the cod, herring, and sprat stocks in the central Baltic from 1982 to 2013. It considers the trophic interactions among these stocks (predation of cod on herring, sprat, and young cod), the environmental impact on growth of cod and herring and density dependent growth of sprat. Predation in the model depends on the biomass of available food, thus cod cannibalism is dependent on clupeid biomass. Model simulations were run using Excel 2010 with VisualBasic.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All three models provide information about the biomasses of three stocks of interest (cod, herring, sprat) in the central Baltic (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211320.g001" href="#pone.0211320.g001">Fig 1</a>), with EwE and MSPM providing limited information about the internal structure of each stock (both simulating only a few stanzas per stock). Only Gadget represents age and size structure of populations in both biomass and numbers. On the other hand, EwE and MSPM both incorporate the dependency of the cod biomass growth on prey availability, although partly through different mechanisms (
   <a rid="pone.0211320.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0211320.t001">Table 1</a>), while in Gadget the growth of cod is not limited by the amount of available prey biomass. Both direct and indirect interactions of seals with the fisheries via predation for the same fish resources and via damage of the catches in the small-scale fisheries are accounted for by EwE and Gadget but not by MSPM. For a summary of model assumptions see 
   <a rid="pone.0211320.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0211320.t001">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0211320.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0211320.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Comparison of key assumptions with respect to population structure (1–3), trophic interactions (3–6) and human and abiotic environmental pressures (7–8).</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0211320.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model assumptions on</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecopath with Ecosim</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gadget</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multispecies Stock Production Model</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Fish population structure</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biomass density (t/km
        <span class="sup">2</span>) of adult and young fish components
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total number of individuals in stock; Length-age groups, biomass derived from length-weight relationship</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total biomass (t) of adult and young fish components</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Stock-recruitment (SR) relationship</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex, number of recruits depends on weight-dependent fecundity and on environmental forcing</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hockey-stick on all stocks</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cod: Ricker; herring and sprat: Beverton-Holt</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Cod predation</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increases up to a maximum level with increasing cod biomass and linearly increases with prey biomass. Maximum predation mortality by cod much lower for herring than for sprat.</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increases up to a maximum level with increasing cod biomass and increases with prey availability.</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predation mortality of a certain prey linearly increases with increasing cod biomass and declines with total prey biomass</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Prey feedback on cod</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population growth varies with food consumption</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not included</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High biomass of clupeids leads to decline in cod cannibalism and vice versa</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Clupeid predation</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynamics explicitly modelled, clupeids compete for shared prey</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not included</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not included</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. Seal predation</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saturating function of seal biomass and linear function of prey biomass. Potential increase of predation mortality by seals on any prey compared to current levels is limited</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear function of seal biomass and increasing function of prey biomass</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not included</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. Abiotic environmental dependency</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reproduction, consumption rates of zooplankton and some benthos groups, primary production</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not included</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth efficiency (anabolism rate, only cod and herring)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. Fishing mortality (F) implemented as</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual catch/biomass</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quarterly catch/harvestable biomass in respective quarter</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Instantaneous fishing mortality</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To focus on structural differences and minimize data-driven differences among models, we used the same datasets for model parametrization (e.g. surveys, commercial catches and assessments, see Table D in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211320.s001" href="#pone.0211320.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, chapter 4) as far as it was possible. A common database containing cod stomach survey data was used to parametrise the diet of cod, the most important predator in all models [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref061">61</a>]. We tested hindcast performance of the models by comparing simulated values to observations (catch, profit) or to the mean value of the three model estimates (biomass, demersal to pelagic ratio) from 2004–2012, which is the cross-section of the calibration periods of the models.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Performance indicators</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We considered three indicators: spawning stock biomass (SSB), catches (by stocks) and profit (by fleet segments). In EwE and MSPM SSB was approximated as the biomass of the adult fish components. In Gadget SSB was estimated using age specific proportion of mature fish [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref062">62</a>] and results from quarterly time steps were aggregated into yearly means before any further analysis. There are three fleet segments of interest defined in the case study: 1) active (bottom trawls, BT) and 2) passive (gillnets, longlines, mostly small-scale fishery, GN) gears targeting cod and 3) pelagic trawl (PT) fishery targeting sprat and herring.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In EwE and MSPM the amounts of cod landings by BT vs. GN are calculated based on the total amount of cod catch in the model output (based on F). Total cod catches were distributed to the two fleet segments based on the relative amount of cod catches in 2013 (landings data from ICES), which were 83% BT and 17% GN. Gadget predicts cod catches separately for BT and GN assuming that their relative contribution to the catch follows the average of their relative harvest rate in the period 2009–2013 and their specific selection patterns. We assume all catches as landings since we expect discards to be reduced in the future because of the implementation of the landings obligation within the European Union.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all models, the profit in each year is calculated as landings multiplied by price minus costs. Fish prices are based on Swedish sale notes (average values 2011–2015). In the case of cod, costs are calculated as F times a cost coefficient [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref063">63</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref064">64</a>]. Cost coefficient parameters are calculated separately for BT and GN fisheries based on the data by the Scientific, Technical and Economic Committee for Fisheries (STECF). In the Gadget and EwE models profits in the cod fishery are negatively affected by seal abundance. We assume that increasing seal abundance increases the amount of damaged and therefore discarded cod within the passive gears segment. Costs of the clupeid fisheries are calculated as landings multiplied by a cost coefficient. Cost coefficient parameters are taken from [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref065">65</a>]. Profit of PT is calculated as the sum of herring and sprat profits. More details on the calculation of costs, profits and the effect of seal abundance on profits are included in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211320.s001" href="#pone.0211320.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, chapter 6.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model simulations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a multi-factorial simulation design: one simulation was run for each unique combination of two nutrient load scenarios (‘Business-As-Usual’, BAU, and Baltic Sea Action Plan, ‘BSAP’) and/or two seal population growth scenarios (Low Seal, LSE, and High Seal, HSE), and fishing mortality (varied in a range, e.g. 0–1.4, among simulations), for the years 2014–2032 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211320.g002" href="#pone.0211320.g002">Fig 2</a>). This resulted in a large number of simulations, and we calculated temporally aggregated metrics, such as cumulative yield and profit during the whole modelled period for meaningful comparison of the outcomes. We investigated the F-cumulative yield (= summed catches 2014–2032) relationship under each environmental scenario based on these simulations.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0211320.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0211320.g002</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Summary of the framework.</div>
    <p>Light shaded rectangles describe the main steps of the modelling work, dark shaded rectangles indicate scientific products potentially useful for ecosystem-based fisheries management. See 
     <a rid="pone.0211320.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0211320.t002">Table 2</a> for description of alternative fisheries management scenarios and Methods for the definition of nutrient and seal scenarios.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="pone.0211320.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0211320.t002</span>
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Alternative management scenarios.</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0211320.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.t002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario</th>
       <th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Objective
        <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001" href="#t002fn001">
         <span class="sup">a</span>
        </a>
       </th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscivore Exploitation (PE)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximize summed cumulative discounted profit of bottom trawlers (BT) and gillnetters (GN) based on their cod catches</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <div id="pone.0211320.e001" class="inline-formula">
         <div class="alternatives">
          <div id="pone.0211320.e001g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.e001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
          <div id="M1" class="math">
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">m</span>
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">a</span>
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">x</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
             <div class="munderover">
              <span stretchy="false" class="mo">∑</span>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</span>
               <span class="mo">=</span>
               <span class="mn">2014</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</span>
               <span class="mo">=</span>
               <span class="mn">2032</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">P</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">c</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forage Fish Exploitation (FE)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximize cumulative discounted profit of pelagic trawlers (PT) based on their herring and sprat catches</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <div id="pone.0211320.e002" class="inline-formula">
         <div class="alternatives">
          <div id="pone.0211320.e002g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.e002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
          <div id="M2" class="math">
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">m</span>
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">a</span>
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">x</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
             <div class="munderover">
              <span stretchy="false" class="mo">∑</span>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</span>
               <span class="mo">=</span>
               <span class="mn">2014</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</span>
               <span class="mo">=</span>
               <span class="mn">2032</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <div class="mrow">
               <span class="mo">(</span>
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">P</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">h</span>
              </div>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">+</span>
             <div class="msub">
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">P</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">s</span>
              </div>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">)</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portfolio Fishery (PF)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximize cumulative discounted total fisheries profits.</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <div id="pone.0211320.e003" class="inline-formula">
         <div class="alternatives">
          <div id="pone.0211320.e003g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.e003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
          <div id="M3" class="math">
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">m</span>
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">a</span>
           <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">x</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
             <div class="munderover">
              <span stretchy="false" class="mo">∑</span>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</span>
               <span class="mo">=</span>
               <span class="mn">2014</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">y</span>
               <span class="mo">=</span>
               <span class="mn">2032</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">P</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">c</span>
               <span class="mo">,</span>
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">h</span>
               <span class="mo">,</span>
               <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">s</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piscivore Recovery (PR)</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximize cod biomass compared to clupeids with constraint keeping herring and sprat at viable levels
        <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002" href="#t002fn002">
         <span class="sup">b</span>
        </a>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <div id="pone.0211320.e004" class="inline-formula">
         <div class="alternatives">
          <div id="pone.0211320.e004g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.e004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
          <div id="M4" class="math">
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="bold" class="mtext">max</span>
             <span class="mo">(</span>
            </div>
            <span width="1pt" class="mspace"/>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msubsup">
              <div class="mrow">
               <div accent="true" class="mover">
                <div class="mrow">
                 <div class="mfrac">
                  <div class="mrow">
                   <div class="msub">
                    <div class="mrow">
                     <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
                    </div>
                    <div class="mrow">
                     <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">c</span>
                    </div>
                   </div>
                  </div>
                  <div class="mrow">
                   <div class="msub">
                    <div class="mrow">
                     <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
                    </div>
                    <div class="mrow">
                     <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">s</span>
                    </div>
                   </div>
                   <span class="mo">+</span>
                   <div class="msub">
                    <div class="mrow">
                     <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
                    </div>
                    <div class="mrow">
                     <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">h</span>
                    </div>
                   </div>
                  </div>
                 </div>
                 <span class="mo">)</span>
                </div>
                <span class="mo">-</span>
               </div>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span class="mn">2028</span>
              </div>
              <div class="mrow">
               <span class="mn">2032</span>
              </div>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">,</span>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="break"/>
        <div id="pone.0211320.e005" class="inline-formula">
         <div class="alternatives">
          <div id="pone.0211320.e005g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.e005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
          <div id="M5" class="math">
           <div class="msubsup">
            <div class="mrow">
             <div accent="true" class="mover">
              <div class="mrow">
               <div class="msub">
                <div class="mrow">
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">S</span>
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">S</span>
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
                </div>
                <div class="mrow">
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">h</span>
                </div>
               </div>
              </div>
              <span class="mo">-</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mn">2028</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mn">2032</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">&gt;</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">l</span>
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">i</span>
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">m</span>
             <span class="mo">,</span>
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">h</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="break"/>
        <div id="pone.0211320.e006" class="inline-formula">
         <div class="alternatives">
          <div id="pone.0211320.e006g" xlink:href="pone.0211320.e006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
          <div id="M6" class="math">
           <div class="msubsup">
            <div class="mrow">
             <div accent="true" class="mover">
              <div class="mrow">
               <div class="msub">
                <div class="mrow">
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">S</span>
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">S</span>
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
                </div>
                <div class="mrow">
                 <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">s</span>
                </div>
               </div>
              </div>
              <span class="mo">-</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mn">2028</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mn">2032</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">&gt;</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">B</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">l</span>
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">i</span>
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">m</span>
             <span class="mo">,</span>
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">s</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Status Quo (SQ)</td>
       <td align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fs set to average of the last three years’ (2011–2013) values in model hindcast</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="t002fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">a</span>Fishing mortality rate (F) values were individually selected in each model according to the objectives of each scenario, except for the ‘Status Quo’ scenario which represents a continuation of current practices. 
      <span class="italic">P</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">i</span>
      </sub> values represent yearly discounted profits to net present value from fisheries on stock 
      <span class="italic">i</span>, 
      <span class="italic">B</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">i</span>
      </sub> annual biomasses and 
      <span class="italic">SSB</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">i</span>
      </sub> spawning stock biomasses of stock 
      <span class="italic">i</span>, where the subscripts 
      <span class="italic">c</span>, 
      <span class="italic">h</span> and 
      <span class="italic">s</span> refer to cod, herring and sprat, respectively.
     </p>
    </fn>
    <fn id="t002fn002" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">b</span>
      <span class="italic">B</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">lim</span>
      </sub> values were taken from ICES assessments [
      <a rid="pone.0211320.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref053">53</a>], rescaled in each model based on the correlation of model hindcasts on SSB with ICES estimates (for details see 
      <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211320.s001" href="#pone.0211320.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, chapter 7).
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two nutrient management scenarios [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref066">66</a>] have an effect on the eutrophication of the basin and severity of oxygen depletion. One is BAU, assuming increasing nutrient loads in the future. The other scenario, BSAP, assumes future nutrient loads corresponding to the Baltic Sea Action Plan. Both of these scenarios were simulated assuming climate change as in the IPCC scenario A1B, implying moderate warming [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref067">67</a>], based on regionally downscaled outputs from the HadCM3 global climate model [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref068">68</a>]. Environmental scenarios were simulated by BALTSEM [
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref069">69</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0211320.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref070">70</a>], a hydrodynamical-biogeochemical model and its output was used to force the multispecies models. Thus, environmental scenarios are realistic projections of possible future developments taking into account irregular events, such as saltwater inflows. Scenario generation using BALTSEM is described in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211320.s001" href="#pone.0211320.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, chapter 5. BALTSEM scenarios were implemented in EwE and MSPM as described in Table E in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211320.s001" href="#pone.0211320.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, chapter 5. The two models also used BALTSEM hindcast results for the periods 2004–2013 and 1982–2012, respectively, as forcing during model calibration. The two seal population growth scenarios investigated include 5% (LSE) and 10% (HSE) growth rates.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequently, we analysed simulated model advice in five hypothetical management scenarios (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211320.g002" href="#pone.0211320.g002">Fig 2</a>). Here, we define ‘management scenario’ by a given management key objective, for example the profit for one or more of the Baltic fisheries (
   <a rid="pone.0211320.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0211320.t002">Table 2</a>). Fisheries management under the ‘Piscivore Exploitation’ and the ‘Forage Fish Exploitation’ scenarios aims to maximize profits of the cod and clupeid fisheries, respectively, and the total profits under the ‘Portfolio Fishery’ scenario. We assume that in each of these scenarios fisheries aim to maximize cumulative discounted profits, i.e. net present value by applying a 3% discount rate. In the case of the ‘Piscivore Recovery’ management scenario, the cod-clupeid biomass ratio is maximized. As this scenario represented the most ‘environmentally conscious’ management of all scenarios considered, we added the criteria that herring and sprat spawning stock biomasses (SSB) could not fall below minimum levels (
   <span class="italic">B</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">lim</span>
   </sub>). The ‘Status Quo’ scenario was defined as the continuation of ‘current’ fishing practices, that is, fishing mortalities corresponding to the average of values 2011–2013.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From all simulations, we selected those where the management scenario objective was satisfied, separately for each nutrient and seal scenario and each model (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211320.g002" href="#pone.0211320.g002">Fig 2</a>). For example, from all simulations of the EwE model run under the combination of the BAU nutrient and HSE seal scenario, we selected those where cod/clupeid/total profits were the highest (‘Piscivore Exploitation’/’Forage Fish Exploitation’/’Portfolio Fishery’ scenario, respectively), those that fulfilled biomass criteria (‘Piscivore Recovery’) or where Fs equaled those of the average of the last three years (‘Status Quo’). We repeated this for Gadget and MSPM, and we compared model agreement on Fs and a set of performance indicators corresponding to each of the five management scenarios, and we repeated this for all combinations of environmental scenarios. We assumed that models insensitive to nutrient or seal scenarios provide the same information in both scenarios (e.g. Gadget outputs under BAU and BSAP are equivalent).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model agreement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We define model agreement as being negatively related to the dispersion of model outputs (the more deviating outputs models provide, the less they agree). Model agreement was quantified in two ways. The first method (‘
   <span class="italic">A</span>’ index) is based on measures of dispersion of qualitative variables, e.g. diversity indices. It aims to describe model agreement regarding relative trends, including cases when a model does not provide information (i.e., according to the model, multiple possible trends are possible). The second index is based on a quantitative measure of dispersion, the coefficient of variation (CV). We calculate 1/CV, the inverse of the CV of numeric model outputs (thus, only including cases when models provide such outputs). We determine model agreement using these two methods both in terms of selected Fs and performance of management scenarios.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ‘
   <span class="italic">A</span>’ index measures how often for one management scenario the different models provide the same information on Fs (‘how much does F need to be changed to reach the management objective of the scenario?’) or management scenario performance (‘how is a performance indicator going to change under that scenario?’). ‘A’ also considers the influence of environmental scenarios. For example, if one model provides different information on a performance indicator under the same management scenario, but different environmental scenarios, ‘A’ becomes lower. This way ‘A’ integrates model and environmental uncertainty of the advice. We calculate 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">i</span>
   </sub> as 
   <div id="pone.0211320.e007" class="disp-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.e007.jpg" id="pone.0211320.e007g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M7" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">A</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">i</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">∑</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">j</span>
         <span class="mo">=</span>
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">j</span>
         <span class="mo">=</span>
         <span class="mn">6</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="mfrac">
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">N</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mi">j</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">N</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">i</span>
             <span class="mi">j</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">-</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">N</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mi">i</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">N</span>
            </div>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">i</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">-</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">,</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div> where 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">i</span>
   </sub> is the total number of cases when model information on 
   <span class="italic">i</span> (selected F for a stock or a performance indicator) is provided, of which 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">ij</span>
   </sub> belong to the category 
   <span class="italic">j</span> (
   <div id="pone.0211320.e008" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.e008.jpg" id="pone.0211320.e008g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M8" class="math">
      <span class="mi">j</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">1,2</span>
      <span class="mo">,</span>
      <span class="mo">…</span>
      <span class="mn">6</span>
      <span class="mo">;</span>
      <span width="1pt" class="mspace"/>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="munder">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">∑</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">j</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">i</span>
          <span class="mi">j</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">i</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>). We use the following 6 categories: compared to average 2011–2013 values, 
   <span class="italic">1</span>: more than 20% decrease, 
   <span class="italic">2</span>: 10–20% decrease, 
   <span class="italic">3</span>: not more than +/- 10% change, 
   <span class="italic">4</span>: 10–20% increase, 
   <span class="italic">5</span>: more than 20% increase, 
   <span class="italic">6</span>: no information. For example, 
   <div id="pone.0211320.e009" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.e009.jpg" id="pone.0211320.e009g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M9" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">N</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">F</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">c</span>
          <span class="mi">o</span>
          <span class="mi">d</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">3</span>
      <span class="mi">*</span>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
      <span class="mi">*</span>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">12</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> when calculating 
   <div id="pone.0211320.e010" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.e010.jpg" id="pone.0211320.e010g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M10" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">A</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">F</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">c</span>
          <span class="mi">o</span>
          <span class="mi">d</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> for a particular management scenario on the advice on F for cod (3 models, 2 environmental and 2 seal scenarios) and 
   <div id="pone.0211320.e011" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.e011.jpg" id="pone.0211320.e011g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M11" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">N</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">S</span>
          <span class="mi">S</span>
          <span class="mi">B</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">c</span>
          <span class="mi">o</span>
          <span class="mi">d</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">12</span>
      <span class="mi">*</span>
      <span class="mn">13</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">156</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> when calculating 
   <div id="pone.0211320.e012" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="pone.0211320.e012.jpg" id="pone.0211320.e012g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <div id="M12" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">A</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">S</span>
          <span class="mi">S</span>
          <span class="mi">B</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">c</span>
          <span class="mi">o</span>
          <span class="mi">d</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> on scenario performance for the SSB of Eastern Baltic cod, as we include SSB outputs from 13 years (each year 2020–2032). We exclude the years 2014–2019 from the analysis of performance indicators (SSBs, catches and yearly profits) as transition period. To calculate 
   <span class="italic">A</span>, the overall model agreement on one scenario, 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">i</span>
   </sub> values calculated across stocks (selected Fs) or performance indicators (scenario performance) are averaged. In Gadget, clupeid Fs have no influence on cod yields and therefore profits, and thus, nor values for clupeid Fs that maximize cod profits (the objective of the ‘Piscivore Exploitation’ scenario) neither corresponding stock status or catches of clupeids could be estimated. The category ‘no information’ was used in the case of Gadget, referring to clupeid Fs and related indicators (SSBs of herring and sprat, profit of pelagic trawls and total profit) in the ‘Piscivore Exploitation’ scenario.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
