<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To identify areas of high threat intensity from climate and land-use change for vertebrate species richness (high threat, hereafter), we used a spatial threshold approach (
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>). As high-threat areas, we identified the 25% of all grid cells globally with the highest loss in projected species richness (summed probability of occurrence) as obtained by the SDMs or with the highest increase in percentage cover of the respective land-use type. To allow for a better comparison between the RCPs (RCP2.6 and RCP6.0), GCMs, and model algorithms (GAM, GBM), we first pooled all values for the respective threat and for each grid cell from all these categories and then calculated one 25% cut-off value for each of the four threats and each taxon based on these pooled datasets. We stress that by applying this approach we did not consider the scenarios separately, but combined all grid cells of both scenarios and identified the 25% of cells with the highest negative threat levels for this combined dataset. For example, as the overall increase in bioenergy cropland area is extremely low in RCP6.0, but very high in RCP2.6, this leads to a much larger number of high-threat grid cells in RCP2.6. We highlighted high-threat areas separately for climate change only and land-use change only (the latter separately for bioenergy cropland, nonbioenergy cropland, and pastures), as well as for areas of threat overlap (i.e., for any combination of the four different threats) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S10
 </ext-link>) separately for each taxon and under the no-dispersal and basic dispersal assumptions.
</p>
