<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The intensification of the interannual correlation between temperature and precipitation during the warm season (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">Fig. 4B</xref>) is possibly caused by an increased land-atmosphere feedback in a warmer climate (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>). Warmer temperatures and stronger radiative forcing generate higher evaporation rates, potentially drying out the soil earlier in the season and therefore reducing evaporative cooling during summer (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>). In particular, in higher latitudes, an overall greener land surface in combination with a longer growing season may also lead to higher transpiration rates in spring (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>), decreasing soil moisture and thus potentially further increasing temperatures by increasing sensible heat (
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">35</italic>
 </xref>). The importance of the land surface for this change in correlation is also underlined by the fact that, over oceans, the negative correlation between temperature and precipitation is absent or reversed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1A</xref>). In addition to land surface feedbacks, changes in dynamical forcing may explain some of the observed trends in interannual correlation. In particular, changes in atmospheric circulation patterns related to changes in planetary waves may be partly responsible for the detected change in correlation in some regions (
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">36</italic>
 </xref>). For instance, certain planetary waves have been linked to extreme conditions in precipitation and temperature in midlatitudes (
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">37</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">39</italic>
 </xref>) and may be amplified in response to anthropogenic climate change (
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">38</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">39</italic>
 </xref>). However, model projections of circulation patterns are highly uncertain (
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">40</italic>
 </xref>). Unraveling the drivers of the change in correlation is important for assessing the robustness of the model results and estimating future risks related to compound events.
</p>
