<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent study [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C52">52</a>] used a scenario-based approach to propose a larger remaining carbon budget for limiting warming to below 1.5°C than the IPCC-AR5 assessment [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C15">15</a>]. This was based, in part, on applying ranges of ESM-based uncertainty in the warming response to cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions to deduce remaining budgets for further warming above the present-day climate state, but did not try to further constrain the TCRE or effective TCRE from the ESM range. Here, we have analysed the implications of the observational record of warming and cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions to update previous observational constraints on the TCRE. While uncertainties associated with natural variability and poorly constrained ERF of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> climate forcers are generally large, we find a best-estimate TCRE from an attribution analysis of the historical record of 1.31 K/TtC, in the lower half of the IPCC-AR5 likely range, with uncertainties approximately spanning the 0.8–2.5 K/TtC AR5 TCRE range (0.88–2.60°C/TtC 5–95% range). We find a higher upper uncertainty bound on TCRE than found using observational constraints in [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C2">2</a>], possibly associated with the different methodologies for accounting for uncertainty in the fractional contribution of CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming to total forced warming. Differences over the historical period between ESMs and observations seem to arise in part from a higher mean CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming in the ESM ensemble, rapid non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming since 2000 in some ESMs, and from lower than observed diagnosed cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions for many members of the ESM ensemble.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on our best-estimate of the historical effective TCRE (1.84°C/TtC), assuming a constant effective TCRE into the future would be compatible with a best-estimate 520 GtC remaining budget (approx. 47 years of current emissions—all budgets given to nearest 5 GtC) for 2°C and 250 GtC (approx. 23 years of current emissions) for 1.5°C. Using global air-temperature warming from ESM simulations only, IPCC-AR5 assessed that limiting warming below 2°C relative to preindustrial, with a probability greater than 66%, requires cumulative carbon emissions (since preindustrial) to remain below 790 GtC (top purple cross in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">c</span>). AR5 Synthesis Report [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C15">15</a>] provided a 615 GtC all-time budget for remaining below 1.5°C in 66% of CMIP5 RCP8.5 simulations (assuming a constant effective TCRE compatible with the 2°C budget would imply a 1.5°C all-time budget of 590 GtC). Subtracting the latest estimates of historical emissions, updated to 2016 inclusive (565 GtC, [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C24">24</a>]), the remaining cumulative carbon emissions consistent with the 1.5°C and 2°C target could be inferred as 50 and 225 GtC, respectively, equivalent to approximately 5 and 20 years of present-day emissions. As the ESM distribution lies to the top end or even outside of the uncertainty distribution for the historical effective TCRE, estimates of the carbon budget to keep warming likely below 1.5°C based on the upper end of the ESM effective TCRE distribution may be overly restrictive.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observational uncertainties that we consider here do not include the effect of methodological choices for both historical warming and cumulative emissions, which can be large. As a sensitivity exercise we use the Berkeley Earth temperature dataset [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C23">23</a>] (which displays a larger warming from preindustrial than HadCRUT4-CW), and the recently released GCP 2017 dataset [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C25">25</a>], which includes a substantial increase in the best-estimate of historical land-use change CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions. Using the Berkeley Earth temperature dataset (electronic supplementary material, figure S5) would increase the estimated effective TCRE best-estimate to 2.05°C/TtC (1.46°C/TtC for the CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE), while using the 2017 GCP dataset (electronic supplementary material, figure S6) would reduce the effective TCRE best-estimate to 1.72°C/TtC (1.23°C/TtC for CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE), with widened uncertainty bounds associated with greater uncertainty over historical land-use change emissions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are several reasons to be cautious about extrapolating carbon budgets from effective TCRE estimates derived from historical data alone. Inferences from the historical period may not be particularly useful for understanding climate changes under very high future emission scenarios. Climate feedbacks may evolve substantially over time [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C53">53</a>], leading to increases in important climate response parameters such as the transient climate response beyond the first doubling of CO
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C54">54</a>]. However, for very ambitious mitigation scenarios, changes in the transient climate response and the effect of additional carbon-cycle feedbacks on remaining budgets would be expected to be much smaller than seen under high future emission scenarios. Therefore, if risks of ‘tipping-point’ Earth system feedbacks below 2°C are small, the historical record could indeed offer relevant information about the TCRE that is useful for assessments of pathways to meet ambitious mitigation goals. However, the risk of currently unpredicted and unmodelled Earth system feedbacks still remains possible and acts as a caveat on all inferences about remaining carbon budgets from the historical period. The probability of additional Earth system feedback, and its impact on remaining carbon budgets, should be a topic for further scientific investigation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An additional important caveat regarding the use of the historical record to constrain remaining carbon budgets is the extent to which the future relationships between CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming, non-CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and natural variability are likely to change. As emissions of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and other climatically important gases are co-emitted in many cases, it remains unclear to the extent that CO
  <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> mitigation can be considered separable at a global scale, given uncertainties in future technological development and economic demand [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C55">55</a>]. Rogelj 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C56">56</a>] indicates that future emission scenarios span a wide range of best-estimate contributions from non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming at the time of crossing temperature thresholds, which, when convolved with the physical uncertainties for a specific emission scenario (see electronic supplementary material, figure S4), leads to substantial uncertainty regarding the relative changes in the fractional contribution of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming to temperature thresholds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If future non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> mitigation could be implemented to reduce the fraction of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming below today's levels by the time of net-zero CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, then remaining budgets would be further extended. For example, if this fraction could be reduced to approximately 15% at peak warming, our best-estimate remaining budgets for 1.5°C and 2°C may be extended to approximately 730 and 410 GtC, respectively (based on the best-estimate CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE), indicating the potential importance of this uncertainty for ambitious mitigation policy. Understanding possible future evolutions of this fraction under climate policy therefore remains an important challenge for further research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the currently irreducible uncertainties in observationally based estimates of the TCRE, prudent climate policy to hedge against the possibility of a high TCRE is required. However, climate policies should ideally be designed to incorporate new information about the climate response into the ratcheting up of mitigation ambition over the century, as we learn more about the climate response over time. Earth system modelling approaches that more directly parallel the Paris Agreement's goal-driven pledge and review mechanism to end up with stabilized warming at specific thresholds [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C57">57</a>] may be more effective ways of using Earth system modelling frameworks to assess what future mitigation pathways might be consistent with ambitious mitigation goals.
 </p>
</sec>
