<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="s3a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating effective TCRE from the observational record and ESMs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed warming is driven by multiple anthropogenic forcing agents; however, the concept of TCRE was derived from model-based results that focused primarily on CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only forced simulations [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C2">2</a>,
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C9">9</a>]. The physical mechanisms that give rise to the approximate linearity between CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and cumulative emissions, namely the compensation between logarithmic CO
   <sub>2</sub> radiative forcing and increasing airborne fraction [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C9">9</a>,
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C37">37</a>], apply to CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming only. As such, a time-independent effective (all-forcing) TCRE would only be expected to the extent that CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming dominates the forcing mix, or if the relative contribution of non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> forcing to warming remains approximately constant over time.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observational time-series (together with their uncertainties, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>) can be used to assess the extent that the effective TCRE varies over time in the observational record. Grey bars in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span> show the 5–95% of historical effective TCRE associated purely with observational uncertainty. These are estimated using independent pairings of the HadCRUT4-CW and historical cumulative emission ensembles averaged over the periods shown to the right of the bars. They show a non-constant effective TCRE increasing from the early 1970s up until the 2010s. For the most recent decade (2007–2016), purely observational uncertainty in effective TCRE spans a 1.51–2.19°C/TtC 5–95% range, dominated by uncertainty in the historical cumulative emissions which vary by ±17% (5–95% uncertainty) compared with ±8% for the HadCRUT4-CW ensemble. 
   <div id="RSTA20160449F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Implications of the historical record for constraining TCRE. (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Time-series of warming as a function of cumulative emissions for members of the observational HadCRUT4/GCP ensemble (grey), the best-estimate HadCRUT4-CW/GCP time-series (red) and best-estimate human-induced warming for HadCRUT4-CW (black) with beige lines showing a random sample from the joint human-induced warming/emission uncertainty. Estimates for the effective TCRE over a range of periods are shown in (
      <span class="italic">b</span>), derived from the same data as in (
      <span class="italic">a</span>). Grey bars show 5–95% ranges for observational uncertainty from the HadCRUT4/GCP ensemble. Beige bars show 5–95% ranges for total uncertainty from the human-induced warming calculation and emission observations. (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) The best-estimate (black line) and a random sample from the joint evolution of CO
      <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and cumulative emissions over the historical period (beige lines). Panel (
      <span class="italic">d</span>) as for panel (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) but using the data in panel (
      <span class="italic">c</span>). Black dots mark the best-estimate CO
      <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE estimate for each period. (Online version in colour.) 
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed warming is determined by a combination of an externally forced warming (associated with human and natural forcing on the climate system) and natural climate variability. Unlike contributions from natural variability, warming driven by human activity is expected to evolve relatively smoothly in time. To estimate human-induced warming, we use an attribution analysis. This analysis is based on the optimal fingerprinting method of detection and attribution of climate change [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C38">38</a>], which uses a multiple linear regression to decompose observed warming, Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>obs</sub>, into a forced component associated with anthropogenic drivers, Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>anthro</sub>—the human-induced warming, a forced component associated with natural drivers, Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>nat</sub>, and an unforced residual natural variability (
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>), with 
   <span class="italic">δ</span> acting as a regression constant, 
   <div id="RSTA20160449M3.1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">3.1</span>
    <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-e1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> We use a two-time constant impulse response model to simulate the forced warming regressor, Δ
   <span class="italic">T
    <sub>n</sub>
   </span>, for a particular component, 
   <span class="italic">F
    <sub>n</sub>
   </span>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>), of the total ERF acting on the climate system [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C39">39</a>,
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C40">40</a>], 
   <div id="RSTA20160449M3.2" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">3.2</span>
    <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-e2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> where impulse response model parameters, 
   <span class="italic">q
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">d
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span>, represent parameters of the climate response to radiative forcing. Using an impulse response model to estimate Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>anthro</sub>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>) and Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>nat</sub>(
   <span class="italic">t</span>), as opposed to using simulations from the CMIP5 archive, allows the latest revisions in estimates of historical ERF components, and a broader range of possible fractional contributions of CO
   <sub>2</sub> to net forcing than simulated in the CMIP5 ensemble, to be used when making inferences about TCRE over the historical period. We account for uncertainty in the historical ERF using a distribution of possible ERF histories (see §2a) and parametric uncertainty using a sampling of 
   <span class="italic">q
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">d
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span> consistent with distributions for the realized warming fraction (the ratio of transient climate response—TCR—to equilibrium climate sensitivity [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C40">40</a>]) and the short thermal response timescale of the climate system from Millar 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C41">41</a>], approximating the distributions of these variables across CMIP5 general circulation models. Observational uncertainty is sampled using the HadCRUT4-CW ensemble and uncertainty associated with natural climate variability is sampled by adding realizations of control climate variability from CMIP5 to the observed time-series. Total uncertainty (5–95%) in attributed human-induced warming is shown by the purple shading in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F2" href="#RSTA20160449F2">figure 2</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>. Haustein 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C27">27</a>] showed that the dominant sources of uncertainty in this calculation are ERF and internal variability uncertainties. As control variability is added using global surface air-temperature fields, this may somewhat over-estimate the contribution of internal variability uncertainty in the blended air-temperature/sea-surface temperature product. 
   <div id="RSTA20160449F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Comparison of ESM-simulated warming (blended) and diagnosed cumulative CO
      <sub>2</sub> emissions (thin pastel coloured lines) with unsmoothed in-filled observations (HadCRUT4-CW/GCP—thick red) and its attributed human-induced component (black—with 5–95% shading shown in purple in (
      <span class="italic">a</span>)). (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Warming relative to the average of 1861–1880, (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) diagnosed cumulative CO
      <sub>2</sub> emissions since 1870 (GCP observations are shown in red with grey shading 5–95%), (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) the joint evolution of warming and cumulative CO
      <sub>2</sub> emissions, and in (
      <span class="italic">d</span>) the all-forcing effective TCRE calculated with a moving average. The black line in (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) and (
      <span class="italic">d</span>) uses the attributed human-induced warming time-series from (
      <span class="italic">a</span>). ESM temperature time-series are ‘blended’ air/sea warming smoothed using a 10 year centred running mean in all cases. Beige shading in (
      <span class="italic">d</span>) indicates the total uncertainty from the calculation of human-induced warming and historical emissions. The purple crosses in (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) mark the all-time likely below carbon budget from the IPCC-AR5 Synthesis Report (IPCC SYN). (Online version in colour.) 
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effective TCRE calculated using human-induced warming (black in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>) displays substantially less variation over time than estimates from pure observed warming (grey bars) as the changing contributions of both temporary natural forcing (such as volcanic eruptions) and natural climate variability have been regressed out. This indicates that natural climate variability typically has a larger impact on estimates of effective TCRE from observations than changing fractional contributions to forced warming associated with evolving historical non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> forcing. Total uncertainty in the attributed effective TCRE is larger (beige bars in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>) than that associated with purely observational uncertainty, as decadal mean uncertainty is much larger in human-attributable warming than observed warming. Over the 2007–2016 period, the total uncertainty on the attributed effective TCRE displays a 5–95% range of 1.43–2.37°C/TtC and a best-estimate of 1.84°C/TtC.
  </p>
  <sec id="s3a1" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(i)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effective TCRE in ESMs</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As CMIP5 ESM simulations were driven by observed atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration pathways, compatible anthropogenic emissions can be diagnosed from the simulated land and ocean carbon sinks compatible with the prescribed increase in atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C33">33</a>]. Therefore, CMIP5 historical simulations can be explicitly validated against the observational record in terms of their joint simulation of warming and anthropogenic cumulative CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions, as both of these variables are outputs of the ESM simulations.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparisons between the observed record and ESMs for temperature and diagnosed cumulative CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions are shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F2" href="#RSTA20160449F2">figure 2</a>
    <span class="italic">a</span>,
    <span class="italic">b</span>. In 2016, the ensemble mean of the smoothed global mean blended air/sea warming for the ESMs (solid thin coloured lines) was 0.10°C (0.41 to −0.27°C ensemble range) warmer than the estimated human-induced warming from global (HadCRUT4-CW) observations (solid black line approximately 1°C in 2016). Historical cumulative CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions (to the end of 2016) are typically underdiagnosed relative to the GCP observations in many of the ESMs (by 27 GtC for the multi-model mean, 121 to −65.7 GtC ensemble range), with nine out of 15 ESMs diagnosing historical cumulative emissions to be less than best-estimate observed emissions between 1870 and 2016. As many ESMs typically underestimate land or ocean carbon sinks, and hence compatible annual anthropogenic CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions needed to close the carbon budget [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C6">6</a>,
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C33">33</a>,
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C42">42</a>,
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C43">43</a>], such underestimates in historical cumulative emissions are expected. This underestimate of cumulative emissions in ESMs relative to the best-estimate observed value is persistent over the last half century and as such cannot be attributed to an artefact of the so-called ‘hiatus’ in warming which could have acted to temporarily reduce the observed annual airborne fraction, therefore allowing models to meet a similar concentration evolution with lower diagnosed emissions.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combining the ESM simulations of warming and diagnosed cumulative emissions typically produces estimates of the effective TCRE greater than the best-estimate from the historical period (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F2" href="#RSTA20160449F2">figure 2</a>
    <span class="italic">c</span>,
    <span class="italic">d</span>). Subsequent to substantial variability in the effective TCRE prior to 1980, in both ESMs and observations the effective TCRE has been approximately constant since 2000. ESMs show a higher value than estimated from the observational best-estimate in 12 out of 15 ESMs by 2016 (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
    <span class="italic">d</span>). Despite the substantial variation between different observationally based estimates of the effective TCRE, and substantial uncertainty in human-induced warming, the mean ESM effective TCRE (2016) is 0.27°C/TtC higher than the estimate based on attributable human-induced warming, and four out of 15 ESMs have effective TCREs greater than the observational 95th percentile for 2016 (approx. 2.45°C/TtC; 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F2" href="#RSTA20160449F2">figure 2</a>
    <span class="italic">d</span>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Remaining carbon budgets estimates from ESMs are determined by the coevolution of simulated warming and diagnosed CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions and not by either in isolation. All but three of the 15 ESMs considered here have a greater warming than observational best-estimate human-induced warming when diagnosed cumulative emissions reach 565 GtC in both the blended and global surface air-temperature ESM time-series, with some models displaying warming already in excess of 1.5°C for 565 GtC emissions (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F3" href="#RSTA20160449F3">figure 3</a>
    <span class="italic">a</span>) for both types of model output. Similarly, both blended and global surface air-temperature ESM time-series can have substantially lower diagnosed cumulative emissions than the observed best-estimate when warming reaches the 2016 best-estimate human-induced value of approximately 1.0°C (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F3" href="#RSTA20160449F3">figure 3</a>
    <span class="italic">b</span>). 
    <div id="RSTA20160449F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>ESM estimates of warming after 565 GtC of diagnosed cumulative CO
       <sub>2</sub> emissions (
       <span class="italic">a</span>) and diagnosed cumulative CO
       <sub>2</sub> emissions after 1.0°C of simulated warming (
       <span class="italic">b</span>). Filled red bars show results calculated with full global coverage surface air-temperature warming and dashed blue outlines show blended ESM output. Dotted-dashed red and blue vertical lines indicate ESM ensemble means (for global and global blended outputs) and dotted-dashed black vertical lines indicate the observations, the human-attributable component of observed warming from HadCRUT4-CW in (
       <span class="italic">a</span>) and the GCP cumulative emissions in (
       <span class="italic">b</span>). (Online version in colour.) 
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating the CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE from observations requires an estimate of the fraction of human-induced warming that is attributed to CO
   <sub>2</sub>. While CO
   <sub>2</sub> radiative forcing is relatively well constrained, total anthropogenic forcing remains uncertain largely due the range of possible aerosol ERF once interactions with clouds are accounted for [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C26">26</a>,
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C44">44</a>,
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C45">45</a>]. For a given member of the ERF uncertainty sampling (subscript 
   <span class="italic">i</span>), linear regression (equation (3.1)) can be used to decompose attributed human-induced warming, 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i2.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> (
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i3.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>), into the forced warming associated with each component of the anthropogenic radiative forcing, 
   <div id="RSTA20160449M3.3" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">3.3</span>
    <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-e3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> where responses to the sampled individual components of the forcing (e.g. 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i4.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>) are computed using equation (3.2). Convolving independent sampling of ERF uncertainty and other uncertainties, as described in §3a, provides a distribution for 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i5.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> that can be combined with uncertainty in historical cumulative CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions to make inferences about the CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE from observations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large uncertainty in aerosol ERF propagates into a wide range of possible contributions of CO
   <sub>2</sub> to observed warming today. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">Figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">c</span> shows 300 members of the joint distribution of CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and cumulative emissions (beige lines) with the best-estimate marked with the black line. The estimated CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming to-date (2016) ranges from as little as 0.51°C (5th percentile) to as much as 1.43°C (95th percentile) respectively, representing extremal cases in which non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> greenhouse gas forcing strongly dominates a weakly negative aerosol forcing (5th percentile) and when net non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> forcing is itself negative due to a strong negative aerosol forcing, partly masking the CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming in the present-day climate (95th percentile). As long-lived forcing on the climate system is largely associated with elevated CO
   <sub>2</sub> and N
   <sub>2</sub>O concentrations (N
   <sub>2</sub>O currently contributes only approx. 9% of the forcing associated with CO
   <sub>2</sub> in the best-estimate case), our results indicate that there is a low, but non-zero, chance that current warming from long-lived GHGs already exceeds 1.5°C based on current-forcing uncertainties. This indicates that it still remains relatively unlikely that we are yet geo-physically locked-in to a long-lived component of warming in excess of the high ambition goal of the Paris Agreement and therefore a need to use carbon removal or solar geoengineering techniques to limit long-term warming beneath this threshold.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The best-estimate of CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming in 2016 is 0.74°C, corresponding to the best-estimate radiative forcing components, in which CO
   <sub>2</sub> forcing represents 74% of the net forcing in 2016. Approximately linear relationships between cumulative emissions and attributed CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming are seen across the uncertainty range from the attribution analysis (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">c</span>), leading to approximately period-invariant best-estimates and uncertainty intervals on the implied CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE estimates (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">d</span>). The best-estimate CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE estimate over the most recent decade (2007–2016) is 1.31°C/TtC and is approximately invariant over the four previous decades considered here. The 5–95% range of the TCRE over the most recent decade is 0.88–2.60°C/TtC, extending beyond the upper end of the 0.8–2.5°C/TtC 
   <span class="italic">likely</span> range of TCRE assessed by AR5. The overall similarity between the two ranges might be expected due to the inclusion of observational constraints in the expert judgement underlying the AR5 assessment. While observational attribution supports a best-estimate CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE in the bottom half of the AR5 likely range, the uncertainties associated with historical forcing mean that uncertainties in the observationally estimated CO
   <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE remain large, and a high TCRE cannot be conclusively ruled out by current observations.
  </p>
  <sec id="s3b1" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(i)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM-simulated historical CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using a combination of historical simulations and idealized 1%/yr CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration increase experiments, it is possible to partition simulated historical warming in ESMs into CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced components. From a time-series of simulated warming under the 1%/yr experiments for a given ESM, it is possible to estimate the CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming for a given level of cumulative CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions. Comparisons with the estimate of the simulated warming in the historical simulations for the same level of cumulative emissions allows a quantification of the warming induced by CO
    <sub>2</sub> alone versus the warming from non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> anthropogenic and natural forcing components.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This method assumes a linear separability between CO
    <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> warming, and a perfect scenario independence of the relationship between cumulative CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions and CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming. While evidence exists for dependence of carbon-cycle feedbacks on the total warming within the climate system [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C46">46</a>,
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C47">47</a>], as well as some scenario dependence of the response to cumulative emissions [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C48">48</a>], to a first order these remain good assumptions to partition ESM-simulated historical warming into CO
    <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> contributions. An additional implicit assumption is that carbon-cycle feedbacks (which give rise to the relationship between warming and cumulative emissions in these experiments) estimated from the 1%/yr simulation are a good proxy for the carbon-cycle feedbacks over the historical period. For example, as the 1%/yr simulations have fixed preindustrial land-use forcing, unlike the historical simulation, some differences might be expected in the land carbon feedbacks between the two experiments for a single climate model. We provide a proxy test of the similarity between ESM carbon-cycle feedbacks in the two experiments using a simple climate carbon-cycle model in the electronic supplementary material. Based on this technique, we conclude that the difference in carbon-cycle feedbacks between the two experiments is unlikely to have a large effect on the diagnosed cumulative emissions over the historical integration, but could be expected to have a substantial effect under high future emission scenarios such as RCP8.5.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diagnosed cumulative emissions for a given atmospheric concentration evolution will also somewhat depend on the profile of other forcing agents, due to both non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> contributions to warming affecting natural carbon sinks and (in the case of aerosols) changes to the biogeochemical carbon-cycle feedback by direct impact on diffuse surface radiation. MacDougall 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C49">49</a>] showed that in the UVic intermediate complexity model, the inclusion of non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> radiative forcing only caused a small reduction in diagnosed cumulative CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions over the historical period. Similarly, the study of MacDougall &amp; Knutti [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C50">50</a>] indicates only a fractionally small increase in long-lived warming associated with the effect of present-day methane emission rates on the efficacy of carbon sinks. Therefore, while the effects of both non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> forcing on carbon sinks, and possible difference between carbon-cycle feedbacks in the 1%/yr and historical integrations, add uncertainty to estimates of ESM CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming, the method used here can serve as a useful approximation over the historical period.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM-derived CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced air-temperature warming evolves steadily over time (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
    <span class="italic">a</span>) and reaches a mean value of 0.93°C in 2016 (0.59–1.40°C 5–95% range), 0.13°C higher than the best-estimate observed surface air-temperature warming (which we calculate by ‘de-blending’ the observational product using the CMIP5 mean ratio between global air-temperature and blended air/ocean warming from Richardson 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
    <a rid="RSTA20160449C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C51">51</a>]). The ESM simulations span a range of CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming consistent with uncertainties in the estimated attributable CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming from observations. This similarity would be expected due to a similar range of TCRE uncertainty in attributed CO
    <sub>2</sub> warming and the ESM 1%/yr experiments. 
    <div id="RSTA20160449F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Figure 4.</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Historical CO
       <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
       <sub>2</sub>-induced global surface air-temperature warming. ESMs (global mean air-temperature warming) are shown with thin coloured lines and estimated values from the observational attribution with a thick brown line (best-estimate—brown shading indicates 5–95% uncertainty). The observational estimate has been ‘de-blended’ (to estimate observed global mean surface air-temperature warming compatible with the blended air/ocean temperature observational series) to allow a like-for-like comparison with global mean air-temperature warming in the 1%/yr simulation from the ESMs. (
       <span class="italic">a</span>) Estimated CO
       <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and (
       <span class="italic">b</span>) estimated non-CO
       <sub>2</sub> anthropogenic and naturally forced warming. (
       <span class="italic">c</span>) The fraction of total warming due to non-CO
       <sub>2</sub> drivers for the post-2000 period. (Online version in colour.) 
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Non-CO
    <sub>2</sub>-simulated warming in the ESMs (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
    <span class="italic">b</span>) has an ensemble mean value approximately equal to the observationally based best-estimate, while three out of 11 ESMs for which CO
    <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> contributions to warming are calculable have non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> warming greater than the 95th percentile of the attribution-estimated contribution in 2016, with some ESMs displaying a sharp increase in non-CO
    <sub>2</sub> warming around 2005 (the start of the RCP scenarios). Non-CO
    <sub>2</sub>-induced warming as a fraction of total warming has remained relatively stable in both ESMs and as estimated from observations since 2000 (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
    <span class="italic">c</span>), with a recent uptick observed in the observational best-estimate largely associated with an increase in methane radiative forcing over the last decade.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
