<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating the CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE from observations requires an estimate of the fraction of human-induced warming that is attributed to CO
  <sub>2</sub>. While CO
  <sub>2</sub> radiative forcing is relatively well constrained, total anthropogenic forcing remains uncertain largely due the range of possible aerosol ERF once interactions with clouds are accounted for [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C26">26</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C44">44</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C45">45</a>]. For a given member of the ERF uncertainty sampling (subscript 
  <span class="italic">i</span>), linear regression (equation (3.1)) can be used to decompose attributed human-induced warming, 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i2.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i3.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>), into the forced warming associated with each component of the anthropogenic radiative forcing, 
  <div id="RSTA20160449M3.3" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">3.3</span>
   <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-e3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> where responses to the sampled individual components of the forcing (e.g. 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i4.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>) are computed using equation (3.2). Convolving independent sampling of ERF uncertainty and other uncertainties, as described in §3a, provides a distribution for 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="rsta20160449-i5.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> that can be combined with uncertainty in historical cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions to make inferences about the CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE from observations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large uncertainty in aerosol ERF propagates into a wide range of possible contributions of CO
  <sub>2</sub> to observed warming today. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">Figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">c</span> shows 300 members of the joint distribution of CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and cumulative emissions (beige lines) with the best-estimate marked with the black line. The estimated CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming to-date (2016) ranges from as little as 0.51°C (5th percentile) to as much as 1.43°C (95th percentile) respectively, representing extremal cases in which non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> greenhouse gas forcing strongly dominates a weakly negative aerosol forcing (5th percentile) and when net non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing is itself negative due to a strong negative aerosol forcing, partly masking the CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming in the present-day climate (95th percentile). As long-lived forcing on the climate system is largely associated with elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> and N
  <sub>2</sub>O concentrations (N
  <sub>2</sub>O currently contributes only approx. 9% of the forcing associated with CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the best-estimate case), our results indicate that there is a low, but non-zero, chance that current warming from long-lived GHGs already exceeds 1.5°C based on current-forcing uncertainties. This indicates that it still remains relatively unlikely that we are yet geo-physically locked-in to a long-lived component of warming in excess of the high ambition goal of the Paris Agreement and therefore a need to use carbon removal or solar geoengineering techniques to limit long-term warming beneath this threshold.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The best-estimate of CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming in 2016 is 0.74°C, corresponding to the best-estimate radiative forcing components, in which CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing represents 74% of the net forcing in 2016. Approximately linear relationships between cumulative emissions and attributed CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming are seen across the uncertainty range from the attribution analysis (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">c</span>), leading to approximately period-invariant best-estimates and uncertainty intervals on the implied CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE estimates (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F1" href="#RSTA20160449F1">figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">d</span>). The best-estimate CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE estimate over the most recent decade (2007–2016) is 1.31°C/TtC and is approximately invariant over the four previous decades considered here. The 5–95% range of the TCRE over the most recent decade is 0.88–2.60°C/TtC, extending beyond the upper end of the 0.8–2.5°C/TtC 
  <span class="italic">likely</span> range of TCRE assessed by AR5. The overall similarity between the two ranges might be expected due to the inclusion of observational constraints in the expert judgement underlying the AR5 assessment. While observational attribution supports a best-estimate CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE in the bottom half of the AR5 likely range, the uncertainties associated with historical forcing mean that uncertainties in the observationally estimated CO
  <sub>2</sub>-only TCRE remain large, and a high TCRE cannot be conclusively ruled out by current observations.
 </p>
 <sec id="s3b1" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(i)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM-simulated historical CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using a combination of historical simulations and idealized 1%/yr CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration increase experiments, it is possible to partition simulated historical warming in ESMs into CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced components. From a time-series of simulated warming under the 1%/yr experiments for a given ESM, it is possible to estimate the CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming for a given level of cumulative CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions. Comparisons with the estimate of the simulated warming in the historical simulations for the same level of cumulative emissions allows a quantification of the warming induced by CO
   <sub>2</sub> alone versus the warming from non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> anthropogenic and natural forcing components.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This method assumes a linear separability between CO
   <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> warming, and a perfect scenario independence of the relationship between cumulative CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions and CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming. While evidence exists for dependence of carbon-cycle feedbacks on the total warming within the climate system [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C46">46</a>,
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C47">47</a>], as well as some scenario dependence of the response to cumulative emissions [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C48">48</a>], to a first order these remain good assumptions to partition ESM-simulated historical warming into CO
   <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> contributions. An additional implicit assumption is that carbon-cycle feedbacks (which give rise to the relationship between warming and cumulative emissions in these experiments) estimated from the 1%/yr simulation are a good proxy for the carbon-cycle feedbacks over the historical period. For example, as the 1%/yr simulations have fixed preindustrial land-use forcing, unlike the historical simulation, some differences might be expected in the land carbon feedbacks between the two experiments for a single climate model. We provide a proxy test of the similarity between ESM carbon-cycle feedbacks in the two experiments using a simple climate carbon-cycle model in the electronic supplementary material. Based on this technique, we conclude that the difference in carbon-cycle feedbacks between the two experiments is unlikely to have a large effect on the diagnosed cumulative emissions over the historical integration, but could be expected to have a substantial effect under high future emission scenarios such as RCP8.5.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diagnosed cumulative emissions for a given atmospheric concentration evolution will also somewhat depend on the profile of other forcing agents, due to both non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> contributions to warming affecting natural carbon sinks and (in the case of aerosols) changes to the biogeochemical carbon-cycle feedback by direct impact on diffuse surface radiation. MacDougall 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C49">49</a>] showed that in the UVic intermediate complexity model, the inclusion of non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> radiative forcing only caused a small reduction in diagnosed cumulative CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions over the historical period. Similarly, the study of MacDougall &amp; Knutti [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C50">50</a>] indicates only a fractionally small increase in long-lived warming associated with the effect of present-day methane emission rates on the efficacy of carbon sinks. Therefore, while the effects of both non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> forcing on carbon sinks, and possible difference between carbon-cycle feedbacks in the 1%/yr and historical integrations, add uncertainty to estimates of ESM CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming, the method used here can serve as a useful approximation over the historical period.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM-derived CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced air-temperature warming evolves steadily over time (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>) and reaches a mean value of 0.93°C in 2016 (0.59–1.40°C 5–95% range), 0.13°C higher than the best-estimate observed surface air-temperature warming (which we calculate by ‘de-blending’ the observational product using the CMIP5 mean ratio between global air-temperature and blended air/ocean warming from Richardson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
   <a rid="RSTA20160449C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C51">51</a>]). The ESM simulations span a range of CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming consistent with uncertainties in the estimated attributable CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming from observations. This similarity would be expected due to a similar range of TCRE uncertainty in attributed CO
   <sub>2</sub> warming and the ESM 1%/yr experiments. 
   <div id="RSTA20160449F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 4.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Historical CO
      <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
      <sub>2</sub>-induced global surface air-temperature warming. ESMs (global mean air-temperature warming) are shown with thin coloured lines and estimated values from the observational attribution with a thick brown line (best-estimate—brown shading indicates 5–95% uncertainty). The observational estimate has been ‘de-blended’ (to estimate observed global mean surface air-temperature warming compatible with the blended air/ocean temperature observational series) to allow a like-for-like comparison with global mean air-temperature warming in the 1%/yr simulation from the ESMs. (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Estimated CO
      <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) estimated non-CO
      <sub>2</sub> anthropogenic and naturally forced warming. (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) The fraction of total warming due to non-CO
      <sub>2</sub> drivers for the post-2000 period. (Online version in colour.) 
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Non-CO
   <sub>2</sub>-simulated warming in the ESMs (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>) has an ensemble mean value approximately equal to the observationally based best-estimate, while three out of 11 ESMs for which CO
   <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> contributions to warming are calculable have non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> warming greater than the 95th percentile of the attribution-estimated contribution in 2016, with some ESMs displaying a sharp increase in non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> warming around 2005 (the start of the RCP scenarios). Non-CO
   <sub>2</sub>-induced warming as a fraction of total warming has remained relatively stable in both ESMs and as estimated from observations since 2000 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
   <span class="italic">c</span>), with a recent uptick observed in the observational best-estimate largely associated with an increase in methane radiative forcing over the last decade.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
