<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(i)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM-simulated historical CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using a combination of historical simulations and idealized 1%/yr CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration increase experiments, it is possible to partition simulated historical warming in ESMs into CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced components. From a time-series of simulated warming under the 1%/yr experiments for a given ESM, it is possible to estimate the CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming for a given level of cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions. Comparisons with the estimate of the simulated warming in the historical simulations for the same level of cumulative emissions allows a quantification of the warming induced by CO
  <sub>2</sub> alone versus the warming from non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> anthropogenic and natural forcing components.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This method assumes a linear separability between CO
  <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming, and a perfect scenario independence of the relationship between cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions and CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming. While evidence exists for dependence of carbon-cycle feedbacks on the total warming within the climate system [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C46">46</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C47">47</a>], as well as some scenario dependence of the response to cumulative emissions [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C48">48</a>], to a first order these remain good assumptions to partition ESM-simulated historical warming into CO
  <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> contributions. An additional implicit assumption is that carbon-cycle feedbacks (which give rise to the relationship between warming and cumulative emissions in these experiments) estimated from the 1%/yr simulation are a good proxy for the carbon-cycle feedbacks over the historical period. For example, as the 1%/yr simulations have fixed preindustrial land-use forcing, unlike the historical simulation, some differences might be expected in the land carbon feedbacks between the two experiments for a single climate model. We provide a proxy test of the similarity between ESM carbon-cycle feedbacks in the two experiments using a simple climate carbon-cycle model in the electronic supplementary material. Based on this technique, we conclude that the difference in carbon-cycle feedbacks between the two experiments is unlikely to have a large effect on the diagnosed cumulative emissions over the historical integration, but could be expected to have a substantial effect under high future emission scenarios such as RCP8.5.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diagnosed cumulative emissions for a given atmospheric concentration evolution will also somewhat depend on the profile of other forcing agents, due to both non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> contributions to warming affecting natural carbon sinks and (in the case of aerosols) changes to the biogeochemical carbon-cycle feedback by direct impact on diffuse surface radiation. MacDougall 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C49">49</a>] showed that in the UVic intermediate complexity model, the inclusion of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> radiative forcing only caused a small reduction in diagnosed cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions over the historical period. Similarly, the study of MacDougall &amp; Knutti [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C50">50</a>] indicates only a fractionally small increase in long-lived warming associated with the effect of present-day methane emission rates on the efficacy of carbon sinks. Therefore, while the effects of both non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing on carbon sinks, and possible difference between carbon-cycle feedbacks in the 1%/yr and historical integrations, add uncertainty to estimates of ESM CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming, the method used here can serve as a useful approximation over the historical period.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM-derived CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced air-temperature warming evolves steadily over time (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>) and reaches a mean value of 0.93°C in 2016 (0.59–1.40°C 5–95% range), 0.13°C higher than the best-estimate observed surface air-temperature warming (which we calculate by ‘de-blending’ the observational product using the CMIP5 mean ratio between global air-temperature and blended air/ocean warming from Richardson 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C51">51</a>]). The ESM simulations span a range of CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming consistent with uncertainties in the estimated attributable CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming from observations. This similarity would be expected due to a similar range of TCRE uncertainty in attributed CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming and the ESM 1%/yr experiments. 
  <div id="RSTA20160449F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Historical CO
     <sub>2</sub>-induced and non-CO
     <sub>2</sub>-induced global surface air-temperature warming. ESMs (global mean air-temperature warming) are shown with thin coloured lines and estimated values from the observational attribution with a thick brown line (best-estimate—brown shading indicates 5–95% uncertainty). The observational estimate has been ‘de-blended’ (to estimate observed global mean surface air-temperature warming compatible with the blended air/ocean temperature observational series) to allow a like-for-like comparison with global mean air-temperature warming in the 1%/yr simulation from the ESMs. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) Estimated CO
     <sub>2</sub>-induced warming and (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) estimated non-CO
     <sub>2</sub> anthropogenic and naturally forced warming. (
     <span class="italic">c</span>) The fraction of total warming due to non-CO
     <sub>2</sub> drivers for the post-2000 period. (Online version in colour.) 
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsta20160449-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Non-CO
  <sub>2</sub>-simulated warming in the ESMs (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>) has an ensemble mean value approximately equal to the observationally based best-estimate, while three out of 11 ESMs for which CO
  <sub>2</sub> and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> contributions to warming are calculable have non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming greater than the 95th percentile of the attribution-estimated contribution in 2016, with some ESMs displaying a sharp increase in non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> warming around 2005 (the start of the RCP scenarios). Non-CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced warming as a fraction of total warming has remained relatively stable in both ESMs and as estimated from observations since 2000 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20160449F4" href="#RSTA20160449F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">c</span>), with a recent uptick observed in the observational best-estimate largely associated with an increase in methane radiative forcing over the last decade.
 </p>
</sec>
