<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESM simulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ESM data used in this paper are taken from experiments conducted under the 5th Coupled Model Intercomparison Project—CMIP5 [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C31">31</a>]. We use results from the historical simulation as well as from the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) scenarios [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C32">32</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C33">33</a>] and the idealized 1%/yr atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration increase experiment [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C34">34</a>]. The list of ESMs used in this analysis is as follows: CESM1-BGC, CanESM2, GFDL-ESM2G, GFDL-ESM2M, HadGEM2-CC, HadGEM2-ES, IPSL-CM5A-LR, IPSL-CM5A-MR, IPSL-CM5B-LR, MIROC-ESM-CHEM, MIROC-EMS, MPI-ESM-LR, NorESM1-ME, bcc-csm1–1 and inmcm4. Models for which data are not available for the 1%/yr experiment are omitted from analysis that involves the use of those experiments (§3b(i)). In comparing the ESMs against the observational record, we consider the effect of observational processing on the modelled temperature anomalies to allow a like-for-like comparison with observational products. ‘Blended’ time-series of globally complete simulated warming are taken from [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C22">22</a>], which processed model output using a blend of surface air-temperatures (over land) and sea-surface temperatures (over ocean), similar to as in observational products. This enables a direct ‘like-for-like’ comparison between globally complete model output and observational products that are statistically in-filled to address observational coverage gaps in order to estimate a global mean value. We use the RCP8.5 scenario [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C35">35</a>] when comparing ESMs to observations over the post-2005 period.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diagnosed ESM CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions from Jones 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C33">33</a>] (historical and RCP experiments) and Gillett 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C2">2</a>] (1%/yr experiment) are used throughout. Land-use emissions have been added, where required, identically to as in [
  <a rid="RSTA20160449C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160449C36">36</a>]. Time-series of both warming and cumulative emissions for all RCP ESM simulations are smoothed with a 10 year centred moving average to remove modes of unforced natural variability and help isolate the externally forced signal (1%/yr ESM simulations are smoothed with a 15 year running mean).
 </p>
</sec>
