<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We developed species distribution models using the popular machine-learning algorithm for ecological modeling, Maxent [
 <xref rid="B26-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Maxent estimates a species’ probability distribution that has maximum entropy (closest to uniform), subject to a set of constraints based on the sampling of presence-only data [
 <xref rid="B45-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Because of the difficulty and impracticality of obtaining accurate absence data, presence-only data are most often used in species distribution modeling. In order to offset the lack of absence data, Maxent uses a background sample to compare the distribution of presence data along environmental gradients with the distribution of background points randomly drawn from the study area [
 <xref rid="B46-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Locality data and the randomly sampled background points are combined with climatic data to predict the probability of the species’ occurrence within each raster grid cell. We used environmental climate data from WorldClim [
 <xref rid="B49-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] at 30 arc-second resolution or approximately 1 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> grid cells. Bioclimate variables and elevation layers were each clipped to the extent of North America using ESRI (Environmental Systems Research Institute) ArcMap 10.0, and data extracted to 
 <italic class="italic">S. diana</italic> sample localities. Additionally, we collected the same types of locality data for three other species of North American butterflies (
 <italic class="italic">Speyeria cybele</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Speyeria idalia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Battus philenor</italic>), which served as 5628 random background points for our models. We utilized these background data to minimize spatial bias in our modeling, as data represented by similar butterfly species can be used as pseudo-absence data with the same collection bias as our occurrence data, improving the accuracy of the model [
 <xref rid="B50-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. 
</p>
