<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One concern when modeling species distributions is whether the occurrence records are spatially biased with respect to site accessibility (e.g., towns, roads, trails) [
 <xref rid="B63-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. To address this concern, we applied a spatial filter to remove all sampling points that were within 5 km of each other using ESRI ArcMap 10.0. The spatial filter resulted in 254 unique presence points for 
 <italic class="italic">S. diana</italic> that were used in the final model. We first modeled the distribution of these 254 occurrences in present-day climate, and then projected the fitted species distribution under two future climate scenarios for the period 2040–2069 (hereafter referred to as 2050). Future climate scenarios were taken from two global circulation models (GCMs) obtained from 
 <uri xlink:href="www.worldclim.org" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</uri>; the community climate system model (CCSM) [
 <xref rid="B64-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>] and the model for interdisciplinary research on climate (MIROC) [
 <xref rid="B65-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. These GCMs differ in the reconstruction of several climatic variables and are well known to produce different outcomes for butterfly species [
 <xref rid="B67-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. For example, in hind-casting Mediterranean butterflies, the CCSM model projects narrower distributions at the last glacial maximum than does MIROC [
 <xref rid="B65-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. For each of these two GCMs, we considered two different representative concentration pathways (RCPs) [
 <xref rid="B69-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>], which are cumulative measures of human emissions of greenhouse gases from all sources expressed in Watts per square meter. These pathways were developed for the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [
 <xref rid="B67-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] and correspond to a total anthropogenic radiative forcing of RCP = 4.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (low) and RCP = 8.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (high) [
 <xref rid="B72-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-insects-09-00094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>].
</p>
