<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Climate change has profoundly impacted the distributions of species across the globe
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Rising temperatures of the last few decades have shifted the latitudinal and altitudinal ranges of many species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. This is particularly concerning for alpine species, for which there may not be sufficient suitable alpine habitats at higher altitudes to facilitate their migration. This phenomenon has been termed the “nowhere to go” hypothesis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. Chen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup> conducted a meta-analysis of over 1,000 species and found that the median rate of increased altitudinal range shifting was 11 meters per decade, while latitudinal range shifts showed a median rate of 16.9 kilometers poleward per decade (animals only). Lenoir 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup> investigated 171 plant species in European montane regions, and found that mean elevation of ranges had moved upward by 29 meters per decade, coincident with rapidly rising temperatures occurring after 1986. These altitudinal shifts were faster for species adapted to montane regions than for more broadly-distributed species and for herbaceous plants compared to woody plants
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. These studies collectively suggest that, under future climate warming scenarios, montane species, especially herbaceous plants, may face the aforementioned “nowhere to go” predicament. However, other researchers predict that global climate warming may drive snowlines upward, exposing new areas of suitable habitat that could facilitate alpine species’ upward migration; thus the notion of “nowhere to go” may be an oversimplification of the future of alpine taxa
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>. For example, Holzinger 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> reported that species richness of vascular plants in montane communities increased by 11% per decade under climatic warming. Clearly more research is required to fully explore the effects of global warming on alpine plants.
</p>
