<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We obtained a list of IPS from the IUCN/SSC Invasive Species Specialist Group (ISSG) including a comprehensive dataset of IPS (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.issg.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.issg.org/</uri>) and occurrence data, especially geographic coordinates from the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF; 
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.gbif.org</uri>; accessed in January 2015). The 387 selected IPS share characteristics including the significant impacts of the IPS on the ecoregion, general functional traits indicating representative issues, and invasion at large scales (e.g. country level) based on the ISSG database (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.issg.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.issg.org/</uri>). In total, approximately five million occurrence records of these 387 IPS were collected from GBIF. We used Google Maps to remove occurrence records with the spatial sampling bias according to the following aspects: (1) duplicated records within the area of 10.0-arc-minute spatial resolution; (2) records with both longitude and latitude = 0°; (3) records with equal geographic coordinates (i.e. longitude = latitude); and (4) the records with incorrect species names (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.google.com/maps/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.google.com/maps/</uri>; 
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.issg.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.issg.org/</uri>; 
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Beck et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Aiello-Lammens et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">García-Roselló et al., 2015</xref>). We used 387 species with over 100 records in 10.0 arc-minute pixel cells (16 km at the equator; 
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Araújo et al., 2011</xref>) as the input for the climatic suitability model, and 741,114 occurrence records with geographic coordinates were obtained for 387 IPS. We considered the entire globe as the extent of the input data (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1">Table S1</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr">Wisz et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Merow, Smith &amp; Silander, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-99" ref-type="bibr">Zhang &amp; Zhang, 2014</xref>). We classified the 387 species into nine clusters based on growth forms, such as palm, succulent, alga, fern, aquatic plant, vine, shrub, tree, and herb, according to ISSG (
 <xref rid="ref-98" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.issg.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.issg.org/</uri>).
</p>
