<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Diarrheal case reports were obtained for the study from 10 health facilities (9 government health clinics and 1 primary hospital) through 2 passive surveillance systems operated under the Botswana Ministry of Health (MoH). Under-5 diarrhea case data were acquired from the Integrated Disease Surveillance and Response (IDSR) program (January 2007–June 2017), which collates weekly numbers of under-5 diarrhea cases presenting to district health facilities (
 <xref rid="pmed.1002688.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Total monthly outpatient cases of diarrhea (all ages) were also obtained from the MoH for January 1998–June 2017. These case reports were extracted from the same 10 health facilities, stratified by diarrhea type, age (&lt;1, 1–4, 5+ years), and sex of the patient. Outpatient data include the IDSR weekly data (a subset) as all patients must access the health system through outpatient services. These data are useful as they provide information on all patients by age over and above those less than 5 years. Outpatient data were included to provide a more complete demographic and clinical picture of diarrheal disease in the district. A diarrhea case was defined as the occurrence of at least 3 loose stools in a 24-hour period within the 4 days preceding the health facility visit. The diarrhea type was characterized by the attending physician or nurse as diarrhea with no dehydration, diarrhea with some dehydration, diarrhea with severe dehydration, or bloody diarrhea. Each selected study village had a clinic, with the largest town, Kasane, having 2 clinics and a primary hospital (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 3). For both the IDSR and outpatient datasets, data from the clinic in the village of Pandamatenga were excluded because residents in this village obtained water from boreholes and were expected to have variable exposure to surface water resources from other villages and towns in the district. Demographic statistical analyses were conducted using chi-squared tests for differences in proportions between groups.
</p>
