<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Changes in functional composition were quantified using indices that characterize the affinities of taxa within communities with temperature (CTI), drought (CDTI), light (CSTI) and disturbance (CDI). These community indices were calculated as follows. First, indices that quantify taxon-specific relationships with temperature, drought tolerance, shade tolerance and disturbance were assigned to the main 17 taxa present in the historical and modern datasets (Supplementary Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref>). The “taxon temperature index” (TTI) was calculated as the median annual temperature across the geographic range of a given taxon
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup> using interpolated annual surface temperature maps
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup> and continental scale distribution maps
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup>. To assess the robustness of our analyses to the decision to use median temperatures, we also calculated variants of TTI using the mean, 10th percentile, and 90th percentile of temperatures across the geographic range of a given taxon (see Supplementary Methods; Supplementary Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">4</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">5</xref>), with the latter two representing the cold and warm limits of distributions, respectively. Because none of these variants significantly changed the results (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">7</xref> and Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">6</xref>), we report only results for the median in the main text. Taxon drought tolerance and shade tolerance indices (TDTI and TSTI, respectively, Supplementary Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref>) were taken from a database of northern hemisphere trees and shrubs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>. These indices were derived from a meta-analysis of published literature ranking taxa according to their drought and shade tolerance on a common scale (from low tolerance; 1, to high tolerance; 5); they have been frequently used to quantify tree functional composition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>. The rankings obtained with our taxon climatic indices (TTI and TDTI) are also consistent with recent analyses of growth–climate relationships of restricted pools of taxa considered in our analysis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Concerning disturbance-related indices, since TSTI mostly accounts for adaptions to severe stand-replacing disturbances (e.g., land clearing, clearcutting), we also developed for this study a more comprehensive taxon disturbance index (TDI) that considers adaptations to both severe and partial disturbances (e.g., partial cutting). TDI was calculated with a point system involving 11 key traits (Supplementary Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>) taken from various sources including the PLANTS and TRY databases
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup> and references on tree species ecology
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>. Five traits were considered primarily as adaptations to stand-replacing disturbances: shade tolerance, growth rate, longevity, age at sexual maturity and capacity of vegetative reproduction. Six additional traits were considered to reflect adaptations to both stand-replacing and partial disturbance: fruiting frequency, seed abundance, effective seed dispersal, germination substrate requirement, seedling vigor, and response to release. For each trait, the range of values across species was first standardized to vary from 0 to 1 (giving them equal weight) and then summed across traits for a given taxon to obtain TDI values.
</p>
