<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The researcher used a qualitative research method for this study. Household survey was carried out using semi-structured and face-to-face interviews with participants conducted between April and July 2017. The questionnaire consists of methods of adaptation to climate change that farmers frequently used. The researcher allowed participants to compare the climate conditions of past 30 years with respect to the mean precipitation and temperature. If they had noted changes, they were asked actions in which they had taken to the perceived climate changes. The study used purposeful sampling technique, which is also known as purposive and selective sampling. This sampling technique enables the researcher to recruit participants who can provide in-depth and detailed information to ensure that research questions were answered. Palys (
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) argues that purposive sampling reaches a target sample quickly, economical and it gives better results. However, like any other sampling technique, purposive sampling has its own disadvantages. There is no equal chance for all the items of the universe being included in the sample (Palys 
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). The study was made up of three purposively selected villages, namely Kawondera, Gwamba and Tigere. The researcher focused on participants who were either aged 45 years and above. Age restriction was done to engage people who were capable of giving a comparative explanation of climate change between the periods when they were young. A total number of 40 households were interviewed and it comprised 23 women and 17 men. Two focus group discussions were conducted, which consisted of 11 people from different age groups. Focus group discussions were aimed specifically to gather and capture the information on the diversity of livelihood activities that reflect adaptive capacity. They were used to have an insight of people’s perceptions on climate change and how it affects food security and nutritional status of communities. Participant individual interviews were drawn from two staff at Agritex Department, one at Ministry of Environment, Water and Climate, three head men and one non-profit organisation (NGO) staff. Coding was used to structure the data. A phrase was assigned to capture whatever is salient. Qualitative data from interviews and focus group discussion were analysed using context analysis.
</p>
