<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At present, climate change and ambient air quality deterioration are serious issues of the atmospheric environment. In the past, they were separately studied by researchers and policymakers. As the research on the relationship between weather, climate, and air pollution deepened, the interaction between climate change and air quality has drawn more concern [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-01528">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-01528">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-01528">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-01528">4</a>]). Previous studies focused on the impacts of greenhouse gases and aerosols on climate system [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-01528">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-01528">6</a>], and there are relatively few investigations on the impacts of climate change on ambient air quality [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-01528">1</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-01528">4</a>]. The variations of meteorological factors caused by climate change can lead to changes in the air quality [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-01528">1</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-01528">4</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>]. Thus, to better protect our ambient air quality and to adapt ourselves to the changing climate, the impact of regional and global climate changes on ambient air should attract more attention.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ozone (O
  <sub>3</sub>), one of the major air pollutants in the air, is harmful to human health and ecological balance [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-01528">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-01528">10</a>]. In recent years, the regional O
  <sub>3</sub> pollution has aggravated. The photochemical reaction is regarded as the main cause of O
  <sub>3</sub> pollution, and severe pollution episodes usually occur on sunny days or under adverse weather conditions with plenty of precursors [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>,
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-01528">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-01528">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-01528">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-01528">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-16-01528">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-16-01528">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-01528">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-01528">18</a>]. Several meteorological factors can affect surface ozone. First, there is a negative correlation between the planetary boundary layer height and ozone concentration [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-01528">11</a>]. Second, elevated air temperatures can increase the chemical productions of O
  <sub>3</sub> and O
  <sub>3</sub> concentration [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-01528">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-01528">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-01528">14</a>,
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-16-01528">16</a>]. Third, the increased local wind speed can enhance the advection and diffusion processes of O
  <sub>3</sub> and thereby abate O
  <sub>3</sub> pollution [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-01528">11</a>]. Moreover, climate change can change these meteorological factors, which may affect the chemical reactions of O
  <sub>3</sub> and natural emissions of O
  <sub>3</sub> precursors. Consequently, the variation tendency of ground-level O
  <sub>3</sub> is inevitably linked with climate change [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-01528">1</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-01528">4</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>]. Over the past few decades, many researchers have studied this issue. Most of them used different models to simulate the O
  <sub>3</sub> concentration changes over the next few decades and explored how global climate change would impact regional meteorology and air pollution. Over years of exploration, scholars have gradually realized that the global climate change can affect the emission, transportation, diffusion, chemical reaction, and deposition of air pollutants by affecting the regional air temperature, solar radiation, relative humidity, wind speed, mixed layer height, and emission of ozone precursors [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-01528">1</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-01528">4</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>,
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-01528">11</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-16-01528">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-16-01528">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-16-01528">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-01528">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-16-01528">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-16-01528">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-16-01528">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-01528">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-16-01528">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With rapid economic development and increasing energy consumption, many regions in China are facing O
  <sub>3</sub> pollution [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>,
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-16-01528">15</a>,
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-01528">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-01528">18</a>,
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-01528">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-01528">30</a>]. Several researchers linked it with climate change and predicted future O
  <sub>3</sub> pollution in China. Based on the simulations from MOZART-2.4, Lin et al. [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-01528">22</a>] found that O
  <sub>3</sub> concentration might increase by 1–5% from 1990 to 2090 in the east of China for the scenario B1 and that the value might be 3–12% for A1FI. Using GEOS-Chem driven by GISS GCM (NASA, Washington, DC, USA), Wang et al. [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-01528">26</a>] revealed that climate change could increase O
  <sub>3</sub> in the east of China and decrease O
  <sub>3</sub> in the west of China from 2000 to 2050, and 40% of the increase might result from the strengthened biogenic volatile organic compounds (BVOCs) emission. With the aid of WRF-Chem driven by CCSM3, Liu et al. [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>] found that climate change and biogenic emission could result in the increase of O
  <sub>3</sub> by 1.6 ppb (−5 to 5 ppb) over South China in 2050, while the uncontrolled anthropogenic emissions would increase O
  <sub>3</sub> up to 12.8 ppb. Lee et al. [
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-01528">13</a>] predicted the future O
  <sub>3</sub> trend in Hong Kong and indicated that the pollution would continue to rise until 2025. By using WRF-CALGRID (ARB, Sacramento, CA, USA) driven by CCSM3, Xie et al. [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>] studied the variation trend of O
  <sub>3</sub> in the Yangtze River Delta (YRD) region. They found that the variations in meteorological fields caused by climate change could result in an increase (5 to 15 ppb) in the north and a decrease (−5 to −15 ppb) in the south and that the enhanced natural emissions could contribute approximately 20% to the surface O
  <sub>3</sub> increase, with the biggest increase up to 2.4 ppb. Obviously, the trend and the magnitude of O
  <sub>3</sub> variations resulted from climate change, varying from region to region in China. Despite a couple of investigations in these dynamic economic regions, more studies are needed. Moreover, among current studies, most researchers only focused on the changes in O
  <sub>3</sub> concentration, and few have emphasized the variations of the transportation, diffusion, chemical reaction, and deposition processes of O
  <sub>3</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To offer a full understanding of the variation mechanism of O
  <sub>3</sub> under the future weather conditions, the air quality model WRF-Chem is applied in this study to quantify the effects of climate change on O
  <sub>3</sub> in the YRD—one of the world’s most vigorous economic regions under severe O
  <sub>3</sub> pollution. Many surface sites showed that the O
  <sub>3</sub> concentration in this region even reached 140 ppb, far above the limit value of 1-hour average O
  <sub>3</sub> concentration in the “Ambient air quality standards” (GB3095-2012) published by the Chinese Ministry of Environmental Protection [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-01528">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-01528">32</a>]. Moreover, the mean monthly highest 5% O
  <sub>3</sub> at Lin’an increased at the rate of 1.8 ppb/year during 1996–2006 [
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-01528">33</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As natural emissions and their effects in the YRD under future climate conditions have been studied [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>], the impacts of climate change on individual processes of O
  <sub>3</sub> formation are discussed in this paper. The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. The model, its configurations, and the input data are introduced in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-ijerph-16-01528" href="#sec2-ijerph-16-01528">Section 2</a>. The validation of model performance, the change in future meteorology, the impact of climate change on O
  <sub>3</sub>, its precursors, and O
  <sub>3</sub>–NO
  <sub>X</sub>-VOC sensitivity are discussed in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3-ijerph-16-01528" href="#sec3-ijerph-16-01528">Section 3</a>. Finally, a brief summary is given in 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec4-ijerph-16-01528" href="#sec4-ijerph-16-01528">Section 4</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
