<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot3-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Changes in Ozone Precursors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a> shows the differences of ozone precursors at the surface between FUTMET and PREMET. For NO
  <sub>x</sub>, the change pattern during the daytime (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>a) is similar to that at night (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>b). The increases appear in the north of Shanghai and Hangzhou. In the daytime, the maximum increase is 6.5 ppb in Shanghai. At night, the maximum increase is 11.9 ppb in Hangzhou. These increases of NO
  <sub>x</sub> match the decreases of PBLH, implying the accumulation of air pollutants under worse diffusion conditions. Also, the stronger southerly wind in the daytime can lead to increases of concentration in the north. However, more high values appear in Hangzhou at night than in the daytime, caused by an enhancement of the westerly wind along Nanjing-Shanghai line, which blocks the northward transportation of NO
  <sub>x</sub>. The change patterns of VOCs and CO are similar to that of NO
  <sub>x</sub>. The higher increments also appear in the northern YRD. The maximum changes for VOCs are 3.7 ppb (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>c) in the day and 6.1 ppb at night (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>d). Those values for CO are 134.3 ppb (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>e) and 154.1 ppb (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>f), respectively [
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-01528">48</a>]. The differences of change patterns between day and night, as well as the main causes, are similar with those of NO
  <sub>x</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand the impacts of the changes caused by climate change in individual atmospheric process, the monthly mean differences between FUTMET and PREMET for the CHEM, VMIX, and ADVT processes of NO
  <sub>x</sub> in the YRD are investigated. The contributions of VMIX and ADVT to NO
  <sub>x</sub> variations are the largest, while CHEM has little effect. Thus, only the changes in the VMIX and ADVT processes of NOx (respectively referred to as Vmix_NOx, and Advt_NOx hereafter) at the surface are presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>a, during the daytime, the maximum increase of Vmix_NO
  <sub>x</sub> locates at the center of the YRD with a value of 8.1 ppb/h. This high value should be attributed to the decrease of PBLH (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>e) and higher NO
  <sub>x</sub> emissions in this area. At night, however, Vmix_NOx decreases in most of the YRD with a maximum reduction of −7.2 ppb/h. The decreases are related to the increase of PBLH (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>c), which can bring more pollutants to the higher levels. For Advt_NO
  <sub>x</sub>, its changes are closely related to the variations of wind fields. During the daytime, the increments of Advt_NO
  <sub>x</sub> are more than 1.5 ppb/h in the north of the YRD (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>c), implying that the southerly wind (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>f) brings more NO
  <sub>x</sub> to the north. At night, NO
  <sub>x</sub> is transported from south to north under the dominant southerly wind in most parts (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>d). However, there are high values of Advt_NO
  <sub>x</sub> to the south of Nanjing-Shanghai line, which may be connected with a strengthening of the easterly wind in this area in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>d.
 </p>
</sec>
