<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot5-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Impact of Climate Change on Regional Ozone Control Policy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ratio of certain secondary photochemical products, such as H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/NO
  <sub>Z</sub> and H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub>, can be used as the efficient indicators to distinguish NO
  <sub>X</sub>- or VOC-sensitive regimes of O
  <sub>3</sub> chemistry (Xie et al., 2014). In this study, H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub> is adopted to investigate the O
  <sub>3</sub>–NO
  <sub>X</sub>-VOC sensitivity in the YRD under different climate conditions. According to the previous study [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>], the transition value of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub> in the present summer is quantified to be 0.3–0.5, while it will change to 0.4–0.8 under the future conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a> shows the mean values of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub> at the first model layer over the YRD during afternoon (13:00–16:00 LST) from FUTMET and PREMET. For PREMET, low values (&lt;0.3) of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub> are mainly located in Shanghai, Nanjing, Hangzhou, and most land areas in the northern YRD (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a>a). The results mean that the O
  <sub>3</sub> chemistry in the typical cities and the northern YRD is VOC-sensitive and that VOCs should be preferentially reduced in these areas at present. However, in the future, more and more areas in YRD are covered by high values of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a>b). The values in the vast majority of grids are over 0.8, which means the O
  <sub>3</sub> chemistry is NO
  <sub>x</sub>-sensitive in most parts of the YRD. Lower values (&lt;0.4) only appear around Shanghai. The values in the cities of southern Jiangsu and northeastern Zhejiang are also close to 0.4. The change in the distribution pattern of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub> implies that O
  <sub>3</sub> chemistry in the future of YRD tends to be insensitive to VOCs and is more easily affected by NO
  <sub>x</sub>, which is in accordance with the findings of Xie et al. [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>]
 </p>
</sec>
