<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec4-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of climate change on surface ozone in summer over the YRD region is studied by using WRF-Chem, with a special emphasis on the changes in meteorological factors and their impacts on individual atmospheric processes of O
  <sub>3</sub> formation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulations predict that solar radiation and a 2-m air temperature increase in the daytime in most of the YRD region with average increments of 33.2 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> and 1.5 °C, respectively. The absolute humidity and precipitation increase in the north and decrease in the south with variations of −30.0–40.0 μg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span> and −2.0–8.0 mm, respectively. PBLH increases about 100.0 to 200.0 m in the south and decrease about −100.0 to −400.0 m in the north. The change pattern of wind speed is similar to air temperature, with an average increment of 1.2 m/s. The southerly wind will be strengthened. At night, the change patterns of the meteorological factors are similar to those during the daytime but with small variations. The regional average increments of T
  <sub>2</sub> and wind speed are 1.9 °C and 0.8 m/s, respectively. Easterly wind will be strengthened along the Shanghai-Nanjing line. The absolute humidity varies −20.0 to 30.0 μg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span>, and PBLH increases about 100.0–200.0 m.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the effects of climate change on air pollutants, the change patterns of O
  <sub>3</sub> precursors (NO
  <sub>x</sub>, VOC, and CO) are similar, with an increase in the north and a decrease in the south. The maximum increments of NO
  <sub>x</sub>, VOC, and CO in the day can reach 6.5, 3.7, and 134.3 ppb, respectively. Those at night are 11.9, 6.1, and 154.1 ppb, respectively. According to a process analysis, their increases are related with the decreases of PBLH and the input effect of stronger southerly wind, while the decreases are attributed to the output effect of the stronger southerly wind. Surface O
  <sub>3</sub> variations will increase in the north and decrease in the south during the daytime. According to process analysis, the increase of surface O
  <sub>3</sub> in the north is dominated by gas phase chemical process related to the increases of solar radiation, air temperature, and O
  <sub>3</sub> precursors. The decrease in the south is mainly caused by the transport process changing with the strengthened southerly wind. During the nighttime under the future climate, the surface O
  <sub>3</sub> changes amplitude is less than the daytime, with the same change pattern as that in the day. The less O
  <sub>3</sub> variations at night can be attributed to an O
  <sub>3</sub> titration reaction with NO, the changes in NO
  <sub>x</sub> concentrations, and the increases of nocturnal PBLH. Moreover, climate change can affect the chemical relationship between O
  <sub>3</sub> and its precursors. With the aid of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>/HNO
  <sub>3</sub>, O
  <sub>3</sub>–NO
  <sub>x</sub>-VOC sensitivity over the YRD region is found to be easily affected by NO
  <sub>x</sub> in the future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study provides us a scope of understanding how the future climate affects the surface ozone in the YRD region. However, only the IPCC RCP4.5 scenario from CCSM4 is considered. To obtain a comprehensive understanding, the future meteorological inputs should be provided by more global climate models based on more future climate scenarios, including Socio-Economic Pathways (SSPs) scenarios. Moreover, the manmade emissions may decrease in the future, and the land-use types may continue to change for decades. These future changes should be taken into consideration in the follow-up studies as well.</p>
</sec>
