<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Methodology</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Model Description and Configuration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, WRF-Chem version 3.5 (NOAA, Colorado, USA) was applied to investigate the impacts of climate change on air quality over the YRD. WRF-Chem is a new generation of air quality modeling system, which is composed of the meteorological component (WRF) and the air quality component (Chem). The two components are fully coupled, and they use the same coordinates and physical parameterizations [
   <a rid="B34-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-16-01528">34</a>]. WRF-Chem has been widely adopted in simulating the air quality of Chinese city clusters and investigating its formation mechanism [
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-01528">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>,
   <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-01528">30</a>,
   <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-01528">35</a>,
   <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-01528">36</a>,
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-01528">37</a>]. Also, it is of a relatively good capability in simulating climate change and its effects on air quality [
   <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>,
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f001" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f001">Figure 1</a>, three nested domains were used. The model domains were centered at (32.8° N, 87.5° E) with Lambert Conformal Conic projection. The grid sizes of these domains were 56 × 42, 109 × 82, and 178 × 136, with grid spacings of 81, 27, and 9 km, respectively. The outer domain covered a fairly large area of East Asia. The inner domain covered the YRD and its surrounding waters. For all domains, there were 31 vertical layers from the surface to the model top of 100 hPa, with about 10 layers in the planetary boundary layer.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The major physical options selected in WRF-Chem simulations are shown in 
   <a rid="ijerph-16-01528-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-01528-t001">Table 1</a>. The Purdue Lin microphysics scheme [
   <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-01528">38</a>] makes progress that the addition of a snow field to the cloud model significantly modifies the microphysical processes; it is more consummate. In the RRTM (Rapid Radiative Transfer Model) longwave radiation scheme, the speed of execution compares favorably with those of other rapid radiation models, and the model can be used in general circulation models [
   <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-01528">39</a>]. The Goddard shortwave radiation scheme results in considerable improvement in reproducing the model’s thermal structure, such as the zonal mean air temperature, its latitudinal gradient, and vertically integrated temperature [
   <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-01528">40</a>]. In the Kain–Fritsh cumulus parameterization scheme, the specific formation of the modifications can produce desired effects in numerical weather prediction and render the scheme closer to observations and cloud-resolving modeling studies [
   <a rid="B41-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-16-01528">41</a>]. The NOAH/LSM (NCAR, Boulder, CO, USA) scheme can not only provide reasonable diurnal variations of surface heat flues but also correct seasonal evolutions of soil moisture in the context of a long-term data assimilation system [
   <a rid="B42-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-16-01528">42</a>]. The MYJ (Mellor–Yamada–Janjic) PBL scheme makes progress on the basis of the MY PBL scheme, and the new scheme for calculating the MY level 2.5 master length scale is rectified [
   <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-01528">43</a>]. The chemical mechanism used to simulate gas concentration is the Carbon-Bond Mechanism version Z (CBMZ). The CBMZ is developed from a new lumped-structure mechanism, largely based on the widely used Carbon Bond Mechanism (CBM-IV). Major improvements include a revised inorganic chemistry, an explicit treatment of the lesser reactive paraffins, methane, and ethane [
   <a rid="B44-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-16-01528">44</a>]. The adopted option for aerosol is the four-bin sectional Model for Simulating Aerosol Interactions and Chemistry (MOSAIC). MOSAIC is found to be in excellent agreement with a benchmark version of the model using a rigorous solver for integrating the stiff ordinary differential equations (ODEs). Therefore, MOSAIC is a good choice in air quality and regional/global aerosol models [
   <a rid="B45-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-16-01528">45</a>]. The initial and boundary chemical conditions are derived from the modeling results of the global chemistry transport model MOZART-4.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Simulation Cases</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate how climate change influences the O
   <sub>3</sub> concentration in the YRD, two simulation cases are specially designed and conducted. One uses the present meteorology in 2014, 2015, and 2016 and the present emission (referred to as PREMET hereafter). The other uses the future meteorology in 2050, 2051, and 2052 and the present emission (referred to as FUTMET hereafter). In the YRD, the observation results show that a high O
   <sub>3</sub> concentration usually appears in late spring and early summer and that O
   <sub>3</sub> is more sensitive to environment in summer [
   <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-01528">17</a>,
   <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-01528">18</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>]. Thus, the PREMET simulations are conducted from 00 UTC July 1st to 18 UTC July 31st in 2014, 2015, and 2016. Also, the FUTMET simulations are conducted from 00 UTC July 1st to 18 UTC July 31st in 2050, 2051, and 2052. An initial 48-hour model integration period is used for the spin-up of the simulations. The difference between the modeling results from FUTMET and PREMET can demonstrate the effect of climate change on air quality (EF
   <sub>climate</sub>), which can be calculated by the following equation:
   <div id="FD1-ijerph-16-01528" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
    <div id="mm1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">EF</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">climate</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msubsup">
          <span class="mo">∑</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">t</span>
           <span class="mo">=</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">V</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">F</span>
             <span class="mi">U</span>
             <span class="mi">T</span>
             <span class="mi">M</span>
             <span class="mi">E</span>
             <span class="mi">T</span>
             <span class="mo">,</span>
             <span class="mo"> </span>
             <span class="mi">t</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">−</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">V</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">P</span>
             <span class="mi">R</span>
             <span class="mi">E</span>
             <span class="mi">M</span>
             <span class="mi">E</span>
             <span class="mi">T</span>
             <span class="mo">,</span>
             <span class="mo"> </span>
             <span class="mi">t</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mi">N</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">,</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where 
   <span class="italic">t</span> represents one modeling time step; 
   <span class="italic">N</span> represents the total modeled time; 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm2" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">F</span>
         <span class="mi">U</span>
         <span class="mi">T</span>
         <span class="mi">M</span>
         <span class="mi">E</span>
         <span class="mi">T</span>
         <span class="mo">,</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> and 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm3" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">P</span>
         <span class="mi">R</span>
         <span class="mi">E</span>
         <span class="mi">M</span>
         <span class="mi">E</span>
         <span class="mi">T</span>
         <span class="mo">,</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> are the hourly modeling outputs of variable 
   <span class="italic">V</span> (meteorological factors or air pollutants) from FUTMET and PREMET, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Present and Future Climate Data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present and future climate data are used to drive WRF as the initial meteorological fields and boundary conditions. These data are obtained from the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Community Climate System Model version 4 (CCSM4) outputs with a horizontal resolution of T85 (about 1.41°). The CCSM4 RCP4.5 outputs for 2050, 2051, and 2052 used in this study are based on the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Fifth Assessment Report. RCP4.5 is a midline future climate scenario for CO
   <sub>2</sub> emission and economic growth, which can ensure our results to be moderate. For the present year, the CCSM4 outputs in 2014, 2015, and 2016 are used. The data are also compared with the National Centers for Environmental Prediction (NCEP) Final Analysis (FNL) data with the spatial resolution of 1°, and the difference is ignorable.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Anthropogenic Emissions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the PREMET case, the anthropogenic emissions in China are from the Multi-resolution Emission Inventory (MEIC) developed by Tsinghua University based on a technology-based emission model. The MEIC inventory contains monthly anthropogenic emissions of SO
   <sub>2</sub>, NO
   <sub>X</sub>, CO, NH
   <sub>3</sub>, PM
   <sub>2.5</sub>, PM
   <sub>10</sub>, BC, OC, and VOCs in five sectors (agriculture, industry, power plants, residential, and transportation) [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-01528">46</a>]. Those for the areas out of China are mainly from the inventory developed by the NASA INTEX-B (NASA, Washington, DC, USA), including the emissions of SO
   <sub>2</sub>, NO
   <sub>x</sub>, CO, PM
   <sub>10</sub>, PM
   <sub>2.5</sub>, BC, OC, and VOCs from the power, residential, industry, and transportation sectors with a resolution of 0.5° [
   <a rid="B47-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-16-01528">47</a>]. Furthermore, these data have been specially modified for simulations in the YRD following the work of Xie et al. [
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For future anthropogenic emissions, some previous investigations estimated them by some hypothetical growth factors [
   <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>,
   <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-01528">26</a>]. However, the Chinese government has formulated a series of strict emission reduction policies to protect air quality, implying that the hypothetical increase of emissions is inapplicable. On the other hand, the main purpose of this study is to demonstrate the changes of meteorological factors under future climate and their effects on individual processes of O
   <sub>3</sub> formation. Therefore, it is reasonable to assume that the future anthropogenic emissions will remain at the current level. In the FUTMET case, the emissions are set to be the same as PREMET.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Process Analysis Method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">WRF-Chem version 3.5 contains a simple process analysis function, which can present the contributions of individual atmospheric processes, including chemical reaction (CHEM), vertical mixing coupled with dry deposition (VMIX), and advection transportation with horizontal and vertical components (ADVT). These variables can show the relative significance of each process and provide a particular interpretation of air pollution. In this study, by comparing the values of CHEM, VMIX, and ADVT from FUTMET with those from PREMET, we can figure out how the changes in meteorological factors influence the individual atmospheric processes of O
   <sub>3</sub> chemistry. Moreover, the O
   <sub>3</sub> change (accumulation or consuming) in different processes is called Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub> in the CHEM process, Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub> in the VMIX process, and Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub> in the ADVT process. The unit of Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub>, Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub>, and Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub> is ppb/h, implying the changes in one hour in this process.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot6-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Model Performance Evaluation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean bias (MB), root mean square error (RMSE), and correlation coefficient (CORR) between thet observations and the simulation results from PREMET are used to verify the performance of WRF-Chem. In statistics, they are usually defined as 
   <div id="FD2-ijerph-16-01528" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
    <div id="mm4" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">M</span>
       <span class="mi">B</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <span class="mn">1</span>
        <span class="mi">N</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span class="mo">∑</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">i</span>
         <span class="mo">=</span>
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mi">N</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">S</span>
          <span class="mi">i</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">−</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">O</span>
          <span class="mi">i</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">,</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="FD3-ijerph-16-01528" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
    <div id="mm5" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">R</span>
       <span class="mi">M</span>
       <span class="mi">S</span>
       <span class="mi">E</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="msqrt">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="mfrac">
          <span class="mn">1</span>
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
         <div class="msubsup">
          <span class="mo">∑</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">i</span>
           <span class="mo">=</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
         <div class="msup">
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mo">(</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">S</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">−</span>
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">O</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <span class="mo">)</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">,</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="FD4-ijerph-16-01528" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(4)</span>
    <div id="mm6" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">and</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext"> </span>
        <span class="mi">CORR</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msubsup">
          <span class="mo">∑</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">i</span>
           <span class="mo">=</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">S</span>
            <span class="mi">i</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">−</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">S</span>
            <span class="mi">m</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">O</span>
            <span class="mi">i</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">−</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">O</span>
            <span class="mi">m</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msqrt">
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msubsup">
            <span class="mo">∑</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">i</span>
             <span class="mo">=</span>
             <span class="mn">1</span>
            </div>
            <span class="mi">N</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mo">(</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">S</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">−</span>
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">S</span>
              <span class="mi">m</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <span class="mo">)</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <div class="msqrt">
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msubsup">
            <span class="mo">∑</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span class="mi">i</span>
             <span class="mo">=</span>
             <span class="mn">1</span>
            </div>
            <span class="mi">N</span>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mo">(</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">O</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">−</span>
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">O</span>
              <span class="mi">m</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <span class="mo">)</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">,</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm7" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">S</span>
        <span class="mi">i</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> and 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm8" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">O</span>
        <span class="mi">i</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> are the simulated and the observed values, respectively, and 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm9" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">S</span>
        <span class="mi">m</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> and 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="mm10" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">O</span>
        <span class="mi">m</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> are the averaged values of simulation and observation, respectively. Generally, the modeling results are acceptable if MB and RMSE are close to 0 and if CORR is close to 1 [
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three observation sites are selected for comparison, namely NJ (32.00° N, 118.80° E) in Nanjing, HZ (30.23° N, 120.16° E) in Hangzhou, and SH (31.40° N, 121.46° E) in Shanghai. Their hourly observational data of 2-m temperature (T
   <sub>2</sub>), 10-m wind speed (WS
   <sub>10</sub>), and 2-m relative humidity (RH
   <sub>2</sub>) in July of 2014, 2015, and 2016 are obtained from the observation database in the Wyoming Weather Web. Their hourly air pollutant concentration records can be acquired from the air quality real-time publishing platform. The observational methods and the quality assurance/quality control (QA/QC) procedures for these data strictly follow the Chinese national standard. Also, the manual inspection of invalid and lacking data is performed during data processing [
   <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-01528">17</a>,
   <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-01528">18</a>,
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-01528">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>,
   <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-01528">30</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
