<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussions</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Model Evaluation for WRF-Chem</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a rid="ijerph-16-01528-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-01528-t002">Table 2</a> shows the statistical comparisons between the observations and the modeling results from PREMET. OBS and SIM are represented the observation and simulation. For T
   <sub>2</sub>, the model slightly overvalues T
   <sub>2</sub> at all sites, which might result from the uncertainty of urban canopy and surface parameters [
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-01528">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>,
   <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-01528">36</a>,
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-01528">37</a>]. However, the overestimation is acceptable because the MB values of T
   <sub>2</sub> are only 0.5–1.7 °C, the RMSE of T
   <sub>2</sub> is 2.8–3.9 °C, and the CORR between observations and simulations are over 0.8 at all sites (statistically significant at the 95% confidence level). Moreover, the lowest value 0.5 °C for MB and the highest value 0.9 for CORR show that the best simulation of T
   <sub>2</sub> is at NJ. For RH
   <sub>2</sub>, though the modeling results are slightly underestimated, the CORR values are over 0.8 at most sites. Therefore, the simulations for RH
   <sub>2</sub> are relatively acceptable. The lowest value 0.7 for CORR is at SH, which may be attributed to the uncertainty of the land-use data that cannot well describe waters around SH [
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>]. For WS
   <sub>10</sub>, the modeling values are overestimated at HZ and SH but underestimated at NJ. The CORR (close to 0.5) for WS
   <sub>10</sub> is the lowest in three meteorological factors. The wind components were not simulated very well, just as in previous studies, which may be caused by urban canopy parameters [
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-01528">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>,
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-01528">37</a>]. Compared with previous studies, the biases in this study are acceptable.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With respect to O
   <sub>3</sub>, the CORRs are more than 0.6 at most sites. The lowest value for MB (−1.2 ppb) and the highest CORR value (close to 0.7) indicate that the simulation at SH is good. However, the modeling results overestimate O
   <sub>3</sub> concentrations at NJ and HZ, and the values of MB are around 8.0. These biases might be related to the modeled stronger solar radiation reaching the surface, which can cause positive biases in T
   <sub>2</sub> and thereby produces more O
   <sub>3</sub> [
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>,
   <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-01528">37</a>]. At the same time, the high bias about simulated wind might result in the O
   <sub>3</sub> concentration uncertainty. In addition, there are also some uncertainties in the emission, which might cause O
   <sub>3</sub> concentration bias.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All in all, the performance of WRF-Chem in modeling climate and air quality is acceptable over the YRD region in this study. Some biases are still found in simulations, but the difference between PREMET and FUTMET can still demonstrate how meteorological factors could impact O
   <sub>3</sub>, as all other settings are the same in both simulations.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Regional Meteorology Changes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The regional meteorological changes caused by global climate change are shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>. The values in these figures present the differences between FUTMET and PREMET. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a> shows the changes during the daytime (from 7:00 to 18:00 LST (Local standard time)). For solar radiation (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>a), the values in the land area of YRD significantly increase, with the average value of 33.2 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>. The maximum increase of 76.0 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> appears in the southwest. The changing pattern of T
   <sub>2</sub> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>b) is similar to that of solar radiation. The average increase of T
   <sub>2</sub> is predicted to be 1.5 °C over the entire region. High values can be found in the southwest of the YRD, with a maximum of 3.6 °C. The good relevancy between 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>a,b can be explained by the fact that the increase of T
   <sub>2</sub> is caused by solar radiation. For absolute humidity (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>c), it increases over 10.0 μg/m
   <span class="sup">3</span> in the northern and central YRD, which is related to the precipitation increase with the value over 4.0 mm in those areas (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>d). However, in the southern YRD, the air becomes dryer (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>c), caused by the precipitation decrease there (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>d). For planetary boundary layer height (PBLH) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>e), it increases by the maximum value (about 234.3 m) in the southern YRD, which can be attributed to high increments of solar radiation and air temperature. However, PBLH decreases by 200.0 m in most of northern and central areas. The decreases may be caused by the small increase of T
   <sub>2</sub> and the high humidity, which can increase latent heat and lower PBLH. For WS
   <sub>10</sub> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>f), the change pattern is similar to that of T
   <sub>2</sub>. The regional mean increment is 1.2 m/s, and the high increases appear in the south with the maximum value of 4.2 m/s. For the wind direction, a southerly wind will dominate the YRD in the future under the strengthening of the Northwest Pacific Subtropical High.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a> shows the changes at night (from 19:00 to 6:00 LST). For T
   <sub>2</sub> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>a), it is predicted to increase about 1.9 °C over the entire YRD, with the higher increases over 5.0 °C in the southwest. The increments are slightly higher than those in the daytime, which may be related to more clouds at night. More clouds may strengthen the insulation effect. For absolute humidity (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>b), the regional mean changing value (9.6 μg/m
   <span class="sup">3</span>) is smaller than that in the daytime, related to a weaker evaporation at night. For PBLH (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>c), higher increasing values occur in the southwest of the YRD, with a maximum of 268.6 m. The pattern is similar to 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>a, implying the effect of air temperature on PBLH. For wind field (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>d), due to the rising of T
   <sub>2</sub>, the wind speed increases as well. The regional average increase is 0.8 m/s, and the maximum increase is 3.9 m/s. For the wind direction, the southerly wind dominates the region at night just as the changes in the daytime.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The estimated change trends and intensities of the above meteorological factors are in agreement with previous findings [
   <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>,
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>,
   <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-01528">26</a>]. During the daytime, the increase of solar radiation and T
   <sub>2</sub> can enhance the O
   <sub>3</sub> photochemical reactions over the entire YRD. Although the increase of PBLH in the north can dilute O
   <sub>3</sub> concentration in lower atmosphere, the decrease in the south can increase the O
   <sub>3</sub> pollution level. However, the strengthened southerly wind can transport more O
   <sub>3</sub> from the south to north, which may increase O
   <sub>3</sub> in the north and decrease O
   <sub>3</sub> in the south. The change trend of O
   <sub>3</sub> in the daytime might be different from that at night. The increase of T
   <sub>2</sub> can enhance the titration reaction between NO and O
   <sub>3</sub>. The increase of PBLH in the north can bring surface O
   <sub>3</sub> to the higher layers. The southerly wind may increase O
   <sub>3</sub> in the north but decrease it in the south. Consequently, it is hard to tell the change of O
   <sub>3</sub> just by the changes in meteorological factors either in the daytime or at night. Further analyses are needed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Changes in Ozone Precursors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a> shows the differences of ozone precursors at the surface between FUTMET and PREMET. For NO
   <sub>x</sub>, the change pattern during the daytime (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>a) is similar to that at night (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>b). The increases appear in the north of Shanghai and Hangzhou. In the daytime, the maximum increase is 6.5 ppb in Shanghai. At night, the maximum increase is 11.9 ppb in Hangzhou. These increases of NO
   <sub>x</sub> match the decreases of PBLH, implying the accumulation of air pollutants under worse diffusion conditions. Also, the stronger southerly wind in the daytime can lead to increases of concentration in the north. However, more high values appear in Hangzhou at night than in the daytime, caused by an enhancement of the westerly wind along Nanjing-Shanghai line, which blocks the northward transportation of NO
   <sub>x</sub>. The change patterns of VOCs and CO are similar to that of NO
   <sub>x</sub>. The higher increments also appear in the northern YRD. The maximum changes for VOCs are 3.7 ppb (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>c) in the day and 6.1 ppb at night (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>d). Those values for CO are 134.3 ppb (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>e) and 154.1 ppb (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>f), respectively [
   <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-01528">48</a>]. The differences of change patterns between day and night, as well as the main causes, are similar with those of NO
   <sub>x</sub>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand the impacts of the changes caused by climate change in individual atmospheric process, the monthly mean differences between FUTMET and PREMET for the CHEM, VMIX, and ADVT processes of NO
   <sub>x</sub> in the YRD are investigated. The contributions of VMIX and ADVT to NO
   <sub>x</sub> variations are the largest, while CHEM has little effect. Thus, only the changes in the VMIX and ADVT processes of NOx (respectively referred to as Vmix_NOx, and Advt_NOx hereafter) at the surface are presented in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>a, during the daytime, the maximum increase of Vmix_NO
   <sub>x</sub> locates at the center of the YRD with a value of 8.1 ppb/h. This high value should be attributed to the decrease of PBLH (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>e) and higher NO
   <sub>x</sub> emissions in this area. At night, however, Vmix_NOx decreases in most of the YRD with a maximum reduction of −7.2 ppb/h. The decreases are related to the increase of PBLH (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>c), which can bring more pollutants to the higher levels. For Advt_NO
   <sub>x</sub>, its changes are closely related to the variations of wind fields. During the daytime, the increments of Advt_NO
   <sub>x</sub> are more than 1.5 ppb/h in the north of the YRD (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>c), implying that the southerly wind (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>f) brings more NO
   <sub>x</sub> to the north. At night, NO
   <sub>x</sub> is transported from south to north under the dominant southerly wind in most parts (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f005" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f005">Figure 5</a>d). However, there are high values of Advt_NO
   <sub>x</sub> to the south of Nanjing-Shanghai line, which may be connected with a strengthening of the easterly wind in this area in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>d.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot4-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Changes in Ozone Driven by Climate Change</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f006" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f006">Figure 6</a> shows the differences of surface ozone between FUTMET and PREMET in the YRD. During the daytime (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f007" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f007">Figure 7</a>a), O
   <sub>3</sub> increases in the north but decreases in the south. The high increase values with a maximum of 18.5 ppb are along the coastal areas of Jiangsu Province, while the high reductions (over −15.1 ppb) are mainly in the inland areas of Jiangsu, Zhejiang, and Anhui Provinces. At night (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f007" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f007">Figure 7</a>b), the change pattern of O
   <sub>3</sub> is similar to that in the day, but the increase and the decrease values are lower. The regional averaged change value is just −0.2 ppb, the maximum increase is 17.5 ppb, and the maximum decrease is about −12.0 ppb. Less O
   <sub>3</sub> variations at night may be attributed to nocturnal O
   <sub>3</sub> chemical reactions. Moreover, the above O
   <sub>3</sub> change patterns are similar to those of NO
   <sub>x</sub>, VOCs, and CO, implying that O
   <sub>3</sub> changes are tightly related to O
   <sub>3</sub> precursors and are highly affected by chemical processes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f007" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f007">Figure 7</a> shows the different spatial distributions of major individual O
   <sub>3</sub> formation processes between FUTMET and PREMET during the daytime. The changes in O
   <sub>3</sub> chemical production (Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub>) vary from −2 to 4 ppb/h (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f007" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f007">Figure 7</a>a). The increases of Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub> occur in most areas of the YRD, which should be induced by enhanced gas phase reactions related to the increases of solar radiation (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>a) and surface air temperature (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>b). The higher increments over 3.0 ppb/h are mainly located along the coastal areas of Jiangsu Province, which is also the area with great increase of O
   <sub>3</sub> precursor concentration (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>a,c,e). Over the southern YRD, the decreases of absolute humidity and O
   <sub>3</sub> precursor concentration should result in reductions of Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub> in extensive areas, with the maximum decrease about −2.2 ppb/h to the south of Hangzhou. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f007" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f007">Figure 7</a>b illustrates that the changes in transport process of O
   <sub>3</sub> (Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub>) are between −3.0 to 4.0 ppb/h, which is closely related to the variation of horizontal wind speed and wind direction [
   <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-01528">7</a>]. Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub> rises up over 0–4.0 ppb/h in most areas of the northern YRD, with the higher increments over 2.1 ppb around Shanghai. The decreases of Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub> are mainly located in the southern YRD. The change pattern of Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub> further proves that the strengthened southerly wind in the YRD (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>f) can bring O
   <sub>3</sub> from the south to the north. For the vertical mixing and dry deposition process (Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub>), it ranges between –4.0 to 4.0 ppb (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f007" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f007">Figure 7</a>c). Though PBLH would decrease in the north (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f002" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f002">Figure 2</a>e, may increase O
   <sub>3</sub> at surface), Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub> can produce more O
   <sub>3</sub> in lower atmospheres (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f008" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f008">Figure 8</a>a) and more O
   <sub>3</sub> would be transported to the upper atmospheric layer or deposition to the ground (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f008" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f008">Figure 8</a>b). Thus, Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub> in the northern YRD mainly decreases. In the south, however, there is little change in Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub> (0–1.0 ppb/h). The high values close to some cities would be caused by the local atmospheric circulation related to urban heat island [
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-01528">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-01528">29</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At night, the changes in three main processes are smaller. The changes in Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub> vary from −1.0 to 2.0 ppb (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f009" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f009">Figure 9</a>a). The decreases of Chem_O
   <sub>3</sub> mainly appear in the north, which should be attributed to the enhancement of an O
   <sub>3</sub> titration reaction with NO at night due to temperature increase (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>a) and the sufficient NO
   <sub>x</sub> in the north (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>b). In a similar way, the increases in the south are related with the decrease of NO
   <sub>x</sub> there (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f004" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f004">Figure 4</a>b), which would weaken the O
   <sub>3</sub> consumption reaction. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a>b shows that the changes in Advt_O
   <sub>3</sub> are between −3.0 and 2.0 ppb in most areas. O
   <sub>3</sub> accumulation along the Nanjing-Shanghai line is due to the strengthening of the easterly wind. The changes in Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub> range between −3.0 and 2.0 ppb (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f009" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f009">Figure 9</a>c). The decreases of Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub> are related to the increases of nocturnal PBLH over the YRD (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>c). The maximum increases of Vmix_O
   <sub>3</sub> are in the south of the YRD. The increases are caused by great increases of wind speed that can weaken the dry deposition in this area (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f003" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f003">Figure 3</a>d).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot5-ijerph-16-01528" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Impact of Climate Change on Regional Ozone Control Policy</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ratio of certain secondary photochemical products, such as H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/NO
   <sub>Z</sub> and H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub>, can be used as the efficient indicators to distinguish NO
   <sub>X</sub>- or VOC-sensitive regimes of O
   <sub>3</sub> chemistry (Xie et al., 2014). In this study, H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub> is adopted to investigate the O
   <sub>3</sub>–NO
   <sub>X</sub>-VOC sensitivity in the YRD under different climate conditions. According to the previous study [
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>], the transition value of H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub> in the present summer is quantified to be 0.3–0.5, while it will change to 0.4–0.8 under the future conditions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a> shows the mean values of H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub> at the first model layer over the YRD during afternoon (13:00–16:00 LST) from FUTMET and PREMET. For PREMET, low values (&lt;0.3) of H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub> are mainly located in Shanghai, Nanjing, Hangzhou, and most land areas in the northern YRD (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a>a). The results mean that the O
   <sub>3</sub> chemistry in the typical cities and the northern YRD is VOC-sensitive and that VOCs should be preferentially reduced in these areas at present. However, in the future, more and more areas in YRD are covered by high values of H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01528-f010" href="#ijerph-16-01528-f010">Figure 10</a>b). The values in the vast majority of grids are over 0.8, which means the O
   <sub>3</sub> chemistry is NO
   <sub>x</sub>-sensitive in most parts of the YRD. Lower values (&lt;0.4) only appear around Shanghai. The values in the cities of southern Jiangsu and northeastern Zhejiang are also close to 0.4. The change in the distribution pattern of H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub>/HNO
   <sub>3</sub> implies that O
   <sub>3</sub> chemistry in the future of YRD tends to be insensitive to VOCs and is more easily affected by NO
   <sub>x</sub>, which is in accordance with the findings of Xie et al. [
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-01528" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-01528">8</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
