<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Bay scallop populations along the eastern US have encountered numerous challenges in recent decades with overharvest (Barber &amp; Davis, 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>), habitat loss (Orth et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Serveiss et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>), and recurring harmful algal blooms (Cosper et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>; Summerson &amp; Peterson, 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>) contributing to a 97% decline in landings since the 1980s (NOAA Fisheries Landings 1980–2016; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.noaa.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.noaa.gov</ext-link>) and population‐level declines in areas where bay scallop fisheries were once significant (Tettelbach et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). While some bay scallop restoration efforts have exhibited success (Tettelbach et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), findings presented here demonstrate that the presence of multiple stressors may complicate future restoration. As carbon emissions continue to warm and acidify coastal ecosystems, the associated adverse effects on bay scallop populations may intensify. As anthropogenic activities continue to establish conditions along coastal zones that are more permissive for the growth and persistence of multiple species of harmful algae (Gobler et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Heisler et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35100-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), further population‐level declines among bay scallops are likely. Given that realistic levels of both harmful algal species and climate change stressors were used in the current study, the more intense mortality and transcriptomic responses to harmful algae compared to climate change stressors by the scallop larvae suggest that HABs may be a more pressing threat to bay scallops in the near‐future.
</p>
