<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There have been very few long‐term monitoring studies of Lepidoptera in tropical rainforests, with exceptions such as Leidner et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), Grøtan et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), and Valtonen et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). In the tropics, insect species commonly produce eight generations every year (Nair, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Polar, Cock, Frederickson, Hosein, and Krauss (
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) mention four generations per year for 
 <italic class="italic">Hylesia</italic> spp. Data from Janzen (
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1984b</xref>) suggest between three and six generations per year. This figure suggests that our short time‐series of 8 years for BCI saturniids nevertheless represent &gt;30 saturniid generations for most species. Both the data on faunal composition (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33515-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>) and the time‐series (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33515-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, Fig. S5) suggest that year 2011 was rather different from other years, with distinct peaks in populations for six of the 14 saturniid species studied. Other peaks of saturniid abundances occurred mainly in 2015 and 2016. Although the relationship between monthly ENSO and saturniid abundance is not straightforward (as judged by our multiple regressions, Table S5), we note that years 2011, 2015, and 2016 are qualified as weak‐to‐moderate La Niña event, very strong El Niño event, and very strong El Niño event, respectively (National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The number of saturniid species peaking each year appears to be related to the magnitude of these events, which also is reflected in changes in faunal composition, as illustrated by NDMS plots (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33515-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>), with Axis 1 clearly separating these three years from other sampling years. The lowest overall faunal similarity was also between a pre‐El Niño year (2014) and an El Niño year (2015, Table S2). Our results suggest that saturniid abundances and composition are affected by El Niño and La Niña events, but that longer time‐series including more of these events are certainly needed to build a comprehensive understanding of insect responses to such climate anomalies.
</p>
