<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Birds of the Mojave Desert exhibited a dominant signal of occupancy decline and erosion of site-level species richness over the last century (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). Both diminished by about half: The average species occupancy probability declined from 0.24 to 0.11, and sites lost on average 43% of their species. The decline of birds in the Mojave Desert appears to be exceptional compared with resurveys of adjacent ecoregions in the Sierra Nevada (
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>) and Central Valley (
 <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>) that occurred on the same timescale, at similar geographic scales, and following the same methods. Whether in the more diverse Sierras (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 205 species) or slightly less diverse Central Valley (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 122), little change in richness occurred over the past century (mean of −2.6 and +1.9 species per site, respectively) compared with the Mojave (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 135 species) that experienced a loss of 17.9 species per site. Moreover, there were roughly similar increases and decreases in species-level occupancy in the Sierras (10.2% of species decreased and 19.5% increased significantly) and the Central Valley (22.1% decreased and 28.7% increased). In contrast, there was no counterbalance to decline of species (28.9%) in the Mojave, where only the common raven increased significantly in occupancy. Beyond California, studies have found increases or stability in species richness, affiliated with expansions of warm-adapted species or generalists, though studies performed thus far have been biased toward temperate regions (
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>). The trends we observed in the Mojave are corroborated by findings of the North American Breeding Bird Survey (BBS). There has been a 46% decline in the abundance of arid-land indicator species since the onset of BBS surveys in 1968 (
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>).
</p>
