<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par130" class="p">The study confirms the sustainable rural livelihoods framework. People increase their livelihood resilience by adding on an alternative livelihood activity, as this reduces the risk of losing all income sources (Scoones 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">1998</xref>, Scoones 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2009</xref>). The alternative livelihood activities were often less dependent on natural resources, such as brick and garment factory work. The informants also comprehensively described the inter-linkage between loss of resources, tension in social interactions, and conflicts. Disasters and climate change impacts need to be perceived as stressors that overload the coping capacity of human societies and the resilience level of social systems (Blaikie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2014</xref>; Homer-Dixon 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2009</xref>; Raleigh and Kniveton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">2012</xref>). People-centred research can help structure people’s responses and behaviour around stress, scarcity, and power relations. As environmental stress and shocks become more frequent and intense worldwide, due to climate change, understanding how people can and cannot adapt provides valuable lessons. People all over the world will, for example, continue to use migration from rural to urban areas as an adaptation strategy. It is, therefore, necessary to better understand not just the number of people migrating, but also people’s decisions, and behaviour in the migration process. Adaptation strategies sometimes fail or add on other risks and pressures to peoples’ wellbeing, health, and livelihood resilience. A more people-centred research approach can help mitigate failures and risks (Black et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2011a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2013</xref>; Kniveton et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2012</xref>; McNamara et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
