<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Food security and food systems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Food security</span> represents a state of complete physical and economic access to sufficient, safe and nutritious food that meets a person´s dietary needs and food preferences for an active and healthy life [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref037">37</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref038">38</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Food systems</span> are understood as a set of human activities to produce, process, distribute, and consume food, and underpin the food security of human populations [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref039">39</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref041">41</a>]. Given the high reliance of Shawi livelihoods on natural resources [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref042">42</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref043">43</a>] and recognizing the importance of food systems not only for nutrition but also for other health and socio-cultural components [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref039">39</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref044">44</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref045">45</a>], this paper focuses on how disruptions in any of the four key food security components (i.e. availability, food access, utilization and stability) affect household and community food systems vulnerability to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref019">19</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref020">20</a>]. Under this framework, food 
  <span class="italic">availability</span> is driven by food production, exchange, or distribution; a
  <span class="italic">ccess</span> represents the ability to consume preferred food sources; and 
  <span class="italic">utilization</span> refers to the quality and the social value that people give to their food. At the same time, these food security components need to be 
  <span class="italic">stable</span> over time to assure food security [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref040">40</a>]. As such, food insecurity includes, for example, when food might be available but may not satisfy cultural preferences; food could be available and culturally acceptable, but not necessarily cover individual nutritional needs; or; food could cover nutritional needs and be culturally acceptable, yet availability throughout the year is not guaranteed.
 </p>
</sec>
