<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec030" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Past and present experiences are shaping the future adaptive capacity of Shawi household and communities</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Past-present trajectories of vulnerability associated with demographic changes and environmental degradation have being reported as important for future adaptation among Pacific Island populations where the “desire to make money” has resulted in the development of more cash cropping which in turn has eroded the social cohesion and reduced subsistence resources [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref057">57</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref058">58</a>]. Similarly, a demographic driver related with a less mobile settlement pattern and increasing farming practices was identified as a key proximal pathway for Shawi households and community food security. The Shawi have consistently increased their population over the last half century [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref063">63</a>]. Improved access to health services, particularly vaccination, and the erosion of Indigenous fertility regulations (e.g. polygyny, marriage rules, contraception), have been hypothesised as key factors in the recovery of Indigenous Amazonian populations after major population declines following encounters with Western societies [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref094">94</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref095">95</a>]. Although we did not find updated Shawi data on infant mortality, the last Peruvian census (2007) indicates that the Shawi population was relatively young, with higher fertility rates compared to the Peruvian average (7.7 vs 2.6 children per women) [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref096">96</a>]. This implies that the Shawi population may continue to increase in the future. Youth participants indicated that they intended to have fewer children and this intention may represent the potential for declining fertility rates if barriers to accessing appropriate and effective contraception planning are addressed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, past and current Peruvian policies were associated with reported changes in community settlement pattern and interact with current Peruvian economic development policies (e.g. infrastructure and agroindustry). For example, a Peruvian law (D.L. 20653, 1975) was dictated to legalize native communities and to provide incentives (e.g. economic aid and loans) to promote agricultural practices [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref097">97</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref098">98</a>]. The law was intended to provide land ownership and promote economic participation among Indigenous populations. Despite this, the law has resulted in the fragmentation and reduction of ancestral Indigenous territory, consequently limiting Indigenous public access to land and to wild food system activities [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref042">42</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref099">99</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref100">100</a>]. More recently, surrounding areas of Shawi settlements, in the San Martin region for example, were impacted by the promotion of bio-combustibles production [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref098">98</a>] and the development of a road for transportation [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref101">101</a>], with the Shawi expressing their concern about future land tenure conflict, immigration, deforestation, and reduced game availability [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref043">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So long as Shawi communities are losing their ability to migrate within their territory, dispersion as a coping mechanism to respond to extreme climatic events will be also threatened. Dispersion into the forest to access wild foods under extreme climatic events has been reported among the Yanomani people. The Yanomani turned to the forest to access food after an intense fire destroyed their crops during an extreme drought reported in the Amazon (1972–1973) [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref102">102</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref103">103</a>]. At that time, availability of forest wild food among the Yanomani was described as a reliable and important resource to supporting a 
  <span class="italic">“nomadic existence</span>” [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref102">102</a>]. Our results concur with reports from elsewhere in Latin America, suggesting that alteration of settlement patterns associated with increasing dependence on agricultural activities represents a key determinant of Indigenous Amazonian food security vulnerability [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref104" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref104">104</a>]. This trend, however, also implies decreasing capacity to adapt to hazardous climatic events. Economic development may offer opportunities to improve local livelihoods, and therefore might increase adaptive capacity to face extreme climatic extreme events, yet lack of recognition of cultural values (e.g. food preferences and food systems activities) and nutritional importance of forest resources continues to exclude the Shawi from economic and nutritional benefits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The predominance of non-climatic drivers influencing the short and long term adaptive capacity of Shawi food security under changing climatic conditions identified in this article suggest that the susceptibility of Shawi people to climate change is strongly related to cultural, socioeconomic and environmental changes rather than climatic risks per se. In addition, our findings about proximal and distal drivers of Shawi food insecurity, acting at a local levels but reinforced by past and current, socioeconomic governmental Peruvian policies, could help to explain why Indigenous Amazonian populations have consistently worse nutritional outcomes compared to non-Indigenous populations in the region.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A series of maladaptive trajectories have the potential to increase social and nutritional inequalities, and indicate that to assure a sustainable adaptive pathway for the Shawi population, transformational food security adaptation should include consideration of Indigenous perceptions and priorities, and should be part of Peruvian food and socioeconomic development policies.</p>
</sec>
