<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec026" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Proximal drivers of food security vulnerability to climate change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Demographic drivers directly affected food availability and exacerbated the Shawi food system sensitivity to climatic risks. Demographic changes in the context of concentrated community settlements were elevating pressure on wild food sources and extending the spatial extent and patterning of farming by using river edges for crop production, which in turn increased natural resource degradation. Cropping near the river was recognized as exacerbating the exposure of people and crops to climatic hazards Despite the risk that river edges represent for crops, key informants described the need to plant new plots close to the edge of the rivers because of an increasing dependence on farmed food. This marginal cropping was reported to occur in the context of limited opportunities to access cash and decreasing wild animal food sources. In parallel, lower tree density arising from deforestation for cropping along river edges negatively affected water dynamics and compromises fishing availability.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As long as fishing and other wild food sources were less available, the local Indigenous mechanisms for organizing collective work for crop production and collective fishing were compromised. The increased number and density of food insecure people seeking food in the forest were also encroaching household land boundaries and affecting Shawi social norms. This trajectory leads to diminishing local social institutions and the knowledge associated with the production and use of wild food, which is essential to responding to climatic hazards events. Furthermore, people were building new crop land on river edges, which increased their exposure to crop failure due to more frequent flooding events (Sistema Nacional de Defensa Civil-Balsapuerto, 2014, Sistema Nacional de Defensa Civil-Balsapuerto, 2015, Sistema Nacional de Defensa Civil-Balsapuerto, 2016). Consumption of wild food combined with increasing population was compromising the availability of wild food, implying that this cycle was unlikely to be sustainable.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second proximal pathway was driven by the desire of formal education (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205714.g005" href="#pone.0205714.g005">Fig 5</a>). Desire for educational opportunities presented a trade-off between investing in education (purchase of school supplies and transport), maintaining food security, and facilitating illegal logging. Community authorities recognized that even when local regulations exist to prevent indiscriminate deforestation, poor access to cash income for children’s school expenses (e.g. parents’ association fees, school supplies, transport) led them to agree to sell trees from their land to visitors, who were frequently illegal loggers. Selling to illegal loggers implies that benefits were not guaranteed and there was greater chance of exploitation. Increased education, in its current form, may conflict with and compromise Indigenous Shawi knowledge, as children spend less time with their parents, and youth leave the community for school, often losing knowledge of the land, food production, and local food consumption. Desire for education was also driving changes in settlement patterns with impacts on people’s access to, and relationship with, wild food sources. Other researchers have highlighted access to schools and education as a key driver of changing settlement pattern among Shawi people [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref043">43</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref063">63</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third there are changes in the local climate system, including warming temperatures, changes in seasonality, extreme precipitation and more frequent flash flooding events that interacted with the other two non-climatic drivers. Recent perceived alterations in climate variability were affecting the Shawi food system and compromising availability of food. According to our participants, warmer temperatures affected soil and local water bodies, and were particularly problematic during the dry season when most people needed to work outside to prepare the land, whereas river and creeks were the closest sources of animal foods. During transect walk activities, participants noted that temperatures have warmed in recent years, making it difficult to spend long working hours on the land. Previous researchers working with Shawi participants have also reported that warming temperatures were affecting water quality, which in turn affected the availability of fisheries in the dry season when water river decreased; temperatures were hotter and the expected minimum precipitation was perceived to decrease since 2005 [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref032">32</a>]. In addition to changes in temperature and precipitation, respondents reported that the predictability of seasons was also changing, with winter perceived as starting earlier than usual in the year. Local “
  <span class="italic">August winds”</span> that marked the beginning of the winter season were reported as occurring one month earlier than normally expected. According with local observations, not only was annual variability is changing, but also the behaviours of the fauna, which implies more uncertainty around the availability and stability of food. For example, 
  <span class="italic">zikizapa</span>, an edible specie of ant, appeared early in September on 2014, compared to its normal expected emergence in October or November.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One key informant stated:</p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>
   <span class="italic">“In the past</span>, 
   <span class="italic">we had a specific time when the summer began</span>, 
   <span class="italic">when the winter is</span>. 
   <span class="italic">Today there are days when it rains during the summer</span>, 
   <span class="italic">it rains for a whole week</span>! 
   <span class="italic">It is no longer in order</span>, 
   <span class="italic">it is in disorder</span>”
  </p>
  <p>(B001, male 25 years old).</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the Shawi, social activities and celebrations were based on wild food (to compensate for the collective labour carried out in the community). Preparing the land for cultivation by practicing collective activities—
  <span class="italic">Mairesu</span>, for example—was considered critical to avoid rains during planting. Early arrival of rains and unpredictable seasons made this collective capacity even more crucial. Since wild animals were central to preparing meals to organize this activity, the scarcity of game and fish compromises the ability of families to organize social activities around land cultivation and food availability from the farming sub-system is thus also affected. Shawi participants from other communities have also reported on the importance of game and wild fish for their community socialization[
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref043">43</a>]. Moreover, food sharing networks are embedded predominantly in the wild food sub-system and to a lesser extent the farming sub-food system, but not at all within the external sub-system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indigenous knowledge about food species and climatic characteristics were reported critical to cope with the impacts of climatic stresses. Wild food was a critical back-up when natural hazards destroyed crops or other food: the wild food system was thus an important safety net. Key informants explained that in 1995 because of intense rain in the highlands at the head of the river, a slope of the mountain collapsed, causing a mudslide. This mudslide was also reported by Peruvian authorities in the Balsapuerto district [
  <a rid="pone.0205714.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205714.ref081">81</a>]. Participants explained that after this event they turned to the forest and wild food sources as a substitute for the damaged crops. Recognition of multiple plant varieties, animals, and wild fungus was critical to accessing food as part of the communities’ coping strategy to access food during the 1995 flood and mudslide. Key informants mentioned that they were able to survive on typical forest foods during this time, including: macambo (
  <span class="italic">Theobroma bicolor)</span>, cocona (
  <span class="italic">Solanum sessiliflorum)</span>, churo (
  <span class="italic">Pomacea maculata</span>), congompe (kind of snail), callampa (wild edible fungus), suri (multiple species of larvae) and chonta (multiple species of heart palm tree).
 </p>
</sec>
