<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The purpose of protected areas (PAs) is to conserve species by preserving crucial habitats, but different socio-political boundaries separating individual PAs fragment and diminish their conservation value [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Species are now also moving their distributions in response to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], and while many static PAs are critically important for realizing these movements [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], they are not all equally well positioned to accommodate climate-induced changes to species’ geographic ranges [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Other areas beyond the current network of PAs are needed to ensure climate change adaptation [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Dynamic or floating PAs have been advanced as a potential solution [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], but implementation would require a fundamental paradigm shift in conservation planning, which we may not have time for given the rate and magnitude of climate change. An intermediate solution between expanding vs. moving PAs is to partner or coordinate conservation actions of existing PAs with surrounding areas, thus forming what we define as “conservation partnerships”, in order to increase the effective scale of conservation [
 <xref rid="pone.0191468.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. However, the benefits of such partnerships for promoting climate change adaptation have not been quantified globally, which limits discussion of their conservation utility and precludes identification of strategic partnering opportunities.
</p>
