<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dynamic Indicators of Resilience</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Borrowing from the literature in physics, it has been found that subtle changes in the dynamics of systems may often be used to quantify the proximity of a tipping point and to allow steps to be taken to avoid the transition (or to encourage it, if the system is in an unfavorable state to begin with). The most important of those early warning indicators are based on the phenomenon of “critical slowing down” (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). Phrased simply, slower recovery from small perturbations (e.g., the recovery of mood after a bad experience) is an indicator that the system is becoming fragile and that a tipping point (e.g., into depression) may be near. In mathematical terms, critical slowing down happens in continuous-time systems when the real part of the dominant eigenvalue of the Jacobian matrix of the linearized model about a steady state tends to zero as a bifurcation point is approached. Although there are transitions in dynamical systems that may not be characterized in this simple way (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>, 
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>), empirical studies across widely different systems suggest that critical slowing down is a surprisingly generic indicator of reduced resilience (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cause of critical slowing down can be seen in an intuitive way from stability landscapes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>). As the basin of attraction becomes smaller and shallower, its slopes become less steep (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2 
   <span class="italic">B</span> vs. 
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>), implying that the return rate to equilibrium upon small perturbations becomes slower (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2 
   <span class="italic">D</span> vs. 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>). In principle, measuring this requires an experimental perturbation. However, there is a way around that. All complex systems (including our body) are continuously subject to stochastic variations in external conditions. The effect of this natural regime of perturbations can be used to infer loss of resilience from a change in the nature of fluctuations in the state of a system (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>
  <a href="#r39">*</a>–
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>, 
  <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>). Explaining the mathematical background of this universal principle would go beyond the scope of this review, but the essence can be grasped intuitively. Stochastic fluctuations in the state of a system in part reflect microrecoveries from small, natural perturbations. Therefore, as the intrinsic recovery rate from perturbations becomes slower, fluctuations in the state will become slower overall, which can be seen from an elevated correlation between the state in subsequent moments, the so-called “temporal autocorrelation,” which tends to go hand-in-hand with an increase in variance (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2 
   <span class="italic">F</span> vs. 
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>) (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>
  <a href="#r39">*</a>–
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>, 
  <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in recovery rates and the associated temporal autocorrelations are not the only class of generic indicators of resilience. Many complex systems can be seen as networks of subsystems, and organisms are no exception (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>). In such systems, the capacity to bounce back from challenges implies a capacity to avoid a cascading collapse that brings the entire network down. It has been shown that in networks in which the elements depend on each other (facilitative networks), a rising correlation between the fluctuation in the time series of different elements may indicate the risk of such a systemic collapse (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>). This makes intuitive sense for organisms. Malfunctioning of one subsystem (e.g., inflammation) will affect the outcome of other subsystems (e.g., cognition and gait) more strongly if those other subsystems already have a low resilience. Thus, as individual elements become less resilient, sensitivity to fluctuations in the functioning of other elements increases, which may lead to a rising cross-correlation between the ups and downs in the functioning of the different elements of the system (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">H</span>
  </a>) (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" href="#r58">58</a>). The network perspective also helps show why resilience is an emergent property and why changes in components will combine to shape systemic resilience of the organism as a whole.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that, as indicators of critical slowing down relate to changing dynamics around equilibria, they cannot be linked in simple ways to the resilience of systems characterized by cycles or chaotic dynamics. Critical transitions in such systems have a complex nature and are difficult to foresee (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). The heart and the brain are examples. Possible early warning signals for seizures and particular kinds of heart failure have been linked to phenomena in dynamical systems theory but remain challenging to pick up from data (
  <a rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" href="#r59">59</a>
  <a href="#r60">*</a>–
  <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>). Here, we limit ourselves to the relatively intuitive class of resilience indicators related to slowing down. Slowing down will not happen before all transitions, and even if it does, it can be challenging to detect. On the other hand, the generic nature of this phenomenon implies a strikingly wide scope of potential applications. Indeed indicators of slowing down have been shown to signal the loss of resilience before critical transitions in systems ranging from populations of yeast (
  <a rid="r62" ref-type="bibr" href="#r62">62</a>, 
  <a rid="r63" ref-type="bibr" href="#r63">63</a>), zooplankton (
  <a rid="r64" ref-type="bibr" href="#r64">64</a>), and cyanobacteria (
  <a rid="r65" ref-type="bibr" href="#r65">65</a>) to complex systems such as the climate (
  <a rid="r66" ref-type="bibr" href="#r66">66</a>), tropical forests (
  <a rid="r67" ref-type="bibr" href="#r67">67</a>), and Neolithic societies (
  <a rid="r68" ref-type="bibr" href="#r68">68</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the framework of critical slowing down, the capacity of the system to bounce back upon perturbation can be reflected in three characteristics: variance, temporal autocorrelation (correlations between states on subsequent moments), and cross-correlation (between different elements of the system). We coin those indicators “dynamic indicators of resilience” (DIORs) to contrast them with the traditional static correlates of the condition or health of a system. While static indicators have long dominated medicine and animal science, technological advances now allow the assessing such DIORs. An extensive practical guide to the methods used for computing indicators of resilience is published elsewhere (
  <a rid="r69" ref-type="bibr" href="#r69">69</a>) linked to a website with freely available open-source software tools.
 </p>
</sec>
