<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resilience of the Subsystems</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One way to deal with the complexity of studying animals and humans is to view them as sets of subsystems linked through a web of fast (nervous system) and slower (autocrine, paracrine, endocrine systems) feedbacks. The links allow organs to work together to maintain vital parameters within safe limits (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>). Depending on the functional reserve (overcapacity) of organs and the effectiveness of their coordination, subsystems regulating critical factors such as temperature and body posture may run into disorder when challenged. Some subsystems may gradually lose their function. However, others are “tipping elements” (
  <a rid="r70" ref-type="bibr" href="#r70">70</a>, 
  <a rid="r71" ref-type="bibr" href="#r71">71</a>) in the sense that failure has a sharp, all-or-none character often associated with severe health problems (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810630115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>) (
  <a rid="r72" ref-type="bibr" href="#r72">72</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A well-known example of a tipping element in humans is blood pressure. Pressure drops if a person suddenly stands up, but this is quickly sensed and corrected by contraction of blood vessels and increased pumping by the heart. If such rapid regulation fails, blood pressure in the head drops, resulting in syncope (fainting) (
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>). There are also tipping elements that are not limited to our internal physiology. The mood system is an example. While depressed feelings are transient in most persons, for others stressful life events may trigger a state of clinical depression that involves disturbances in several other subsystems such as sleep and appetite and from which recovery can be difficult (
  <a rid="r73" ref-type="bibr" href="#r73">73</a>, 
  <a rid="r74" ref-type="bibr" href="#r74">74</a>). The profoundness and irreversibility of such depressed states are due in part to a set of reinforcing feedback mechanisms. For instance, a depressed person is likely to encounter negativity in relationships, take less physical exercise, make less social contact, and eat less healthily, all of which may deepen the depression (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="r75" ref-type="bibr" href="#r75">75</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The microbiomes on which humans and animals depend are complex ecosystems in their own right, tightly linked to the host system in intricate ways. Just like wetlands (
  <a rid="r76" ref-type="bibr" href="#r76">76</a>), forests (
  <a rid="r77" ref-type="bibr" href="#r77">77</a>) and coral reefs (
  <a rid="r78" ref-type="bibr" href="#r78">78</a>), such microbiomes may tip to an alternative state. A well-known example is acute rumen acidosis in beef cattle (
  <a rid="r79" ref-type="bibr" href="#r79">79</a>). If animals are fed a high level of rapidly digestible carbohydrates, fermentation increases, resulting in lower pH of the rumen (first stomach). This decrease can favor acid-tolerant bacteria that in turn produce more lactic acid that drives pH down even more, thereby potentially tipping the rumen into a highly acidic state, causing a severe crisis and potentially leading to death (
  <a rid="r79" ref-type="bibr" href="#r79">79</a>, 
  <a rid="r80" ref-type="bibr" href="#r80">80</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shifts between alternative states are typically triggered by stochastic events and therefore can never be accurately predicted. However, there are good reasons to expect that DIORs may be used to aid risk assessments. In the human health literature, there are already various lines of evidence that slowing down of recovery may signal reduced resilience for a range of subsystems (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810630115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
  </span>). For instance, subjects with a slow rise in blood pressure following exercise have a five times higher risk of ischemic stroke (
  <a rid="r81" ref-type="bibr" href="#r81">81</a>), and persons with a slow rate of recovery of blood pressure upon standing up are more likely to experience syncope (fainting) (
  <a rid="r82" ref-type="bibr" href="#r82">82</a>, 
  <a rid="r83" ref-type="bibr" href="#r83">83</a>). In psychiatry, slowness of mood change (reflected in elevated temporal correlation and variance of emotions) has been found to be indicative of the risk of falling into a clinical depression later (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="r84" ref-type="bibr" href="#r84">84</a>). In the elderly, a cohort study found an increase of correlation and variance of self-reported mood and physical well-being with (independently assessed) frailty (
  <a rid="r85" ref-type="bibr" href="#r85">85</a>), while in another group of elderly the DIORs assessed from the rapid dynamics of postural balance have been found to correlated with successful aging (
  <a rid="r86" ref-type="bibr" href="#r86">86</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
