<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0195" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.7.3.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fisheries management</div>
 <p id="par0680" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the absence of any institutional improvements, modelling suggests that increased levels of fishing effort on adult or 
  <span class="italic">jatka</span> populations could lead to a collapse of hilsa stocks in Bangladesh within one to two decades (
  <a rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0050">Bala et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0200">Fernandes et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0385">Mome and Arnason, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0485">Sharma, 2012</a>). Given the Government’s aim to increase hilsa production, and given industry trends, the marine fishery – both artisanal and industrial sectors – looks set to continue expanding (
  <a rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0180">DoF, 2002</a>). This expansion would require improvements in post-harvest technology and infrastructure, which could lead to overexploitation in the Bay of Bengal (
  <a rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0250">Habib et al., 2014</a>). Even with these improvements, it is unlikely that the export ban will be lifted, and so expansion of the export market is unlikely.
 </p>
 <p id="par0685" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total aquaculture production will almost certainly continue its upward trend, although the Government is mindful of maintaining its capture fisheries (
  <a rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0200">Fernandes et al., 2015</a>). Currently hilsa is not suitable for aquaculture. Even if substantial progress is made with economically viable hilsa cage culture, it would be unlikely to take much pressure off the wild capture hilsa fishery, given the social and cultural importance of and demand for hilsa. Recommendations have been made for effort restrictions on the artisanal fishery, but given the weak enforcement capacity these are probably much less realistic than the current spatial and temporal fishing bans (
  <a rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0385">Mome and Arnason, 2007</a>). If a major threat to 
  <span class="italic">jatka</span> and spawning adults is indeed overfishing, then improved monitoring and enforcement of current management rules could prevent collapse and potentially lead to increased hilsa abundance (
  <a rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0085">Bladon, 2016</a>). 
  <a rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0485">Sharma (2012)</a> pointed out that since intrinsic growth rates are high, hilsa should respond quickly to conservation interventions. Projections indicate that with more sustainable management, some climate change impacts on marine hilsa production could be mitigated, although it would not halt a long-term decline (
  <a rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0200">Fernandes et al., 2015</a>). However, in light of the projected development of the marine fishery, the efficacy of these rules, which are enforced largely inland, is uncertain. The proposed development of a regional hilsa fishery management programme should reduce the impacts of physical drivers or fishing pressure from adjacent countries, but it is ‘only an idea’ (M. Khan, Bangladesh Fisheries Research Institute, personal communication, 19th May 2014).
 </p>
 <p id="par0690" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the time of writing, a Conservation Trust Fund (CTF) was going through the ratification process, with the aim of generating financial resources for hilsa conservation (
  <a rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0340">Majumder et al., 2015b</a>). Although the proposed CTF does not conform to best practice standards in terms of governance structure, it could be used to finance increased coverage of the 
  <span class="italic">jatka</span> fisher rehabilitation programme and other management interventions, and pave the way for a more effective public-private partnership in the future (
  <a rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0085">Bladon, 2016</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
