<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="par0445" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An effective conservation or management intervention should have a measurable benefit, and thus requires the specification of an appropriate frame of reference against which it can be evaluated (
  <a rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0130">Bull et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0345">Maron et al., 2013</a>). A robust frame of reference should include a baseline that expresses conditions at a fixed point in time (whether a current or past reference state), and one or more counterfactuals (dynamic baselines or scenarios that use background rates of change to estimate potential states of a system in the absence of an intervention; 
  <a rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0140">Bull et al., 2016</a>). This baseline and counterfactual should capture ongoing trends in the ecological status of the intervention target (in fisheries management, this will usually be a specific species of interest); as well as the institutional, social, economic, and physical factors driving these trends; and the potential interactions and feedbacks between these factors (
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0205">Ferraro and Pattanayak, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0400">Nicholson et al., 2009</a>). Ideally, the development and evaluation of any intervention should consider the historical context within which it operates, using major events and system shifts to understand the main factors driving the dynamics of the social-ecological system (
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0430">Pooley, 2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="par0450" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior development of a counterfactual enables the rigorous measurement and attribution of impact, i.e. the difference between the outcome of the intervention and the estimated outcome in the absence of the intervention (
  <a rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0125">Bull, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0410">Pattanayak et al., 2010</a>). However, counterfactuals are rarely developed early in the intervention design process and, when they are, they often contain incorrect or vague assumptions (
  <a rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0245">Gurney et al., 2015</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0240">2014</a>; 
  <a rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0345">Maron et al., 2013</a>). A common reason for this is lack of data; counterfactuals are subject to numerous sources of uncertainty and it can be challenging to develop and validate projected trends when knowledge is poor (
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al., 2015</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0130">2014</a>). In fisheries management, uncertainties often limit the ability of policymakers to project trends and predict the effects of management interventions (
  <a rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0175">Davies et al., 2015</a>). These challenges are particularly pronounced in small-scale and developing-world fisheries, where data limitations mean even fixed baselines can be difficult to estimate (
  <a rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0145">Carruthers et al., 2014</a>). Useful counterfactuals can nevertheless be developed in these circumstances, as long as assumptions and limitations are acknowledged; and the process of developing them can highlight key areas of uncertainty which might hinder the development of effective interventions and limit evaluations (
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al., 2015</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0130">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="par0455" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al. (2015)</a> conceptualized and demonstrated a structure for developing a frame of reference in the context of terrestrial biodiversity offsetting. This paper uses the hilsa (
  <span class="italic">Tenualosa ilisha</span>) fishery in Bangladesh as a case study to demonstrate the wider utility of this approach in conservation, and its potential value for fisheries management, even when data are limited. The hilsa fishery is currently managed through a combination of regulatory measures, as well as a fisher rehabilitation programme that aims to incentivize compliance with these regulations (Section 
  <a rid="sec0120" ref-type="sec" href="#sec0120">3.5.1</a> and mmc2 in Supplementary material), but since no counterfactuals were developed before the introduction of these interventions, attempts to evaluate impact have lacked rigor (
  <a rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0095">Bladon et al., 2016</a>). The frame of reference developed in this paper combines qualitative and some quantitative analyses of secondary datasets and literature in a qualitative way to explore: a) patterns of social, economic, institutional and physical change relevant to the management of hilsa in Bangladesh; and b) ecological trends in the hilsa fishery. Two plausible qualitative counterfactuals are put forward, which could be used to evaluate potential future hilsa management and conservation interventions.
 </p>
</sec>
