<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6139246</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Animal Behavior</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Zoology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mass fluctuation in breeding females, males, and helpers of the Florida scrub-jay <italic>Aphelocoma coerulescens</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cucco</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><email>marco.cucco@uniupo.it</email><email>cucco@unipmn.it</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>Reed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>DISIT, University of Piemonte Orientale</institution>, <city>Alessandria</city>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Avian Ecology Program, Archbold Biological Station</institution>, <city>Venus</city>, <state>FL</state>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sorci</surname><given-names>Gabriele</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2018-09-13"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e5607</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2018-03-10"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2018-08-19"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2018 Cucco and Bowman</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cucco and Bowman</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/5607"/><abstract><p>Much evidence suggests that birds actively regulate their body mass reserves relative to their energy needs. Energy requirements during reproduction may differ in relation to sex-specific behavioural roles or, in the case of cooperative breeders, breeders relative to helpers. We measured body mass of free-living Florida scrub-jays throughout the nesting season by training them to land on an electronic balance. Jays exhibited a pattern of diurnal linear mass gain, from morning to afternoon. Day-to-day mass fluctuations, defined as the difference between mass on two consecutive days, were small (&#x0003e;80% were within 2 g, less than 3% of the mass of an adult bird) for all classes of jays: female breeders, male breeders and prebreeding helpers. The jays, which live in subtropical south-central Florida, did not exhibit changes in day-to-day mass fluctuation relative to weather or climate variables or calendar date. Day-to-day mass fluctuations influenced mass fluctuation between the following third and fourth days. These changes were usually compensatory, indicating that jays are able to regulate their body mass on a short-term basis, despite strong differences in their roles in reproduction. During reproduction, jays have a relatively predictable and abundant food supply, thus the appropriate strategy may be to maintain a stable body mass that balances some energy reserves against maintaining a low body mass for efficient flight, as required during reproduction.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Florida scrub-jay</kwd><kwd>Mass variation</kwd><kwd>Electronic balance</kwd><kwd>Helpers</kwd><kwd>Cooperative breeder</kwd><kwd>Reproduction</kwd><kwd>Parents and helpers</kwd><kwd>Daily</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>University of Piemonte Orientale</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Archbold Biological Station</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This research received financial support from the University of Piemonte Orientale to Marco Cucco, and from Archbold Biological Station. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Changes in body mass of birds should reflect a trade-off between costs and benefits of energy storage (reviewed in&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Witter &#x00026; Cuthill, 1993</xref>). Costs of energy storage include a reduction in flight efficiency and thereby increased risk of predation (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Lima, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Rogers, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Gosler, Greenwood &#x00026; Perrins, 1995</xref>); benefits include lower probabilities of starvation and thermal stress, as well as a higher likelihood to survive in case of diseases and their related periods of pathogen-induced anorexia (<xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Speakman, 2018</xref>). Much evidence suggests that birds actively regulate energy reserves relative to their needs (reviewed in&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Witter &#x00026; Cuthill, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Witter, Swaddle &#x00026; Cuthill, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Thomas, 2000</xref>), increasing reserves as food resources become more unpredictable (e.g., <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bednekoff &#x00026; Krebs, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Ekman &#x00026; Hake, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Hurly, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Ekman &#x00026; Lilliendahl, 1993</xref>; but see <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Acquarone et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Cucco et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Boon, Visser &#x00026; Daan, 1999</xref>) or predictably scarce, as when overnight temperatures decrease (e.g.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Ekman &#x00026; Hake, 1990</xref>). The ability of birds to regulate their body mass might be compromised during periods of elevated energy expenditure, as during the feeding of dependent young. The reproductive stress hypothesis invokes this idea to explain the mass loss during breeding (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Bryant, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Moreno, 1989</xref>). Alternately, it has been suggested that birds might deliberately maintain a lower mass to save energy during frequent flight as when flying back and forth while feeding young (flight adaptation hypothesis; <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Freed, 1981</xref>; <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Norberg, 1981</xref>).</p><p>In several studies body mass was positively correlated with fat reserves (see&#x000a0;<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Witter &#x00026; Cuthill, 1993</xref>), therefore fluctuations in body mass may provide insight into the trade-off between costs and benefits of fat storage on a daily basis. Most mass-regulation studies have looked at mass change within one day or change in body mass from before and after some experimental manipulation. We propose that the amplitude and pattern of day-to-day fluctuations in body mass over several days also can provide insight into management of energy reserves by birds.</p><p>Most mass-regulation studies have focused on temperate-zone birds that experience food shortages in winter (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Lehikoinen, 1987</xref>; except <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Acquarone et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Cucco et al., 2002</xref>, which looked at temperate zone birds in spring). Little is known about variation in body mass of birds living in tropical areas. Limited evidence suggests that under relatively uniform tropical conditions, seasonal variation in body mass of residents is small (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Ward, 1969</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Clark Jr, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Nwaogu et al., 2017</xref>). In subtropical Florida scrub-jays, body mass varies little throughout the year (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden, 1978</xref>). It may be important for birds living in a mild climate and experiencing relatively predictable foraging conditions to maintain a stable and low body mass that is optimal for flight efficiency, because conditions in which energy reserves are useful are infrequent.</p><p>We measured the body mass of free-living Florida scrub-jays during the breeding season in south central Florida, USA. Florida scrub-jays breed cooperatively and maintain permanent, all-purpose territories (<xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1996</xref>). A strict dominance hierarchy exists within scrub-jay families in which males dominate females and, within each sex, breeders dominate helpers (<xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1977</xref>). A recent study on long term mass variation for females and males breeders throughout the breeding season showed that both sexes lost mass during the period of nestling care, but not when feeding fledglings. Although post-fledging is a period of peak effort (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Brand &#x00026; Bowman, 2012</xref>) this is also the period during which contributions by helpers is at its highest, suggesting that their contributions might buffer mass losses by breeders. Despite this, few studies have examined mass loss in non-breeding helpers of cooperative species. We examined variation in day-to-day mass fluctuation relative to social class (female breeder, male breeder, or prebreeding helper), stage of the breeding cycle (building, incubation, dependent nestlings, dependent fledglings) and fortnight of the breeding season. We sought to examine whether mass fluctuations were greater in birds lower in the social dominance hierarchy (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Krams, 2002</xref>), and in the periods of higher energy demand, i.e.,&#x000a0;when nestling feeding occurrs (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Moreno, 1989</xref>). We tested for the ability of individuals to maintain a stable mass by looking at the effect of body mass fluctuation between two consecutive days on fluctuation between the following third and fourth day. Beside the energy demands of parental effort during reproduction, bird mass could be influenced by local factors, such as predator presence or food abundance (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Krams, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Krams, 2002</xref>), and by daily weather conditions (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Wiley &#x00026; Ridley, 2016</xref>). We do not quantify variation in predator abundance among different scrub-jay territories. Most of the study area is well managed using prescribed fire. We do know that predator abundance increases and jay survival and reproduction declines with time since fire, but virtually all of our birds occupy habitats that are earlier than this successional decline in demography. From this we assume that predation risk is relatively evenly spread among all the territories. To test for possible short-term effects of climatic stress on mass (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Lima, 1986</xref>), we also investigated whether day-to-day fluctuation in mass were related to any of six weather variables collected in the study area.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials &#x00026; Methods</title><p>This study was conducted at Archbold Biological Station in south-central Florida (27&#x000b0;10&#x02032;N 81&#x000b0;21&#x02032;W) as part of the long-term study of the Florida scrub-jay (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Mumme et al., 2015</xref>; Fitzpatrick &#x00026; Bowman; data collected under SFWS permit TE824723-9 issued to R. Bowman). Each jay in the population is uniquely marked with metal and plastic colour rings (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden, 1975</xref>), and all individuals are easily identifiable in the field. All birds are sexed genetically at only 11 days post-hatch, but later confirmed behaviourally; only females incubate and brood and give a characteristic &#x0201c;hiccup&#x0201d; vocalization (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1984</xref>). Prebreeding helpers, which remain in their natal territories for one or more years and help the breeders raise young, were distinguished from breeders by their histories and by behaviour, especially dominance-subordinance relationships (<xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1977</xref>). Data were collected during the breeding season of 1996, during which nesting began in mid-March, and almost all pairs had eggs by mid-April.</p><p>We collected mass measurements daily from 2 April to 9 June 1996. We placed electronic balances (accuracy 0.1 g) on the ground several tens of meters from the nest in numerous territories. The jays, which are remarkably tame to humans and accustomed to receiving peanut bits from us, were induced to perch on the balance by placing a few bits on the plate. The mass of peanuts provided daily to individual birds was less than 0.2 g, or about 0.3% of the mass of an adult jay (77 g; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1996</xref>). We used two methods for obtaining mass measurements. When a stable mass value was visible on the scale display, we read the scale directly. Otherwise, we inspected a series of mass values (approximately three per second) collected by a computer attached to the scale to find a stable mass value, defined as at least three consecutive identical values. All data were collected by the same observer (MC). We recorded only a single mass value for each visit of a bird to the scale. We obtained 438 mass values by reading the scale directly and another 494 from the attached computer for a total of 932 measurements (31 individuals: seven female breeders, 15 male breeders, and nine prebreeding helpers, sexes combined; mean = 30.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.6 measurements per bird). For all visits, the observer recorded the identity of the bird and the time the mass value was obtained.</p><p>We divided date into five fortnight intervals (15 days) from 1 April through 15 June. We divided the breeding cycle into four stages: nest building and egg laying (hereafter referred to as building), incubation, nestlings, and dependent fledglings. Mass measurements obtained from birds after the failure of their last nest were excluded. We utilized mixed-effect models to compare mass values between the fortnight periods, or between the breeding stages. In the models, fortnight or breeding stage was inserted as fixed factor, and jay identity was inserted as a random effect to account for repeated measures (<italic>lme4</italic> package for R vers. 3.4.3, (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2017</xref>). Post-hoc comparisons with Tukey correction were computed by the package <italic>multcomp</italic>, and group means for fixed factors with confidence intervals were obtained by the package <italic>lmerTest</italic>.</p><p>We define day-to-day mass fluctuation as the difference in mass between two consecutive days. We define the amplitude of mass fluctuation as the absolute value of the day-to-day mass fluctuation. We examined day-to-day mass fluctuation relative to date and breeding stage separately for three social classes, e.g.,&#x000a0;female and male breeders and prebreeding helpers. Of the 932 mass values, 595 represented paired measurements of the same individuals on successive days. Because mass values taken over a sequence of days are potentially more correlated than masses that are further away in time (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Ekstrom, 2012</xref>), we modelled the relationship between mass variation and elapsed days using mixed models with serial correlation in the <italic>nlme</italic> package (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Pinheiro et al., 2018</xref>). In the models, the jay identity was inserted as a random term, while social class and breeding stage were inserted as fixed terms. We modelled both linear and quadratic effects.</p><p>We examined the influence of weather on day-to-day fluctuation in body mass using air temperature and rainfall: (1) maximum temperature on the day of weighing, (2) mean maximum temperature on the day of weighing plus the previous day, (3) minimum temperature on the day of weighing, (4) mean minimum temperature on the day of weighing plus the previous day, (5) amount of rainfall on the day of weighing, and (6) amount of rainfall on the day of weighing plus the previous day. Temperature and rainfall values were collected <italic>in situ</italic> and obtained from Archbold meteorological archives. Relationship between mass fluctuation and weather variables was tested both individually for each variable and in a multiple regression analysis, followed by stepwise backward and forward selection. Multivariate models were compared using Akaike information criterium&#x02019;s values computed by the <italic>nlme</italic> package.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Within-day increase in body mass</title><p>We observed an increase in body mass daily from morning to afternoon in 27 individuals that were weighed twice in the same day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). The average increase was 0.205 &#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.117 g/h, with no significant differences between the three social classes (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,24</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.035, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.15). The mass increase during the examined central hours of the day was best explained by a linear increase (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.691, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), while the addition of a quadratic term was not significant (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.354, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.35).</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Mass change of Florida Scrub-Jays within a day. Circles represent female breeders; diamonds, male breeders; squares, helpers.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-g001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Mean body mass by fortnight and stage of the breeding cycle</title><p>The mean mass of jays was influenced by date and stage during the breeding season (<xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The mass of females was higher during the first fortnight and the first phase of the breeding stages, then mass values were significantly lower (mixed model ANOVA, five fortnights: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,177</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;52.4, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; three stages: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,162</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;73.1, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The mass of females was lower during the nestling stage (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.74, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, post hoc comparison with Tukey correction) and the fledgling stage (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.69, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) than during incubation. The mass of males and helpers showed significant differences in relation to date (five fortnights, males: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,511</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.9, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.003; helpers: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,244</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;36.1, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) and to breeding stage (three stages, males: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,439</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;38.2, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; helpers: <italic>F</italic><sub>2,206</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;38.6, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001). However, mass in males showed no trend to decrease with time; their mass was highest during the middle fortnight (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.38, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.006) and middle stage (nestlings: <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.89, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.004). The mass of helpers was highest in the third and fifth fortnights (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.02 and <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.19, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) and in the last two stages (nestlings, <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.77, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; fledglings, <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.15, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001).</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Day-to-day fluctuations in body mass of Florida Scrub-Jays relative to date.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Body mass (g, mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;s.e.) of Florida scrub-jays relative to fortnight and breeding stage.</title><p>Differences within a class among time periods are indicated by different superscript letters.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Period</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Helpers</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fortnight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">April 1&#x02013;15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.59<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.17<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.98<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">April 16&#x02013;30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.57<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.16<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.96<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 1&#x02013;15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.56<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.16<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.95<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">May 16&#x02013;31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.56<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.16<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.93<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">June 1&#x02013;15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.57<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.16<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.97<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breeding stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incubation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.16<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.15<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.02<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nestlings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.08<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.14<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.01<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fledglings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.06<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.15<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.01<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Variation and extent of day-to-day mass fluctuations in three classes of Florida Scrub-Jay. Black: females; white: males; grey: helpers.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-g003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Day-to-day fluctuations in mass</title><p>Most day-to-day fluctuations in mass were small, most (80%) within 2 g, which is less than 3% of the mass of an adult bird (77 g). The median fluctuation was 0.2 g with a range from &#x02212;4.0 to +6.4 g. The amplitude of mass fluctuations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>) did not vary by date (Mixed-effect model with serial correlation; Julian date: <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.703, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.48; quadratic term Julian<sup>2</sup>: <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.736, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.46; scrubjay identity inserted as a random effect). We found no difference in the mean day-to-day mass fluctuation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>) or the amplitude of mass fluctuations between females, males, and helpers (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,355</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.28, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.76; <italic>F</italic><sub>2,355</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.27, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.28; respectively).</p><p>Day-to-day mass fluctuation did not vary by fortnight for females (five fortnights: <italic>F</italic><sub>4,62</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.57, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.68) and helpers (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,80</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.70, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.59; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1">Supplemental Information 1</xref>). Day-to-day mass fluctuations varied for males (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,201</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.46, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05), but only the first (April 1&#x02013;15; <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i001.jpg"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\bar {x}=-0.58\pm 0.42$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-76"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> &#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>58</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>42</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> SD) and last (June 1&#x02013;15; <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i002.jpg"/><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$\bar {x}=0.60\pm 0.19$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-77"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> &#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b1;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>19</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> SD) fortnights were significantly different (Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparisons, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.03). The amplitude of mass fluctuations did not vary by fortnight for females (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,62</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.73, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.58), males (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,201</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.09, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.36) or helpers (<italic>F</italic><sub>4,80</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.17, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.33; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">Supplemental Information 2</xref>). Day-to-day mass fluctuation did not differ between breeding stages (four stages: <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.39, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.22), for females (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.41, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.09), males (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.56, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.31) or helpers (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,77</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.31, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.08; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-1">Supplemental Information 1</xref>). The amplitude of mass fluctuations did not vary by breeding stage for helpers (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,77</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.13, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.95). However, the amplitude of mass fluctuations was significantly higher for both females (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.32, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.04) and males (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,176</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.75, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.003) during the building stage than for any other breeding stage (Tukey&#x02019;s test, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 for all comparisons, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-2">Supplemental Information 2</xref>).</p><p>Day-to-day fluctuation in mass of a scrub-jay was positively associated with the maximum temperature on the first day of weighing, as well as with maximum temperature of the first and second days of weighing (<xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Day-to-day fluctuation in mass was not associated with minimum temperatures, nor with rainfall. A multivariate analysis of all climatic variables and period of the breeding cycle or class (female breeder, male breeder, or helper) resulted in a final model including only the two maximum temperature values. This result was consistent with findings from the single-factor correlations.</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Correlations between weather variables and day-to-day mass fluctuations in Florida scrub-jays.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Std. Error</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single weather variables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 day maximum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.002**</bold></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 days maximum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.972</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.049*</bold></td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 day minimum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0077</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.993</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 days minimum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 day rain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 days rain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0899</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stepwise complete model, AIC = 475.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.0743</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.702</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Julian date</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.247</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breeding stage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0026</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.566</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Status [helper]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Status [male]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.1315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1724</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.762</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref>1 day maximum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0683</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.747</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006**</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-2fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref>2 days maximum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0342</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0278</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.228</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 day minimum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0087</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 days minimum temperature</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.748</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 day rain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1728</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:1pc;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 days rain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0829</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.619</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-2fn1"><label>a</label><p>Stepwise selected variables (forward and backward selection) AIC = 461.9.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Regulation of body mass</title><p>Day-to-day mass fluctuation influenced mass fluctuation between the second and third consecutive days (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,236</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;22.2, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i003.jpg"/><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${r}_{\mathrm{adj.}}^{2}=0.082$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-106"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">adj.</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>082</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>). Usually the mass fluctuation from the second to third day was compensatory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4A</xref>); however, the influence had only an immediate, short-term effect, and disappeared by the fourth consecutive day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig.&#x000a0;4B</xref>; <italic>F</italic><sub>1,129</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.2, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.65, <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i004.jpg"/><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${r}_{\mathrm{adj.}}^{2}=-0.006$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-109"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">adj.</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>006</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>). The effect of day-to-day mass fluctuation on mass fluctuation between the second and third days was significant for all classes: female breeders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,44</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.81, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.008, <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i005.jpg"/><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${r}_{\mathrm{adj.}}^{2}=0.131$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-112"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">adj.</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>131</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>), male breeders (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,142</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.65, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.006, <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i006.jpg"/><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${r}_{\mathrm{adj.}}^{2}=0.044$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-115"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">adj.</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>044</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>), and helpers (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,45</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.46, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02, <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-i007.jpg"/><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${r}_{\mathrm{adj.}}^{2}=0.088$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-118"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">adj.</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>088</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>). Mixed-effect models with serial correlation showed that mass fluctuations over three-day series (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.658, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.51) did not differ from those over a four-day series (<italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.835, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.40); <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-3">Supplemental Information 3</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Relationship between mass fluctuation between two consecutive days and the second and third day (A) and the third and fourth day (B).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Temporal patterns of mass variation</title><p>Florida scrub-jays exhibited a pattern of diurnal mass gain frequently observed in other diurnal birds (reviewed in <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Clark Jr, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Haftorn, 1989</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Ekman &#x00026; Lilliendahl, 1993</xref>; but see <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Manu &#x00026; Cresswell, 2013</xref>). Birds weighed the least in the morning, presumable because of nighttime fasting, and gained weight throughout the day. Birds in all social classes&#x02014;female and male breeders and helpers&#x02014;exhibited this pattern, although only one helper was measured multiple times within a single day. The 0.205 g gain in mass per hr is great enough to warrant caution whenever mass measurements taken at different times of day are compared. In this study we accordingly inserted the time of the day in all models comparing mass measurements. Time-adjusted measurements of the same birds taken on consecutive days, possible in this study because individuals were trained to land on an electronic balance and therefore were measured without capture are a useful alternative to repeated measurements of birds at the same time of day, for example dawn or dusk, employed in many laboratory studies (e.g., <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Thomas, 2000</xref>), but very difficult to obtain and very stressful for free-living birds (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Carpenter, Paton &#x00026; Hixon, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">MacLeod et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">MacLeod &#x00026; Gosler, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Moiron, Mathot &#x00026; Dingemanse, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Breeding stage and calendar date (fortnights) affected the mass of female breeders. Females exhibited the common pattern in passerines of mass loss between the incubation and nestling stages (reviewed in <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Moreno, 1989</xref>). Mass during the fledgling stage also was lower than mass during the incubation stage. Male breeders did not show a tendency to decrease in mass during the breeding period. Their weigh fluctuated and showed some significant difference when comparing different stages or fortnights, but the differences were small (&#x0003c;1 g). The patterns of mass variation for female and male breeders in this study are consistent with mass data for an adjacent study population of the Florida scrub-jay collected over three years during the building, incubation and nestling stages (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Schoech, 1998</xref>) and to data collected in the same population in different years (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Brand &#x00026; Bowman, 2012</xref>). However, in these studies the patterns of mass variation in helpers were never examined in detail before. Helpers exhibited an increase of mass in the last part of the breeding period, which is somewhat surprising given their energetically demanding contributions to feeding of nestlings (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Stallcup &#x00026; Woolfenden, 1978</xref>) and fledglings (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">McGowan &#x00026; Woolfenden, 1990</xref>). This suggests helpers may be employing a bet hedging strategy by providing help to their parents thereby increasing their indirect fitness, yet at the same time attempting to maintain or even gain mass thereby not potentially reducing their longer-term survival prospects. Several studies documented costs associated with helping in cooperative breeders (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Reyer, 1984</xref>; <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Heinsohn &#x00026; Cockburn, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">MacLeod &#x00026; Clutton-Brock, 2015</xref>). Florida scrub-jay helpers might be attempting to minimizing these costs to protect their long-term direct fitness potential by surviving to become breeders.</p></sec><sec><title>Day-to-day fluctuations in mass</title><p>Day-to-day fluctuations in mass might be stochastic variation or might reflect difficulty in maintaining body mass, such as during unfavorable foraging conditions, cold weather, or a period of elevated energy expenditure. Consistent with the relative stability of Florida scrub-jays&#x02019; average mass during this study, most day-to-day fluctuations in mass were small, and overall did not vary between male breeders, female breeders and helpers despite their different breeding-season activities. Mass fluctuations varied significantly relative to season only for male breeders, and only between two fortnights, but these differences were small (&#x02212;0.58 g during the first fortnight compared to 0.60 g during the last fortnight) and were not reflected by differences in average mass of males between fortnights. Also, the amplitude of mass fluctuations did not vary by fortnight.</p><p>In Florida scrub-jays, female breeders perform all incubating and brooding, but feed nestlings at a relatively low rate compared to the male breeder. Male breeders feed the female during incubation and brooding, and feed nestlings at a high rate. Both males and females feed fledglings at an increasing rate that peaks about two weeks post-fledging (<xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Stallcup &#x00026; Woolfenden, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">McGowan &#x00026; Woolfenden, 1990</xref>). We found that despite the different reproductive activities of Florida scrub-jays, day-to-day mass fluctuations did not differ among social classes in different stages of the breeding cycle. The amplitude of these fluctuations also did not differ between classes. However, the amplitude of mass fluctuations was higher for female and male breeders during the building stage than during any other stage. The building stage encompassed the prelaying period, so the large amplitude of mass fluctuations for females likely reflects mass gain during the building stage. The average amplitude and fluctuation are equal for this stage, indicating that all fluctuation measurements were positive. The larger amplitude for males during the building stage is more difficult to explain. The average fluctuation for this stage was smaller than the average amplitude, though it was still positive, indicating that day-to-day mass gains were partly offset by losses. No differences in amplitude existed for helpers.</p><p>Weather variables explained less than 2% of the total variation in day-to-day mass fluctuation. The lack of effect of daily minimum temperature on mass fluctuation suggests that during the study period the nocturnal energy expenditure of jays was not influenced by nighttime temperature. It is not surprising that Florida scrub-jays in the subtropical climate of south-central Florida, particularly in the spring months of April, May and June, would not exhibit fat storage patterns observed in birds that experience colder temperatures (e.g., <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Rogers, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Rogers &#x00026; Smith, 1993</xref>; review in <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Witter &#x00026; Cuthill, 1993</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Regulation of body mass</title><p>Day-to-day mass fluctuation explained 8% of the variation in mass on the third consecutive day. Female breeders, male breeders and helpers exhibited similar short-term mass regulation, with the effect strongest in female breeders (13% of variation explained). Small mass fluctuations over two days, combined with the ability to compensate for these fluctuations on the third day, indicate that during the breeding season scrub-jays are able to regulate their body mass on a short-term basis. A number of studies have found differences in mass regulation strategies between dominant and subordinate birds (<xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Krams, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Krams, 2002</xref>). Theory predicts that subordinates should carry greater fat reserves than dominants (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Clark &#x00026; Ekman, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Gosler, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Ratikainen &#x00026; Wright, 2013</xref>) as insurance against poor foraging conditions, during which dominants would exercise their priority access to food. Some studies have found that the body mass of subordinates varies less than that of dominants, likely because smaller adjustments are needed to subordinates&#x02019; already larger reserves (in Willow Tits <italic>Parus montanus</italic>, <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Ekman &#x00026; Lilliendahl, 1993</xref>; Great Tits <italic>Parus major,</italic>
<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Gosler, 1996</xref>; and Greenfinches <italic>Carduelis chloris</italic>, <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Hake, 1996</xref>; but the opposite result in Coal Tits <italic>Parus ater,</italic>
<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Polo &#x00026; Bautista, 2002</xref>). In contrast, in Florida scrub-jays, although helpers are subordinate to male breeders, they exhibited similar day-to-day mass fluctuations, amplitude of fluctuations and short-term mass regulation. These previous studies were performed on dominance-structured winter flocks of genetically unrelated individuals in which dominants were able to monopolize food resources, leading to different strategies. In Florida scrub-jays, dominant and subordinate birds within groups are closely related. Jays tend to forage individually primarily on insects and, to a lesser extent, small reptiles, amphibians, and mammals all well hidden in the vegetation. This reduces the chance for dominant birds to monopolize food. In fall and winter, each jay feeds primarily on acorns, cached during the later summer. Each jay scatter-hoards 6-7000 individual acorns (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">DeGange et al., 1989</xref>). When caching, jays adopt behaviors that appear to minimize kelptoparsitism by dominant jays, suggesting that it may happen but is minimized within groups (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Toomey, Bowman &#x00026; Woolfenden, 2007</xref>). Thus year-round feeding patterns do not favor despotic control of food. Since breeder and helper jays both contribute to rearing young, it is not surprising that in this species, mass regulation strategies did not differ by social status.</p><p>Because the jays rarely experience severe climate or food shortages in spring (<xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick, 1996</xref>), a strategy of fattening may be more of a disadvantage (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Lima, 1986</xref>) than an advantage. Instead, for this species, the appropriate strategy seems to be maintain a stable body mass that effectively balance the need to maintain some energy reserves against the need for efficient flight and foraging, as required during reproduction.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The mechanism for maintaining a stable body mass in Florida scrub-jays appears to operate on a daily basis, with birds experiencing a mass gain or loss over two consecutive days making a compensatory adjustment during the third day. Future studies could investigate whether or not scrub-jays are able to maintain such a short-term regulation of body mass in other seasons of the year, if this regulation can be supported in poor quality territories (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Mumme et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Fitzpatrick &#x00026; Bowman, 2016</xref>) and in territories were food is less predictable (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Schoech, Bowman &#x00026; Reynolds, 2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Supplemental material 1</title><p>Average day-to-day mass fluctuation (g, mean &#x000b1;sd) ( <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;number of independent data couplets measured during each fortnight or stage) of Florida scrub-jays relative to fortnight and breeding stage. Differences within each class among time periods are indicated by different superscript letter.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Supplemental material 2</title><p>Average amplitude of day-to-day mass fluctuation (g, mean &#x000b1;&#x000a0;sd) (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;number of independent data couplets measured during each fortnight or stage) of Florida Scrub-Jays relative to fortnight and breeding stage. No significant differences existed between females, males, and helpers, for fortnight or for breeding stage; nor did differences exist within each sex among fortnights or stage.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/supp-3</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 3</label><caption><title>Supplemental material 3</title><p>Difference in mass along 3-days-long series, and 4-days-long series. Mixed models with serial correlation. The scrubjay identity was inserted as a random effect. Breeding stage and breeding class were inserted as fixed effects, and time elapsed between measures as a serial variable.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/supp-4</object-id><label>Data S1</label><caption><title>Raw data on mass increase within the same day</title><p>Florida scrub jay mass variation within the same day.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-s004.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.5607/supp-5</object-id><label>Data S2</label><caption><title>Raw data on each individual daily mass</title><p>Mass values for individual Florida scrub jays.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-06-5607-s005.txt"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We dedicate this paper to the memory of Glen E. Woolfenden (1930-2007). Glen began the long-term study of Florida scrub-jays in 1969 and we were privileged to have worked on and continue the research.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Marco Cucco</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Reed Bowman</xref> analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft, managed long-term marked population.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Field Study Permissions</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied relating to field study approvals (i.e., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>Data were collected under USFWS permit TE824723-9 issued to R. Bowman.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-2"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>The raw data are provided in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplemental-information">Supplemental Files</xref>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Acquarone et&#x000a0;al. (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Acquarone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cucco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li&#x000a0;Cauli</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacarne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Effects of food abundance and predictability on body condition and health parameters: experimental tests with the Hooded Crow</article-title><source>Ibis</source><volume>144</volume><elocation-id>E155&#x02013;E163</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Bednekoff &#x00026; Krebs (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bednekoff</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Great tit fat reserves: effects of changing and unpredictable feeding day length</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2390009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Boon, Visser &#x00026; Daan (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Daan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Feeding and growth of Japanese quail (<italic>Coturnix c. japonica</italic>) chicks with unpredictable food access</article-title><source>Netherlands Journal of Zoology</source><volume>49</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/156854299X00164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Brand &#x00026; Bowman (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Body mass variation in breeding Florida scrub-jays</article-title><source>Journal of Field Ornithology</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1557-9263.2012.00374.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Bryant (1979)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year><article-title>Reproductive costs in the house martin (<italic>Delichon urbica</italic>)</article-title><source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Carpenter, Paton &#x00026; Hixon (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hixon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1983</year><article-title>Weight gain and adjustment of feeding territory size in migrant hummingbirds</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><volume>80</volume><fpage>7259</fpage><lpage>7263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16593394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Clark&#x000a0;Jr (1979)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark&#x000a0;Jr</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year><article-title>Body weights of birds: a review</article-title><source>The Condor</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1367288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Clark &#x00026; Ekman (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Dominant and subordinate fattening strategies&#x02014;a dynamic game</article-title><source>Oikos</source><volume>72</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3546222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Cucco et&#x000a0;al. (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cucco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottonelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raviola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malacarne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Variations of body mass and imMune function in response to food unpredictability in magpies</article-title><source>Acta Oecologica</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1146-609X(02)01154-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>DeGange et&#x000a0;al. (1989)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeGange</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Layne</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Acorn harvesting by Florida Scrub Jays</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>70</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1937539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Ekman &#x00026; Hake (1990)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Monitoring starvation risk: adjustments of body reserves in greenfinches (<italic>Carduelis chloris</italic> L.) During periods of unpredictable foraging success</article-title><source>Behavioural Ecology Sociobiology</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/beheco/1.1.62</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Ekman &#x00026; Lilliendahl (1993)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilliendahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Using priority to food access: fattening strategies in dominance-structured willow tit (<italic>Parus montanus</italic>) flocks</article-title><source>Behavioural Ecology</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/beheco/4.3.232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Ekstrom (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ekstrom</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><source>The R primer</source><publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Fitzpatrick &#x00026; Bowman (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Florida scrub-jay: oversized territories and group defense in a fire-maintained habitat</article-title><source>Cooperative breeding in vertebrates: studies of ecology, evolution, and behavior</source><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Freed (1981)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>Loss of mass in breeding wrens: stress or adaptation?</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1937282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Gosler (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gosler</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Environmental and social determinants of winter fat storage in the great tit <italic>Parus major</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/5695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Gosler, Greenwood &#x00026; Perrins (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gosler</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JJD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrins</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Predation risk and the cost of being fat</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>377</volume><fpage>621</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/377621a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Haftorn (1989)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haftorn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Seasonal and diurnal body weight variations in titmice, based on analyses of individual birds</article-title><source>Wilson Bulletin</source><volume>101</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Hake (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Fattening strategies in dominance-structured greenfinch (<italic>Carduelis chloris</italic>) flocks in winter</article-title><source>Behavioural Ecology Sociobiology</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002650050268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Heinsohn &#x00026; Cockburn (1994)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinsohn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cockburn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1994</year><article-title>Helping is costly to young birds in cooperatively breeding white-winged choughs</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B</source><volume>256</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.1994.0083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Hurly (1992)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurly</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Energetic reserves of marsh tits (<italic>Parus palustris</italic>): food and fat storage in response to variable food supply</article-title><source>Behavioural Ecology</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/beheco/3.2.181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Krams (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krams</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Length of feeding day and body weight of Great Tits in a single- and a two-predator environment</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002650000214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Krams (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krams</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Mass-dependent take-off ability in winterng great tits (<italic>Parus major</italic>): comparison of top-ranked adult males and subordinate juvenile females</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00265-002-0452-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Lehikoinen (1987)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehikoinen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Seasonality of the daily weight cycle in wintering passerines and its consequences</article-title><source>Ornis Scandinavica</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3676769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Lima (1986)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>Predation risk and unpredictable feeding conditions: determinants of body mass in wintering birds</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>67</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1938580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>MacLeod et&#x000a0;al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Body mass change strategies in blackbirds <italic>Turdus merula</italic>: the starvation-predation risk trade-off</article-title><source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2656.2005.00923.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>MacLeod &#x00026; Clutton-Brock (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clutton-Brock</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Low costs of allonursing in meerkats: mitigation by behavioral change?</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/beheco/aru205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>MacLeod &#x00026; Gosler (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacLeod</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosler</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Capture and mass change: perceived predation risk or interrupted foraging</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><volume>71</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2005.07.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Manu &#x00026; Cresswell (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Diurnal patterns of mass gain in tropical granivores suggest avoidance of high midday temperatures during foraging, rather than the starvation&#x02013;predation risk trade-off</article-title><source>Ostrich</source><volume>84</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2989/00306525.2013.821683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>McGowan &#x00026; Woolfenden (1990)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGowan</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year><article-title>Contributions to fledgling feeding in the Florida Scrub Jay</article-title><source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Moiron, Mathot &#x00026; Dingemanse (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moiron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathot</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingemanse</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>To eat and not be eaten: diurnal mass gain and foraging strategies in wintering great tits</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B</source><volume>285</volume><fpage>20172868</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29540518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Moreno (1989)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Strategies of mass change in breeding birds</article-title><source>Biological Journal of the Linnean Society</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8312.1989.tb01907.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Mumme et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mumme</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruett</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Natal territory size, group size, and body mass affect lifetime fitness in the cooperatively breeding Florida scrub-jay</article-title><source>Auk</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1642/AUK-14-258.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Norberg (1981)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>Temporary weight decrease in breeding birds may result in more fledged young</article-title><source>American Naturalist</source><volume>118</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/283874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Nwaogu et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nwaogu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tieleman</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Breeding limits foraging time: evidence of interrupted foraging response from body mass variation in a tropical environment</article-title><source>Journal of Avian Biology</source><volume>48</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jav.01132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Pinheiro et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>DebRoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><collab>R&#x000a0;Core&#x000a0;Team</collab></person-group><year>2018</year><data-title>nlme: linear and nonlinear mixed effects models</data-title><version designator="3.1-137">R package version 3.1-137</version><uri xlink:href="https://CRANR-project.org/package=nlme">https://CRANR-project.org/package=nlme</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Polo &#x00026; Bautista (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Daily body mass regulation in dominance-structured coal tit (<italic>Parus ater</italic>) flocks in response to variable food access: a laboratory study</article-title><source>Behavioural Ecology</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/beheco/13.5.696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>R&#x000a0;Development Core&#x000a0;Team (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R&#x000a0;Development Core&#x000a0;Team</collab></person-group><year>2017</year><data-title>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</data-title><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc><uri xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Ratikainen &#x00026; Wright (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ratikainen</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Adaptive management of body mass by Siberian jays</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><volume>85</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2012.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Reyer (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reyer</surname><given-names>H-U</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><article-title>Investment and relatedness: a cost/benefit analysis of breeding and helping in the pied kingfisher (<italic>Ceryle rudis</italic>)</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-3472(84)80233-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Rogers (1987)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><article-title>Predation risk and fasting capacity: do wintering birds maintain optimal body mass?</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>68</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1938377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Rogers &#x00026; Smith (1993)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JNM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Life-history theory in the nonbreeding period: trade-offs in avian fat reserves?</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>74</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1939303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Schoech (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoech</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><article-title>Physiology of helping in Florida scrub-jays</article-title><source>American Scientist</source><volume>86</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1511/1998.17.916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Schoech, Bowman &#x00026; Reynolds (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoech</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Food supplementation and possible mechanisms underlying early breeding in the Florida scrub-jay (<italic>Aphelocoma coerulescens</italic>)</article-title><source>Hormones and Behavior</source><volume>46</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2004.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15555498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Speakman (2018)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speakman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>The evolution of body fatness: trading off disease and predation risk</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source><volume>221</volume><comment>Article UNSP jeb167254</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.167254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Stallcup &#x00026; Woolfenden (1978)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stallcup</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>Family status and contributions to breeding by Florida scrub jays</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>1144</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-3472(78)90104-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Thomas (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Strategic diel regulation of body mass in European robins</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1999.1360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10792933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Toomey, Bowman &#x00026; Woolfenden (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toomey</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>The effects of social context on the food-caching behavior of Florida Scrub-Jays (<italic>Aphelocoma coerulescens</italic>)</article-title><source>Ethology</source><volume>113</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0310.2007.01366.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Ward (1969)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1969</year><article-title>Seasonal and diurnal changes in the fat content of an equatorial bird</article-title><source>Physiological Zoology</source><volume>42</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/physzool.42.1.30152469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Wiley &#x00026; Ridley (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The effects of temperature on offspring provisioning in a cooperative breeder</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><volume>117</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anbehav.2016.05.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Witter &#x00026; Cuthill (1993)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witter</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuthill</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>The ecological costs of avian fat storage</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B</source><volume>340</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1993.0050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Witter, Swaddle &#x00026; Cuthill (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witter</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaddle</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuthill</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Periodic food availability and strategic regulation of body mass in the European Starling, <italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic></article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2390146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Woolfenden (1975)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1975</year><article-title>Florida Scrub Jay helpers at the nest</article-title><source>Auk</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/4084414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Woolfenden (1978)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>Growth and survival of young Florida scrub jays</article-title><source>Wilson Bulletin</source><volume>90</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick (1977)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1977</year><article-title>Dominance in the Florida Scrub Jay</article-title><source>The Condor</source><volume>79</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1367524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1984</year><source>The Florida Scrub Jay: demography of a cooperative-breeding bird</source><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Woolfenden &#x00026; Fitzpatrick (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolfenden</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Florida scrub-jay (<italic>Aphelocoma coerulescens</italic>)</article-title><source>The birds of North America, (228)</source><comment>Philadelphia: The Academy of Natural Sciences, and Washington, D.C.: The American Ornithologists&#x02019; Union</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>