<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supporting Information</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s001" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S1 Fig</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Map of Trask Watershed, OR, USA, with Photos of Field Sites.</div>
   <p>Sub-basin of Pothole Creek is purple, Gus Creek is light blue, Upper Mainstem Trask is yellow, and Rock Creek is brown. Modeled stream reaches representing actual field sites are orange.</p>
   <p>(PNG)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s001.png" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s002" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S2 Fig</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Summer Biomass of Trout over Time.</div>
   <p>Mean total summer biomass (g) from five replicate simulations for all trout ages grouped together over time for each scenario of forest harvest (FH), climate change (CC), and their combined effects (FH+CC) compared to baseline, in Gus Creek, Pothole Creek, Rock Creek, and Upper Mainstem (UM). Scenarios include manipulations of stream temperature and regimes (see 
    <a rid="sec002" ref-type="sec" href="#sec002">methods</a> narrative for detail). Each data point represents one year of the simulation run. Line represents 1:1 ratio between the scenario and baseline. Only significant comparisons (P &lt; 0.05) are shown with values that correspond to pseudomedian of differences in biomass (g) between scenario and baseline.
   </p>
   <p>(JPG)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s002.jpg" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s003" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S1 File</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">This file contains input files for inSTREAM and output files used to generate Figures and tables.</div>
   <p>Calibration calculations and values for environmental regimes can be found in [
    <a rid="pone.0135334.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref033">33</a>].
   </p>
   <p>(XLSX)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s003.xlsx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s004" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S1 Table</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Characteristics of Study Streams.</div>
   <p>Description of environmental (ENVR) regimes, instream habitat features, and calibration values for Gus Creek, Pothole Creek, Rock Creek, and Upper Mainstem Trask (UM). ENVR regimes display average values with standard deviation values in parentheses for data collected from March 2007 to September 2011. Winter is January and February and summer is July and August. Distance to hiding cover, availability of velocity shelter, spawning gravel, velocity by season, and depth by season are averaged values (total/no. of cells in stream). Higher distance to hiding cover values represent less overall hiding cover availability. Velocity shelter and spawning gravel are each estimated as a percentage of cell area with that characteristic.</p>
   <p>(DOCX)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s004.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s005" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S2 Table</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Trends of Differences in Summer Biomass of Trout between Scenarios and Baseline.</div>
   <p>Trends of differences in magnitude of total biomass (g) of trout in summer for forest harvest (FH), climate change (CC), and combined (FH + CC) scenarios compared to baseline in modeled streams, including Gus Creek, Pothole Creek, Rock Creek, and Upper Mainstem (UM). Annual trends in total biomass (g/decade) were averaged across five replicate simulations. They were analyzed using the Mann-Kendall test and p-values were corrected for serial correlation for 1
    <span class="sup">st</span> harvest, 2
    <span class="sup">nd</span> harvest, and the entire study period. Scenarios include manipulations of stream temperature and flow regimes (see 
    <a rid="sec002" ref-type="sec" href="#sec002">Methods</a> for details). Significant p-values in bold (alpha ≤ 0.05) represent increasing or decreasing trends of magnitude in comparison to baseline. Magnitude is Sen slope (g/decade) over time.
   </p>
   <p>(DOCX)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s005.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s006" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S3 Table</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Pairwise Comparisons of Summer Biomass of Trout.</div>
   <p>Pairwise comparisons of total summer biomass (g) of trout for baseline, forest harvest (FH), climate change (CC), and combined (FH + CC) scenarios in Gus Creek, Pothole Creek, Rock Creek, and Upper Mainstem (UM) for the entire study period. Individual influences from stream temperature and flow were considered for single scenarios of FH and CC. Scenarios include manipulations of stream temperature and flow regimes (see 
    <a rid="sec002" ref-type="sec" href="#sec002">Methods</a> for details). Values of summer biomass by year were averaged for five replicate simulations and were analyzed using Wilcoxon signed rank test (V) with continuity correction resulting in a pseudomedian of difference between group 1 and group 2 (Δ). Significant p-values in bold (alpha ≤ 0.05).
   </p>
   <p>(DOCX)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s006.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s007" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S4 Table</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Trends in Fry Emergence of Trout across Scenarios.</div>
   <p>Median DOY of fry emergence of trout for forest harvest (FH), climate change (CC), and combined (FH + CC) scenarios in four modeled streams, including Gus Creek, Pothole Creek, Rock Creek, and Upper Mainstem (UM). Annual trends in fry emergence (days/decade) were averages of the five replicate simulations and were analyzed using the Mann-Kendall test and p-values were corrected for serial correlation for dates of the 1
    <span class="sup">st</span> harvest, 2
    <span class="sup">nd</span> harvest, and the entire study period. Scenarios include manipulations of stream temperature and flow regimes (see 
    <a rid="sec002" ref-type="sec" href="#sec002">Methods</a> for details). Significant p-values in bold (alpha ≤ 0.05) represent increasing or decreasing trends. Magnitude is the Sen slope (days/decade) over time.
   </p>
   <p>(DOCX)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s007.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="pone.0135334.s008" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">S5 Table</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Pairwise Comparisons of Winter Survival, Growth, and Biomass by Trout Age Class.</div>
   <p>Pairwise comparisons of winter survival (proportion of total in that age class that survive), growth (cm/month), and biomass (g) for three age classes (ages 1, 2, 3+) of trout in relation to baseline for forest harvest (FH), climate change (CC), and combined (FH + CC) scenarios in four modeled streams over 63 years. Streams include Gus Creek, Pothole Creek, Rock Creek, and Upper Mainstem (UM). Scenarios include manipulations of stream temperature and flow regimes (see 
    <a rid="sec002" ref-type="sec" href="#sec002">methods</a> for detail). The magnitude of change for each scenario relative to baseline is an average of five replicate simulations and is calculated as: [(median scenario − median baseline)/median baseline]*100. Winter is January and February. Age classes during winter were restricted to ages 1+ because the model assigns an additional year to each trout on January 1
    <span class="sup">st</span> every year, thus there are no age 0 trout in winter. Responses were analyzed using Kruskal-Wallis one-way analysis of variance on ranks. Negative values indicate that the values for the response of the scenario of interest is lower than baseline values for that stream and positive values indicate that it is higher than baseline. Only significant responses are shown (alpha ≤ 0.05).
   </p>
   <p>(DOCX)</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.s008.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
