<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although most studies that have considered the combined effects of land use and climate change have focused on range shifts at the edges of species distributions [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref003">3</a>], it is likely that many responses to both land use and climate change occur well within these edges, with changes in population demography that precede detectable changes in species distributions [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref004">4</a>]. Although several studies have addressed how population demography is affected by climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref005">5</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref008">8</a>], land use [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref009">9</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref011">11</a>], or their combined effects [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref012">12</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref013">13</a>], few studies have focused on disentangling the underlying mechanisms explaining these changes [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref005">5</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref008">8</a>]. Within the range of a species, it is reasonable to expect increased variation in local environmental conditions initially, with more homogeneous and coherent changes manifested as the effects of land use and climate change intensify [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref014">14</a>]. Accordingly, local variability in environmental conditions may play a key role for understanding emerging responses to land use and climate change, but it has yet to be fully explored [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref015">15</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref018">18</a>]. Local environmental conditions create unique microclimates or “idiosyncrasies of place” where individuals and populations of species experience change [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref017">17</a>]. In the context of land use and climate change, an improved understanding of such local variability can provide critical insights into processes behind observed changes in species distribution and abundance [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref019">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we consider local variability in the vulnerability of stream-living trout to changes in temperature and flow linked to forest harvest and climate change. We used an individual-based model of Coastal Cutthroat Trout (
  <span class="italic">Oncorhynchus clarkii clarkii)</span> population dynamics [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref021">21</a>] to model the separate and combined effects of stream temperature and flow under forest harvest and climate change scenarios on trout responses of biomass, survival, growth, and timing of fry emergence in four neighboring streams located within the same headwater catchment (
  <a rid="pone.0135334.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0135334.g001">Fig 1</a>). We parameterized the model with multi-year, daily measurements of stream temperature, flow, and turbidity (2007–2011), and field measurements of both instream habitat structure and three years of annual trout population estimates. The forest harvest scenario encompassed two harvests leading to increased stream temperature in summer [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref022">22</a>], increased summer flows, and increased magnitudes of storm events [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref023">23</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref024">24</a>] for 1–2 decades following each simulated harvest [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref025">25</a>]. The climate change scenario involved increasing stream temperature year-round [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref026">26</a>] and decreasing flow during fall and winter [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref027">27</a>]. The combined scenario captured the simultaneous effects of forest harvest and climate change, allowing us to evaluate the interactive effects of these changes on the dynamics of local populations.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0135334.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0135334.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Representation of Key Processes in inSTREAM.</div>
   <p>We highlight how the daily time series inputs of stream temperature, flow, and turbidity drive individual growth and survival and hence population dynamics including responses of fry emergence and biomass. A more detailed explanation of inSTREAM can be found in [
    <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>–
    <a rid="pone.0135334.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref021">21</a>].
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0135334.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
