<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most visible response of trout to change was a phenology metric</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most visible and consistent response from our simulations was earlier fry emergence driven by climate change (
  <a rid="pone.0135334.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0135334.g004">Fig 4</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s007">S4 Table</a>), whereas demographic responses of survival, growth, or biomass were not detectable and inconsistent across scenarios and streams (
  <a rid="pone.0135334.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0135334.g002">Fig 2</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s002">S2 Fig</a>). Under the climate change and combined scenarios, there were consistent trends toward earlier fry emergence for all streams over time. Over the entire study period, median timing of fry emergence was earlier by 4 to 7 days/decade for climate change, but it was earlier by only 4 to 5 days days/decade for the combined scenario due to the trend towards later emergence generally observed with forest harvest. Early fry emergence under the climate change scenario largely results from warmer stream temperature that accelerates the development of eggs across streams over time. Similarly, a lab study shows that fry emergence can be delayed due to increased temporal variance in temperature regimes [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref070">70</a>]. Collectively, we highlight the importance of magnitude and variability of temperature regimes on emergence. Studies of salmonid fishes in other systems have shown that earlier emergence timing can negatively influence survival of subsequent life stages [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref071">71</a>]. In general, changes in phenology are a reliable indicator of climate change on diverse taxa [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref061">61</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref072">72</a>]. Although we find a coherent change in fry emergence across streams for the climate change scenario, this does not consistently translate into changes in trends of trout biomass or other demographic responses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Demographic responses of survival, growth, or biomass depended on scenarios and streams (
  <a rid="pone.0135334.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0135334.g002">Fig 2</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s002">S2 Fig</a>). Most of the changes in trout demography occurred for climate change and combined scenarios, rather than for forest harvest in both summer and winter (
  <a rid="pone.0135334.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0135334.t001">Table 1</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s008">S5 Table</a>). Overall, survival and growth of age-0 and age-1 trout frequently responded to changes linked to forest harvest and climate change more than older age classes. Age-0 trout exhibited increased survival over summer for all scenarios because earlier fry emergence (
  <a rid="pone.0135334.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0135334.g004">Fig 4</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0135334.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s006">S3 Table</a>) increased recruitment, with the exception of Upper Mainstem which is similar to an observational study [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref071">71</a>]. Age-0 trout exhibited increased growth over summer in the climate change and combined scenarios compared to baseline (except for Upper Mainstem and Rock Creek). Age-0 trout showed increased biomass for climate change and combined scenarios compared to baseline (except Gus Creek under the combined scenario). During both seasons, age-1 trout showed mixed responses in growth and biomass for climate change and combined scenarios compared to baseline across streams. In contrast, biomass responded more uniformly across all age classes. Age-2 and age-3+ trout most consistently showed reductions in biomass for climate change and combined scenarios compared to baseline across streams. These idiosyncratic responses for demography may have been driven by the complex interplay of underlying factors, including density-dependence, specific requirements of environmental conditions at each age class (habitat), and variability in demography and the environment [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref073">73</a>]. In our simulations, we held most variables constant and equal across streams, except for local differences in physical habitat conditions and variability in environmental regimes among streams highlighting habitat (depth and area of available habitat) as the key driver [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref033">33</a>]. The lack of coherence among responses of demography of trout has practical consequences because biological responses commonly quantified in field studies (survival, growth, and biomass) may not be able to consistently indicate the effects of land use and climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref074">74</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
