<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated population biomass (g), growth (cm/month; fork length), and survival (proportion of total that survived in each age class) by season each year over the five replicate model runs. To provide an overall view of differences among streams and scenarios, we evaluated summer and winter responses of median biomass, growth, and survival for each age class for each scenario (baseline, forest harvest, climate change, and combined) across all 63 simulation years using non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis one-way analysis of variance on ranks. In cases of statistically significant differences (alpha ≤ 0.05) indicated by these analyses, we evaluated pairwise comparisons among the four scenarios using a non-parametric Tukey’s test on ranks. We focused these tests on deviations of responses from a stream’s specific baseline scenario to responses observed for that stream related to forest harvest, climate change, and combined scenarios (i.e., baseline vs. other scenarios). When the scenario for a stream deviated significantly from its own baseline, we also examined the direction and magnitude of the observed differences.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual trends of both the median date of fry emergence and difference in magnitude of biomass of scenario compared to baseline for each stream were evaluated using the Mann-Kendall test [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref041">41</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref042">42</a>]. This rank-based test is robust to outliers and non-linear trends [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref043">43</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref044">44</a>]. The Mann-Kendall trend values were corrected for serial correlation [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref045">45</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref046">46</a>] using the package FUME for R [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref047">47</a>]. We evaluated annual trends of date of fry emergence and difference in magnitude of the scenario of interest and baseline over three timescales, including up to year 20, from year 20 to year 63, and over the 63-year duration of the study for all scenarios. By examining the trend up to year 20, we capture the time period when forest harvest may have the greatest impact and in a timeframe that a trend signal could be detected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The question of whether total biomass of trout in summer under each scenario differed from baseline values at each stream was examined using a Wilcoxon signed rank paired test with continuity correction using the package STATS for R. In addition, within the simulated scenarios of forest harvest and climate change, we tested the individual influences of stream temperature and flow on differences in biomass of trout in summer relative to baseline values. We tested the null hypothesis that the median of the difference between baseline and the other scenarios was symmetric about 0. A nonparametric confidence interval and an estimator for the pseudo-median for the difference between the scenarios was also computed [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref048">48</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref049">49</a>]. The Kruskal-Wallis, Mann-Kendall analyses, and Wilcoxon signed rank analyses were analyzed using software R ver. 2.15.1 [
  <a rid="pone.0135334.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref050">50</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
