<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Enhanced measurements can have economic value only if they are used. By positing a decision context in which society adopts reduced emissions scenarios when high values of equilibrium climate sensitivity are established with requisite confidence, the authors have shown that the real option value of enhanced observation systems, over and above the existing systems, runs into trillions of dollars (Cooke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2015</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2016</a>). This underscores the broader message that probabilistic thinking has economic impact, not just in selecting optimal measurement portfolios, but also in quantifying their social value. While there are many challenges to developing and implementing a more rigorous and accurate long-term climate observing system, the economic benefits suggest that this may be one of the society’s best investments.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Valid probabilistic reasoning is subtle, and trusting untrained intuitions can lead to errors. Scientists, science communicators, policy makers, and general public need to understand that disagreement in science is not dysfunctional but is essential to progress. Cultivating valid probabilistic intuitions through exercises like that performed here hope to promote this understanding.</p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As final caveat, this study follows the US Interagency Memo on the Social Cost of Carbon. A 2017 study of the National Academies of Sciences (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2017</a>) identifies many areas in which the existing methodology can and should be improved. In particular, the state-independent carbon cycle models (as they are called, otherwise known as a system of ordinary differential equations) started at equilibrium cannot reproduce features observed in the data and predicted by Earth system Models of Intermediate Complexity (EMICs).
 </p>
</sec>
