<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Confronted with unwelcome scientific advice, interested parties may seek out, or in some cases even generate, conflicting scientific views to neutralize the unwelcome impact (Oreskes and Conway 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2010</a>). Lacking the ability to evaluate the advice, public media striving for balance can unwittingly promote the idea that conflicting advice can simply be ignored. Behind this perspective is a lack of understanding among the general public about the role of disagreement in science. In addition, there is a defective understanding, rooted in the classical statistical methods which most scientific researchers are taught, of how multiple lines of evidence should be combined, as elaborated in Section 
  <a rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec2">2</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The authors’ recent uncertainty decomposition of current and enhanced measurements for equilibrium climate sensitivity (Cooke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2015</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2016</a>) provides a basis for exploring the effects of conflicting measurements. The future measurement values invoked for this purpose are of course hypothetical but the effects are obtained by conditionalizing a vetted joint distribution for equilibrium climate sensitivity (ECS), the rate of decadal temperature rise (DTR) and rate of change of cloud radiative forcing (CRF) as measured by current and future enhanced observing systems. This analysis profits from the fact that a prior distribution over equilibrium climate sensitivity and theoretical models connecting ECS with DTR and CRF are provided by the US inter-agency memo on the social cost of carbon (IWGSCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2009</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2013</a>). This enables a fully Bayesian analysis of these complex interlocking measurement platforms which brings many surprising features to light. Relative to the current prior distribution on ECS, we show that after 30 years of observing with the current systems, the 2
  <span class="italic">σ</span> uncertainty band for ECS would be shrunk on average to 73% of its current value. With the enhanced systems over the same time, it would be shrunk to 32% of its current value. The actual shrinkage depends on the values actually observed. These results are conditional on the current understanding of the uncertainty of ECS (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2013</a>; IWGSCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2009</a>), as well as recent scientific advances in the decomposition of cloud feedbacks, which dominate the uncertainty of ECS, into their individual observable components (Soden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2008</a>; Zhou et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a>). To be clear, uncertainty in emissions (including aerosols) and the effect of “slow feedbacks” outside the current SCC paradigm are not taken into account. Whereas this paper focuses on probabilistic interpretations of measurements and their overall impact on ECS uncertainty, another paper (Hanea et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2018</a>) uses this model to explore counter-intuitive results more generally. The choice to use climate sensitivity for this example is based on the lack of progress in reducing uncertainty in climate sensitivity in the last 30 years of research (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: Section 
  <a rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec2">2</a> reviews combining evidence from the popular point of view and from the simple classical error models. Section 
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">3</a> describes the current and enhanced measurement platform forming the basis for this analysis. Section 
  <a rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec4">4</a> illustrates how conflicting measurements can be almost as informative as concordant measurements. Section 
  <a rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec8">5</a> treats overall uncertainty from different combinations of measurement platforms. A final section gathers conclusions. An appendix provides a mathematical background for the results in Section 
  <a rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec4">4</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
