<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measuring equilibrium climate sensitivity</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An enhanced Earth Observing System (EOS) component 
  <span class="italic">CLARREO</span> (Climate Absolute Radiance and Refractivity Observatory, Wielicki et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2013</a>) uses better calibration than existing systems to observe trends in the decadal rate of global surface temperature rise, and decadal percentage changes in CRF. This is compared with existing systems: For global temperature rise, these are weather satellite infrared spectrometers IASI (Infrared Atmospheric Sounder Interferometer, Hilton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2012</a>), 
  <span class="italic">AIRS</span> (Atmospheric Infrared Sounder, Aumann et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2003</a>), and 
  <span class="italic">CrIS</span> (Cross Track Infrared Sounder, Strow et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2013</a>), abbreviated as IAC. They look at about 1/3 of the Earth’s emitted infrared radiation where CO
  <sub>2</sub> and H
  <sub>2</sub>O absorb radiation in varying levels (low absorption levels see to the surface, high absorption see to 20-km altitude, others see to intermediate depths). They use this to gauge temperature and water vapor vertical profiles from the surface to about 20-km altitude. For reflected shortwave 
  <span class="italic">CRF</span>, the existing system is the 
  <span class="italic">CERES</span> system, a broadband radiation budget instrument. It measures total reflected solar energy as a single value, and total emitted thermal infrared energy as a second value (Wielicki et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1996</a>). All references to CRF in this paper are to reflect shortwave CRF. Note that cloud radiative forcing or CRF is also often referred to as cloud radiative effect or CRE.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is no correlation of the uncertainties of the 
  <span class="italic">CERES</span> and IAC instruments. There is almost no common technology, and their calibration issues are very different. The enhanced EOS 
  <span class="italic">CRF</span> employs a reflected solar spectrometer with a large 2D detector array (512 by 512 detectors) that uses scans of the sun, moon, and nearby deep space to do calibration and international standards (SI) traceability. It shares no types of components with the IR spectrometer, uses a 2-axis gimbal to point the entire instrument so that the exact same optics path is used for solar, lunar, and earth viewing observations. The IR spectrometer that measures temperature change is an interferometer that uses deep cavity blackbodies (0.9998 emissivity where 1.0 is perfect), three different temperature phase change cells to calibrate temperature of the blackbody to SI standards, a blackbody emissivity monitor, and varies its blackbody temperatures for calibration from 200 to 320 K. The physics of how such instruments would change in orbit has no common element, even the electronics of these instruments are very different.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the integrated assessment model 
  <span class="italic">DICE</span> (Nordhaus and Sztorc 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2013</a>), certified by the Inter-Agency Working Group on the Social Cost of Carbon IWGSCC (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2009</a>), theoretical values for decadal temperature and percentage decadal change in 
  <span class="italic">CRF</span> are determined by 
  <span class="italic">ECS</span>, the carbon cycle, and the emissions scenario, as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. The relationship between ECS and CRF follows the decomposition of climate sensitivity into individual feedback components such as cloud feedback (Soden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2008</a>; Zhou et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a>). To be clear, these values are not measured but derived from models. Details on the relationship can be found in Cooke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2016</a>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Percentage change in 
     <span class="italic">CRF</span> (left) and global temperature rise (right) computed with DICE and the Business as Usual emissions path for values of ECS varying ranging from very low (2C) to very high (10C)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="10584_2018_2315_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cloud feedback uncertainty in climate models is dominated by low clouds (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2013</a>). The effect of low clouds on the climate system is in turn dominated by cloud-driven changes in Earth’s reflected solar radiation to space which is typically measured by global mean reflected shortwave CRF (Soden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2008</a>; Zhou et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a>). Interannual and decadal changes in shortwave CRF have been shown by climate models to be the key measure of cloud feedback (Soden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2008</a>; Dessler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2010</a>; Zhou et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2016</a>; Zelinka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2017</a>). While we use the simpler framework of Soden et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2008</a>) for this demonstration example, newer results have shown that spatial patterns of changes in shortwave CRF can be used to reduce the noise of short-term interannual variability in extracting long-term low cloud feedbacks (Zhou et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2016</a>). It has also been shown that use of 500 hPa temperature change in the place of surface temperature change may also reduce the effects of natural variability or short-term climate change (Dessler et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2018</a>; Dessler and Forster 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2018</a>). In the future, both the spatial pattern effects and 500-hPa temperature changes could be incorporated into the framework presented in this paper. Additional climate feedbacks could also be added. We focus on a simpler framework to provide examples of how information from multiple lines of evidence interact.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global temperature and change in 
  <span class="italic">CRF</span> are observed against the background of natural variability, whose effects on trend measurements are attenuated by longer observational times. When perturbed by natural variability (
  <span class="italic">var</span>), orbit sampling uncertainty (
  <span class="italic">orbit</span>) and instrument calibration drift (
  <span class="italic">cal</span>) over observation time 
  <span class="italic">t</span>, the variance 
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> of the trend estimate is derived from (Leroy et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2008</a>):
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="Equa" class="disp-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ {\sigma}^2=12{\left(\Delta t\right)}^{\hbox{--} 3}{\left({\sigma^2}_{\mathrm{var}}{\tau}_{\mathrm{var}}+{\sigma^2}_{\mathrm{cal}}{\tau}_{\mathrm{cal}}+{\sigma^2}_{\mathrm{orbit}}{\tau}_{\mathrm{orbit}}\right)}_{.} $$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
     <div class="msup">
      <span class="mi">σ</span>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mn">12</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div close=")" open="(" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
        <span class="mi">t</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">–</span>
       <span class="mn">3</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div class="msub">
      <div close=")" open="(" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="msup">
          <span class="mi">σ</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mi">var</span>
        </div>
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">τ</span>
         <span class="mi">var</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">+</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="msup">
          <span class="mi">σ</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mi">cal</span>
        </div>
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">τ</span>
         <span class="mi">cal</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">+</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="msup">
          <span class="mi">σ</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mtext">orbit</span>
        </div>
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">τ</span>
         <span class="mtext">orbit</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">.</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="10584_2018_2315_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The units of the one-period variance components 
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>var,</sub>
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>cal</sub>, and 
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>orbit</sub> are the squares of the physical units being measured. The characteristic times 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>var</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>cal</sub>, and 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>
  <sub>orbit</sub> are in years and reflect the serial correlation. Autocorrelation time scales for natural variability are dominated by ENSO (~ 1.5 years), satellite orbit sampling by the averaging time (1 year), and instrument calibration by instrument lifetime, here assumed to be 5 years (Leroy et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2008</a>; Wielicki et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2013</a>). The units of 
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> are thus [physical units squared / time squared]. The effects of noise in observing trends are attenuated by longer observation times. The variance components are considered to be independent normal variables with mean zero (for a detailed discussion see Cooke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>). The statistical formulation is based on an AR(1) process that accounts for short-term climate variability such as ENSO. Longer term climate variability such as Pacific Decadal Oscillation can also be significant and could be included using an AR(2) or other statistical process in future analysis (Brown et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2015</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
