<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Other studies have shown that volcanic eruptions like the 1991 Mount Pinatubo eruption significantly increased annual global land C uptake during 1 to 2 years after the eruptions (Ciais et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Jones &amp; Cox, 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Le Quéré et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Mercado et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), while the CESM‐LME results suggest that eruptions larger than the 1991 eruption during the PILM caused a sharp increase in land C uptake on the year of the event, followed by a reduction in NBP over the next 2 years. The volcanic eruptions appeared to lower both NPP and RH due to cooling of the land surface, but an increase in D (e.g., modeled fires) most likely due to increased drought and decreased precipitation from altered atmospheric circulations. For example, it has been shown that monsoonal rainfall over China following volcanic eruptions was reduced in response to volcanic aerosols over the past 700 years (Zhuo et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). This short‐term effect on land C uptake generally lasts 3 years, and the accumulated impacts over this period from huge eruptions are still very uncertain (Figure 
 <xref rid="jame20902-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>). However, the effect of large‐scale massive volcanic eruptions, as propagated by slower climate‐carbon feedback represented in the CESM over the last millennium, are found to strongly increase terrestrial C sink (such as increased carbon stock over the NH during LIA caused by the cumulative effect of several huge volcanic eruptions). Our modeling analysis suggests that the cooling during the LIA was largely contributed by a series of huge volcanic eruptions over the LIA period. The cooling‐induced terrestrial C uptake was consider as the cause of the observed lower ice‐core CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> level record during the LIA (Rubino et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). These long‐term impacts were evident over timescales of around few hundred years until the land C cycle returns to equilibrium and contributed 25% of variance in NPP and RH on centennial timescales (Figure 
 <xref rid="jame20902-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>). This long‐term (short‐term) volcanic effect on terrestrial ecosystem can drive atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> changes of more than 15 years (within 3 years) in another ESM (MPI‐ESM; Giorgetta et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Jungclaus et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), which was mostly due to changes in C pools across the tropical and subtropical regions, where RH was most significantly reduced in response to the surface cooling after eruptions (Brovkin et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Lehner et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, the simulated impacts of volcanic eruptions on the C cycle are still model‐dependent (Lehner et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
