<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It has been shown that future development of NEE varies much according to ecosystem model and applied climate forcing. According to 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ahlström et al. (2012)</xref>, simulations with a dynamic global vegetation model (LPJ-GUESS), forced by 18 CMIP5 climate projections, showed net release by 2100 for the boreal region. However, the projections were not in full agreement with each other. The magnitude of the release varied, and even turned to uptake in some simulations. Further, according to an ensemble of CMIP5 models both uptake and release of C by land ecosystems is accelerated in the twenty-first century (
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shao et al., 2013</xref>). The boreal latitudes could become a major C sink by 2100 in many models. It should also be recognized that there is a trade-off situation between the ES supply of “harvestable wood” and “avoided radiative forcing.” According to calculations by the Finnish Climate Change Panel, meeting the Finnish targets for implementing the Paris climate change agreement would, in addition to stringent GHG emission reductions, also require a large increase in the C sinks (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Finnish Climate Change Panel, 2018</xref>). Similar measures would be required also at the global level (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rockström et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rogelj et al., 2018</xref>). Intensification of biomass removals from forests may invoke harmful impacts on forest productivity, biodiversity, soil quality, and climate change mitigation potential (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aherne et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Forsius et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mäkelä et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soimakallio et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vanhala et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Eyvindson et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
