<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our three functional descriptors of the spatiotemporal patterns of primary production were derived from satellite images captured by the MODIS sensor onboard the NASA TERRA satellite (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.modis.gsfc.nasa.gov/</ext-link>). We used the MOD13Q1 EVI product, which consists of 16-day maximum value composite images (23 per year) of the EVI at a 231 x 231 m pixel size. This product has atmospheric, radiometric and geometric corrections. We used EVI instead of NDVI because it is less influenced by soil background and saturation problems at high biomass levels [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. We first used the Quality Assessment (QA band) information of this product to filter out those values affected by high content of aerosols, clouds, shadows, snow or water. Next, we calculated the mean seasonal EVI profile (average year) for the 2001–2013 period and derived the EVI annual mean (
 <italic class="italic">EVIMEAN</italic>) as the mean of the 23 images of the average year and the intra-annual coefficient of variation of EVI (
 <italic class="italic">EVICV)</italic> as the intra-annual standard deviation divided by 
 <italic class="italic">EVIMEAN</italic>. The spatial standard deviation of 
 <italic class="italic">EVIMEAN</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">EVISTD</italic>) was calculated in windows of 3 x 3 km (13x13 MOD13Q1 pixels) throughout the study area. The size of this window was determined based on the suggested 9 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> home range of the European badger for low suitability habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Horticultural greenhouses are intensively used in this area [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], and because the EVI values of greenhouses cannot be interpreted as vegetation greenness [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], we removed all grid cells containing greenhouses (5% of the study area) to avoid their influence of species distribution modeling.
</p>
