<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9" class="p">Indeed, there are already various mechanisms in place to incentivize and ensure non-state actors’ contributions to cutting GHGs. Many non-state actors, including a considerable number of large corporations, have already committed themselves to several emission cuts. These cuts are, however, voluntary commitments without any external verification or compliance assurance. For such voluntary approaches to be effective, there are at least two requirements that need to be met. First, there should be an incentive mechanism to prompt more corporations to accept such voluntary emission cuts, because the success of the agreement very much relies on the participation of a large number of MNCs. Such an incentive mechanism should have high gains—such as public acknowledgement of a corporation’s role in combatting climate change—and high losses, such as clear reporting on noncompliance and public exposure (naming), along with some kind of condemnation of such behaviour (shaming) (building on Friman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2015b</xref>). Second, since reporting on voluntary cuts is often based on self-assessments, there needs to be a verification mechanism in order to ensure compliance with the agreed-upon cuts. Section “
 <xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" class="xref">The Role of Non-state Actors in Global Emission Cuts</xref>” focuses on specifying the non-state actors and their roles in combatting climate change. Section “
 <xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Effectiveness of Shaming as a Strategy: Governmental and Non-governmental Approaches</xref>” presents several 
 <italic class="italic">quasi</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">judicial</italic>
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5" class="xref">5</xref> (inter)governmental and non-governmental experiences with similar issues. By drawing comparisons with Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) and with agreements to voluntarily commit to environmental programs supported by intergovernmental and non-state actors, we investigate the extent to which “naming and shaming” could be a viable strategy for securing the contributions of MNCs for combatting climate change.
</p>
