<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our findings suggest convincing teachers that climate change is real, but not necessarily human caused, may have profound impacts on students. Research suggests that individuals are more receptive to climate change communication from trusted messengers [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], and our results support findings suggesting that teachers are among the trusted messengers for adolescents [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Most teachers (98% in the national survey [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] and 92% in our sample) believe that global warming is happening, and our results suggest that those beliefs may transfer to their students, with strength in agreement that global warming is happening positively correlated between teachers and students. Teachers are more polarized on the causes of global warming [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], but encouragingly, our results suggest that these beliefs do not transfer to students. Overwhelmingly, research suggests that teachers’ disagreement with the scientific consensus about climate change causes is likely rooted in political ideology and worldviews [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. However, research among adolescents suggests that these factors may not shape climate change beliefs among children to the same degree as they do among adults [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. It is possible that if teachers are effective messengers of the reality of climate change, students are able to distill its anthropogenic causes even when teachers do not believe in anthropogenic causes. Although our results suggest that teacher beliefs about human causes have little relationship with student beliefs, we did not examine what actually occurs in the classroom. Future research should address whether these trends hold among teachers who send “mixed messages” that many scientists believe that climate change is human-caused while others attribute to natural causes, as was reported in a national science teacher survey [
 <xref rid="pone.0161462.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
