<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study was to investigate whether the mutation rate could evolve to higher values in the course of local adaptation of an isolated population of a sexual species experiencing directional climate change. This work was inspired by a previous study that found adaptive evolution of the mutation rate which advances invasion speed of a sexual population inhabiting an environmental gradient [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. According to our results, the mutation rate can evolve to relatively high values only under conditions of complete linkage or, without such linkage, under the assumption of 50% beneficial mutations. Under complete linkage, the mutation rate can evolve under intermediate to high rates of environmental change, and when the percentage of beneficial mutations is at least 25%. The scenario of complete linkage suggests mutation rates can be expected to evolve in asexual organisms, which is in line with current theory [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. For example, it was demonstrated for 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> populations that mutator alleles could be fixed by hitchhiking on beneficial mutations at other loci [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. In a sexual species, scenarios resembling intermediate to complete linkage may occur if the mutator locus is somehow linked to the trait under selection (e.g., by close proximity on the same chromosome), such that it can hitchhike on beneficial mutations occurring on the evolving trait. Scenarios of intermediate linkage (
  <span class="italic">pR = 0.5</span>) can also yield slightly elevated mutation rates, relative to the unlinked scenario. However, assuming a definite location of the mutator locus in the genome (as, e.g., a locus encoding for a DNA polymerase), most traits under selection can be expected to be encoded far away from the mutator locus, such that the unlinked scenario seems most appropriate for sexually reproducing species.
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, under unlinked recombination scenarios, the mutation rate evolved to relatively higher values only under scenarios of 50% beneficial mutations, particularly when the rate of environmental change was fast. When the percentage of beneficial mutations was low (10 and 25%), either there were too few data points [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>] to derive any conclusion, or the population went extinct for all runs when the rate of environmental change was increased. Thus, the likelihood of beneficial mutations occurring under scenarios of rapid climate change becomes of high importance for organisms with limited plasticity and standing genetic variation, in order to allow for evolutionary rescue in specialist species. These results are in contrast with those in Cobben et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>] where the mutation rate facilitated range expansion and evolved towards higher values even under the assumption of 90% lethal mutations. In our model, given that we implemented the percentage of beneficial mutations 
  <span class="italic">bm</span> directly into the distribution of fitness effects of mutations, the negative effects of mutations (especially when 
  <span class="italic">bm</span> was low) became stronger, the higher the rate of directional environmental change. Under these conditions, elevated mutation rates only evolved in scenarios of high percentage of beneficial mutations. This emphasizes potential outcome differences in studies focused on the evolution of the mutation rate depending on the implementation methods for deleterious mutations. Since our method is consistent with the concept of slightly deleterious mutations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], our simulation of beneficial mutations is presumably more realistic than using a gaussian distribution centered on zero, typically for IBMs of explicit genetics (e.g., [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]) under scenarios of directional selection. According to empirical data, however, most mutations are negative, some are neutral, and only few are beneficial [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. The common assumption in IBM eco-evolutionary models of 50% beneficial mutations is therefore unrealistic and may overestimate evolutionary rescue (or invasion speed) under directional climate change scenarios. We interpret our results as indication that implementation of beneficial mutation percentages more in line with reality may preclude evolution of elevated mutation rates in sexual species, unless there is strong linkage between mutator and trait locus.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to our model, the evolution of the mutation rate may be possible in asexual unicellular organisms, provided that inherited differences in the function of repair and replication mechanisms exist which could serve as “mutator”. In sexual unicellular organisms the mutation rate can evolve if the organisms experience high rate of environmental change and the probability of occurring beneficial mutations is high, or if mutator genes happen to occur close to genome sequences coding for the evolving trait, such that they can hitchhike with beneficial mutations at other loci. In multicellular organisms, the mutator locus is expected to be present and affect germ and soma alike. This was not considered in our model and represents a model limitation. In these organisms an increase in genomic mutation rate may lead to tissue damage and reduced survival. In the model, the mutation rate affected only the process of inheritance of the traits into the next generations. Therefore, the mutation rate may still evolve in multicellular organisms as suggested by the model if the effects of increased mutation rates compromise survival after reproduction takes place [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>], or unless the mutation rate can be somehow increased for segments of the genome (e.g., traits, locus, germ-line). The later scenario may not be consistent with the mutator locus approach as implemented here (e.g., a locus encoding for a DNA polymerase). However, the immune system of vertebrates is an example of high frequency mutations locally restricted to few genes and cell types in multicellular organisms and that has evolved in response to the constant need of novel mutations in the arm race between host and pathogens [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings that mutation rates evolve to higher values only with unrealistically high percentages of beneficial mutations or complete linkage seem to be independent from some characteristics of the environmental change, as it was replicated for the different levels of environmental stochasticity or noise color. This supports and expands the observation of no systematic variation in the mutation rate among asexual organisms experiencing different habitats [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], to sexual species. Thus, the mutation rate is expected to be determined by “deep general forces” balancing the deleterious effects of mutations and the physiological cost of further reducing mutation rates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], and not by external properties of the habitat. However, there are environmental conditions (e.g., chemicals, radiation) that produce DNA damage or modify the chemistry of enzymes potentially affecting replication fidelity and promoting mutations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Such conditions lead to non-adaptive elevations of the mutation rate. Another potential source of variation in the mutation rate is the difference in condition between individuals and populations. Increased mutation rates could occur through costs of DNA repair in maladapted individuals/populations experiencing a lag-load to the moving environmental optimum under environmental change. It has been shown that environmental and genetic stress compromise DNA repair mechanisms and therefore, causes individuals to pass on a greater mutation load to their offspring [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. The phenotypic condition can be directly related to the ability of individuals of overcoming the physiological cost of high-fidelity replication [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. Thus, individuals able to pay the cost of fidelity are expected to reduce the mutation rate down to the drift limit, as further reductions will be effectively neutral [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. Those not able to pay the cost are expected to experience relatively elevated values of the mutation rate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
