<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The overall algorithm for the method is illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214535.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>. The method estimates model weights from calibration period observations, and has one fixed parameter 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>, quantifying model error. Larger 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic> values lead to higher model errors, and as a result broader projections with higher coverage of the 90% posterior credible intervals. Unlike standard Bayesian analysis, we first choose 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic> to obtain approximately correct empirical coverage of the 90% posterior credible intervals during cross-validation. For the cross-validation, each model is selected as the “truth” one-at-a-time. Models are weighted using the output from the “true” model. The “true” model is then excluded from the model set, and the future weighted projections from the remaining models are compared to the output from the “true” model. Once 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic> achieves approximately correct empirical coverage, the method is used for actual projections constrained by real observations. If there are many replicates (or regions) of the system, cross-validation can also be performed by splitting the calibration period into two subperiods. In step 1, observations during the first subperiod in each region/replicate can be used to assign replicate/region-specific weights. In step 2, observations during the second subperiod can test the empirical coverage of the posterior credible intervals. Here, however, we focus on the one-at-a-time cross-validation using future model output. This is because (i) the length of historical record for which high-quality observations are available is too short for most of the experiments [
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0214535.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], (ii) observational records suffer from observational errors, and (iii) climate signal (e.g., the magnitude of climate changes) is quite low in the historical period. We choose various variables and periods to test the method under different conditions.
</p>
