<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-ijerph-12-11025" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Disease Surveillance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A timely disease surveillance system is essential for detecting, reporting and monitoring cases and outbreaks of infectious diseases. The existing public health system in China has been equipped with a comprehensive web-based real-time disease surveillance system built into a network of Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) at the national level, provincial level, prefectural level and county level. China’s disease surveillance system enables 98% of counties and higher-level hospitals and 88% of township hospitals to have direct connection to the CDC disease reporting system [
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-12-11025">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-12-11025">21</a>]. If a notifiable infectious disease case is diagnosed and laboratory confirmed, the case will be reported to the web-based real-time surveillance system, the public health officer, the CDC and the health department, who will take responsibility to investigate the case when necessary [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-11025">22</a>]. Laboratory diagnostic capacity has also been strengthened in recent years [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>]. However, the capacity of this system to detect and verify emerging/re-emerging infectious diseases and rapidly respond to future disease outbreaks still has room for improvement [
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-12-11025">16</a>,
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-11025">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-12-11025">24</a>]. The status of the overall infectious disease surveillance infrastructure, health workforce and the underreporting of infectious diseases in some areas of China are of concern.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Firstly, previous research has demonstrated that the overall infectious disease surveillance infrastructure was underfunded in China, especially in poor and rural areas [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>,
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-11025">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-11025">23</a>]. Although China has risen to become one of the largest economic powers in the world over recent decades, its health care investment is out of pace with its rapid economic growth [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-12-11025">25</a>]. Compared with other countries in the world, China ranks among the poorest in terms of public financing for health care [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-12-11025">25</a>]. Consequently, the lack of funding in public health has resulted in limitations in technical capacity and insufficient human resources in disease control and prevention to meet the challenge of potential emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases outbreaks [
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-11025">23</a>]. Whilst China’s comprehensive county-to-national level network CDC surveillance and reporting system has been reported as being one of the best in the world [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>], greater effort is required to improve the infectious disease surveillance infrastructure. In urban areas infectious disease surveillance infrastructure has received, and continues to receive, financial support from local governments. However, maintenance and update of disease surveillance in county-level rural areas has relatively been neglected, leading to a regional imbalance between urban and rural areas [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>]. Furthermore, despite the relative supremacy of urban disease surveillance infrastructure over its rural counterpart, it still has some limitations. In urban areas, for instance, most public health resources are concentrated in tertiary hospitals and central public health departments, while disease surveillance infrastructure in community-level health service centers needs to be strengthened. Better pathogen-based surveillance infrastructure for disease detection in urban areas and a more rapid response to infectious disease outbreaks is needed to ensure the risks of transmission are minimized in areas of high population density [
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-12-11025">16</a>]. It is imperative, therefore, that initiatives and actions to maintain and update rural disease surveillance infrastructure be taken, whilst concomitantly reinforcing and optimizing urban disease surveillance infrastructure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondly, the health workforce in some rural areas remains poorly trained and unmotivated [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>]. In rural and poor areas there are relatively few health workers who have been professionally trained to effectively deal with infectious disease outbreaks. Likewise, few health professionals at provincial or lower levels CDCs have received formal epidemiological training and communication with international counterparts would be limited [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>]. The ‘Chinese Field Epidemiology Training Program’ was established in 2001 with the support of the World Health Organization (WHO) and the US Centers for Disease Control (USCDC) with a view to developing and strengthening China’s disease surveillance, field epidemiology, and response capacity. As of 2014, only 194 public health professionals had graduated from the program [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-12-11025">26</a>]. However, it still cannot meet the increasing needs for an adequate number of competent and motivated epidemiologists. In addition, for clinical doctors in hospitals, patients are their priority, not public health, which may have an influence on disease surveillance and reporting. One possible reason is that Chinese medical values, cultural norms and heavy workload have shaped clinical doctors who mainly focus on disease treatment rather than prevention [
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-12-11025">27</a>]. However, in the modern health care system doctors play an important role in infectious disease detection, diagnosis, reporting, treatment and cooperation with local CDC staff. This concern is especially applicable in China, where it is estimated that more than 70% of the health care visits occur at village-level rural clinics. However, local health workers may lack relevant skills in awareness, diagnosis and treatment of rare diseases and emerging infectious diseases [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-11025">7</a>]. In this light, it is of critical importance to provide systematic and regular training for the health care workforce in CDCs, hospitals and relevant health departments, especially in rural and remote areas of inland provinces.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thirdly, underreporting of infectious diseases is not uncommon in some areas of China, although in recent years the situation has improved as regulations are now in place. Disease reporting has been listed as an important indicator for evaluating local government’s performance and hospitals are now randomly inspected to monitor the accuracy and quality of infectious diseases reporting. Underreporting may still occur due to various reasons [
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-12-11025">28</a>]. Moreover, hospital doctors may not always report diseases as required [
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-12-11025">29</a>]. Effective communication and information sharing between local hospitals and CDCs are critical for addressing the threats to disease control and prevention, yet doctors do not gain any direct and tangible benefits from the provision of disease surveillance information [
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-12-11025">24</a>]. This communication and information sharing may benefit from effective incentive mechanisms to ensure accurate disease reporting procedures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, strengthened disease surveillance infrastructure, better trained health workers and further consideration of underreporting are needed to improve the infectious disease surveillance system. The importance of improving the system is further accentuated by the likely impacts on infectious disease transmission of two important issues facing this nation: urbanization and climate change.</p>
</sec>
