<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Case study: Protected areas management in Colombia</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Colombia is one of the most biologically diverse countries in the world, with over 9000 endemic species; and habitats that vary from Andean glaciers to tropical rainforests and arid deserts. Culturally, Colombia is home to over 100 different ethnicities, including pre-Colombian indigenous peoples and Afro-Colombian communities. This diversity is represented in 59 natural areas (2017) that belong to the Systems of National Natural Parks (SINAP), which represent 14 268 224 ha; 11% of continental land surface and 1.5% of marine jurisdiction. This is a multilevel system that provides managerial instruments to stakeholders from different governance sectors and levels (private, communitarian, regional, national scale) for terrestrial and marine areas within broader “strategic landscapes”, providing specific rules and policies for their implementation (CONPES 3680, law 2372 from 2010). PNN is a Special Administrative Unit with administrative and financial autonomy and jurisdiction in all the national system of protected areas.</p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate adaptation has appeared in Colombia´s protected areas portfolio since 2004, acknowledging climate as major driver of transformation in landscapes and biodiversity. From the outset, conservation–based actions were identified as a key component of the country’s climate adaptation agenda. Adaptation work in Colombia aimed to provide evidence about the role ecosystems play in enabling people to adapt and for mobilising resources for conservation. By doing so, it also informs and influences decisions towards vulnerable people, places and ecosystems, and ensures that the conservation of priority places and ecosystems is incorporated into the ongoing climate and development planning processes. WWF-C has taken a national leadership role on these issues. Colombia was selected as our case study due to WWF-C’s role in developing “Climate Smart Conservation”, a learning-oriented approach based on anticipation of climate change, and PNN’s work understanding the impacts of climate change and developing associated policy initiatives. The Future-Proofing Conservation process was piloted in two areas where WWF-C work closely with PNN: Amazon Piedmont (Churumbelos, Guacharos and Alto Fragua National Parks), and the Coffee-Growing Region (Otun Quimbaya Flora and Fauna Sanctuary and Nevados National Park). These sites were selected as presenting diverse contexts (biophysically and socially) as well as diverse histories of engagement with climate adaptation.</p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Future-Proofing Conservation project was composed of two phases. First, a co-design and co-production phase, where the research team worked closely with a small number of partners from PNN to develop a context-relevant intervention that could assist a wider range of participants (protected area managers and policymakers) engage with the transitions described in “
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Four transitions towards future-oriented conservation</a>”. The activities in each phase are summarised in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. Second, a piloting phase, where the draft intervention was tested in two pilot protected areas. While the main focus of this article is to document the implementation in Phase 2, a brief description of Phase 1 will be given here.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summary of activities in Phase 1 and Phase 2 of the project</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Phase</th>
      <th align="left" colspan="4">Phase 1: Co-design and co-production</th>
      <th align="left" colspan="3">Phase 2: Piloting future-proofing conservation</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="2">Date</th>
      <th align="left">August 2015</th>
      <th align="left">Nov 2015</th>
      <th align="left">May 2016</th>
      <th align="left">October 2016</th>
      <th align="left">March–April 2017</th>
      <th align="left">April 2017</th>
      <th align="left">May–June 2017</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Initial scoping workshop</th>
      <th align="left">First co-design workshop</th>
      <th align="left">Second co-design workshop</th>
      <th align="left">Third co-design workshop</th>
      <th align="left">Pilot phase planning and implementation</th>
      <th align="left">Pilot phase site #1 Amazon</th>
      <th align="left">Pilot phase site #2 Otun</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Duration</td>
      <td align="left">3 days</td>
      <td align="left">2 days + team debrief</td>
      <td align="left">2.5 days + debrief</td>
      <td align="left">2.5 days + debrief</td>
      <td align="left">Ongoing</td>
      <td align="left">2 days</td>
      <td align="left">2 days</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Participants</td>
      <td align="left">International participants: academics (3), civil society (15), practitioners (2)</td>
      <td align="left">Research team and core partner representatives: academics (5), civil society (9), advisers (1) and practitioners (15)</td>
      <td align="left">Research team and core partner representatives: academics (4), advisers (1) civil society (7), and practitioners (5)</td>
      <td align="left">Research team and core partner representatives: academics (3), advisers (2) and civil society (7) and practitioners (3)</td>
      <td align="left">WWF team and partner representatives
       <span class="break"/>(various) from Pilot site #1, plus community representatives for PA-BAT activity
      </td>
      <td align="left">Research team and participants from Pilot site #1: 14 Park managers, 2 Territorial (provincial) staff, 3 National office staff</td>
      <td align="left">WWF team and participants from pilot site #2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Aim</td>
      <td align="left">Generating ideas and critical input for building a ‘ground up’ approach to FOC</td>
      <td align="left">Learning from partners about PNN context. Establish a shared vision for the project. Test initial ideas for concepts and methods</td>
      <td align="left">Learning from partners about PNN context. Testing refined ideas for concepts and methods</td>
      <td align="left">Test “futures workshop”. Refine ideas consolidated into a proposed multi-step process for staff engagement</td>
      <td align="left">Test “Lessons learned” and PA-BAT activities; collect data regarding knowledge and decision-making</td>
      <td align="left">Test the Futures Dialogue final workshop of the proposed process</td>
      <td align="left">Test the full process</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Activities</td>
      <td align="left">Brainstorming, theory of change, small and large group discussion</td>
      <td align="left">Presentation, feedback and discussion. Additional research needs identified</td>
      <td align="left">Presentation, feedback and discussion. Pilot sites identified</td>
      <td align="left">Feedback and discussion, further refinement and planning for piloting</td>
      <td align="left">Lessons learned workshop;
       <span class="break"/>PA-BAT workshop; knowledge governance interviews
      </td>
      <td align="left">Structured discussion based on the questions of the FD framework. Feedback and lessons</td>
      <td align="left">Lessons learned, PA-BAT, Futures Dialogue workshops. Feedback and lessons</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Facilitation</td>
      <td align="left">Facilitated by academic partners</td>
      <td align="left">Facilitated by academic partners and WWF</td>
      <td align="left">Facilitated by academic partners and WWF</td>
      <td align="left">Facilitated by WWF</td>
      <td align="left">Workshops facilitated by WWF. Interviews conducted by academic partners</td>
      <td align="left">Facilitated by WWF. Presentations by academic partners</td>
      <td align="left">Facilitated and presented by WWF</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
