<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation has always operated in the context of complex, multifaceted threats. But as climate change-induced ecological transformation becomes a reality, the practical challenges of planning, developing policy and establishing change-ready management practices are emerging. Practitioners and advocates need to develop new ways of articulating the role of conservation as ecosystems change, with new rationales for its importance, and new ideas for achievement. The seeds of these ideas are already well embedded in conservation thinking. Conservationists from all sectors are starting to debate how to value emerging or altered ecosystems; whether and how to intervene in facilitating change; and what kinds of strategies may ensure a more dynamic approach.</p>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Future-Proofing Conservation process reflects emerging literature (Eriksen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2015</a>; Manuel-Navarrete and Pelling 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2015</a>; Wyborn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2016</a>; Colloff et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2017</a>) that these debates are largely social and institutional rather than technical, and are intimately connected with how we value natural and cultural landscapes. Adopting the evolutionary learning philosophy brought these values to the fore in an open and consultative way. It allowed conservation participants to consider the future of protected areas in ways that aimed to be empowering and focused on useful ways forward. Co-designing, developing, testing and piloting the activities and ultimately the whole process in active collaboration between academic, civil society and practitioner communities ensured that we struck an appropriate balance between challenging concepts, institutional realities and practical application.
 </p>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Establishing a shared goal of “future-oriented conservation” is not difficult; the challenge lies in populating this idea with accessible concepts, appropriate strategies and effective practices to bridge the implementation gap. Being able to explore new governance arrangements that anticipate and prepare for ecosystem change while remaining focused on the shared values that underpin protected areas is crucial. By developing this larger transition to new governance, through a series of smaller, interconnected transitions that linked values, rules and knowledge, the participants could work through a series of steps that enable new ways of thinking about the role of protected areas in conservation and consequently new ways to manage them.</p>
</sec>
