<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Case study: Protected areas management in Colombia</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Colombia is one of the most biologically diverse countries in the world, with over 9000 endemic species; and habitats that vary from Andean glaciers to tropical rainforests and arid deserts. Culturally, Colombia is home to over 100 different ethnicities, including pre-Colombian indigenous peoples and Afro-Colombian communities. This diversity is represented in 59 natural areas (2017) that belong to the Systems of National Natural Parks (SINAP), which represent 14 268 224 ha; 11% of continental land surface and 1.5% of marine jurisdiction. This is a multilevel system that provides managerial instruments to stakeholders from different governance sectors and levels (private, communitarian, regional, national scale) for terrestrial and marine areas within broader “strategic landscapes”, providing specific rules and policies for their implementation (CONPES 3680, law 2372 from 2010). PNN is a Special Administrative Unit with administrative and financial autonomy and jurisdiction in all the national system of protected areas.</p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate adaptation has appeared in Colombia´s protected areas portfolio since 2004, acknowledging climate as major driver of transformation in landscapes and biodiversity. From the outset, conservation–based actions were identified as a key component of the country’s climate adaptation agenda. Adaptation work in Colombia aimed to provide evidence about the role ecosystems play in enabling people to adapt and for mobilising resources for conservation. By doing so, it also informs and influences decisions towards vulnerable people, places and ecosystems, and ensures that the conservation of priority places and ecosystems is incorporated into the ongoing climate and development planning processes. WWF-C has taken a national leadership role on these issues. Colombia was selected as our case study due to WWF-C’s role in developing “Climate Smart Conservation”, a learning-oriented approach based on anticipation of climate change, and PNN’s work understanding the impacts of climate change and developing associated policy initiatives. The Future-Proofing Conservation process was piloted in two areas where WWF-C work closely with PNN: Amazon Piedmont (Churumbelos, Guacharos and Alto Fragua National Parks), and the Coffee-Growing Region (Otun Quimbaya Flora and Fauna Sanctuary and Nevados National Park). These sites were selected as presenting diverse contexts (biophysically and socially) as well as diverse histories of engagement with climate adaptation.</p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Future-Proofing Conservation project was composed of two phases. First, a co-design and co-production phase, where the research team worked closely with a small number of partners from PNN to develop a context-relevant intervention that could assist a wider range of participants (protected area managers and policymakers) engage with the transitions described in “
   <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Four transitions towards future-oriented conservation</a>”. The activities in each phase are summarised in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. Second, a piloting phase, where the draft intervention was tested in two pilot protected areas. While the main focus of this article is to document the implementation in Phase 2, a brief description of Phase 1 will be given here.
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Summary of activities in Phase 1 and Phase 2 of the project</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Phase</th>
       <th align="left" colspan="4">Phase 1: Co-design and co-production</th>
       <th align="left" colspan="3">Phase 2: Piloting future-proofing conservation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="2">Date</th>
       <th align="left">August 2015</th>
       <th align="left">Nov 2015</th>
       <th align="left">May 2016</th>
       <th align="left">October 2016</th>
       <th align="left">March–April 2017</th>
       <th align="left">April 2017</th>
       <th align="left">May–June 2017</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Initial scoping workshop</th>
       <th align="left">First co-design workshop</th>
       <th align="left">Second co-design workshop</th>
       <th align="left">Third co-design workshop</th>
       <th align="left">Pilot phase planning and implementation</th>
       <th align="left">Pilot phase site #1 Amazon</th>
       <th align="left">Pilot phase site #2 Otun</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Duration</td>
       <td align="left">3 days</td>
       <td align="left">2 days + team debrief</td>
       <td align="left">2.5 days + debrief</td>
       <td align="left">2.5 days + debrief</td>
       <td align="left">Ongoing</td>
       <td align="left">2 days</td>
       <td align="left">2 days</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Participants</td>
       <td align="left">International participants: academics (3), civil society (15), practitioners (2)</td>
       <td align="left">Research team and core partner representatives: academics (5), civil society (9), advisers (1) and practitioners (15)</td>
       <td align="left">Research team and core partner representatives: academics (4), advisers (1) civil society (7), and practitioners (5)</td>
       <td align="left">Research team and core partner representatives: academics (3), advisers (2) and civil society (7) and practitioners (3)</td>
       <td align="left">WWF team and partner representatives
        <span class="break"/>(various) from Pilot site #1, plus community representatives for PA-BAT activity
       </td>
       <td align="left">Research team and participants from Pilot site #1: 14 Park managers, 2 Territorial (provincial) staff, 3 National office staff</td>
       <td align="left">WWF team and participants from pilot site #2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Aim</td>
       <td align="left">Generating ideas and critical input for building a ‘ground up’ approach to FOC</td>
       <td align="left">Learning from partners about PNN context. Establish a shared vision for the project. Test initial ideas for concepts and methods</td>
       <td align="left">Learning from partners about PNN context. Testing refined ideas for concepts and methods</td>
       <td align="left">Test “futures workshop”. Refine ideas consolidated into a proposed multi-step process for staff engagement</td>
       <td align="left">Test “Lessons learned” and PA-BAT activities; collect data regarding knowledge and decision-making</td>
       <td align="left">Test the Futures Dialogue final workshop of the proposed process</td>
       <td align="left">Test the full process</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Activities</td>
       <td align="left">Brainstorming, theory of change, small and large group discussion</td>
       <td align="left">Presentation, feedback and discussion. Additional research needs identified</td>
       <td align="left">Presentation, feedback and discussion. Pilot sites identified</td>
       <td align="left">Feedback and discussion, further refinement and planning for piloting</td>
       <td align="left">Lessons learned workshop;
        <span class="break"/>PA-BAT workshop; knowledge governance interviews
       </td>
       <td align="left">Structured discussion based on the questions of the FD framework. Feedback and lessons</td>
       <td align="left">Lessons learned, PA-BAT, Futures Dialogue workshops. Feedback and lessons</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Facilitation</td>
       <td align="left">Facilitated by academic partners</td>
       <td align="left">Facilitated by academic partners and WWF</td>
       <td align="left">Facilitated by academic partners and WWF</td>
       <td align="left">Facilitated by WWF</td>
       <td align="left">Workshops facilitated by WWF. Interviews conducted by academic partners</td>
       <td align="left">Facilitated by WWF. Presentations by academic partners</td>
       <td align="left">Facilitated and presented by WWF</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phase 1—Co-design and co-production</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of the first phase of the project (2015–2017) was to develop an interactive process that could be applied by PNN or WWF partners to support the transitions towards future-oriented conservation in their organisations. In accordance with our evolutionary learning approach, Phase 1 drew on design thinking (Brown 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2008</a>; Adams et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2011</a>; Beier et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2016</a>) and co-production processes (Kirchhoff et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2013</a>; Mauser et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2013</a>; Clark et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2016</a>) to collaboratively explore the challenge in context; to generate shared visions for the future; and to create new ideas for achieving the transitions described in “
   <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Four transitions towards future-oriented conservation</a>”. The research team worked with partners to learn about the context that policymakers and protected area managers operate within, establish shared goals, and test workshop activities and facilitation processes. Phase 1 included four workshops organised from August 2015 to June 2017. The participants, aims, methods and leaders are summarised in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. In these workshops, the academic research team presented tools or concepts from the literature, which were tested and critiqued by partners and practitioners, and discussed extensively. The heuristic of VRK was applied throughout to ensure that the conversation included deliberations on social and political values; institutional settings, conventions and rules; and technical and non-technical knowledge. Formal and informal feedback processes, theory of change (Vogel 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2012</a>), and scorecard evaluations were used to provide multiple avenues of dialogue and reflection, and document the process as it advanced.
   <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Summary of results and outcomes from the pilot workshops</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Activity</th>
       <th align="left">Results Amazon</th>
       <th align="left">Results Otun</th>
       <th align="left">Outcomes</th>
       <th align="left">Feedback</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">PA-BAT workshop</td>
       <td align="left">PA main benefits identified, in order of priority:
        <span class="break"/> Reducing climate change impacts
        <span class="break"/> Water quality, quantity and access
        <span class="break"/> Sacred places/sites
        <span class="break"/> Tourism
       </td>
       <td align="left">PA main benefits identified, in order of priority:
        <span class="break"/> Water quality and quantity
        <span class="break"/> Sites of unique beauty
        <span class="break"/> Reducing climate change impacts
        <span class="break"/> Tourism
       </td>
       <td align="left">Communities and PA staff generated shared documentation of priority benefits, ranked in order of importance. Additional outputs such as maps included specific locations of sacred sites</td>
       <td align="left">Participants Pilot #2
        <span class="break"/>“The tool is useful to engage diverse stakeholders; as there are no ‘wrong’ answers, all can participate. Wider representation of other community groups would have improved the workshop”
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Lessons learned workshop</td>
       <td align="left">Participants noted that:
        <span class="break"/> Risk management is linked to climate change
        <span class="break"/> Little monitoring and research completed, what has been done is uncoordinated
        <span class="break"/> Communities are aware of climate change; opportunities for education
       </td>
       <td align="left">Participants noted that:
        <span class="break"/> Technical studies of climate change impacts have been completed
        <span class="break"/> Limited capacity to develop management changes based on research
        <span class="break"/> Solid foundation of cooperation across sectors and communities
       </td>
       <td align="left">Barriers identified:
        <span class="break"/> Institutional complexity and disconnect
        <span class="break"/> Poor knowledge sharing
        <span class="break"/> Existing knowledge is too technical for many local managers
        <span class="break"/> Local knowledge is not recognised
       </td>
       <td align="left">Participant Pilot #1 “Climate is not something that depends on a specific space, we must expand … and link ourselves to a larger scale than the protected area”</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Futures dialogue</td>
       <td align="left">Participants identified actions that could be taken now to prepare for climate change, including
        <span class="break"/> Extending networks for collaboration in planning, such as water utility departments;
        <span class="break"/> Reviewing existing and potentially establishing new monitoring programmes to document baselines for benefits as well as species;
        <span class="break"/> Integrating PABAT into existing planning frameworks to ensure benefits are considered alongside conventional objectives
       </td>
       <td align="left">Participants identified actions, recognising that 
        <span class="italic">transformation</span> is different from 
        <span class="italic">impacts,</span> including
        <span class="break"/> Need to review conservation objectives in light of transformation;
        <span class="break"/> Protected areas alone cannot ‘save’ biodiversity, must involve communities;
        <span class="break"/> Larger scale (territorial) organisation and planning is needed, but difficult
       </td>
       <td align="left">Participants developed an alternate way of thinking about planning for climate change that reflected the current state of technical knowledge, incorporated values and benefits, and considered existing decision-making processes and tools.
        <span class="break"/>Participants did not follow through the change in thinking with a fully revised approach to PA policy, planning and management; ideas were generated but proposed incremental rather than transformative changes.
       </td>
       <td align="left">Participant FD #1 Park manager “We need to manage relationships with other actors, to maintain benefits that Parks generate”
        <span class="break"/>Participant FD #1 National office: “This project has achieved a dialogue between different [park management] levels”.
        <span class="break"/>Participant FD#1 Park manager: “how do we take these ideas into policies, plans and management frameworks for conservation?”
       </td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following each workshop, the research team distilled the feedback and gradually refined the approach to a suite of concepts and tools that became the “Future-Proofing Conservation process”. Key issues that emerged from Phase 1 included a need to synthesise and summarise existing technical knowledge on climate change relevant to the pilot sites; more intensive research to understand the complex decision-making settings within PNN; the value of opportunities to reflect on previous work and existing knowledge in protected area sites; and activities to engage communities as well as professionals in identifying opportunities for change.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phase 2—Piloting the Future-Proofing Conservation process</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Future-Proofing Conservation process that emerged from Phase 1 comprises a tailored technical synthesis report, interview-based research, 2 preliminary workshops, and a final culminating workshop. A summary of the process, results and outcomes are presented in Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>.
  </p>
  <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change science synthesis report</div>
   <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ability to examine and explore locally relevant information on ecological impacts of climate change was an important initial stage for participants in the process. This was both to inform decisions, and to provide reassurance that science was ‘covered’ before focusing on management. Thus, we recruited a local expert (author, Abud Hoyos) to work with the academic team to create a synthesis report focused on the pilot areas. This brought together the best available projections and expected ecological change in the specific sites.</p>
   <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The synthesis focused on documenting diverse observed and anticipated impacts on biodiversity and ecosystem services, not just expected species movements or loss, and drew on modelling to indicate the potential magnitude of change. Expected impacts included melting glaciers, changes in water provision, increased coastal erosion, shifts in species distribution and migration patterns, more extreme climatic events, and changes in ecosystem types and function. Changes in species and ecosystems in protected areas affect the provision of ecosystem benefits, and other threats to biodiversity may be exacerbated. For example, projections show that warmer temperatures may force coffee growers to move crops to higher altitudes. Impacts may be amplified by existing threats such as invasive species, habitat loss and fragmentation, mining, agricultural and urban expansion. Many questions remain unanswered, and discussion in the synthesis report explicitly considered the high level of uncertainty but also highlighted impacts that are likely.</p>
   <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By emphasising both what we do know as well as the limitations of the current state of knowledge, participants were confident that they were not deliberating management or governance in ignorance of the scientific knowledge base. Emphasising the pervasive and inevitable nature of ecological change underpinned Transition #1, from resisting change to anticipating it. The synthesis report was incorporated into the final stage of the Future-Proofing Conservation process, the Futures Dialogue workshop.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Knowledge governance mapping</div>
   <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Knowledge governance mapping is an interview-based method where key stakeholders share their experience of knowledge-based processes and the application of climate information to decisions within their social and institutional context (van Kerkhoff and Pilbeam 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2017</a>). These interviews provided in-depth understanding of existing governance structures, supporting Transition #3: from climate change as a scientific issue to a governance issue. We conducted semi-structured interviews with 28 participants with an active role in protected areas planning and management to understand how scientific information (especially climate and ecosystem services) influenced decision-making and management of protected areas. Participants were purposively sampled to include managers and practitioners from national, territorial and local levels at the pilot study sites. Participants were encouraged to reflect on whether, how and to what extent climate adaptation is understood to be a scientific issue and/or a governance one, and to gauge how well these two domains were connected. Interviews were digitally recorded, transcribed, and thematically analysed.
   </p>
   <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interviews revealed that protected area managers and agencies have been actively looking for information to support decision-making regarding management of biodiversity under climate change, and so were largely at the Traditional side of Transition #3. Barriers to moving towards a governance-based approach included the perceived need to build a shared understanding of climate variability, ecological transformation and climate change. Participants also identified the need for clarity on key management questions before they could use climate information strategically, grappling with how climate adaptation might ‘fit’ within existing structures. The findings from these interviews were used as background for the research team to inform the interactive sessions; they were also summarised in the Futures Dialogue (“
    <a rid="Sec12" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec12">Futures Dialogue workshop</a>”) to encourage deliberation on existing governance structures.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“Climate adaptation lessons learned” workshop</div>
   <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This workshop compiled experience on what has previously been learned about climate adaptation from projects, policies or planning activities, addressing Transition #4: problem-solving to ongoing learning. This acknowledges that participants are not ‘starting from zero’, but have relevant expertise and experience and that understanding the adaptation context requires an assessment of local knowledge and perspectives. The workshop engaged local managers at the pilot sites. The objectives were to: (i) understand whether, how and to what extent local PA staff have integrated climate change into management strategies; (ii) understand opportunities and barriers for climate change management on a PA level; and (iii) create a space for sharing knowledge on climate change and PA management. The workshops sought to meet the need identified in the interviews by creating a shared understanding of key climate concepts and practices (known in Colombia as “conceptual levelling”); exploring participants perceptions of climate-related impacts; and creating a learning journey, a shared timeline of climate adaptation-related activities, policy changes or other significant developments. Through these activities, participants reflected on their existing expertise, their observations, and on processes of change including what enabled or prevented further developments, and associated challenges and opportunities. Different interpretations of events were explored and there was no pressure to reach a single narrative. The output of the learning journey was a large visual timeline that documented the evolution of climate change thinking and action, with the most significant lessons drawn from this experience.</p>
   <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This activity enabled collective reflection on processes of change at the site level. The research team was interested to see whether previous actions focused on discrete projects or tackled more systemic, interconnected issues. Where activities addressed knowledge generation, we looked both at the products (such as climate projection maps) and the processes through which these informed policy, planning or management (facilitating learning).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Protected areas benefits assessment workshop</div>
   <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following from the “Lessons learned” activity, we used the Protected Area Benefits Assessment Tool (PA-BAT) to identify the benefits derived from a PA, creating the groundwork for Transition #2: from ecological attributes to social values and benefits (extended in the Futures Dialogue, see “
    <a rid="Sec12" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec12">Futures Dialogue workshop</a>”). PA-BAT provides a quick and standardised way of collecting information about the ecosystem services derived from a protected area, drawing on knowledge from a range of stakeholders (Dudley and Stolton 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2009</a>). It is an inclusive, workshop-based approach that assembles a diverse group of stakeholders and reaches decisions by consensus. In this context, the workshops included local level PA managers (most of whom had participated in the previous workshop) but also included local community representatives and stakeholders.
   </p>
   <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PA-BAT consists of 24 questions covering different benefits related to provisioning services (food, water, materials), regulation services (climate risk reduction, natural hazards control), cultural services (tourism, recreation, aesthetic values, education, knowledge generation, cultural and historical values, mental wellbeing) and regulation services (pollination, pests control). Participants explore current and potential importance (economic and non-economic) and the critical question of who benefits as well as location in the protected area (Dudley and Stolton 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2009</a>). Prior to the workshop, managers and others identify which benefits are to be assessed (the tool is global so not all will be appropriate) and approach different stakeholders (15–30 people) to participate. A series of slides are projected to summarise the key benefits through photographs and words in the local language. These slides allow discussion about the importance (economic and non-economic) and potential of the benefit. While based around a set series of questions, facilitators are open to other benefits and oral testimony is recorded; these stories are often the most useful part of the exercise. In Colombia, we employed an artist to summarise perceptions of the benefits and linkages, using a combination of sketches, icons and words. Participants were also invited to locate some of the benefits directly onto maps, with debate and discussion over exact locations revealing benefits which were often unknown by the management. PNN staff in Colombia also argued strongly that participants should be given the opportunity to discuss illegal but common uses as well as part of a separate but linked process (Figueroa and Behar 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2017</a>).
   </p>
   <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PA-BAT was implemented in Colombia in the two pilot areas. For Otun, a landscape of protected areas in the Andes mountains, water quantity and quality, places with unique beauty, and reducing climate change effects such as heatwaves or drought, are perceived as the most important benefits of conservation. For the more remote Amazon Piedmont protected areas, knowledge generation, reducing climate change effects and tourism were perceived as the most important benefits. This set the stage for considering the relationships between ecological features and social benefits, and so ‘priming’ participants for the Futures Dialogue (“
    <a rid="Sec12" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec12">Futures dialogue workshop</a>”). It also helped facilitators to gauge how readily participants can identify benefits that are connected with, but separate from ecological features, as a key component of Transition #2.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Futures Dialogue workshop</div>
   <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of the previous activities established the basis for the final step, the Futures Dialogue workshop. This 2-day workshop guides participants through a series of structured questions, working through the four transitions to reach the final goal of defining practical steps towards governance that effectively anticipates climate change and prepares for it. The questions are summarised in Table 
    <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>, which also indicates the dominant concept and supporting resources from previous activities that were used in each step. In between interactive sessions, members of the research team gave short summary presentations relating to the previous activities, as a reminder and in recognition of the fact that not all participants had attended all activities. Participants are arranged into small groups of 6–8, and a facilitator at each small group guides the conversations.
    <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
     <span class="label">Table 3</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>The question-based structure of the Futures Dialogue, with links to core concepts (column 2) and prior activities (column 3)</p>
     </div>
     <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
      <thead>
       <tr>
        <th align="left" colspan="3">Stage 1: Values, benefits and transformation</th>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <th align="left">Question</th>
        <th align="left">Focus on</th>
        <th align="left">Resources</th>
       </tr>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">A—What benefits are provided by the protected area?</td>
        <td align="left">Values</td>
        <td align="left">PABAT</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">B—What ecological or landscape features provide that benefit?</td>
        <td align="left">Knowledge</td>
        <td align="left">Climate change synthesis</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">C—How might that feature transform under climate change?</td>
        <td align="left">Values and knowledge</td>
        <td align="left">PABAT, CCS</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">D—as the climate changes, what features will remain or stay the same?</td>
        <td align="left">Knowledge</td>
        <td align="left">CCS</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">E—How might the benefit be affected by climate-related change?</td>
        <td align="left">Values and knowledge</td>
        <td align="left">PABAT, CCS</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">F—what could be done differently to maintain benefits as change occurs?</td>
        <td align="left">VRK</td>
        <td align="left">All</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left" colspan="3">Stage 2: Managing differently</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">G—what would managers and planners need to do better/more to maintain benefits? What would need to be done differently? Should priorities change?</td>
        <td align="left">Rules, values</td>
        <td align="left">Lessons learnt</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">H—what are the barriers and opportunities for change?</td>
        <td align="left">VRK</td>
        <td align="left">Governance mapping</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">I–J—who is responsible for change? Who has authority to change?</td>
        <td align="left">Rules</td>
        <td align="left">Governance mapping</td>
       </tr>
       <tr>
        <td align="left">K—how can we prepare our management system for change? How do we engage those with authority to learn about multiple implications and anticipate change?</td>
        <td align="left">VRK</td>
        <td align="left">All</td>
       </tr>
      </tbody>
     </table>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first sessions aim to build shared understanding that 
    <span class="italic">ecological change is inevitable</span> and recognise the difference between ecological change as a biophysical phenomenon and its effects on benefits for society. Questions A-B draw linkages between ecological features and benefits. Facilitators start with values participants expressed through the previous PA-BAT workshop as benefits from protected areas, and consider whether the ecological or landscape features that support that benefit are known to be vulnerable to change.
   </p>
   <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The participants then differentiate climate-related ecological change and potential changes to benefits, recognising that benefits will not necessarily be affected directly or proportionately (questions C–E). Through facilitated discussion the groups identify changes in management that could help maintain benefits in the longer term (questions F, G), and near-term opportunities and barriers, including knowledge gaps, to achieving those changes (question H). This includes recognising that access to detailed scientific information is not always essential to start planning for climate change adaptation. Finally, participants considered the process of changing management more specifically: what would need to change and how, and the people, organisations or institutions that can help enable these changes (questions I–K). This session includes consideration of incremental changes to implement now, and larger changes needing individual and institutional learning, political groundwork and ‘windows of opportunity’ before more systemic transitions could be tackled.</p>
   <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, in the Otun Coffee-Growing Region, participants identified “Livelihoods from tourism” as an important benefit. The questions guided participants to recognise that tourism is not solely dependent on particular ecological features, but can be supported in a changing environment. This may, however, require different or additional management to support the provision of benefits. The Futures Dialogue questions stimulated discussion and insight; however, while the first few questions were easier to address, the later questions needed more guidance and a greater level of facilitation.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
