<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is one of the key threats to agricultural production and indeed to the species survival in the Anthropocene (Godfray et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Hoffmann, Sgrò, &amp; Kristensen, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Johnson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Body size constrains tolerance and the smaller size is an adaptation to the warmer climate (McCain &amp; King, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Savolainen, Lascoux, &amp; Merila, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Hence, how species cope with change will be important in defining their likelihood of future success (Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). As we cannot predict all traits that may in future be advantageous, the conservation of biodiversity within domestic livestock is important, especially in the face of rapidly depleting biodiversity during climate change (Isbell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Moreover, heat stress is becoming an increasingly important constraint on animal productivity in various parts of the world (Collier, Renquist, &amp; Xiao, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Potential solutions for vulnerable populations are to engineer the environment (e.g., controlled environment buildings), which may prove to be unsustainable from an economic, environmental, or animal welfare perspective, or to change/adapt the animal to one that is more suited to the climate (Godfray et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Hoffmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Johnson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Here, we focus on the latter, which requires an understanding of the mechanisms of heat acclimatization and/or adaptation in animals (Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref> ; Savolainen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Seebacher, White, &amp; Franklin, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This includes a knowledge of the genetic architecture of traits, that is, how functional traits like heat tolerance and body size can change through individual phenotypic plasticity or population‐level evolution (Klockmann, Gunter, &amp; Fischer, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref> ). To date, few studies have attempted to analyze the differential tolerance to warming and underlying functional mutations among phenotypically disparate populations (Brans et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Seebacher et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Specifically, previous studies lack either a wide‐ranging understanding of the mechanism behind functional traits at physiological and molecular levels or the genetic milieu by which they evolved, or both (Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref> ).
</p>
