<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Generally, separate and geographically isolated populations that are widely distributed and abundant enhance the ability to identify genetic architecture linked with phenotypic variations (Savolainen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). In domestic cattle, genetic composition has been shaped by geographic segregation, ancient human movements, cross‐breeding, and gene flow among domestic and wild cattle populations (Jia et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Park et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Taye et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Troy et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). Two subspecies of cattle; 
 <italic class="italic">Bos taurus indicus</italic> (indicine) and 
 <italic class="italic">Bos taurus taurus</italic> (taurine), were domesticated from extinct aurochs (
 <italic class="italic">Bos primigenius</italic>) (Decker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Indicine and taurine lineages are diverged from auroch ancestors about 0.74–1 Mya (Loftus, MacHugh, Bradley, Sharp, &amp; Cunningham, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>) and three main assemblages of modern cattle: African and Eurasian taurine and Asian indicine are now farmed (Upadhyay et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Indicus haplotypes 1 and 2 diverged from a common ancestor about 5.3 ± 2.6 and 10.9 ± 3.5 thousand years ago, respectively (Hiendleder, Lewalski, &amp; Janke, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Asian indicine cattle are composed of 
 <italic class="italic">B. t. taurus</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> B. t. indicus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">B. javanicus</italic> (Decker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The locally adapted hybrids in Asia, Africa, and America are crosses of hump‐less taurine and humped indicine (also called zebu) cattle, while the African taurine lineage predominates in European Mediterranean breeds (Decker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Hence, domestic cattle display extensive temporal and spatial variations in phenotype and genetic makeup (Elsik, Tellam, &amp; Worley, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) including body size variation such as dwarfism, the molecular genetic basis of which also varies widely. For example, Boegheim, Leegwater, Lith, and Back (
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) explained that the inherited forms of dwarfism in some cattle breeds are caused by genetic mutations leading to structural, hormonal, and signaling pathway disruptions. However, DCB may be evolved following dispersal to extremely isolated environments, for example, the evolution of dwarf 
 <italic class="italic">Anoa</italic> buffaloes at Sulawesi and Sunda islands (Rozzi, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The Indicus haplotype consists of both dwarf (DCB) and standard size (SCB) cattle breeds. A proportionate reduction in body size (and hence a greater surface area to volume ratio to improve thermoregulation) is one possible evolutionary adaptation to increasing heat stress (Collier &amp; Gebremedhin, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Rozzi, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Savolainen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) but this is subject to evolutionary and agronomic trade‐offs (Tilman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). For example, larger high‐yielding breeds are preferred over native smaller breeds in intensive agriculture. However, DCB such as the Vechur breed (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34550-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) may represent candidates for adaptation to global climate change due to their climatic resilience (Eisler et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Kerala state in India, with 93% crossbred SCB (
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">indicus </italic>× 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>.
 <italic class="italic"> taurus</italic>) and 6% DCB (
 <italic class="italic">B</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">indicus</italic>), represents a large‐scale “natural experimental spot” for studying domestic cattle evolution in action.
</p>
