<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate is one of the main explanatory variables for large ruminant morphology and largely, phenotypic changes are confined locally due to geographical isolation (Hill, Hill, &amp; Widga, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Martin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). However, not all species have decreased in size over time and mechanisms other than improved heat dissipation may contribute to size reduction (e.g., changes in food availability or hunting; see Hill et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Machac, Graham, &amp; Storch, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Increased temperature and humidity affect physiology and in turn functional traits like body size in different ways (Kim, Park, &amp; Sin, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). There is an inverse relationship between enhancing environmental temperature and body size of ruminants in the last 40,000 years since warming decreases body size by altering metabolic loads and available resources (Martin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Phylogenetic diversity (PD, which measures evolutionary history among taxa) and functional diversity (FD, that represents quantitative measures of functional traits, like body size) capture the patterns in the diversity of traits, and studying their interaction can be informative (Tucker, Davies, Cadotte, &amp; Pearse, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Thus, linking physiology and phylogeny may help to identify mechanisms of dwarfing in cattle and aid to forecast the effect of environmental warming on ruminant adaptation and evolution. We hypothesized that concomitant increase in temperature and humidity in Kerala has resulted in adaptive changes in physiology and genetic architecture which may have facilitated a high level of morphological diversification in cattle, leading to the evolution of dwarf breeds.
</p>
