<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The persistence of populations and species in the face of environmental change is ultimately shaped by dynamic and often complex feedbacks between ecology and evolution (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">Kinnison &amp; Hairston 2007</a>). Ecological factors include direct and indirect effects on births, deaths, dispersal rates, and species interactions, whereas evolutionary factors include changes in the genetic and phenotypic constitution of populations (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">Parmesan 2006</a>). Typically, ecological and evolutionary responses to environmental change are considered separately (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">Ferrière et al. 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">Kokko &amp; Lopez-Sepulcre 2007</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">Pelletier et al. 2009</a>). Evolution, however, often occurs rapidly and can influence contemporaneous ecological dynamics (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">Hairston et al. 2005</a>). Global climate change will not only affect migration patterns, biotic interactions, and local population dynamics, but also the selective pressures experienced by populations. Coupled ecological and evolutionary changes are therefore expected under climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ignoring evolutionary processes can produce an incomplete picture of likely biotic responses to climate change (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">Holt 1990</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">Davis et al. 2005</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b68" href="#b68">Visser 2008</a>). For example, most projections of species responses to climate change are based on niche models, which assume that a species has a single, static environmental tolerance function. Regional populations, however, are often locally adapted to a more limited range of conditions (e.g., temperatures) than that experienced by the species as a whole. Overlooking regional differentiation can lead to overestimates of probabilities of population persistence (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">Davis et al. 2005</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">Etterson 2008</a>) or erroneous projections of poleward or elevational range expansions if local adaptation in peripheral populations is disrupted (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">Pelini et al. 2009</a>). Conversely, by overlooking the possibility that environmental tolerances might evolve or increase through phenotypic plasticity, static niche models can overestimate probabilities of extinction or range contraction (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">Holt &amp; Gomulkiewicz 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">Davis et al. 2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Realistic assessment of probabilities of population and species persistence thus requires information on both current levels of adaptation and future adaptive potential (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">Davis et al. 2005</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">Etterson 2008</a>). Additionally, evolutionary assessments must incorporate key ecological considerations, such as the demographic consequences of strong selection in closed populations (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">Lynch &amp; Lande 1993</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">Gomulkiewicz &amp; Holt 1995</a>) or metapopulations (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">Holt &amp; Gomulkiewicz 2004</a>), the modulating effects of phenotypic plasticity on population and evolutionary dynamics (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" href="#b60">Price et al. 2003</a>), and potential feedbacks between selection and population regulation (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">Kinnison &amp; Hairston 2007</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">Kokko &amp; Lopez-Sepulcre 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determining limits to phenotypic plasticity and evolutionary potential in traits affecting survival, reproduction, and dispersal will be critical to assessing demographic responses to climate change (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">Hellmann &amp; Pineda-Krch 2007</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">Bradshaw &amp; Holzapfel 2008</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">Gienapp et al. 2008</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b68" href="#b68">Visser 2008</a>). We attempted to clarify how evolution, phenotypic plasticity, and demography are linked in the context of climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
