<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Adaptive Surface</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fitness landscapes are heuristic tools that represent the fitness consequences of major environmental changes (e.g., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">Hellmann &amp; Pineda-Krch 2007</a>). Individual-level fitness (adaptive) surfaces illustrate the relation between phenotype (measurable traits of an organism) and relative fitness. The topography of this surface reflects the probable lifetime reproductive success of individuals with different phenotypic characteristics in that environment. Further an individual's phenotype is from the optimum, the lower its relative fitness. If population mean fitness (average number of offspring produced per capita per time period, also called absolute fitness) is plotted against a range of hypothetical mean trait values, the resulting surface is called a phenotypic adaptive landscape, which can have one or several “adaptive peaks” (fitness optima).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the mean phenotype does not correspond to an adaptive peak (i.e., if local adaptation is imperfect), mean absolute fitness is reduced relative to the optimum, and the population experiences directional selection uphill toward the nearest peak (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">Lande 1976</a>). Hereafter, we consider simple adaptive landscapes that are characterized by a single adaptive peak, even though real environments are generally more complex (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" href="#b3">Arnold et al. 2001</a>). Deviation of the mean phenotype from the optimum is called the lag, whereas the relative decrease in mean fitness resulting from the lag is called the lag load, or evolutionary load (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">Lynch &amp; Lande 1993</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">Bürger &amp; Krall 2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change can alter fitness landscapes in several ways. Suboptimal temperatures or changes in other key variables could increase mortality or lower fecundity independent of phenotype, which would effectively lower the overall elevation of the fitness surface (improved conditions would do the opposite). At the same time, climate change can shift the location of the phenotypic optimum through trait space (e.g., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">Grant &amp; Grant 2002</a>) and potentially alter the shape of the fitness surface (e.g., 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">Charmantier et al. 2008</a>). If the optimum changes consistently through time but the mean phenotype lags behind, extreme phenotypes closer to the optimum will have consistently higher fitness and the population will experience increasingly strong directional selection. Alternatively, if fluctuations in the optimum about a fixed or slowly changing mean become stronger or more frequent, the population will experience selection that varies increasingly in intensity and possibly also in direction (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">Bürger &amp; Krall 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">Hellmann &amp; Pineda-Krch 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if environmental change does not affect the phenotypic optimum, selection pressures could change if maladaptive plasticity causes individuals to produce phenotypes that are locally suboptimal. If the mean phenotype deviates consistently from the optimum, the resulting maladaptation might depress population growth below replacement level. Unless demographic rescue from neighboring populations occurs, there are only three options: move, adapt, or die (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">Pease et al. 1989</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">Lynch &amp; Lande 1993</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extant species have persisted through numerous past climate shifts. Two phenomena can facilitate adaptive tracking of temporal changes in the environment: adaptive evolution (changes in population gene frequencies across generations that result in phenotypes that are more likely to persist in new environments) and adaptive phenotypic plasticity (fitness-enhancing responses by individuals to environmental cues). Plastic phenotypic responses do not involve genetic change at the population level, but the capacity for plasticity itself can be adaptive and genetically variable within populations, and this capacity may evolve in response to changes in environmental variability (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b62" href="#b62">Scheiner 1993</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" href="#b63">Svanbäck et al. 2009</a>). Whether populations can persist depends on the nature, magnitude, and rate of change in selective pressures, the capacity for evolutionary and plastic (including migration) responses, and the demographic context of adaptation.
 </p>
</sec>
