<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgement</div>
 <p>This work is part of a Research Project funded by the Basic Science CONACYT program (project number CB-2012-1-183377). MTR-P thanks CONACYT for the scholarship awarded for the completion of this study and financial support by FORDECYT/193512/2012. We thank Dr. Gerardo Argüello-Astorga who provided us space and material support for the project’s execution, as well as helpful suggestions, and G. Valkiūnas who granted us access to a lab in the Nature Research Center, Vilnius, Lithuania and provided help interpreting parasite images. All authors thank Carlos Armando, Jachar Arreola and Karina Monzalvo who helped in the field work. The collection of samples was made using a permit granted by SEMARNAT with number FAUT −0157.</p>
 <sec id="d30e1794" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Authors’ contributions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">JCC-D, LCV, MTR-P, and LRR, conceived the study, MTR-P, JCC-D and LCV collected samples; MTR-P and JCC-D processed samples and generated molecular and sequencing data; MTR-P, LRR and JCC-D aligned and analyzed the sequences; MTR-P and JCC-D processed and analyzed blood smears; MTR-P and JCC-D analyzed the results, MTR-P and JCC-D prepared the manuscript, and all authors reviewed the manuscript and approved the final version.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="d30e1799" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Competing interests</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="d30e1804" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All fieldwork was conducted using a bird capture permit issued by SEMARNAT, the Secretariat for Environmental Management and Natural Resources of Mexico (Permit number FAUT-0157). We complied with all Mexican and international regulations required for conducting wildlife research in the field including those from IUCN and CITES. No individuals were harmed during data collection, and all individuals were released on the capture location after samples and measurements were taken.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
