<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study area is located between the municipalities of Charcas and Catorce, in the Mexican state of San Luis Potosi. Three communal-owned areas (ejidos) were included in the study: La Cardoncita (LC), Presa de Santa Gertrudis (PSG), and Guadalupe Victoria (GV) (UTM: E271793.37 N2610708.64, E278059.47 N2599525.12, E276057.75 N2582923.98 Zone 14 N). All study sites were embedded in a region known as “Zona Ixtlera” (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), where trees of the genus 
  <span class="italic">Yucca</span> have been historically extracted to obtain fiber, locally known as “Ixtle”, which is used for manufacture of ropes and other crafts. The vegetation in the area is characterized by the presence of rosette microphylous scrublands dominated by 
  <span class="italic">Yucca</span> spp. in the tree layer, and 
  <span class="italic">Larrea tridentata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Flourensia cernua</span> in the shrub layer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. A high diversity of species from the family Cactaceae is also present. The area contains gentle slopes and low mountains that facilitate storm water runoff to the lowlands. Annual rainfall averages 350 mm, and annual average temperature ranges from 10 to 20 °C [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Altitude ranges from 2000 to 2300 m.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Study area. Location of sampling sites at the “Ixtlera” region in northern San Luis Potosi, Mexico</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13071_2016_1569_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the early 1930’s, a large portion of the expropriated land within the Mexican territory was given to local communities, and thus tenure in these lands was established in the “ejido” scheme. At this time, regional economies incentivized 
  <span class="italic">Yucca</span> extraction for “Ixtle” production. Overgrazing was also established as an additional form of local economic subsistence. Because these economic activities continue to date, shrubland habitat degradation through the growth of villages, extraction of tree species, and overgrazing in their surrounding still prevail, thus creating a habitat gradient consisting of at least the following habitat types [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]: (i) “Isotal”, thereafter moderately degraded shrublands, where grazing and tree extraction is moderate; (ii) microphylous shrublands dominated by creosote bush in which the tree layer has been eliminated and intense goat grazing is ongoing, thereafter highly degraded shrublands; and (iii) villages where the natural vegetation has been almost completely removed and substituted by houses and unpaved roads. Three sampling sites representative of these levels of habitat degradation were established in each ejido. In each study site, bird communities were surveyed, and blood samples from birds were taken according to the methods described below.
 </p>
</sec>
