<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this paper, we analyse life-history evolution in response to climate change in three rare plant species, 
 <italic class="italic">C. parviflorum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. candidum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ophrys sphegodes</italic> (all Orchidaceae). We focus on the evolution of sprouting probability because: (i) all of these species are capable of vegetative dormancy and (ii) vegetative dormancy, its causes and its evolutionary benefits are still poorly understood. The results of this study may, therefore, provide insights into its evolution and ecological function [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Shefferson 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] developed adaptive dynamics models, based on life histories of individual plants across 3-year periods, that accurately predict observed sprouting probabilities in 
 <italic class="italic">C. parviflorum</italic>. Unlike matrix and integral projection models, which are commonly used to parametrize adaptive dynamics models [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], these models included costs of growth and long-term costs of reproduction [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. We now extend these models to include observed sprouting responses to annual variation in climatic variables. We then use climate predictions from two state-of-the-art, spatially high-resolution general atmospheric circulation models [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], to predict patterns in the evolution of sprouting probabilities under realistic climate change scenarios. Because vegetative dormancy is believed to be a response to stress [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>], we hypothesize that sprouting probability will decline as a buffer against the risk of greater mortality in the face of the changing, novel climate conditions predicted for the future.
</p>
