<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">To evaluate how NDVI might change over the next decade (2020–2029) we developed a predictive multivariate model using a range of decadal scale climate and geospatial data inputs (Supplemental Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S7</xref>), selected as important predictors in the BRT analysis. However, because of the decadal scale input datasets
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup> we are unable to explicitly and directly evaluate year-specific observations of browning (i.e. 2011)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> within this modeling framework. We still were able to provide insights into potential controls on greenness. Generally, it has been postulated that recent observations of browning, may have arisen from an array of annual/seasonal regional/site level changes that are largely correlated with decadal climate and land cover datasets, such as the delayed onset of the growing season and longer snow cover
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>, summer cloudiness
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>, winter warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>, or thermokarst development
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Model NDVI forecasting (Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>) identified greening to likely continue on the ACP, but will be highly dependent on the amplitude of future climate change (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Predicted NDVI by 2020–2029 was found to be variable dependent on climate model and RCP (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>), but the magnitude in greening versus browning was generally explained by the inverse relationship between temperature and NDVI change, as the greater the temperature change the lower the NDVI. Generally, all simulations find regional specific browning to occur on the southwestern Chukchi coast and greening to occur on the northeastern Beaufort coastal plains but the magnitudes vary by climate model (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>).
</p>
