<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stratospheric ozone protects life on Earth by absorbing ultraviolet radiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. In polar regions, stratospheric ozone depletion results in a temperature decrease in the stratosphere through a strong radiative cooling effect, which enhances the meridional gradient of temperature and westerly winds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. The process eventually leads to a stronger polar vortex, which has a significant influence on the tropospheric climate in both hemispheres
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. This phenomenon is much stronger in the Antarctic than in the Arctic.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent years, the impacts of stratospheric ozone on climate changes have received widespread attention. The connection between Arctic stratospheric ozone (ASO) variations and tropospheric climate change over the Northern Hemisphere has been revealed in observations and simulations. As early as the 1990s, some studies noted a significant surface temperature warming trend in the mid-to-high latitudes of the Eurasian continent since the late 1970s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Though inevitably connected to the increase in atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations, the warming trend was also found to be strongly associated with enhanced westerly winds caused by ASO depletion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. A large fraction of the variability in the March–April surface temperature in certain regions of the Northern Hemisphere is associated with variations in March Arctic ozone from observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. Recently, numerous modeling studies have analyzed the possible linkage between ASO and tropospheric climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. Previous studies found that the signal of spring ASO changes can propagate to the ground, resulting in changes to the climate of the mid-to-high latitudes of the Northern Hemisphere; this includes changes to sea level pressure (SLP) and the tropospheric jet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Based on observations and simulations, it is found that the northern stratospheric circulation anomalies induced by ASO radiative anomalies could cause North Pacific SST anomalies (Victoria Mode anomalies)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. The SST anomalies link to the North Pacific circulation that in turn influences El Niño–Southern Oscillation (ENSO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> and tropical rainfall
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to substantial emissions of ozone-depleting substances, Antarctic stratospheric ozone losses exceeded 40% of the total ozone at the end of the 20th century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. The Antarctic ozone hole has been shown to have a significant influence on the Southern Hemispheric climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. Some studies pointed out that the signal of enhanced winds related to the Southern Annular Mode can extend from the stratosphere to the surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, causing climate warming on the eastern Antarctic Peninsula and cooling in the Antarctic interior during recent decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, although other studies suggesting that the warming and cooling trends may be a manifestation of natural variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Previous studies demonstrated that stratospheric cooling caused by the Antarctic ozone hole resulted in a poleward shift of the extratropical westerly jet and extension of the Hadley cell in the Southern Hemisphere during austral summer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, the displacement of the westerly jet was also associated with a poleward shift of the subtropical dry zone, with increased rainfall in mid latitudes and reduced rainfall in the high latitudes of the Southern Hemisphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. In addition, it has been shown that the variations in storm tracks and ocean circulation in the Southern Hemisphere were clearly affected by the Antarctic ozone hole
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies showed that the variations in stratospheric ozone in the northern and southern high latitudes could significantly influence climate changes of Northern and Southern hemispheres. This inspires us to check whether the ozone forcing in our climate model is in agreement with observations. If there is a significant difference between the ozone forcing and the observed ozone variations, it is likely to have a negative impact on the quality of the simulation results.</p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigate the stratospheric ozone forcing in a fully coupled global climate model, the Community Earth System Model (CESM) Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model, version 4 (WACCM4) with WACCM4-GHG scheme (more details of the model are given in section Simulations and Data), and compare the ozone variations specified in the model with observations. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> shows the correlation coefficients between the stratospheric ozone variations from WACCM4 model forcing (based on CMIP5 ozone output) and Stratospheric Water and OzOne Satellite Homogenized (SWOOSH) (see the data description in section Simulations and Data). It is found that the stratospheric ozone variations in the WACCM4, which is based on CMIP5 ozone output, are well correlated with the observations in mid and lower latitudes, but not in the high latitudes of the Northern and Southern hemispheres. It is because ozone in the polar vortex regions has much higher variability than lower latitudes which might require much larger ensemble size to capture the observed ozone variations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b and c</a> shows the variations in stratospheric ozone averaged over the region 60°–90°N and 150–30 hPa and in the region 60°–90°S and 200–50 hPa for the period 1979 to 2015, respectively. The both variations in ozone from WACCM4 forcing data (based on CMIP5 ozone output) and from observations (SWOOSH) showed a clear decreasing trend from 1979 to 2005 in the stratosphere at the two poles. However, the ozone variability in WACCM4 is evidently different from that in observations in the two regions. These results can be further confirmed by observations from Global Ozone Chemistry and Related trace gas Data Records for the Stratosphere (GOZCARDS) (see section Simulations and Data, data description) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d–f</a>). Note that in these two regions the variability and depletion of ozone concentration are most pronounced
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span> and have the most important influence on surface climate in the Northern and Southern hemispheres
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison of forcing ozone and observed ozone. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Correlation coefficients between stratospheric ozone variations in the WACCM4 model input data and in SWOOSH for the period 1979–2005. Input data is the standard CESM ozone forcing used in WACCM4. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Variations in stratospheric ozone averaged over the region 60–90°N and 150–50 hPa from WACCM4 model input data (blue line) and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) over the region 60–90°S and 200–100 hPa from SWOOSH (red line). (
     <span class="bold">d</span>–
     <span class="bold">f</span>) Same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">c</span>), but for stratospheric ozone from WACCM4 model input data (blue line) and GOZCARDS (red line). (
     <span class="bold">g</span>–
     <span class="bold">i</span>) Same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">c</span>), but for stratospheric ozone from MERRA2 (blue line) and SWOOSH (red line). (
     <span class="bold">j</span>–
     <span class="bold">l</span>) Same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">c</span>), but for stratospheric ozone from MERRA2 (blue line) and from GOZCARDS (red line).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_32656_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e511" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a–f</a> shows that although the trend of stratospheric ozone is well represented in the WACCM4, the stratospheric ozone variability from the WACCM4 is not in good agreement with the observed stratospheric ozone variability in the high latitudes. This poor agreement is also found in many other climate models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. It is well known that a large number of model evaluation studies showed that although the simulated spatial patterns of climatic elements in historical experiments from Coupled Model Intercomparison Project 3 (CMIP 3) to CMIP 5 are closer to the observations, the simulated variability of these climatic elements needs further improvement. Here, we pose a question: if we replace the ozone forcing in WACCM4 with ozone data that have variations closer to those observed, would this help to improve the simulated climatic elements in the reproduced experiments by WACCM4?
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1g</a> shows the correlation coefficients between stratospheric ozone variations from MERRA2 and SWOOSH (see section Simulations and Data of the data description). It is found that the stratospheric ozone variations from MERRA2 not only have a good correlation with those from SWOOSH in the mid and lower latitudes but also in the high latitudes in both hemispheres. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1h,i</a> shows the variations in stratospheric ozone averaged over the region 60°–90°N and 150–30 hPa and over the region 60°–90°S and 200–50 hPa, respectively. The ozone variability based on MERRA2 is in good agreement with that based on SWOOSH over these two regions. These results can be further confirmed by the observations from GOZCARDS (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1j–l</a>) (see section Simulations and Data). Replacing the originally specified stratospheric ozone forcing in WACCM4 by MERRA2 ozone to perform the historical experiment would help to test the sensitivity of the simulated climate to stratospheric ozone forcing. Note that MERRA2 ozone data are used because they have no missing values in the stratosphere compared with ozone from SWOOSH and GOZCARDS. The global surface temperature variability partly reflects the characteristics of global climate change. In this study, we choose the surface temperature to check whether improving the stratospheric ozone variability improves the simulation of global climate change in WACCM4. The experimental design is described in the next section.
 </p>
</sec>
