<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulations and Data</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the National Center for Atmospheric Research’s CESM, version 1.0.6, which is a fully coupled global climate model that incorporates an interactive atmosphere (CAM/WACCM) component, ocean (POP2), land (CLM4), and sea ice (CICE). For the atmospheric component, we used version 4 of WACCM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>. WACCM4 is a climate model that has detailed middle-atmosphere chemistry and a finite volume dynamical core, and it extends from the surface to approximately 140 km. For our study, we disabled the interactive chemistry (WACCM-GHG scheme). WACCM4 has 66 vertical levels, with a vertical resolution of about 1 km in the tropical tropopause and lower stratosphere layers. Simulations used a horizontal resolution of 1.9° × 2.5° (latitude × longitude) for the atmosphere and approximately the same for the ocean.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eight transient experiments (E
  <sub>1</sub>–E
  <sub>8</sub>) with the fully coupled ocean incorporated both natural and anthropogenic external forcings, including spectrally resolved solar variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, transient greenhouse gases (GHGs) (from scenario A1B of IPCC 2001), volcanic aerosols (from the Stratospheric Processes and their Role in Climate (SPARC) Chemistry–Climate Model Validation (CCMVal) REF-B2 scenario recommendations), a nudged quasi-biennial oscillation (QBO) (the time series in CESM is determined from the observed climatology over the period 1955–2005), and specified ozone forcing derived from the CMIP5 ensemble mean ozone output. An overview of all coupled experiments (E
  <sub>1</sub>–E
  <sub>8</sub>) is given in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. All the forcing data used in this study are available from the CESM model input data repository.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ozone values were obtained from the Stratospheric Water and OzOne Satellite Homogenized (SWOOSH) dataset, which is a merged record of stratospheric ozone and water vapor measurements taken by a number of limb sounding and solar occultation satellites over the previous 30 years, spanning 1984 to 2013
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>. Moreover, its primary product is a monthly-mean zonal-mean gridded dataset containing ozone and water vapor data from the SAGE-II/III, UARS HALOE, UARS MLS, and Aura MLS instruments. The horizontal resolution and vertical pressure range of the ozone data are 2.5° zonal mean (latitude: 89°S to 89°N) and 316–1 hPa (31 levels), respectively. Another ozone dataset is available from the Global Ozone Chemistry and Related trace gas Data Records for the Stratosphere (GOZCARDS, 1984–2013) project
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>. The zonal mean satellite–based GOZCARDS (1984–2013) is produced from high quality data from past missions (e.g., SAGE, HALOE data) as well as ongoing missions (ACE-FTS and Aura MLS). Its meridional resolution is 10° with 25 pressure levels from the surface up to 0.1 hPa. MERRA2 ozone (longitude × latitude resolution: 0.5° × 0.5°) uses 72 pressure levels from the surface up to 0.1 hPa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>. The vertical resolution of MERRA2 is ~1–2 km in the upper troposphere and lower stratosphere (UTLS) and 2–4 km in the middle and upper stratosphere. MERRA2 is produced using the Goddard Earth Observing System Model, Version 5 (GEOS-5) with ozone from the Solar Backscattered Ultra Violet (SBUV) radiometers from October 1978 to October 2004, and thereafter from the Ozone Monitoring Instrument (OMI) and AURA Microwave Limb Sounder (MLS)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span> (Bosilovich 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2015). The MERRA2 reanalysis ozone compares well with satellite ozone observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span> and represents the QBO and stratospheric ozone better than MERRA1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global surface temperature data is from the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies (GISS) Surface Temperature Analysis (GISTEMP)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
  </span>. GISTEMP combines land surface air temperatures primarily from the GHCN-M version 3 with sea surface temperature (SST) data from the ERSSTv3b analysis into a comprehensive global surface temperature data set spanning the period from 1880 to the present at monthly resolution, on a 2° × 2° latitude–longitude grid. The other surface temperature dataset used in this paper is version 4 of HadCRUT4, which is a set of reanalysis monthly data at a horizontal resolution of 5° × 5° from the UK Met Office Hadley Centre and the University of East Anglia’s Climatic Research Unit
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>
  </span> that combines the global land surface temperature data set, CRUTEM4, and the global SST data set, HadSST3. SST data were obtained from the UK Met Office Hadley Centre for Climate Prediction and Research SST (HadSST) field datasets. Geopotential height, temperature, and zonal wind were obtained from the ERA-Interim reanalysis.
 </p>
</sec>
