<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">First, we estimated how much PD would be lost across the entire phylogeny of monocots if all genera occurring on a given island went extinct. To do so, we simulated the “loss” of an island, i.e. local extinction of all its taxa. We then estimated the probability of extinction for each genus on an island as the expected proportion of the genus’ global range lost if the island would disappear. Geographic range has been found to be one of the main predictors of species extinction risk, but presence-only data and the huge number of islands and species studied here did not allow assessing individual species range size. Yet, changes in the number of localities where a species occurs is also an essential factor of extinction risk and is used in the criteria B of the IUCN Red List threat status. In our analysis, species range was therefore measured as the number of islands a genus occurs on. This posits that each island equally contributes to a genus’ survival and, therefore probabilities of extinction are given by the proportion of native islands from which a genus disappears. Following Faith
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, each branch of the phylogenetic tree was weighted by the product of the extinction probabilities of all its descendants, 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>. equal to the proportion of the range lost for each genera found on the “lost” island and equal to 0 for all other genera. The branches supporting genera which had not lost any proportion of their range were considered safe (probability of extinction equal to 0). We calculated the expected loss of insular PD following the loss of a given island as the sum of weighted branch lengths (
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>; Eq. 
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>). This measure estimates how much PD is expected to be lost on a global scale following local extinctions on a given island. It also allows us to consider the phylogenetic complementarity of extinction risks, i.e. the shared responsibility of taxa to safeguard deep branches
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>.
 <disp-formula id="Equ1">
  <label>1</label>
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ExpPDloss(tree,\,proba)=\sum _{b}{L}_{b}\,\prod _{{k}_{b}}{p}_{{k}_{b}}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M2" display="block">
    <mi>E</mi>
    <mi>x</mi>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mi>P</mi>
    <mi>D</mi>
    <mi>l</mi>
    <mi>o</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mi>s</mi>
    <mrow>
     <mo stretchy="true">(</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mi>t</mi>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>e</mi>
      <mi>e</mi>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mspace width=".25em"/>
      <mi>p</mi>
      <mi>r</mi>
      <mi>o</mi>
      <mi>b</mi>
      <mi>a</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo stretchy="true">)</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <munder>
     <mo>∑</mo>
     <mi>b</mi>
    </munder>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi>L</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>b</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mspace width=".25em"/>
    <munder>
     <mo>∏</mo>
     <mrow>
      <msub>
       <mrow>
        <mi>k</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi>b</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
     </mrow>
    </munder>
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi>p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <msub>
       <mrow>
        <mi>k</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi>b</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
      <mspace width=".25em"/>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>k</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>b</italic>
 </sub> designates the 
 <italic>k</italic>
 <sup>th</sup> descendant of branch 
 <italic>b</italic> on the tree, 
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>kb</italic>
 </sub> is the extinction probability of the 
 <italic>k</italic>
 <sup>th</sup> descendant of branch 
 <italic>b</italic>, and L
 <sub>
  <italic>b</italic>
 </sub> is the length of branch 
 <italic>b</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
