<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">In the “
 <xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" class="xref">CMIP5 simulation of Sahel rainfall</xref>” section, we show that the CMIP5 multi-model mean reproduces the twentieth century evolution of Sahel rainfall, rendering discussion of its attribution to external forcing possible. In the “
 <xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Climate change in the Sahel through the lens of oceanic influence</xref>” section, we propose an explanation that reconciles studies of variability, which typically seek to relate oceanic forcing and regional rainfall response, with studies of change, which typically seek to attribute regional response to external forcing, natural or anthropogenic, by developing an argument for indirect attribution of Sahel rainfall, through the influence of anthropogenic emissions on sea surface temperatures. In the “
 <xref rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Transformation of predictors</xref>” sub-section, we exploit Singular Value Decomposition (SVD) to describe the linearly independent linear combinations of the two SST predictors defined above, i.e., the averages of sub-tropical North Atlantic and global tropical SSTs. In the “
 <xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Linear regressions of Sahel rainfall</xref>” sub-section, we use the resulting singular vectors in bivariate linear regressions that describe their influence on Sahel rainfall. We present explicit formulas for these SVD-based predictors in the bivariate case; although, as noted by Preisendorfer (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">1988</xref>), such formulas had been available since a publication by Pearson (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">1901</xref>), their presentation in terms of non-dimensional parameters, introduced here, helps to visualize the underlying relationships and facilitates the interpretation of results. In particular, we show that when the ratio of standard deviations of the original predictors is close to one, the bivariate SVD rotation results in the sum and difference of these original predictor time series. In our case, this means that NARI, the difference of NA and GT, which we defined above based on a physical argument, is nearly proportional to one of the SVD predictors and is exhaustively complemented by the other, which is nearly proportional to the sum of the same SST indices, and represents global warming. The derivation of all necessary formulas is relegated to the Appendix. In the “Conclusions: Past is not prologue” section, we conclude with a synthesis that finds coherence in attributing past Sahel drought to anthropogenic emissions, while lending credence to projections of a wetter future.
</p>
