<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Projected variations in global temperature as a consequence of climate change have underscored renewed interest in addressing questions about temperature-dependent organismal performance [
 <xref rid="B1-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The re-emergence of emphasis on ecological physiology of organisms is rooted in the notion that physiological traits are strong determinants of species response to climate change [
 <xref rid="B6-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In light of the climate change phenomenon, what mechanisms underlie organismal response to environmental temperature variations? In an attempt to establish the foundation for continuing investigations addressing this central question, this study was designed to explore the effects of temperature on whole-organism performance, specifically prey-capture kinematics, in three orders of invasive-teleost fishes. To our knowledge, these are the first three invasive species used to investigate the effects of environmental temperature on feeding kinematics in light of climate change. The use of invasive fishes to examine temperature-dependent performance increases the relevance of this study because of the belief that the coupled effects of climate change and species invasion on ecosystems are more alarming than the effects of each taken independently [
 <xref rid="B14-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. It is predicted that, as a consequence of global warming, tropical invasive species expand their range poleward, thus, extending their well-known negative biological impacts to previously undisturbed, high-latitude ecosystems [
 <xref rid="B14-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>].
</p>
