<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effects of environmental temperature on physiological processes are widespread in both animals and plants, but in fishes its effects on skeletal-muscle performance and property have been the focus of most basic and applied physiological studies. It is expected that the direct effects of environmental temperature on body temperature mediate physiological processes, most especially metabolic rate. In fishes, as with any poikilothermic vertebrate, physiological performance peaks at a narrow range of body temperature, and environmental temperature remains a major constraint in their range of distribution [
 <xref rid="B4-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Metabolic rate, in general, and contraction rate of skeletal muscle fibers, in particular, increase with environmental temperature until a threshold level is achieved, after which these rates decline with further increase in environmental temperature [
 <xref rid="B18-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. The ability of an individual to perform a certain task (e.g., prey capture) driven by a temperature-dependent process (e.g., rate of contraction of buccal-expansion muscles) is constrained by the reduction in biological rates as a consequence of decrease in environmental temperature. Furthermore, the expression of temperature-induced changes in fish-muscle physiology varies according to different temporal scales (i.e., daily, seasonal, or life-history, developmental time scales) and levels of organization (i.e., from molecular to organismal to ecosystem) [
 <xref rid="B27-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. For example, intracellular and extracellular ionic concentration and acid balance are destabilized by instant changes in environmental temperature [
 <xref rid="B28-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Seasonal temperature change may induce modifications of the properties and composition of the contractile elements of the muscle fiber [
 <xref rid="B27-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. This time scale may allow fish to acclimate to the new ambient temperature and drive plastic response in muscle-fiber phenotypes and trigger behavioral and other mechanisms that buffer temperature effects and maintain homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B28-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. At the whole-organism level, responses to environmental temperature change may be taxon- and ontogenetic- specific. Indeed, environmental temperature has a profound influence on the fish’s ability to successfully accomplish relevant tasks such as swimming, feeding, mating, and escaping from predators.
</p>
