<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Age-class challenges</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the challenges of captive breeding long-lived, slowly maturing species with ambiguous phenotypic sex differences is planning effective releases which will offer optimal sex ratios. Ploughshares reach sexual maturity at approximately 300 mm carapace length, and males can be distinguished from females using secondary sexual characteristics at about 350 mm carapace length [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref048">48</a>]. Size and age are generally correlated in chelonians, and those animals from 300–350 mm carapace length are estimated to be approximately 20–25 years old. If the sex of an animal is unknown for 15–25 years, as in this and many other chelonian species, a conservation strategy may be severely impaired or carried out without enough information to be successful. This has been an ongoing challenge for chelonian conservation management plans in general [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref101">101</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref102">102</a>]. One option for premature sexing of chelonians is the investigation of circulating hormone concentrations. It has been suggested that T concentrations may be used a biomarker to distinguish between the sexes in sub-adult chelonians and has been used successfully in 
  <span class="italic">Caretta caretta</span> (loggerhead sea turtles) and 
  <span class="italic">Gopherus agassizii</span> (desert tortoises; [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref103">103</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref105" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref105">105</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, wild sub-adults could be distinguished from wild males via higher CORT and lower T. The trend of lower T than adult males is carried over among all the study populations. Plasma T concentrations were no different in sub-adults than females, but were significantly different than adult males. This suggests that sub-adult individuals exhibiting high T concentrations, especially during peak T months for adult males, could be assigned as male. In this species, it appears as though any T detection higher than 20 ng/mL from a sub-adult during the months October–November housed in Madagascar, or one housed in the U.S. during April–May, could be assigned as male relatively confidently; however, we caution that more directed investigations be done to hone the method. Additionally, if female hormones are to be investigated for this purpose, we suggest using E2 over P as the single male sample we ran for both hormones did exhibit detectable P, but not E2.</p>
</sec>
