<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Endocrine control of reproductive cycles in ectotherms is generally documented using monthly mean hormone concentrations, which ebb and flow, peaking multiple times a year for species that nest multiply [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref062">62</a>]. To characterize baseline and variation in reproductive and stress hormones of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span>, we conducted surveys for, and sampled animals from, both wild and captive populations throughout three years (2013–2015).
 </p>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animals, populations, and sampling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As part of another study, we conducted distance and meandering transect surveys in four areas where remaining natural and wild populations of 
   <span class="italic">A</span>. 
   <span class="italic">yniphora</span> are known to occur [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref045">45</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref049">49</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref051">51</a>] from early 2013 through late 2015. We sampled animals opportunistically during surveys and tracking. Sampling occurred during both the animals’ natural active seasons (wet season; November–April) and inactive seasons (dry season; May–October) during 2013–2015. Courtship, mating, and nesting are seasonal and generally occur from December through May. Upon detection, we first collected a blood sample, animal weight (g) using spring scales, maximum carapace length (MCL; mm) using calipers, visually sexed using secondary sexual characteristics (as described in [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref048">48</a>]), observed activity prior to disturbance (walking, resting in open, resting in vegetation, eating, basking, or other), and environmental variables (air and ground temperatures, ground humidity, cloud cover, and vegetation cover) as described in [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref063">63</a>]. Upon capture, each animal was individually PIT tagged and uniquely marked using a fine saw blade to create notches along the marginal scutes following a modified Cagle scheme [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref064">64</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref066">66</a>]. Tracked animals were identified by those identifiers and associated transmitter frequencies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two captive populations (Madagascar and USA) were sampled for comparison to wild animals. The Malagasy population is located approximately 160 km from the native range in northwestern Madagascar, managed by Durrell Wildlife Conservation Trust and is the only known successfully breeding captive population of 
   <span class="italic">A</span>. 
   <span class="italic">yniphora</span> in the world [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref061">61</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref067">67</a>]. The much smaller U.S. population in the opposing global hemisphere was included as an outgroup for comparison. The U.S. population is housed at the Behler Chelonian Center in southern California, is managed by Turtle Conservancy, and began recording courtship and nesting activities within the group in November 2013. Details on the captive husbandry of these facilities were not recorded for the purposes of this study. We sampled these populations monthly whenever possible from 2013 through 2015. We included 16 males, 21 females, and 42 sub-adults from the Madagascar captive population and the single male, the two females, and 10 sub-adults from the U.S. captive population. In both populations, individuals were frequently paired for mating and monitored by staff. Pairings between adult individuals were recorded.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We collected blood samples (~1 cc) from the subcarapacial sinus [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref068">68</a>] using a 23-gauge needle on a 3-cc syringe. This method calls for minimal restraint and does not require head or limb extraction, which reduces distress during sampling [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref069">69</a>]. Blood samples that were collected at facilities with electricity were processed following the procedure described in [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref070">70</a>]. We modified this procedure when in the field in remote Madagascar (see details in [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref071">71</a>]). Briefly, we placed wild animal samples into heparinized vials and onto cool packs in an insulated bag while completing surveys and hiking back to camp (generally within 5 hours), where we field centrifuged samples using solar-stored power, pipetted plasma to a cryovial, and immediately submerged tubes in liquid nitrogen for field storage until transfer to a -20° freezer (generally within 1–4 weeks; [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref071">71</a>]). Samples were imported to the U.S. on dry ice and all samples were transferred to a -80°C cryogenic freezer at the laboratory. All animals were handled per the USC Institutional Care and Use Committee Protocol #12046. Passes and permits for this work were acquired through Madagascar National Parks and the Ministry of Environment, Ecology, and Forests. (permit #s 008/13, 009/13, 214/13, 271/13, 112/14, 129/14, 005/15, 006/15, and 035/16). Samples were exported from Madagascar and imported to the USA under permit from the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES) (export permit #118C-EA03/MG15, import permit #14US34804B/9).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand natural variation in stress and give us the ability to compare with captive populations, we quantified plasma corticosterone (CORT) using enzyme immunoassays (Cayman Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI, USA; kit #500655) as in [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref071">71</a>]. All samples were run in duplicate or triplicate and any pair with coefficient of variation (CV) greater than 15% were re-analyzed. Inter- and intra-assay CVs were 5% or less. The assay platform was validated for use in 
   <span class="italic">A</span>. 
   <span class="italic">yniphora</span>. Serial dilutions of pooled plasma yielded curves that were parallel to the standard curve (ANCOVA, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.05). Accuracy was assessed using recovery of known standard additions to pooled plasma (
   <span class="italic">r</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.98; mean recovery = 94.3 ± 4.2%).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radioimmunoassays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To gain a clear picture of reproductive cycles and potential in each population, we measured plasma concentrations of Testosterone (T), estradiol-17β (E2), and progesterone (P) using commercially available radioimmunoassay kits (Immuno-Biological Laboratories Inc., Minneapolis, MN. #KIR1709 [T], #KIP0629 [E2], and #KIP1458 [P]). Kits were validated using pooled plasma samples to perform serial dilutions compared against standard curves. Dilutions displayed parallelism to the standard curves, indicating that binding affinities were similar in samples and kit standards (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182004.g002" href="#pone.0182004.g002">Fig 2</a>). Recovery of added standards averaged 96.2 ± 2.3%, 102.3 ± 3.2%, 98.3± 3.1% for T, E2, &amp; P respectively. Each sample was run in duplicate and inter-assay variation averaged 1.8–5.1%. Assay sensitivities were 0.05 ng/mL (T), 2.7 pg/mL (E2), and 0.05 ng/mL (P).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0182004.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0182004.g002</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Radioimmunoassay hormone validation curves for 
     <span class="italic">Astrochelys yniphora</span>.
    </div>
    <p>Closed circles are standards, open circles are serial diluted pooled plasma samples.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0182004.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body condition scores (BCSs) were determined by regressing all records of body weight by their corresponding MCL of each animal, fitting a second degree polynomial curve to the point spread (
   <span class="italic">r</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.91; e.g., [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref048">48</a>]), and calculating the residuals of each point from that line. Negative values represent animals with body conditions below the line (fitted mean). To evaluate seasonal body condition, stress, and reproductive hormone concentrations, we grouped plasma hormone concentrations by population, sex, and/or month. We used linear mixed models (LMM) with animal ID as the repeated measure to test for differences within or between the groupings. When significant differences were present we performed post-hoc comparisons of groups using Tukey HSD. Model residuals were visually assessed for approximate normality and homoscedascity. All analyses were performed in JMP statistical software [
   <a rid="pone.0182004.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref072">72</a>] and significance was determined at 
   <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
