<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environment and behaviors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Air temperatures, ground temperatures, humidities, and cloud cover were significantly different between months and populations (all 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.0001; 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0182004.t001" href="#pone.0182004.t001">Table 1</a>). Temperatures selected for by animals (ground temperatures) in the wild population remained relatively constant over time (averaging 33.2°C) with a couple exceptions that correspond to other measurable changes in hormones and BCS, and were generally higher overall than the captive populations. The selected monthly temperatures varied more widely in both captive populations than the wild population (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182004.g009" href="#pone.0182004.g009">Fig 9</a>). In all populations, males preferred overall cooler temperatures than females or sub-adults, with the highest temperatures preferred by sub-adults (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0182004.t001" href="#pone.0182004.t001">Table 1</a>). Vegetation cover where animals were found was different between months (e.g., seasonality; 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>11,254</sub> = 3.974, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.0001), but not between populations.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0182004.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0182004.g009</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Environmental factors associated with 
    <span class="italic">Astrochelys yniphora</span>.
   </div>
   <p>Mean air temperature, ground temperature, and ground humidity by month and sex at 
    <span class="italic">A</span>. 
    <span class="italic">yniphora</span> locations between the two Madagascar populations from 2012–2015.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0182004.g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We detected differences in the distribution of activity exhibited by the animals between the populations (L-R 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 135.606, df = 10, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.0001; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182004.g010" href="#pone.0182004.g010">Fig 10</a>), but not between the sexes. Concordantly, observed animal activity also differed by ground humidity (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 17.631, df = 4, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0015), cloud cover (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 11.840, df = 4, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0186), and vegetation cover (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 15.747, df = 4, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0034). When separated by population, we further found differences. Animals in the wild were more often found to be under vegetation than either of the captive populations, while the Madagascar captive were more often eating and walking (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182004.g010" href="#pone.0182004.g010">Fig 10</a>). Of the variables measured, wild 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> activity was most affected by ground temperature and humidity (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 62.062, df = 32, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0011); where low temperatures (32.8 ± 0.37°C) and humidities (62.1 ± 1.6%) were associated with resting in vegetation while higher temperatures (33.7 ± 0.8°C) were associated with eating and resting in the open, and higher humidities (74.3 ± 2.7%) were associated with resting in the open and walking. For the Madagascar captives, we found that ground humidity, cloud cover, and vegetation cover had significant effects on activity (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 40.553, df = 21, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0064). Madagascar captives would more often be walking in higher humidity (75.0 ± 1.9%) and vegetation cover (56.7 ± 3.7%), resting in the open when cloud cover was higher (53.7 ± 3.2%), and eating and resting in the vegetation in lower cloud cover (33.8 ± 13.8%) and vegetation covered areas (35.8 ± 11.4%). In the U.S. captive population, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> activity was most affected by air temperature (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 8318, df = 2, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0156). U.S. captive animals were more often resting in the open or walking in higher temperatures (32.2 ± 2.0°C), and eating, basking, or exhibiting reproductive behaviors in cooler temperatures (25.2 ± 2.5°C).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0182004.g010" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0182004.g010</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 10</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Observed activity of 
    <span class="italic">Astrochelys yniphora</span> populations.
   </div>
   <p>Percent of total observed activity of 
    <span class="italic">A</span>. 
    <span class="italic">yniphora</span> from three populations (wild, Madagascar Captive, and U.S. Captive).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0182004.g010" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigated environmental variables’ influence on activity by month in the Madagascar populations for which we had enough data. In the month of December, wild 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> behaviors depended on ground temperatures, finding warmer temperatures (37.5 ± 1.0°C) in vegetation as opposed to in the open (32.5 ± 1.0°C; 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>3,12</sub> = 3.826, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0391). They were found eating and walking much more in February when there was high cloud cover (70–90 ± 20.6%) opposed to only resting when cloud cover was low (22–24 ± 9.0%; 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>3,15</sub> = 4.300, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0223). For the Madagascar captive population, air and ground temperatures and ground humidity in November separated walking (35.5 ± 0.5°C, 64.1 ± 1.2%) and resting activities (32.5 ± 0.3°C, 53.2 ± 1.8%; all 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,21</sub> = 20.0–25.8, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.0002). In May, the Madagascar captives’ activity was also associated with environment, where air temperature, ground temperature, cloud cover, and vegetation cover, resting in higher temperatures and vegetation cover under lower cloud cover (all 
  <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.0172).
 </p>
</sec>
