<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessing the relative extinction risk of a species depends on the population size, genetic diversity, distribution, demographics, stressors, life history traits, and threats, amid other criteria. These risks are evaluated by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN), which publishes conservation statuses in the IUCN Red List to highlight those species at higher risk (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.iucnredlist.org</span>). The IUCN Red List defines a taxon as Critically Endangered (CR) when data indicates that the species is facing an extremely high risk of extinction in the wild defined by a high percentage and recent population size reduction, a highly restricted geographic range, a very low adult population size estimate, or a high probability of extinction in the wild within 10 years. This designation is superseded by Extinct in the Wild (EW) if extensive surveys fail to record any animal of a species within its expected range or habitat. It may be only a few combined factors that cause a CR species to become EW; the risk of extinction increases and the recovery efforts become more challenging if we lack natural ecological information [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref001">1</a>]. Conservation strategies for CR wildlife involves the captive breeding of wild-caught individuals for enhancing the captive gene pool and repatriation to native habitats, in what have come to be known as assurance colonies. As with all conservation management plans, the captive breeding approach is accompanied by a variety of challenges [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref001">1</a>]. Successful relocation, including to captivity, is dependent upon knowledge of biological constraints (e.g., natural environmental and habitat requirements) as well as basic ecology and health parameters [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref005">5</a>]; information that is often unavailable in emergency recovery situations [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref006">6</a>]. In addition, animals can become stressed in captivity, making reproduction physiologically impossible [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref007">7</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref009">9</a>]. There are successes, however; animal populations reduced to functionally extinct numbers have been taken from the wild into captivity and, over time, brought into reproductive condition such as the California condor and black-footed ferret. Those successes came through multiple studies on reproduction, mirroring wild conditions, social behavior, and more [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref010">10</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref013">13</a>]. The captive breeding and eventual repatriation of these individuals and their offspring to native habitats was arguably the single most important step for the survival of the species [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref001">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Creating and maintaining captive husbandry conditions that promote natural behaviors, health, and reproductively viable individuals is challenging, particularly when little ecological information exists for rare/elusive taxa. These challenges are confounded by the protracted survival probability curve in long-lived species [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref014">14</a>]. This is pertinent with CR species in particular, as effective captive breeding colonies may one day act as source populations for extirpated wild ones (i.e., assurance colonies). Understanding typical seasonal environmental and physiological patterns in natural populations (i.e., baseline) should be the standard to which we compare captive populations. We can use baseline variation of body conditions (natural seasonal fluctuation in size and weight) and temporal changes of hormone concentrations, activity, and environmental fluctuations recorded in wild populations to evaluate health of captive populations because these factors relate to aspects of stress and reproduction (e.g., immune function, energy budgets, behavior, etc.; [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref015">15</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref017">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stress is a physiological response to a perceived threat. It can greatly affect an animal’s ability to cope with changes in environment. Though adaptive in the short term, the stress response can disrupt normal, seasonal processes such as reproduction [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref018">18</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref019">19</a>]. When a perceived stressor occurs, the animal’s hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis is stimulated and begins to produce a cascade of hormones (catecholamines and glucocorticoids), triggering immediate behavioral and physiological responses intended to promote survival of the organism [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref020">20</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref021">21</a>]. When a stressor persists over longer periods of time (chronic stress), the HPA continues producing the glucocorticoid stress hormone, which can have far-reaching deleterious effects on diel and seasonal functions such as immune response and reproduction [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref022">22</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref025">25</a>]. Though the primary glucocorticoid stress hormone (CORT) in most mammals and fish is cortisol, it is corticosterone in reptiles and birds [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref026">26</a>]. The production of CORT can help the animal divert physiological resources from non-vital functions to those which will aid in short-term survival ([
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref027">27</a>]. An increase in the production of CORT elevates blood glucose concentrations and constrains the production on gonadal steroid secretions, growth, and immune system function as well as causes altered behaviors [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref019">19</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref020">20</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref028">28</a>]. Continued production of CORT above baseline values (baseline = unstressed concentrations; [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref029">29</a>] throughout a season and/or year(s) (i.e., chronic stress) may therefore prevent an animal from entering a reproductive state. For wild animals, particularly for those CR species under threat of extinction, the inability to reproduce in any given year might be the difference between population recovery and extirpation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animals may perceive various types of stressors depending on their surroundings and situation. In the wild, stressors may be in the form of environmental perturbations (e.g., extreme temperatures, drought, strong storms, etc.), human-wildlife conflict (e.g., encroaching agriculture, habitat harvesting, grazing, etc.), inter- and intraspecific interaction (e.g., invasive species or competition), or simply a lack of resources (e.g., cover, forage, mates, etc.). Altered activity patterns can be exhibited by stressed individuals, such as increased wandering behaviors in search of forage or mates, causing them to divert physiological resources from functions such as reproduction to survival [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref019">19</a>]. In captivity, activity and physiology may be altered due to stressors such as insufficient space, inadequate nutrition, limited environmental enrichment, continual human perturbation, etc. [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref030">30</a>]. Through the investigation of stress and reproductive hormones, we can determine the reproductive state of individuals and interpret seasonal hormone profiles to characterize populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reproductive rates and patterns are used as indicators of biological fitness [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref031">31</a>] and can be tracked or monitored physically and hormonally. Stress and reproductive state are exhibited by an animal through physical signs such as altered body condition and/or activity patterns [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref019">19</a>]. Clinically healthy and reproducing animals are generally described as being in better body condition (larger and heavier) and exhibiting normal activity (movement patterns and behaviors; [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref031">31</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref033">33</a>]). Defining and measuring clear categories of these indicators as well as associated environmental parameters in wild animal populations helps define baseline physical and ecological data of a particular species. Comparisons of endocrine hormone profiles along with environmental and behavioral data from wild populations will provide baseline values on a suite of ecophysiological parameters required for successful management.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of particular concern are CR reptiles because an ectotherm’s behavior and physiology are obligatorily tied to environmental conditions; even relatively minor environmental perturbations could have ongoing effects [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref034">34</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref037">37</a>]. These perturbations may cause years of altered behavior and health, making husbandry particularly difficult with these taxa. Temperature has been shown to be the most important cue for reproduction in reptiles [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref038">38</a>], so fluctuations in environmental temperatures can disrupt reproduction. Captive breeding and reintroductions of ectotherms can be successful, but past efforts emphasize the need for detailed analyses of multiple environmental factors alongside reproduction and health monitoring of animals themselves [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref039">39</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref040">40</a>]. When research science and captive management work together, key features which sustain healthy, wild populations are identified and implemented in captivity [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref041">41</a>]. Research needs to be conducted to assess the key environmental, ecological, and physiological parameters for ectotherms [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref042">42</a>], and a call has been made for habitat features to be closely evaluated for their importance in captive management situations [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref043">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigated the ecophysiology of a CR ectotherm from a biodiversity hotspot, Madagascar. All endemic Malagasy chelonians are threatened by extinction [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref044">44</a>], and Madagascar’s ploughshare tortoise (
  <span class="italic">Astrochelys yniphora</span>) is widely considered the most endangered tortoise species in the world [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref045">45</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref047">47</a>]. This is Madagascar’s largest chelonian species [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref048">48</a>] with a highly-domed shell, extended epiplastral projection, a unique golden color, (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182004.g001" href="#pone.0182004.g001">Fig 1</a>) and a highly restricted in range [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref049">49</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref051">51</a>]. Until very recently, population estimates of this species hovered around 400 [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref050">50</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref052">52</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref054">54</a>], but since January 2016, this species is close to extirpation at all four of their historically wild locations [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref055">55</a>]. Previous declines were attributed to various threats including brush fires, bush pigs, habitat loss, and collection for pets [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref044">44</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref046">46</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref056">56</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref057">57</a>]. But it is the very recent and dramatic increase in collection for the illicit pet trade of this “golden tortoise” that is causing the present precipitous drop; perhaps already falling into an EW designation [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref055">55</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref058">58</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref059">59</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0182004.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0182004.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Wild 
    <span class="italic">Astrochelys yniphora</span> in its native habitats.
   </div>
   <p>This “golden tortoise” is near extinct in the wild (EW) due to wildlife smugglers.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0182004.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to past and ongoing threats to the species, the development of captive assurance colonies is being considered, but successful reproduction over multiple generations has thus far only occurred in one captive collection, which is very near to the species’ native range. Little is known about reproductive state and seasonality in wild 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref060">60</a>], though behavioral studies have documented mating and nesting activities [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref050">50</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref061">61</a>]. Understanding the reproductive physiological changes that wild ectotherms undergo, along with those of the successfully reproducing captive animals, will give conservation managers a baseline from which to gauge successes and challenges. Using 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> as a model, we aimed to: 1) characterize baseline and seasonal patterns of stress and reproductive hormones in a CR ectotherm and use those characterizations to test; 2) if those characterizations relate to body condition and activity; 3) whether captivity affects stress, reproduction, and body condition of animals; and 4) which key environmental factors influence herpetofauna health and behaviors for use in captive management.
 </p>
</sec>
