<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec018" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Females</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Female ploughshares produce 2–5 eggs per clutch, and have been seen to clutch multiply in both captivity and in the wild [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref061">61</a>]. They have been reported to produce an average of 1.5–6.4 clutches depending on individual and location, but individuals in captivity produce both more clutches and more eggs per clutch than their wild counterparts as well as extend their nesting period into later months [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref061">61</a>]. Increases in E2 are associated with vitellogenesis and ovulation, while P peaks post-ovulation [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref062">62</a>]. These peaks may be within days of each other, and our monthly sampling regime was not frequent enough to detect these changes in individuals. On the population-level, however, it is general practice to describe seasonal cycles as monthly trends in reproductive hormones, usually only over the months known for reproductive activity [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref062">62</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref069">69</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref093">93</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref098">98</a>]. We were able to collect data for every month of the year (though, not for every population), and we do see distinct cycle trends among population in female BCS, CORT, E2, and P on an annual basis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Female chelonians exhibit increased weights at the time when follicular development/vitellogenesis occurs. Concordantly, mean BCSs in adult females from all three populations were found to be positive, and changes in BCS over time appear to reflect nesting events. Both captive populations exhibited higher BCSs in adult females than the wild; however, monthly trends were less evident than in wild females. It has been shown that captive female 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> housed in Madagascar lay more clutches than wild 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref061">61</a>] which may be due to access to mates stimulating ovarian development [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref060">60</a>]. Therefore, the difference in captive females’ BCSs were probably not only due to restricted vagility alongside constant access to food and water resources, but probably also due to increased clutches per year. The idea that females may need to be paired with males for ovulation to occur suggests that: 1) this species may not have the capacity for sperm storage as is seen in many other chelonians and 2) the declining population density could directly affect reproductive output, exacerbating declines (as was seen in the passenger pigeon). For chelonian species where both vagility and density are low, the ability to store viable sperm from one season to the next is an incredible adaptation maintaining species survival. Unfortunately for the ploughshare, they may not have this ability yet, but it should be further investigated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current study, general monthly hormone trends of female 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> displayed synchronous upticks in CORT, E2, and P which were followed by decreases in BCSs. For the captive populations, these trends often lined up with observations of nesting. Generally, females exhibited two peaks in E2 and P. For wild females, E2 and P exhibited one smaller peak two months prior to a larger peak, suggesting that two clutches may be produced annually in the wild which is concordant with the study on nesting behavior by [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref061">61</a>]. The two hormone peaks we note in females align with the two CORT peaks in wild males, and we also see the strongest uptick in female CORT along with those second peaks. Higher basal CORT concentrations have been associated with mating other species; both the male and female degu (
  <span class="italic">Octodon degus</span>) exhibit higher CORT in captivity and in the wild [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref092">92</a>]. It begs the question as to whether 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> are encountering or seeking out each other more often during those peak times. Further, female 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> may not ovulate without having been paired with a male during the previous mating season, despite having preovulatory follicles [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref060">60</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that CORT was highest in females from the U.S. captive population, and consistently lowest in the Madagascar captive population. It is likely that these trends are directly related to their particular captive conditions. Females from the Madagascar captive population are separated from males in their group enclosures during all times except for matings. The two females in the U.S. population are relatively new imports to the facility and are offered little retreat from the males’ advances with which they are regularly housed. Those U.S. females’ E2 and P appear completely disrupted without clear peaks. Female reproductive cycles may become disrupted for a variety of reasons, and captivity may delay the onset on ovulation by months or years. Though some species have the capacity to attenuate reproduction in any given year, the underlying physiological regulation of this ability is not well understood [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref099">99</a>]. It is probable that the females’ cycles are affected by the transfer into the northern hemisphere and are not yet acclimatized to the change. Though there are possible acclimation and persistent courtship stressors, the females are well fed and undergoing periods of follicular development [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref100">100</a>] and nesting events. We further discuss the acclimation issues in the Environmental Considerations section below.
 </p>
</sec>
