<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Males</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The U.S. population’s adult male scored the highest positive BCSs, but males from both the Madagascar populations showed mean negative BCSs. Over time, both the Madagascar populations’ males exhibited similar BCS trends to one another, peaking mid-dry-season in July, which is likely associated with growth of testicular tissue (spermiogenesis and/or spermiation) as a surge in T occurs at that time. In many herpetofauna, reproductive timing in males is altogether or partially offset from mating season [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref093">93</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref094">94</a>], and this appears to be true in 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> as well. Courtship and mating are seasonal in ploughshares, and generally occurs from October through December at the onset of the region’s wet season. Body condition scores dipped to the lowest values during the early wet season, when male-male competition for mates would be peaking. It has been suggested that males need to engage in combat in order to trigger their sexual interest in females [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref067">67</a>], and the combat itself will cause males to take in fewer food and water resources, altering BCSs. Males housed in the Madagascar captive population are regularly placed in shared enclosures, often specifically for these combat rituals, which may also help explain why they expressed BCSs and T concentrations more similar to wild individuals. Because the Madagascar captive population is generally fed native plant material, there may be a nutritional component to the similarity, as well as environmental, behavioral, and physiological components.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the wild population, males exhibit two CORT peaks which align with the time of ovulation in females, suggesting that competition for (and possibly defense of) mates is stressful for males. Monthly CORT in captive males was much more variable, and may be due to the changing of pairings and enclosures. However, we found that captive males which sired nests had overall higher basal CORT and T concentrations, suggesting that male-male competition is both stressful and requires aggression/dominance throughout the year. Similarly, in the eastern black rhinoceros (
  <span class="italic">Diceros bicornis michaeli</span>), dominant males exhibited significantly higher T and became sires by monopolizing more matings than non-sires [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref095">95</a>]. Although male sires in the current study had higher overall mean T, they exhibited significantly lower T during the months for which they sired. It logically follows that this strategy would be adaptive. For species which competition determines mating rights, aggressive males with higher T would generally be more successful in combat, but those T-linked aggressive behaviors could attenuate successful mating if directed at mates themselves. Dominant male 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> may therefore undergo a reduction in T concentrations after combat to avoid misdirecting overly aggressive behaviors (e.g., causing harm or refusal by mates) and consequently, for courtship to take place.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nearly half of all the T samples collected from the U.S. captive male 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> were extremely high for much of the year (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182004.g005" href="#pone.0182004.g005">Fig 5</a>). The U.S. male is not housed with other adult males and without the need to compete for access to females. His CORT concentrations remain low throughout the year while his T concentrations remain high throughout courtship, and aggression toward the females was noted. Although the females to which the U.S. male has access nested multiple times during this study, no fertilized eggs have been detected and sperm were not present in two eggs which were sacrificed to inspect them for the presence of sperm [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref096">96</a>]. This single example is concordant with the data presented above, suggesting that male 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">yniphora</span> may need to reduce T concentrations (through increasing CORT or otherwise) to successfully reproduce. Yet, there is still debate on what the variation in T signals with regard to an individual’s biology, and investigations into the relative importance and extrinsic influences that contribute to variation need be conducted to better interpret variation in T [
  <a rid="pone.0182004.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0182004.ref097">97</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
