<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CCSM3 simulations</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Paleoclimate simulations were performed using the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Community Climate System Model (CCSM) version 3.5
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>
  </span> in the fully coupled configuration (active atmosphere, ocean, land, and sea ice). The ocean model has a zonal resolution that varies from 340 km at the equator to 40 km around Greenland and 350 km in the Northern Pacific. This spatially varying resolution is achieved by placing the north pole of the grid over Greenland and reflects the different relevant length scales of the two processes that are important in maintaining a stable global climate; deep convection around Greenland and in the Arctic as well as ocean heat uptake at the equator. In the vertical there are 25 depth levels; the uppermost layer has a thickness of 8 m and the deepest layer has a thickness of 500 m. This and the atmospheric, land, and sea-ice models operate under the T31_3_3 setup
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>
  </span>, which have been developed specifically for long paleoclimate and biogeochemistry applications.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insolation was calculated using orbital parameters from Berger and Loutre
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> and CH
  <sub>4</sub> were prescribed (CO
  <sub>2</sub>, IGBP PAGES/WDCA contribution series number: 2008–055
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>
  </span>; CH
  <sub>4</sub>, IGBP PAGES/WDCA contribution series number: 2008–054
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>.) Continental ice sheets and sea level (i.e., land-ocean boundaries) were prescribed by scaling the ICE-5G ice distribution for the LGM to present
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>
  </span> to the marine benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O record
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>and saving these parameters as boundary conditions for the model. At the end of each year of the simulation, the orbital parameters and the atmospheric greenhouse gases were advanced by 100 years. When the model boundary conditions changed (e.g., land-ocean boundaries changing due to sea level rise or fall equivalent to 40 m), all the components of the model were reconfigured manually and the model was restarted using the previous year as the initial conditions. This acceleration technique, similar to those used in other paleoclimatic modeling studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>
  </span>, enables us to gain insight into the temporal evolution of the climate system given restricted computer resources. Several studies have shown that acceleration factors of 10 and 100 produced similar results
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>
  </span>. Jackson and Broccoli
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>
  </span>, for example, used an acceleration factor of 30 in a simulation of the past 165,000 years. The upper ocean and the atmosphere reach quasi-equilibrium in this acceleration approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. In our acceleration approach, the change in insolation forcing is small (&lt;0.5 W/m) from year to year at all latitudes in the shortest orbital cycle (precession)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment consisted of three separate simulations, beginning with an insolation only simulation, followed by addition of greenhouse gasses, followed by addition of ice-volume and sea level (Fox-Kemper et al., manuscript in preparation). Successively adding boundary conditions is a useful method for understanding the sensitivity of the model response to these forcing mechanisms. Results in this manuscript are from the simulation using the full set of boundary conditions. Model precipitation data were averaged for the regions depicted in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Monthly maximum, minimum, and annual average model output were used in comparison with proxy data. Use of monthly maximum and minimum values (as opposed JJA, DFJ) accounts for the fact that the timing of maximum insolation, in the northern hemisphere (for example), can occur in May, June, or July depending on the orbital configuration and is thus, not tied to any single orbital configuration (e.g., June 21 Perihelion).
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently, accelerated models assume that Earth’s orbit is fixed, meaning that changes in the length and strength of Earth’s seasons due to changes in Earth’s orbital parameters are not accounted for in the definition of the calendar upon which monthly values are computed. While this is not a major issue for Holocene-scale studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>
  </span>, it becomes important for orbital-scale simulations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>
  </span>. Therefore, it is important to identify and correct for this calendar effect if one wishes to accurately relate paleoclimate model results to real-world paleoclimate records. The calendar problem was corrected for (Nelson A.D. et al., manuscript in preparation) by following the methodology of other works
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
