<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the eccentricity band, light U1429 δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub> and Pearl River Valley δ
  <span class="sup">2</span>H
  <sub>wax</sub> occur during glacial intervals (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>). Light glacial-age δ
  <span class="sup">2</span>H
  <sub>wax</sub> may result from rainout over the emergent continental shelf resulting in lighter inland precipitation isotopes, increased rainout along the moisture transport path (including the emergent Sunda Shelf)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>, changes in glacial-age source water locations, or cooler local precipitation condensation temperatures. Differentiation among these possible mechanisms, or some combination thereof, is not possible at this time but will benefit from rapidly evolving isotope-enabled simulations that incorporate realistic changes in boundary conditions, including ice-volume and sea level. Interpreted in the context of salinity (rainfall and YRV runoff), the 100-ky variance in the local δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub> signal is likely influenced by shoreline migration, bringing the YRV freshwater source closer to the site during glacial sea level low stands
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>, counteracting the effect of decreased precipitation indicated by an array of independent proxy records of EAM rainfall
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span> and model simulations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterodyne variance in U1429 and in the Lantian–Weinan section to the north likely reflect interactions of variance associated with eccentricity and obliquity forcing as described in Thomas et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Thomas et al. note a significant difference in the spectral structure of East Asian water-isotope proxy records (δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>cave</sub> and δ
  <span class="sup">2</span>H
  <sub>wax</sub>) relative to those of loess-based summer monsoon (magnetic susceptibility) and winter monsoon (grain size) proxy records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. The loess-based records, also including δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C of inorganic carbonate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> and an array of isotopic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> and magnetic property proxies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span> for summer monsoon precipitation are dominated by primary orbital periodicity (eccentricity, obliquity, and precession). The water-isotope proxies, in contrast, contain large amounts of variance at heterodyne periods, the concentration of which increases from south to north. Thomas et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> attribute the northward increase in heterodyne variance (spectral complexity) to the increasing influence of multiple environmental parameters contributing to the water-isotope signal; records in the south are primarily dominated by summer monsoon variance with simple spectra, composed mostly of primary orbital-scale variance peaks, whereas water-isotope records further north are influenced by both summer- and winter-monsoon variability (i.e., temperature, winter- and summer-monsoon precipitation) resulting in more complex spectra that include heterodyne variance. Our δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub> record is consistent with this interpretation, having a combination of primary and heterodyne variance.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spectral signatures of most EAM proxies are not dominated by 23-ky variance but, rather, by spectral variance at the 100- and 41-ky periods more characteristic of late Pleistocene global ice volume and greenhouse gas forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. The spectral signature of ECS local δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub>, a record for which the impact of temperature and seawater δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O have been removed, is also well matched to that of CH
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, CO
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>, and the global benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O stack
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a–c</a>). All are dominated by eccentricity-band variance with lesser amounts of obliquity-band variance. With the exception of CH
  <sub>4</sub>, all have the least amount of variance in the precession-band. The precession-band variance in CH
  <sub>4</sub> (co-equal with obliquity-band variance) has been attributed, in part, to tropical wetland sources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. In any case, these records, and their spectral signatures, bear little resemblance to that of direct local or high-latitude summer-insolation forcing (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5d, e</a>). These findings indicate that the EAM does not respond dominantly and directly to external insolation forcing but, rather, is strongly sensitive to the internal redistribution of this energy, resulting in spectral signatures more similar to those of greenhouse gasses and global ice volume.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, the precession- and millennial-band structure characteristic of YRV δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>cave</sub> is also found offshore in ECS δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>pf</sub>. However, after quantitative removal of the local temperature and global seawater δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O signals, the resulting local δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub> record (a proxy for rainfall and YRV runoff) no longer matches δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>cave</sub>. Local δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub> is dominated by eccentricity- and obliquity-band variance as well as heterodynes thereof, not by precession-band variance as in δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>cave</sub>. The local δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>sw</sub> spectrum, similar to an array of other proxies across the EAM region, is consistent with that of CO
  <sub>2</sub>, CH
  <sub>4</sub>, and global ice volume. This indicates that EAM rainfall variability is more sensitive to internal forcing mechanisms related to high-latitude ice sheet and greenhouse gas variability, and less sensitive to direct insolation forcing, as is commonly inferred on the basis of the precession-dominated YRV δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O
  <sub>cave</sub> spectrum.
 </p>
</sec>
