<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oceanography and climatology</div>
  <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Site U1429 (31.62°N, 129°E, 732 mbsl)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span> is located at the north end of the Okinawa Trough (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Winters are characterized by cool sea surface temperature (SST) and strong winds (~18 °C, 5–7  ms
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) while summers are characterized by warm SST and weak winds (~28 °C, 1–2  ms
   <span class="sup">−1</span>)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>. The surface moisture balance (precipitation minus evaporation; P − E) is positive in the summer and negative in the winter, consistent with seasonal differences in insolation, winds, and precipitation. Surface water salinity is also seasonal, due to increased P − E and YRV summer runoff. Modern salinity at Site U1429 ranges from 33.5 in the summer to 34.7 in the winter
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span> and is very highly correlated with rainfall over the YRV (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). This strong correlation extends to the interannual scale as well; YRV flood and drought conditions related to El Niño and La Niña variability can alter salinity by +1 and −6 psu (respectively) out to 500 km offshore
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
   </span> and are accompanied by interannual variability in chororphyll-
   <span class="italic">a</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span>. These observations are consistent with strong correlation (
   <span class="italic">r</span> &gt; 0.97) of seawater δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O with chlorinity and salinity, which indicate near-complete mixing of Yangtze River outflow and ocean waters in the estuary
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
   </span> and in the eastern ECS
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>.
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Modern precipitation and salinity climatologies, rivers, and surface currents. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Locations of IODP Site U1429 and sediment trap site JAST-01
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
      </span> in the East China Sea. δ
      <span class="sup">2</span>H
      <sub>wax</sub> records precipitation isotopes from the Pearl River Valley
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
      </span> and the Loess Plateau
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
      </span>, deposited at IODP Site 1146 and Weinan, respectively. Boxes are area averages for CCSM3 model results. Kuroshio current (KC) and Tsushima warm current (TsWC) split south of U1429
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>, 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
      </span>. Taiwan warm current (TWC) enters from the south. Sanbao, Linzhu, and Hulu caves are the locations from which the composite δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub> record was constructed
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
      </span>. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Modern rainfall in the Yangtze River Valley (brown) is highly correlated to salinity at East China Sea Site U1429 (green). At the annual cycle with the lag removed, 
      <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.89 and the result is significant at 
      <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Monthly climatology from 
      <span class="bold">b</span>. Salinity from ORAS4
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>
      </span>. Rainfall from GPCC
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
      </span>. Base-map created using commercially available MATLAB software
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5814_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e709" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strong link between modern YRV rainfall and offshore salinity extends into the geological past as well. Kubota et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span> reconstructed the mid-Holocene (7 Ka BP) to present freshwater budget for the U1429 region, employing Heshang cave δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O as a proxy for the isotopic composition of the freshwater end member. They found that local seawater δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O and river discharge have similar responses (no change in the mean) from 7 Ka to present whereas Heshang δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O indicates a 2.5‰ increase, a trend previously interpreted to represent decreased rainfall
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. This finding, no systematic reduction in monsoon rainfall from the mid-Holocene to present, is consistent with a range of independent and diverse rainfall proxies from the EAM region
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
   </span> and indicates a decoupling of YRV precipitation amount and precipitation δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O in the past.
  </p>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Air mass backtrack trajectory analysis indicates both continental and marine moisture sources to the YRV during the modern summer and winter seasons, with 59% of precipitation falling during the summer monsoon months (June through September; Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. Detailed analysis of YRV moisture sources
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span> indicates that the contribution of moisture from land roughly equals that from the Pacific and Indian Oceans combined during both summer (May–September) and winter (October–April). The relative contributions of modern continental and marine moisture sources over the course of the seasonal cycle, weighted by their isotopic composition, successfully replicates modern cave calcite δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O in the EAM region
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Precipitation δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O (δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub>) values reflect the origin, temperature, humidity and transport history of the water vapor
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>. These factors are significantly different for terrestrial and marine air masses contributing to modern EAM rainfall during summer and winter
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span>. Analysis of cave drip water
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span> indicates that δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub> variability in the modern monsoon region of China cannot be explained by either temperature or precipitation alone, likely due to the multiple interacting vapor sources. In addition, Liu et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span> examined the Global and Chinese Network of Isotopes in Precipitation (GNIP and CHNIP) finding that δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub> in the YRV region is best related to water vapor content of the atmosphere; the amount effect is minor. Hence, there is little evidence, at least from modern data, that EAM water-isotope proxies can be interpreted directly as indicators of local rainfall amount. For these reasons, reconstructing ECS local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> is important, providing an independent proxy indicator of changes in ECS salinity, varying as a function of precipitation and runoff.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Water-isotope proxy drivers</div>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oxygen isotopic composition of ECS planktonic foraminifer (δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub>) and YRV δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> have a number of drivers in common as well as a number of drivers that influence each independently (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). Both records reflect global-scale changes in source water δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O as well as local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub> since both are under the influence of the EAM, and linked by YRV runoff. Changes in surface temperature, in contrast, may be expressed differently in these two proxies. The dominant impact on δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> will be changes in the temperature of calcite precipitation; the impact of evaporation will be minimal because precipitation plus runoff dominates over evaporation in the ECS, where annual average salinity values range between 30 near the coast and 34.5 offshore, out to 130°E
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span>. Changes in temperature affect δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub> and can also be propagated into the cave environment, influencing the temperature of calcite precipitation. Temperature may also have a significant influence through changes in soil zone evaporation and evaporation in the cave atmosphere itself
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>. Duan et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. monitored monthly to bi-monthly δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub> and cave drip water δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O (δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>dw</sub>) at 34 sites in the cave region of China to evaluate the impact of processes in the soil, epikarst, and cave environment. They found that 82% of the drip sites showed little variation in δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>dw</sub> throughout the 3-year study, indicating that δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> incorporates multi-year average signals modulated by seasonally changing recharge and evaporation regimes. Twelve percent of the drip sites recorded damped seasonal to monthly δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>dw</sub>, compared to δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub>. Six percent fell between the two extremes, with constant, low δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>dw</sub> during the wet season and variable, relatively high δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>dw</sub> in the dry season, thought to result from flow switching in the karst or evaporation within the cave. James et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span> made the case that seasonal cave ventilation is an important driver of cave-air CO
   <sub>2</sub> and hence calcite precipitation; the result being that speleothems from temperate and boreal regions, for example, can be biased toward cool-season calcite precipitation. None of these factors impact δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub>, calcite precipitated by planktonic foraminifers in the offshore surface environment.
  </p>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, biases independent of those impacting δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> can impact ECS δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub>. Sediment trap results from the Okinawa Trough indicate that 
   <span class="italic">Globigerinoides ruber</span> specimens in the size fraction used for this study (Methods) are reduced in abundance between December and March, potentially introducing a seasonal bias
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. Site U1429 is located at the bifurcation point of the Kuroshio Current and Tsushima Warm Current
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
   </span>; variability in these current regimes could impact δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub>, although the path of the Kuroshio appears stable with regard to glacial sea level changes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span>. Migration of the shoreline closer to Site U1429 during glacial-age sea level low stands (120 m isobath, Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>) may alter the delivery and extent of mixing between 
   <span class="sup">18</span>O-enriched seawater from the Kuroshio Current with 
   <span class="sup">18</span>O-depleted river water at Site U1429. The relative influences of these various independent δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> drivers may vary at different time scales.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Foraminifera δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
  </div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The U1429 benthic foraminifer δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O (δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>bf</sub>) record was mapped to the global benthic isotope stack
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span> to produce a traditional benthic age model (Methods, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). Cross-spectral analysis indicates high coherence and near-zero phase across the Earth-orbital eccentricity, obliquity, and precession bands, verifying the U1429 chronostratigraphy (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>).
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Proxy time series and spectra. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> U1429 δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>bf</sub> mapped to the benthic chronology
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
      </span>. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> U1429 δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>pf</sub> on the benthic age model. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub>
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
      </span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> Notched δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>pf</sub> mapped to δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub>. Labeled dashed lines denote primary orbital frequencies (frequency = 1/period in ky)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5814_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1081" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The U1429 δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> time series is dominated by eccentricity with lesser, sub-equal variance in the obliquity bands and precession bands (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). In contrast, YRV δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
   </span> is dominated by precession-band variance (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>), a primary reason why the EAM has been interpreted as a system responding dominantly and directly to northern hemisphere summer-insolation forcing
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
   </span>. The very strong degree to which δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> variance is also embedded in offshore δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> is illustrated by notch filtering δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> (removing eccentricity- and obliquity-band variance) and then mapping the sub-orbital structure to δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub>, creating a cave-based age model (Methods); all further analyses use the cave-based age model. Notched δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>) demonstrates that the precession-band structure in YRV δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> resides in δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> as well; the spectra are nearly indistinguishable. This strong orbital-scale correspondence is not due to fine-tuning the benthic age model by correlating the notched δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> to δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub>; the cave-based age model is spectrally indistinguishable from the benthic age model (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>bf</sub> on the two age models is highly coherent (0.99 CI) with near-zero phase at the eccentricity (0.08 ± 0.35 ky), obliquity (−0.23 ± 0.29 ky) and precession (0.23 ± 0.17 ky) bands.
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strong similarities extend to the sub-orbital scale as well. δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> have the same millennial-scale structure during both glacial and interglacial intervals (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b, c</a>), including Heinrich and Dansgaard–Oeschger events. Finally, U1429 δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> has enhanced resolution of sub-orbital-scale structure within the interval 250 to 340 ka where δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> is less resolved or smoothly varying (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>). Strong similarities at the orbital (precession) and sub-orbital (millennial) scales confirm that δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> share common drivers at these time scales, both likely monitoring the δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O of local precipitation; potential biases that impact each of the two proxies independently are not apparent in these records.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Millennial-scale structure in notched δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>pf</sub> compared to δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub>. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Notched U1429 δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>pf</sub> on the cave-based age model. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Expanded 20–80 ka interval with millennial-scale Dansgaard–Oeschger (DO) and Heinrich events numbered. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Expanded 100–210 ka interval. 
      <span class="bold">d</span> Expanded 250–340 ka interval showing structure not previously resolved in δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5814_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1276" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seawater δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
  </div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a climate change standpoint, however, reconstruction of rainfall amount is an important goal. Interpretation of water-isotope proxies as rainfall amount has been a point of contention given that modern data, described above, show that δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>precip</sub> and rainfall amount are uncorrelated in the YRV region. This is addressed by quantitatively removing the effects of changing sea surface temperature (SST) and global seawater δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O from δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> (Methods, Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This yields a record of local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub>, a proxy that is linearly related to salinity
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>, responding strongly to YRV runoff as well as direct precipitation to the ECS
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Removing the SST signal from δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>) yields the total δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>). Removing global seawater δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O from total δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>) yields local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>). In contrast to δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub>, local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> has almost no precession-band variance. Instead, it is dominated by variance at primary orbital periods, including 100 ky (eccentricity), 41 ky (obliquity), and both heterodynes thereof (29 and 69 ky). While this spectral structure is very different from that of YRV δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub>, it shares strong similarities with precipitation-isotope records to the north and south as well as with global-scale changes in CO
   <sub>2</sub>, CH
   <sub>4</sub>, and terrestrial ice volume (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a–c</a>).
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Time series used in deriving local δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>sw</sub>, and associated spectra. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> U1429 δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>pf</sub> (and spectrum) with Mg/Ca SST, both derived from 
      <span class="italic">G. ruber</span> (250–355 μm size fraction). 
      <span class="bold">b</span> U1429 total δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>sw</sub> (and spectrum) with U1429 δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>bf</sub> scaled to match the global δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>sw</sub> curve
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>
      </span>; this approach preserves the age model and high temporal resolution of the U1429 data. 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> U1429 local δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>sw</sub> (and spectrum) with the Pearl River Valley δ
      <span class="sup">2</span>H
      <sub>wax</sub> record (and spectrum) from Site 1146
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
      </span>. Labeled dashed lines denote primary orbital frequencies (frequency = 1/period in ky). Orbital-scale peaks for frequencies &lt;0.05 labeled with * do not meet the 
      <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.05 threshold level for probability of chance occurrence (Methods)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5814_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1474" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Spectral comparisons of EAM proxy records with global ice volume, greenhouse gases, and insolation. Local δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>sw</sub>, a record for which the effects of temperature and seawater δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O have been removed, compared to 
      <span class="bold">a</span> global CH
      <sub>4</sub>, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> global CO
      <sub>2</sub>, and 
      <span class="bold">c</span> global ice volume. δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub>, a record for which the effects of temperature and seawater δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O have not been removed, compared to 
      <span class="bold">d</span> local summer and 
      <span class="bold">e</span> high-latitude summer-insolation forcing. Labeled lines denote primary orbital frequencies (frequency = 1/period in ky)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5814_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1525" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The eccentricity-band (100 ky) variance in local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> is coherent (0.92 CI) and near-zero phase (4 ± 2 ky) with the Site 1146 (Pearl River) δ
   <span class="sup">2</span>H
   <sub>wax</sub> record
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span> located ~1000 km south of the YRV; both are dominated by 100 ky eccentricity-band variance with little to no precession-band variance (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>). The Site 1146 record dominantly reflects input from the Pearl River but has contributions from Taiwan and Luzon as well
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
   </span>. The heterodyne periods (29 and 69 ky) are consistent as well with the 31- and 72-ky heterodynes that dominate variance in the Lantian–Weinan loess δ
   <span class="sup">2</span>H
   <sub>wax</sub> record
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span> ~300 km north of the YRV.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transient model simulations</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonality and the extent to which the local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> proxy is consistent with model rainfall simulations is assessed by comparison with results from a 300,000 year long accelerated transient climate simulation using the Community Climate Systems Model version 3.5 (CCSM3)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span>. The CCSM3 simulation (Methods, Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>) was run with varying orbital insolation, greenhouse gasses, ice volume, and sea level, following methods and boundary conditions detailed in Chen et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
   </span>, in order to capture the climate response to transient forcing
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
   </span>. EOF comparison of the model and modern EAM precipitation fields for summer and winter seasons are consistent with one another (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). These simulation results have been previously used in the EAM region to assess the transient response to changing surface temperature and monsoon precipitation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having removed the effects of surface temperature and global seawater δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O from δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pf</sub>, the result (local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub>) is compared to model precipitation. Both the YRV and ECS regions (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) were evaluated for monthly maximum (summer), minimum (winter), and annual average precipitation in order to assess spatial and seasonal variability. The local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> heterodyne variance at the 29- and 69-ky periods is unique to the YRV annual average model precipitation field (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>), suggesting it is transmitted to the ECS via runoff. The 100-ky variance is found in all three (maximum, annual average, and minimum) ECS precipitation records, indicating decreased precipitation during glacial intervals. The same set of proxy-model comparisons was conducted for YRV δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub>, including model temperature since the impact of changing local temperature is unknown. δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> is well matched to model YRV surface temperature maximum and precipitation maximum (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>). Hence, the degree to which changes in local temperature or precipitation drive YRV δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> cannot be differentiated with these data. More in-depth interpretation of δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>cave</sub> and local δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>sw</sub> would benefit from isotope-enabled transient model simulations that incorporate realistic greenhouse gas, ice volume, and sea level boundary conditions.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Comparison of model (annual average, red) and U1429 (blue) time series and spectra. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> U1429 local δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>sw</sub> and East China Sea (ECS) model annual average precipitation. The U1429 record is consistent with 
      <span class="bold">b</span> annual average precipitation over the Yangtze River Valley (YRV) accounting for the 29- and 69-ky variance and 
      <span class="bold">c</span> ECS annual average precipitation, accounting for the 100- and 41-ky variance. Supplementary Figure 
      <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a> shows comparisons of δ
      <span class="sup">18</span>O
      <sub>cave</sub> (for which temperature has not been removed) with model temperature and precipitation (monthly annual, maximum, and minimum)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5814_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1703" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
