<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HSE and SWI</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The economic multiplier is a factor that is multiplied by the output value from an economic activity (e.g., fisheries) to estimate the total direct and indirect economic contribution of this activity to the whole economy through other sectors and is used to emphasize that the fisheries industry has many linkages throughout the economy (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>). After the fish is landed at the port, they are transported and sold in markets, delivered to the processing plants, and/or sold directly to retailers or restaurants before they are consumed. Along the value chain after fish is landed, a portion of the output value in each sector in this value chain can be traced back to capture fisheries. Economic impacts thus capture the value added along the value chain after a fish is landed, and this final value of seafood is what is paid by consumers, here termed HSE (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>, indicator v). A related income multiplier specifies the proportion of economic impacts that accrue to seafood-related workers as income throughout the value chain, termed here SWI (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>, indicator iv).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We applied the economic multipliers for each maritime country reported in (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>); the authors used I-O analysis, a technique developed by Nobel Laureate, Wassily Leontief (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>) to estimate the economic multiplier for each country (table S7), which was split by the level of development (table S8). The net multiplier is then equal to the Leontief multiplier minus one to take into account the fact that we estimated the multiplier effects using industry output rather than final demand (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>), extracted I-O tables from the Global Trade Analysis Project (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gtap.agecon.purdue.edu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.gtap.agecon.purdue.edu/</span>) database at Purdue University, and obtained fisheries-related income and economic multipliers for each coastal country. The total HSE and SWI can be calculated using the following simple equations
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div id="m8" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mtable">
       <div class="mtr">
        <div class="mtd">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mtext">HSE</span>
          <span class="mo"> </span>
          <span class="mo">=</span>
          <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
           <div class="munderover">
            <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
             <span class="mo">=</span>
             <span class="mn">1</span>
            </div>
            <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="msub">
           <span class="mtext">FR</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">*</span>
          <div class="msub">
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">V</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mtr">
        <div class="mtd">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mtext">SWI</span>
          <span class="mo"> </span>
          <span class="mo">=</span>
          <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
           <div class="munderover">
            <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
             <span class="mo">=</span>
             <span class="mn">1</span>
            </div>
            <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
          <div class="msub">
           <span class="mtext">FR</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">*</span>
          <div class="msub">
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">Z</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>where FR
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> is the FR, which represents the total industry output, of each country 
  <span class="italic">i</span>. The parameters 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> and 
  <span class="italic">Z</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> represent the economic impact and income multipliers for fisheries, respectively, for each country 
  <span class="italic">i</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
