<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
  <p>Supplementary material for this article is available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/2/eaau3855/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/2/eaau3855/DC1</span>
  </p>
  <p>Fig. S1. Projected differences taken between outcomes of meeting Paris Agreement targets.</p>
  <p>Fig. S2. Sensitivity analysis of economic indicators (FR, SWI, and HSE) to changes in price flexibilities aggregated globally, by region, and for select species.</p>
  <p>Table S1. Projected differences of indicators relative to 2001–2010 period between outcomes of meeting Paris Agreement targets (+1.5°C) and maintaining high greenhouse gas concentrations trajectory (+3.5°C) relative to preindustrial levels.</p>
  <p>Table S2. Current (2001–2010 average) annual values for fisheries indicators of the top 10 revenue-generating species for each country, grouped by continent.</p>
  <p>Table S3. Year in which target warming temperature is reached for each RCP within each ESM.</p>
  <p>Table S4. Price flexibility by marine species group and country development group.</p>
  <p>Table S5. Number of countries and their share in world marine capture catch, by share of exports volume in total domestic supply (2011–2015).</p>
  <p>Table S6. Estimated and observed domestic price percent changes for fish with 13% decrease in world price.</p>
  <p>Table S7. Multipliers used to determine impacts on SWI and HSE.</p>
  <p>Table S8. List of countries by geographic region and FAO development grouping.</p>
  <p>Table S9. Projected differences for the top 10 species by landed value globally taken between outcomes of meeting Paris Agreement targets (+1.5°C) and maintaining high emissions (+3.5°C).</p>
  <p>References (
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
    <span class="italic">41</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">
    <span class="italic">58</span>
   </a>)
  </p>
 </div>
</div>
