<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We further performed idealized AGCM experiments using the Community Earth System Model (CESM) version 1.2.0 with F‐compset to examine the slow response due to aerosol‐induced SST changes. F‐compset consists of interactive atmosphere model (Community Atmosphere Model, CAM5) and land surface model (Community Land Model 4.0, CLM4) with prescribed SSTs and sea ice concentration. A detailed description of the model can be found in Neale et al. (
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). We use 1.9
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup> latitude × 2.5
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup> longitude horizontal resolution, 26 vertical levels, and the 
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>4 physics package with prescribed gases (except for water vapor) and bulk aerosols. The control simulation (CTRL) is run with year 1850 aerosol concentration and 1951–2000 climatological SST and sea ice concentration from the Hadley Centre Sea Ice and Sea Surface Temperature data set (Rayner et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). The forced experiment (AEROSST) uses the same aerosol and sea ice concentration as the control experiment but adding an SST anomaly derived from the CMIP5 historical aerosol forcing only simulations to the observed climatological SST (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S8</xref>). The SST anomaly is the climatological difference between 1981–2005 and 1861–1885 using the multimodel mean (MMM) of the five common CMIP5 models listed in Table 
 <xref rid="grl56839-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>. All other gaseous species are fixed at preindustrial levels. Both experiments are run for 60 years (after an initial 1 year spin‐up); the climatological difference between AEROSST and CTRL quantifies the slow response.
</p>
