<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As discussed in the “
 <xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Theory</xref>” section, updrafts do become somewhat faster with warming when lapse rates are allowed to equilibrate (rather than being imposed) in simulations of RCE, although the dynamical contribution to changes in precipitation extremes is still relatively small [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>]. Nonetheless, large deviations from Clausius-Clapeyron scaling have been found in a study of RCE because of changes in precipitation efficiency at mean surface temperatures below 295 K [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>]. The 99.99th percentile of precipitation from this study is shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3a</xref> for durations from instantaneous to daily.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4" class="xref">4</xref> Warming shifts the percentile curves upwards in intensity in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3a</xref>, but the rate at which they shift upwards varies with duration and temperature. As shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3b</xref>, the precipitation extremes follow Clausius-Clapeyron scaling at roughly 6–7 % K
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> for temperatures above 295 K. However, for temperatures below 295 K, the sensitivity varies widely depending on temperature and accumulation period in a manner that is not fully understood. Instantaneous precipitation extremes increase at close to double the Clausius-Clapeyron rate for temperatures below 295 K, and this has been shown to be due to increases in precipitation efficiency with warming, related in part to increases in hydrometeor fall speed as more of the precipitation in the column changes from solid to liquid [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>]. Such changes in precipitation efficiency might be expected to occur for variability within a climate as well as for longer term climate change, but in the simulations, they depend strongly on the choice of cloud microphysics scheme, and it remains to be seen if they are relevant for observed precipitation extremes.
</p>
