<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Despite this strong association of isopod communities and habitat diversity, there are several studies that have failed to find significant effects of habitat disturbance on isopod diversity. Even if this sounds counter-intuitive, it is not necessarily so, as we’ll try to explain below. According to 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tajovský et al. (2012)</xref>, who studied isopods in 13 forest fragments in the Czech Republic ranging in area (0.1 to 254.5 ha), shape and composition of forest vegetation (thermophilous oak, mesophilous oak-hornbeam, thermophilous oak-hornbeam, acidophilous oak, basiphilous oak, beech oak-hornbeam, moist mixed deciduous forest, plantations of deciduous and coniferous trees), highest density and epigeic activity was recorded in the smallest fragments, despite of the fact that larger fragments contained a wider range of habitats. The authors found that forest fragmentation does not necessarily result in a decrease in isopod species richness. Similarly, no support for the hypothesis that diversity decreases in response to habitat disturbance or that species richness is highest in moderately disturbed sites (intermediate disturbance) was found by 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hornung et al. (2007)</xref> in a study comparing urban, suburban, and rural sites in Hungary, albeit species composition did change along the gradient. According to 
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vilisics et al. (2007a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>), less than half of the species comprising assemblages in different habitats showed significant association with analysed habitat features. Furthermore, the responses of those that did show some association with certain habitat features were variable, reflecting their more-or-less known ecological characteristics. On the contrary, though, 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Messina et al. (2014)</xref> found a strong association of isopod species with specific plant communities and soil types at a coastal area of Sicily.
</p>
