<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20050630//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6704330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">97320630015467</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6026/97320630015467</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular modelling and docking of Mus musculus HMGB1 inflammatory protein with CGA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>Alok</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shrinet</surname><given-names>Kriti</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Vinay Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Arvind</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>School of Biotechnology, Institute of Science, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi-221005,India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Arvind Kumar<email>arvindkumararvind8@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 Biomedical Informatics</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. This is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p> Recently, High Mobility Group Box1 (HMGB1) protein has been reported as an inflammatory cytokine present in all nucleated cells
with crucial role in the genesis and promotion of cancer. No HMGB1 protein mice model and its active site details are available to
validate mice in vivo experiments. Here, for the first time we have reported in silico mice HMGB1 model using human HMGB1
template. Prepared HMGB1 secondary structure showed 6-&#x003b1; helices, 5-&#x003b2; turns, 2-&#x003b3; turns with 67% &#x003b1;-helices, 32% coil and 9% turn
without &#x003b2;-sheet, and classified as &#x003b1;-class protein. Ramachandran plot analysis showed 98.2% and 92.3% residues lies in favoured
region, verified by RAMPAGE and PDBsum server respectively. Cancer atlas of HMGB1 protein showed up-regulated expression of
HMGB1 gene in different cancer, proved by CAB (CAB005873) and HPA-antibody (HPA003506) in silico. HMGB1 protein showed
interaction with different biologically important inflammatory protein as depicted in STRING result.Prominent active site has residues
Tyr<sup>78</sup>Ile<sup>79</sup>Pro<sup>80-81</sup>Lys<sup>82</sup>Gly<sup>83</sup>vGlu<sup>84</sup>Thr<sup>85</sup>Lys<sup>86-88</sup>Phe<sup>89</sup>Lys<sup>90</sup>Asp<sup>91</sup>Pro<sup>92</sup>Asn<sup>93</sup>Tyr<sup>162</sup>Lys<sup>165</sup> with 310 &#x000c5;<sup>3</sup> site volume.Interacting residues of
CGA-HMGB1 docked complex were ILE<sup>79</sup>PRO<sup>80-81</sup>LYS<sup>82</sup>GLY<sup>83</sup>GLU<sup>84</sup>LYS<sup>86-88</sup>PHE<sup>89</sup>Arg<sup>163</sup>Ala<sup>164</sup>LYS<sup>165</sup>Gly<sup>166</sup> with docking score 3872 and
surface area 412.6. CGA-conformer C3950 showed best docking than CGA and conformer-ZINC03947476, iso-chlorogenic acid and cischlorogenic acid.
HMGB1 mice model could be a good therapeutic target for anti-cancerous drugs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>HMGB1</kwd><kwd>CGA</kwd><kwd>modelling</kwd><kwd>docking</kwd><kwd>cancer</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Cancer is a foremost cause of global death and recently, HMGB1
has been recognized for inflammation related cancer genesis 
[<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R02" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].
It is made up of three domains, A-box (N-terminal domain), Bbox
(central domain) and terminal C-domain 
[<xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Active secretion
of HMGB1 occurs from immune cells e.g. macrophages,
monocytes, NK cells, while passive secretion occurs from
damaged necrotic cells [<xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].
It has extracellular activities as a
cytokine, since mediates inflammation, proliferation and
migration in different cancers [<xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Up-regulation of HMGB1 is
associated with the hallmarks of cancer and clinically it has
crucial role in the autoimmune diseases, apart from cancer 
[<xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>-<xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
Phenolics are natural antioxidant obtained from plants one of
them is chlorogenic acid (CGA), naturally present in coffee,
apple, mulberry, Achyranthes aspera etc 
[<xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. CGA has anti type-2
diabetes mellitus, antioxidant activity, anti-inflammatory and anti-carcinogenic property 
[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Biologically CGA checks the
growth and proliferation of cancerous cells the reason of which is
still unknown and need to be proved experimentally 
[<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Here
we reported that CGA binds with the active site of HMGB1 as
proved by molecular docking experiment, thus mitigating its
activity and ability to cause cancer. The therapeutic molecule
HMGB1 could be targeted by CGA-conformers or other biomolecules
drugs to cure and prevent cancer, as our in silico data
revealed.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Molecular structure characterization and modelling:</title><p>The three dimensional (3D) structure of mice HMGB1 protein
was not available in PDB database, hence an attempt has been
made to determine the 3D structure of mice HMGB1 protein
based on homology modelling. Human HMGB1 protein structure
was used for characterization of mice HMGB1 protein model
using BLASTp algorithm. Characterized mice HMGB1 protein
sequence was used for modelling and visualization by Discovery
Studio 3.0 software [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Model quality assessment and verification:</title><p>Structural assessment and verification of predicted HMGB1
protein model was performed by RAMPAGE and PDBsum server
[<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Verified mice HMGB1 protein model was deposited in
Protein Model Database (PMDB) [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Status of HMGB1 protein expression in different cancer:</title><p>Human Protein Atlas Database (HPAD) has expression level of
different cancer causing genes of interest in 20 most commonly
occurring cancers [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Expression level of HMGB1 protein was
checked in different cancers by using HPA003506 (SIGMAALDRICH)
and CAB005873 (ABCAM-PLC) antibodies.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Protein-protein interactions:</title><p>STRING (Search Tool for the Retrieval of Interacting Genes)
server was used to identify the function of HMGB1 protein based
on direct and indirect physical as well as functional proteinprotein
interaction network [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>MeSH (Medical Subject Headings) classification for CGA conformer's identification:</title><p>PubChem classification browser was used for the MeSH (Medical
Subject Headings) tree classification of CGA for identification of
conformers [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Substances resulted from classification browser
search results were used for the phylogeny tree preparation using
structural clustering tool of PubChem database. The compounds
were clustered together based on the 3D Tanimoto structure
using single linkage algorithm. Representative candidate
structure from each hierarchy level was selected for further
preparation of closest possible phylogeny tree using structural
clustering.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Active site identification:</title><p>The Q-site Finder server based on interaction energy calculation
between the protein and Vander walls probe, was used for the
identification of ten prominent active sites of prepared model.
Docking scores and active site volumes for each predicted active
sites were also predicted [<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Molecular docking and docking complex visualization:</title><p>Molecular docking calculation was performed by PatchDock
server and algorithm was based on shape complementarity
principle. This method utilises protein-ligand molecule
complexes during the docking process [<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. CGA molecule (CID-
1794427) and other conformers obtained by structure clustering
approach were used for docking, complex preparation and
selection for best docked complex. Docked complex of HMGB1-
CGA was visualized by Discovery studio 3.0.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Molecular structure characterization and modelling:</title><p>Predicted mice HMGB1 sequence (Accession ID-BAE29962.1)
showed 99 % identity and 77% query cover with human HMGB1
protein sequence (PDBID: 2YRQ). Only A-chain sequence i.e.
2YRQ: A of template (human) was utilized for target (mice)
sequence prediction [<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Predicted protein model contains 6-&#x003b1;
helices, 5-&#x003b2; turns, 2- &#x003b3; turns without &#x003b2;-sheet and hence it was
classified as &#x003b1;-class protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>). The structural
composition of mice HMGB1 protein model was confirmed by
the PDBsum server (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Model quality assessment and verification:</title><p>According to RAMPAGE server analysis 98.2% residues were lies
in favoured region, 1.2% residues were lies in allowed region and
0.6% residues were in outlier region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1c</xref>). However,
PDBsum server analysis showed that most favoured regions have
92.3% residues and additional allowed regions were having 7.7%
residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1d</xref>). PMDB-ID of mice HMGB1 protein model
submitted to PMDB database is PM0079141.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>HMGB1 protein expression in different cancer by Human Protein Atlas Database:</title><p>The cancer atlas of HMGB1 protein showed that the expression
level was highest in carcinoid, glioma, head and neck cancer,
while lowest in testis cancer detected with CAB-antibody
(CAB005873) in silico (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>). However, expression level of
HMGB1 protein was highest in glioma and thyroid cancer, while
lowest in prostate and testis cancer detected with HPA-antibody
(HPA003506) in silico (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>STRING database for protein-protein interactions:</title><p>STRING database results showed a strong networking with
reference to protein-protein interaction, depicting HMGB1
protein capability to interact with different biologically important
proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c</xref>). Predicted functional partners of HMGB1
protein were AGER (Advanced glycosylation end product-specific
receptor), HMGB2 (High Mobility Group Box 2), NF-&#x003ba;B1
(nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer in Bcells1),
RELA (v-rel reticulo endotheliosis viral oncogene
homolog A), Trp53 (transformation related protein 53), Chuk
(conserved helix-loop-helix ubiquitous kinase), I&#x003ba;BK&#x003b2; (inhibitor
of kappa-B kinase-&#x003b2;), S100b (S100 protein, -&#x003b2; polypeptide, neural),
NF-&#x003ba;B2 (nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer
in B-cells2) and TLR4 (Toll-like receptor4).</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>MeSH (Medical Subject Headings) classification for CGA conformer's identification:</title><p>Total one hundred substances were obtained for CGA (CID-
1794427; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref>), a ligand molecule from PubChem
classification browser search. Structural similarity algorithm was
applied for structure clustering of resultant substances and ninety
eight structures were clustered in eight level of hierarchy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b</xref>).
One substance from each hierarchy level was selected as
representative substance because same hierarchy level substances
considered as a same substance. Most importantly substance with
SID-211535102, 196107032 and 316538495 were showing common
CID-1794427 which is similar to the core ligand molecule CGA.
Remaining four substances with CID-1794425 (cis-chlorogenic
acid), 24802030 (C3950), 11870309 (ZINC03947476) and 5315832
(iso-chlorogenic acid) were used as final conformers of CGA
which was selected for the further in silico studies.</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Active site identification:</title><p>Total ten active sites were predicted by Q-site Finder server for
prepared HMGB1 protein model to decipher the docking of CGA
ligand. The first active site was most prominent and suitable for
any ligand binding due to highest site volume. The prominent
active site has Tyr<sup>78</sup>Ile<sup>79</sup>Pro<sup>80</sup>Pro<sup>81</sup>Lys<sup>82</sup>Gly<sup>83</sup>Glu<sup>84</sup>Thr<sup>85</sup>
Lys<sup>86</sup>Lys<sup>87</sup>Lys<sup>88</sup>Phe<sup>89</sup> Lys<sup>90</sup>Asp<sup>91</sup>Pro<sup>92</sup>Asn<sup>93</sup> Tyr<sup>162</sup>Lys<sup>165</sup> AAs
residues.</p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title>Molecular docking of ligand CGA with HMGB1 protein:</title><p>CGA molecule (CID-1794427) showed 3872 docking score with surface
area 412.6 (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Visualization of docked complex (HMGB1-CGA)
showed interaction of Ile<sup>79</sup>Pro<sup>80</sup>Pro<sup>81</sup>Lys<sup>82</sup>Gly<sup>83</sup>
Glu<sup>84</sup>Lys<sup>86</sup>Lys<sup>87</sup>Lys<sup>88</sup>Phe<sup>89</sup>Arg<sup>163</sup>Ala<sup>164</sup>Lys<sup>165</sup>Gly<sup>166</sup> residues of HMGB1
prominent active site with ligand CGA (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Docked HMGB1-CGA
model was successfully submitted to PMDB database with generated
PMDB-ID PM0079142 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3c</xref>). Docking of selected conformers of
ligand CGA molecule was also done with prominent active site of
HMGB1 protein, to find out the extent of their comparative stability. The
conformers docked model were successfully deposited to PMDB database
with generated PMDB-ID for C3950 conformer (CID-24802030)
PM0080912 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3d</xref>), for ZINC03947476 conformer (CID-11870309)
PM0080911 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e</xref>), for iso-chlorogenic acid conformer (CID-5315832)
PM0080910 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3f</xref>), and for cis-chlorogenic acid conformer (CID-1794425)
PM0080909 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3g</xref>). Docking complex prepared with
conformer C3950 (CID-24802030) showed best docking score and surface
area interaction value 4296 and 508.4 respectively and residues involved
in the interaction are Met<sup>75</sup>Ile<sup>79</sup>Pro<sup>80-81</sup>Lys<sup>82</sup>Glu<sup>84</sup>Lys<sup>86-
88</sup>Phe<sup>89</sup>Asp<sup>91</sup>Tyr<sup>162</sup>Lys<sup>165</sup>Gly<sup>166</sup> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Sequences used for homology modelling of mice HMGB1 protein
showed 99% structural identity and 77% query cover with human
HMGB1. This was to confirm that first ever generated mice
HMGB1 model is as good as that of reference human HMGB1
model for further experiments. According to Ramachandran,
predicted protein structures could be acceptable if it contained
overall high percentage of &#x003a6; and &#x003a8; values within allowed range.
Our results of Ramachandran plot generated by RAMPAGE and
PDBsum servers showed that percent residues were maximum
lied in favoured region and none of the residues were in the
disallowed region, indicated that the protein model is of good
quality. Expression of HMGB1 protein was observed upregulated
in most of the cancers as shown in generated cancer
atlas result (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>),confirming that HMGB1
protein could be targeted in various types of cancers. HMGB1
structure plays various key roles by auto up-regulated expression
as cytokines to activate immune cells, many inflammatory
cytokine genes and also as TFs to bind and up-regulates the
responsible cancer genes, observed by in silico study using CAB
and HPA antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>, 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>). HMGB1 plays an
important role by protein-protein interaction with TLR-4, NF-&#x003ba;B,
and other TFs e.g. STAT and thus involved in the activation of
inflammatory pathway [<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The activity of HMGB1 protein got
inhibited was proved by docking experiments, where inhibitor
molecule CGA binds to its active site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3c</xref>). Surprisingly, all
four docking complex showed better docking score as well as
docking area in comparison to initially docked CGA molecule
(<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Docking result with all CGA molecules conformer was
good but C3950 conformer docked complex was found best and
stable. By using this approach anyone could predict the
conformer of any ligand molecule which showed best docking
with selected target.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Overall, our finding based on results of HMGB1 protein structure
model is very trustworthy, first ever report in mice and could be
utilized for the docking as well as prediction of CGA, CGAconformers
like natural biomolecule drugs that should bound to
the prominent active target site of cancer causing inflammatory
cytokine HMGB1 to prevent and cure several types of cancer. The
designed mice HMGB1 protein model and HMGB1-CGA in silico
docking model might be path breaking finding in the discovery
of potential universal anticancer drug effective against various
cancer types.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>AT and KS are thankful to UGC, New Delhi for financial support.
The corresponding author is thankful to DST-PURSE, UGC-SAP
and DBT-DIC for the research grant support to the School of
Biotechnology, Institute of Science, BHU, India.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest present.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Edited by P Kangueane</bold></p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="other"><p><bold>Citation: </bold>Tripathi <italic>et al.</italic> Bioinformation 15(7):467-473 (2019)</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Toxicol Rep </source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>253</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30911468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30911468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Int J Oncol </source><year>2018</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>659</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29845254?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29845254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bustin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Biochim Biophys Acta </source><year>1990</year><volume>1049</volume><fpage>231</fpage><?supplied-pmid 2200521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2200521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klune</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Mol Med </source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>476</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18431461?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18431461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Leukoc Biol </source><year>2005</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1</fpage><?supplied-pmid 15734795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol </source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15940</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26884867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26884867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Cell Death Dis </source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>648</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29844348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source> Nat Rev Rheumatol</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>195</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22293756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22293756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Orient Pharm Exp Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>51</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>801457</fpage><?supplied-pmid 24062792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24062792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Mol Med Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1106</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23982123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23982123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Anal Methods Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>617243</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23762780?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23762780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2507</fpage><?supplied-pmid 17075131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17075131</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>43830</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28272408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28272408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castrignano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D306</fpage><?supplied-pmid 16381873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponten</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J Pathol</source><year>2008</year><volume>216</volume><fpage>387</fpage><?supplied-pmid 18853439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18853439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>D447</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25352553?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25352553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bull Med. Libr. Assoc</source><year>1963</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>114</fpage><?supplied-pmid 13982385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13982385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1908</fpage><?supplied-pmid 15701681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15701681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneidman-Duhovny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>W363</fpage><?supplied-pmid 15980490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http//www.rcsb.org/structure/2YRQ/">http://www.rcsb.org/structure/2YRQ/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><?supplied-pmid 21372296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21372296</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Submitted PMDB-ID of docked complex with docking score, surface area and interacting residues of active site.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S. No.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ligand used for docking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMDB-ID of docked complex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Docking Score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface area</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residues involved in docking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Common residues in All docking model</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CID 1794427 (CGA)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM0079142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3872</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">412.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ile79, Pro80, Pro81, Lys82, Gly83, Glu84, Lys86,Lys87, Lys88, Phe89, Arg163, Ala164, Lys165 and Gly166 (14 residues)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CID 24802030 (C3950)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM0080912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4296</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Met75, Ile79, Pro80, Pro81, Lys82, Glu84, Lys86,Lys87, Lys88, Phe89, Asp91, Tyr162, Lys165 and Gly166 (14 residues)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ile79, Pro80, Pro81, Glu84, Lys86, Lys87, Phe89 (7 residues)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CID 11870309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM0080911</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">474.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ile79, Pro80, Pro81, Lys82, Gly83, Glu84, Lys86, Lys87 and Phe89 (9 residues)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CID 5315832</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM0080910</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">495.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thr51, Met52, Ala54, Lys55, Glu57 and Lys57 (6 residues)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CID 1794425</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PM0080909</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">424.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ile79; Pro80, Pro81, Gly83,Glu84, Thr85, Lys86,Lys87, Lys88, Phe89,Lys90, Asp91, Tyr162 and Lys165 (14 residues)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(a) Mice HMGB1 protein model generated by homology modelling approach (PMDB ID: PM0079141); (b) PDBsum wiring
diagram representation of secondary structure elements containing 6-&#x003b1; helices, 5-&#x003b2; turns, and 2-&#x003b3; turns; (c) Structural assessment and
verification by RAMPAGE server (d) Structural assessment and verification by PDBSum server.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630015467F1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(a) Detection of expression level of HMGB1 in different cancer using CAB antibody; (b) Detection of expression level of
HMGB1 in different cancer using HPA antibody; (c) Protein-protein interactions assessment by STRING database.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630015467F2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(a) Structure of chlorogenic acid used as a ligand for molecular docking (CID-1794427); (b) Identification of CGA conformers
by structure clustering approach; (c) Molecular Docking of CGA with mice HMGB1 protein (PMDBID: PM0079142) and representation
of active site residues and force of attractions involved in docking; (d) Molecular Docking of conformer C3950 with mice HMGB1
protein (PMDB ID: PM0080912) and representation of active site residues and force of attractions involved in docking; (e) Molecular
Docking of conformer ZINC03947476 with mice HMGB1 protein (PMDB ID: PM0080911) and representation of active site residues and
force of attractions involved in docking; (f) Molecular Docking of conformer iso-chlorogenic acid with mice HMGB1 protein (PMDB ID:
PM0080910) and representation of active site residues and force of attractions involved in docking; (g) Molecular Docking of conformer
cis-chlorogenic acid with mice HMGB-1 protein (PMDB ID: PM0080909) and representation of active site residues and force of
attractions involved in docking.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="97320630015467F3"/></fig></floats-group></article>