<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predicting future conditions and the loss of organic archaeological deposits</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CoupModel was used to investigate the effects of future climate warming on soil temperatures at the five study sites. This was done by simulating two different climate change scenarios (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) based on the mean predictions from the regional climate model RCM HIRHAM5
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> driven with RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 greenhouse gas concentration scenarios (IPCC)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. A three-pool degradation model was included in the CoupModel to investigate the effects of changes in soil thermal and hydrological conditions on the degradation of organic carbon (OC). Based on terminology and values used in other studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, the total pool of OC was divided into a fast (5%), a slow (50%), and a passive pool (45%). The fast pool was considered to represent new OC from fresh plants and animal residues, the slow pool old OC from both archaeological and natural sources and the passive pool highly degraded and no longer biologically active OC. The total observed degradation rate derived from the oxygen consumption measurement was considered to be a sum of three pool-specific rates with turnover times under drained conditions at 5 °C of 1, 50 and &gt;4,000 years, respectively. The absolute loss of carbon was calculated for each soil layer in 24 hour steps and adjusted to the depth-specific temperatures and water contents represented by specific climate change scenarios (see methods section).
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Future climate scenarios.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Temperature increase (°C)</th>
      <th>RCP4.5</th>
      <th>RCP8.5</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Yearly</td>
      <td>2.5</td>
      <td>5.0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Winter (DJF)</td>
      <td>3.1</td>
      <td>6.0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Spring (MAM)</td>
      <td>2.5</td>
      <td>5.0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Summer (JJA)</td>
      <td>2.0</td>
      <td>3.9</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Autumn (SON)</td>
      <td>2.5</td>
      <td>5.0</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>The two climate change scenarios used in the CoupModel to predict future soil temperatures were based on RCM HIRHAM5 driven with RCP 4.5 and 8.5 greenhouse gas concentration scenarios. The increase in air temperature by 2100 was relative to the 2000–2017 mean.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results show that a 2.5 °C (RCP 4.5) and 5.0 °C (RCP 8.5) warming from 2017–2100 could increase mean annual temperatures at the five sites (0.4 m depth) by 0.4–1.0 °C and 1.2–2.6 °C respectively. Depending on the climate change scenario, this will increase the amount of TDD with 196–379 °C or 425–760 °C (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>) and prolong the duration of the frost-free period with 23–75 days or 53–104 days. Currently 0.3–0.8% of the slow OC pool (containing the archaeological OC fraction) is lost per year at 0.4 m. If temperatures increase as predicted, the loss may increase to 0.5–1.1% year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (RCP 4.5) and 0.8–1.6% year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (RCP 8.5). As a result, 20–63% of the current slow OC pool in 0.4 m could be lost within the next 80 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). When integrated over the upper 0.5 m of the deposits for the same time period, results show that 30–70% of the slow OC fraction could be lost. The most rapid degradation appears to occur in the relatively dry continental inland parts of the study region, where many important remains of the Norse Viking Age settlers are found
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. Here a loss of more than 35% within the upper 0.5 m may occur over the next 30 years. These values represent the loss of the current slow OC pool in the deposit. Although in an ecosystem context, this loss will be partly offset or maybe even exceeded by a similar carbon uptake by growing plants
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>
  <sub>,</sub> this has little relevance for the loss of significance of archaeological remains. Because very limited knowledge is available concerning the long-term degradation of archaeological materials and artefacts, it is not possible to estimate how long it will take to destroy remains of for example human hair, bone collagen or DNA. However, we expect the loss of OC in the organic deposits to be closely linked to a loss in quality of buried organic artefacts
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> and that this loss of information is a continuous process. Therefore, the scientific potential of these remains may be reduced significantly before all the archaeological OC has been degraded.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Model results. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Modelled sum of TDD in 0.4 m depth at the five key sites under current climatic conditions (squares), RCP 4.5 (circles) and RCP 8.5 (triangles). (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Percentage loss from 2017–2100 under RCP 4.5 (blue) and RCP 8.5 (red) of the slow OC pool containing the archaeological OC fraction.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45200_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e828" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies of organic archaeological deposits at the site Qajaa, located 550 km north of Nuuk, have shown that permanently frozen archaeological deposits produce substantial quantities of heat when thawed/decomposed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. We performed our simulations with and without heat production and found that the warming effect from microbial heat production was negligible. The degradation rates observed in the Nuuk area are on average 3 times slower than those at Qajaa, and the Nuuk deposits are much thinner (&lt;1 m compared to 3 m). This explains the low heat production potential and confirms that the archaeological deposits in the “warmer” Nuuk area are already significantly degraded.
 </p>
</sec>
