<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The average advance of leaf‐out and flowering to temperature is −3.11 and −2.87 day/°C, respectively, with large interspecific variation. Our observed average flowering response to temperature was weaker than a similar study in Xi'an, China (5.99 day/°C; range: −2.84 to −11.44; Dai, Wang, &amp; Ge, 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013a</xref>), which is 11° latitude south of our study site. This does not support the expectation that the phenological response should be stronger as the result of a stronger seasonal variation at higher latitude in the Northern hemisphere (Jones et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). The tendency for spring phenophases of woody plants to be stronger at lower latitudes than at higher latitudes has been observed in other studies in China (Chen &amp; Xu, 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Dai, Wang, &amp; Ge, 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013b</xref>; Dai et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ge et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), and suggests that, in certain cases, latitude may not be a strong predictor of species phenological response to temperature. Beyond the average community response, the large interspecific variation in response will also likely affect the structure composition of plant communities as the climate warms (Cleland et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Species in our study less able to respond phenologically to climate change could significantly decline in abundance, putting them at great risk of extirpation and even extinction (Davis et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Willis et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33207-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>).
</p>
