<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Body size is increasingly recognized as an important biotic response to the impacts of climate change (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]). Body size scales strongly with key demographic characteristics, including growth rates, fecundity and survival. These attributes carry significant implications for community- and ecosystem-level responses to climate forcing, and therefore, in turn, for population size and viability, important considerations in conservation planning. Evidence that warming temperatures are linked to reduced body sizes of ectotherms is accumulating [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] and these effects appear to be stronger in aquatic than in terrestrial animals [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. There is also evidence for a wide range of responses of body size to latitude and temperature among some marine invertebrate taxa, between hemispheres and among coastlines, suggesting that the mechanisms driving interspecific patterns in body size may vary strongly across regions and taxa [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Importantly, many of these analyses of body size responses have been conducted across temporal scales ranging from decades to millennia (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]) that necessarily include potential factors other than temperature, which may also affect body size (e.g. competition and predation regimes, food availability, fishing pressure, pollution) (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]). In addition, long-term datasets, museum specimens and fossil evidence suitable for these analyses are not available for many species or ecosystems, particularly for coastal areas, necessitating alternative approaches to body size analyses [
 <xref rid="pone.0177116.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>].
</p>
