<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Potato plants employ several strategies to avoid salt injury. One of the key strategies used by potato plants to adapt to salt stress is to exclude Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> accumulation in the cytosol of leaf cells (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Queirós et al., 2009b</xref>). This can be achieved by preventing salt export from shoot to the leaves. Alternatively, the ions can be transported from cytosol to vacuole (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Queirós et al., 2009b</xref>), which not only maintain the enzyme activity in the cytosol but also adjust cell water potential. 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jaarsma and de Boer (2018)</xref> studied the gene expression, corresponding protein levels and activity associated with vacuolar proton pumps and the Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>/H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> antiporters in salt tolerant (cv. Desiree and salt sensitive (cv. Mozart) potato cultivars subject to 60 mM NaCl. Their result revealed that potato plant achieve salt tolerance by accumulating ions in the vacuole through vacuolar proton pump-driven Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> transport across the tonoplast in exchange for H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>. The activity of V-H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>-ATPase and the V-H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>-PPase, and the corresponding protein levels were inhibited in both cultivars following salt treatment (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jaarsma and de Boer, 2018</xref>). However, upon salt treatment, the V-H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>-PPase activity and protein amount were higher in resistant versus sensitive cultivars, which is likely to confer salt tolerance in Desiree. Furthermore, these cultivars responded differentially to H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> pump activity such that the decline in H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> pump activity was less pronounced in the salt tolerant Desiree relative to sensitive Mozart. This was reflected to higher Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>/H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> exchange activity and increased Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> affinity in Desiree than in Mozart. The authors suggest that the higher capacity for Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>/H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> exchange and affinity for Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> uptake confers salt tolerance in Desiree. These results were consistent with previous study, which revealed that salt tolerance in potato is associated with Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> sequestration into vacuole through increase Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>/H
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> antiport activity and pH gradient across the tonoplast (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Queirós et al., 2009b</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jaarsma et al. (2013)</xref> grew six potato cultivars varying in salt tolerance under hydroponic system with different NaCl levels. Their study suggest that the Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> accumulation in shoot is positively correlated with salt tolerance with tolerant cultivars capable of inhibiting Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> export from shoot to leaves.
</p>
