<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Similar to drought adaptation strategy potato plants adapt to salinity stress through osmotic adjustment by accumulating compatible solutes in the cytosol (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fidalgo et al., 2004</xref>). Salinity decreased leaf water potential leading to reduced cell turgidity, growth retardation and tuber yield loss (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Levy et al., 1988</xref>). Accumulation of compatible solutes is believed to maintain cell turgor pressure without affecting cytosolic enzymatic reactions. This notion is supported by the fact that the proline, a well-known compatible solute, content of Desiree leaves increased by 3.5-fold and 11-fold at 100 and 200 mM NaCl, respectively, compared to untreated controls (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fidalgo et al., 2004</xref>). Similar result was obtained following short-term exposure or long-term growth under saline conditions (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Queirós et al., 2011</xref>). However, recently 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Odemis and Caliskan (2014)</xref> reported that the foliar application of proline was not effective to minimize the effects of salinity on several physiological characteristics and yield parameters. Thus, effects of proline on salt stress tolerance needs further study. Potato plants under salinity stress adapt to osmotic stress by reducing leaf area and advancing premature leaf senescence to preventing transpirational water loss. Potato plants also avoid salt injury by shortening growth cycle such that the early-maturing exhibits lower tuber yield loss compared to late-maturing cultivars (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Levy et al., 1988</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Legay et al. (2009)</xref> reported that potato plants adapt to osmotic stress through induction of transcription factors mediated by ABA-dependent or ABA-independent pathways. Salt stress induced the synthesis of ABA in both leaf and xylem sap (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akhtar et al., 2015</xref>). ABA is a well-known signaling molecules for closing stomata and inducing expression of several genes involved in stress tolerance including salinity.
</p>
