<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical reconstruction of wetland dynamics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The soil moistures in the middle and bottom soil layers were better correlated with observed wetland water levels than other water balance variables (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s001">S1 Fig</a>). The best predictor differed among years and regions. Soil moisture in the middle soil layer was the best predictor for most of wetlands based on observed data in 1992 for Mount Rainier National Park and 2000 for Olympic National Park (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s002">S2 Fig</a>). However the strength of correlations differed substantially between the 1992 Mount Rainier and 2000 Olympics datasets, with fairly strong correlations between wetland water levels and middle layer soil moisture in Mount Rainier and far weaker correlations and poor overall model performance in the Olympic sites in 2000. Overall, though, soil moisture in the bottom soil layer was the best predictor for all wetlands except the 1992 Mount Rainier and 2000 Olympics datasets, with fairly robust correlations between simulated and empirical data (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s002">S2 Fig</a>). After choosing the best single predictor for each wetland, we developed a regression model for each individual wetland.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The R
  <span class="sup">2</span> values showed that the regression models match empirical observations reasonably well, with a mean R
  <span class="sup">2</span> for all for wetland types above 0.8, though a few wetlands (6 out of 125; 4.8%) had an R
  <span class="sup">2</span> value below 0.6 (Figs 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g004">4</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s003">S3</a>). Overall, ephemeral and intermediate wetlands showed the best model fits, while perennial ponds had the weakest fit among wetland types (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g004">Fig 4</a>). The observed timing and pattern of seasonal drawdown generally were captured well by simulations for montane wetlands across the majority of our different sites (0.82 &lt; R
  <span class="sup">2</span> &lt; 0.98) (Figs 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g005">5</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g006">6</a>). 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g005">Fig 5</a> illustrates representative wetlands for each pond type from Mount Rainier (left column) and Olympic National Parks (right column), selected from sites with the most observed data. Exceptions to the overall good model performance were the minimum water level for the year 2006 for Deschutes National Forest, Oregon (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g006">Fig 6A</a>) and the timing of drawdown for the year 2003 in Trinity Alps Wilderness, California (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g006">Fig 6C</a>). For the Deschutes National Forest, the observed minimum water level for year 2006 was 13% of full capacity but the simulation minimum was 22–34%. For the Trinity Alps Wilderness site, the wetland started drawdown about one month later in 2003 compared to the other years but the simulation was not able to reproduce this timing.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0136385.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136385.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Boxplot of goodness of fit (R
    <span class="sup">2</span>) between observed and simulated data for each wetland type.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136385.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0136385.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136385.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Four representative wetlands in Mt. Rainier National Park, WA (a-d) and in Olympic National Park, WA (e-h) for ephemeral hydroperiod (a,e), intermediate hydroperiod(b,f), perennial (c,g) and permanent wetland (d,h).</div>
   <p>Solid circles show observed data that are used for developing regression model and calculating R
    <span class="sup">2</span> values and open circles are remaining observed data. Blue lines are simulated wetland levels.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136385.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0136385.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136385.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Observed wetland water levels compared with simulation using the regression models for a) Deschutes National Forest, OR, b) Willamette National Forest, OR, and c) Trinity Alps Wilderness, CA.</div>
   <p>Dark blue lines are produced by the regression equation deriving from the best fit from all available years. Blue bands show the range of uncertainty associated with alternate regression parameters deriving from other years of data.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136385.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For sites where multiple years of data existed, we found considerable uncertainty and variation in model performance (Figs 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g006">6</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g007" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g007">7</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s004">S4</a>). For example, different regression models for the Trinity Alps (CA) site, constructed using different years of data, showed an average difference of 47 days between the earliest and latest prediction of minimum water levels in summer (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g006">Fig 6C</a>). While the regression model for Mount Rainier National Park developed based on 1992 data (0.83 &lt; R
  <span class="sup">2</span> &lt; 0.99; 1.60 &lt; RMSE &lt; 8.91) also captured the observed drawdown at the same wetlands in 2012 (1.77 &lt; RMSE &lt; 15.63) (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.g007" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0136385.g007">Fig 7</a>), model performance across different years was poor for Olympic National Park. For Olympic National Park, the regression model based on 2000 observations (0.51 &lt; R
  <span class="sup">2</span> &lt; 0.81; 4.28 &lt; RMSE &lt; 19.67) missed the timing of drawdown and/or minimum water levels observed in 2012 (17.57 &lt; RMSE &lt; 49.12) (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s004">S4 Fig</a>). We therefore might expect comparable levels of uncertainty in the performance of the single-year regression fits for the broader suite of wetlands at Mount Rainier, Olympic and North Cascades National Parks. These issues related to the performance of single-year regression fits once again highlight the need for improved monitoring of wetlands over multiple years.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0136385.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136385.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Observed wetland water level for year 1992 (a-c) and for year 2012 (d-f) for ponds at Mount Rainier National Park compared with the simulated wetland water levels using the regression model that were developed based on 1992 observation.</div>
   <p>Solid circles show observed data that are used for developing regression model and/or for calculating R
    <span class="sup">2</span> values and open circles are the other observed data. RMSE is the root mean squared error, which allows comparison of model fit for the two datasets.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136385.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In investigating the threshold for wetland drying we found that, on average across regions, wetland drying occurred when soil moisture was at roughly 100% field capacity, though there was considerable variation among sites (
  <a rid="pone.0136385.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0136385.s005">S5 Fig</a>). Therefore to have a single metric for landscape-scale analysis, we use 100% field capacity as a mean threshold of drying and proxy for intermediate wetland drying for each VIC grid cell. These values help quantify systematic changes in wetland response over large areas in response to climate change, but probably do not represent the details of individual wetland responses very well.
 </p>
</sec>
