<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, the regression models produced for this study successfully capture historical wetland dynamics during the ecologically important summer drawdown seasons for four different wetland types. However, the regression models were not as robust in capturing different behavior in different years, highlighting the need for longer (&gt;5 year) observed datasets. Additionally, datasets with higher within-year resolution would strengthen the regression approach and enable us to better understand both sources of model error (e.g. geology and soil types, topography, distance from weather stations, etc.) as well as the uncertainty in the range of potential climate impacts and the hydrologic drivers that underlie impacts on wetlands.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nonetheless, these models are an important first step in understanding wetland response to climate, and strongly suggest that, looking forward, climate change will significantly alter water availability for individual wetlands, which will lead to substantial future shifts in the distribution and composition of wetlands across montane landscapes of the Pacific Northwest. These hydrologic shifts imply widespread changes in the many ecological roles served by wetlands, including: habitat for plants and animals, water storage, groundwater recharge, water quality (filtration), and shifts in nutrient cycling. For wetland-reliant species like amphibians and invertebrates that are particularly sensitive to the timing of water availability in montane areas, the projected changes in wetland hydrologic response are likely to reduce habitat availability and recruitment, and cause declines or extinctions in some regions [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref029">29</a>].
 </p>
 <sec id="sec013" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical model performance</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil moisture in the bottom soil layer was the best predictor of wetland drawdown for most of the sites investigated, supporting the hypothesis that wetland drawdown cycles are frequently associated with relatively slow drainage and evapotranspiration processes. The regression models demonstrated generally good performance across all four types of montane wetlands within years, successfully capturing the general time series behavior of each wetland. However, regression models performed better in some years than others and simulations were not able to capture all observed variability (e.g. overestimated wetland minimum water level during 2006 in the Deschutes National Forest site, the error in drawdown timing in the Trinity-Alps in 2003, and the missed drawdown timing and/or minimum water levels in Olympic National Park in 2012). These spatial and temporal variations in model performance are expected, and are seen in other comparisons between simulated and observed data at fine spatial scales, such as snow water equivalent measured at individual snow courses [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref015">15</a>]. One reason for the discrepancy is that local precipitation is often imperfectly captured in the driving data sets for the VIC model at high elevations (e.g. data from meteorological stations at lower elevations are interpolated to higher elevations in landscapes with high orographic variation). The estimated uncertainty using multiple years of observations in the Oregon and California sites confirmed that our approach is fairly robust in some regions and/or years. However, at times uncertainties are broad enough to be biologically meaningful (e.g. in terms of evaluating risk to particular species). Likewise, the failure of the regression models to effectively capture strongly different patterns of wetland response across very different weather years in Olympic National Park shows that this approach is not universally robust. Additional water-level data would help better evaluate the performance of the models, and likely also improve their performance by allowing additional explanatory variables to be included in the regression models.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec014" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate impacts on wetlands</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our climate-change projections demonstrate that all four of the wetland types on which we focused (ephemeral, intermediate, perennial, and permanent wetlands) are likely to experience hydrologic changes in response to future climate. However, the intensity and duration of climate change effects will differ markedly among the four types. These changes are also likely to lead to transitions along the continuum of wetland types captured in our hydrologic classes. Specifically, some ephemeral wetlands may essentially disappear and more than half of currently ecologically productive intermediate montane wetlands are projected to become ephemeral wetlands by the 2080s, as more rapid recession rate and earlier drawdown cause wetlands to reach their bottom volume earlier, resulting in more frequent and longer dry seasons in summer. For some perennial wetlands (e.g. Washington sites), transitions from perennial to intermediate wetlands or even to ephemeral wetlands are also projected as wetland water levels drop under climate change. Driving these changes is the fact that most montane wetlands are located either in snow-dominated watersheds or mixed-rain-and-snow watersheds where snowmelt is a key water source in late spring and summer. Because a warmer climate is likely to cause less snow accumulation in winter and earlier snowmelt in spring, montane wetlands are particularly susceptible to climate change, especially in combination with projected drier summers [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref017">17</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref018">18</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison between wetlands in Washington and those in Oregon and California also shows that wetlands with seemingly similar hydrologic characteristics are likely to have different sensitivity to climate change depending on local conditions. For example, perennial wetlands in our focal sites in Willamette and Deschutes National Forests, Oregon are likely to be less sensitive to climate change in terms of minimum water level compared to those in Washington. For perennial wetlands in Oregon, simulated summer soil moisture in the VIC simulations was close to residual values nearly every year but the wetlands did not dry out (maintaining ~20% of their maximum depth) under the current climate. This behavior suggests that these wetlands are coupled to more extensive deep groundwater sources, not captured in the VIC simulations, than wetlands in Washington. For the climate-change scenarios, wetlands in Oregon and California are projected to have earlier drawdown and reach their minimum water level earlier, but without drying out. This supports the argument that wetlands connected to deeper groundwater sources are less vulnerable to increased frequency of drying when compared to surface water-fed wetlands [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref047">47</a>]. However, because the VIC model does not include a deep groundwater component, more sophisticated modeling approaches (such as the use of fine scale groundwater models) may be required to fully capture these effects [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref048">48</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref049">49</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec015" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological implications of future wetland change for wetland biota</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The broad range of ecological roles played by wetlands means that altered hydrology across whole landscapes will reverberate in many ways, ranging from shifts in wildlife habitat to water storage to patterns of nutrient transfer and transformation. Patterns of soil inundation, for example, determine rates of carbon sequestration and release, nitrogen transformations, and other nutrient cycles. Likewise, changes in temporal pulses of peak water affect local pond metabolism and primary productivity, the structure of plant communities, and patterns of wildlife connectivity [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref006">6</a>]. Montane wetlands serve as critical habitat for a wide variety of species, many of which are adapted and sensitive to particular hydrologic regimes that are projected to shift under future climates.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For wetland-reliant species like amphibians and invertebrates that require minimum durations of water availability to breed and complete aquatic life stages, the projected changes in wetland hydrologic response are likely to reduce the number of sites available for breeding, may affect larval densities, individual correlates of fitness such as size at metamorphosis, and reduce recruitment success [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref029">29</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref050">50</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref051">51</a>]. While many species will be affected by changes in both the timing and frequency of drying, those that metamorphose within a single summer may be more sensitive to changes in the timing of wetland drying. In contrast, species that require multiple years to complete larval development are likely to be most sensitive to changes in the frequency of drying [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>]. In wetlands not at risk of drying entirely, ecological effects may also depend on how thermal conditions in ponds change as the climate warms and water levels drop [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref033">33</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref052">52</a>]. Finally, as the distribution of wetland hydroperiod changes, so will the spatial distribution of suitable wetland habitats. This may affect important drivers of population and community dynamics such as population connectivity, synchrony, and rates of recolonization [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref053">53</a>]. Increased reproductive failures due to drying would further alter local and regional extinction rates [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref029">29</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref054">54</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For amphibians in particular, already known to be in decline in many montane regions, climate impacts are likely to interact with non-climate threats such as disease, pollution, and the presence of introduced fish [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref055">55</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref058">58</a>]. Amphibians and invertebrates are also important prey for many montane species, so population declines in these assemblages could propagate up food webs, negatively affecting the birds, non-avian reptiles, and mammals that rely on them as prey [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref059">59</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref060">60</a>]. Overall, species’ exposure will depend on what kinds of wetland habitat they use, the current distribution of wetland types across landscapes, and the degree of change in spatial and temporal hydrologic patterns under future climates [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next steps</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our approach demonstrates a promising first step in relating simulated macro-scale hydrologic variables to observed wetland hydrologic behavior, and projecting the impacts of climate variability and change on montane wetlands in Washington, Oregon, and California. Our relatively robust results across different wetland types, especially given the limited data on which to build regression models, contradict the assumption that wetland dynamics are by definition too complex to model. Challenges remain, however. Because our methods were applied mostly in wetlands with at most a few years of observed hydrologic data (often only a single year), extending these approaches to confirm the robustness of our approach over different ecoregions, additional wetland types, and across a longer time series are essential next steps. These models also need to be coupled to better on-the-ground or remote sensing-derived data on wetland occurrence and type so that the most useful predictions about historical and/or future wetland changes can be made (e.g. existing wetland maps for Mount Rainier National Park miss &gt;50% of the small, biologically productive wetlands that we discuss here) [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref061">61</a>]. New remote-sensing methods also make it possible in some cases to reconstruct the historical hydrologic dynamics of wetlands [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref062">62</a>], and these in turn provide important validation datasets for retrospective modeling studies. Pairing improved maps with VIC hydrologic projections across large spatial scales will make it possible for the first time to identify hotspots of climate risk to wetlands, how these may interact with other stressors [
   <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>]. Overall, however, the models presented here offer a first step in beginning to fill the gap in scientific resources for wetland conservation, vulnerability assessment, and climate adaptation planning at both local and regional scales.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
