<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wetlands are universally recognized as a globally important ecosystem type that provides food and habitat to a wide range of aquatic and terrestrial species. Wetlands also influence local hydrologic processes (e.g. groundwater recharge, surface water storage, and filtration) and biogeochemical cycles (nutrient cycling, carbon sequestration, sediment and contaminant transport) [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref007">7</a>]. Wetlands are widely considered to be among the most vulnerable ecosystems to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref008">8</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref009">9</a>], particularly in montane and alpine areas that are already experiencing accelerated effects of climate change such as reduced snowpack [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref002">2</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref010">10</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref011">11</a>]. However, the vulnerability of montane wetlands to climate change has not been quantified due in part to a dearth of empirical data and methods for modeling wetland dynamics. Data constraints also exacerbate a broader impression that these diverse and dynamic ecosystems may be too complex to model because of limited ability to characterize the hydrologic details in specific locations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mountain wetlands remain far less impacted by anthropogenic disturbance in comparison to those in the lowlands where water withdrawal, land-use change, and direct destruction (e.g. draining or filling) have caused substantial losses of wetlands over the past two centuries (e.g. &gt;50% loss in the contiguous U.S.) [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref012">12</a>]. For this reason, wetland data from alpine regions are an important resource for understanding baseline patterns and processes of hydrologic variation over time as a function of climate. Also, as climate change accelerates, impacts on montane and alpine areas are expected to intensify [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref005">5</a>]. In the western U.S. where snow is an important component of the hydrologic cycle [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref013">13</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref016">16</a>], increased warming in all seasons and projected decreased summer precipitation are likely to result in loss of mountain snowpack, increased evapotranspiration and increased soil-moisture stress in late summer [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref017">17</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref025">25</a>]. We hypothesize that these hydrologic impacts would also result in loss of sensitive montane wetlands and systematic, landscape-scale changes in wetland structure and function in areas that are otherwise highly protected, such as National Parks and Wilderness Areas. These changes compound lower elevation losses of wetlands due to human development [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref012">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrologic changes and potential shifts in the distribution of wetlands across montane landscapes could have substantial consequences for wetland species, ecosystems, and their extended biological networks. Because many wetland species sort along coarse hydrologic gradients, such as duration of inundation or wetland permanence, as a function of life history and developmental requirements [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref026">26</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref027">27</a>], their vulnerability to climate-induced habitat loss will not be distributed evenly [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref028">28</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref029">29</a>]. Therefore understanding climate impacts on different hydrologic classes of wetlands is critical to assessing vulnerability of particular species or types of wetland ecosystems, and more generally to understanding how the wide range of ecological services wetlands provide is likely to change over time.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The shortage of empirical data on wetland dynamics, coupled with the inherent complexities of studying wetlands (e.g. sheer number of sites, diverse range of wetland types, highly dynamic hydrologic responses, etc.), has allowed an untested assumption to persist, i.e. that wetlands are simply too complex to model with the limited site specific information and data that are available. The challenges are real: existing methods for wetland hydrologic modeling largely focus on individual sites and require a detailed understanding of fine-scale surface and subsurface hydrologic processes (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref030">30</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref031">31</a>]). The data necessary for these models are almost universally lacking for wetlands in general and for small wetlands in particular, which are largely defined by the microtopography of their surroundings and connections to groundwater and small streams. Where data and models are available, a key limitation of such fine-scale approaches is that they generally cannot be applied to answer questions of how wetland dynamics will respond to climate change at the landscape scale. The limited approaches that do exist for predicting landscape-level response require longer time series of hydrometeorological data than are generally available (e.g. WETLANDSCAPE models) [
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0136385.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136385.ref032">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we present new methods not only for reconstructing historical dynamics when observed hydrologic data are limited, thereby filling important data gaps, but also for projecting the impacts of future climate change on wetland water levels. We draw upon an empirical dataset (125 ponds across 5 National Parks and Wilderness Areas in the U.S. Pacific Northwest) to develop a new set of hydrologic models for four classes of montane wetlands that vary in hydroperiod. Our methods generate projections at two spatial scales: a) individual wetlands and b) landscape scales. The approaches we develop allow us to quantify the combined effects of projected future reductions in snowpack and of warmer and drier summers on mountain wetlands. Looking forward, these projections can be used to develop testable hypotheses for wetlands research, develop climate adaptation strategies, and provide specific decision support for managers tasked with wetlands conservation, restoration, and management.</p>
</sec>
