<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have revealed that different vegetation change metrics—change in the cover of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>caerulea</italic>, shrubs, specialist vascular plants and specialist bryophytes—respond to mowing in different ways. At both sites we observed a decrease in 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>caerulea</italic> cover in the mown plots, although there was also a significant interaction with time between surveys for this metric, implying that the changes could be a result of differences in the timing of the initial set up of the plots (up to 17 years). However, this is likely to be related to the large increase in 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>caerulea</italic> in the unmown plots at the oceanic site. Shrub cover also declined at the continental site. The suppression of 
 <italic>M</italic>.
 <italic>caerulea</italic> and shrubs by mowing is likely to be the most important factor in maintaining typical open fen vegetation [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Mowing has been linked with the persistence and restoration of fens by preventing litter accumulation and reducing the density of the field layer, thus reducing competitive interactions and creating space for less competitive, light-demanding species [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Similar outcomes have been recorded in other anthropogenic vegetation types, including prairie grassland [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], temperate grassland [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], wet meadows [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and calcareous sand dune meadows [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Mowing has also been found to favour certain rare species such as the orchid 
 <italic>Dactylorhiza lapponica</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and the grassland endemic 
 <italic>Gentianella praecox</italic> ssp. 
 <italic>bohemica</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. However, in our study, the decline of species such as 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>palustris</italic> and 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>pusilla</italic> occurred regardless of mowing, showing that other environmental drivers are also affecting the vegetation. Although grazing would appear to provide a similar type of disturbance to mowing, the introduction of grazing to a fen may cause extensive damage from trampling due to the wet conditions, creating a more heterogeneous habitat as a result [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In a few examples were grazing was used as a restoration measure in a fen or fen meadow, the cover of fen specialists in grazed areas did not increase relative to similar ungrazed areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], or contained fewer fen specialist species than mown areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Mowing therefore appears to be particularly effective in promoting specialist vascular plant species, which suggests that the propagules of these species are still present, strengthening the argument for restoration before abandonment causes these species to disappear. However, the same is not the case for bryophytes, which could indicate a response to climate warming. Differences in response to mowing between the different species groups occur because of differences in morphology, physiology and ecology [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Bryophytes lack roots for active water uptake from the ground, and are poikilohydric, whereby water and nutrients are absorbed over the whole surface of the plant [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Consequently, bryophyte growth may be more dependent of precipitation patterns than groundwater levels. Bryophytes may therefore respond more negatively to climate change than vascular plants, and may also indicate such changes earlier [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].
</p>
