<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toad collection and management</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We collected 18 female and 20 male 
  <span class="italic">B. calamita</span> by hand during their mating season (January–April) in 2015. Toads were caught while active on rainy nights, or actively searched for under rocks or logs during the day. We distinguished males because their throats are purple-to-pink due to their vocal sacs, and because they show brown or black nuptial pads in their fingers and forelimb tubercles (
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Gómez-Mestre, 2014</a>). For each toad, we measured SVL with a ruler to the nearest mm, body mass with a balance (model CDS-100, precision 0.01 g), and left forelimb sole pad thickness to the nearest 0.01 mm, using a pressure-sensitive micrometer (Mitutoyo). We took three consecutive measures in quick succession, and considered the mean as sole pad thickness (
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Brown, Shilton &amp; Shine, 2011</a>). Afterwards, we subcutaneously injected 0.1 mg of phytohemagglutinin (PHA, Sigma Aldrich L-8754; Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) diluted in 0.01 ml phosphate buffer saline in left forelimb sole pad. We inoculated the same amount of PHA to all individuals because there were no significant differences in body mass between toads from both habitats (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,37</sub> = 0.146; 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.704). PHA is a protein that provokes a safe skin-swelling immune response that involves T-cells and other components of the immune system (
  <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">Kennedy &amp; Nager, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">Martin et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Bílková, Vinklerová &amp; Vinkler, 2015</a>). The magnitude of that swelling is directly proportional to the capacity of the individual to elicit an immune response (
  <a rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-68">Parmentier, De Vries Reilingh &amp; Nieuwland, 1998</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-87">Vinkler, Bainova &amp; Albrecht, 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">Clulow, Harris &amp; Mahony, 2015</a>). This method has proved valid in amphibians (
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Brown, Shilton &amp; Shine, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">Clulow, Harris &amp; Mahony, 2015</a>). According to 
  <a rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-79">Smits, Bortolotti &amp; Tella (1999)</a>, omitting phosphate buffer saline (PBS) controls in PHA tests has little impact on the results, decreases handling errors, and reduces the coefficient of variation resulting from measurement inaccuracy. For this reason, PHA tests are often simplified by not using PBS controls in amphibians (
  <a rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-26">Gervasi &amp; Foufopoulos, 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-39">Iglesias-Carrasco, Martín &amp; Cabido, 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-93">Zamora-Camacho, in press</a>) as well as in other groups (v.gr. 
  <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">Martin, 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Hale &amp; Briskie, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">Moreno-Rueda, 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-60">Moreno-Rueda &amp; Redondo, 2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After inoculations, we measured sole pad thickness as described, once per hour, for the six hours subsequent to inoculations. Early swelling response to PHA in this species peaks before six hours from inoculation (
  <a rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-93">Zamora-Camacho, in press</a>). This procedure allowed us to calculate swelling immune response on an hourly basis, by subtracting sole pad thickness prior to inoculations to sole pad thickness at each hourly measure after inoculation for each individual. At these early stages, swelling response to PHA is directly proportional to recruitment of macrophages, eosinophils and neutrophils, which corresponds to an innate response in closely-related 
  <span class="italic">Rhinella marina</span> toads (
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Brown, Shilton &amp; Shine, 2011</a>). With that information, for each individual, we calculated area under the curve (AUC, in h*mm) resulting from swelling-response progression during the six hours measured, as a directly proportional measurement of swelling response magnitude incorporating time (
  <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Fekedulegn et al., 2007</a>). We obtained AUC with software GraphPad Prism 7.0, which applies the trapezoidal formula. During the whole procedure, we kept toads in individual plastic terraria, with humid peat as a substrate and an opaque piece of plastic as a shelter. Toads were released at their capture sites after the last measure.
 </p>
</sec>
