<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Analysis in the AR5 report lists the following: accelerating rates of global mean SLR: 1.7 mm yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (1901–2010), 2.0 mm yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (1971–2010), and 3.2 mm yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (1993–2010) and predicts 60–100 cm SLR by 2100
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>. Locally, RSLR (relative sea level rise) has been higher, due to a SLR “hot spot” along the Atlantic Coast of North America
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>, part of a region in the North Atlantic above global mean SLR
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>. This “hot spot” extends from Cape Hatteras, NC to Boston, MA and rose 3.80 ± 1.06 mm yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (1970–2009). The Southern Chesapeake Bay region, within this “hot spot,” had a higher rate of SLR (4.40 ± 0.086 mm yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> from 1955–2007), due to land subsidence (2.101 mm yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) due to glacial rebound caused by the Laurentide ice sheet melting
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>, groundwater extraction, as well as after effects of a meteor impact near Cape Charles, VA approximately 35.5 million years ago
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>, which is still causing local land subsidence
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>. Glacial rebound is causing a significant portion of local land subsidence, with groundwater pumping being the other major factor. Aquifer-system compaction is causing more than half of local land subsidence, especially near population and agricultural centers. This compaction can account for more than 50% of observed land subsidence rates in the region and even more so near regions where extensive groundwater pumping is occurring, such as near the cities of West Point, Franklin and Norfolk, Virginia
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>. Due to the isolation of Tangier Island from major population and agricultural centers responsible for extensive groundwater pumping, groundwater pumping related subsidence at Tangier Island may be less than 50% of total subsidence reported locally, but it is likely significant.
</p>
