<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Tangier Islands are a complex of what are now several islands, once connected, located in Virginia waters of Chesapeake Bay (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) near the border between Virginia and Maryland approximately 151 km southeast of Washington DC. The main remaining Tangier Islands are, from north to south, Goose, Uppards, Port Isobel and Tangier Island. The Tangier Islands lie 22 km east of mainland Virginia and 16.2 km west from the Eastern Shore, a peninsula that partially encloses Chesapeake Bay. The West side of the Bay has deeper waters than those East of the Islands. Due to the longer fetch, wave action along western shores of the Islands is more powerful. Large SAV (seagrass) beds (μ = 296 HA from 2003–13
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>) lie immediately east of the Islands, which protect the SAV from the western fetch. A 1.74-km long rock revetment was constructed along the majority of western shore of Tangier Island in 1989 at a cost of 10.614 million (inflation-adjusted 2014 USD). It has successfully protected a small airport (48.98 HA, 1.5 m above PMSL (Present Mean Sea Level) and nearby Town of Tangier (33.59 HA, 1.46 m above PMSL). The Town is on three upland sand ridges ranging in length from 518–1859 m and up to 396 m wide
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>. It is primarily an isolated fishing community, with a significant portion (13%, the highest total for any town in Chesapeake Bay) of the most valuable fishery in the Bay, blue crabs, 
 <italic class="italic">Callinectes sapidus</italic>. This fishery (~30 million USD yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> ex-vessel revenue in Virginia)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref> provides the majority of the income for Tangier fishermen. The Town relies on artesian wells drilled approximately 300 m deep into an Eocene era aquifer beneath the Bay, and the average amount of water pumped has been 380 m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> day
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (Mills 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> 2005), which, when compared to the pumping near large population centers in southeast Virginia that have caused local subsidence near the pumping areas the amount of water pumping by the citizens of the Town of Tangier appears to be insignificant with respect to local subsidence. The construction of a navigation channel between Tangier and Uppards Islands in 1967 may have accelerated local erosion along Uppards due to boat wakes. Placement of dredged material in several landward cells (&lt;10 HA) in the mid-to-late 1900s increased elevation in a few areas, particularly on Port Isobel. Along the eastern shore of Port Isobel, six stone breakwaters were placed in the 2000s for shoreline protection.
</p>
