<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In North America, we should perhaps be more concerned about triatomine bugs known to transmit Chagas disease, a common condition in rural areas of Latin America.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr41-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> Triatomine insects are also very common in the Southern United States.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr41-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr42-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr43-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr44-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr45-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup> Now, Chagas is spreading further North, in parts of the Southern United States where the disease has more recently occurred autochthonously, most likely due to increasing temperature, immigration, and global travel.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr41-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr46-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr47-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> There are at least 11 different species of triatomine insects in the United States, and many reservoir host species also inhabit this country, such as woodrats, racoons, skunks, and coyotes.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr41-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> Certain counties in Texas are particularly at risk because of low-income neighborhoods called “colonias,” which are characterized by poorly constructed residences and sanitation systems that would provide habitat for the insects and easier access into peoples’ homes.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr48-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup> It is also possible that changing climatic conditions could cause a change in the behavior of triatomine insects.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr48-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr49-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr50-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup> Triatomine insects tend to feed more often to avoid dehydration when temperatures are upward of 30°C and humidity levels are low.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr49-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup> It has also been found that when indoor temperatures rise, triatomine insects may take on shorter life cycles, allowing them to increase their population density and increase the chances of spreading disease.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr49-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup> Other published reports have demonstrated faster development of 
 <italic class="italic">Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>, the causative agent of Chagas disease, in some vector hosts when temperatures increase.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr50-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
