<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Adding to this is the preponderance of sand flies, an insect vector for leishmaniasis, encompassing a spectrum of clinical manifestations of variable prognosis that range from skin ulcerative lesions around the infection site, called localized cutaneous leishmaniasis, multiple nonulcerative lesions, called diffuse or disseminated cutaneous leishmaniasis, and severe disfiguring mucosal metastatic disease. It is responsible for significant morbidity and gross domestic product loss in many countries. In the United States, cases are recorded yearly in foreign travelers, immigrants, and military personnel.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr52-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr53-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr54-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> Reports of autochthonous leishmanial infections among individuals who have never traveled outside the United States abound.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr55-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr56-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr57-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr58-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr59-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
  <xref rid="bibr60-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr61-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup> With the effect of climate change contributing to an increased range for sand flies, and flies being found in new locales, in addition to servicemen/women who served in the Middle East and may have been exposed to infection returning home, the opportunity for leishmaniasis in North America to expand both substantially and dramatically is now becoming a reality.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr62-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup> It has been recognized that in certain areas of the world, 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> infection rates are associated with seasonal variation.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr63-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr64-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> Ecological niche models also predicted the expansion of suitable habitat for sand fly vectors, further increasing the risk of leishmaniasis in areas currently not endemic.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr63-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr64-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> Even under the most restrictive model circumstances, human exposure to leishmaniasis is predicted to at least double by the year 2080 in the United States.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr59-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup> However, considering the rates of human migration and global civil unrests leading to massive movement of people from endemic areas to nonendemic regions of the world and international travel, this threshold should be crossed way earlier than predicted.
</p>
