<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A third climate change modeling framework coupled an SDM to a meta-population dynamic model (which we term CC-SDM/MPD), but this effort was specific to hooded warbler, and was focused on assessing model uncertainties. A University of Toronto group used this approach to provide projections of habitat suitability over the entire breeding range for hooded warbler, which include almost all of the Great Lakes Basin [
 <xref rid="pone.0172668.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. The hierarchical modeling framework began with a SDM derived through MaxEnt using the NA-BBS records and point-count locations from the first (1981–1985) and second (2001–2005) Ontario Breeding Bird Atlases and current climate data from the Worldclim database [
 <xref rid="pone.0172668.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Climate variables were selected a priori because on biologically relevant factors for migratory birds over the breeding range and were summarized with months associated with the breeding season. The SDMs were project forward using four downscaled GCMs (HADCM3, CCMA, CSIRO, and NIES), as well as an ensemble model, using the A2 scenario only to assess future climate suitability. Additionally, the authors assessed the deviations among GMCs during late-century projections to understand which climate variables were most significant in determining future projections of habitat suitability. Next, the climate SDM was integrated with a metapopulation model using empirical and expert knowledge [
 <xref rid="pone.0172668.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] and dispersal was modelled in RAMAS GIS [
 <xref rid="pone.0172668.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. A binary map (forest and non-forest) of suitable cover was derived for southern Ontario to map suitable habitat patches of mature forest with openings or gaps greater than 1 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (
 <xref rid="pone.0172668.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The relative habitat suitability map based on the SDMs was modified by multiplying it by the binary forest map. RAMAS GIS was then used to identify patches of suitable habitat and link projections to meta-population dynamic models that considered habitat patch occupancy and extinction risk. This model was then used to assess extinction risk under the GCMs as well as the impact of the direct loss of habitat, where patches were randomly removed from the landscape. The influence of various parameters was assessed using the RandomForest decision tree program. The model including all climate variables produced the highest AUC score (0.802).
</p>
