<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future trends</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The practice, and to some degree the study, of conservation is currently undergoing a major shift—a shift from a focus on nature to a focus on nature and people. The idea that people are a part of ecosystems and that conservation needs to include the social sciences is not new and this is not the shift to which we are referring. This new shift is one from conserving nature for nature’s sake to conserving nature both for nature’s sake and for the use and enjoyment by people 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-85">85</a>
  </span>. This shift has resulted in an apparent change in the missions and the actions of several major non-governmental conservation organizations (for example, The Nature Conservancy, the World Wildlife Fund, and Conservation International). Like the subject of assisted colonization, however, this shift has not been well received by all in the conservation community and there remains a heated debate in conservation circles as well as in the literature about the degree to which conservation should focus on the needs of people 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-85">85</a>– 
   <a rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-88">88</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of this shift can be clearly seen in the way that conservation organizations are addressing climate change and is reflected in the application of all of the approaches mentioned above. With respect to restoration, conservation planning, and connectivity, conservation practitioners have begun to target efforts that consider the roles that natural systems play in protecting people against the potential impacts of climate change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-89">89</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-90">90</a>
  </span>. These ecosystem-based adaptation strategies may be more cost-effective than hard infrastructure-based solutions. One striking example of this approach is The Nature Conservancy’s “flood plains by design” strategy in which stretches of river are restored in places that will simultaneously reduce flooding of nearby communities and restore fish habitat. Another example is the active protection of coastal habitats, which has the potential to reduce the risks and the costs of sea-level rise, providing a critical service in the face of climate change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-91" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-91">91</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because climate-driven changes are likely to be so large in some places, climate change is in part causing conservation practitioners to question their goals as well as the approaches they use 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">7</a>
  </span>. These new goals are beginning to take people’s needs into account. For example, restoration efforts are now being refocused toward ecosystem function and ecosystem services instead of the specific set of species in a given ecosystem 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">19</a>
  </span>. In addition, assisted colonization may be called on not just to preserve threatened species, but also to provide certain functions—and perhaps to allow ecosystems to provide certain services 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-73">73</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-92" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-92">92</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that our understanding of climate change impacts is still evolving, the theory and practice of conservation will likely continue to change at a relatively fast pace. One of the greatest future challenges to the conservation of biodiversity will likely come from how people respond to climate change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-93">93</a>
  </span>. Sea-level rise is forcing human populations to consider radical adaption action, including the construction of massive sea walls and the migration of coastal and island communities 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-94">94</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-95" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-95">95</a>
  </span>. Water shortages and crop failures will similarly result in human migrations, shifts in agriculture, and increased water withdrawals. There is increasing recognition that, in many places, human responses to climate change may further constrain options for biodiversity conservation, and therefore planning needs to simultaneously consider both human and biodiversity responses 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-93">93</a>
  </span>. The tools that conservation practitioners have to address climate change (for example, conservation planning, restoration, species risk assessments, and assisted colonization) will likely be most effective if their application takes human responses to climate change into account.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Continued rapid climate change will also necessitate a shift from discussions of resistance and resilience to more strategies that embrace change and foster transitions 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-96" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-96">96</a>
  </span>. Particularly if society hopes to continue to be the recipient of essential ecosystem services and to enjoy a diversity of plants and animals, conservation efforts will need to focus on smoothly transitioning ecosystems from one state to another. The enormity of that challenge necessitates policies and actions that reduce greenhouse-gas emissions and increase carbon sequestration. Unless adaptation is accompanied by meaningful mitigation efforts, it will be hard for conservation practitioners to accomplish even their shifting and evolving goals.
 </p>
</sec>
