<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climatic spaces occupied by the four subspecies were first compared along each environmental dimensions using violin plots, which combine the functions of boxplot and kernel density, providing a better indication of the shape of the data distribution. We used NicheA, a toolkit to create and visualized ecological niches in environmental spaces [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], to visualize climate niches occupied by each subspecies in reduced multiple environmental spaces: we displayed the first three principal components derived from the 8 bioclimatic layers, and plotted minimum volume ellipsoids (MVEs) around occupied conditions. We quantified niche overlap between pairs of subspecies using Schoener’s 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]; this metric ranges from 0 (no overlap) to 1 (complete overlap), and was used to test niche identity and niche similarity between subspecies. Niche identity and similarity tests were performed to determine whether climate spaces occupied by the two subspecies were identical or exhibited significant difference, and whether these differences were caused by the environmental feature spaces [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Niche identity was tested by randomly allocating occurrence records within each pair 500 times, according to observed numbers of records, and comparing observed and simulated Schoener’s 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> estimates. In contrast, niche similarity was tested by shifting the centroid of the observed occurrence densities to a random location within the available environmental space 500 times, and comparing observed with the null distribution of simulated estimates of Schoener’s 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]; climate variables measured at locations across the available backgrounds of subspecies were combined and projected onto the first two principal components using PCA_env package [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Smoothed densities of occurrences and available environments in each grid cell were calculated and compared among the four subspecies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
