<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035" class="p">Five strategic targets have been set to meet five strategic goals:
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0010" class="list">
  <list-item id="o0010" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(1)</label>
   <p id="p0040" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Actively manage and transition the Melbourne Gardens landscape and plant collections</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0010" class="list-item">
   <p id="p0045" class="p">By 2036, 75% of taxa in the Gardens will be suited to the projected climate of 2090 (this target does 
    <italic class="italic">not</italic> preclude the growing of plants in microclimates – for example, near water bodies or in glass and shade houses – that would allow them to tolerate otherwise more extreme conditions).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0015" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(2)</label>
   <p id="p0050" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Establish a mixed-age selection of plants composed of a diversity of taxa</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0015" class="list-item">
   <p id="p0055" class="p">By 2036, plant diversity will be equal to or greater than the current 8400 taxa, of variable age, and including greater than 35% wild provenance-sourced plants (an increase on the current percentage of 20%).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0020" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(3)</label>
   <p id="p0060" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Maximise sustainable water availability and use</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0020" class="list-item">
   <p id="p0065" class="p">By 2020, 100% of landscape irrigation needs will be provided by sustainable water sources.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0025" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(4)</label>
   <p id="p0070" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Maximise the benefits of the green space and built environment through landscape design</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0025" class="list-item">
   <p id="p0075" class="p">Any new green and built infrastructure will be capable of mitigating and withstanding predicted climatic extremes.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0030" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(5)</label>
   <p id="p0080" class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Improve understanding of the impacts of climate change on botanical landscapes</italic>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0030" class="list-item">
   <p id="p0085" class="p">The Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria will continue to demonstrate that life is sustained and enriched by plants, and to encourage and facilitate climate change as a key consideration in planning and managing ‘green space’.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
