<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9" class="p">Prior to the isotope analysis, the first 25 years of each core were removed to avoid “juvenile age effects” on the tree-ring isotopes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, pooling was necessary because 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">orientalis</italic> is a slow-growing conifer with very narrow rings, making it difficult to obtain enough material to measure the individual isotopic series. In addition, the small ring size would have created an unacceptably high risk of measurement error. Several recent studies have tested and proved the representativeness of pooled isotopic series for tree-ring δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C compared to individual isotopic series
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>. The cores were divided into individual rings using a scalpel to cut along ring lines under a stereomicroscope (40× magnification) and rings within the same year were pooled. Earlywood and latewood were not separated for the isotopic analyses, as recent studies have shown that there is no difference between the two wood types at an isotopic level
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. Each pooled sample was ground into a powder using a ball mill, followed by sieving through an 80-mesh sieve. Cellulose was extracted from all samples to avoid isotope variations during the iWUE calculation, so that they were based purely on the changes in the relative abundance of individual wood constituents that typically have different isotope signatures
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. The method for cellulose extraction was modified from Loader
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Cellulose samples and whole wood samples were used for δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C analysis using a high temperature reactor (HT-O, HEKAtech GMBH, Wegberg, Germany) coupled to a DELTAplus XP Mass Spectrometer (ThermoFinnigan, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, MA, USA). Each sample was analyzed three times, and the average values were calculated.
</p>
