<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sites</div>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was conducted at 3 sites in Narragansett Bay, Rhode Island: Fort Wetherill (41.478°N, 71.362°W), Land’s End (41.450°N, 71.314°W), and Bass Rock Road (41.405°N, 71.456°W). Narragansett Bay is a 259 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> embayment with a mean depth of 9 m and maximum depth of 60 m and which opens to the south into Rhode Island Sound adjacent Long Island Sound to the west
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>. The sites are moderately wave-exposed based on the angle to which each site is open to exposure from Rhode Island Sound and the criteria discussed in Lewis
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Sites span an east (Land’s End) to west (Bass Rock Road) gradient and consist of sloping bedrock and large boulders that grade to sand at ~7 m depth.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kelp biomass</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured kelp biomass at 2 sites (Fort Wetherill and Land’s End) for comparison with available baseline data from the early 1980s
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>. For consistency with the methodology of historical measurements, kelp biomass was measured in June/July at 2 m depth (season and depth of greatest historical kelp density) within n = 6 randomly placed quadrats at each site. While Brady-Campbell 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>) sampled 0.1 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> quadrats, kelp biomass was measured within 0.25 to 1 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> quadrats in our study to minimize zero values at low kelp abundance. For biomass measurements, the wet weight of blotted-dry kelp, destructively sampled from each quadrat, was determined to the nearest 0.01 g with a spring scale to give an estimate of kelp fresh biomass in units of g m
   <span class="sup">−2</span>. Given that Brady-Campbell 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>) report their data as dry weight of kelp, for comparison, we converted their measurements to wet weight with the formula for conversion of dry weight (DW) to fresh weight (FW) of 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span>: DW = 0.113 FW (r
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.970)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>. No individuals of 
   <span class="italic">L. digitata</span> were observed in the quadrats at any site.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kelp density</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared kelp density at Fort Wetherill in 2017–18 to baseline data collected in 1980–81 by Brady-Campbell 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>). To measure the density of kelp, divers counted kelp in belt transects at 2 to 6 m depth (n = 2–3 transects) on 1 Dec 2017, 20 Dec 2017, 9 Feb 2018, and 23 Mar 2018, and in quadrats placed randomly at 2 to 6 m depth (n = 20 1-m
   <span class="sup">2</span> quadrats) on 20 Jun and 30 Nov 2018. Belt transects were used on the earlier dates due to very low (near zero) kelp density, which required a large sampling area to minimize zero values. On each sampling date, divers counted and measured the blade lengths of all kelp encountered within the belt transects or quadrats. Blade lengths were used to produce size-frequency distributions. The width of the transect was 2 m, but the length varied throughout the season (ranging from 3 to 30 m) to accommodate changing kelp density, with larger transects used on lower density dates. The total number of individuals observed on each sampling date ranged from 48 to 139. Transects and quadrats were pooled to determine overall density. In all density surveys conducted at Fort Wetherill, only a single individual of 
   <span class="italic">L. digitata</span> was observed (20 Dec 2017).
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We observed both a winter and spring recruitment pulse of 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span> at Fort Wetherill (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). In early December 2017, all kelp observed along belt transects were &lt;70 cm in blade length, indicating recently recruited individuals. By March 2018 individuals with blade lengths up to 180 cm were observed, indicating somatic growth of winter recruits. A second pulse of recruits with blade lengths &lt;70 cm was observed during sampling in June 2018 (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). Individuals with blade lengths &gt;70 cm were rare on 20 Jun (7 out of a total of 139 individuals observed), indicating low survival of the winter recruits.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Percent cover of turf</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the abundance of turf algae at sites in Narragansett Bay, we measured the percent cover of turf-forming macroalgae from video data collected at 2 to 6 m depth at 3 sites (Fort Wetherill, Land’s End, and Bass Rock Road). In late June or early July 2018, divers swam along 30 m transects parallel to shore at each depth and site with a GoPro Hero 4 camera positioned ~1 m above bottom. For each video, photoquadrats were extracted every 3 m (n = 10 per video) and pooled over depths to calculate percent cover of turf (n = 20 images per site/date). For the image analysis, a 50 × 50 cm grid was superimposed on the photoquadrat using the width of the transect tape to set the scale. Percent cover of turf was then estimated by assessing the presence or absence of turf on each section of the grid
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
   </span>. Occasionally, poor resolution in the photo rendered a section of the image unreadable. In such cases the section was discarded, and percent cover was estimated based on the remaining part of the photoquadrat. Image analysis was conducted with the program Image J.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Turf species assemblage</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To characterize the turf-forming macroalgal community, we determined the identity of macroalgal species at Fort Wetherill from destructive sampling of n = 3–6 0.1 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> quadrats placed haphazardly ~5 m apart at 4 m depth on 1 Dec 2017, 9 Feb 2018, and 1 May 2018. For the turf collection, a stainless-steel scraper was used to release all macroalgae from the substratum and divers manually collected the macroalgae and placed it in a mesh bag (5 mm diameter mesh). Species were identified under a dissecting microscope in the laboratory using guides for algae identification for the East Coast of the United States
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span> and Algaebase.org. Wet weight of each turf species was measured to the nearest 0.01 g to assess the biomass contribution of each species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental drivers</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We acquired weekly sea surface temperature data from the Narragansett Bay Plankton Time Series at the Graduate School of Oceanography, University of Rhode Island (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span> and 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.uri.edu/plankton/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://web.uri.edu/plankton/</span>). Data were analyzed over a 58-year period from 1959 to 2017 to determine the total number of weeks in each year with sea temperatures greater than or equal to 7 thresholds between 14 and 26 °C (2 °C increments). The thermal integral of weeks with sea temperatures ≥22 °C was then calculated for each year as the sum of weekly temperature for weeks with temperatures ≥22 °C (degree-week). Nutrient data also were acquired from the Narragansett Bay Plankton Time Series and analyzed from 1972 to 2018 to test for temporal changes in ammonium, nitrate, and phosphate concentrations indicative of local nutrient loading.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kelp recruitment onto turf</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion of kelp recruiting onto turf-forming macroalgae versus rocky substratum was determined in belt transects surveyed for kelp density at Fort Wetherill (see Kelp density). To determine the proportion of kelp attached to turf-forming macroalgae, divers noted the number of kelp individuals in transects with holdfasts attached to turf or rock. The percentage of kelp recruited to turf was calculated as the number of individuals on turf divided by the total number of individuals observed on either substrate.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Force to detach kelp from turf and rock</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations that kelp were commonly recruited onto turf-forming macroalgae prompted a study to examine the attachment strength of kelp attached to rocky substrate versus turf to determine the risk of detachment by wave forces for these 2 groups of kelp. We predicted that kelp attached to turf would require less force to detach than kelp attached to rocky substrate, as kelp appeared loosely attached to the turf. On 20 Dec 2017 (n = 15 rock, and 12 turf), 9 Feb 2018 (n = 5 rock, and 6 turf), and 22 May 2018 (n = 8 rock, and 9 turf), divers used a resettable modified dynamometer
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span> consisting of a spring scale attached to an elastic nylon cord (to avoid tearing the holdfast) to test attachment strength of kelp attached to rock and turf. Kelp were selected haphazardly within an ~200 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> area of reef at 4 m depth at Fort Wetherill. The scale was attached to kelp by threading the nylon through the holdfast (attached to rock or turf) and secured with a loose knot. Kelp were then pulled perpendicular to the substrate until the kelp (including holdfast) was dislodged or holdfast failure occurred (cord pulls through the material of the holdfast). The indicator deflection distance on the spring scale was measured with calipers and the attachment strength was determined by multiplying the indicator deflection distance by the known spring constant
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blade lengths of kelp detached from the substrate on 20 Dec 2017 were significantly different among turf- and rock-attached individuals, with turf-attached individuals having a significantly smaller mean blade length (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). To ensure that force to detach measurements were not biased by kelp blade length (i.e. kelp age/size), we plotted the force to detach as a function of the length of individuals within each group (turf- and rock-attached). We found no relationship between force to detach and blade length (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kelp holdfast morphology on turf and rock</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To quantify potential differences in holdfast morphology, holdfasts of kelp attached to rocky substrate and turf-forming macroalgae were haphazardly collected at Fort Wetherill from within an ~200 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> area of reef at 4 m depth on 9 Feb (n = 10 rock, and 9 turf), 12 Apr (n = 10 rock, and 10 turf), and 1 May 2018 (n = 10 rock, and 9 turf). The blade and stipe were removed from the holdfast of the kelp and each section was weighed to the nearest 0.01 g to determine the percentage of the total biomass (%) occupied by the holdfast. Additionally, the total number of bifurcations of haptera within each holdfast was measured to determine holdfast complexity for kelp collected at 4 m depth at Fort Wetherill on 23 Mar (n = 10 rock, and 9 turf), 12 Apr (n = 10 rock, and 10 turf), and 1 May 2018 (n = 10 rock, and 9 turf).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kelp growth rates on turf and rock</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine a potential trade-off associated with the allocation of greater energy to the holdfast of turf-attached versus rock-attached kelp, we examined growth rates of kelp attached to each substrate type in the field. Growth rate was assessed with the hole-punch method, whereby a hole is punched in the blade at a known distance above the meristematic tissue and migration of the hole is measured through time as an indication of blade growth
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>. Rock-attached and turf-attached individuals that were ~100 cm in blade length were selected haphazardly within ~200 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> of reef at each of 2 m (n = 8 rock-attached and 10 turf-attached) and 6 m (n = 4 rock-attached and 11 turf-attached) depth. On 12 Apr 2018, individuals were hole-punched 10 cm above the meristematic tissue and then tagged with a plastic numbered tag for individual identification. Divers determined survival (retention) of individuals after 35 days (12 Apr to 17 May), and for surviving individuals, measured the migration distance of the hole on each individual to the nearest cm with a plastic measuring tape. Apr to May is the period over which Brady-Campbell 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>) observed maximal growth of kelp at Fort Wetherill in 1980 and 1981. Egan and Yarish (ref.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
   </span>) also observed maximal growth of 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span> in Long Island Sound in Apr and May.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two-way ANOVAs were used to examine the effect of substrate (fixed factor, two levels: rock and turf) and month (random factor, three levels: ranging from Dec to May) on 1) the force (N) required to detach 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span>, 2) the percentage of biomass allocated to the holdfast of 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span>, and 3) the total number of bifurcations within the holdfast of 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span>. Two-way ANOVA also was used to examine the effect of substrate (fixed factor, two levels: rock and turf) and depth (random factor, two levels: 2 and 6 m) on the growth rate (cm d
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) of 
   <span class="italic">S. latissima</span> over 35 d from 12 Apr to 17 May 2018. Assumptions of normality were examined with the Shapiro-Wilk test (α = 0.05). Assumptions of homogeneity of variance were examined with the Brown–Forsythe test (α = 0.05). Data were analyzed with Statistica 13.2 (StatSoft) and SigmaStat 4.0 (Systat).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
