<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">pnas</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PNAS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0027-8424</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1091-6490</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Academy of Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6431205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30782803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">201815828</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1815828116</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>PNAS Plus</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biological Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><series-title>From the Cover</series-title><series-title>PNAS Plus</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Narrow safety margin in the phyllosphere during thermal extremes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7964-5861</contrib-id><name><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>Sylvain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1666-295X</contrib-id><name><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J&#x000e9;r&#x000f4;me</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><sup>a</sup>Institut de Recherche sur la Biologie de l&#x02019;Insecte, UMR 7261, CNRS, <institution>Universit&#x000e9; de Tours</institution>, 37200 Tours, <country>France</country>;</aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>b</sup><institution>Institut Universitaire de France</institution>, 75231 Paris Cedex 05, <country>France</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><sup>1</sup>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <email>sylvain.pincebourde@univ-tours.fr</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by Ian T. Baldwin, Max Planck Institute for Chemical Ecology, Jena, Germany, and approved January 14, 2019 (received for review September 24, 2018)</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Author contributions: S.P. and J.C. designed research; S.P. performed research; S.P. and J.C. analyzed data; and S.P. and J.C. wrote the paper.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>116</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>5588</fpage><lpage>5596</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 the Author(s). Published by PNAS.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="vor"/><license-p>This open access article is distributed under <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 4.0 (CC BY-NC-ND)</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="pnas.201815828.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="executive-summary"><title>Significance</title><p>The thermal limits of terrestrial ectotherms vary more locally than globally. Local microclimatic variations can explain this pattern, but the underlying mechanisms remain unclear. We show that cryptic microclimatic variations at the scale of a single leaf determine the thermal limit in a community of arthropod herbivores living on the same host plant. Herbivores triggering an increase in transpiration, thereby cooling the leaf, had a lower thermal limit than those decreasing leaf transpiration and causing the leaf to warm up. These subtle mechanisms have major consequences for the safety margin of these herbivores during thermal extremes. Our findings suggest that temperate species may be more vulnerable to heat waves than previously thought.</p></abstract><abstract><p>The thermal limit of ectotherms provides an estimate of vulnerability to climate change. It differs between contrasting microhabitats, consistent with thermal ecology predictions that a species&#x02019; temperature sensitivity matches the microclimate it experiences. However, observed thermal limits may differ between ectotherms from the same environment, challenging this theory. We resolved this apparent paradox by showing that ectotherm activity generates microclimatic deviations large enough to account for differences in thermal limits between species from the same microhabitat. We studied upper lethal temperature, effect of feeding mode on plant gas exchange, and temperature of attacked leaves in a community of six arthropod species feeding on apple leaves. Thermal limits differed by up to 8 &#x000b0;C among the species. Species that caused an increase in leaf transpiration (+182%), thus cooling the leaf, had a lower thermal limit than those that decreased leaf transpiration (&#x02212;75%), causing the leaf to warm up. Therefore, cryptic microclimatic variations at the scale of a single leaf determine the thermal limit in this community of herbivores. We investigated the consequences of these changes in plant transpiration induced by plant&#x02013;insect feedbacks for species vulnerability to thermal extremes. Warming tolerance was similar between species, at &#x000b1;2 &#x000b0;C, providing little margin for resisting increasingly frequent and intense heat waves. The thermal safety margin (the difference between thermal limit and temperature) was greatly overestimated when air temperature or intact leaf temperature was erroneously used. We conclude that feedback processes define the vulnerability of species in the phyllosphere, and beyond, to thermal extremes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>thermal adaptation</kwd><kwd>leaf temperature</kwd><kwd>biophysical ecology</kwd><kwd>extended phenotype</kwd><kwd>plant&#x02013;insect interactions</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="gs1"><funding-source id="sp1">Agence Nationale de la Recherche (ANR)<named-content content-type="funder-id">501100001665</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp1">ANR-2010 BLAN-1706-02</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Sylvain Pincebourde</principal-award-recipient><principal-award-recipient>J&#x000e9;r&#x000f4;me Casas</principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="gs2"><funding-source id="sp2">Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS)<named-content content-type="funder-id">501100004794</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="sp2">PEPS ThermalGame</award-id><principal-award-recipient>Sylvain Pincebourde</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="flushleft">Climate change erodes biodiversity by causing niche shifts and extinctions (<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). There is an urgent need to forecast the ecological impact of climate change accurately to anticipate its consequences for land use, the management of pest and invasive species, and biological conservation. Sophisticated statistical approaches have been developed for predicting the impact of climate change on species distributions with little a priori knowledge about the species concerned (<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), but only mechanistic approaches can address the question as to how climate change will affect species (<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Recent approaches have integrated physiological traits, including the thermal tolerance limits of species, with the biophysical modeling of ectotherm body temperature to depict relationships between microhabitat choice and the physiological limits of ectotherms in changing environments (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). These studies constitute a major step forward, but they consider physiological limits in terms of coarse-scale climatic variables, largely ignoring microclimate diversity at finer scales (<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). This is problematic, as patterns in the physiological limits of ectotherms are better explained by environmental gradients than by macroecological processes (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p><p>Thermal tolerance limit is currently the best available metric for assessing the thermal safety margin available to ectotherms. Macroecological studies on high-temperature tolerance limits in ectotherms have demonstrated only a weak latitudinal trend, with tropical species slightly more tolerant than temperate ectotherms in general (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Thermal tolerance limits may be phylogenetically constrained, and the relatedness of species may limit opportunities for local adaptation (<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Alternatively, according to thermal ecology theory, thermal tolerance limit is a trait adapted to the microenvironmental conditions experienced by the organism (<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). These microclimatic conditions may display a high degree of spatial variability and heterogeneity such that the use of a geographic scale is likely to blur patterns of local adaptation seen at the scale of the microhabitat (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The interspecific variability of upper thermal tolerance limits, particularly at temperate latitudes (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), can be explained by the predictions of thermal ecology theory: The thermal tolerance limits of ectotherms may differ between contrasting microhabitats present in the same local area (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), but they may also differ between species living in the same microhabitat (<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The determination of macroecological patterns, therefore, requires comparative data for the various communities living at each site and in each microhabitat, and such knowledge is not yet available. We investigated the role of fine-scale microclimate variations as a driver of thermal limit diversity in a community of arthropods living on leaves. Even if different species seem to use the same microhabitat (e.g., the leaf surface), they may experience contrasting microclimatic conditions due to the subtle changes in the thermal properties of the leaf microhabitat that they introduce. We focus on thermal extremes because they directly determine survival and because the comparison of their metrics with thermal tolerance limits is straightforward (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>The plant leaf surface, or phyllosphere, hosts a tremendous diversity of communities (<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The phylloclimate is defined as the microclimatic conditions occurring at the phyllosphere (<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Leaves absorb some of the energy from the radiation they intercept, but they also lose energy during evapotranspiration and exchange convective energy with the surrounding air (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Leaf surface temperature may, therefore, deviate from the temperature of the surrounding air by several degrees (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Leaf surface temperature can affect the temperatures experienced by arthropods small enough to be embedded within the leaf boundary layer (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref><xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The thermal tolerance limits of ectotherms living within the leaf boundary layer in relation to leaf surface temperature patterns have never before been studied, despite species-specific herbivore-induced modifications to leaf surface temperature (<xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). However, an analogous situation has been described for ants living in different boundary layers across the vertical gradient of trees (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Leaf surface temperature is modulated by leaf ecophysiology, in particular stomatal behavior, which sets leaf transpiration rate (<xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). All else being equal, lower levels of transpiration (stomata closed) cause the leaf surface to warm up, whereas higher levels of transpiration (stomata open) are associated with a cooling of the leaf surface. Leaf transpiration responds to diverse factors, including temperature and light (<xref rid="r41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Leaf transpiration is also affected by biotic stresses. Arthropod herbivores feeding on leaf tissues induce marked changes in leaf ecophysiology (<xref rid="r42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref><xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr"/>&#x02013;<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Some species, such as aphids, increase transpiration by causing the stomata to open, whereas others, such as spider mites, reduce leaf transpiration by causing stomatal closure or dry necrosis (<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Thus, arthropods causing a decrease in leaf transpiration should also cause an increase in leaf surface temperature. According to thermal ecology predictions, these arthropods should have higher thermal limits than species that increase leaf transpiration and cool the leaf surface. We tested this prediction by comparing the thermal limits of herbivore species and the leaf temperature resulting from their feeding on a leaf during extreme thermal events.</p><p>We studied a community of six phytophagous arthropod species feeding on the same host plant (apple leaves) to avoid any confounding effects of host-plant species. The influence of each species on leaf photosynthesis rate was used as an indicator of the degree of injury caused by feeding (three of the species considered are tissue piercers, two are phloem feeders, and one is a leaf miner; detailed life histories are in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, Box 1</ext-link>). The species were studied separately to prevent confounding interspecific interactions. We investigated the link between thermal tolerance limits and leaf temperatures during the early development of populations on leaf surfaces, when the leaves are still photosynthesizing. We described and identified the mechanisms underlying the relationship between leaf transpiration and thermal tolerance limits in three steps. We first obtained a phenomenological description. The thermal tolerance limits of the different species [upper lethal temperature (ULT), defined as the temperature causing 50% mortality in a given group after exposure for 1 h to the experimental temperature (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)] and the gas exchanges in the leaves (photosynthesis, transpiration rate, and stomatal conductance) attacked by each species were measured under optimal conditions. The shape of the relationship between thermal limit and leaf transpiration rate was used to assess the link between the feeding mode of the herbivores and their tolerance of high temperatures. The temperature of attacked leaves was measured for most species under moderate conditions to determine the direct effect of herbivores on their host leaf&#x02019;s temperature. We then performed a mechanistic analysis to determine whether the temperature of the attacked leaf during thermal extremes could account for ULT variations in the arthropod community studied. We modified the &#x0201c;classic&#x0201d; biophysical model of leaf temperature (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) for this purpose, by including ecophysiological parameters corresponding to the effects of each arthropod on the leaf, to predict the temperature of the leaf attacked by each herbivore species under extreme thermal conditions (high air temperature and high levels of solar radiation). Finally, we carried out a vulnerability analysis, in which we used a combination of thermal tolerance limits and leaf temperatures to determine the tolerance of the various species to warming. We explored the feedback loop between herbivores and their plant environment, by determining the extent to which the predicted warming tolerance of each arthropod species was biased if the subtle mechanisms by which herbivores modify their thermal environment were ignored, with cascading effects on the thermal tolerance limit of the species concerned.</p><sec sec-type="results" id="s1"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2"><title>Thermal Limits and Plant Gas Exchange.</title><p>In a dynamic ramping assay reflecting the thermal conditions at the leaf surface in the field when the surrounding temperature is increasing (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s10"><italic>Materials and Methods</italic></xref>), we found that the ULT of the six species differed by up to 8.5 &#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>). ULT ranged from 37.4 &#x000b0;C for the rosy apple aphid to 45.9 &#x000b0;C for the two-spotted spider mite. Overall, tissue piercers (spider mites and the lace bug) had a higher ULT than phloem feeders (the two aphid species considered). The leaf miner was intermediate: Its fourth stage had a ULT close to that of phloem feeders, whereas the ULT of its fifth stage was close to that of tissue piercers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>). For all species, the logistic dose&#x02013;response curve fitted survival rate as a function of experimental temperature well (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x0003e; 0.78 and <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 for all; see detailed statistics in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S1</italic> and Table S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig01" fig-type="featured" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Determining the ULT of species. The survival rate of each group is shown as a function of experimental temperature. Each dot represents the result for a group (<italic>n</italic> = 10 to 15 individuals). The curves are logistic dose&#x02013;response fits. The intersection of the nonlinear regression line and the 50% threshold (horizontal dashed lines) corresponds to the ULT (indicated in gray type). Colors indicate feeding guild: phloem feeder (green), leaf miner (blue), and tissue piercer (orange). Species included spotted tentiform leaf miner, <italic>Phyllonorycter blancardella</italic>; rosy apple aphid, <italic>Dysaphis plantaginea</italic>; green apple aphid, <italic>Aphis pomi</italic>; pear lace bug, <italic>Stephanitis piri</italic>; brown mite, <italic>Bryobia rubrioculus</italic>; and two-spotted spider mite, <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic>.</p></caption><graphic id="gra1" xlink:href="pnas.1815828116fig01"/></fig><p>We used an infrared gas analyzer to measure assimilation rate, transpiration rate, and stomatal conductance on leaves attacked by the arthropod species, under optimal conditions for apple leaves (<xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>): irradiance, 1,500 &#x000b5;mol&#x022c5;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x022c5;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; leaf temperature, 25 &#x000b0;C; water vapor deficit, 1 kPa; and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in the air, 390 ppm (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s10"><italic>Materials and Methods</italic></xref>). The various herbivore species had different effects on plant gas exchange during early infestation. Phloem feeders increased assimilation rates, whereas tissues piercers impaired photosynthesis little, if at all (ANOVA: F<sub>7,112</sub> = 8.26, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). A similar ranking of effects was obtained for stomatal conductance (ANOVA: F<sub>7,112</sub> = 40.69, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S2</italic></ext-link>) and leaf transpiration rate (ANOVA: F<sub>7,112</sub> = 28.36, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S2</italic></ext-link>). Phloem feeders increased leaf transpiration rate, whereas tissue piercers tended to decrease transpiration rate.</p><fig id="fig02" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>The effect of arthropod feeding mode on plant performance. The photosynthesis rate (mean &#x000b1; SEM) of the leaves attacked by each herbivore species is shown, ranked by feeding mode: phloem feeding (green), leaf mining (blue), and tissue piercing (orange). The gray bar and the gray horizontal band represent the mean photosynthesis rates of intact leaves (&#x000b1;SEM). Identical letters indicate a lack of significant difference.</p></caption><graphic id="gra2" xlink:href="pnas.1815828116fig02"/></fig><p>The link between thermal limits and plant responses to herbivory was analyzed by focusing on leaf transpiration rate, because this response variable is the one with the most direct effect on leaf temperature. ULT was correlated with the transpiration rate of attacked leaves under optimal conditions, with a nonlinear trend (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>; power regression analysis, <italic>y</italic> = a<italic>x</italic><sup>b</sup>: a = 44.47, b = &#x02212;0.14, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.71, F<sub>1,5</sub> = 12.49, <italic>P</italic> = 0.017). Species inducing an increase in leaf transpiration rate had a lower ULT than those decreasing leaf transpiration rates. The temperature of leaves attacked by the species inducing the most extreme changes in leaf transpiration matched the expectations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>): The two-spotted spider mite caused a decrease in leaf transpiration rate and lived at a surface 8 &#x000b0;C warmer than the air, while the green apple aphid increased leaf transpiration and developed at a leaf temperature only 1 &#x000b0;C above ambient air. Further experimental support, including a fully coherent ranking of all species, was obtained in the highly unnatural environment of the leaf chamber of the LI-6400 (LI-COR Inc.) gas analyzer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S3</italic></ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>The thermal tolerance limit of arthropods is related to their effect on leaf transpiration. The ULT (estimated from the nonlinear regression &#x000b1; 95% confidence interval) is shown as a function of the transpiration rate of attacked leaves (mean &#x000b1; SEM). The vertical gray bar indicates the mean transpiration rate of intact leaves as a reference. Colors indicate feeding mode (green, phloem feeding; blue, leaf mining; orange, tissue piercing). The regression line is a power function. <italic>Inset</italic> shows the temperature excess (leaf minus air temperatures; mean &#x000b1; SEM) of leaves attacked by three of the considered species, illustrating the thermal effects of herbivore feeding.</p></caption><graphic id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1815828116fig03"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Biophysical Modeling.</title><p>We used a biophysical model to calculate mean leaf temperature as a function of the environmental conditions and properties of intact and attacked leaves. We then compared the temperatures of leaves attacked in extremely hot conditions with the thermal limits of the arthropod species studied. The biophysical model is based on a leaf heat budget, taking into account transfers of heat between the leaf and its surroundings. It includes the heat gained or lost during the absorption and emission of radiation, convective and conductive transport, and evapotranspiration via stomata (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). The classic version of the leaf heat budget model (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) was used to calculate the mean temperature of intact leaves (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S4</italic></ext-link>). Modified versions of this model were then used to simulate the temperature of leaves attacked by the various arthropods under extreme air temperatures (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S4</italic></ext-link>). The main parameter of the model including the effects of the herbivores considered was stomatal conductance, resulting in changes in leaf transpiration rates. The models were run with environmental parameters set to values corresponding to extreme climatic events (high levels of radiation, low wind speed; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s10"><italic>Materials and Methods</italic></xref>). In particular, the simulations were performed with different air temperatures, corresponding to the 90th, 95th, 99th, and 99.9th percentiles of the hourly air temperature distribution for 2012 near Tours, France (27.4 &#x000b0;C, 29.7 &#x000b0;C, 33.6 &#x000b0;C, and 37 &#x000b0;C, respectively; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S5</italic></ext-link>). These quantiles are often used to describe thermal extremes (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><p>Unsurprisingly, the model predicted an increase in the temperature of the attacked leaf with increases in the temperature of the atmosphere, for all species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4</xref>). Nevertheless, leaf temperature differed among the arthropod species considered, depending on their effect on leaf transpiration rate at a given environmental temperature. Phloem feeders systematically experienced cooler leaf temperatures than tissue piercers, for all surrounding air temperatures considered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>). Phloem feeders were predicted to decrease leaf temperature, whereas tissue piercers were expected to increase leaf temperature. These herbivore-induced changes in leaf temperature were linked to effects on gas exchange and latent heat loss (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S6</italic></ext-link>). The leaf miner species again yielded intermediate results, depending on larval stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>A</italic></xref>). The excess leaf temperature (number of degrees above the temperature of the surrounding air) was systematically smallest for species inducing an increase in transpiration rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4<italic>B</italic></xref>). Overall, the difference in excess temperature between the two most extreme species (two-spotted spider mite versus the rosy apple aphid) was about 4 to 5 &#x000b0;C. Finally, ULT was correlated with the temperature of the attacked leaf at all surrounding air temperatures used in the model (Pearson correlation coefficient between 0.76 and 0.84, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S7</italic></ext-link>). The environmental temperature corresponding to the 99th percentile of the air temperature distribution (i.e., 33.6 &#x000b0;C) was considered a thermal danger to about half the species considered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><fig id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>The temperature of the attacked leaf differs between arthropod species. The simulated attacked leaf temperature (<italic>A</italic>) and the simulated attacked leaf excess temperature relative to the surrounding air (<italic>B</italic>) are shown as a function of the effect of each species on leaf transpiration rate. Model simulations were run at different surrounding air temperatures (&#x025a1;, 27.4 &#x000b0;C; &#x02662;, 29.7 &#x000b0;C; &#x025b3;, 33.6 &#x000b0;C; &#x025cb;, 37 &#x000b0;C) corresponding to the air temperature extremes for 2012 at the study site. Colors indicate feeding mode (green, phloem feeding; blue, leaf mining; orange, tissue piercing). The large open symbols represent the temperature of the intact leaf. Regression lines are polynomial functions for visual purposes.</p></caption><graphic id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1815828116fig04"/></fig><fig id="fig05" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Leaf temperature during extreme air temperature conditions accounts for thermal limits. The ULT of each species is shown as a function of the simulated attacked-leaf temperature at an air temperature of 33.6 &#x000b0;C, corresponding to the 99th percentile of the air temperature distribution for 2012. Colors indicate feeding mode (green, phloem feeding; blue, leaf mining; orange, tissue piercing). The thermal danger zone (shaded area, delimited by the 1:1 relationship) represents the area of the graph in which the microclimatic temperature exceeds the ULT.</p></caption><graphic id="gra5" xlink:href="pnas.1815828116fig05"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Vulnerability Analysis: Warming Tolerance.</title><p>We analyzed vulnerability to extreme heat events by calculating the warming tolerance of each species. Warming tolerance is defined as the difference between the temperature experienced and the thermal tolerance limit (<xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). A positive warming tolerance indicates that the insect can tolerate warming, up to a certain amplitude, before 50% of the population dies. By contrast, a negative warming tolerance indicates that the tolerance threshold has already been exceeded and that further increases in temperature are likely to prove fatal. We calculated three different warming tolerance metrics with various degrees of tightness of coupling between the arthropod and the leaf (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). First, the realized warming tolerance was calculated as the difference between the temperature of the leaf attacked and the ULT for each species. The outputs of the biophysical model at different air temperature values (see above) were used for this calculation. Second, the approximate warming tolerance was calculated with intact leaf temperature and used to quantify the effect of the herbivore-induced changes in gas exchange on warming tolerance. Third, the naive warming tolerance of each species was calculated, based on air temperature, to quantify the error of prediction due to a lack of consideration of the microclimatic component. The warming tolerance metrics were calculated for the environmental temperature corresponding to the 99th percentile of the air temperature distribution (i.e., 33.6 &#x000b0;C).</p><p>The realized warming tolerance (i.e., taking the temperature of the leaf attacked into account) differed between species and was generally small. The two spider mite species (tissue piercers) had the highest warming tolerance levels (2 to 3 &#x000b0;C), whereas phloem feeders were either close to the thermal danger threshold or had already crossed it (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6</xref>). The leaf miner was not tolerant to this extreme air temperature event. By contrast, a naive approach, ignoring microclimatic temperatures and instead using surrounding air temperature, consistently overestimated warming tolerance by 4 to 12 &#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6</xref>). The approximate approach, based on leaf temperature, but without taking into account changes in transpiration rate, overestimated warming tolerance for spider mites and underestimated it for phloem feeders and the fifth larval stage of the leaf miner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig06">Fig. 6</xref>). The warming tolerance of the lace bug was well predicted by intact leaf temperature, because this species has little influence on leaf gas exchange. The amplitude of the bias in warming tolerance prediction was generally linked to herbivore-induced modifications to leaf ecophysiology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S8</italic></ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig06" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Thermal safety margin as function of the tightness of coupling between the herbivore and the leaf. The warming tolerance (WT) of each arthropod species was calculated using the surrounding air temperature (black bars, erroneous naive approach), the temperature of intact leaves (green bars, a mostly erroneous approach), and the attacked-leaf temperature (orange bars, the best estimate). Warming tolerance quantifies the amplitude of warming that a species can tolerate before it dies under a given set of conditions. Herbivorous species are arranged according to their feeding guild (background colors: blue, leaf miners; pale green, phloem feeders; pink, tissue piercers); see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref> for the names of the species.</p></caption><graphic id="gra6" xlink:href="pnas.1815828116fig06"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5"><title>Discussion</title><p content-type="flushleft">Despite the differences in ULT between tissue piercers and phloem feeders, both had realized warming tolerances of the same order of magnitude, &#x000b1;2 &#x000b0;C, leaving little opportunity to cope with extreme events. This narrow safety margin during extreme heat is much smaller than previously suggested (<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Thermal ecology theory explains the interspecific variability of thermal limits when the subtle processes through which organisms modify their microhabitat are taken into account. This theory can thus be applied to many other systems to determine the thermal safety margin of ectotherms more globally. Other organisms living on the leaf surface, such as phytopathogens, are directly influenced by leaf temperature (<xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). These fungi and bacteria often modify leaf ecophysiology, including transpiration rate (<xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Furthermore, many entomopathogenic bacteria and viruses make use of the leaf surface to infest new insect hosts (<xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), and their propagation is undoubtedly driven by leaf temperature. This same principle applies to host&#x02013;parasite relationships. The thermal biology of parasites relative to hosts determines infection risk (<xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>), but parasite species can have markedly different thermal limits (<xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Herbivorous arthropods are themselves hosts to various parasites and parasitoids, which are in turn dependent on the thermal dynamics induced by their hosts. Finally, ecosystem engineers generally create new environments that are not necessarily linked to another trophic level (<xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Nothing is known about the thermal limits of ecosystem engineers, but we would expect there to be a relationship, at the local scale, between their thermal limits and the thermal environment they create, resulting in small thermal safety margins for these organisms too.</p><p>Our biophysical modeling approach has limitations, however, because it focuses exclusively on air temperature as the primary environmental driver of leaf energy budgets (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Other factors, such as wind, shade, and drought, probably also modulate microclimatic temperatures (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S9</italic></ext-link>). In addition, biophysical models predict the mean temperature of a leaf surface (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), but temperature is heterogeneous over the surface of the leaf (<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), and arthropods can make use of this heterogeneity for behavioral thermoregulation (<xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S9</italic></ext-link>). Finally, the quantification of thermal extremes may be more complex than simply determining distribution quantiles (<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Our approach was designed to focus on thermal extremes that are challenging the thermal limits of arthropods at the leaf surface. We quantified the thermal safety margin of these herbivores under the worst possible extreme scenario without thermoregulation.</p><sec id="s6"><title>The Thermal Tolerance Thresholds of Herbivores.</title><p>An understanding of the thermal biology of species is crucial for assessments of the vulnerability of organisms to changing climates (<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The thermal tolerance limits of ectotherms vary locally along thermal gradients, as elegantly demonstrated for ants (<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) and frogs (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) across vertical forest gradients and for crabs in the rocky intertidal ecosystem (<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In these examples, thermal tolerance limits varied by 5 to 10 &#x000b0;C. Here, a similar amplitude of variation in thermal limits was measured for a community of herbivorous arthropods inhabiting the same microhabitat, the phyllosphere. The thermal limits of the six species studied here varied by 8.5 &#x000b0;C. Phloem feeders (aphids) were less tolerant to high temperatures than tissue piercers (spider mites), and the leaf miner was intermediate between the two, with variation during development. About 62% of the variability in thermal tolerance limits in these species can be explained by herbivore-induced leaf temperature. Indeed, the changes in transpiration rate generated differences in leaf temperature of 5.26 &#x000b0;C (with a range of 8.5 &#x000b0;C for thermal limits). This variability is similar to the range of critical temperatures reported for arthropods at the same latitude (<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S10</italic></ext-link>). The microclimate of species at a very fine scale may, therefore, account for much of the variability of critical or lethal temperatures for ectotherms.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Damage and Plant Ecophysiology.</title><p>Various effects on leaf ecophysiology were observed, depending on feeding mode, consistent with the findings of previous broad-scale studies on the effects of insect-mediated injury on plant gas exchange (<xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="r60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Tissue piercers reduced transpiration rate (by 75% for the two-spotted spider mite), whereas phloem feeders increased transpiration rates (by 182% for the rosy apple aphid). Tissue piercers, such as mites and bugs, severely damage leaf tissues by piercing mesophyll cells to feed on their contents (<xref rid="r61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="r62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). This activity does not necessarily influence plant gas exchange at low-to-moderate herbivore densities (<xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). However, at higher densities, decreases in leaf transpiration and rates of photosynthesis are commonly observed after tissue-piercer feeding (<xref rid="r62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). By contrast, phloem feeders, such as aphids, can induce an increase in stomatal conductance and photosynthesis rate (<xref rid="r64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="r65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Evapotranspiration may sometimes occur through the injuries caused by the stylet, which must be inserted through the leaf epidermis to reach the phloem (<xref rid="r66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). The leaf miner is a particular case, with a gradual decrease in leaf transpiration rate from the fourth to fifth larval stage, due to the induction of stomatal closure (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Thermal limits are known to vary with larval stage in several insects (<xref rid="r67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="r68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), and we suggest that the temporal dynamics of their leaf microclimate can account for much of this developmental variation.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>The Thermal Biology of Communities.</title><p>The subtle effects of each herbivore on gas exchange in its host plant have implications at the community scale. With the exception of the two aphid species, these herbivores are only rarely found together on the same apple tree, although they can coexist in the same orchard. Strong competitive interactions between these herbivores probably prevent them from coexisting on the same leaves at the same time in the growing season, although competition by exclusion alone may be too simplistic to explain herbivore assemblages (<xref rid="r69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). The two aphid species can be observed on the same apple tree, but on different leaves (<xref rid="r70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, <xref rid="r71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>): The rosy apple aphid mostly develops on leaves in the shade, whereas the green apple aphid is found on apical leaves exposed to full sun (<xref rid="r72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). This suggests niche partitioning consistent with their thermal tolerance limits, but this process has never been studied in detail in these species. The application of thermal adaptation theory to our findings would result in a prediction that the two-spotted spider mite, which has the highest ULT, should exclude the other herbivores under extreme environmental conditions if all are present on the same plant at the same time. However, there are currently no data available to test this prediction. In addition, this ranking of potential competitors may vary across the temperature range, because the thermal optima for development differ between these herbivores: about 30 to 35 &#x000b0;C for the two-spotted spider mite (<xref rid="r73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="r74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>) versus &#x0223c;28 &#x000b0;C for the green apple aphid (<xref rid="r75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Spider mite populations may, therefore, perform less well than aphids at temperatures below 30 &#x000b0;C. Communities of arthropods in the phyllosphere could be used as a system model to link community processes and microclimate mosaics within especially complex microhabitats, particularly given that plant biochemistry can also modulate herbivore interactions (<xref rid="r76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Ectotherms Are More Vulnerable to Thermal Extremes than Previously Thought.</title><p>We explored the consequences of the subtle mechanism of thermal adaptation in these herbivores on their level of tolerance to extreme heat. The more tolerant species (tissue piercers) already inhabit a warmer microclimate than phloem feeders. We therefore need to integrate both thermal tolerance limits and the effect of warming on the insect microclimate into our analyses (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Phloem feeders were found to be slightly more vulnerable than tissue piercers, suggesting that particular groups may be more at risk than others under climate change, depending on feeding mode. The large discrepancies between the realized and naive warming tolerances (up to 12 &#x000b0;C) highlight the huge error of prediction that can occur if vulnerability to climate change is investigated without taking the microclimate into account. Even worse, most studies of global change use monthly mean air temperature to calculate these vulnerabilities (<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Unfortunately, such approaches buffer single extreme events sufficient to kill a significant portion of the populations present. Overall, environmental temperatures above the 99th percentile of the distribution for 2012 constituted a thermal danger for half the herbivore species studied (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig05">Fig. 5</xref>). This result suggests that (<italic>i</italic>) high-resolution sampling of environmental variables is essential to capture these rare extreme events, and (<italic>ii</italic>) a detailed understanding of the microclimate of species is required to determine the extent to which environmental variables are filtered at the scale of the organism. These aspects are particularly crucial for temperate ectotherms (as studied here), which already experience thermal extremes close to those observed in the tropics (<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Moreover, the amplitude of change in these thermal extremes due to climate change is greater in temperate regions than at low latitudes (<xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Unlike the forest understory (<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="r77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>), temperate phylloclimates are magnifying these thermal extremes, thereby placing species inhabiting the phyllosphere at greater risk of extinction.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s10"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s11"><title>Plants and Insect Species.</title><p>The species were collected in the apple orchard of La Morini&#x000e8;re, close to the laboratory (47&#x000b0;09&#x02032; N, 0&#x000b0;35&#x02032; E; elevation, 95 m above sea level). Each species was collected in a different year because they were not all present simultaneously: two spider mite species (the two-spotted spider mite <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> and the brown mite <italic>Bryobia rubrioculus</italic>) in 2011, two aphid species (the green apple aphid <italic>Aphis pomi</italic> and the rosy apple aphid <italic>Dysaphis plantaginea</italic>) and the spotted tentiform leaf miner (<italic>Phyllonorycter blancardella</italic>) in 2012, and the pear lace bug (<italic>Stephanitis piri</italic>) in 2015. All arthropods were subsequently reared on 1- to 2-y-old apple seedlings (<italic>Malus domestica</italic>, Golden cultivar) in a greenhouse in Tours, France (47&#x000b0;21&#x02032; N, 0&#x000b0;42&#x02032; E). Arthropods from spring generations were used in all experiments. Leaf gas exchange was measured 1 or 2 y after the establishment of the populations on apple seedlings in the greenhouse. Apple seedlings were planted in earthenware pots (11.5 cm in diameter) and watered every 2 d. A nutrient solution was added to the water once weekly (6% nitrogen, 6% P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>5</sub>, and 6% K<sub>2</sub>O, by volume). The daily amplitude of change in conditions was similar throughout the spring and between years (2011&#x02013;2015) in the greenhouse. In particular, daily air temperature (daily range, 14.5 to 38.5 &#x000b0;C; global mean, 24.4 &#x000b0;C), daily relative humidity (daily range, 29.5 to 95%; global mean, 74%), and radiation load, which was up to 875 W/m<sup>2</sup> at the level of the plants, were similar between years. All measurements (thermal tolerance limits and leaf gas exchange) were made at the same time in the spring of the abovementioned years. For a given species, the thermal limits of different groups of individuals (see below) were measured within the same week, and all individuals experienced very similar daily temperature conditions in the greenhouse during the 2 wk before a given trial (i.e., mean daily air temperature, 25.3 &#x000b0;C; mean daily minimum air temperature, 18.1 &#x000b0;C; and mean daily maximum air temperature, 34.8 &#x000b0;C).</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Thermal Tolerance Limits.</title><p>Thermal tolerance limits were determined by measuring the ULT of the adult stage for all species except the leaf miner, for which tolerance limits were determined at the fourth and fifth larval stages (this species has five larval stages, which develop within the mined leaf). ULT is defined as the temperature causing 50% mortality in a given group (essentially the LD<sub>50</sub>) after exposure to the experimental temperature for 1 h (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Both experimental and modeling studies showed that the daily maximal temperature experienced by these species at the surface of apple leaves or within leaf tissues (leaf miner) lasted no more than about 1 h, at about midday (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="r78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, <xref rid="r79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). A ramping temperature assay was used to simulate realistic thermal conditions, but see ref. <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> for a discussion on the influence of methodology on thermal limit determination (e.g., time of exposure versus rate of increase in temperature). Field measurements showed that the temperature of apple leaf surfaces and mines exposed to solar radiation changed at a rate of 0.37 &#x000b0;C/min on average (range, 0.11 to 3.35 &#x000b0;C/min) (<xref rid="r78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). This rate of temperature increase occurs when a surface is exposed to solar radiation in the morning up to noon.</p><p>We placed a group of 10 to 15 individuals of a given species in a Petri dish in a climatic chamber (VB 1014-A; V&#x000f6;tsch) and assessed mortality after 1 h of exposure to the experimental temperature. Insects were collected from leaves in the greenhouse in the morning, when air temperature was about 25 &#x000b0;C, and were immediately placed in a Petri dish. Petri dishes (one for each group of insects) were equipped with a fine copper/constantan thermocouple (type T, 0.2 mm in diameter; TC S.A.; connected to a CR1000 station; Campbell Scientific) measuring the temperature inside the dish close to the arthropods. A piece of wet cotton wool was used to generate high humidity within the sealed Petri dish so that organisms did not dry out. After an acclimation period of 15 min at 29 &#x000b0;C, the temperature was ramped up at a rate of 0.32 &#x000b0;C/min until the experimental temperature was reached. The experimental temperature was then maintained for 1 h. Survival was assessed 15 h after treatment. During this 15-h period, the arthropods were kept in the Petri dishes at 25 &#x000b0;C, with a freshly cut apple leaf to prevent deaths due to nutritional stress. The test involved touching the arthropods with a fine needle; those that were alive responded by moving. Possible bias due to thanatosis (individuals pretending to be dead), a particular problem with the lace bug, was overcome by marking the position of individuals in the Petri dish. Individuals were considered to be dead if they did not change position over a period of 30 min. Each group was exposed to a single temperature treatment. In total, 765 individuals were processed.</p></sec><sec id="s13"><title>Leaf Gas Exchange.</title><p>Gas exchanges were measured with an infrared gas analyzer equipped with a 2 &#x000d7; 3 cm leaf chamber system (LI-6400; LI-COR Inc.) and an external light source (6400-02B; LI-COR Inc.). Assimilation rate, transpiration rate, and stomatal conductance were measured on leaves attacked by the arthropod species, sometimes in a different year for some herbivores. The gas exchanges of intact apple leaves were also measured during each session to ensure that gas exchanges were similar between years. Each session occurred during the same period of the year (May and June) in the greenhouse. Gas exchange was measured under optimal conditions for apple leaves (<xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>): irradiance, 1,500 &#x000b5;mol&#x022c5;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x022c5;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; leaf temperature, 25 &#x000b0;C; water vapor deficit, 1 kPa; and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration in air, 390 ppm. Leaves were allowed to equilibrate for 20 to 30 min before any measurements were taken, and data were discarded if stomatal conductance was not stable after 45 min. Each session in a given year involved measurements on both attacked and intact leaves. The gas exchanges of intact apple leaves did not differ between sessions. For attacked leaves, the leaf surface was gently brushed with a fine pencil to eliminate any arthropods from the surface so that the gas exchange from the animals did not bias the measurements for the leaf. For the leaf miner, gas exchange in the area of the leaf mine was assessed as previously described (<xref rid="r80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>). Intact portions of leaf around the mine were covered with plant oil to prevent transpiration from intact leaf tissues. Leaves were cut and scanned after measurements. Scans were analyzed with ImageJ software (W. Rasband, NIH) to measure mine areas for the expression of stomatal conductance per unit of transpiring surface.</p><p>Different species may be found on leaf cohorts of different ages. The various species overlap (to a large extent) over the leaf age gradient; however, later leaf-miner stages are more frequently found on moderately old leaves, and the green apple aphid is essentially observed on relatively young leaves because it moves to the newly emerging leaves at the top of the shoots. Spider mites and lace bugs can colonize leaves of any age, but their densities result in measurable effects only after several weeks, when the leaves are mature. We therefore sampled gas exchange across a large spectrum of leaf ages (total range, 7 to 100 d; mean leaf age, 36 d for intact leaves, and 40, 36, 34, 56, 52, 41, and 45 d for leaves attacked by the green apple aphid, pear lace bug, brown mite, two-spotted spider mite, spotted tentiform leaf miner fifth and fourth larval stages, and rosy apple aphid, respectively). Mean leaf age was comparable for intact leaves and the leaves attacked by each arthropod species. Herbivore pressure was also standardized for each species according to the level of leaf damage, and not according to the density of the herbivore, because each species has a markedly different population growth rate. Furthermore, similar densities of spider mites and aphids have different effects on leaf ecophysiology, because these species differ considerably in body size, per capita feeding rate, and life span. A single leaf miner causes visible damage to a leaf, whereas the effect of a single spider mite cannot be detected. We therefore measured leaf gas exchange on leaves bearing one to two spotted tentiform leaf miners (focusing on the mined surface only, see method in ref. <xref rid="r80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>), 10 to 14 brown mite individuals (a leaf can host up to 22 individuals), and 10 to 21 individuals of the two-spotted spider mite. The number of two-spotted spider mites on a single leaf can be much higher, up to several hundreds, but we focused here on the period of population development at the leaf surface before the individuals begin producing silk and living above the leaf surface. In addition, three to 12 pear lace bug adults (a leaf contained up to 15 adults), and 11 to 28 individuals each of the green apple aphid and the rosy apple aphid were used. All these densities correspond to relatively early stages of infestation, and feeding on the plants started several weeks before measurements.</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Leaf Temperature Measurements.</title><p>We measured the temperature of attacked and intact leaves to determine the amplitude of temperature changes induced by the herbivores when feeding on an apple leaf. These measurements were done on key species that showed the most extreme ULTs, namely, the two-spotted spider mite, the spotted tentiform leaf miner, and the green apple aphid. These species were studied separately with a different approach. The temperature of leaves attacked by the two-spotted spider mite (<italic>n</italic> = 36) was measured with a thermal imaging device (B335; FLIR Systems) equipped with a macro lens (10 mm infrared lens; FLIR Systems) as in ref. <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>. Leaf temperatures were measured under controlled conditions in a climatic chamber (VB 1014-A; V&#x000f6;tsch): air temperature, 25 &#x000b0;C or 30 &#x000b0;C (we did not observe any difference in leaf temperature excess between these two groups; therefore, we merged them here); relative humidity, 60%; wind speed, 0.3 m/s; and global radiation level, 220 to 240 W/m<sup>2</sup> (see ref. <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> for more details). For the spotted tentiform leaf miner [both L4 (<italic>n</italic> = 10) and L5 (<italic>n</italic> = 13)], the temperature of mines was measured using fine thermocouples as in ref. <xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> in the same climatic chamber: air temperature, 25 &#x000b0;C; relative humidity, 65%; wind speed, 0.3 m/s; and global radiation level, 516 to 565 W/m<sup>2</sup> (see ref. <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> for more details). For the green apple aphid, the temperature of attacked leaves was measured in the field, in the same apple orchard as above, using fine thermocouples (copper/constantan, type T, 0.2 mm in diameter; TC S.A.) connected to a weather station (CR1000 equipped with a multiplexer AMT25; Campbell Scientific) set to record temperatures every 10 min. The thermocouples were positioned underneath the surface of five leaves hosting a colony of aphids and five leaves without any aphid on the same apple tree. We extracted the data measured at 1400, 1500, and 1600 hours during 12 cloudless days between June 19 and July 1 in 2012 to report temperatures of attacked leaves when solar radiation was high (mean &#x000b1; SE, 583 &#x000b1; 38 W/m<sup>2</sup>; range, 147 to 981 W/m<sup>2</sup>). Air temperature varied in the range 17.6 to 29.4 &#x000b0;C during that period. All temperature data were merged, since no difference was observed among the time intervals. Finally, we calculated the leaf temperature excess, which is defined as the difference between leaf and air temperatures.</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>Biophysical Modeling.</title><p>We used a biophysical model to calculate mean leaf temperature as a function of the environmental conditions and the properties of intact and attacked leaves, for comparison with arthropod thermal limits. The biophysical model is based on a leaf heat budget, with calculation of the heat transfers between the leaf and its surroundings (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). This heat budget model of an intact leaf has been fully validated in various contexts by different groups (<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Modified versions of the classic leaf heat budget model (<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) were used to simulate the temperature of leaves attacked by the various arthropods (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S4</italic></ext-link>). For the leaf miner species, we used the biophysical model previously developed for predicting temperatures within leaf mines (<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="r78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, <xref rid="r79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). This model introduces a new term, the heat exchanged between the mine and the adjacent leaf tissues, and considers the change in leaf surface absorbance for incoming radiation and changes in stomatal behavior (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S4</italic></ext-link>). For the other arthropod species, we changed the stomatal conductance parameter in the classic version of the leaf heat budget, except for the two-spotted spider mite, for which the absorbance of the attacked leaf tissues was also modified due to the rapid change in leaf color after spider mite attack (<xref rid="r81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). For all species, we simulated leaf temperature for the corresponding maximal stomatal conductance. The stomatal responses to temperature, light, and vapor pressure deficit in attacked leaves were considered to be similar to those of intact leaves (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S4</italic></ext-link>). Stomatal functions reaching a plateau at high temperatures were used, because transpiration rate becomes unresponsive to small changes in temperature and vapor pressure deficit at the extreme end of the range (<xref rid="r82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). We calculated microclimatic temperatures under constant wind speed (1 m/s) and humidity parameters (relative humidity, 75%). The models do not consider plant water and nutritional limitations but were used to calculate microclimatic temperatures for leaves fully exposed to solar radiation at midday, when the surrounding air temperature reaches the daily maximum. The radiation level was set to 982 W/m<sup>2</sup>, corresponding to the 95th percentile of the distribution of hourly global radiation levels for 2012 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S5</italic></ext-link>). The models were run for different values of air temperature corresponding to the 90th, 95th, 99th, and 99.9th percentiles of the hourly air temperature distribution for 2012 (27.4 &#x000b0;C, 29.7 &#x000b0;C, 33.6 &#x000b0;C, and 37 &#x000b0;C, respectively; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new"><italic>SI Appendix</italic>, <italic>Supplemental Information S5</italic></ext-link>). Finally, we compared the temperature of leaves attacked at these air temperatures with the ULT for each species to infer the vulnerability of each species to extreme conditions.</p></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Data Analysis.</title><p>The ULT of each species was extracted from a logistic regression analysis of survival and temperature. Using TableCurve software (Systat Software), we fitted a logistic dose&#x02013;response model to data for survival rate as a function of experimental temperature. This nonlinear model contains four parameters, including the LD<sub>50</sub> value (<xref rid="r78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, <xref rid="r83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). This procedure also estimates the 95% confidence interval of ULT for each species. The influence of each species on leaf gas exchange (assimilation rate, transpiration rate, and stomatal conductance) was then compared using ANOVA, with species as a fixed factor and with the calculation of pairwise probabilities in Fisher&#x02019;s least significant difference test. All the data for leaf gas exchange were normally distributed, with equal variances. The link between ULT and leaf transpiration rate was best described by a power relationship (<italic>y</italic> = a<italic>x</italic><sup>b</sup>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Am&#x000e9;lie Ezanic and Robin Caillon for their help with experimental procedures; the La Morini&#x000e8;re experimental station for allowing us to sample pest species in their apple orchards; and the two reviewers for their useful comments. This study was funded by the Agence pour la Recherche Scientifique program MicroCliMite (Grant ANR-2010 BLAN-1706-02) and the Projets Exploratoires Premier Soutien program of the CNRS/Institute of Ecology and Environment (project ThermalGame).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>This article is a PNAS Direct Submission.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>See Commentary on page <related-article related-article-type="commentary" id="d35e1162" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.1901972116">5220</related-article>.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>This article contains supporting information online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new">www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815828116/-/DCSupplemental</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffers</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The broad footprint of climate change from genes to biomes to people</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>354</volume><fpage>aaf7671</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27846577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radosavljevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Making better Maxent models of species distributions: Complexity, overfitting and evaluation</article-title><source>J Biogeogr</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>643</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Mechanistic niche modelling: Combining physiological and spatial data to predict species&#x02019; ranges</article-title><source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19292794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrl&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Predicting changes in the distribution and abundance of species under environmental change</article-title><source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25611188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Predicting organismal vulnerability to climate warming: Roles of behaviour, physiology and adaptation</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><volume>367</volume><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>1679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22566674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunday</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Thermal-safety margins and the necessity of thermoregulatory behavior across latitude and elevation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>111</volume><fpage>5610</fpage><lpage>5615</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24616528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maino</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Mechanistic models for predicting insect responses to climate change</article-title><source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27720078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>The roles of microclimatic diversity and of behavior in mediating the responses of ectotherms to climate change</article-title><source>J Therm Biol</source><volume>54</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26615730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sears</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Fine-scale microclimatic variation can shape the responses of organisms to global change in both natural and urban environments</article-title><source>Integr Comp Biol</source><volume>56</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27107292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suggitt</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennie</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Fine-scale climate change: Modelling spatial variation in biologically meaningful rates of warming</article-title><source>Glob Change Biol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arthur Woods</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Microclimatic challenges in global change biology</article-title><source>Glob Change Biol</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>2932</fpage><lpage>2939</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanoviak</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Thermal adaptation generates a diversity of thermal limits in a rainforest ant community</article-title><source>Glob Change Biol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1092</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Warming tolerance across insect ontogeny: Influence of joint shifts in microclimates and thermal limits</article-title><source>Ecology</source><volume>96</volume><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26230019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunday</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dulvy</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Global analysis of thermal tolerance and latitude in ectotherms</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><volume>278</volume><fpage>1823</fpage><lpage>1830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21106582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Addo-Bediako</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chown</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Thermal tolerance, climatic variability and latitude</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><volume>267</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10819141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chown</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clusella-Trullas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Upper thermal limits in terrestrial ectotherms: How constrained are they?</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>949</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Heat freezes niche evolution</article-title><source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>1206</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23869696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Angilletta</surname><given-names>MJJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><source>Thermal Adaptation&#x02013;A Theoretical and Empirical Synthesis</source><publisher-name>Oxford Univ Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Adaptation to temperature stress and aerial exposure in congeneric species of intertidal porcelain crabs (genus <italic>Petrolisthes</italic>): Correlation of physiology, biochemistry and morphology with vertical distribution</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>199</volume><fpage>1845</fpage><lpage>1855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9319758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strickler</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Rapid evolution of ant thermal tolerance across an urban-rural temperature cline</article-title><source>Biol J Linn Soc Lond</source><volume>121</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>257</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowd</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Thermal variation, thermal extremes and the physiological performance of individuals</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>218</volume><fpage>1956</fpage><lpage>1967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26085672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffers</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diesmos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Microhabitats reduce animal&#x02019;s exposure to climate extremes</article-title><source>Glob Change Biol</source><volume>20</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>503</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franken</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huizinga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Heated communities: Large inter- and intraspecific variation in heat tolerance across trophic levels of a soil arthropod community</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><volume>186</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29224117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingsolver</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Quantifying thermal extremes and biological variation to predict evolutionary responses to changing climate</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc B Biol Sci</source><volume>372</volume><fpage>20160147</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mechaber</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mechaber</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jobe</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1996</year><article-title>Mapping leaf surface landscapes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>4600</fpage><lpage>4603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11607676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The phyllosphere: Microbial jungle at the plant&#x02013;climate interface</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source><volume>47</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Phylloclimate or the climate perceived by individual plant organs: What is it? How to model it? What for?</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15869641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Climate uncertainty on leaf surfaces: The biophysics of leaf microclimates and their consequences for leaf-dwelling organisms</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>853</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><source>An Introduction to Environmental Biophysics</source><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unsworth</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><source>Principles of Environmental Physics</source><publisher-name>Academic</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc><edition>3rd Ed</edition></element-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1980</year><source>Biophysical Ecology</source><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michaletz</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The energetic and carbon economic origins of leaf thermoregulation</article-title><source>Nat Plants</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>16129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27548589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saudreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Temperature heterogeneity over leaf surfaces: The contribution of the lamina microtopography</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>40</volume><fpage>2174</fpage><lpage>2188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28710812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Promises and challenges in insect-plant interactions</article-title><source>Entomol Exp Appl</source><volume>166</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>343</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linacre</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name></person-group><year>1967</year><article-title>Further notes on a feature of leaf and air temperatures</article-title><source>Theor Appl Climatol</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>436</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caillon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suppo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Warming decreases thermal heterogeneity of leaf surfaces: Implications for behavioural thermoregulation by arthropods</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>1449</fpage><lpage>1458</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caillon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Do aphids alter leaf surface temperature patterns during early infestation?</article-title><source>Insects</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>E34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29538342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Ontogenetic changes in the body temperature of an insect herbivore</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>1322</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidowitz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Insect eggs protected from high temperatures by limited homeothermy of plant leaves</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>212</volume><fpage>3448</fpage><lpage>3454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19837886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nobel</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><source>Physicochemical and Environmental Plant Physiology</source><publisher-name>Academic</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><edition>2nd Ed</edition></element-citation></ref><ref id="r41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year><article-title>The interpretation of the variations in leaf water potential and stomatal conductance found in canopies in the field</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source><volume>273</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>610</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zangerl</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Impact of folivory on photosynthesis is greater than the sum of its holes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Comparison of photosynthetic damage from arthropod herbivory and pathogen infection in understory hardwood saplings</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><volume>149</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16758220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Arthropod impact on plant gas exchange</article-title><source>Insect-Plant Interactions</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernays</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Multitrophic biophysical budgets: Thermal ecology of an intimate herbivore insect-plant interaction</article-title><source>Ecol Monogr</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>194</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massonnet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regnard</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Stomatal regulation of photosynthesis in apple leaves: Evidence for different water-use strategies between two cultivars</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><volume>100</volume><fpage>1347</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17901058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Temperature extremes: Geographic patterns, recent changes, and implications for organismal vulnerabilities</article-title><source>Glob Change Biol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>3829</fpage><lpage>3842</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Impacts of climate warming on terrestrial ectotherms across latitude</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>105</volume><fpage>6668</fpage><lpage>6672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18458348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffers</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Thermal buffering of microhabitats is a critical factor mediating warming vulnerability of frogs in the Philippine biodiversity hotspot</article-title><source>Biotropica</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>635</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Why tropical forest lizards are vulnerable to climate warming</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><volume>276</volume><fpage>1939</fpage><lpage>1948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19324762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sache</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suffert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chelle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>The development of a foliar fungal pathogen does react to leaf temperature!</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><volume>198</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23373986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>All&#x000e8;gre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Stomatal deregulation in <italic>Plasmopara viticola</italic>-infected grapevine leaves</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><volume>173</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17286831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cory</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Plant-mediated effects in insect-pathogen interactions</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16697914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowakowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Infection risk decreases with increasing mismatch in host and pathogen environmental tolerances</article-title><source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27339786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gehman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Host and parasite thermal ecology jointly determine the effect of climate warming on epidemic dynamics</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29311324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Thermal biology in insect-parasite interactions</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>350</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Extended phenotypes and extended organisms</article-title><source>Biol Philos</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>352</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saudreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Structure is more important than physiology for estimating intracanopy distributions of leaf temperatures</article-title><source>Ecol Evol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>5206</fpage><lpage>5218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29876095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>GlobTherm, a global database on thermal tolerances for aquatic and terrestrial organisms</article-title><source>Sci Data</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>180022</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29533392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RKD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higley</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Arthropods injury and plant gas exchange: Current understandings and approaches for synthesis</article-title><source>Trends Agric Sci</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stocking</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year><article-title>Some immediate effects on almond leaves of feeding by <italic>Bryobia rubrioculus</italic> (Scheuten)</article-title><source>Acarologia</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Leaf cell and tissue damage of cucumber caused by twospotted spider mite (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><volume>95</volume><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klingeman</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Iersel</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buntin</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braman</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Whole-plant CO<sub>2</sub> exchange measurements on azaleas injured by azalea lace bug (Heteroptea: Tingidae) feeding</article-title><source>J Econ Entomol</source><volume>93</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10826185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitlow</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><article-title>Effects of leaf and sap feeding insects on photosynthetic rates of goldenrod</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><volume>92</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28313218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Retuerto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Lema</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roiloa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obeso</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Increased photosynthetic performance in holly trees infested by scale insects</article-title><source>Funct Ecol</source><volume>18</volume><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>669</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Auclair</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1963</year><article-title>Aphid feeding and nutrition</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>490</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Life stages of an aphid living under similar thermal conditions differ in thermal performance</article-title><source>J Insect Physiol</source><volume>99</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28283383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Truebano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tills</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rundle</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year><article-title>Thermal strategies vary with life history stage</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><volume>221</volume><fpage>jeb171629</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29559547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denno</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Interspecific interactions in phytophagous insects revisited: A quantitative assessment of competition theory</article-title><source>Ecol Lett</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17855811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauri</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Defrance</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauphanor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Does manipulation of fruit-tree architecture affect the development of pests and pathogens? A case study in an organic apple orchard</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci Biotechnol</source><volume>81</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>773</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evenhuis</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1964</year><article-title>The interrelations between apple aphids and their parasites and hyperparasites</article-title><source>Entomophaga</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>231</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahr</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Verification and extension of a sampling plan for apple aphid, <italic>Aphis pomi</italic> DeGeer (Hemiptera: Aphididae)</article-title><source>Environ Entomol</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>488</fpage><lpage>496</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonato</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>The effect of temperature on life history parameters of <italic>Tetranychus evansi</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bounfour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanigoshi</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Effect of temperature on development and demographic parameters of <italic>Tetranychus urticae</italic> and <italic>Eotetranychus carpini borealis</italic> (Acari: Tetranychidae)</article-title><source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source><volume>94</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>404</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontodimas</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahragard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Estimating development of <italic>Aphis pomi</italic> (DeGeer) (Homoptera: Aphididae) using linear and nonlinear models</article-title><source>Environ Entomol</source><volume>35</volume><fpage>1208</fpage><lpage>1215</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>The layers of plant responses to insect herbivores</article-title><source>Annu Rev Entomol</source><volume>61</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26651543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Frenne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>Microclimate moderates plant responses to macroclimate warming</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>18561</fpage><lpage>18565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24167287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinoquet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Combes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Regional climate modulates the canopy mosaic of favourable and risky microclimates for insects</article-title><source>J Anim Ecol</source><volume>76</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17439460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saudreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2013</year><article-title>On the canopy structure manipulation to buffer climate change effects on insect herbivore development</article-title><source>Trees</source><volume>27</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinoquet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regnard</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Herbivory mitigation through increased water-use efficiency in a leaf-mining moth-apple tree relationship</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>2238</fpage><lpage>2247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17081256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luedeling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dharmasri</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Remote sensing of spider mite damage in California peach orchards</article-title><source>Int J Appl Earth Obs Geoinf</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>255</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="r82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ocheltree</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nippert</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><article-title>Stomatal responses to changes in vapor pressure deficit reflect tissue-specific differences in hydraulic conductance</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><volume>37</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23701708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="r83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanford</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helmuth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Body temperature during low tide alters the feeding performance of a top intertidal predator</article-title><source>Limnol Oceanogr</source><volume>53</volume><fpage>1562</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>