<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sampling Methods and Study Locations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We collected data in 1995 from eight UK locations (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g001" href="#pone-0053959-g001">Fig. 1</a>) used in previous work on oak gallwasp community dynamics 
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge1">[9]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge3">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge4">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge5" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge5">[34]</a> whose tree stands and cynipid communities are detailed by Schönrogge 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge3">[16]</a>. All sites were visited with landowner permission, and no permits for sampling were required. Samples were collected in mid-late April, at an appropriate time to capture all developing galls prior to the ejection of emerged galls by developing buds. At each site we selected 12 
  <span class="italic">Q. cerris</span> trees at random or, if fewer than 12 were present, sampled all available trees. We pruned 15 branches (defined as 4 years’ growth following Schönrogge 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge3">[16]</a>) from each tree, collected haphazardly from all aspects and heights up to 8.0 m. From each branch, we randomly selected six shoots (defined as one year’s growth, identified by ring scars on the bark, following Schönrogge 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053959-Schnrogge3">[16]</a>). The sexual generation bud galls of all three 
  <span class="italic">Andricus</span> species are conical and small enough that only the tip of a mature gall is visible above the bud scales of the closed buds on 
  <span class="italic">Q. cerris</span>. To reveal gall density and fate we dissected 
  <span class="underline">all</span> buds on each sampled shoot in the lab under a dissecting microscope (a total of 11,100 shoots, 33,440 buds and 3,474 galls). Since young galls of the three study species are available simultaneously, contain very similarly-sized larvae and are morphologically indistinguishable, we treated all three species as a single resource. On the basis of adults dissected from galls, we know that in all surveys &gt;50% of the galls were 
  <span class="italic">A. lignicolus</span>.
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0053959-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Geographic locations of the eight sampling sites in Britain.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0053959.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Galls attacked by birds show ragged removal of the gall apex, rather than the smooth apertures made by emerging insects. Though we could easily identify galls attacked by birds, we do not attempt to distinguish between galls opened by different bird species.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In spring 2006, we collected additional data at one location (Puttenham Common; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g001" href="#pone-0053959-g001">Fig. 1</a>) to allow analysis of temporal patterns of bird predation within a single season. We sampled as above the same twelve 
  <span class="italic">Q. cerris</span> trees each week for five weeks from March 25, over which period the galls matured and the adults emerged. To identify probable bird species attacking alien galls at this site in this season, we observed six Turkey oaks for one hour in each of weeks 2–5. We observed 72 gall predation incidents by a total of seven bird species. Seventy-five percent involved tits, predominantly blue tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus caeruleus</span>, 55%) and great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>, 18%). Other birds observed were Long-tailed tits (
  <span class="italic">Aegithalos caudatus</span> (L.), 1.4%), robins (
  <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span> (L.), 11.1%), song thrushes (
  <span class="italic">Turdus philomelos</span> Brehm, 5.5%), blackbirds (
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span> L., 6.9%), and green woodpeckers (
  <span class="italic">Picus viridis</span> L., 1.4%).
 </p>
</sec>
