<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We chose the maximum entropy modeling approach implemented in Maxent (Phillips &amp; Dudík, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) to identify current habitat suitability, the importance of permutation, the contribution of each environmental variable, and future status under climate change by 2050. This model is considered as a typical method for habitat suitability modeling of the impacts of climate change by associating presence‐only data, habitat variables, and climatic variables (Gallagher, Hughes, &amp; Leishman, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Due to occurrence bias across giant panda sign points, we thinned the set of occurrence trails with the delete identical function in ArcGIS 10.0 based on 1,800 m tolerance (the radius of a giant panda home range in Qinling; Pan, Mcshea, Garshelis, Wang, &amp; Harris, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), to reduce the possibility of the model overestimating environmental conditions at sites of sign clustering and underestimating environmental conditions in areas with low sampling density. After bias removal, the calibration points consisted of 465 sign points from 1,810 trial records. To further characterize model performance, we calculated the average test values of the area under the curve (AUC) with different random subsamples (70% training and 30% test data). The AUC value is widely used as an indicator of a model's ability to discriminate between suitable and unsuitable habitats (Dan &amp; Seifert, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and the models were considered reliable when AUC &gt; 0.75 (Rebelo, Tarroso, &amp; Jones, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Permutation importance depends on the final model and is better for evaluating the importance of a particular variable (Songer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Therefore, we evaluated the importance of the habitat variables based on permutation importance.
</p>
