<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">The interview transcripts were analysed systematically by means of a qualitative content analysis (see Mayring 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2010</xref>, Kuckartz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>). Facilitated by the software Atlas.ti (see atlasti.com for more information), the qualitative content analysis was performed in two steps. In the first step, codes were deductively defined based on the theoretical model outlined above, and relevant text passages of the empirical material were assigned to these codes in Atlas.ti. Deductive codes included, for example, belief in climate change, perceived/expected changes in climate conditions, perceived/expected climate change-related risks/opportunities, already implemented/planned adaptation measures, perceived effectiveness/efficiency of adaptation measures, and perceived adaptation costs. Code definitions were based on the relevant theoretical literature (Grothmann 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>; Grothmann and Patt 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2005</xref>; Grothmann and Reusswig 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>) and saved as code comments in Atlas.ti. In a second step, these codes were further decomposed inductively, i.e. based on the empirical material, for instance to introduce sub-categories or an evaluation. Furthermore, new codes were added for emerging topics. The combination of theoretically- and empirically-driven coding is known as deductive-inductive strategy and widely recommended in the literature in order to increase analytical flexibility and thus utilize the qualitative material as effectively as possible (Gläser and Laudel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2013</xref>; Kuckartz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2014</xref>; Schreier 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2014</xref>). It should be noted that there is no algorithm for automatically assigning text passages of the interview transcripts to the defined codes. Developing and applying the code system is an interpretative process based on the intellectual performance of the analysts. The code system was developed in close cooperation by a team of researchers, whereby text segments of the interview transcripts and respective coding were discussed thoroughly in order to improve and refine the code system iteratively.
</p>
