<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-16-02460" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Land Cover and Land Cover Category Change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently, croplands and tropical evergreen forests are the two most abundant land cover categories in the region, each representing almost 20% of the study area (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02460-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02460-f002">Figure 2</a>). Croplands are most commonly found across India, Myanmar, Thailand, and Vietnam, while tropical evergreen forests are most prominently distributed in Malaysia, Indonesia, Brunei, Philippines, Cambodia, Vietnam, and other Southeast Asian countries. Land covered by cropland, either irrigated or naturally flooded, is distributed mainly in the northern part of India, accounting for 13% of the study area. The areas covered by mosaic cropland/natural vegetation in both tropical and temperate regions account for more than 5% of the total, with most of this land cover type existing in Southeast Asia.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between 1992 and 2015, the land cover category changed across 553.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> of the region, and the most common conversions were urban expansion, land reclamation, and deforestation. The single largest proportion change in land cover was associated with urban expansion. The total amount of land classified as urban area in South and Southeast Asia increased by 41.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, representing a 1.72 fold increase from 1992 to 2015. Land cover categories, such as tropical mosaic cropland/natural vegetation, urban areas, and temperate scrub/woodland, expanded rapidly by increasing more than 25 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> for each type during the period in question. Tropical deciduous forest, tropical mosaic cropland/natural vegetation, and temperate scrub/woodland increased by more than 10%. Differently, shrubland, tropical peat forest, tropical evergreen forest, and tropical broadleaved, deciduous forest experienced the most significant decline, reducing in area by more than 18 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> for each type. Tropical peat forest and shrubland were both reduced by more than 20% over the time period.
 </p>
</sec>
