<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional effect on ostracode δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O values
 </div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O values in the N2015 core from Lake Nakaumi fluctuated between 1.0 and −1.25 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). The interval over which the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records were obtained from the N2015 core overlapped to with the interval for the X core between AD 300 and 1100
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. The 500 yr running mean values of the ostracode δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O from the N2015 core were similar to those in the X core during the interval; moreover, a common gradually decreasing trend was also found. Overall, the long-term δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O values gradually declined beginning in BC 900. This trend corresponds to a decrease in salinity induced by ostracode assemblage changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, suggesting that the long-term trend in the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of ostracode shells was caused by a regional environmental shift accompanied by a gradual decrease in salinity (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O records from ostracode shells of 
     <span class="italic">Bicornucythere bisanensis</span>. The data from the N2015 core (blue) were represented by adding the records from the X core (green)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
     </span>. The coloured thick, thin and extra-thin lines suggest 500 yr and 50 yr running mean values and measurement values, respectively. Environmental changes were derived from fossil ostracode assemblages
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41359_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e410" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The standardized δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O values between the two cores taken from Lake Nakaumi displayed anti-correlation between AD 300 and AD 1000 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). During this period, the reconstructed EASM intensity in the N2015 core showed a positive correlation with that in the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records from stalagmites in Wanxiang Cave, China
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>, whereas there was a negative correlation with the records from the X core
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. These anti-correlations of the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records in the ostracode shells of Lake Nakaumi could be ascribed to the differences in water mass that affected the core sites. Complicated water discharge patterns are currently observed in Lake Nakaumi: A large volume of low-salinity water that outflows from the surface of the lake causes an increase in the inflow of seawater at the bottom of the lake from the Sea of Japan
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. The location of the X core is far from the mouth of the Iinashi River, which transports a large volume of freshwater that is discharged into the lake, which does not occur at the site of the N2015 core (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). In addition, the X core is located in the area where seawater directly flows from the entrance to the central part of the lake at the bottom. Thus, it is estimated that marine water strongly affected the bottom portion of the X core during periods of heavy precipitation. The positive correlations between the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of stalagmites in Wanxiang Cave and the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of adult ostracode shells from the X core are identical since AD 1100, which is approximately equivalent to the timing of the environmental shift to closed blackish lake conditions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Furthermore, the common peaks of the three records in Lake Nakaumi and Wanxiang Cave support that the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of adult ostracode shells in the lake represent the EASM variations. Hence, these observations infer that the centennial-scale δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of adult ostracode shells in the lake reflect the intensity of the EASM; however the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of ostracode shells taken from the X core show anti-variations before AD 1100. Yamada 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> interpreted these anti-variations between the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of ostracode shells taken from the X core and the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records of stalagmites in Wanxiang Cave as the northwestern migration of the monsoon limit. However, additional δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records from ostracode shells in the present study reveal that the anti-correlation was probably caused by the local water circulation conditions in the lake.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparisons of EASM records in the monsoonal region, sun activity and climatic records. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Insolation at 30°N in June
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Standardized cosmogenic atmospheric 
     <span class="sup">14</span>C
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Standardized δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O records in ostracode shells of 
     <span class="italic">Bicornucythere bisanensis</span> from the N2015 core in Lake Nakaumi, southwest Japan. (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Standardized δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O in ostracode shells of 
     <span class="italic">B</span>. 
     <span class="italic">bisanensis</span> from the X core in Lake Nakaumi, southwest Japan
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">e</span>) Standardized δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O records from stalagmites from Wanxiang Cave, central China
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">f</span>) Standardized δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O records from stalagmites from Heshang Cave, central China
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">g</span>) Standardized δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O records from stalagmites from Dongge Cave, south China
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">h</span>) Red colour intensity from the lake in southern Ecuador
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">i</span>–
     <span class="bold">k</span>) weak EASM events identified in the millennial-scale EASM records from Baeg-nyong Cave, Korean Peninsula
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
     </span>, Tibetan Plateau, central China
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
     </span>, and Dongge Cave, south China
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
     </span>. Vertical grey bars indicate enhanced EASM periods from the records in Lake Nakaumi.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41359_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e589" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
