<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An ongoing challenge facing society is how to minimize the negative impacts of global climate change. As noted by Newell, McDonald, Brewer, and Hayes[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], tackling this problem requires an understanding of how people think and reason about (1) environmental systems, and (2) the (adverse) effects that human activities have on these systems. A key insight is that the problem of climate change mitigation can be understood in terms of the more general problem of how people manage and control dynamic causal systems[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Osman[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] provided a recent review of the multitude of tasks that have been developed to investigate how people interact with, and manage, dynamic systems, and the different classes of theories that have been developed to explain performance. A common finding is that people often lack insight into the rules, or interactions among variables, that govern how these systems behave. It follows that the 
 <italic class="italic">mental models</italic>—the psychological representation of system variables and their effects—people rely on to complete these tasks are lacking in important ways[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Generally speaking, people’s mental models of complex systems inaccurately represent and/or relate variables to one another[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], are missing important mechanistic relationships[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], and misrepresent the underlying system dynamics[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. It follows, then, that people’s ability to control causal dynamic systems tends to be quite poor[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. A practical challenge lies in identifying ways in which people’s reasoning about causal dynamic systems can be improved, such that better management and control outcomes can be achieved.
</p>
