<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The need to improve the accuracy of people’s mental models is especially important for climate change mitigation. Several authors view an accurate mental model of climate change as a necessary step toward adoption of effective mitigation policies[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. However, it is known that laypeople possess highly inaccurate mental models about the causes of climate change[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], and that they do not accurately represent the stock-and-flow dynamics that govern the accumulation of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Because misconceptions about climate change dynamics have been argued to encourage complacency with respect to climate change mitigation[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], a goal of recent research has been to identify ways of overcoming the limitations of people’s mental models to improve their understanding of climate change dynamics. These studies have focused on improving people’s reasoning about accumulation dynamics in tasks with an explicit environmental goal: to stabilize levels of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. In this article, we build upon this work, by investigating performance in a novel repeated-decision task, where people have an explicit 
 <italic class="italic">economic</italic> goal to achieve—rather than an environmental goal—but their progress toward that goal can be hindered by negative effects of global warming within the system. We show that people’s ability to achieve the economic goal is tied to receiving accurate causal knowledge about the system variables. Causal knowledge about the interactions between economic and climate variables within the system appears to bias people toward more cautious means-ends pursuit of the economic goal. The effect of causal knowledge appears to be robust over time and incremental changes in the state of the causal system, and persists for over two hundred consecutive decisions.
</p>
