<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">This finding suggests that a strongly non-linear interaction between background climate, local warming and precipitation changes causes the local warming effect on rainfall to exhibit steep geographical gradients in its seasonal cycle (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>), see Supplementary Information. Two locations with roughly the same annual value in local temperature induced rainfall (ΔR
 <sub class="sub">ΔT</sub>), one in the North Atlantic and the other on the North Pole, exhibit totally opposing seasonal cycles (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4a</xref>). Over the central Arctic Ocean ΔR
 <sub class="sub">ΔT</sub> peaks in summer, whereas over the North Atlantic ΔR
 <sub class="sub">ΔT</sub> reaches maximum values during the frigid winter months. This reversal is decidedly linked to seasonal changes in the temperature-dependent snowfall fraction: ambient temperatures should be around zero to allow local warming to have an appreciable effect on the snowfall fraction (see Supplementary Information). In too cold (central Arctic winter) or too mild (subarctic summer) conditions, temperature changes do not lead to substantial changes in the snowfall fraction (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4b</xref>), even for projected winter warming rates as high as about 20 °C in de central Arctic (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4c</xref>). Therefore, paradoxically, the projected extreme winter warming in the central Arctic Ocean will only lead to minute effects on rainfall, whereas quite moderate summer warming rates will cause a strong increase in rainfall. This stems from the non-linear dependence of snowfall fraction on temperature (change)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>, and results in steep spatial gradients in the magnitude and seasonality through which projected future changes in Arctic rainfall can be linked to local warming.
</p>
