<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As the modeling algorithm, we employed the maximum entropy algorithm as implemented in MaxEnt v. 3.3 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>, whose output is a map of habitat suitability ranging from 0 to 1 per grid cell. MaxEnt for species habitat modeling has some advantages compared to other SDM methods, including its convenience, its use of presence-only species records, and a generally excellent predictive performance
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>. We used only ‘linear’ and ‘quadratic’ feature to avoid producing too complex a model, which could lead to extrapolation errors
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref>. The distribution model for 
 <italic class="italic">D. involucrata</italic> under current conditions was projected to three time slices: mid-Holocene (ca. 6000 yr BP), LGM (ca. 21,000 yr BP), and 2070 (average for 2061–2080). For both past scenarios, we used paleoclimatic layers simulated by the Community Climate System Model Version 4 (CCSM4)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>, the Model for Interdisciplinary Research on Climate Earth System Model (MIROC-ESM)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref>, and the New Earth System Model of the Max Planck Institute for Meteorology (MPI-ESM-P: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mpimet.mpg.de/en/science/models/mpi-esm/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.mpimet.mpg.de/en/science/models/mpi-esm/</ext-link>). To predict potential shifts of the geographic distribution that might be caused by global climate change, we used three of the models with the best performance among the various available ones that have participated in the 5th Coupled Model Inter-Comparison Project (CMIP5) experiment
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" class="xref">36</xref>: CCSM4, the NOAA Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory Coupled Model 3 (GFDL-CM3)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" class="xref">37</xref>, and MPI-ESM-LR. The three models were run in two of the four representative concentration pathways (RCPs) that were used in the Fifth Assessment IPCC report, RCP 2.6 and RCP 8.5 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" class="xref">38</xref>. RCP 2.6 represents the most “benign” scenario (i.e., a likely increase of 0.3–1.7 °C for ca. 2081–2100), whereas RCP 8.5 is the most extreme scenario (a likely increase of 2.6–4.8 °C for ca. 2081–2100). All 19 bioclimatic variables for both past and future climate scenarios were also downloaded from the WorldClim website, at the same resolution (2.5 arc-min).
</p>
