<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">We used the predictive movement maps to quantify the impacts of the climate change and conservation scenarios on the simulated caribou movement behavior. We assessed three potential impacts: the distance of movement beyond the present subpopulation ranges; the proportion of time spent outside these ranges; and the use of the biodiversity reserves. We measured the movement distance as the number of cells outside the present subpopulation ranges that were visited at least once (Dist
 <sub class="sub">Out</sub>). We used the mean number of visits in these cells to measure the amount of time spent outside the ranges (Use
 <sub class="sub">Out</sub>). We measured the use of biodiversity reserves as the mean number of visits over all cells within the biodiversity reserves (Use
 <sub class="sub">RB</sub>). We tested for scenario effects on these indicators using 3 factor ANOVAs with main effects and all 2-way interactions, without replication. The values calculated for the scenario predictive movement maps are estimates of the expected value of the simulated indicators, given the scenario specifications. The climate and conservation (protected areas and roads) scenarios are represented as treatment factors of 4, 2 and 3 levels, respectively. Therefore, the model degrees of freedom are 6 = 3 + 1 + 2 for the main effects plus 11 = 3 + 6 + 2 for the 2-way interactions, leaving 6 = 24 − 1 − 6 − 11 residual degrees of freedom. In a traditional ANOVA with replications, effects are assessed relative to the process variance, and significance levels decrease with the number of replicates, which can be made arbitrarily large. In ANOVA without replication, effects are assessed relative to a residual variance determined by the experimental design, and significance levels depend on the design but not on the number of replicates per se. Rather, increased replications decreases the standard error of the estimated scenario means. For these reasons, we consider ANOVA on the group means to be appropriate for analysis of simulation experiments.
</p>
