<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concluding remarks and research needs</div>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This review outlined the societal aspects of OA aiming to identify its major social and political causes, and subsequently also the primary mitigation and adaptation responses needed to reduce future OA and alleviate current and future consequences if not being mitigated properly. In regards to (Q1): 
  <span class="italic">What are the primary causes of anthropogenic ocean acidification from a social science perspective?</span> We found that the primary causes of anthropogenic OA from a social science perspective relate to governance and market failures. These failures are exacerbated by the global nature of OA which requires cooperation among states to address it. However, the prospects for coordinated policy efforts, and the extent to which policy diffusion or transfer is possible, are unclear due to contextual variations. In addition, substantial impacts of OA on the generation of ecosystem services and hence on human well-being will likely alter resource distribution between individuals, which may seem unfair for those who lose out and especially among those who lose out while having contributed least to the occurrence of the problem. Further, assuming linear changes, the rate of adaptation to OA in our human systems would have at least to keep pace with rates of ecological change in order for people to continue to derive benefits from key marine ecosystem services. With the potential for ecological tipping points, the rate of adaptation may even have to be much more rapid to avoid negative societal impacts. Our review highlights the current scant knowledge related to the extents and impacts of different market and governance failures in relation to OA, and how these interact with each other.
 </p>
 <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This review also outlined multiple ways in which (Q2) 
  <span class="italic">society can respond to ocean acidification</span>, with a special focus on a Swedish context. Little is currently known about the appropriateness of various existing policies, legal provisions, mechanisms, and administrative systems that address either the main cause of OA (i.e. increasing atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub>), or the additional stressors that may influence resilience and adaptation. This lack of knowledge prevents informed assessment of the current institutional framework within which OA arises, and subsequently the design of additional or modified measures to deal with OA. Our review also clearly demonstrates the lack of a comprehensive overview of mitigation structures, in Sweden and elsewhere.
 </p>
 <p id="Par59" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a Swedish perspective, reducing locally managed anthropogenic pressures (e.g. fisheries) could increase resilience to OA in the short run. Thus, devising strategies for changing local management practices for non-OA stressors may reduce threats from OA to key ecosystem services. However, this is likely not a long-term solution. The global extent of OA, its complex social–ecological dynamics involving potential tipping points, the clear role of anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions to worsen it, the large uncertainties associated with most of its dimensions, and the potentially very large impacts, all together speak for a precautionary approach to address OA (see e.g. Crépin and Folke 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2015</a>). While current knowledge of the problem is alarming enough to justify putting in place substantial mitigation policies, better knowledge about the socioeconomic dimensions involved in OA would contribute to policy improvements.
 </p>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we identified 
  <span class="italic">major knowledge gaps and research</span> needs with regard to the future study of OA (Q3), which we summarize in Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>.
  <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Research needs in social sciences with regard to ocean acidification, key domains are highlighted</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" colspan="2">Research needs</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" colspan="2">
       <p>• Identify the types and magnitude of 
        <span class="italic">market failures</span> relevant to OA, their consequences, quantify their relative importance and interactions among them
       </p>
       <p>• Analyse the coherency and/or conflicts between the 
        <span class="italic">national</span>, 
        <span class="italic">EU</span>, 
        <span class="italic">and international legal and administrative systems</span> relevant for OA
       </p>
       <p>• Further explore contradictions, overlaps, and gaps in 
        <span class="italic">existing institutional arrangements</span> that cause OA, and how they can be amended, focusing on the legal and administrative feasibility including the degree of readiness to pursue required changes among concerned actors
       </p>
       <p>• 
        <span class="italic">Build a schematic understanding</span> of how the existing regulations and management structures link to OA, and to each other and how current policy tools reinforce (or counteract) each other in the aim of changing human behaviour
       </p>
       <p>• Analyse whether increased 
        <span class="italic">public knowledge</span> of the causes and consequences of OA, and policy tools to address this problem, could increase public policy support
       </p>
       <p>• Understand the importance of 
        <span class="italic">political</span>–
        <span class="italic">economic context</span> for policy support, and how this interacts with 
        <span class="italic">individual</span>-
        <span class="italic">level mechanisms</span> driving policy support and behavioural change
       </p>
       <p>• Develop knowledge on how to foster, evaluate and implement increased 
        <span class="italic">ecosystem resilience to OA through habitat repair and protection</span>
       </p>
       <p>• Improved 
        <span class="italic">resource allocation strategies</span> (e.g. transitional compensation systems, support to new activities, etc.), and identification of winners and losers among societal groups
       </p>
       <p>• Investigate the 
        <span class="italic">impacts of different measures on incentives for innovation</span> in order to avoid lock-ins and maintenance of old structures that are not adapted to the new situation
       </p>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
