<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigation</div>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigation strategies aim to treat the problem at its root by reducing its very causes. In the long term, limiting emissions of CO
  <sub>2</sub> to the atmosphere, and reducing the amount of CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere (Billé et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>), are the only mitigation strategies available to comprehensively address OA (Pacala and Socolow 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2004</a>; Cooley and Doney 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>). Hence many (though not all, see Herr et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2014</a>) of the policies targeting climate change already in place will also mitigate OA. However, although increasing anthropogenic inputs via CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions drive acidification globally, local acidification is also the result of non-atmospheric stressors on the local level such as abiotic processes, eutrophication, hypoxia, upwelling events bringing low-pH water to near-shore areas, sulphur dioxide precipitation, and runoff from acidic fertilizers caused by agriculture, mineral extraction, and poor ecosystem management (cf. Kelly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>). Therefore, mitigating OA requires concerted efforts on several levels—from the local to the global. On the one hand, 
  <span class="italic">global</span> mitigation strategies require a wide range of efforts on the global and international scale, several of which have already been initiated through multilateral cooperation such as the 2015 Paris Agreement (UNFCCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201" href="#CR201">2016</a>), the 1992 Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">1992</a>), and the 2013 Kiruna Declaration (AC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200" href="#CR200">2013</a>). On the other hand, multilateral processes are typically complex and politically contested, requiring the involvement of a range of different actors and therefore not “quick fixes” (Sterner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2006</a>), partly due to the anarchic nature of the international political system (cf. Bäckstrand 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2006</a>). Indeed, as pointed out by Osborne et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>, p. 404) “the required actions to mitigate and adapt to ocean acidification have yet to be incorporated in international policy”. From this follows that short-term mitigation responses to OA (including both CO
  <sub>2</sub>-emissions and non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> stressors)—as well as the social science research on these matters—should rather focus on developing policy at the local and regional levels, where existing management structures and legal systems are more likely to effectively address these challenges (Cooley and Doney 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>; Kelly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>; Cooley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>). Also, internationally agreed measures almost invariably need to be translated into (legal) measures at the national or subnational level to have direct impact on the behaviour of individuals and firms, thereby further strengthening the case for paying attention to measures at these levels as well as the EU level where measures can have similar effects.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although not overwhelming, some examples on such national and subnational efforts to both adapt to, and mitigate future OA problems, do exist in the more recent literature. One prominent example put forward on political responses to OA concerns the collapse of the oyster industry on the US west coast. This, in turn, sparked reactions on both the local level, building networks among researchers and stakeholders to monitor changes and disseminate information, as well as the state level of government, integrating OA into long-term state resource management plans (Osborne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>). In Maine, on the US east-coast, a similar problem led to similar network-building reactions on the local and state levels, and a number of state bills addressing the problem with nutrient pollution from farms and septic systems have since been put forward (Cooley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>). In addition, in the case of the US, it has been suggested to use the Federal Clean Water Act to limit OA-inducing pollutants as a national-level response to acidification, although its authority is limited to land-based point source pollutants (cf. Kelly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>), and the adoption in the US of the Federal Ocean Acidification Research and Monitoring Act of 2009 are examples on national-level responses spurred by the increasing public attention to the OA problem (Osborne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>). A range of examples on similar efforts to build knowledge, natural science research capacity, and political attention also exists outside the US: the Brazil OA Research Network (BROA), the Biological Impacts of OA Program (BIOACID) in Germany, and the United Kingdom’s Ocean Acidification Research Programme (UKOA) to name but a few (Cooley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>). In parallel, also cross-national networks, such as the European Project on Ocean Acidification (EPOCA), and the MedSeA Project to study OA in the Mediterranean Sea funded by the European Commission have been launched during the past 10 years.
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> However, although these efforts have served to raise awareness and knowledge about the problem among policy makers, a next step in mitigating OA is the real-life design and implementation of concrete policy tools, capable of addressing practices and behaviours that contribute to the anthropogenic stressors for OA. This, however, presents policy makers with significant challenges as behavioural change is not easily governed. In these endeavours, social science research can and will play an important role, for example, in the designing of effective policy tools, simultaneously utilizing opportunities and negotiating barriers for successful policy development and implementation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We discuss here the challenges of changing behaviour with policy tools and the rationale behind different types of policy tools.</p>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changing behaviour with policy tools</div>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> OA exhibits the characteristics of a classic collective-action problem: lack of cooperation among actors responsible for OA results in suboptimal outcomes for the collective (Olson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">1965</a>). As Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>c illustrates, limiting CO
   <sub>2</sub>, and thus OA, will rarely be provided in sufficient quantity, (if at all), because of the difficulties of aggregating all actors’ willingness to pay for it. There is an imminent risk of free-riding arising regardless of whether or not the collective willingness-to-pay for an additional limitation of CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions is large (e.g. Ostrom 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">1990</a>). Significant voluntary behavioural changes are therefore unlikely among individuals. The same holds true regarding potential appropriate responses to the negative externalities, large uncertainties, and the risk of tipping points involved in OA (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a, b, d). Some form of intentional, third party coordination or 
   <span class="italic">governmental coercion</span> (Mansbridge 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2014</a>) is usually necessary to address market failures and initiate cooperation, especially when the number of involved actors is very large, dispersed over vast geographical areas, and therefore mostly anonymous to each other. Such governmental coercion usually takes the form of various policy tools aimed at changing the incentive structures governing behavioural choices, either by increasing the attractiveness of preferred behaviour or by exacerbating the negative impact of an undesired behavioural choice.
  </p>
  <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global nature of OA creates a need for global cooperation but the lack of a supranational authority and limited enforcement mechanisms at that scale suggest that legal measures to initiate multilateral cooperation must take the form of voluntary entered into agreements and treaties. Thus, this set-up is largely dependent on the will and the ability of individual states. This can be extremely tricky to achieve (see e.g. the recent withdrawal of the US from the Paris Agreement), in particular agreements of how costs and benefits should be distributed across national borders, and negotiating multiple free-riding problems (cf. Barrett 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2003</a>). Although not directed towards OA specifically, several international legal regimes addressing the direct and indirect sources of OA are already in place. Global strategies for CO
   <sub>2</sub> mitigation arise from the UNFCCC and subsequent instruments, including the Kyoto Protocol and the recent Paris Agreement. Despite increasing knowledge about OA, the global climate regime contains no provisions explicitly aimed at or related to OA. This has triggered proposals for the elaboration of a specific international agreement focusing on combating OA (Kim 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2012</a>) or for at least highlighting OA as a problem separate from climate change within the present agreements (Herr et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2014</a>). These global-level agreements must be implemented in domestic (or in the case of the EU, regional) legal systems to directly affect the legal situation of individuals or companies. Implementation leaves significant discretion for individual states to choose instruments and methods that are consistent with their legal traditions and political preferences resulting in diverse rules and mechanisms subsequently employed in different jurisdictions.
  </p>
  <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Governments across the world, have proposed, developed, and implemented many pro-environmental policy measures in their attempts to overcome large-scale collective-action problems and, thus, to induce positive individual-level behavioural changes (Jordan 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2005</a>; Sterner and Coria 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">2012</a>; IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2014</a>). Rather than focusing on OA per se, relevant current literature is concerned with policy measures aimed at lowering CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions for the purpose of mitigating climate change.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regulatory, market-based and informative policy tools
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6" href="#Fn6">6</a>
  </div>
  <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, economic policy responses aim to alter incentive structures by directly addressing market failures (i.e. negative externalities, information deficits, public-goods provisions, etc.) that give rise to unwanted behavioural patterns. Typically, regulating CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions, or emissions of other GHG’s and pollutants, using economic policy instruments is done through quantity regulation (the amount that should be produced), price regulation (taxes), or mixed regulation (e.g. Cap and Trade; see Hepburn 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2006</a>). Such policies have been extensively studied in the context of climate change reduction, but, in principle, OA mitigation could be achieved by the same means. The use of CO
   <sub>2</sub> taxes is widely regarded as one of the most cost-effective means of limiting emissions and changing behaviour, and has been implemented in Sweden since 1991 with gradually increasing public support (Jagers and Hammar 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2009</a>; Jagers and Matti 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2010</a>). Similarly, taxes on the commercial use of fertilizers and pesticides as well as on (land-based) NO
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">x</span>
   </sub> and SO
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">x</span>
   </sub> emissions have been in place since the early 1990s.
  </p>
  <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other types of economic policy tools that currently are, or could be, directed towards reductions of emission include pull-instruments that subsidize more favourable alternatives. These can target the production of alternative energy sources (e.g. feed-in-tariffs for biofuels or other renewables) and consumer behaviour (e.g. eco-car subsidies) (Söderberg 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">2011</a>). Several such subsidies are already implemented in Sweden.
  </p>
  <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to regulations and market-based instruments, informative policy tools serve to highlight the problem aiming to initiate voluntary action and increase support for implementing more coercive policy tools. Informative policy tools can also decrease information asymmetries between different actors. Examples of information instruments include eco-labelling or certification schemes for products or technologies, and collection and disclosure of data on identified greenhouse gas emissions by significant polluters (Krarup and Russell 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2005</a>). Such types of policy can also trigger changes in social norms if the information can change the perception of large groups in society about what is accepted behaviour and what is not (Nyborg et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2016</a>). This is, however, complex as consumers have many different reasons for choosing an eco-labelled product, which are not always well correlated with information/knowledge about environmental impacts (Jagers et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2016</a>; Jonell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2016</a>). Nonetheless, as research demonstrates that people are largely unaware of OA and its potential consequences (Leiserowitz et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2010</a>; Frisch et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2015</a>; Capstick et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2016</a>), and people in general are unsupportive of solutions to unfamiliar problems (e.g. Stern et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">1995</a>), better information on OA is a potentially important tool to legitimizing mitigation policies.
  </p>
  <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second aspect of information relates to appropriate provision of research for understanding the mechanisms underlying OA and its impacts. Identifying what levels of OA might be acceptable would require assessing all the trade-offs between valuable economic activities that generate OA (i.e. CO
   <sub>2</sub>), the harm to society caused by the resulting increase in OA but also the economic values and losses arising from activities that amplify the negative effects of OA. Consequently, the optimal price of CO
   <sub>2</sub> to society cannot be calculated, making it difficult to calibrate any policy instrument targeting OA in Sweden. This task is currently intractable given the relatively low levels of knowledge in particular about the impacts of OA. More knowledge is needed about the problem and its causes and about ways of targeting the problem (Armstrong et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>; Turley and Gattuso 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2012</a>; Brander et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>). As with OA mitigation, however, research is a public good, which necessitates governmental intervention.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
