<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Causes of ocean acidification</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> suggests that the human behaviours of multiple types of actors who undertake multiple kinds of activities impact the environment via anthropogenic stressors that influence OA. Many types of human behaviours are currently contributing to the undesirably increasing levels of OA via CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, from local to global levels, and in sectors as diverse as the production of transport, energy, heating, and food. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> illustrates the main sectors of activity that generate CO
  <sub>2</sub>: land-use change; deforestation (increases albedo, but releases CO
  <sub>2</sub>, and reduces CO
  <sub>2</sub> capture creating changes in the “land sink”); and burning fossil fuel and other industries. The extents to which different activities contribute to acidification, however, vary rather substantially between different geographical locales. For example, in a Swedish context, burning fossil fuel and other industries are likely to have a much larger impact than land-use change, while deforestation is probably not relevant at least on average. In the Baltic Sea, emissions from shipping play an increasing role. On the US east-coast, as well as in southern Australia, pollutants and soil erosion are suggested as significant contributors to create acidification hot spots (Kelly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>). In addition, some other actors may also affect the impacts of OA via interacting stressors (e.g. eutrophication, wastewater discharge, fishing, and varying degrees of water salinity). Finally, some other actors also contribute at multiple scales to make marine ecosystems more vulnerable to the impacts of OA. This is a broader context of issues that we do not discuss here.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Formal and informal institutions form social restrictions to human actions. For example, the market price of fish may influence how much fish people can afford to buy, sell and produce. In contrast, preferences and tastes not only constitute individual restrictions, but they also influence whether people prefer to buy fish or some other type of food. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> illustrates how both kinds of restrictions provide incentives that steer human action in a direction that can influence the level of OA and its impacts. Hence, if the formal and informal institutions fail to provide the right incentives, the resulting outcome is likely to be an undesirable level of OA because many of the sources of CO
  <sub>2</sub> can increase in uncontrolled ways. The literature (e.g. Hepburn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2006</a>) provides substantial evidence that spurious incentives typically result from failures in the formal institutions either through market failure or governance failure. Successful societal responses to OA therefore require addressing both market failure (“
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Market failure</a>” section) and governance failure (“
  <a rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec8">Governance failure</a>” section), which we are going to explain here.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Market failure</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local, national and international markets
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2" href="#Fn2">2</a> provide places of exchange for goods such as meat, fish, dairy products, wood products or public transportation, and thus influence the supply and demand for these goods and hence the way they are produced (i.e. use of energy, land-use, industrial activities), which also impacts emissions of CO
   <sub>2</sub>. For example, global markets for fossil fuels and air transportation affect CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions directly and substantially. Many goods and services traded in markets (e.g. cement) also generate CO
   <sub>2</sub> as a by-product and thus contribute indirectly to the increasing levels of OA. While the economic literature on market failures in general is extensive, the results devoted specifically to OA are rare in this discipline, and a search for key word “ocean acidification” in the database ECONLIT (21 March 2018) returned only 18 publications, most of them focusing on impacts rather than causes, with a few exceptions (Fauville et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2011</a>; Harrould-Kolieb and Herr 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2011</a>; Galaz et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2012</a>; Miller et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In theory, markets with perfect competition
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3" href="#Fn3">3</a> could deliver—and allocate in time and space—the amount of OA 
   <span class="italic">optimally</span> for the long-term global well-being of human society. The level of OA would be 
   <span class="italic">optimal</span> in the sense that any other level or allocation of OA could only improve the situation for anyone if someone else was made worse off (Arrow 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">1951</a>; Arrow and Debreu 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">1954</a>). Hence, economic theory would suggest that levels of OA greater than would be 
   <span class="italic">optimal</span> for society are essentially due to multiple kinds of market failures
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4" href="#Fn4">4</a> when perfect competition cannot be achieved. Four kinds of market failure seem particularly pervasive in the case of OA. We describe them individually although they typically occur simultaneously.
   <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5" href="#Fn5">5</a>
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Negative externality</span> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a). Property rights to the seas are often ill defined (especially outside exclusive economic zones), and emissions of CO
   <sub>2</sub> have impacts far away from their sources. Hence, current CO
   <sub>2</sub>-emitting activities do not account for the true cost that these emissions generate to people not involved in the market transaction. National policies could provide incentives to internalize the cost of carbon. However, in order to account for the true costs of carbon on global warming, these must also be globally coordinated, address all sources of carbon, and account for climate change including warming 
   <span class="italic">and</span> other changes due to CO
   <sub>2</sub> including acidification effects related to carbon discussed here (Turley and Gattuso 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2012</a>; de Campos Rodrigues 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2016</a>), but also other effects like hypoxia. Sweden has already in place a substantial set of carbon taxes. Meanwhile these do not cover all emitting industries, they are not globally coordinated and do not account for OA (Sterner and Coria 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">2012</a>).
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Four market failures causing excessive OA: 
      <span class="bold">a</span> the market does not account for all the cost associated with emitting CO
      <sub>2</sub>; 
      <span class="bold">b</span> there is substantial lack of information about the impacts of OA, so market cost of CO
      <sub>2</sub> + OA impacts are represented by an area of potential location of that curve; 
      <span class="bold">c</span> reducing CO
      <sub>2</sub> emissions is a public good so individuals will not be willing to pay so much even though collectively they would benefit, and hence the market will not reduce emissions sufficiently if at all; 
      <span class="bold">d</span> “tipping points” may occur, such that multiple equilibria are possible for large levels of demand and the system may reach a suboptimal equilibrium. The blue curves represent market demand (marginal benefits, here downward sloping) and market supply (marginal costs, upward sloping), with or without cost of OA impacts. 
      <span class="italic">p</span>
      <sub>market</sub> and 
      <span class="italic">q</span>
      <sub>market</sub> denote, respectively, the price and quantity that will occur spontaneously on the market, while 
      <span class="italic">p</span>
      <sub>optimal</sub> and 
      <span class="italic">q</span>
      <sub>optimal</sub> denote, respectively, the price and quantity that would be optimal
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13280_2018_1103_Fig2_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Limited information on costs</span> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>b). Knowledge about the impacts of OA, and—in part—the processes that influence it, is limited and consequently OA-relevant decision-making must deal with substantial uncertainty (Polasky et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">2011</a>). Armstrong et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>) identified limitations of knowledge that complicate the economic evaluation of the impacts of OA while Brander et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>) refer to knowledge gaps (see Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). However, recent development (e.g. Seung et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">2015</a>; Colt and Knapp 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2016</a>; Narita and Rehdanz 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">2017</a>) indicates that progress is rapidly being made in that area.
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Areas of knowledge limitations and gaps with regard to the impacts of ocean acidification on society (Armstrong et al. 
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>; Brander et al. 
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>)
     </p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Armstrong et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>)
       </th>
       <th align="left">Brander et al. (
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>)
       </th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">
        <p>(i) effects of OA on ocean ecosystems (structures and functions)</p>
        <p>(ii) how OA affects/will affect ecosystem services from the sea</p>
        <p>(iii) economic values of those ecosystem services</p>
        <p>(iv) methodological limitations with regard to economic valuations of such services</p>
        <p>(v) only scant knowledge of human preferences for services from the ocean</p>
       </td>
       <td align="left">
        <p>(i) understanding the relation between changes in the marine environment and socioeconomic impacts</p>
        <p>(ii) the ecosystem services that have been assessed</p>
        <p>(iii) the distribution of impacts</p>
        <p>(iv) the vulnerability of different human populations</p>
       </td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Global public good</span> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>c). The capacity of the oceans to buffer the effects of OA, and the ability of marine ecosystems to adapt and function under changed pH, can both be seen as global public goods, in the sense that any effort by an individual to attain such buffering automatically benefits other individuals equally. Decentralized decision-making in markets generally lead to under-provision of public goods, since the parties generating the public good do not account for the positive effects imposed on others. This dimension of the problem is particularly complex for OA because causes and impacts span the entire planet, implying that no single country can unilaterally address it. Hence regulating the limitation of OA as a public good cannot be achieved unless countries cooperate to implement the agreed upon policy. Such regulation would require lump-sum financial transfers between individuals, which are practically difficult within a nation state, and even more doubtful in an international context (Sandmo 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2003</a>); this could, for example, imply that one country would have to compensate other countries that decrease their emissions.
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Tipping points</span> (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>d). Ecosystem responses to OA may be rapid, and at the same time influence evolutionary processes (Sunday et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">2011</a>). Hence, OA will involve both slow and fast processes, which may trigger rapid, substantial and persistent change—so-called 
   <span class="italic">regime shifts</span>—in marine ecosystems beyond some particular threshold level of OA also called tipping point (Scheffer et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">2001</a>; Casini et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2009</a>; Hughes et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2013</a>). Due to unique local environments, heterogeneity, biological adaptation, etc. these tipping points will typically differ in each single location. Several international initiatives aim to identify these changes (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.regimeshifts.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.regimeshifts.org</span>; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.resalliance.org/thresholds-db" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.resalliance.org/thresholds-db</span>). This implies that some management choices could be irreversible and that the effects of current levels of OA could impact current and future generations very differently. For example, in Sweden, Finland or the Baltic States, OA could interfere with tipping points in the Baltic Sea that trigger eutrophication (Gustafsson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2012</a>) and changes in marine food chains (Tomczak et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Governance failure</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">OA interacts with many drivers and outcomes, including climate change, marine biodiversity, and food security, therefore its ecological and social repercussions are embedded in a highly diffuse and complex institutional setting. Several actors and international institutions act in this problem domain, where poor political, administrative, and other institutional arrangements, results in slow progress (Galaz et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2012</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous research in the environmental social sciences has demonstrated that both the type of political institutions as well as the quality of these play an important role in countries’ environmental performance (Jagers 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2007</a>; Min 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">2015</a>; Povitkina 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">2018</a>). For example, democratic institutions tend to provide more public good than non-democratic alternatives (e.g. Lake and Baum 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">2001</a>; Bueno de Mesquita 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2003</a>; Acemoglu and Robinson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2006</a>), thus democratic institutions may have better conditions to cope with OA compared to non-democratic countries. However, even democratic institutions sometimes fail to provide public goods. Politicians focusing on re-election do not always benefit the public interest (Besley and Coate 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">1998</a>; Sterner et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2006</a>), as rational, vote-maximizing politicians are unlikely to introduce policies that they fear the electorate could dislike (Page and Shapiro 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">1983</a>; Stimson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">1995</a>; Burstein 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2003</a>). Elected leaders often work with short time horizons (Haggard 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">1991</a>; Sterner et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2006</a>; Keefer 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2007</a>), while mitigation of, and adaptation to, OA is a truly long-term undertaking. In addition, government policy interventions may result from multiple goals and prioritizations, sometimes contradictory. For example, policies focusing on energy provision or decentralization may even worsen OA if they promote cheap energy or subsidize transport activities that generate more acidification (Anthoff and Hahn 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2010</a>; Helm 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2010</a>). In addition, for both democratic and non-democratic states, the quality of government (e.g. degree of transparency, impartiality, and corruption) conditions the overall environmental performance (Lægreid and Povitkina 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2018</a>). A range of studies have demonstrated the necessity of an uncorrupted state for delivering environmental public goods (Weidner and Jänicke 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">2002</a>), a capable public administration in implementing environmental policies (Duit 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2016</a>), as well as the importance of rule of law (Fredriksson and Mani 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2002</a>) and the low level of corruption in securing environmental policy implementation (Pellegrini 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2011</a>; Sundström 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the policies surrounding OA are “characterized by the absence of multilateral agreements for policy coordination among states” (Dimitrov et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2007</a>, p. 231) and the Paris Agreement (2015) barely has improved this situation, a few state actors attempt to respond and prepare for the repercussions of OA. For example, states around the Coral Triangle (in the tropical waters of Indonesia, Malaysia, Papua New Guinea, Philippines, and others) collaborate in the region to improve food security and protect marine ecosystems at risk (Fidelman et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2012</a>; Rosen and Olsson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2012</a>), in 2015 the G7 countries issued a joint statement pointing towards the risks with OA, and the EU has funded several initiatives to better understand the causes and consequences of OA (cf. Osborne et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>). In addition, several international initiatives (led by non-governmental organizations and the United Nations agencies) exist to create awareness around the problem, synthesize and disseminate scientific information, and try to influence high-level negotiation arenas such as the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) and the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) (e.g. the Ocean Acidification International Coordination Centre: OA-ICC). Substantial outcomes from these processes, in terms of governmental action to implement concrete policies and policy tools with the capacity to generate behavioural change necessary to prevent OA in specific, are still largely unseen (Galaz et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2012</a>; Osborne et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
