<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses to ocean acidification</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With a few prominent exceptions (e.g. Pacala and Socolow 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2004</a>; Cooley and Doney 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>; Harrould-Kolieb and Herr 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2011</a>; Kelly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>; Rau et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">2012</a>; Billé et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>; Kelly and Caldwell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2013</a>; Colt and Knapp 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2016</a>; Narita and Rehdanz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">2017</a>), the majority of research on societal responses relevant to OA focuses explicitly on other factors that drive and/or threaten marine systems, notably the overarching concept of climate change. Nonetheless, research on environmental politics and policy (in particular with regards to global climate change) is also highly relevant to address OA, either because we can translate lessons from other empirical areas to fit the problem (e.g. administrative structures, multilateral cooperation, use of policy instruments, etc.), or because addressing one well-researched major problem (CO
  <sub>2</sub>-induced climate change) also directly affects OA. Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> provides an overview of possible responses to OA found in the social science literature.
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Broad categories of suggested responses to OA in the social science literature (e.g. Cooley and Doney 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>; Billé et al. 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Category of response</th>
      <th align="left">Target</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Mitigation of the main source of OA</td>
      <td align="left">Anthropogenic CO
       <sub>2</sub> emissions
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Mitigation of other greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions</td>
      <td align="left">NO
       <sub>
        <span class="italic">x</span>
       </sub> and SO
       <sub>
        <span class="italic">x</span>
       </sub> emissions
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Mitigation of other local/regional factors that contribute to (or compound the effect of) OA</td>
      <td align="left">Pollution, eutrophication (phosphor, nitrogen), biodiversity loss</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Adaptation of ecosystems and human activities that build resilience to OA</td>
      <td align="left">Reducing environmental stress through adjusted fishing quotas and fishery management plans (encouraging multispecies fishing), enhanced electrochemical weathering, increasing aquaculture, labour market adjustments (supporting job transitions from fishery/tourism), social support to local marine-resource-dependent communities in transition</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Restoration activity</td>
      <td align="left">Developing marine protected areas, enabling the survival of non-commercial species and the preservation of fundamental ecosystem functions and services, reintroduction of coral and marine plants, e.g. seagrasses</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We present the Swedish legal framework in place (“
  <a rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec10">The legal framework</a>” section) before we address more specifically mitigation (“
  <a rid="Sec11" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec11">Mitigation</a>” section) and adaptation efforts (“
  <a rid="Sec14" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec14">Adaptation</a>” section).
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The legal framework</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most prominent governmental instrument used for achieving behavioural change is law; at the international level predominantly as a means to agree on and coordinate action by multiple (state) actors, at the national (and partly EU) level, as a more direct instrument for inducing or forcing behavioural change among individuals and corporations. In the field of environmental protection, legal measures provide the basis both for what is often referred to as ‘command and control’ measures (e.g. technology requirements, emission limits, etc.) and for market-based instruments (e.g. cap and trade schemes).</p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multiple legal policy tools targeting CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions are already in place at the regional, national and subnational levels. They are not designed to address OA specifically, but can be marginally adapted to do so (Billé et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>). The main source of OA—CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions—is subject to international agreements, notably the Paris Agreement committing states to make recurring and increasingly ambitious undertakings and implement them in the form of affective measures. Various measures aiming to affect the behaviour of business and industry in relation to CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions are prescribed by EU law. In a similar way, the Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution (CLRTAP) and several EU legal acts regulate emissions of other important stressors that compound the effects of OA (emissions of SO
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">x</span>
   </sub> and NO
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">x</span>
   </sub>, and eutrophication caused by release of nitrates and phosphates into water). Further, several legal instruments have been developed with the primary, or secondary, aim to protect the marine environment. See Table 
   <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a> for overviews. All major EU measures in these areas take the form of directives rather than directly applicable regulations, so member states must transpose them into binding measures at the national level (e.g. Langlet and Mahmoudi 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2016</a>; Lindegarth et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">2016</a>). This transposition generally results in significant variations between member states as to how the EU measures are applied and, in some cases, with respect to how the EU requirements are construed or interpreted.
   <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>EU directives relevant to OA</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Directive numbers</th>
       <th align="left">Area of regulation covered</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2003/87/EC</td>
       <td align="left">Emission trading scheme</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2009/28/EC</td>
       <td align="left">Measures for the promotion of energy from renewable sources</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2012/27/EU</td>
       <td align="left">energy efficiency</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2008/50/EC</td>
       <td align="left">Ambient Air Quality</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2008/50/EC</td>
       <td align="left">National Emission Ceilings</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2016/2284/EU</td>
       <td align="left">Reduction of national emissions of certain atmospheric pollutants</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2000/60/EC</td>
       <td align="left">Water Framework</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">2008/56/EC</td>
       <td align="left">Marine Strategy Framework</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">91/676/EEC</td>
       <td align="left">Nitrates (targets water pollution related to nitrates from agricultural sources)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">91/271/EEC</td>
       <td align="left">Urban Waste Water</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taking Sweden as an example, relevant EU directives are implemented inter alia through the Act (2004:1199) on emission trading, the Air Quality Ordinance (SFS 2010:477), and the Environmental Code (SFS 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1998</a>, p. 808). The Environmental code and associated legislation also include various rules for the agriculture sector, targeting eutrophication. The national and local levels have, at least formally speaking, significant possibilities to regulate nutrient leakage through measures pertaining to land use. OA was mentioned briefly in preparatory works to legal acts relating to climate-change mitigation and to protection of the marine environment, without directly leading to specific measures and has received very little attention in the legal literature with a national or regional focus.
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing is one of the more prominent stressors that may compound the effects of OA. In contrast to OA, legal aspects of the management of fisheries have been more extensively discussed in the legal literature, both as regards international law and that of the EU, but again hardly ever with regard to how it may interact with OA (Churchill and Owen 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2009</a>; Christiernsson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2015</a>; Lado 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2016</a>). Within the EU, fisheries are mainly regulated under the EU’s common fisheries policy. There is some limited room for individual member states to regulate fishing in the vicinity of their own coast and conducted by their own fishing fleet (CFP Regulation (EU) No. 1380/2013; Christiernsson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2015</a>). Despite their local significance, these local powers cannot provide a system-level impact on the stressors relevant to OA. OA impacts on fishing have not yet affected decisions on fish quotas or other management measures. Marine protected areas may contribute to increase resilience in ecosystems subject to multiple stressors. They are partly regulated at the EU (e.g. through minimum requirements of protection as part of the Natura 2000 network, and through restrictions posed by EU fisheries policy) and partly at national levels. Typically, these decisions are not either influenced by concerns on OA. However, considerations of climate-change and OA impacts are beginning to be incorporated into the marine spatial planning efforts required by the EU law (Directive 2014/89/EU establishing a framework for maritime spatial planning).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigation</div>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigation strategies aim to treat the problem at its root by reducing its very causes. In the long term, limiting emissions of CO
   <sub>2</sub> to the atmosphere, and reducing the amount of CO
   <sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere (Billé et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>), are the only mitigation strategies available to comprehensively address OA (Pacala and Socolow 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2004</a>; Cooley and Doney 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>). Hence many (though not all, see Herr et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2014</a>) of the policies targeting climate change already in place will also mitigate OA. However, although increasing anthropogenic inputs via CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions drive acidification globally, local acidification is also the result of non-atmospheric stressors on the local level such as abiotic processes, eutrophication, hypoxia, upwelling events bringing low-pH water to near-shore areas, sulphur dioxide precipitation, and runoff from acidic fertilizers caused by agriculture, mineral extraction, and poor ecosystem management (cf. Kelly et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>). Therefore, mitigating OA requires concerted efforts on several levels—from the local to the global. On the one hand, 
   <span class="italic">global</span> mitigation strategies require a wide range of efforts on the global and international scale, several of which have already been initiated through multilateral cooperation such as the 2015 Paris Agreement (UNFCCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201" href="#CR201">2016</a>), the 1992 Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">1992</a>), and the 2013 Kiruna Declaration (AC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200" href="#CR200">2013</a>). On the other hand, multilateral processes are typically complex and politically contested, requiring the involvement of a range of different actors and therefore not “quick fixes” (Sterner et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2006</a>), partly due to the anarchic nature of the international political system (cf. Bäckstrand 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2006</a>). Indeed, as pointed out by Osborne et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>, p. 404) “the required actions to mitigate and adapt to ocean acidification have yet to be incorporated in international policy”. From this follows that short-term mitigation responses to OA (including both CO
   <sub>2</sub>-emissions and non-CO
   <sub>2</sub> stressors)—as well as the social science research on these matters—should rather focus on developing policy at the local and regional levels, where existing management structures and legal systems are more likely to effectively address these challenges (Cooley and Doney 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>; Kelly et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>; Cooley et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>). Also, internationally agreed measures almost invariably need to be translated into (legal) measures at the national or subnational level to have direct impact on the behaviour of individuals and firms, thereby further strengthening the case for paying attention to measures at these levels as well as the EU level where measures can have similar effects.
  </p>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although not overwhelming, some examples on such national and subnational efforts to both adapt to, and mitigate future OA problems, do exist in the more recent literature. One prominent example put forward on political responses to OA concerns the collapse of the oyster industry on the US west coast. This, in turn, sparked reactions on both the local level, building networks among researchers and stakeholders to monitor changes and disseminate information, as well as the state level of government, integrating OA into long-term state resource management plans (Osborne et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>). In Maine, on the US east-coast, a similar problem led to similar network-building reactions on the local and state levels, and a number of state bills addressing the problem with nutrient pollution from farms and septic systems have since been put forward (Cooley et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>). In addition, in the case of the US, it has been suggested to use the Federal Clean Water Act to limit OA-inducing pollutants as a national-level response to acidification, although its authority is limited to land-based point source pollutants (cf. Kelly et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2011</a>), and the adoption in the US of the Federal Ocean Acidification Research and Monitoring Act of 2009 are examples on national-level responses spurred by the increasing public attention to the OA problem (Osborne et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>). A range of examples on similar efforts to build knowledge, natural science research capacity, and political attention also exists outside the US: the Brazil OA Research Network (BROA), the Biological Impacts of OA Program (BIOACID) in Germany, and the United Kingdom’s Ocean Acidification Research Programme (UKOA) to name but a few (Cooley et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>). In parallel, also cross-national networks, such as the European Project on Ocean Acidification (EPOCA), and the MedSeA Project to study OA in the Mediterranean Sea funded by the European Commission have been launched during the past 10 years.
  </p>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> However, although these efforts have served to raise awareness and knowledge about the problem among policy makers, a next step in mitigating OA is the real-life design and implementation of concrete policy tools, capable of addressing practices and behaviours that contribute to the anthropogenic stressors for OA. This, however, presents policy makers with significant challenges as behavioural change is not easily governed. In these endeavours, social science research can and will play an important role, for example, in the designing of effective policy tools, simultaneously utilizing opportunities and negotiating barriers for successful policy development and implementation.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We discuss here the challenges of changing behaviour with policy tools and the rationale behind different types of policy tools.</p>
  <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changing behaviour with policy tools</div>
   <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> OA exhibits the characteristics of a classic collective-action problem: lack of cooperation among actors responsible for OA results in suboptimal outcomes for the collective (Olson 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">1965</a>). As Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>c illustrates, limiting CO
    <sub>2</sub>, and thus OA, will rarely be provided in sufficient quantity, (if at all), because of the difficulties of aggregating all actors’ willingness to pay for it. There is an imminent risk of free-riding arising regardless of whether or not the collective willingness-to-pay for an additional limitation of CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions is large (e.g. Ostrom 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">1990</a>). Significant voluntary behavioural changes are therefore unlikely among individuals. The same holds true regarding potential appropriate responses to the negative externalities, large uncertainties, and the risk of tipping points involved in OA (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a, b, d). Some form of intentional, third party coordination or 
    <span class="italic">governmental coercion</span> (Mansbridge 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2014</a>) is usually necessary to address market failures and initiate cooperation, especially when the number of involved actors is very large, dispersed over vast geographical areas, and therefore mostly anonymous to each other. Such governmental coercion usually takes the form of various policy tools aimed at changing the incentive structures governing behavioural choices, either by increasing the attractiveness of preferred behaviour or by exacerbating the negative impact of an undesired behavioural choice.
   </p>
   <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global nature of OA creates a need for global cooperation but the lack of a supranational authority and limited enforcement mechanisms at that scale suggest that legal measures to initiate multilateral cooperation must take the form of voluntary entered into agreements and treaties. Thus, this set-up is largely dependent on the will and the ability of individual states. This can be extremely tricky to achieve (see e.g. the recent withdrawal of the US from the Paris Agreement), in particular agreements of how costs and benefits should be distributed across national borders, and negotiating multiple free-riding problems (cf. Barrett 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2003</a>). Although not directed towards OA specifically, several international legal regimes addressing the direct and indirect sources of OA are already in place. Global strategies for CO
    <sub>2</sub> mitigation arise from the UNFCCC and subsequent instruments, including the Kyoto Protocol and the recent Paris Agreement. Despite increasing knowledge about OA, the global climate regime contains no provisions explicitly aimed at or related to OA. This has triggered proposals for the elaboration of a specific international agreement focusing on combating OA (Kim 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2012</a>) or for at least highlighting OA as a problem separate from climate change within the present agreements (Herr et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2014</a>). These global-level agreements must be implemented in domestic (or in the case of the EU, regional) legal systems to directly affect the legal situation of individuals or companies. Implementation leaves significant discretion for individual states to choose instruments and methods that are consistent with their legal traditions and political preferences resulting in diverse rules and mechanisms subsequently employed in different jurisdictions.
   </p>
   <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Governments across the world, have proposed, developed, and implemented many pro-environmental policy measures in their attempts to overcome large-scale collective-action problems and, thus, to induce positive individual-level behavioural changes (Jordan 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2005</a>; Sterner and Coria 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">2012</a>; IPCC 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2014</a>). Rather than focusing on OA per se, relevant current literature is concerned with policy measures aimed at lowering CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions for the purpose of mitigating climate change.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regulatory, market-based and informative policy tools
    <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6" href="#Fn6">6</a>
   </div>
   <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, economic policy responses aim to alter incentive structures by directly addressing market failures (i.e. negative externalities, information deficits, public-goods provisions, etc.) that give rise to unwanted behavioural patterns. Typically, regulating CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions, or emissions of other GHG’s and pollutants, using economic policy instruments is done through quantity regulation (the amount that should be produced), price regulation (taxes), or mixed regulation (e.g. Cap and Trade; see Hepburn 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2006</a>). Such policies have been extensively studied in the context of climate change reduction, but, in principle, OA mitigation could be achieved by the same means. The use of CO
    <sub>2</sub> taxes is widely regarded as one of the most cost-effective means of limiting emissions and changing behaviour, and has been implemented in Sweden since 1991 with gradually increasing public support (Jagers and Hammar 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2009</a>; Jagers and Matti 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2010</a>). Similarly, taxes on the commercial use of fertilizers and pesticides as well as on (land-based) NO
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">x</span>
    </sub> and SO
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">x</span>
    </sub> emissions have been in place since the early 1990s.
   </p>
   <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other types of economic policy tools that currently are, or could be, directed towards reductions of emission include pull-instruments that subsidize more favourable alternatives. These can target the production of alternative energy sources (e.g. feed-in-tariffs for biofuels or other renewables) and consumer behaviour (e.g. eco-car subsidies) (Söderberg 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">2011</a>). Several such subsidies are already implemented in Sweden.
   </p>
   <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to regulations and market-based instruments, informative policy tools serve to highlight the problem aiming to initiate voluntary action and increase support for implementing more coercive policy tools. Informative policy tools can also decrease information asymmetries between different actors. Examples of information instruments include eco-labelling or certification schemes for products or technologies, and collection and disclosure of data on identified greenhouse gas emissions by significant polluters (Krarup and Russell 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2005</a>). Such types of policy can also trigger changes in social norms if the information can change the perception of large groups in society about what is accepted behaviour and what is not (Nyborg et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2016</a>). This is, however, complex as consumers have many different reasons for choosing an eco-labelled product, which are not always well correlated with information/knowledge about environmental impacts (Jagers et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2016</a>; Jonell et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2016</a>). Nonetheless, as research demonstrates that people are largely unaware of OA and its potential consequences (Leiserowitz et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2010</a>; Frisch et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2015</a>; Capstick et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2016</a>), and people in general are unsupportive of solutions to unfamiliar problems (e.g. Stern et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">1995</a>), better information on OA is a potentially important tool to legitimizing mitigation policies.
   </p>
   <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second aspect of information relates to appropriate provision of research for understanding the mechanisms underlying OA and its impacts. Identifying what levels of OA might be acceptable would require assessing all the trade-offs between valuable economic activities that generate OA (i.e. CO
    <sub>2</sub>), the harm to society caused by the resulting increase in OA but also the economic values and losses arising from activities that amplify the negative effects of OA. Consequently, the optimal price of CO
    <sub>2</sub> to society cannot be calculated, making it difficult to calibrate any policy instrument targeting OA in Sweden. This task is currently intractable given the relatively low levels of knowledge in particular about the impacts of OA. More knowledge is needed about the problem and its causes and about ways of targeting the problem (Armstrong et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>; Turley and Gattuso 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2012</a>; Brander et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>). As with OA mitigation, however, research is a public good, which necessitates governmental intervention.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation</div>
  <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation strategies focus on treating the 
   <span class="italic">symptoms</span> of OA by adjusting natural or human systems such that damage is reduced, and/or beneficial opportunities taken advantage of (Adger et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2007</a>). Adaptation does not target the causes of the problem but rather aims to maintain social well-being in spite of OA. These types of strategy are likely to be easier to apply than mitigation strategies, especially in the short term, because symptoms of OA are problematic at local and regional levels where people can also address them (Cooley and Doney 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>). Hence adaptation usually requires less coordination effort than global mitigation policies, and those efforts are typically located at the local and regional level where relevant national institutions are usually already in place. Nonetheless, practical examples of OA adaptation remain scarce, and the barriers to negotiate are in many ways the same as those for mitigation strategies, including collective-action problems and information deficits. Three broad types of adaptation strategy can be identified, spanning structural–physical, social, and institutional adaptation. All of these require further government policies and programmes to be initiated and funded (IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2014</a>). In addition to the main strategies outlined in this section, broader adaptation potential can be increased through capacity-building activities such as infrastructural improvements, increasing institutional capacity, information, and access to resources (Smit et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">2001</a>).
  </p>
  <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strategies to reduce the negative impacts of acidification on marine ecosystems</div>
   <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystem resilience to OA can be strengthened in the short term by alleviating pressure from other stressors, e.g. by reducing the rate and magnitude of eutrophication, pollution, and fishing. Ecosystems with higher diversity are more resilient to other forms of environmental stress, including OA as available data suggests. Hence, ecological restoration may be a particularly valuable tool in maintaining/increasing diversity and thereby increasing resilience to OA (Worm et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" href="#CR109">2006</a>), implying synergies with efforts to conserve or restore biodiversity (e.g. CBD 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">1992</a>). As long as ecosystems remain within critical thresholds, human activities such as fisheries and aquaculture can adapt to change. For example, the effects of OA and warming on shallow seagrass ecosystems are similar to the effects of eutrophication and increased fishing pressure (Alsterberg et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2013</a>); thus, reducing eutrophication and fishing pressure may (in the short term) directly offset the effects of OA and warming. Furthermore, counteracting OA by alkalinization may be useful in hotspots such as coastal environments but seems to have very limited potential and feasibility at larger scales (e.g. Billé et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>; Weatherdon et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" href="#CR107">2015</a>). In two recent publications, Osborne et al. (
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>) as well as Cooley et al. (
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>) outline further adaptation strategies.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strategies to adapt the way society organizes</div>
   <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The impacts of OA are likely to affect ecosystem services produced in the oceans. Turley and Gattuso (
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2012</a>) list broad categories of OA impacts on these services including fisheries, aquaculture and food security, coastal protection, tourism, climate regulation, and carbon storage. OA may strengthen some services and reduce others. Negatively affected provisioning services (e.g. landings of fish for human consumption) will likely lead to price increases and impact on food security. A key question is then to what degree those fish may be substituted? For example, fish can become relatively more expensive than other sources of protein and market forces will then automatically steer the economy towards less dependence on fish. This may, however, increase production of substitutes like land animals that can generate higher release of CO
    <sub>2</sub> compared to fish, thus further adding to climate change and OA.
   </p>
   <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If such transition processes are slow and costly, progress may be accelerated by: (i) compensating losers (e.g. fishermen), (ii) providing transitional support, and/or (iii) stimulating innovation to accelerate emergence of alternatives and technical replacement solutions. However, substitutes for the goods or services damaged by OA may not always be available (e.g. loss of fisheries and tourism income due to degradation of high diversity coral reef systems; Worm et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" href="#CR109">2006</a>). Hence, societal priorities will be forced to target less-damaged (or undamaged) goods and services. In the extreme case when life-support systems are affected and no substitute is available, this could have catastrophic impacts on human well-being (although such impacts are perhaps unlikely to arise from OA). This is true even if the absence of substitutes is temporary. These types of response can be deployed either by individual countries or through multilateral cooperation.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strategies to compensate people who lose from ocean acidification</div>
   <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in the provision of marine ecosystem services arising from OA will likely generate redistributions of resources between user groups. For example, the different responses of two Arctic fishing communities to the disappearance of north-west Atlantic cod stocks led to two very different outcomes—one community lost substantially while the other was able to target other species and increased income (McCain et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2016</a>). The opportunity for such responses may, however, be limited if OA has negative impacts on most fish species. Viable adaptation strategies include compensation to disadvantaged groups, and/or helping them adapt to the new situation by stimulating education, investment, etc. However, avoiding the establishment of spurious incentives that effectively reward some sections of society for not managing the change is vital, and therefore such strategies should be transitional (Dixit and Londregan 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1995</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
