<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current emissions of anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) generate increasing temperatures, changing weather patterns, shrinking ice-sheets, a poleward shift of marine species ranges (Doney et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2012</a>; García Molinos et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">2016</a>), and an increase in the amount of CO
  <sub>2</sub> dissolved in the oceans leading to lower ocean pH—a process known as ocean acidification (OA).
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1" href="#Fn1">1</a> Anthropogenic OA occurs when increasing concentrations of atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> dissolve in the surface water to form carbonic acid. OA is identified as a global environmental problem in the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goal 14.3, and has been classified as one of the nine planetary boundaries of importance for regulating the stability of the Earth’s system (Rockström et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2009</a>). It is a global issue as its cause is the rising amounts of CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the almost perfectly mixed atmosphere, even though emission patterns differ locally. The effects of OA are geographically highly heterogeneous and uncertain (Steffen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">2015</a>). Although the understanding of the natural science processes underpinning OA, and consequences thereof, is continuously improving (Doney et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2012</a>; Cooley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>; Gaylord et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2015</a>; Riebesell and Gattuso 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">2015</a>; Osborne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>), there is a general lack of understanding and public debate on the societal causes and policy options in most countries in relation to OA. This lack of understanding critically affects the ability to project—and adapt to—the likely effects of these changes on important ecosystem services provided by the seas, e.g. fisheries, coastal protection, nutrient recycling, recreation, and tourism. Hence contributions to increasing OA, and the measures taken to reduce acidification or to alleviate its societal consequences, vary considerably between contexts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> illustrates how OA interacts with the tight connections between society and the natural environment. Existing formal and informal institutions create incentive structures that frame and limit the preferences and actions of individuals. People’s actions affect the natural environment in various ways, for example, increasing levels of CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere. Further, the resulting OA risks affecting society by changing ecosystem structure and functions and hence influencing the services that these ecosystems produce.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic representation of ocean acidification, focus of this paper in grey. (Author names withheld) Focuses on the remaining parts</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2018_1103_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This interdisciplinary review therefore targets the societal aspects of OA, primarily, legal, political, and economic aspects. It forms a complementary contribution to the growing literature which focuses on the environmental impacts of OA, and to which we refer for more details on these aspects (e.g. Doney et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2009</a>; Hönisch et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2012</a>; Riebesell and Gattuso 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">2015</a>; Osborne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>). We summarize current knowledge about major anthropogenic causes of OA, and what the social sciences have pointed out as needed primary responses to mitigate these causes and alleviate OA’s direct and indirect consequences. Three questions have guided our joint efforts:
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par15">(Q1) What are the primary causes of anthropogenic ocean acidification from a social science perspective?</p>
   <p id="Par16">(Q2) How can society and politics respond to ocean acidification?</p>
   <p id="Par17">(Q3) What are the major knowledge gaps and research needs in the social sciences with regard to the future study of OA?</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite its potentially severe negative implications for nature and society, the acidification of our coastal and ocean waters is seldom highlighted in media, public debate, or within national environmental politics, although a number of efforts to bring OA into the spotlight of political attention have been made during the past decade (see “
  <a rid="Sec9" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec9">Responses to ocean acidification</a>” section). In studies emanating from the natural sciences, practical examples on initiatives at both international and subnational levels to address OA problems can indeed be found (cf. Cooley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2015</a>; Osborne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2017</a>), but these do not, naturally, engage with the possible contributions of social science research on these matters. The efforts to increase awareness and scientific knowledge notwithstanding, researches on possible political and policy responses in the current social science literature are few and far between. For example, Armstrong et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>) claim that OA has generated very few economic or social science studies in any country, despite the fact that the few studies that 
  <span class="italic">have</span> been conducted anticipate significant negative impacts on fisheries (Cooley and Doney 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>; Narita et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">2012</a>), coral habitats (Brander et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2012</a>), and marine ecosystem services (Turley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">2010</a>). An important and ambititious aim with this review is thus to highlight and help recognize OA as a key issue among disciplines conducting social environmental studies and also to outline potential avenues for future research in the social sciences. By highlighting the major knowledge gaps in the current literature, and suggesting avenues for moving forward, this article thereby hopes to encourage social science research to further engage with this highly relevant and topical problem.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the following sections of this paper, we review the literature on societal causes to OA (“
  <a rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec2">Causes of ocean acidification</a>” section); the legal, economic and political contexts, and possible mitigation as well as adaptation responses and challenges (“
  <a rid="Sec9" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec9">Responses to ocean acidification</a>” section), and we provide concluding remarks including a number of research gaps (“
  <a rid="Sec18" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec18">Concluding remarks and research needs</a>” section).
 </p>
</sec>
