<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regulatory, market-based and informative policy tools
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6" href="#Fn6">6</a>
 </div>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, economic policy responses aim to alter incentive structures by directly addressing market failures (i.e. negative externalities, information deficits, public-goods provisions, etc.) that give rise to unwanted behavioural patterns. Typically, regulating CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, or emissions of other GHG’s and pollutants, using economic policy instruments is done through quantity regulation (the amount that should be produced), price regulation (taxes), or mixed regulation (e.g. Cap and Trade; see Hepburn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2006</a>). Such policies have been extensively studied in the context of climate change reduction, but, in principle, OA mitigation could be achieved by the same means. The use of CO
  <sub>2</sub> taxes is widely regarded as one of the most cost-effective means of limiting emissions and changing behaviour, and has been implemented in Sweden since 1991 with gradually increasing public support (Jagers and Hammar 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2009</a>; Jagers and Matti 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2010</a>). Similarly, taxes on the commercial use of fertilizers and pesticides as well as on (land-based) NO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub> and SO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub> emissions have been in place since the early 1990s.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other types of economic policy tools that currently are, or could be, directed towards reductions of emission include pull-instruments that subsidize more favourable alternatives. These can target the production of alternative energy sources (e.g. feed-in-tariffs for biofuels or other renewables) and consumer behaviour (e.g. eco-car subsidies) (Söderberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">2011</a>). Several such subsidies are already implemented in Sweden.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to regulations and market-based instruments, informative policy tools serve to highlight the problem aiming to initiate voluntary action and increase support for implementing more coercive policy tools. Informative policy tools can also decrease information asymmetries between different actors. Examples of information instruments include eco-labelling or certification schemes for products or technologies, and collection and disclosure of data on identified greenhouse gas emissions by significant polluters (Krarup and Russell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2005</a>). Such types of policy can also trigger changes in social norms if the information can change the perception of large groups in society about what is accepted behaviour and what is not (Nyborg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2016</a>). This is, however, complex as consumers have many different reasons for choosing an eco-labelled product, which are not always well correlated with information/knowledge about environmental impacts (Jagers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2016</a>; Jonell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2016</a>). Nonetheless, as research demonstrates that people are largely unaware of OA and its potential consequences (Leiserowitz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2010</a>; Frisch et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2015</a>; Capstick et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2016</a>), and people in general are unsupportive of solutions to unfamiliar problems (e.g. Stern et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">1995</a>), better information on OA is a potentially important tool to legitimizing mitigation policies.
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second aspect of information relates to appropriate provision of research for understanding the mechanisms underlying OA and its impacts. Identifying what levels of OA might be acceptable would require assessing all the trade-offs between valuable economic activities that generate OA (i.e. CO
  <sub>2</sub>), the harm to society caused by the resulting increase in OA but also the economic values and losses arising from activities that amplify the negative effects of OA. Consequently, the optimal price of CO
  <sub>2</sub> to society cannot be calculated, making it difficult to calibrate any policy instrument targeting OA in Sweden. This task is currently intractable given the relatively low levels of knowledge in particular about the impacts of OA. More knowledge is needed about the problem and its causes and about ways of targeting the problem (Armstrong et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2012</a>; Turley and Gattuso 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">2012</a>; Brander et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>). As with OA mitigation, however, research is a public good, which necessitates governmental intervention.
 </p>
</sec>
