<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The legal framework</div>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most prominent governmental instrument used for achieving behavioural change is law; at the international level predominantly as a means to agree on and coordinate action by multiple (state) actors, at the national (and partly EU) level, as a more direct instrument for inducing or forcing behavioural change among individuals and corporations. In the field of environmental protection, legal measures provide the basis both for what is often referred to as ‘command and control’ measures (e.g. technology requirements, emission limits, etc.) and for market-based instruments (e.g. cap and trade schemes).</p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multiple legal policy tools targeting CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions are already in place at the regional, national and subnational levels. They are not designed to address OA specifically, but can be marginally adapted to do so (Billé et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2013</a>). The main source of OA—CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions—is subject to international agreements, notably the Paris Agreement committing states to make recurring and increasingly ambitious undertakings and implement them in the form of affective measures. Various measures aiming to affect the behaviour of business and industry in relation to CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions are prescribed by EU law. In a similar way, the Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution (CLRTAP) and several EU legal acts regulate emissions of other important stressors that compound the effects of OA (emissions of SO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub> and NO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub>, and eutrophication caused by release of nitrates and phosphates into water). Further, several legal instruments have been developed with the primary, or secondary, aim to protect the marine environment. See Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a> for overviews. All major EU measures in these areas take the form of directives rather than directly applicable regulations, so member states must transpose them into binding measures at the national level (e.g. Langlet and Mahmoudi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2016</a>; Lindegarth et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">2016</a>). This transposition generally results in significant variations between member states as to how the EU measures are applied and, in some cases, with respect to how the EU requirements are construed or interpreted.
  <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>EU directives relevant to OA</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Directive numbers</th>
      <th align="left">Area of regulation covered</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2003/87/EC</td>
      <td align="left">Emission trading scheme</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2009/28/EC</td>
      <td align="left">Measures for the promotion of energy from renewable sources</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2012/27/EU</td>
      <td align="left">energy efficiency</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2008/50/EC</td>
      <td align="left">Ambient Air Quality</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2008/50/EC</td>
      <td align="left">National Emission Ceilings</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2016/2284/EU</td>
      <td align="left">Reduction of national emissions of certain atmospheric pollutants</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2000/60/EC</td>
      <td align="left">Water Framework</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">2008/56/EC</td>
      <td align="left">Marine Strategy Framework</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">91/676/EEC</td>
      <td align="left">Nitrates (targets water pollution related to nitrates from agricultural sources)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">91/271/EEC</td>
      <td align="left">Urban Waste Water</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taking Sweden as an example, relevant EU directives are implemented inter alia through the Act (2004:1199) on emission trading, the Air Quality Ordinance (SFS 2010:477), and the Environmental Code (SFS 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1998</a>, p. 808). The Environmental code and associated legislation also include various rules for the agriculture sector, targeting eutrophication. The national and local levels have, at least formally speaking, significant possibilities to regulate nutrient leakage through measures pertaining to land use. OA was mentioned briefly in preparatory works to legal acts relating to climate-change mitigation and to protection of the marine environment, without directly leading to specific measures and has received very little attention in the legal literature with a national or regional focus.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing is one of the more prominent stressors that may compound the effects of OA. In contrast to OA, legal aspects of the management of fisheries have been more extensively discussed in the legal literature, both as regards international law and that of the EU, but again hardly ever with regard to how it may interact with OA (Churchill and Owen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2009</a>; Christiernsson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2015</a>; Lado 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2016</a>). Within the EU, fisheries are mainly regulated under the EU’s common fisheries policy. There is some limited room for individual member states to regulate fishing in the vicinity of their own coast and conducted by their own fishing fleet (CFP Regulation (EU) No. 1380/2013; Christiernsson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2015</a>). Despite their local significance, these local powers cannot provide a system-level impact on the stressors relevant to OA. OA impacts on fishing have not yet affected decisions on fish quotas or other management measures. Marine protected areas may contribute to increase resilience in ecosystems subject to multiple stressors. They are partly regulated at the EU (e.g. through minimum requirements of protection as part of the Natura 2000 network, and through restrictions posed by EU fisheries policy) and partly at national levels. Typically, these decisions are not either influenced by concerns on OA. However, considerations of climate-change and OA impacts are beginning to be incorporated into the marine spatial planning efforts required by the EU law (Directive 2014/89/EU establishing a framework for maritime spatial planning).
 </p>
</sec>
