<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To build a correlative statistical model of the influence of climate on adult fertility (
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>; the proportion of individuals that are reproductively active in a given age class during a given year), we fit a binary logistic regression model using mean annual temperature and annual precipitation for each year from 1996–2008 to Hayes’ female reproductive success data for fringed myotis in Boulder County, Colorado [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], using U.S. National Oceanic &amp; Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Earth System Research Laboratory mean annual temperature and annual precipitation data for Boulder, Colorado (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/</ext-link>). In this model we used the annual mean temperature (°C) for a given year using the NOAA data from the same reference period (1986–2005) as used by the NCAR-UCAR CCSM4 future climate models (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180693.t001" class="xref">Table 1</xref>; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gisclimatechange.ucar.edu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://gisclimatechange.ucar.edu/</ext-link>). The mean annual temperature for this reference period for Boulder, Colorado was 10.85°C. We likewise used the annual precipitation for a given year (reference period mean = 541 mm), also using the NOAA data. We fit a binary logistic response function [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] for the female reproductive data from our study area: 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0180693.e002" class="disp-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0180693.e002.jpg" id="pone.0180693.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M2" class="math">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Pr</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">{</mo>
     <mi class="mi">Y</mi>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mn class="mn">1</mn>
     <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">}</mo>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msup class="msup">
        <mi class="mi">e</mi>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <msub class="msub">
          <mi class="mi">β</mi>
          <mn class="mn">0</mn>
         </msub>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <msub class="msub">
          <mi class="mi">β</mi>
          <mi class="mi">T</mi>
         </msub>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">(</mo>
         <mi class="mi">T</mi>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">)</mo>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <msub class="msub">
          <mi class="mi">β</mi>
          <mi class="mi">P</mi>
         </msub>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">(</mo>
         <mi class="mi">P</mi>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">)</mo>
        </mrow>
       </msup>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mn class="mn">1</mn>
       <mo class="mo">+</mo>
       <msup class="msup">
        <mi class="mi">e</mi>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <msub class="msub">
          <mi class="mi">β</mi>
          <mn class="mn">0</mn>
         </msub>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <msub class="msub">
          <mi class="mi">β</mi>
          <mi class="mi">T</mi>
         </msub>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">(</mo>
         <mi class="mi">T</mi>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">)</mo>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <msub class="msub">
          <mi class="mi">β</mi>
          <mi class="mi">P</mi>
         </msub>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">(</mo>
         <mi class="mi">P</mi>
         <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">)</mo>
        </mrow>
       </msup>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
    <mo class="mo">,</mo>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula> where Pr{
 <italic class="italic">Y</italic> = 1} is the predicted mean probability of adult females in a given age class being reproductively active given the temperature (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>) and precipitation (
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>) conditions for a given year, and the 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>’s are beta estimates for the logit model. We considered both annual temperature and annual precipitation to be highly plausible abiotic covariates, which were not highly correlated [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]; on the other hand, we recognized that the factors influencing fertility for a given age class likely involve a complex suite of abiotic and biotic factors that are not likely to be fully captured by this simplifying model, and that no future climate model is yet capable of capturing these covariates. Thus, we emphasize that the logistic model used here and the simulation results presented are only used as first approximation models [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] to evaluate the conjecture that a changing climate might have non-trivial impacts on some simulated bat populations. To build a dataset for the logistic fertility model, we used the data related to adult female fringed myotis captured or collected in Boulder County, Colorado, for 1996–2008 compiled by Hayes (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] for a full list). We used data in which the biologist or collector listed the following information: the species; that the sex of the individual was female; that the individual was an adult; and that the reproductive status of the adult female individual was evaluated and determined as non-reproductive, pregnant, lactating, or post-lactating; if the reproductive status of the bat was listed as unknown or not listed, the information from that record was not used in the analysis. Early in the reproductive season (for example in May and early June) it can be difficult to identify whether individuals are pregnant. Similarly, it can be difficult to identify if a female is post-lactating in the late summer. Therefore, we restricted the data set to those records collected by a biologist or collector who we expected had the knowledge, skills, and experience to accurately identify the species, sex, age, and reproductive condition of individual bats in the Southern Rockies. The Boulder study area for this analysis was within the Southern Rockies ecoregion and includes foothills shrublands and mid-elevation forests, and is within the South Platte River basin.
</p>
