<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We developed and ran 13 Monte Carlo simulations for fringed myotis populations in western North America using the age-structured population model as follows. We used a Stable Model, which assumed that vital rates in our study area in Boulder County, Colorado, will stay approximately at or near initial values through year 2086. We used 4 Boulder Models with yearly mean annual temperature and annual precipitation values projected by each of the 4 emission scenarios (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, RCP8.5) using the NCAR-UCAR future climate models for each year from 2009–2086. The RCP2.6 emissions scenario assumes the least change in carbon emissions from historic levels and the RCP8.5 scenario assumes the largest increase in carbon emissions. We also used 4 Boulder Ensemble Models with averaged projections for mean annual temperature and annual precipitation values for year 2070 derived from the mean projection of 11 future climate models (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180693.t001" class="xref">Table 1</xref>); we used the year 2070 climate values to estimate fertility rates for this year and then projected values for each year between 2009–2069 and 2071–2086 for each of the 4 emission scenarios using a step function such that each year including 2070 represented an equivalent change in adult fertility. Finally, we used 4 General Models with projected mean annual temperature and annual precipitation values for year 2070 for each of the &gt;2,000 fringed myotis occurrence locations in the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.gbif.org</ext-link>) dataset, and with the mean fertility rate prediction for all locations in 2070 using the same logistic model as used for the Boulder Models; for each year between 2009–2069 and 2071–2086 we calculated fertility rates using a step function such that each year including 2070 represented an equivalent change in adult fertility in the same way as for the Boulder Ensemble Models. In this analysis we focused on the influence of fertility rates (
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>) on population dynamics and assumed that survival rates were not substantially affected by climate conditions, and the sex ratio of newborns was at parity in all years. These are simplifying assumptions for this analysis. To calculate fertility rates for the General Models, for each occurrence location we extracted the mean annual temperature and annual precipitation projection for years 1950–2000. We then used the temperature and precipitation projections for each location for year 2070 using each of the 11 future climate models, and used these projections to calculate a grand ensemble mean fertility projection for all locations (future climate data available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</ext-link>; 10 minute data). By combining climate information for pooled range-wide occurrence locations, the General Models represent ensemble simulations of the potential influence of changing climate conditions on a hypothetical fringed myotis population in western North America, whose mean fertility rates are equal to the mean fertility rates for the occurrence records in the GBIF dataset. Each Monte Carlo simulation consisted of 10,000 runs of 77 years representing years 2009 to 2086. For each Monte Carlo simulation we calculated the mean of the 10,000 final populations in year 2086, the percent change in the mean population from the original 2,000 females (% change), the minimum population size, the maximum population size, and the standard deviation of the populations. As a final step we created maps of fringed myotis occurrence locations in western North America and mapped the change (Δ
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>) in estimated fertility rate (
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>) for each cell (with each cell 10 minutes of a degree) using future climate projections derived from the General Ensemble Model projections for year 2070 using the four representative concentration pathways (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, RCP8.5). We considered using a finer-scale resolution, such as ~1 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, but concluded that the courser resolution used here reflects a scale that is closer to the home range of a fringed myotis [
 <xref rid="pone.0180693.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. We also concluded that this resolution is appropriate for considering the influences of a changing climate on the landscapes used by individual bats over the course of a year. The map indicates the mean predicted change in fertility derived from the 11 future climate models when comparing mean values for 1950–2000 climate to year 2070 projections for the ensemble models. We also calculated mean change (
 <inline-formula id="pone.0180693.e003" class="inline-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0180693.e003.jpg" id="pone.0180693.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M3" class="math">
    <mover accent="true" class="mover">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</mi>
     <mo class="mo">¯</mo>
    </mover>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula>) in fertility rates for all fringed myotis locations used.
</p>
