<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We assumed a hypothetical ecological community of 50 species and tracked annual population change over a 20-year period. The abundance changes of each species over the years were affected by two species attributes: their temperature preference and their habitat breadth. Species’ temperature preferences and habitat breadths were drawn from random normal distributions with the same mean and variance. Species with warmer temperature preferences were assumed to have more positive population growth as a result of climate change. Species with broader habitat breadths were assumed to have more positive population growth as a result of being more tolerant to land use change. We ran three sets of simulation models. In the first set, only temperature preference affected species population growth, and these communities were used to calculate the “true CTI”. We regard this as the true CTI because it the CTI that results when only temperature preference, and hence climate change, affects the dynamics (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0184275.s006" class="xref">S1 Table</xref> defines our terminology). In the second set of simulations, we assumed both temperature preference and habitat breadth affected growth and there was no covariation between species’ temperature preferences and their habitat breadths. In the third set, we assumed that both temperature preference and habitat breadth affected growth and that they negatively covaried (r = -0.6), i.e., species that were habitat generalists were cool-adapted—a scenario discussed by Stefanescu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] when comparing warm-adapted Mediterranean specialist butterflies with more cold-adapted and larger-ranged European generalist species. In all models, temperature preference and habitat breadth (when included) had the same magnitude of effects on population growth. Specifically, the abundance of each species in each year was: 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0184275.e003" class="disp-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0184275.e003.jpg" id="pone.0184275.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M3" class="math">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mtext class="mtext">log</mtext>
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">N</mi>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">s</mi>
       <mo class="mo">,</mo>
       <mi class="mi">t</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
     <mo class="mo"> </mo>
     <mo class="mo">~</mo>
     <mo class="mo"> </mo>
     <mtext class="mtext">log</mtext>
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">N</mi>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">s</mi>
       <mo class="mo">,</mo>
       <mi class="mi">t</mi>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <mn class="mn">1</mn>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
     <mo class="mo">+</mo>
     <mi class="mi">b</mi>
     <mo class="mo"> </mo>
     <mi class="mi">T</mi>
     <mi class="mi">e</mi>
     <mi class="mi">m</mi>
     <mi class="mi">p</mi>
     <mo class="mo">.</mo>
     <mi class="mi">p</mi>
     <mi class="mi">r</mi>
     <mi class="mi">e</mi>
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">f</mi>
      <mi class="mi">s</mi>
     </msub>
     <mo class="mo">+</mo>
     <mi class="mi">b</mi>
     <mo class="mo"> </mo>
     <mi class="mi">H</mi>
     <mi class="mi">a</mi>
     <mi class="mi">b</mi>
     <mi class="mi">i</mi>
     <mi class="mi">t</mi>
     <mi class="mi">a</mi>
     <mi class="mi">t</mi>
     <mo class="mo">.</mo>
     <mi class="mi">b</mi>
     <mi class="mi">r</mi>
     <mi class="mi">e</mi>
     <mi class="mi">a</mi>
     <mi class="mi">d</mi>
     <mi class="mi">t</mi>
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">h</mi>
      <mi class="mi">s</mi>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic> is the abundance of species 
 <italic class="italic">s</italic> in year 
 <italic class="italic">t</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">b</italic> is the effect of temperature preference/habitat breadth on 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. For simplicity, we assumed that the effects of the attributes remained constant over time.
</p>
