<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">Estimated current mean daily maximum temperature for the study site from WorldClim estimates was significantly lower (mean 2.7 °C lower) than the average daily maximum temperature taken from the weather station throughout the duration of this study (2011–2016), and estimated mean daily rainfall was higher (mean 0.4 mm) than the average value from the weather station throughout the duration of this study (2011–2016). These differences are likely due to the interpolation method used by WorldClim, based on poor weather station coverage across Africa (Bogale et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">2011</xref>), as well as the fact that WorldClim estimates were calculated for the whole study site rather than the location of the weather station alone. As the WorldClim current estimates differed consistently from the measurements from the weather station in the study site, which were used to build our models, two predicted change variables were created by subtracting the WorldClim estimate of current temperature across the study site, at a resolution of 30°, from the projected future temperature across the study site, at a resolution of 30°. This procedure was then repeated for current and future rainfall. The average projected changes in temperature and precipitation were calculated by taking the mean across all pixels across the study site in the predicted change rasters. We then calculated the average activity and distances traveled under current temperature conditions using the mean values from the weather station on site, and calculated the values predicted by the model of denning and non-denning periods combined, and for the denning period only. To get future predictions of activity and distances traveled, we added the predicted change in temperature and precipitation, derived from the WorldClim estimates, to average temperature and precipitation from the weather station data, and used these values to calculate activity and distances traveled predicted by the models of denning and non-denning periods combined, and the non-denning period only, under the expected changes in temperature and precipitation. Current mean activity and distances traveled was then subtracted from future activity and distances traveled to get the predicted future change in the dependant variables between now and 2070. Analyses were carried out using the 
 <italic class="italic">rgdal</italic> (Bivand et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2017</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">raster</italic> (Hijmans 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2017</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">sf</italic> (Pebesma 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2018</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">maptools</italic> (Bivand and Lewin-Koh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2017</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">rgeos</italic> (Bivand and Rundel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2017</xref>) packages.
</p>
