<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref001">1</a>] predicts that global climate warming will continue and the average temperature on the planet will have increased by 0.3–4.5°C through the end of the 21st century (relative to the 1986–2005 baseline). Current changes have already markedly affected the temporal and spatial properties of climate in China: (1) the spatial and temporal distributions of the heat resource have become very uneven, (2) the cold regions of the north have experienced rapid increases in temperature, and (3) the spatial unevenness of precipitation is increasing [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref002">2</a>]. Changes in the spatiotemporal pattern of climate will have strong impacts on soil properties, plant phenology, plant diseases, insect pests, and the properties of forest ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref001">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate shifts alter species’ geographic distributions, which in turn affect the patterns of climate change since surface vegetation has a major controlling effect on atmospheric properties. Consequently, a capacity for predicting the distribution patterns of species under future climate conditions will contribute substantially to the academic disciplines of biogeography and global change biology. Predicting the future impact of climate change on the areal extent of landscape containing appropriate habitat for particular species [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref005">5</a>] will alert managers to the potential threats of climate change on species distribution ranges and effectively guide the establishment of biological strategies for resource development and utilization, including germplasm preparation and storage. Predictions on critical habitat availability will also contribute to better understanding ecological system stability and the distribution patterns of genetic variation within species [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref006">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species distribution modeling (SDM) is widely used in ecology, biogeography, and evolutionary studies [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref007">7</a>]. In recent years, SDM using Maxent method has contributed significantly to the prediction of biodiversity loss under future climate scenarios [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref008">8</a>] and to the rational use of environmental resources [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref009">9</a>] threatened by upcoming climate changes. Importantly, Maxent is able to function with presence-only data, such as those of species’ distribution records. It requires only geo-referenced occurrence data to predict the distribution of suitable habitat for a species through determinations of the probability distribution of maximum entropy [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref010">10</a>] coupled with environmental information for the whole study area.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Platycladus orientalis</span> (L.) Franco, a member of the family Cupressaceae, is a widespread conifer in China [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref011">11</a>]. This species is able to endure drought and persist on barren soil, and consequently, it is commonly used for ecological restoration projects in arid mountain landscapes of northern China, where the species is used in protection forests for sand stabilization and soil erosion control. The species has unique abilities in the absorption and accumulation of atmospheric pollutants (SO
  <sub>2</sub>, Cl
  <sub>2</sub>) and heavy metal pollutants in soil (Cu, Zn, among others) [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref012">12</a>]. Its wood is strong and decay-resistant, making it valuable in building, furniture, and ship construction [
  <a rid="pone.0132326.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132326.ref013">13</a>]. Until now, little is known about the properties of the habitat distribution for this tree, and the important eco-environmental factors shaping the suitability. Whether changing climate will impact the areal extent of suitable habitat for 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">orientalis</span> is a crucial issue given the ecological and economic significance of the species, and enhancing the powers of prediction would contribute to management planning.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on an extensive collection of geo-referenced occurrence records for 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">orientalis</span> and large-scale, high-precision meteorological environmental data, this study aims (1) to identify the main impact factors for habitat suitability shift of 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">orientalis</span>, (2) to examine the properties and trends of shifts in the areal extent of suitable habitat under a variety of current and future climate scenarios, and (3) to project and quantify the spatial pattern of shifts in the areal extent of suitable habitat under future climate conditions, thereby providing a theoretical reference framework for global change biology, as well as for the plantation, management, and utilization of 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">orientalis</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
