<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Initially, all incubators (volume, 1000 ml) were filled with filtered (0.2 μm) and UV-sterilized seawater (34 PSU) adjusted to the respective fertilization treatment and stocked with positively buoyant eggs. With regard to oxygen supply in a stagnant incubator, it is important to ensure that the eggs have enough space to arrange themselves in a single layer beneath the water surface. We therefore adjusted the amount of eggs per incubator (Atlantic cod: ~300 to 500; Polar cod: ~200 to 300) according to differences in egg size between Atlantic cod (~1.45 mm) and Polar cod (~1.65 mm). Loaded incubators were then located in differently thermostatted seawater baths (volume, 400 liters) to ensure a smooth temperature change inside the incubator. The transparent, bottom-tapered incubators were sealed with a Styrofoam cover to prevent CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> outgassing and temperature fluctuations. According to natural light regimes, Atlantic cod eggs received dim light with a daily rhythm of 8 hours light/16 hours darkness, and Polar cod eggs were kept in darkness except for dim light exposure during handling. Every 24 hours, 90% of the water volume of each incubator was replaced by filtered (0.2 μm) and UV-sterilized seawater to avoid oxygen depletion. An outlet valve was mounted at the bottom of the incubators to drain the seawater with dead eggs, which lose buoyancy and descend to the bottom. Each seawater bath contained two 60-liter reservoir tanks, which were used to preadjust seawater to the corresponding temperature and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sc class="sc">co</sc>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> conditions. Water temperatures inside the water baths were controlled by thermostats and recorded automatically every 15 min (±0.1°C) via a multichannel aquarium computer (IKS-Aquastar, IKS Systems, Germany). Future 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sc class="sc">co</sc>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> conditions were established by injection of pure CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> gas into the submerged 60-liter reservoir tanks at each temperature. A multichannel feedback system (IKS-Aquastar), connected to individual pH probes (IKS-Aquastar) and solenoid valves, was used to control water pH and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sc class="sc">co</sc>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> values. The 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sc class="sc">co</sc>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> of the reservoir tanks was measured in situ before each water exchange with an infrared 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sc class="sc">co</sc>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> probe (Vaisala GMP 343, manual temperature compensation, ±5 μatm accuracy; Vaisala, Finland). The probe was equipped with a MI70 Reading device and an aspiration pump, which was connected to a degassing membrane (G541, Liqui-Cel, 3M, USA) to measure 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sc class="sc">co</sc>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in air equilibrated to dissolved water gases (
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">34</italic>
 </xref>). Factory calibration was confirmed by measurements of seawater previously bubbled with a technical gas mixture (1000 μatm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in air, Air Liquide, Germany). Before the daily water exchange, pH values of the reservoir tanks were measured with a laboratory-grade pH electrode to three decimal places (Mettler Toledo InLab Routine Pt 1000 with temperature compensation, Mettler Toledo, Switzerland), which was connected to a WTW 3310 pH meter. A two-point calibration with NBS (National Bureau of Standards) buffers was performed on a daily basis. To convert NBS to the free proton concentration scale for seawater pH (
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">35</italic>
 </xref>), the electrode was calibrated with tris-HCl seawater buffers (
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">36</italic>
 </xref>), which were acclimated to the corresponding incubation temperature before each measurement. Seawater pH values refer to the free pH scale (pH
 <sub class="sub">F</sub>) throughout this manuscript. Seawater parameters are summarized in fig. S3.
</p>
