<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control region</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nucleotide composition of the control region in the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species has a bias against G, which is common in the mitogenome sense strand of vertebrates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. The control region of 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> is located in the conserved position between 
  <span class="italic">trnE</span> and 
  <span class="italic">trnF</span> and the length (1146 nucleotides) is conserved in all four species. The control region contains three domains: the ETAS Domain I (nt 1–312), Central Conserved Domain II (nt 313–780) and CSB Domain III (nt 781–1146). The A + T content of the three domains is similar in all the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species; Domains I, II, and III have higher contents of C and A, T, and A, respectively, relative to other bases. Domain III contains a higher percentage of A than Domain II, and Domain II has the highest G content among the three domains. The distribution of variable sites and conserved sites suggests that Domain II has relatively more conserved sites and Domain I has more variable sites compared to other domains.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ETAS Domain I can be divided into two parts: part A, from nt 1–163 and part B, from nt 164–312. There are two conserved blocks in part A, ETAS1 (nt 64–126) and ETAS2 (nt 124–163), which are similar to motifs previously identified in other avian and mammalian species. The first block is perfectly conserved among the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species and has sequence similarity to the “goose hairpin” described in some phasianids and 
  <span class="italic">Anas</span> species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>] (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">7</a>). The secondary structure of this hairpin is determined by a stem of seven complementary Cs/Gs and a loop containing a TCCC motif also present in mammalian control region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>], which was associated experimentally with termination of H strands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. There are two copies of TCCC located at nt 22–25 and 183–186. The second block, which is perfectly conserved among the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species, has sequence similarity to the mammalian TASs, including the highly conserved motif GTGCAT, which is present in all sequenced Phasianids and Anseriforms. The motif GYRCAT (Y = C/T; R = A/G) is widespread in Domain I of some mammalian control region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>], and it has been duplicated in the R1 repeats of many species, including the opossum [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>] and several rodents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. Its functional importance is suggested by both comparative [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>] and experimental [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>] data. Single-stranded Domain I can form potential secondary cloverleaf structures. The first 190 nucleotides of Domain I of the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species can form stable secondary structures (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">7</a>). The configurations of the cloverleaves are similar in 
  <span class="italic">C. harmani</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> and vary slightly in 
  <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. auritum</span>; the stem-loop structures of the cloverleaves always include the “goose hairpin”. The control region of 
  <span class="italic">C. harmani</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> have similar structures with five stems, while 
  <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. auritum</span> have only four.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Central Conserved Domain II of the control region of the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species includes 468 conserved nucleotides, from the hyper-variable site at position 313 at the end of the ETAS domain to the beginning of the putative O
  <sub>H</sub> sequence block at position 781. Several conserved blocks of the central conserved domain are similar to the F (nt 350–377), E (nt 395–414), D (nt 455–479), and C (nt 504–529) boxes of vertebrates and other avian species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>], and a bird similarity box is also present.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CSB Domain III is highly variable and has sequences similar to mammalian CSB1. A poly(C) sequence (nt 781–792), similar to the O
  <sub>H</sub> of mammals, maps just a few nucleotides downstream from the putative CSB1 (nt 803–828). However, it is difficult to identify sequences corresponding to mammalian CSB2 and CSB3. The secondary structures of CSB1 and the putative goose hairpin in 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> are consistent with those of 
  <span class="italic">G. gallus</span> (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">7</a>). The bidirectional LSP/HSP promoters (nt 982–1003) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>] are almost perfectly conserved among the 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species. A stable hairpin (nt 1004–1017) that is rich in poly (T) and poly (A) strings is located immediately upstream of the promoters.
 </p>
</sec>
