<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic analyses of Phasianidae</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Datasets containing 13 protein-coding genes (PCG) and all 37 genes plus the control region (mitogenome) were used to study the phylogenetic relationships within Phasianidae. Phylogenetic analysis based on nucleotide sequences was performed using PAUP*4.0b10 for the Maximum parsimony (MP) method [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>], RAxML-7.0.3 for maximum likelihood (ML) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>] and MrBayes 3.1.2 for Bayesian inference (BI) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. For ML and BI analyses, models of the concatenated nucleotide sequences datasets were assessed independently using AICc in MrModeltest2.2 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. The best fit model GTR + I + G was chosen for the likelihood and Bayesian analyses. A consensus tree was generated for MP analysis under the majority rule. The reliability of the clades in the phylogenetic trees was assessed by bootstrap probabilities (BSP) computed using 1000 replicates, with random addition for each bootstrap replicate. The 1000 replicates bootstrap support was also performed in the ML analysis. Bayesian analysis with Markov Chain Monte Carlo sampling was run for 1000000 generations saving a tree every 100 generations, with one cold and three heated chains, and the burn-in time was determined by the time to convergence of the likelihood scores. The Bayesian posterior probabilities (BPP) were estimated on a 50% majority rule consensus tree of the remaining trees.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We examined the performance of individual genes and datasets based on nucleotides; PBS analyses were performed in the program combining TreeRot.v3 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>] and PAUP*4.0b10 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. The following datasets were used for analysis: 13 protein-coding genes, 
  <span class="italic">rrnS</span>, 
  <span class="italic">rrnL</span>, CR partitions, the first, second and third codons of PCG, the three tRNA gene cluster (IQM, WANCY and HSL), ATP (
  <span class="italic">atp6</span> + 
  <span class="italic">atp8</span>), COX (
  <span class="italic">cox1</span> + 
  <span class="italic">cox2</span> + 
  <span class="italic">cox3</span>) and NADH (
  <span class="italic">nad1</span> + 
  <span class="italic">nad2</span> + 
  <span class="italic">nad3</span> + 
  <span class="italic">nad4</span> + 
  <span class="italic">nad4L</span> + 
  <span class="italic">nad5</span> + 
  <span class="italic">nad6</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MEGA 4.1 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>] was used to calculate the pairwise genetic distance for four 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species with default parameters. The mitogenome aligned data and four single genes (
  <span class="italic">nad2</span>, CR, 
  <span class="italic">cytb</span> and 
  <span class="italic">rrnS</span>) obtained from GenBank (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>) were used to calculate the genetic distances. These genes were aligned singly, and be adjusted to consistent sequence lengths manually.
 </p>
</sec>
