<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">The Jiujiang red earth section is located on the second terrace of the Yangtze River (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>), at 29°42′40.27″N, 116°00′13.7″E, 41 m above sea level
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. The study area has a wet subtropical monsoonal climate that is warm and humid in summer and relatively cool and dry in winter, with mean annual precipitation (MAP) of 1000 to 1600 mm and mean annual temperatures (MAT) of 16–18 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. The red earth profile is 14 m thick and divided lithologically into three units (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). The upper unit (0–3.9 m) consists of light orange yellow (7.5YR 9/8) to light moderate orange (2.5YR 7/8) sandy red earth, contains minor amounts of Fe-Mn cutans and Mn nodules, and exhibits a homogeneous texture without white veining. The middle unit (3.9–6.2 m) consists of light moderate orange (2.5YR 7/8) to strong reddish orange (7.5R 6/12) red earth and exhibits white fine net-like veins. The lower unit (6.2–14.0 m) consists of strong reddish orange (7.5R 6/12) to deep reddish orange (7.5R 4/12) red earth and exhibits white coarse net-like veins, which are more abundant and larger than those in the middle unit (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Optically stimulated luminescence (OSL) dating of samples at 0.8 and 2.2 m yielded ages of 40.8(±4.9) and 51.9(±5.8) ka, respectively, and electron spin resonance (ESR) dating of samples at 6.3, 8.1, 10.9, and 13.8 m yielded ages of 393(±45), 452(±43), 592(±77), and 685(±65) ka, respectively. The OSL method is usually more reliable for materials &lt;100 ka and the ESR method more reliable for materials &gt;100 ka. An age of 685(±65) ka for the base of the Jiujiang section indicates that the red earth accumulated after the middle Pleistocene
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>, and ages of 40.8(±4.9) and 51.9(±5.8) ka for the top of this section demonstrates that the upper unit was deposited during the late Pleistocene
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Average sedimentation rates are 12.6 cm/kyr for the upper unit (based on ages at 0.8 and 2.2 m) and 2.57 cm/kyr for the middle and lower units (based on ages at 6.3 and 13.8 m). Comparison with an earlier Sm-Nd isotopic study shows that the Jiujiang red earth sediments have a provenance similar to that of red earth deposits in the middle to lower reaches of the Yangtze River
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>. This suggests that all of the red earth sediments were generated within the middle to lower Yangtze River hydrologic basin.
</p>
