<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Adaptation means adjusting to ongoing and future climate changes (Heltberg, Siegel &amp; Jorgensen 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) and may be influenced by many factors, including the protection of economic well-being or improvement of safety (Adger, Arnell &amp; Tompkins 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). In order to deal with challenges of climate change at the local level we need to go beyond vulnerability analyses and focus on coping and adaptation strategies. Adaptation assumes that a catastrophic damage to the natural systems should not necessarily result in disastrous and irreversible damage to humans (Adger et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Heltberg et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Much of the adaptation to climate change has been reactive in the sense that it is triggered by past or current catastrophic events (Adger et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). Thus, there is the need for scientists to understand future climate change scenarios in order to develop multi-scalar anticipatory adaptation capacity to climate change perturbations. Adaptation takes place against a structural hierarchy, but the stakeholder levels interact. Individuals, communities and institutions have different reasons for adaptation. Rural people’s interest would be to benefit by deriving a livelihood (Adger et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>). Government and public bodies’ interest would be to protect their citizens and advancing their political careers (Adger et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). Rather than focussing on single interventions and single adaptation actions, researchers should consider the interests of different stakeholders in order to help co-manage change along continuously adaptive pathways, and attending to shifting contextual challenges (Vervoort et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
