<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exploring the climate–density interaction</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a preliminary analysis, we first explored the impact of ROS and population density on annual reindeer population growth rates over the study period 1994–2014 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), obtained from the posterior means of an integrated population model (IPM) combining mark-recapture and count data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Because the trend for Arctic greening
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> due to gradually warmer and longer summers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> is likely to influence the carrying capacity of the reindeer population
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>, we accounted for variation in winter length and a linear change in carrying capacity. As expected, we found a strong negative effect of ROS on annual population growth rate (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a> and Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This effect was diminished at low densities, when food competition is weak or negligible (cf. ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>) even under icy conditions.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Density-dependent effects of rain-on-snow (ROS) and icing shape reindeer population fluctuations. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Occasionally, icing causes die-offs. This calf died from starvation in the 2001/2002 winter, which was characterized by high reindeer density and high ROS amounts. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Annual fluctuations in ROS (blue line) and total female population size 
     <span class="italic">N</span> (black line) in the study period. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Density-dependent effect of ROS on the population growth rates (see Supplementary Table 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). For illustration, population densities (
     <span class="italic">N</span>) are classified into low (yellow symbols), medium (orange), and high (red)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9332_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e537" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic summary of the different analytical steps. Boxes with rounded corners show the analytical steps used in this paper. Square boxes contain data or estimates that are fed into the models in steps 1–4. 
     <span class="italic">S</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">i</span>,
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub> and 
     <span class="italic">F</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">i</span>,
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub> refer to survival and fecundity estimates for age class 
     <span class="italic">i</span> at time 
     <span class="italic">t</span>, 
     <span class="italic">N</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub> is the population size at time 
     <span class="italic">t</span>, either age-structured before the hunting season (
     <span class="italic">N</span>
     <sub>prehunt,
      <span class="italic">i</span>,
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub>) or right after the end of the hunting season (
     <span class="italic">N</span>
     <sub>posthunt,
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub>), and ROS is a measure of rain-on-snow, as defined in the Methods. Note that in this figure, we use the term density in place of population size when considering density effects of population size on population growth (i.e., density dependence). This is to aid the reader in following how 
     <span class="italic">N</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub> was used in different steps of our analysis (as a cause of density dependence, or as a response variable), and does not indicate a change in the way 
     <span class="italic">N</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">t</span>
     </sub> was estimated
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9332_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e610" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
