<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Four scientists scored climate exposure in consultation with a broader group of climate scientists. Prior to scoring, the experts received an overview of the output of the climate model ensembles [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. Experts then used information on species distribution and the exposure maps of ocean surface temperature, ocean surface salinity, air temperature, and pH to estimate exposure in the Northeast U.S. Shelf ecosystem. The comparisons between species distribution and exposure maps were made visually by each expert independently. This species specific exposure was then converted to a score using pre-defined criteria (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s006" class="xref">S4 Supporting Information</xref>). Scores for exposure were: low, moderate, high, and very high. If a species was not exposed to a given factor, it was scored as low exposure (e.g., Acadian Redfish is not exposed to changes in precipitation because they live in deep, offshore waters). For sea-level rise and ocean currents, which were not included in the climate model output, the experts reviewed the exposure summaries (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s004" class="xref">S2 Supporting Information</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s005" class="xref">S3 Supporting Information</xref>) and then discussed these documents as a group. Species with no exposure to change in currents were scored as low and species with exposure to currents were scored on the basis of the magnitude of change estimated by expert opinion (clarified in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s004" class="xref">S2 Supporting Information</xref>). With regard to Sea-Level Rise, species with no reliance on nearshore habitats were scored low and species that use these habitats were scored based on the magnitude of the impacts of sea-level rise estimated by expert opinion (clarified in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s005" class="xref">S3 Supporting Information</xref>).
</p>
