<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The U.S. National Park System, one of the world’s premier protected area systems, will likely be increasingly important to the conservation of birds in the face of climate change. Potential colonization exceeds potential extirpation in more than 60% of parks under both emissions pathways, and if projected extirpations and colonizations were realized, the average park would have 29% more species in winter and 6% more species in summer. While not assessed directly here, the likelihood of these projections occurring may be higher for birds than for other taxa. Birds are highly mobile, making the prospect of range expansion more realistic [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Many species are also strongly responsive to climatic factors, with distributions that shift from year to year in response to interannual variation in weather [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Of course, colonization requires not just suitable climate, but also suitable habitat. Vegetation, in particular, may lag behind, or fail to follow, climate, such that species dependent on mature trees may not find suitable habitat until and unless that vegetation can establish itself [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Alternatively, some birds may colonize new regions by showing behavioral plasticity, a form of phenotypic plasticity in which a species demonstrates the ability to change behavior in response to climatic or other drivers of environmental change [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Phenotypic plasticity may allow a species, for example, to switch to newly encountered species and vegetation types for foraging and nesting, though with potential biotic costs (e.g., reduced nest success [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]). Regardless of the mechanism, colonization in nearly all compass directions along range boundaries has already been observed across bird species [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>].
</p>
