<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38" class="p">As systematic biases are inevitably introduced in climate modeling, GCM outputs are often bias-corrected using observational information such as station-based and gridded observation data. In addition, because of the inconsistency regarding the spatial resolutions between GCM data and a climate change impact assessment, GCM data are often downscaled to finer resolutions, and often into existing weather stations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" class="xref">93</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">94</xref>
 </sup>. For this study, the CMIP5 GCM outputs (precipitation, maximum and minimum temperature) of the Ohio River study watersheds were statistically bias-corrected over the period from 1950 to 2099 using a hybrid semi-parametric approach proposed by Ho 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>. This bias-correction method is considered computationally efficient and easy to implement
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>
 </sup>. Using Eq. 
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>, the method matches the location (mean), scale (variance), and shape (skewness) parameters of GCM outputs with those of the historical observations to preserve the consistency of their statistical features over long-term periods:
 <disp-formula id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">1</label>
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <tex-math id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\hat{X}^{\prime} }_{m}={\mu }_{o}+\frac{{\sigma }_{o}}{{\sigma }_{m}}({X^{\prime} }_{m}-{\mu }_{m})$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M2" display="block" class="math">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mover accent="true" class="mover">
       <mi class="mi">X</mi>
       <mo class="mo">ˆ</mo>
      </mover>
      <mo class="mo">′</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">m</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo class="mo">=</mo>
    <msub class="msub">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">μ</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">o</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo class="mo">+</mo>
    <mfrac class="mfrac">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <msub class="msub">
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mi class="mi">o</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <msub class="msub">
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mi class="mi">m</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">(</mo>
    <msub class="msub">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">X</mi>
      <mo class="mo">′</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">m</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo class="mo">−</mo>
    <msub class="msub">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">μ</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">m</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">)</mo>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_41334_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>where X, μ, and σ respectively represent the variable of interest, mean, and standard deviation of a climate, the subscripts of o and m respectively signify the observable and simulated climate variables of interest, the superscript of “
 <bold class="bold">′</bold>” indicates a future time period, and the symbol of “ ^” represents a bias-corrected variable. The bias correction approach used in this study assumes that discrepancies between observed and modeled climate variables do not change over time or in the future
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, future observables could be directly predicted based on historical observations using a transfer function that maps simulated climate onto observations. The transfer function was estimated by matching the predicted future probability distributions of climate variables to their empirical (historical) distributions (Eq. 
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>). Then, the multi-GCM ensemble averages of precipitation, temperature, and hydrological components such as direct runoff and groundwater were determined by averaging the bias-corrected projections with equal weights, which is often called the “one model, one vote” weighting scheme.
</p>
