<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">The first field experiment was conducted between late August and late October 2013 to test the growth and mortality responses to possible high temperatures during upwelling relaxation, and upwelling-related hypoxic events. Juvenile green abalone, 
 <italic class="italic">Haliotis fulgens</italic> (1.44 ± 0.12 cm, mean length ± s.d.), were deployed at 7 and 12 m in depth (Figs 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>) on two sides of Isla Natividad (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a,b</xref>). These depths were targeted because green abalone range from the intertidal to ~12 m (and as deep as 18 m at some locations), with the greatest abundances between 5–8 m. Thus, the shallow deployments (7 m) correspond with the depth where this species is most abundant, and the deeper deployments (12 m) are at the edge of the depth distribution for green abalone, where animals may experience the most stressful conditions, particularly periodic exposure to hypoxic waters. We placed n = 12 abalone in four Vexar mesh cages (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>) to keep the groups of abalones separate from each other and facilitate weekly assessment of their survivorship. Each compartment contained a sheet of fiberglass to provide a hard surface for the animals to attach. These compartments were placed within a larger steel wire metal cage (85 × 70 × 30 cm; Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>) that provided structure and support. In total, n = 384 juvenile abalone in 32 Vexar cages, were outplanted in a total of 8 steel wire cages for this experiment, with 2 replicate steel cages placed ~10 m apart at each of four field sites: MP7m, MP12m, PP7m and PP12m (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). All juvenile green abalones for the 2013 experiment were cultured in the Isla Natividad aquaculture facility from 11 adults collected at Morro Prieto.
</p>
