<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Potato is considered to be sensitive to salinity stress. Soils that are rich in salt content are detrimental to plant growth and tuber development. The magnitude of salinity effects on potato plant, however, varies with cultivars and salt levels. Salinity hastened the onset of leaf senescence, leaf yellowing and desiccation, and reduced tuber fresh and dry weight per plant (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Levy et al., 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Levy, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akhtar et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jaarsma et al. (2013)</xref> also reported growth inhibition and early senescence in salt sensitive cultivars Mozart and Mona Lisa in response to salt treatment. Salinity inhibited the shoot growth and total fresh and dry biomass although the inhibition was more pronounced in salt sensitive cultivar, Concord, relative to tolerant cultivar, Kennebec (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aghaei et al., 2009</xref>). The decrease in shoot growth and biomass became severe in both cultivars with increased salt dose. Salt stress decreased leaf area, relative water content, leaf stomatal conductance and transpiration rate substantially (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fidalgo et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Odemis and Caliskan, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akhtar et al., 2015</xref>). Salt stress also significantly inhibited rates of photosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Odemis and Caliskan, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akhtar et al., 2015</xref>). At ultrastructural level, salinity induced cell vacuolation and thylakoid swelling, and caused reduced grana stacking (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fidalgo et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Queirós et al., 2009a</xref>). Salinity substantially increased the callus Na+ and Cl
 <sup class="sup">-</sup> content, increased lipid peroxidation and reduced the growth rate of the callus (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Queirós et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Potato plants grown under saline conditions exhibited higher sodium content in leaves, stems, and tubers (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ghosh et al., 2001</xref>), Salinity delayed seedling emergence, and inhibited tuber growth and dry matter content, the extent of which increased with higher salt levels (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ghosh et al., 2001</xref>). Salt stress reduced the total and marketable tuber yield, which was associated with lower tuber number per plant and average tuber weight (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ghosh et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Odemis and Caliskan, 2014</xref>). Salinity is suggested to increase the contents of water-soluble carbohydrates, starch and total non-structural carbohydrates in leaves (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ghosh et al., 2001</xref>). The decreased tuber dry matte content but increased leaf carbohydrate content may suggest that salt stress may retard carbon translocation to tuber. Salinity is also believed to increase tuber nitrogen content but decrease nitrogen reductase activity of leaf (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ghosh et al., 2001</xref>). Through cDNA microarray study, 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Legay et al. (2009)</xref> observed that when exposed at 150 mM NaCl potato plants down-regulate expression of genes associated with photosystem (PSII) and PSI chlorophyll synthesis and Calvin cycle enzymes.
</p>
