<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Furthermore, Wang et al., [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>] reported that a species’ geographic range and its ecological attributes influenced genetic diversity; and that high heterozygosity favoured long-lived plants especially in the arid zones. Our study is congruent with this assumption and is of particular importance when the historical range shifts 
 <italic class="italic">Senegalia senegal</italic> had experienced [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], the complex landscapes and fragile ecosystems it occupies [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref081" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>], and its ecological characteristics, are taken into consideration [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref082" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Asynchrony in flowering season has been observed for nearby 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">senegal</italic> populations (personal observation), which limits inter-population gene flow [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>]. Perennial insurgence of wild fires, insect pest invasion, soil erosion, overexploitation and grazing are common ecological challenges throughout these areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref081" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. These factors potentially influence or impact gene flow of 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">senegal</italic>, as shown for several tropical species [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>] and was further supported by Robledo-Arnuncio 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref087" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. The impact of these factors on gene flow could have slightly affected the heterozygosity and allele estimates detected in our study, although 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">senegal</italic> has been shown to be an outcrossing species [
 <xref rid="pone.0194726.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>].
</p>
