<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evidence of Interannual Variability in Fe Dust Deposition at Station ALOHA</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time-series records of labile Fe plus total dissolvable Fe (TDFe) (i.e., the soluble plus the acid labile particle Fe fraction) in the surface layers of the water column at Station ALOHA have been intermittent and do not allow for a rigorous quantitative analysis of the long-term interannual variability of Fe in the context of shifts in climate indices (
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>). Nevertheless, at seasonal scales, TDFe concentrations follow a similar pattern as that observed in dust storm events over Asia, with maxima in spring or early summer and minimum values observed during late summer and autumn (
  <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>). In a detailed analysis of the seasonal and interannual TDFe concentration variability, Fitzsimmons et al. (
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>) observed that the intraannual variability was as large as that observed at interannual scales, suggesting that the residence time of TDFe in the upper ocean cannot be longer than a few months since the maximum seasonal concentrations observed in spring (May) appear to be depleted by late summer (October). In addition, as a result of their intensive daily sampling during field campaigns in the region near Station ALOHA, these authors were able to document a sudden increase in Fe between August 8th and 12th of 2012 that may have been caused by the upwelling associated with the passage of a cyclonic eddy just north of the sampling site. Although this and other observations (
  <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>) highlight the importance of stochastic events in modulating short-term availability of Fe at Station ALOHA, a deep-water upwelling event will result in an increase in P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>, leading to a potential surplus of P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> relative to Fe (
  <a rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" href="#r58">58</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alternatively, a long-term time-series aerosol record collected at the Mauna Loa Observatory between 1988 and 2011 provides field data to assess potential seasonal and interannual variability in atmospheric Fe availability in the vicinity of Station ALOHA (
  <a rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" href="#r59">59</a>). Based on the aerosol Fe time series (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S6
  </span>), we observe that most years with extremely low late-summer P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> concentrations recorded in the upper euphotic zone at Station ALOHA (e.g., 1994, 1997, and 2006; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>) correspond to years in which the Mauna Loa record displays enhanced spring and early summer aerosol Fe values relative to the previous year. Nevertheless, there are some years with consistently low P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> (e.g., 2003 and 2004) that do not see a concomitant enhancement in atmospheric Fe concentrations, suggesting that the Mauna Loa record may not fully reflect the dynamics of atmospheric dust deposition in the waters sampled at Station ALOHA (i.e., the Mauna Loa Observatory is located at an altitude of 3,339 m and ∼400 km southeast of Station ALOHA; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S6 and S7
  </span>). Additional processes, such as the enhanced stratification recorded between 2002 and 2005 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig05" href="#fig05">Fig. 5</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S3
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </span>), can further contribute to the observed variability in P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>. Still, we find a weak but significant negative correlation between the seasonally detrended Mauna Loa atmospheric Fe record and that of the mean 0- to 45-m P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> concentration at Station ALOHA (
  <a rid="t01" ref-type="table" href="#t01">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another approach to assess the long-term climate-driven patterns of variability in atmospheric dust Fe availability over the North Pacific may be found in the implementation of the Community Atmospheric Model, version 4 (CAM4), embedded within the Community Earth System Model (CESM) (
  <a rid="r60" ref-type="bibr" href="#r60">60</a>). The model is forced with meteorology from the Modern-Era Retrospective Analysis for Research and Applications (MERRA) reanalysis-based simulations. It incorporates an intermediate complexity soluble Fe scheme that includes prognostic dust generation with soil mineralogy differences, combustion iron sources, as well as the transport, atmospheric processing, and deposition of dust, Fe, and soluble Fe (
  <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>). The model has been extensively compared with in situ observations and shown to capture much of the observed spatial and temporal variability (
  <a rid="r62" ref-type="bibr" href="#r62">62</a>), including that derived from the Mauna Loa time-series record (
  <a rid="t01" ref-type="table" href="#t01">Table 1</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S6
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model outputs for the period 1980–2014 yield a positive correlation between PDO and Fe concentration (
  <a rid="t01" ref-type="table" href="#t01">Table 1</a>), aerosol optical depth, and Fe deposition (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>) in the southeastern quadrant of the NPSG, confirming an overall enhancement of dust transport and Fe availability during positive PDO phases in the region surrounding Station ALOHA. A significant enhancement in atmospheric Fe deposition during positive PDO phases (9.8 ± 0.6 μmol Fe⋅m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>⋅y
  <span class="sup">−1</span> versus 6.2 ± 0.7 μmol Fe⋅m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>⋅y
  <span class="sup">−1</span> during negative PDO phases) and the concomitant decrease in sea surface P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> concentrations (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1 and Fig. S1
  </span>), support our hypothesis that climate-driven changes in Asian dust transport and atmospheric Fe deposition across the North Pacific, whose main source is mineral dust at this location (
  <a rid="r50" ref-type="bibr" href="#r50">50</a>, 
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>), may contribute significantly to interannual oscillation between P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>-sufficiency and limitation observed in microbial metabolic activity at Station ALOHA. Furthermore, our results are consistent with the model predictions of Ward et al. (
  <a rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" href="#r10">10</a>), who used global observations and a resource ratio framework to model competition between diazotrophs and nondiazotrophs; their modeling-based analysis suggests that oligotrophic pelagic ecosystems supporting diazotrophy shift from surplus P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> to P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>-deficiency when soluble Fe deposition rates exceed ∼10 μmol Fe⋅m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>⋅y
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
 <div id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Spatial distribution of the correlation coefficient for annual PDO index versus model run results of aerosol optical depth (AOD) attributed to dust (
    <span class="italic">Left</span>) and atmospheric soluble Fe deposition (
    <span class="italic">Right</span>) for the period 1980–2014. A solid red circle marks the location of Station ALOHA.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1900789116fig04" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
