<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="s9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Station ALOHA records of inorganic phosphorus (P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>), nitrate + nitrite (NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span> + NO
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span>), chlorophyll 
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentrations, primary productivity, temperature, salinity, and water column potential density in the upper 200 m were obtained from the HOT program. The program description, data access, and a full description of methods are publicly available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hahana.soest.hawaii.edu/hot/" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hahana.soest.hawaii.edu/hot/</span>. High-sensitivity analytical techniques were used to determine P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> and NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span> + NO
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span> concentrations in the euphotic zone (termed low-level phosphate and low-level nitrogen in the HOT archive). Chlorophyll 
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentrations were measured by high-performance liquid chromatography. Mean 0- to 45-m P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> concentrations for each HOT cruise between October 1988 and December 2015 were computed (standard collection depths at 5, 25, and 45 m) and a total of 261 time points were splined over the full time record, corresponding to an approximate resolution of one observation every 38 d. Similarly, the mean 0- to 45-m 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-based primary production rates, NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span> + NO
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span>, and chlorophyll 
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentrations, as well as mixed-layer temperature, salinity, density, and the density gradient between the mixed layer and 150 m were computed for each cruise. In addition, because the seasonal cycle is a major contributor to the observed variability of upper water column chlorophyll 
  <span class="italic">a</span> concentrations, primary productivity, and mixed-layer temperature, salinity, and density at Station ALOHA, all correlation analyses of these variables were based on the residual time series obtained after removing the mean seasonal cycle by subtracting the climatological (1989–2015) monthly mean. The mean drift direction and speed of the surface-tethered sediment traps were computed for each cruise based on the time and position of deployment and recovery.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of microbial P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> uptake kinetics excludes those assays identified by Björkman et al. (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>) as yielding questionable 
  <span class="italic">K</span>
  <sub>m</sub> values due to a flat uptake response to P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> loading.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NPGO and PDO monthly values are available from Emanuele Di Lorenzo (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.o3d.org/npgo/" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.o3d.org/npgo/</span>) and Nathan Mantua (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://research.jisao.washington.edu/pdo/" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://research.jisao.washington.edu/pdo/</span>), respectively. SLP data are based on the ERA interim global analysis (
  <a rid="r72" ref-type="bibr" href="#r72">72</a>) and were provided by the Asia-Pacific Data Research Center, which is part of the International Pacific Research Center at the University of Hawai’i at Manoa. Monthly Mauna Loa atmospheric aerosol Fe concentrations were calculated from the biweekly records published by Hyslop et al. (
  <a rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" href="#r59">59</a>). Hourly wind speed and direction record from 1988 through 2015 were obtained from buoys 51001 and 51101 maintained by the National Data Buoy Center (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ndbc.noaa.gov/" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ndbc.noaa.gov/</span>). Ocean surface currents, integrated over a 2° × 2° area centered at 23.2°N and 157.2°W for the period 1988 through 2015, were obtained from The Tropical Ocean Surface Currents Analysis Realtime–OSCAR dataset (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://oceanmotion.org/html/resources/oscar.htm" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://oceanmotion.org/html/resources/oscar.htm</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because the P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> record displayed the lowest temporal resolution, all other records were splined to match the P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> resolution before cross-correlation analysis. Furthermore, we applied a 10-point Savitzky–Golay smoothing filter (
  <a rid="r73" ref-type="bibr" href="#r73">73</a>) to all splined time series to minimize the effects of intraannual variability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The skill of the hindcast of P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>* based on 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">Eq. 
   <span class="bold">1</span>
  </a> and SLP (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>) was calculated as follows:
  <div id="eq2" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="me2" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">s</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mo">∑</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msup">
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mo">(</span>
            <div class="mrow">
             <div class="msub">
              <span class="mi">P</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
             </div>
             <span class="mo">−</span>
             <div class="msubsup">
              <span class="mi">P</span>
              <span class="mi">i</span>
              <span class="mo">∗</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <span class="mo">)</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mo">∑</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msubsup">
          <span class="mi">P</span>
          <span class="mi">i</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">.</span>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="label">[2]</span>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The maximum skill score of 0.57 is significant compared with the null hypothesis of forcing by a white Gaussian noise SLP time series. Repeating the fit with 1,891 white-noise time-series runs as forcing yielded lower skill scores for 99.98% of cases.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modeled dust aerosol optical depth, atmospheric Fe, and soluble Fe concentration spatial and temporal distributions were derived from the National Science Foundation/Department of Energy (NSF/DOE) CESM/CAM (
  <a rid="r62" ref-type="bibr" href="#r62">62</a>, 
  <a rid="r74" ref-type="bibr" href="#r74">74</a>), using MERRA reanalysis-based simulations for (1980–2015) and included an intermediate complexity soluble iron scheme (
  <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>). This scheme incorporates prognostic dust generation, including soil mineralogy differences (
  <a rid="r75" ref-type="bibr" href="#r75">75</a>, 
  <a rid="r76" ref-type="bibr" href="#r76">76</a>), and dust; iron and soluble iron are all transported and deposited in the three-dimensional model at 2° × 2° resolution (
  <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>). Comparisons to Mauna Loa Fe observations are at the model level corresponding to the height of the observatory (3.4 km), while the PDO correlations were at the surface model level.
 </p>
</sec>
