<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ruling Out Potential Hawaiian Island Sources of P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> and Fe Interannual Variability
 </div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kīlauea, an active volcano located on the Island of Hawaii ∼400 km southeast of Station ALOHA, has been erupting almost continuously since 1983 (
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). The resulting volcanic plume represents a potentially significant source of P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> and Fe to the marine environment (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>
  <a href="#r45">*</a>–
  <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>). However, neither remote sensing-based plume dispersion observations and models (
  <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>), nor wind patterns recorded by National Data Buoy Center Buoys 51001 and 51101 (24°27.17′N 162°00′W and 24°21.47′N 162°03.5′W, respectively) display significant shifts in velocity and direction between PDO phases (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S4
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, recent studies on the temporal distribution of dissolved Nd and Ra isotopes at Station ALOHA suggest a lithogenic input from the Hawaiian Islands into the surface waters of Station ALOHA during winter months (
  <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>). However, as for the wind fields, the observed velocity and direction of ocean surface currents surrounding Station ALOHA remain consistent between PDO phases (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1900789116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S3
  </span>). This consistency in wind and ocean currents suggests that regional changes in advective patterns around the Hawaiian Islands cannot explain the observed subdecadal variability in P
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> concentrations at Station ALOHA.
 </p>
</sec>
