<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thermal physiology</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated RMR as rates of oxygen consumption by adult pygmy rabbits captured in east-central and south-central Idaho and in southwestern Montana, USA (Idaho Department of Fish and Game Scientific Collection Permits #010813 and #100310; Montana Fish, Wildlife, and Parks Scientific Collection Permit #2014-062). We maintained the animals in captivity at the Small Mammal Research Facility at Washington State University. Animals were housed individually in 1.8 × 1.2 m mesh pens lined with pine shavings inside of a barn with a roof and partial walls. This arrangement exposed the rabbits to ambient temperatures but protected them from direct solar radiation, wind, and precipitation. Cages had corrugated pipe and nest boxes for enrichment and refuge. Food (Purina Professional Rabbit Chow, Purina Mills, St. Louis, MO, USA) and water were available ad libitum. Daily maximum and minimum ambient temperatures were recorded in the facility using a digital thermometer (model number 00613CASB; Chaney Instrument Co., Lake Geneva, WI, USA) during winter (4 January–17 March, 2016) and summer (13 June–7 July, 2016) trial periods. Mean daytime ambient high temperatures in the facility during winter were 7.8 °C (sd = 3.4, range = 2.2–15 °C) and mean lows were 1.1 °C (sd = 2.7, range = −4.4–6.6 °C). During summer, mean daytime ambient highs were 35.5 °C (sd = 6.7, range = 23.3–45.0 °C) and mean lows were 8.4 °C (sd = 2.6, range = 3.3–12.2 °C).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured rates of oxygen consumption (
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i001.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-1" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>, ml O
   <sub>2</sub>/min) during winter (5 January–13 March, 2016) and summer (13 June–7 July, 2016) across a range of temperatures typical of natural habitats. During winter, we evaluated 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i002.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M2" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-2" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> at seven temperatures ranging from approximately −5 to 25 °C and in the summer at six temperatures ranging from approximately 5 to 30 °C. Trials were conducted between 0800 and 1800 h and animals were only exposed to one treatment temperature per day (to the extent that we were able, animals were not subjected to trials on successive days). We did not fast the animals prior to treatment because pygmy rabbits produce and consume cecal pellets and might not be truly post-absorptive, and 
   <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Katzner, Parker &amp; Harlow (1997)</a> did not detect an effect of fasting on RMR of pygmy rabbits. Animals were weighed before each trial and placed in an airtight plexiglass metabolic chamber (volume = 4,500 cm
   <span class="sup">3</span>). Because body heat can influence the internal temperature of the metabolic chamber, we measured temperature inside the chamber using two iButtons® (
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>c</sub>; model number DS1921G; Maxim Integrated, San Jose, CA, USA) positioned on diagonally opposed corners. For all temperatures ≥0 °C, the metabolic chamber was placed inside a temperature controlled environmental cabinet. For the −5 °C winter temperature trials, the chamber was placed inside of a small freezer. We used a wireless infra-red camera (model number NC223W-IR; Shenzhen Anbash Technology, Shenzhen, China) to monitor the activity and welfare of animals.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a pushed flow-through respirometry system to measure 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i003.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-3" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> for 2 h, with the first hour allowing acclimation to the trial temperature and the second hour comprising the sampling interval. Water vapor was removed from room air using a Drierite column (W.A. Hammond Drierite Co., Xenia, OH, USA), and the dried air was forced into the metabolic chamber at a controlled flow rate of 4000 mL/min using a mass flow controller (model 32907-71; Cole Parmer, Vernon Hills, IL, USA). Excurrent air was subsampled, scrubbed of moisture and CO
   <sub>2</sub> using Drierite and indicating soda lime, and pushed into a fuel cell oxygen analyzer (FC-10; Sable Systems, North Las Vegas, NV, USA). Flow rate into the chamber and oxygen concentrations were averaged over 5 s intervals, converted to digital signal by an A–D converter (UI-2; Sable Systems), and recorded to a laptop using Warthog LabHelper software (
   <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Chappell, 2016b</a>; 
   <span xlink:href="http://www.warthog.ucr.edu" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.warthog.ucr.edu</span>). We collected baseline concentrations of room air for 3–5 min at the start of the trial and approximately every 40 min thereafter to correct for drift in the oxygen analyzer. We used Warthog LabAnalyst software to fit a regression to baseline oxygen concentrations and corrected oxygen concentrations accordingly. The 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i004.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M4" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-4" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> was calculated by LabAnalyst (
   <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">Chappell, 2016a</a>) as: 
   <div id="eqn-1" class="disp-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <div xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-e001.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M5" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2} = ({{\rm{F}}_{\rm{i}}}{{\rm{O}}_{\rm{2}}} - {{\rm{F}}_{\rm{e}}}{{\rm{O}}_{\rm{2}}})*{\rm{FR}}/(1 - {{\rm{F}}_{\rm{e}}}{{\rm{O}}_{\rm{2}}})$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-eqn-1" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">F</span>
        <span class="mtext">i</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mtext">2</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">F</span>
        <span class="mtext">e</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mtext">2</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
       <span class="mo">*</span>
       <span class="mtext">FR</span>
       <span class="mo">/</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mn">1</span>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">F</span>
        <span class="mtext">e</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mtext">2</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where FR is the incurrent mass flow rate scrubbed of water vapor and CO
   <sub>2</sub>; F
   <sub>i</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub> is the fractional oxygen concentration in dry, CO
   <sub>2</sub>-free air (0.2095); and F
   <sub>e</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub> is the fractional oxygen concentration of excurrent air scrubbed of water vapor and CO
   <sub>2</sub>. Data were visually inspected, and mean values of oxygen consumption were obtained when 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i005.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M6" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-5" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> was low and stable, reflecting RMR. Precision of the oxygen analyzer was validated via ethanol combustion (
   <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">Lighton, 2008</a>). We estimated whole body thermal conductance (
   <span class="italic">C</span>; mL O
   <sub>2</sub> h
   <span class="sup">−1</span> °C
   <span class="sup">−1</span>; multiply by 0.00558 for watts/°C) for each animal at the coldest trial temperature in summer and winter according to the Irving–Scholander model, 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i006.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M7" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$C = \dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}/({T_{\rm{b}}} - {T_{\rm{c}}})$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-6" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">C</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">/</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">T</span>
        <span class="mtext">b</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">T</span>
        <span class="mtext">c</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>, using previously reported values of winter 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>b</sub> for pygmy rabbits (
   <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Katzner, Parker &amp; Harlow, 1997</a>). Although body temperature can vary seasonally, several species of lagomorph maintain constant body temperature year-round (
   <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">Hinds, 1973</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-29">1977</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-67">Sheriff et al., 2009</a>). In the absence of evidence to the contrary, we assumed the same 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>b</sub> for summer- and winter-acclimatized pygmy rabbits. All animal protocols were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committees at University of Idaho (Protocols #2012-23 and #2015-12) and Washington State University (Protocol #04398-011), and they were in accordance with guidelines for the use of wild mammals in research published by the American Society of Mammalogists (
   <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">Sikes &amp; Animal Care and Use Committee of the American Society of Mammalogists, 2016</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microsite temperature</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the thermal environment in above-ground microsites and burrows available to pygmy rabbits in sagebrush steppe habitat in the Lemhi Valley of east-central Idaho, USA. The valley is high-desert shrub-steppe (elevation = 1,880–2,020 masl) and receives on average &lt;25 cm precipitation annually (
   <a rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-77">Western Regional Climate Center, 2016</a>), most of which falls as rain during late spring. Average temperatures range from a daytime low of −15.7 °C to a high of −1.2 °C in January and 5.4–29 °C in July (
   <a rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-77">Western Regional Climate Center, 2016</a>). The study site is characterized by mounded microtopography known as mima-mounds (
   <a rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-73">Tullis, 1995</a>). These mounds tend to have deeper soils and support taller shrubs than the surrounding matrix, and they are where most pygmy rabbit burrow systems are located. Wyoming big sagebrush (
   <span class="italic">Artemisia tridentata wyomingensis</span>) is the dominant shrub species, with black sagebrush (
   <span class="italic">A. nova</span>), three-tip sagebrush (
   <span class="italic">A. tripartita</span>), green rabbitbrush (
   <span class="italic">Chrysothamnus viscidiflorus</span>), and rubber rabbitbrush (
   <span class="italic">Ericameria nauseosa</span>) occurring less frequently. The matrix between clusters of sagebrush supports a highly variable mix of low-growing shrubs, forbs, and bare ground in the lowest elevations, and more continuous grass and forb cover at higher elevations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used operative environmental temperature (
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub>) to characterize the thermal environment of above-ground sites available to pygmy rabbits (
   <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Bakken, 1980</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Coleman &amp; Downs, 2010</a>). 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> integrates heat transfer from radiative, conductive, and convective sources into a single index that specifies the equilibrium temperature an animal lacking metabolic heat production or evaporative heat loss would attain in a given combination of air temperature, wind, and sunlight. To measure 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub>, we built 10 models of the approximate size and shape of a resting pygmy rabbit (
   <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Bakken, 1992</a>). Models were hollow copper ovoids (12.7 × 10.2 cm) painted a matte dark gray. Copper models have been shown to more precisely measure the above-ground thermal environment experienced by small, diurnal mammals and capture the thermal heterogeneity of habitat better than direct measures of temperature (
   <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Coleman &amp; Downs, 2010</a>). We attached two 8 cm segments of pipe to the bottom of the ovoids to prevent the devices from resting directly on the ground and to anchor them to the substrate. A calibrated iButton® attached to a wooden dowel was inserted into one end of each model and sealed in place by a rubber stopper (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). The iButton® recorded temperature every 30 min for one month (31 days) in the winter (20 January–19 February, 2015) and summer (5 July–4 August, 2015) to capture the coldest and hottest times of the year in the valley.
  </p>
  <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.4511/fig-1</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Cross-section of an operative temperature model (A) and an intact model (B) used to characterize the thermal environment in pygmy rabbit (
     <span class="italic">Brachylagus idahoensis</span>) habitat in eastern Idaho, USA.
    </div>
    <p>Photo credit: Charles Peterson.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pygmy rabbit burrow systems were surveyed on foot during October 2014 according to methods described in 
   <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Price &amp; Rachlow (2011)</a>. Ten active burrow systems were randomly selected for temperature monitoring using ArcMAP 10.2 (ESRI, Redlands, CA, USA). Operative temperature models were placed at random locations on active burrow systems by identifying a random direction (cardinal or intercardinal) and distance (0–3 m, at 0.5 m increments) from the center of the mima mound. If the random point landed in a location where a pygmy rabbit could not reasonably be expected to rest (e.g., above ground on the trunk of a sagebrush plant), the model was placed adjacent to the obstruction as close to the random point as possible. The mean diameter of mima mounds at our study site was 10.6 m (range: 6.6–15.0 m; 
   <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">Parsons et al., 2016</a>), and an entire burrow system was typically encompassed by the boundary of discrete mima mounds (
   <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">McMahon et al., 2017</a>). Pygmy rabbits at this site predominantly use mima mounds with burrow systems (
   <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">McMahon et al., 2017</a>) and rest close to burrow openings (
   <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Milling et al., 2017</a>). Thus, the orientation of 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> models on the mound allowed us to capture a range of above-ground microclimates available to pygmy rabbits, and although the 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> model locations do not represent rest sites where rabbits were observed, they were located on active burrow systems and we often noted fresh fecal pellets within 0.5 m of the sensor locations. We identified 10 additional active burrow systems at which we monitored temperature within burrows; we included only burrows with a minimum of two openings because pygmy rabbits typically construct burrow systems with multiple openings (
   <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Green &amp; Flinders, 1980</a>). Because the thermal environment inside the burrow is not directly influenced by short wave radiation, and we assumed minimal influence of convection, we measured burrow temperature using Onset Stowaway TBI32 Tidbit temperature loggers (hereafter, tidbit; Onset Computer Corp., Bourne, MA, USA). We deployed one tidbit to a depth of 1 m (the average maximum depth of a pygmy rabbit burrow; 
   <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Green &amp; Flinders, 1980</a>) within a randomly selected opening for each burrow by attaching the tidbit to stiff wire nailed at the burrow entrance. This inhibited removal by animals. Tidbits recorded temperature every 10 min for one month in winter (20 January–19 February, 2015) and summer (5 July–4 August, 2015). Of 10 tidbits deployed, one tidbit failed during winter, resulting in nine winter-monitored burrows, and two tidbits failed during summer, resulting in eight summer-monitored burrows. We calculated the mean temperature recorded by all tidbits and also by all operative temperature models per hour to estimate below- and above-ground temperatures with the same temporal resolution.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respirometry data were analyzed using mixed-effects segmented regression to evaluate the relationship between 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i007.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M8" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-7" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> and temperature during summer and winter (
   <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">Gallant &amp; Fuller, 1973</a>). We used season and 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>c</sub> as predictor variables with body mass as a covariate, and we included a random effect for individual identity. The model parameterizes the segments of the relationship between 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i008.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M9" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-8" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> and temperature below and within the TNZ, determines the breakpoint between segments, and estimates the influence of season and mass on the height of the function. From this output, we quantified the slope of the relationship below the 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>lc</sub> in both seasons, determined the value of the 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>lc</sub> (the breakpoint), and estimated summer RMR
   <sub>T</sub>. We tested for a seasonal difference in thermal conductance using a mixed-effects model with fixed effects for season and mass and a random effect for individual identity. Analyses were conducted using the “nlme” and “lme4” packages in R (
   <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">R Core Team, 2016</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Bates et al., 2015</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">Pinheiro et al., 2016</a>), and results were deemed significant if 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 or if a 95% confidence interval on the parameter estimate did not capture zero. Values are reported as mean ± SE, unless otherwise specified.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used results of the regression analyses to estimate approximate seasonal energetic costs of thermoregulation for animals at rest in burrows and in above-ground microsites. We set mass to the mean of our study animals and populated our temperature predictor variable (
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>c</sub>) using measurements of mean 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> and mean burrow temperature. We calculated the proportion of time in each season that the burrow could serve as a thermal refuge for a resting pygmy rabbit. In winter, this was defined as the amount of time that mean 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> &lt; 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>lc</sub>, but the burrow was warmer than mean 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> and therefore had lower associated thermoregulatory costs. In summer, it was calculated as the amount of time that 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> &gt; 35 °C (the average 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>uc</sub> of pygmy rabbit-size eutherian mammals; see 
   <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Araujo et al., 2013</a>) and the burrow was cooler than 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub>. Additionally, we calculated the amount of energy (in kJ, where 20.1 J is equal to 1 mL O
   <sub>2</sub>; 
   <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">Schmidt-Nielsen, 1997</a>) required to thermoregulate for the entire month in burrows exclusively, in above-ground microsites exclusively, and in a combination of the two habitats. For the winter data, we summed the hourly energy expenditure predicted by the regression for the mean burrow temperature and the mean 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> for the entire month. We followed the same procedure for estimating the energy expenditure in the burrow for one month during summer, but because pygmy rabbits demonstrated high capacity for behavioral thermoregulation through above-ground rest site selection during summer (
   <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Milling et al., 2017</a>), we used the lowest measured hourly 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> in the regression for instances when the mean 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>e</sub> exceeded the estimated 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>uc</sub> of pygmy rabbits. To estimate energy expenditure above 35 °C during summer, we assumed that 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i009.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
     <span id="M10" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="mml-ieqn-9" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">˙</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> increased at the same rate above the TNZ as it did with increasing cold below the TNZ, which is an assumption that is supported in at least two other species of leporid (
   <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">Hinds, 1973</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-29">1977</a>). Because model uncertainty propagates to the predicted estimates of thermoregulatory costs, we used a simulation-based approach described by 
   <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Mandel (2013)</a> to estimate the standard errors of the expected cost for each season and microhabitat using the measured temperature values. This method relies on a parametric bootstrap approach using the estimated sampling distribution of the model parameters instead of analytical or numerical derivatives.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
