<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We estimated the potential flight range for each of the 77 species using the program F
 <sc class="sc">light</sc> v. 1.24 [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.bio.bristol.ac.uk/people/pennycuick.htm" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bio.bristol.ac.uk/people/pennycuick.htm</uri>)
 <italic class="italic">.</italic> Flight range calculations were based on species-specific measures of wing area, wing span and fat-free body mass [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Details regarding the collection of these measures, along with the data, can be found in the electronic supplementary material, appendices S1 and S2. For each species we calculated the maximum potential flight range for both the initial migratory journey and subsequent migrations following a refuelling stopover. These two categories were estimated using different calculations due to the different initial fat-loads of birds (see below). The maximum potential flight range before refuelling was defined as the distance an individual could fly before 95% of its fuel reserves were depleted. We also calculated the time it would take each species to fly these distances, based on their typical flight speed. We assumed that migration occurred in still-air conditions and at an altitude of 500 m (air density of 1.17 kg m
 <sup class="sup">−3</sup>); the latter is typical of passerine migration altitudes [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Pre-migratory fat fraction data were not available for most of our study species. Instead, we assumed a pre-migration fat load of 30% for all species, based on typical published pre-departure fat-loads for passerines [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. We assumed a refuelling stopover duration of 5 days for all species, based on published data [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Given an average fuel deposition rate of 4% of non-laden body mass per day [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], we assumed that birds depart from stopovers with a fat load of approximately 20%. By comparing the total required migration distance with the estimates of pre-migration and post-stopover maximum potential flight range for a species, we calculated the minimum number of stopovers required by an individual to complete the migration between pairs of start and end locations (as described above). See electronic supplementary material, appendix S1 for details on calculation of migration duration and number of stopovers.
</p>
