<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dynamics and outcome of predator–prey encounters are likely to be dependent on the different sensitivity of individual species (predators and prey) to elevated CO
 <sub>2</sub>. For example, studies involving predators and prey exposed to increased CO
 <sub>2</sub> have paired coral reef fish recruits with reef-based predators (
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Allan 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>). If we consider the differences between the pelagic environment inhabited by the recruits, and the reef environment, inhabited by the predators, these environments have very different levels of dissolved CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Coral reefs are dynamic shallow water habitats that experience diel cycles in CO
 <sub>2</sub> due to the photosynthesis and respiration of corals. Therefore, it is possible that reef-based predators have already been exposed to high CO
 <sub>2</sub> levels and may be displaying compensatory acclimation. This hypothesis is further supported by Jarrold and colleagues who showed that experimental exposure to diel CO
 <sub>2</sub> cycles (42 dph at 1000 μatm ± 300 and 1000 ± 500 μatm) can reduce associated behavioural impairments in coral reef fish (
 <xref rid="ref86" ref-type="bibr">Jarrold 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). In addition to the effects on the kinematics underlying predator–prey interactions that occur at least in some species, one of the most consistent impairments due to increased CO
 <sub>2</sub> levels is in the olfactory behaviour of species from multiple taxa (fish and invertebrates), across multiple ecosystems, responding maladaptively to predator odours and chemical alarm cues (for review, see 
 <xref rid="ref124" ref-type="bibr">Nagelkerken and Munday, 2016</xref>). A change in the olfactory landscape is a reliable indicator of a potential predatory attack. Therefore, misidentifying these important cues can lead to increased mortality rates (
 <xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Ferrari 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>).
</p>
