<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The most coherent features of the CMIP5 ensemble trends under the RCP4.5/8.5 forcing scenarios in the twenty-first century are summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20130296F6" class="xref">figure 6</xref>. There tends not to be profound differences between the RCP4.5/8.5 scenarios, with RCP8.5 usually simply producing larger changes than RCP4.5. The HIST westerly surface wind stress over the ACC has its maximum biased equatorwards and is too weak in general. Under future forcing, all models show a poleward shift in the westerly wind stress maxima and a general increase in westerly strength, characteristic of a more positive SAM. These changes are mitigated to some extent in the early twenty-first century in weaker climate forcing scenarios by ozone recovery. The ACC itself is better represented than in CMIP3, particularly its circumpolar path, which does not appear to be strongly influenced by wind stress in CMIP5, either in its historical state or under future wind shifts. Although improved relative to CMIP3, the ACC transport still has a very large variance across models, and, under future forcing, there are significant changes in its strength, but no consistency between models. This appears to be linked to changes in the subpolar gyre area, with expanded gyres leading to weaker ACCs, but there is as yet no clear dynamic understanding of this correlation, if one component forces the other or if both are responding to external forcing. The subpolar gyres themselves have dramatically different representations across models in circulation strength, area, vertical structure and response to future forcing. By contrast, the subtropical gyres have a coherent poleward shift in response to climate forcing. Although MOC diagnostics are limited, and there is large inter-model variance, the upper cell generally increases in strength owing to enhanced wind stress and weak eddy compensation, whereas the lower cell exhibits reduced overturning. This is consistent with enhanced CDW upwelling and AAIW formation and reduced AABW formation in water mass budgets. Increased interior mixing from AAIW to CDW confines the strengthening of the upper cell to the Southern Ocean, so the impact on carbon storage may be limited. 
</p>
