<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Harmonisation, coordination and use of local systems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change influences and is influenced by every sector in society, so collaboration between different government sectors, institutions and communities is required for effective adaptation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. The Outcome Statement from the 2012 PRCCHS recognised 
  <span class="italic">“that ‘climate change and health’ is a domain that is multi-sectoral and this consequently needs a broad range of people involved with skills, experience and expertise from all sectors and from grassroots through to national, regional and global levels”</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. The Statement also encourages 
  <span class="italic">“mainstreaming climate change and health issues into formal curricula at the primary, secondary and tertiary levels in health and other training institutions”</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Pacific, the national vulnerability assessments on the health impacts of climate change informed the development of National Climate Change and Health Action Plans (NCCHAPs). These NCCHAPs are highly dependent on donor funding if they are to be implemented; however, if they are implemented according to principles of development effectiveness, they have great potential to promote more harmonised national and regional health systems. It is critical that all agencies involved in climate change and health adaptation initiatives collaborate closely. Having both internal and external partners assessed for their collaborative capacity, including their ability and willingness to collaborate with other players, has been discussed recently by Lai, and is worthy of serious consideration for the Pacific [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change adaptation initiatives, wherever possible, should be conducted through existing national and regional systems and processes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. It is important to ensure that these existing systems are built upon and strengthened rather than ignored. All stakeholders have a responsibility to conduct thorough consultations before embarking on any development activity, including those relating to climate change and health. Part of this consultation should assess what systems are in existence. Regionally, a number of systems and networks are currently in existence, including the PPHSN, and the Pacific Health Information Network (PHIN). Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> gives an example of some needs identified in NCCHAPs and demonstrates what existing regional initiatives are in place to help support these activities.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Examples of needs identified in National Climate Change and Health Action Plans and what existing regional initiatives are in place to help support these activities</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr valign="top">
      <th>
       <span class="bold">PICT</span>
      </th>
      <th>
       <span class="bold">Example of key NCCHAP recommendations</span>
      </th>
      <th>
       <span class="bold">Examples of key existing regional initiatives</span>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td>Niue</td>
      <td>Improve HIS capacity, including data collection, coding, storage and analysis</td>
      <td>● Pacific data for decision-making program</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td rowspan="2"/>
      <td rowspan="2">Improve communication and collaboration between agencies to streamline activities, share information and resources and avoid duplication</td>
      <td>● Pacific Public Health Surveillance Network</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td>● Pacific Health Information Network</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td rowspan="3">Palau</td>
      <td rowspan="3">Build capacity in the following areas: reporting, coding, storage, analysis and dissemination of health data; recruitment and training of health personnel in biostatistics and epidemiology; public health, primary health care, environmental health and laboratory facilities; health research, including public and environmental health.</td>
      <td>● Pacific data for decision-making program</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td>● Pacific Public Health Surveillance Network – EpiNet, LabNet</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td>● Pacific Operational Research Course</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td rowspan="2">Republic of the Marshall Islands</td>
      <td rowspan="2">Improve health information/data collection system, including: improve current biostatistics reporting system; assure ongoing quality control; recruit and/or train extra personnel in environmental health (including vector-borne disease control), biostatistics and epidemiological analysis</td>
      <td>● Pacific data for decision-making program</td>
     </tr>
     <tr valign="top">
      <td>● Pacific Public Health Surveillance Network – EpiNet, LabNet</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change and health should not be viewed as a vertical programme, but rather one that expands across the entire health system and beyond. The real and potential negative impacts of taking a vertical approach to health system strengthening in low- and middle-income countries are well established. These include difficulties coordinating resources and activities, duplication of activities, loss of staff to vertical programs due to better pay, and inequalities created by focusing on vertical programs at the detriment of other important services [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. More than anywhere in the world, Pacific health systems cannot afford the luxury of vertical programs; the structurally limited human resources, largely resulting from tiny populations, within these systems are simply unable to meet the demand of such approaches. Integration of climate change and health across the health system is an issue that requires careful thought and extensive consultation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, efforts to strengthen capacity and systems for climate-sensitive disease surveillance and response should take a system-wide approach. This will have several benefits, including: 1) ensuring that climate change initiatives are well-integrated and embedded within existing systems and thus more likely to be sustained; 2) ensuring that existing systems are built upon rather than duplicated resulting in improved ownership and more effective investment; 3) helping to address the high levels of staff turnover in the Pacific by developing a cadre of health surveillance and response generalists who are equipped to respond to changing environments; and 4) ensuring that other aspects of the health system are not neglected.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information gathering, analysis and dissemination are priorities for the public health community in PICTs, especially in light of increasing risks posed by long-term global changes. Flexible and robust information systems can inform priority setting, the design of evidence-based interventions, the evaluation of outbreak response, and the creation of early warning systems. To date, however, health information systems in many PICTs have been limited and fragmented, and variable data content and quality have made it difficult to capture long-term trends in the region.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All PICTs conduct public health surveillance activities and submit data to regional and international agencies. Each country or territory has its own system of data collection, processing, and reporting. Key challenges are that there is heavy demand on PICTs to provide information on a large number of indicators, which are largely determined by external agencies, and these indicators are usually requested in formats prescribed differently by each of the agencies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further, training programs for data collection, analysis and interpretation at the national level have traditionally not always been coordinated between regional and global partners. The countries and territories concede that it is difficult to provide quality data with the high level of demands upon them, and that the data are therefore of limited usefulness in local and regional decision-making and action. One of the key functions of the PPHSN is to address these challenges. One of the mechanisms for this is through strengthening national syndromic surveillance systems in the Pacific. The WHO, SPC and other PPHSN partners have been working over a number of years to achieve this [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To complement this work, the Pacific Data for Decision-Making program assesses and develops harmonised plans to improve national syndromic surveillance systems. This work is undertaken at DDM courses with regional PPHSN partners and PICT Ministries and Departments of Health. Further work is needed to improve harmonisation of health and development activities in the Pacific; the PPHSN provides an important avenue for this to happen. The final point of the 2012 PRCCHS Outcome Statement highlights this need: 
  <span class="italic">“We recognise the important need for coordination of climate change and health research and activities across the Pacific to avoid duplication and to minimise the burden placed on local communities”</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]
  <span class="italic">.</span>
 </p>
</sec>
