<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Box 1. Interviewees on the topic of addressing external pressures when designing curriculum documents, responding to the question from the researcher: “Politically, climate change is a very controversial topic. Did that influence the approach taken to writing parts of the curriculum that related to climate change?” (if so: “How?”)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 4: …politics doesn’t influence when it comes to that aspect of it. That aspect of writing curriculum.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 1: We weren’t being told by the government—we had a lot of freedom with the document.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 2: There wasn’t really a place to go that said, “This is a good thing to do”. There certainly wasn’t any pressure at any government level to say, “You must incorporate climate change in your curriculum”.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 2: So we do get questions asked a lot from the Ministry of the Environment, but no direction.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 3: It can weigh into our considerations if we have groups come forward and exert pressure to include certain areas in the curriculum. But we really look for a balanced approach to the curriculum.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 6: …but nobody tells us that you have to teach this. But on the other hand there are so many, many groups that want you to teach what they want. Like…</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewer: NGOs?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 6: Environmental groups, yeah, NGOs. So many of all kinds, that want you to teach whatever, that don’t understand why you’re not doing X, Y or Z. Not just for science, for everything. But certainly for all the sciences also.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewee 5: No, climate change was included as a factual component of the curriculum based on the recommendation from [name of provincial report].</p>
</sec>
