<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Curriculum analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier we noted that while scientists and the Canadian government consider climate change to be a serious issue, concern for climate change is not overwhelming amongst young Canadians. One hypothesis that has been considered for the small risk perception associated with climate change is a lack of scientific literacy [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref066">66</a>]. Taken further, this hypothesis suggests that in order to solve the issue of apathy towards climate change we need more science education. However, Kahan et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref067">67</a>] found that scientific literacy does not correlate with concern for climate change among adults, but instead correlates with high polarization on the issue. However, among children ages 11 to 14, increased knowledge of climate change specifically (not general scientific literacy) is correlated with increased acceptance of the anthropogenic cause of climate change, and risk perception of climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref068">68</a>]. It is conjectured that this age-related discrepancy is due to the lack of ideological constraints at a young age. This is further evidenced by examples of teachers who do not themselves believe in anthropogenic climate change delivering climate change material to students who deduce anthropogenic causes independent of the beliefs of their teachers [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref069">69</a>]. Since education offers a way to promote acceptance of agreed upon concepts, it is important that teachers are instructed (through curriculum documents) to present the most relevant material regarding climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our review of curriculum documents, we listed six core teaching topics related to climate change, five of which were associated with support for mitigation policies (see 
  <a rid="pone.0218305.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0218305.t001">Table 1</a>). The remaining topic (It’s climate) simply describes those learning objectives associated with scientific literacy about the general climate, such as the existence and function of ocean currents, or the greenhouse effect. If scientific knowledge did lead to concern about climate change, then this focus on climate knowledge would be sufficient. However, studies have shown that knowledge about the environment does not lead to action for the environment [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref070">70</a>] nor for climate change mitigation [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref067">67</a>]. Yet we see that many provinces neglect to choose standards that go beyond scientific literacy and would actually lead to increased concern or action for climate change in their student populations. Instead they focus solely on what Kaiser and Fuhrer [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref044">44</a>] describe as declarative knowledge, when procedural or effectiveness knowledge (“We can fix it”) would lead to increased environmental citizenship practices. This is consistent with our review of international studies, which also found an emphasis on knowledge at the expense of civic-oriented teachings. We therefore suggest that as curriculum documents are revised in various provinces, more emphasis should be placed on “It’s warming”, “It’s us”, “It’s bad”, “Experts agree” and especially on “We can fix it”. In this process, the curriculum of Saskatchewan may serve as a model, as it performed best in our analysis.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations in the curriculum analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This analysis does not provide a complete picture on climate change education in secondary schools in Canada. Only curriculum documents that were available on government websites were examined, which would exclude locally developed courses (courses which are created for a small area or even a single school). International Baccalaureate courses, which are offered at 156 of the 3400 (or 4%) secondary schools in Canada [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref071">71</a>], and Advanced Placement courses, which are taken by less than 1% of Canadian secondary students [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref072">72</a>], were also not considered. Finally, it should be noted when comparing the different curricula that a province which covers more core teaching topics is not necessarily giving a more thorough treatment of climate change than a province covering fewer topics. For instance, British Columbia covers three topics, but does so in a mandatory course, while Alberta covers four topics, but in a course that not every student will take. In some provinces climate change may have received a more detailed treatment in a different course, for instance in a geography or social science course, or prior to the secondary level. However, we only examined science courses.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analyses such as this one also have temporal limitations: they are snapshots in time, and curriculum development is an ongoing effort. For instance, in June 2018 British Columbia published a major update to its science curriculum, with a full transition expected by the 2019/2020 school year [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref073">73</a>]. The three mandatory learning objectives shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218305.g001" href="#pone.0218305.g001">Fig 1</a> have been removed from Grade 10 in the draft documents for the new curriculum (though these objectives are retained at the elementary level) while new, optional courses in Grade 11 and 12 cover every core topic except for “Experts agree”. Some of these updates, such as acknowledging the importance of vegetarian diets to climate mitigation, are excellent examples of education making changes to reflect the latest scientific understanding [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref004">4</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref074">74</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref075">75</a>]. Because our interviews with curriculum writers referred to the old curriculum documents we make use of the old curriculum in our analysis, but provide details for the new draft documents in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218305.s003" href="#pone.0218305.s003">S1 Table</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are also numerous ways of presenting climate change (or environmental education) in the curricula. Some provinces might attempt to infuse such a topic throughout many different courses and grade levels (“mainstreaming”), while others might design one course with a significant environmental component to cover all desired learning objectives. It is also possible that teachers spend more time on environmental issues in other subjects or use climate change as an example in other units in the science curriculum.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">But there is some evidence that mainstreaming climate change produces inferior results, and it is better to have dedicated courses or units on important topics. When the Ontario government eliminated the environmental science course, intending for ecological concepts to be taught throughout the curriculum, teachers tended to neglect environmental science in favour of the core curriculum [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref076">76</a>]. Another, more recent study consisting of interviews with 11 educators teaching climate change in Alberta found that teachers were already wary of the subject of climate change, partially due to its inherently interdisciplinary nature and the perception of it being a fringe subject in the curriculum [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref077">77</a>]. Not all teachers have interdisciplinary training, so spreading environmental issues throughout many courses may result in them not properly addressing those issues. It also eliminates the credibility that the issue gains by being part of the explicit curriculum. Conversely, if teachers receive proper training and feel comfortable integrating these topics, it might prove to be a more effective method. One curriculum development interviewee, for instance, saw the integration of sustainability concepts throughout different grades and courses as a strong, positive characteristic of their province’s education system.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
