<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relatively high positive correlations between heavy metals in feathers of great and blue tit nestlings found in this study are probably the result of co-occurrence of these elements in the environment. Orłowski et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">2012</a>), analyzing interactions of concentrations of trace elements in various organs and tissues of nestling rooks 
  <span class="italic">C.</span> 
  <span class="italic">fragilegus</span>, showed similar relationships. Some investigators have also suggested that a similar way of gathering food can yield such a result (Pinowski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">1983</a>). Many studies on trace-element interactions in birds have presented antagonistic relations of lead and cadmium with zinc (Kamiński 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">1998</a>; Dauwe et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2002</a>; Kamiński and Warot 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2005a</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">b</a>). A lack of such antagonistic effects in our study is in agreement with results of Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2002</a>) concerning adult great and blue tits where high positive correlations between lead, cadmium and zinc were found in feathers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although, in general, mean lead and cadmium concentrations in feathers of great tit nestlings were higher than those in blue tits, the differences were nonsignificant. In contrast, zinc concentration was significantly higher in nestling blue tits than in great tits.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We are aware of only one other study performed on great and blue tit nestlings in which the investigators analyzed differences in the level of heavy-metal accumulation using feathers (Dauwe et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>). These investigators showed that there were no significant interspecific differences in measured elements between great and blue tit. Similarly to our results, Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>) noted slightly higher concentrations of lead and cadmium for great tit and, in the case of zinc, higher values in feathers of blue tit. In this study, investigators found that both species accumulated much higher amounts of zinc than lead and cadmium. These results were also comparable with our findings concerning differences in amounts of lead, cadmium, and zinc accumulated in feathers of tit nestlings. Studies comparing the quantity of accumulated metals in the case of great and blue tit nestlings were also performed by Eeva et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2009</a>). However in this study, trace elements were examined in nestling excrement without zinc evaluation for possible comparisons. The investigators showed that the levels of studied metals were relatively similar for both species, although there were some slight differences in levels of lead and cadmium with the values being higher for blue tit nestlings.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many investigators have suggested that prey insects may be a main source of metal contamination accumulated by insectivorous birds, particularly nestlings (Nyholm et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">1995</a>; Eeva and Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1996</a>; Berglund et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2011</a>; and many others); consequently, variation in metal concentrations between blue tit and great tit nestlings is likely to be associated with an interspecies difference in the diet. Both of these tit species are known to prefer caterpillars as the main food for nestlings (Cholewa and Wesołowski 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2011</a>), but the blue tit forages almost exclusively in deciduous tree canopies, whereas the great tit is much more versatile and often forages in bushes and even on the ground (Lack 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">1971</a>). An important addition to caterpillars, the principal food for great and blue tit nestlings are spiders (Török 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">1986</a>; Cholewa and Wesołowski 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2011</a>; Michalski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2011</a>). Blue tits are more specialized in caterpillars, especially in small-sized individuals (Nour et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">1998</a>; Bańbura et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1999</a>; Naef-Daenzer and Keller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">1999</a>; Török and Tóth 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">1999</a>). In the case of spiders, the great tit preys mainly on spiders that live on the ground (Lycosoids), whereas blue tits choose spider species living on plants (Török 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">1986</a>). Ground-dwelling spiders are recognized as being strong metal accumulators (Jung and Lee 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2012</a>). In addition, according to Eeva and Lehikoinen (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1996</a>), heavy metals might accumulate more in ground-living prey items. Therefore, differences in diet and foraging methods may have some effect on the interspecies variation in metal concentrations found in our study. In contrast, lower zinc concentration recorded for great tit nestlings may be explained by the physiological effects of pollution. According to Di Giulio and Scanlon (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">1985</a>), increased levels of cadmium can enhance zinc concentrations in the kidneys, probably by inducing metallothionein. This could cause a decrease in zinc accumulation in feathers. Berglund et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2011</a>), studying species-related differences between pied flycatcher and great tit nestlings, presented similar conclusions. They found a higher element concentration in feces and liver tissue of pied flycatcher 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span> nestlings and explained this result by a large proportion of insects of higher trophic levels in the food of pied flycatchers (Eeva et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1997</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2005</a>). The same conclusions come from the study of Eeva and Lehikoinen (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1996</a>) study also performed on pied flycatcher and great tit.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some investigators explain variations in heavy-metal concentrations between species by differences in metabolic rate. Deng et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2007</a>) found that smaller birds having higher metabolic rate showed faster accumulation of trace metals. Lebedeva (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">1997</a>), comparing 24 bird species varying considerably in body size, also showed that smaller specimens accumulated more lead in bones than those with higher body mass. According to the investigator, this resulted from differences in metabolic rate as well. In contrast, our results do not support this explanation. We considered site and year of study as the main factors significantly affecting heavy-metal variations in nestling feathers of great and blue tit. Regarding the differences in foraging methods and type of food, as mentioned previously, we believe that it would be difficult and inappropriate to explain variations in heavy-metal amounts accumulated by both tit species simply relying only on metabolic rate. In addition, Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>) concluded that small differences in heavy-metal concentrations between great and blue tit nestlings cannot be entirely explained by differences in their metabolic rates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Łódź agglomeration has been recognized as an area of ecological threat in Poland, which was confirmed by a special directive of the Polish Government in 1983 (Krok 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2004</a>). This is explained by the fact that on a relatively small area (400 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) with dense population, there are a few large power plants and many smaller local plants with inadequate fly-ash removal systems, which pollute local environment (Bem et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2003</a>). Jankiewicz et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2000</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2001</a>) found high heavy-metal accumulation in soil collected from allotment gardens near major roads and suggested that vehicle traffic is the main source of soil pollution in Łódź. In agreement with our expectations and the results of other investigators, our parkland study site was more contaminated than the forest site. We recorded 4 times higher lead and 5 times higher cadmium concentrations in vegetation samples collected from the parkland site compared with the forest site, although the latter one indicated 2 times higher zinc levels (Table 
  <a rid="Tab7" ref-type="table" href="#Tab7">7</a>). This can be explained by the fact that the parkland site is surrounded by roads with heavy traffic, which constitutes an important source of particulate matter (PM10) contributing heavy metals such as lead, cadmium and zinc (Apeagyei et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2011</a>). Based on data from 2002 to 2008, it was recorded that PM10 concentrations exceeded the permissible level in Łódź city center and its vicinity (Raport o Stanie Środowiska 2009). Thus, the parkland site in our study system is located in a zone of higher contamination than the forest area considering lead and cadmium. The impact of traffic on heavy-metal accumulation was confirmed by Alfani et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2000</a>), who clearly showed that concentrations of heavy metals in unwashed leaves of 
  <span class="italic">Q.</span> 
  <span class="italic">ilex</span> were several times higher along roads compared with urban and suburban parks in Naples. In contrast, higher values of zinc noted at the forest site may be related to the emission of combustion products from an EC3 power plant located in the north part of Łódź. According to Jankiewicz and Adamczyk (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2010</a>) this facility contributed to an increase of zinc in soil samples collected eastward from the power plant site. The investigators found that 26 % of samples collected east of the EC3 plant exceeded permissible levels of zinc. Considering that in Łódź, winds from the west and southwest directions are dominant, it can be assumed that this can be a relevant factor explaining increased levels of zinc at the forest site.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis of heavy-metal concentrations in feathers of tit nestlings collected between 2006 and 2008 showed differences between the study sites. In feathers of nestling blue tits, we found significantly higher lead and cadmium concentrations than in tits from the parkland site. In contrast, great tit nestlings did not differ between study sites, although nonsignificantly higher amounts of lead were recorded at the parkland site as well (Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). Such results may suggest that the blue tit may be considered a more sensitive species than the great tit, thus better allowing to identify and evaluate subtle differences in heavy-metal contamination. To confirm this conclusion, once again one should refer to interspecific dietary differences. According to Eeva et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2009</a>), despite similarities in diet between great and blue tit, the latter is characterized by a higher quantum of aphids (Hemiptera) in food supplied to nestlings. This group of arthropods tends to be particularly abundant in polluted environments (Eeva et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2009</a>) and as such we chose the parkland site in our study. Referring to an earlier study performed by Marciniak et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2007</a>), our study sites varied in percentage share of aphid, with considerably higher numbers observed at the parkland site. Therefore, these facts can explain significant differences found for blue tits and nonsignificant ones for great tits. Consequently, we suggest that blue tit nestling in our study system will better reflect the possible level of contamination.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering the data from the year 2008 only, we found significantly higher levels of lead and zinc in feathers of both tit species from the parkland area. Concentrations of cadmium were comparable among study sites, as in the case of feathers sampled from great tit nestlings, and for blue tit we noted higher values at the parkland site although this result was nonsignificant. The results of analyses of feathers collected in 2008 to some extent correspond with the results obtained in the leaf samples analysis, which showed the parkland area as being a more polluted study site (Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A similar relation between heavy-metal loads in vegetation samples and nestling feathers was reported by Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2004a</a>) for an intensely studied pollution gradient. In an earlier study, Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>) found significantly higher lead concentrations in great tit (4.83 µg/g) and blue tit (3.68 µg/g) nestling feathers collected from a more polluted site. In contrast, zinc concentration was significantly higher at the reference site. Moreover, Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>) showed that in excrements, all metals, including arsenic, cadmium and copper, had higher concentrations in the more polluted sites. The investigators suggested that the difference between the amounts of metals in excrements and in feathers of great and blue tit nestlings can be explained by the operation of homeostatic mechanisms (excretion of larger amounts of metals through excrements).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared with other studies, we found relatively high metal concentrations in feathers of blue tit and great tit nestlings. However, direct comparisons of the results may not be justified because of methodological differences between studies. Specifically, in this study, we sampled secondary flight feathers, whereas Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2004a</a>) used the outermost tail feathers. Different types of feathers develop at different rates, and the stage of feather development may influence metal concentration. Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2000</a>) collected tail feathers that were not fully grown and consisted mostly of the shaft, which, according to Goede and de Bruin (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">1984</a>), contain lower metal levels than the vanes. Burger and Gochfeld (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1992</a>) found significantly lower levels of lead and mercury in growing feathers than in fully formed feathers. Because the secondary flight feathers used in this study were more advanced in development than tail feathers and therefore might have accumulated more heavy metals, they may reflect pollution in a more adequate manner.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that mean metal concentrations in feathers of nestlings of both tit species differed between years. Concentrations of lead and zinc for both species and the concentration of cadmium for blue tit nestlings showed a similar pattern of variation with the means for 2007 being lowest. This suggests that some common factors may be responsible for this pattern. A possible factor, highly variable among the years of the study, is rainfall amount during the nesting stage of tits. A brood timing-specific sum of rainfall was also lowest in 2007, which could potentially contribute to the variation in feather metal loads. Taking into account that heavy metals are relatively easily biomagnified, it seems that it is appropriate to analyze how rainfalls impact plants, which are first-level trophic chain organisms. A few studies showed the influence of rainfalls on variations in heavy-metal concentration in vegetation samples. The presence of metals in plants may be an effect of endogenous accumulation (Bingöl et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2008</a>), but they may also result from concurring endogenous and exogenous pathways of metal contamination (Ho and Tai 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">1979</a>; Steinnes 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">1987</a>; Eriksson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">1996</a>; Thöni et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2011</a>). Bingöl et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2008</a>) reported markedly higher lead and nickel levels in trees 
  <span class="italic">Sophora japonica</span> L. during rainy seasons. According to Eriksson et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">1996</a>), cadmium concentrations accumulated in crops were positively correlated with precipitation. The studies performed in Norway also emphasized the relationship of rainfalls and heavy-metal amounts in the environment. Steinnes (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">1987</a>) noted that greater heavy-metal concentrations were found in vegetation samples collected from areas characterized by a high precipitation level. A similar conclusion can be drawn from the study performed by Thöni et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2011</a>), who showed that amounts of metals accumulated in mosses coincided with rainfalls. The investigators proved that lower rainfalls resulted in a lower input of heavy metals. Therefore, we also suggest that in our study sites, heavy metals can be introduced to the environment in the quantities dependent on the amounts of rainfall.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, the influence of rainfall may indirectly affect the uptake of metals. According to Leech and Crick (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2007</a>) heavy rain decreases the number of available invertebrates by washing them down from the vegetation. Such conditions may cause a limitation of food for canopy-feeders and force them to forage on the ground, and this, as has been shown earlier, may result in supplying offspring with more contaminated food. We suppose that this can explain why, in general, we recorded higher values of analyzed trace elements in years with higher precipitation level. However, we are aware of the need to conduct further research to confirm and refine these findings.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interyear variation in metal concentrations in birds, particularly in tit species, has not been studied intensely. Janssens et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2003</a>) examined the influence of exposure to heavy metals on the condition and health of great tit nestlings in three consecutive breeding seasons, but they did not directly analyze interannual variation. However, it is possible to use their published data to assess interyear differences (Eens et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1999</a>; Dauwe et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2002</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2004a</a>; Janssens et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2002</a>). Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2004a</a>) showed lower values of lead, higher concentrations of cadmium, and slightly higher loads of zinc in the comparison with the results for 1999 presented by Janssens et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2002</a>). The comparison of results obtained by Eens et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1999</a>) and by Dauwe et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2002</a>) shows that concentrations of lead and cadmium in feathers of adult blue tits also differed between years at the same study sites. Those differences can be explained by changes in the functioning of industrial facilities in the study areas. Similar conclusions can be drawn from the study on magpies 
  <span class="italic">Pica pica</span> by Dmowski (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">1997</a>), who noted a marked decrease over the years of lead and cadmium levels in magpie feathers after the activity of steelworks were limited at the turn of the 1990s. Thus, it appears that long-term variation in heavy-metal accumulation is related to changes in the pressure of anthropogenic factors. Closing large industrial factories or decreasing contamination extorted by introducing new, rigorous norms and regulations may significantly affect the overall level of heavy metals in the environment and also their amounts accumulated by birds (Dmowski 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">1997</a>; Dauwe et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2002</a>; Janssens et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2003</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, our results suggest that intersite variation in heavy-metal concentrations in nestlings of the great and blue tit, although not significant in all cases, reflect the level of contamination occurring at the study sites. We showed that concentrations of trace elements may also change between subsequent years. We suppose that rainfall may be considered an important factor determining the mobility of heavy metals in the environment and, thus, a factor enhancing their bioavailability for organisms, but this needs further research.</p>
</sec>
