<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses of data were performed using Statistica 9.1 software (StatSoft, Inc. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR740" href="#CR740">2010</a>). All statistical analyses were performed on ln-transformed values of response variables to normalize their distributions and stabilize variances (Sokal and Rohlf 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">1981</a>). Arithmetic means of nontransformed heavy-metal concentrations per nest with SE values are presented in tables and figures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To analyze the overall differences in heavy-metal concentrations between great and blue tit nestlings from two different study sites during 3 consecutive years, multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) was used. Heavy-metal concentrations were used as a multiple dependent variable with species, site, and year as factors. We applied the protected ANOVA approach by examining concentrations of particular metals using univariate ANOVAs after obtaining significant effects in MANOVA, which led to assessing which individual dependent variables contributed to significant multivariate effects (Scheiner 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">1993</a>). To examine differences among years, we used Tukey’s honestly significant difference (HSD) test preceded by Fisher LSD test. A similar approach to MANOVA, as an introductory step to protected univariate ANOVA, was also used to test differences in heavy-metal concentrations between years within the same site and between sites within each year for each study species separately. To evaluate differences in heavy-metal concentrations in vegetation samples from the two study areas, MANOVA followed by univariate ANOVA was used as well. To analyze the differences in rainfall between breeding seasons, we used ANOVA. Correlations between metals were calculated as Pearson product-moment correlation coefficients. In all statistical analyses, we assumed a level of significance at 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 (Sokal and Rohlf 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">1981</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
