<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosim</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After applying forcing functions and drivers, and fitting the model to observations, the model was successfully calibrated for the seventeen-year period 1996–2012. The application of forcing functions to specific predator-prey interactions improved the fit of the model by reducing sum of squares differences between model results and time-series data. A list of forcing function applications retained in the final model is presented in 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0214814.t003">Table 3</a>. While many alternative applications of forcing functions were evaluated, we retained only those that reduced the total SS, with two notable exceptions. The final model includes open water forcing of the interaction between on-shelf fish and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span> and the interaction between 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span> and other euphausiids because they are necessary for the model to recreate the increase in 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span> biomass documented in time-series observations of this species [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref063">63</a>]. To assess the impact of each forcing function application on the total SS, we singularly removed each forcing function application and noted the difference in total SS.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0214814.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0214814.t003</span>
  <span class="label">Table 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Forcing function applications retained in the final model to influence predator-prey interactions.</div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0214814.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0214814.t003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predator</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prey Forcing</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Killer Whale</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentoo penguin vulnerability increases with open water (0.62)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Leopard Seal</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antarctic fur seal vulnerability increases with open water and observed predation rate (2.16); Chinstrap penguins vulnerability increases with sea-ice index (0.35); Myctophids arena area increases with sea-ice index (0.15)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Antarctic Fur Seal</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalopods vulnerability and arena area increase with open water (0.09); On-shelf fish vulnerability and arena area increase with open water (0.68); Search rate for Large krill increases with sea-ice index (0.1)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Gentoo Penguin</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">On-shelf-fish vulnerability increases with open water (0.69); Large krill vulnerability increase with open water (0.43)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Chinstrap Penguin</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myctophids vulnerability and arena area increase with sea-ice index (0.09); On-shelf fish vulnerability and arena area increase with sea-ice index (0.1); Large Krill vulnerability and arena area increase with sea-ice index (1.33); Macrozooplankton vulnerability and arena area increase with sea-ice index (0.02)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">On-shelf fish</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">C</span>. 
       <span class="italic">gunnari</span> arena area increases with open water (-2.91)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">N</span>. 
        <span class="italic">rossii</span>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large krill vulnerability increases with open water (2.22); Other euphausiids vulnerability increases with open water (8.32)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">C gunnari</span>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other euphausiids vulnerability increases with open water (-4.06)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Large Krill (≥24 months)</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" style="background-color:#F2F2F2" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mesozooplankton vulnerability increases with sea-ice index (0.04); Large phytoplankton vulnerability and arena area increase with chlorophyll-
       <span class="italic">a</span> (3.8); Ice algae vulnerability and arena area increase with chlorophyll-
       <span class="italic">a</span> (1.48)
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Small Krill (&lt;24 months)</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small phytoplankton vulnerability and arena area increase with sea-ice index (0.17); Large phytoplankton arena area increases with chlorophyll-
       <span class="italic">a</span> (0.82); Ice algae vulnerability and arena area increase with sea-ice index (1.09)
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <fn id="t003fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The predator column indicates the impacted predator of the predator-prey interaction. The Prey Forcing column indicates the prey item and which forcing function was applied. The values in parentheses indicate the change in total SS when that forcing was removed. If a predator does not appear in the table, interactions with its prey are not forced in the final model.</p>
   </fn>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the sea-ice index to drive the biomasses of krill and 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span>. The linear response curve improved the group-specific SS for Large Krill from 20.5 to 11.69 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214814.g007" href="#pone.0214814.g007">Fig 7</a>). Applying a sigmoidal response curve with a steep positive response further improved the group-specific SS of Large Krill to 10.18 and coincidently made slight improvements to the fits for Adélie penguin, chinstrap penguin, gentoo penguin, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span> and 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span>. The total SS for the model, was approximately four less using the sigmoidal response curve than when using the linear response curve. We retained the sigmoidal response curve in the model. The model fit for krill was further improved after the fit for 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span> improved. Applying a linear curve to drive 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span>, changed the trajectory of the model results to align with the documented decline in the biomass of this species and reduced the group-specific SS from 9.321 to an SS of 0.621. Applying a normal response curve to drive 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span> decreased model performance, with the group-specific SS rising to 20.20. We retained the linear response curve in the model.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0214814.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0214814.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Evaluation of response curves for krill.</div>
   <p>Comparison of model fits (by group-specific SS) for krill when no curve was applied (a), the linear functional response curve was applied (b), and the sigmoidal functional response curve was applied(c). Curves are displayed in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214814.g003" href="#pone.0214814.g003">Fig 3</a> In all panels the dots represent the observed data and the lines represent model results. Note that the y-scale in panel a is significantly larger than the other two panels.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0214814.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total SS for the model without forcing was 70.77 and simulation results did not fit observed trends in biomass (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214814.g008" href="#pone.0214814.g008">Fig 8</a>). After sea-ice forcing of predator-prey interactions and driving the biomasses of krill and 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span>, the group-specific SS for krill alone decreased nearly 50% from 19.71 to 10.04. The total SS dropped to 25.39, and the simulation results better fitted the observed data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214814.g008" href="#pone.0214814.g008">Fig 8</a>; model results from the final fitted model for the 27 uncalibrated species are presented in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0214814.s007" href="#pone.0214814.s007">S7 File</a>). Although the total SS decreased considerably, the fit for 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span> worsened but its approximation of the patterns documented in the time series for this species improved (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214814.g008" href="#pone.0214814.g008">Fig 8</a>). Sums of squares difference for each species group ranged from less than 0.5 to 10.04 in the final fitted model. Species for which yearly data points were available, and which demonstrated an obvious trend in the biomass, had the smallest group-specific SS values. The largest group-specific SS (10.04) was associated with large krill, which has high variability in the time-series data and lacks an obvious trend in biomass. Krill data were entered into the model without any smoothing because krill biomass is known to be highly variable both temporally and spatially [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref012">12</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref013">13</a>]. While the model was not able to recreate all the variability evident in the krill dataset, the simulation result was a reasonable approximation of krill’s temporal dynamics in Statistical Subarea 48.1.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0214814.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0214814.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Results of Ecosim simulations.</div>
   <p>Biomass time series are plotted as black points. The relative biomass results from the model are plotted as lines. Simulations without sea-ice forcing are shown in grey; simulations with sea-ice forcing are shown in black. The group-specific sum of squares (SS) difference between simulation results and observed data are shown for each species.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0214814.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MC sensitivity analysis yielded 200 simulations that produced balanced models. The total SS for each simulation varied between 21.85 and 38.17. The groups that exhibit the highest variability and contributed most to the SS, and thus were the most sensitive to the input parameters, were the two fish species 
  <span class="italic">N</span>. 
  <span class="italic">rossii</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0214814.g009" href="#pone.0214814.g009">Fig 9</a>). The “best” MC simulation identified a slightly better total SS than that achieved during the model calibration process. This better fit was achieved on runs where the adjusted input parameters resulted in better fitting simulations for 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span>. Among various differences in biomasses and rates, the best fitting MC simulation had notably higher biomass for large krill (9402 t/100 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>), and salps (17458 t/100km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) and lower biomass for myctophids (276 t/100 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>). We chose the purposefully calibrated model over the best MC simulation because the biomass densities of krill and salps in the former model were more consistent with values found in the literature and better supported by field observations. The best fitting MC simulation used parameter estimates that we consider to be less plausible in reality.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0214814.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0214814.g009</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Results of twenty randomly selected Monte Carlo trials.</div>
   <p>Each line represents the relative biomass trajectory of that species over the course of a single trial. Note that the starting value for all species is one, and model results is relative to that value. Also Note that the y-axis scales for 
    <span class="italic">N</span>. 
    <span class="italic">rossii</span> and 
    <span class="italic">C</span>. 
    <span class="italic">gunnari</span> are two to three orders of magnitude larger than the scales for the other species, indicating much higher sensitivity and uncertainty for these two species.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0214814.g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
