<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Western Antarctic Peninsula (WAP) is one of the most rapidly warming regions on Earth [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref003">3</a>] with an average air temperature increase at the surface of approximately 5-6° C since 1960 [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref005">5</a>]. Long-term datasets describing the sea-ice regime illustrate significant changes in response to this prolonged warming and increasing number of days where the air temperature exceeds freezing [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref004">4</a>]. “Permanent” ice shelves that rest over the sea have been retreating for the past 20 years, and winter sea-ice concentration and extent are both decreasing [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref002">2</a>]. Sea ice is forming later in the season and retreating earlier [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref004">4</a>]. Throughout the Antarctic Peninsula region the winter-ice season has decreased by one to two days per year on average [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref004">4</a>], and the total the sea-ice season shrank by 92 days from 1979–80 to 2012–13 [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref002">2</a>]. Sea ice is critically important in structuring WAP marine ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref002">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine food webs in the WAP are often described as krill-centric [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref006">6</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref008">8</a>]. Diet studies of numerous predators in the region indicate that Antarctic krill (
  <span class="italic">Euphausia superba</span>, hereafter krill) is an important prey species for a wide variety of predators [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref009">9</a>]. Krill are the target of the largest (by tonnage) Antarctic fishery, with about 155,000 t yr
  <span class="sup">-1</span> landed from around the WAP, within Statistical Subarea 48.1 as defined by the Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources (CCAMLR) [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref010">10</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref011">11</a>]. Krill are patchily distributed, and krill abundance can vary by orders of magnitude [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref012">12</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref015">15</a>]. These realities imply that the role of krill in the food web can vary both spatially and temporally.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is evidence that warming around the WAP has altered the food web [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref001">1</a>]. In areas that have experienced sustained warming and associated ice loss, salps (
  <span class="italic">Salpa thompsoni</span>) may replace krill as the dominant phytoplankton consumer [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref016">16</a>]. Top predators such as Adélie (
  <span class="italic">Pygoscelis adeliae</span>) and chinstrap (
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">antarcticus</span>) penguins may be declining throughout the WAP, and these declines are correlated with increasing temperatures and ice loss [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref017">17</a>]. Abundant piscine predators like 
  <span class="italic">Gobionotothen gibberifrons</span> also appear to have experienced significant declines yet it is unclear what is causing these trends [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref018">18</a>]. The changing sea-ice regime is likely influencing predator-prey dynamics and population dynamics at all levels of the food web. Marine-resource managers for the region may find it useful to explore how changes in the sea-ice regime and consequent effects on the food web could impact harvested and monitored species before making changes to fisheries-management strategies. Such explorations may be particularly helpful in light of ongoing discussions regarding the design of marine protected areas (MPAs) in the region (paragraphs 5.63–5.69 of [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref019">19</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The software package Ecopath with Ecosim (EwE) was designed to facilitate the creation of dynamic food-web models that can be used to aid the development of fisheries-management strategies, including the development of MPAs [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref020">20</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref021">21</a>]. To explore such options, EwE implements a mass balanced food-web model (Ecopath) and time dynamic simulations (Ecosim) that aim to recreate observed biomass trends for key components in the ecosystem. There are three published EwE models that overlap in whole or in part with the WAP: Cornejo-Donoso and Antezana [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref022">22</a>], Ballerini et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref007">7</a>] and Suprenand and Ainsworth [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref023">23</a>]. Two other EwE models have been made available in the grey literature [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref024">24</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref025">25</a>]. All five sets of authors produced mass balanced Ecopath models, but none of the models were calibrated by fitting to time-series observations in Ecosim. The previous models do not recreate observed trends in the biomasses of several monitored species. Furthermore, because species are aggregated, the existing models do not facilitate consideration of species-specific responses to environmental change and alternative management decisions. These existing models are poorly suited to be used as decision support tools for the MPA process.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The objectives of this study are to1) develop a mass balanced food-web model that explicitly describes the dynamics of monitored and declining species and 2) calibrate the model by fitting time dynamic simulations to observed trends in the biomasses of species that are monitored in the WAP. Having accomplished these objectives, we assert the model would be suitable for further development into a spatial model to be used as a decision support tool within the CCAMLR process to designate MPAs. The work presented here evaluates the extent to which changes in sea-ice cover explain observed variations in species biomass by including the sea-ice regime as an environmental driver. We note that the relationship between krill and sea ice is uncertain [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref014">14</a>] and that other environmental drivers may influence krill and its predators. The work presented here focuses on the role of sea ice in structuring the food web in the WAP as one plausible hypothesis to explain temporal patterns of biomass for eight monitored species.
 </p>
</sec>
