<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea-ice in dynamic simulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current climate models indicate that sea-ice loss will continue [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref074">74</a>]. In the future, successful management of marine living resources around the WAP could depend on understanding and predicting how species might respond to changes in the sea-ice regime. The simulations presented here investigated the role of temporal sea-ice dynamics as one possible mechanism influencing biomass. This was accomplished by using sea ice to force predation interactions and drive the model for large krill and the fish 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span>. Including the sea-ice regime allowed the model to recreate documented biomass trends and improved the fit by decreasing the total SS approximately 65%. While the model now adequately recreates documented changes in biomasses of the eight monitored species, it does not capture all the variability in available time-series data. Some factor not currently included in the model likely has a notable impact on the population dynamics of krill and krill predators. The results of our simulations are consistent with previous studies [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref002">2</a>] and indicate that the role of sea-ice in structuring the WAP marine ecosystem may be both central and complex.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sea-ice index used in our model was a normalized, relative measure of annual minimum sea-ice area. Previous studies used the winter maximum sea-ice to model recruitment and survival of krill dependent predators [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref056">56</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref057">57</a>]. Summer is the breeding season for monitored krill predators such as penguins [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref075">75</a>] and Antarctic fur seals [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref003">3</a>]. These species are central place foragers and are required to return to their colonies to feed their young during the breeding season. Summer environmental conditions, including the interaction of sea-ice, temperature, and precipitation patterns, have been shown to impact breeding success and penguin population dynamics [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref076">76</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref077">77</a>]. While summer sea-ice minima, rather than winter maxima, were used in the present study, our work did not contradict earlier findings. Sea-ice loss is impacted by a positive feedback loop of ice-free waters absorbing more solar radiation and warming faster [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref002">2</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref058">58</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref059">59</a>]; summers following colder icier winters are therefore likely to be colder and icier. Hinke et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref056">56</a>] focused on the northern part of WAP, where there seemed to be more winter sea-ice variability than what was recorded in the Palmer LTER data set. Here we came to the same conclusion as Hinke et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref056">56</a>] that seasonal sea-ice dynamics, whether lagged winter maxima in the north or normalized summer minima in the south, influence krill and penguin abundance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Krill have been considered ice dependent [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref016">16</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref078">78</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref079">79</a>], and the size of the krill population has increased following years of increased winter sea-ice extent [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref016">16</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref041">41</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref060">60</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref061">61</a>]. However, previously published studies describe more general response patterns. Here we present a well-fitting curve that describes how krill respond to our sea-ice index. The curve might be useful in other modeling studies that explore how sea-ice dynamics affect the regional ecosystem. We assert that our model can be used to explore how krill might respond to future changes in the sea-ice regime as the area continues to warm. Similarly, we identified a sea-ice response curve for 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span> that allowed the model to recreate observed trends in the abundance of this fish. A direct link between this species and sea ice has not previously been noted in the literature. While the sea-ice response curve worked in the model, it may represent effects of other (environmental) drivers that have not been well documented for this species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forcada et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref080">80</a>] indicated that sea-ice conditions alone were unlikely to affect penguin population dynamics but suggested that ice might affect trophic dynamics. Similarly, Trivelpiece et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref054">54</a>] suggested that krill availability, which may be tied to sea-ice conditions, influences predator abundance. Our results support the findings of Forcada et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref080">80</a>]. We were only able to recreate historic trends in the biomasses of monitored species when the sea-ice regime was simultaneously used to drive krill biomass and influence predator-prey dynamics for 10 predators. Indeed, sea-ice might influence trophic interactions beyond what was suggested by Forcada et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref080">80</a>], who focused on penguins.
 </p>
</sec>
