<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Adaptation Initiatives in Municipalities or Regional Health Authorities</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among Canada’s six largest municipalities, only Toronto and Vancouver have adaptation plans available. Montreal, Ottawa and Edmonton report health adaptation initiatives in other documents or on websites. Calgary is the only large municipality that does not report any health adaptation initiatives online (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-00623-t004" href="#ijerph-12-00623-t004">Table 4</a>). Though regional health authorities are responsible for sub-provincial or sub-territorial health care delivery, none of the six sampled regional health authorities report any health adaptation initiatives or discuss climate change on their websites. Nonetheless, Vancouver reports a partnership on one initiative with its regional health authority, Vancouver Coastal Health.
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-00623-t004" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="pii" class="object-id">ijerph-12-00623-t004_Table 4</span>
  <span class="label">Table 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Adaptation plans and initiatives in Canada’s largest municipalities.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipality</th>
     <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adaptation Plan Available</th>
     <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Adaptation Initiative(s) Reported</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calgary, AB</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edmonton, AB</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Montreal, QC</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ottawa, ON</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toronto, ON</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vancouver, BC</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
     <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">√</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toronto and Vancouver emerged as leading municipalities in public health adaptation to climate change based on our analysis of publically available information. Both are the only municipalities reviewed to include plans for monitoring and evaluation of adaptations implemented. The majority of Toronto’s health adaptation initiatives were adaptation actions that addressed extreme heat, but others addressed air quality, food safety and security, UV radiation, floods and general health vulnerabilities. Toronto’s adaptation initiatives are highly varied, including actions such as providing cooling centres during extreme heat events, and implementing a heat alert system and hot weather response plan.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, the majority of health adaptation initiatives implemented by the City of Vancouver address heat-related climate change health risks. Almost half of the initiatives consider vulnerable groups, primarily homeless and low-income populations.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Edmonton, Montreal and Ottawa do not have publically available or reported adaptation plans, but they describe a small number of health adaptation initiatives in other documents or on their websites. These initiatives are predominantly management and planning adaptation actions (e.g., contingency plans for the increase in heat waves, emergency response plans for severe weather events), while Ottawa also reports some initiatives aimed at altering practice and behavior (e.g., urban heat island controlling methods, West Nile disease control measures).</p>
</sec>
