<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="simple" id="L1" class="list">
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">True primary prevention of adverse climate change impacts on human health (along with many other aspects of the biophysical world) requires a significant worldwide reduction in greenhouse gas emissions, which is possible to achieve with present technology. It is encouraging that the international community recently agreed to curb their greenhouse gas emissions over the coming decades and to limit global temperature rise to &lt; 2° Celsius in this century relative to pre-industrial levels. An international implementation plan on climate policy is urgently needed to ensure sufficient reductions in emissions at the global level. It is important to note that several countries have already substantially invested in renewable energy and much more can be achieved (
   <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Frankfurt School-UNEP Collaborating Centre for Climate &amp; Sustainable Energy Finance 2016</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Because additional warming is already committed within the climate system irrespective of actions taken today, cost-effective health-protective adaptive strategies are clearly needed, particularly for vulnerable communities and regions. Adverse environmental and social impacts of climate change will reduce the resilience of many communities, especially the poorest, and in the longer term may overwhelm the coping capacity of many societies (
   <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Frumkin et al. 2008</xref>; 
   <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Confalonieri and Tong 2015</xref>). Policies and measures that are implemented need to be monitored, evaluated, and refined through well-designed surveillance and research. Little is known about the effective public health adaptation strategies (
   <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Toloo et al. 2014</xref>). Interdisciplinary research is required to identify, implement, and refine these strategies. More efforts are clearly needed in this area.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Although, at present, most of the temperature-related mortality burden is attributable to cold, and the impact of days of extreme temperature is far less than that attributable to milder but suboptimal weather, this situation can rapidly change as global warming proceeds. Although it is necessary to develop and implement public health interventions for the milder but more significant temperature excursions and increased temperature variability, health authorities should place emphasis on preparing for seasonal changes in mortality patterns and a significant increase in heat-related morbidity and mortality in the near future.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">The frequency, intensity, duration, and geographic extent of extreme weather events (e.g., cyclones, heat waves, floods, bushfires, and droughts) are likely to increase in most parts of the world, as climate change continues. Disaster management, community resilience, health care facilities, and public health infrastructure need to be enhanced to respond to these events. Early warning systems for heat waves, floods, and other disasters should be developed and/or improved so that public health impacts of such events can be minimized and prevented.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Vulnerability assessment is still in its infancy, but it should be an area of research that is encouraged to develop. A literature review on this topic is currently underway. It is important to identify and protect vulnerable communities and population groups in the climate change–related health risk assessment and management.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Emerging and resurging infectious diseases are an important health threat. An enhanced effort is required to develop vaccines for climate sensitive diseases. It is also critical to quantify the impact of climate change on the transmission of infectious diseases.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Co-benefit analyses of climate change mitigation and adaptation strategies are an important and emerging field. More evidence-based co-benefit analyses are required from a policy perspective. For example, the phase out of coal is proposed as part of an early and decisive policy package that targets air pollution from the transport, agriculture, and energy sectors, and it aims to reduce the health burden of particulate matter and short-lived climate pollutants, which will yield immediate gains for society (
   <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Watts et al. 2015</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">It is important to develop scenario-based forecasting models to estimate climate change impacts after incorporating sociodemographic and technological change scenarios because these models can be used in evidence-informed policy making and evaluation. A standard approach for developing scenario-based forecasting models needs to be established and evaluated.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">A global health monitoring and surveillance system (e.g., global burden of disease assessment) needs to incorporate climate change impacts (
   <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">WHO 2014</xref>; 
   <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">GBD 2013 Mortality and Causes of Death Collaborators 2015</xref>). Health risks posed by climate change are likely to increase and no country will be immune from these risks. Climate resilient health systems are urgently required (
   <xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">WHO 2015</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">There is a need to invest in these priority areas from governments, funding agencies, and nongovernment organizations. We believe that these investments are essential to protect population health from the impacts of climate change.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
