<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Apart from these factors, interspecific hybridization has been assumed to foster invasions since a seminal paper of Ellstrand and Schierenbeck (
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). Indeed, there are prominent examples of highly invasive hybrids. For instance, several species of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Tamarix</italic> have been introduced to North America during the 19th century. Although all of these species have escaped cultivation, by far the most successful and widespread invader is the hybrid between 
 <italic class="italic">T. ramosissima</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">T. chinensis</italic> (Gaskin &amp; Kazmer, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Gaskin &amp; Schaal, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). The same Eurasian 
 <italic class="italic">T. ramosissima</italic> has recently started to hybridize with native 
 <italic class="italic">T. usneoides</italic> in South Africa (Mayonde, Cron, Gaskin, &amp; Byrne, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Other examples of genera that have produced successful invasive hybrids include 
 <italic class="italic">Rhododendron</italic> (Milne &amp; Abbott, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> (Thompson, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">Senecio</italic> (Abbott et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Helianthemum</italic> (Rieseberg et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). More generally, the idea that interspecific hybrids may be especially successful invaders has been corroborated by a recent meta‐analysis (Hovick &amp; Whitney, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The possible reasons for hybrid success include increased phenotypic or genotypic variability, phenotypic novelty arising from transgressive segregation or adaptive introgression, and heterosis effects (Prentis, Wilson, Dormontt, Richardson, &amp; Lowe, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Heterosis effects may be maintained especially when hybridization is accompanied by allopolyploidization and/or a shift to apomictic reproduction, which sustain heterozygosity.
</p>
