<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="wcc591-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DETECTING ANTHROPOGENIC TRENDS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of the emissions of greenhouse gases and aerosol particles, the byproducts of industrialization, have already been unequivocally detected in the warming of the Earth since the 19th century. Given the established evidence that Sahel rainfall responds to anomalies in regional energy fluxes and in global SST, we can ask what part of the observed variability was ultimately driven by past anthropogenic emissions and what will be the impact of future emissions.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tools to answer such questions are computer models that are driven by the history of atmospheric composition (Coupled ocean and atmospheric Global Climate Model) or the history of anthropogenic emissions (Earth System Models, which simulate the chemical and biological systems that process anthropogenic emissions and calculate the resulting changes in atmospheric composition).
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="wcc591-note-0005" href="#wcc591-note-0005">4</a> Dozens of such models exist (Taylor, Stouffer, &amp; Meehl, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0138" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0138">2012</a>), with different levels of complexity and performance, and the global climate simulated by each differs in some measure from both the observed climate and that of other simulations. Such disparities derive from systematic model errors (biases) and from the chaotic nature of the climate (internal variability). The mean of the ensemble of simulations provides our best estimate of the forced climate variations (signal) and the intra‐ensemble spread is one (likely optimistic) indicator of the uncertainty of such estimate (noise).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many studies have established the presence of a forced component in the Sahel drought; it is the magnitude of such component that is still vigorously debated. Qualitatively, we understand the drying of the Sahel from the 1960s through the 1980s as influenced by the emissions of reflective aerosols (mostly sulfates) in North America and Europe. These aerosols cause cooling via scattering of solar radiation away from the surface both directly and because they make clouds brighter and more long‐lived. But aerosols are easily removed by the atmosphere (either by dry deposition or by rainfall), so that their cooling effect is regional and hemispheric, not global (Myhre, Shindell, Bréon, &amp; Table, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0097">2013</a>). The cooling of the NH relative to the SH is expected to shift the zonal mean ITCZ to the south (Schneider et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0122">2014</a>, Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0002">2</a>b), and the drying of the Sahel during these decades has indeed been interpreted as part of the ITCZ response to the aerosol forcing (Ackerley et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0001">2011</a>; Biasutti &amp; Giannini, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0012">2006</a>; Booth, Dunstone, Halloran, Andrews, &amp; Bellouin, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0019">2012</a>; Hwang et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0066">2013</a>; Rotstayn &amp; Lohmann, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0114">2002</a>). At the same time, natural variability in the ocean–atmosphere system can also create a hemispheric gradient of SST and especially strong anomalies in the Atlantic basin,
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="wcc591-note-0006" href="#wcc591-note-0006">5</a> either through a change in the deep oceanic circulation (Zhang &amp; Delworth, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0157" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0157">2005</a>) or through atmospheric fluxes acting on the oceanic mixed layer (Clement et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0027">2015</a>). The relative importance of these mechanisms—a radiatively forced cooling, a rearrangement of the oceanic circulation, and atmospheric noise reddened by oceanic processes—in creating the observed SST anomalies is model dependent, with uncertainties deriving mostly from the treatment of the aerosol–cloud interactions (Zhang et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0158" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0158">2013</a>) and the strength of the simulated natural variability in the oceanic meridional circulation (Ba et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0003">2014</a>). The task of going beyond the attribution to external forcing of SST anomalies to attribute Sahel rainfall anomalies themselves to such forcings is especially challenging. Because few models are capable of reproducing the full range of observed variability in the latter (Biasutti, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0011">2013</a>), it is difficult to estimate what fraction of the observed trend ought to be reproducible (and attributable to external forcing), and what fraction is purely atmospheric noise.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The debate on the detection of anthropogenic signals extends to the mechanisms of recovery of the rainfall since the 1990s. If oceanic internal variability is dominant, drying, and recovery would naturally oscillate and their pacing would be well captured by an index of SST variability in the north Atlantic. If aerosols are dominant, the recovery of the rains would follow from reduced sulfate emissions in the United States and Europe and thus a reduction in the inter‐hemispheric aerosol loading (even though pollution of this kind has increased in Asia over the same period so that global sulfate aerosol forcing has held steady; Myhre et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0097">2013</a>). A third option is also possible: Greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions have increased unabated over the most recent three decades—can they be causing positive rainfall anomalies in the Sahel?
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the ensemble mean of the latest generation of climate models, when the GHG‐forced signal is dominant (e.g., in idealized simulations or scenarios for the 21st century). Sahel rainfall does indeed increase (Biasutti, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0011">2013</a> and Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0007">7</a>). Yet, model disagreement is still substantial, which complicates the detection of an emerging GHG signal in the Sahel recovery. We make sense of the model disagreements as a consequence of the two (direct and indirect) paths in which GHG affect Sahel rainfall: via increased energy input into the land surface and the atmosphere and via changes in the global SST.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="wcc591-note-0007" href="#wcc591-note-0007">6</a> The direct effect of GHGs is to wet the Sahel for all models (Biasutti, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0011">2013</a>; Gaetani et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0044">2016</a>). This is consistent with the interpretation of the monsoon as a facet of the energetically direct tropical circulation (Biasutti et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0016">2018</a>) and, mechanistically, with the warming over the Sahara and the strengthening of the monsoonal circulation (Biasutti, Sobel, &amp; Camargo, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0015">2009</a>; Haarsma, Selten, Weber, &amp; Kliphuis, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0053">2005</a>). The key aspect of the anomalous circulation is not the deepening of the heat low and an intensification of the inflow at low level, but the low's shift northward and the weakening of the dry intrusion by the return flow of the shallow meridional circulation (Gaetani et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0044">2016</a>; Shekhar &amp; Boos, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0126">2017</a>). In contrast, SST‐mediated Sahel rainfall anomalies are less robust across models. This is for two reasons: First, because of the uncertainty in the pattern of projected anomalies, specifically in the degree of warming in the North Atlantic (Giannini et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0048">2013</a>; Park et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0106">2015</a>) and the Mediterranean (Park et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0107">2016</a>) relative to the overall warming. Second, because of the different atmospheric sensitivity to the same oceanic anomalies (Biasutti, Held, Sobel, &amp; Giannini, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0013">2008</a>; Gaetani et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0044">2016</a>; Held, Delworth, Lu, Findell, &amp; Knutson, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0058">2005</a>; Hill, Ming, Held, &amp; Zhao, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0062">2017</a>; Park et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0106">2015</a>). Different atmospheric sensitivities to overall warming are likely to stem from how the models produce convective rainfall given a certain large‐scale atmospheric environment.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="wcc591-note-0008" href="#wcc591-note-0008">7</a> Different responses to the same SST patterns are not easily explained (Rowell, Senior, Vellinga, &amp; Graham, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0116">2015</a>). Nevertheless, there is qualitative agreement across models that the indirect effect of GHG is to dry the Sahel (Biasutti, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0011">2013</a>). Thus, the overall effect of GHG is the sum of competing direct and indirect effects.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="wcc591-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Top multimodel averaged, annual mean rainfall anomalies (in mm/day) between future and past (2031–2060 in the RCP8.5 scenario and 1960–1990 in the Historical scenario), averaged over eight climate models. Field values are the anomalies in the raw model output (regridded to 1° resolution). Filled circles are anomalies in the bias‐corrected output. The boxes indicate the sites of West Sahel and Central Sahel. Bottom: Smoothed daily anomalies in rainfall (mm/day, green) and temperature (°C, red) averaged over the sites of (left) West and (right) Central Sahel. The solid line is the multi‐model mean, the shading represents 1 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> scatter (Reprinted with permission from Guan, Sultan, Biasutti, Baron, and Lobell (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0051">2017</a>). Copyright 2017 Elsevier)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="WCC-10-na-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The signature of GHG forcing might be easier to detect in the appearance of zonal asymmetries in Sahel rainfall (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0007">7</a>a). GHGs wet most of the Sahel, but not its westernmost portion. This zonal asymmetry likely derives from the deepening of the SHL. Because the low is not zonally symmetric but is concentrated over the western Sahara, an enhanced heat‐low circulation contributes opposite‐sign anomalies in the east–west direction, as the geostrophic wind advects dry subtropical air to the western Sahel and moist tropical air to its eastern part (Lavaysse, Flamant, &amp; Janicot, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0082">2010</a>). Warming of the Sahara either directly by GHG or through the effect of warm and moist advection from a warmer ocean have the same effect on the position and strength of the SHL, thus the asymmetry between the eastern and western Sahel rainfall anomalies is the result of the combined (direct+indirect) response to GHG (Gaetani et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0044">2016</a>) and can supply a robust metric for the detection of GHG‐induced trends.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another robust aspect of the Sahel response to GHG is its seasonality, in that the wetting is mostly confined to the late portion of the rainy season (Biasutti &amp; Sobel, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0014">2009</a>, Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0007">7</a>b). We expect this seasonal asymmetry to be specific to the GHG forcing. Thus its emergence could help us detect a GHG signal in the Sahel. The reason why we expect this seasonal asymmetry is the following (see also how it was formalized by Song et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0129">2018</a>): The early rainy season is a time when the conditions for convective instability are rarely met—so an increase in global atmospheric stability will exacerbate inhibition and lead to drying (Chou &amp; Neelin, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0026">2004</a>; Giannini, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0046">2010</a>; Lintner &amp; Neelin, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0086">2007</a>). In this view, the role of direct GHGs forcing is to provide the energy necessary to overcome the inhibition and switch from a dry to a wet regime (Giannini, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0046">2010</a>; Seth et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0124" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0124">2013</a>). Conversely, the core rainy season is a time when ascent is always possible—so an increase in global specific humidity will intensify rainfall (Held &amp; Soden, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0059">2006</a>; Huang, Xie, Hu, Huang, &amp; Huang, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0064">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fingerprint of GHG on Sahel rainfall outlined above is muddled by substantial uncertainties. First and foremost, there remain outlier models that project Sahel rainfall anomalies with different seasonal patterns and opposite annual‐mean signs; these are state‐of‐the‐art models without any egregious deficiencies and cannot easily be dismissed (Rowell et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0116">2015</a>). Second, even among the models that agree on the sign of the GHG‐induced signal, there are large differences in the magnitude of the rainfall changes and in the spatial and seasonal patterns: the boundaries between negative and positive anomalies in the east–west direction and between early and late season are highly variable across models (Biasutti, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0011">2013</a>). These uncertainties hamper the unequivocal definition of a global warming signal and the detection of its emergence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, we note that some features of the expected pattern of GHG‐forced anomalies have been recorded in observations. For example, Ali and Lebel (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0002">2009</a>) and Lebel and Ali (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0083">2009</a>) noted that, by 2007, western regions of the Sahel (Senegal and western Mali) had not recovered from drought, while regions further to the east (Burkina Faso and Niger) had done so, in qualitative agreement with expectation from GHG‐forced simulations. In contrast, Zhang, Brandt, Guichard, Tian, and Fensholt (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0159" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0159">2017</a>) reported a stronger recovery of rainfall totals for the 1983–2015 period in the broadly defined West African Sahel, compared to regions to the East (Chad, Sudan), but lack of ground calibration for the satellite‐based data set in the latter region suggests caution. Panthou et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0104">2018</a>) (reproduced in Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0008" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0008">8</a>) show that the Western and Eastern portions of the Sahel do not vary in unison and that the intensity of precipitation has increased the most in the East. Looking at the seasonality of rainfall, Usman, Nichol, Ibrahim, and Buba (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0144">2018</a>) showed that rainfall increases in Niger were mostly concentrated in the later part of the growing season and Lodoun et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0088">2013</a>) reported a delaying trend in the cessation of the rainy season of Burkina. Sanogo et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0119">2015</a>) also reported that positive rainfall trends in the West African Sahel are strongest in August and September and extend into October, outside the traditionally‐defined rainy season. Overall, while a confident attribution is still premature, the spatial and seasonal patterns of recent rainfall anomalies seem to suggest that GHG forcing has been contributing to the observed recovery.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="wcc591-fig-0008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Evolution of (a) the mean number of rainy days and (b) the mean intensity of rainy days (mm/day) over the whole Sahel and subdomains (West, Central, and East Sahel). Error bars (resp. shaded area) delineate 80% confidence intervals for annual values (resp. 11 year rolling mean) (Reprinted with permission from Panthou et al. (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0104">2018</a>). Copyright 2018 the Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 license)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-17" xlink:href="WCC-10-na-g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, one robust consequence of global warming is the increase of mean and extreme rainfall intensity (O'Gorman &amp; Schneider, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0103">2009</a>; Sillmann, Kharin, Zwiers, Zhang, &amp; Bronaugh, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0128" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0128">2013</a>) and the increase of Sahel rainfall since the 1980s is due in nonnegligible part to an intensification of rainfall events, as discussed above. Recent temperature trends over the Sahara are as well consistent with GHG forcing, both in the spatial pattern and in the seasonality (Vizy &amp; Cook, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0147">2017b</a>) and, as pointed out by Taylor et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0135" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0135">2017</a>), this would also imply a robust effect of GHG on the occurrence of intense rainfall. This correspondence is tantalizing, yet it is not easily explained. In observations, storms (at least the most intense ones) have intensified by becoming more organized due to the increased shear, but in current‐generation climate models the spatial resolution is too coarse to represent mesoscale organization and convective parameterizations are insensitive to shear. In order to determine whether the observed intensification of Sahel rainfall is consistent with the emergence of a GHG‐forced signal, we need to elucidate the relative roles of thermodynamic moisture increase and dynamic organization around shear in driving it.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we address the possibility that anthropogenic land use and land cover changes have had a role in either the drought or the recovery of Sahel rainfall. The latest assessments by regional and global models (Boone et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0018">2016</a>; Hagos et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0056">2014</a>) indicate that forcing the atmosphere with a steady and drastic reduction in vegetation cover (such as changing broadleaf trees to broadleaf shrubs and grasses and shrubs to bare soil over all of West Africa) induces a rainfall reduction ranging from 4 to 25%, which is much less than observed. In reality, most of the vegetation changes between 1950 and 1990 were a response to changes in rainfall, rather than vice‐versa (see sidebar), and trends since the 90s have not been spatially homogeneous: woody cover has largely increased in drylands, as a result of increased rainfall (Dardel et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0034">2014</a>) and, to some extent, of conservation practices (Stith et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0130">2015</a>), and has decreased only in humid zones with high population growth (Brandt et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0020">2017</a>). Thus, while vegetation processes may have acted to amplify externally driven climate anomalies at the decadal scale, anthropogenic changes in land use and land cover were at most a minor source of trends.
 </p>
</sec>
