<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="wcc591-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The weather systems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">About 80–90% of the total rainfall amount in the Sahel comes from storms that are especially well organized—they are larger than 80–100,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> and live longer than 6 hr—in spite of those storms being just 11% of the total MCS population (Mathon et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0094">2002</a>). Seasonal rainfall variability, thus, likely depends on the controls upon the number and intensity of such organized storms. The complex links between rainfall, mesoscale storms, and synoptic‐scale forcings are shown in Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0005">5</a>. Wind shear is a key source of organization for convective systems (Houze, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0063">2004</a>) and indeed most squall lines in West Africa are associated with the presence of the AEJ (see also Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0001">1</a>a), their tracks shifting north and south over West Africa in association with the jet's seasonal migration (Fink &amp; Reiner, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0040">2003</a>; Mathon et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0094">2002</a>). Convective episodes are triggered by thermal forcing (especially from elevated terrain, Laing et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0081">2008</a>), but they are often organized by the moist and sheared environment provided by AEW, which transport moisture northward between the trough and ridge and enhance the low‐level vertical shear ahead of the trough (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0005">5</a>b). The system is coupled, as AEW are also enhanced by moist convection (Cornforth, Hoskins, &amp; Thorncroft, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0030">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="wcc591-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Easterly waves can be observed in satellite imagery because of their associated convection. They appear as circular or banded clouds in satellite images. The source of this material is the COMET (textregistered) website at 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://meted.ucar.edu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://meted.ucar.edu/</span> of the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research (UCAR), sponsored in part through cooperative agreement(s) with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), U.S. Department of Commerce (DOC). Copyright 1997–2017 University Corporation for Atmospheric Research. (b) Composite anomalies for 3‐ to 5‐day AEWs for the ERA‐I and TRMM observations. Vectors are 700 hPa wind anomalies (m/s). Red and blue contours are positive and negative 700 hPa geopotential height anomalies (m) drawn every 2 m. Black contours show the 0 m anomalies. Rainfall anomalies (mm/day) are shaded. Only anomalies above |1| mm/day that are significant at the 95% level according to a two‐tailed Student's 
    <span class="italic">t</span> test are shown. (Reprinted with permission from Crétat, Vizy, and Cook (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0032">2014</a>), Copyright 2014 Springer Nature). (c) Hovmüller (longitude–time) diagram of 850 hPa unfiltered meridional wind (v) and cold cloud streaks axes (black lines) averaged between 5°N and 15°N for the period July 1–August 15, 2001. Colored shading shows v at 2 m/s intervals; northerly winds are gold to red and southerly winds are green to blue. White lines are objectively computed positive meridional wind streaks used to identify AEWs. Cold cloud streaks have 
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">b</span>
    </sub> &lt; 233 K. The blue rectangle identifies the convective systems and AEW from which Tropical Storm Alberto formed (Reprinted with permission from Laing, Carbone, Levizzani, and Tuttle (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0081">2008</a>). Copyright 2008 the Royal Meteorological Society)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="WCC-10-na-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the importance of AEW for weather prediction in West Africa cannot be overstated, at the climate scale (monthly and longer) the connection between rainfall variability and either the number or the amplitude of AEW is still debated. For example, while Lafore et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0080">2017</a>) show from case studies how some of the most intense storms in West Africa are associated with the passage of multiple AEWs, in general AEW‐forced squall lines “exhibit no extraordinary characteristics (lifetime, propagation speed, size, and rain rate)” (Fink &amp; Reiner, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0040">2003</a>). Moreover, Laing et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0081">2008</a>) show that rainfall propagates faster than most AEWs, which would seem to suggest that internal organization of the convective system might be more important than the organization provided by the waves (see Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0005">5</a>c). Even so, the variability in the large‐scale fields is bound to imprint on the variability of MCSs, as both shear and mid‐level moisture can directly affect the organization of convective systems by their influence on evaporative downdraughts, cold pools, and inflow.
 </p>
</sec>
