<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="wcc591-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The West African monsoon</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dynamics of Sahel rainfall variability are inextricably connected with the dynamics of the West African Monsoon (WAM). Associated with ascent in the rain band is a divergent circulation, with low‐level southerly flow converging moisture into the Sahel and compensating divergence extending over the depth of the free troposphere. Intertwined with the divergent circulation are the geostrophic circulations: into the Sahara Heat Low (SHL) at low levels and around the anticyclones at mid and upper levels. The anticyclones are associated with two distinct jets, the African Easterly Jet, AEJ, and the Tropical Easterly Jet, TEJ. In Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0001">1</a>a we have shown the low‐level circulation that accompanies the seasonal rainfall. The map view highlights the westerly component of the monsoonal wind and the easterly component of the Harmattan crossing the Sahara (stream lines); also highlighted is the position of the band of maximum mid‐level easterlies that comprise the AEJ. But the zonal component of the flow is not the only important regional feature distinguishing the monsoon circulation from the Hadley cell. Another difference is emphasized in Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0004">4</a> which provides a schematic of the meridional structure of the circulation over West Africa. Superimposed on the deep moist cell that produces the rain band is a shallow circulation: at the surface the southerly flow penetrates well north of the rain band and into the pressure minimum associated with the SHL, shallow and dry ascent maximizes at the ITD, and the northerly return flow of Saharan dry air at about 600mb penetrates into the rain band.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="wcc591-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Schematic cross‐section of the atmosphere between 10°W and 10°E in July. Shown are the positions of the ITD, upper‐level jet streams (African easterly jet [AEJ], tropical easterly jet [TEJ]), the monsoon layer (ML) (as defined by westerly, that is, positive, zonal winds), streamlines, clouds, the freezing level (0°C isotherm), isentropes (
    <span class="italic">θ</span>), minimum (Tn), maximum (
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">x</span>
    </sub>) and mean (
    <span class="italic">T</span>) and dew point temperatures (
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">d</span>
    </sub>), atmospheric pressures (p), and mean monthly rainfall totals (RR) (Reprinted with permission from Parker and Diop‐Kane (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0108">2017</a>). Copyright 2017 Wiley)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="WCC-10-na-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many previous reviews (e.g., Nicholson, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0099">2013</a>) have provided an in depth discussion of the dynamics of the WAM. Here we just want to highlight how its complexity leads to several paths of influence on Sahel rainfall. Changes in the position of the SHL, in the strength of the dry advection within the shallow circulation return flow, or in the moisture supplied by the monsoon flow can independently affect the large‐scale moisture convergence and atmospheric stability at the latitude of the Sahel. Additionally, because vertical and horizontal wind shears are a source of energy for atmospheric waves, changes in the mean flow can influence rainfall indirectly, via the coupling of synoptic disturbances with moist convection. This coupling is discussed below.
 </p>
</sec>
