<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the current adaptation to climate change framework, scientific knowledge has been concentrated at the global and national levels. However, the scale at which stakeholders require scientific information for adaptation is rarely at the global or national scale but rather at local scales (Holman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). Empirical and theoretical evidence points to individuals and societal adaptations to climatic and biophysical risks throughout history (Adger et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Heltberg et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). According to Adger et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>), the resource irregularities offered by different climates and the precariousness which emerges from the vicissitudes of climate have both acted as significant stimuli throughout human history for social and technological innovation. The social actors construct new realities using innovations they value when situations change (Mbereko et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015a</xref>). In the 1990s and before, farm mechanisation was the dominant discourse for enhancing rural resilience to perturbations (Chambers 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1994</xref>). With globalisation, the social actors in rural areas find themselves in a wider system characterised by politics, culture shock, markets, value chains, supply systems and all the links between producers and consumers (Scoones et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). The global and national institutional oppress the rural social actor, social ecology has demonstrated how rural poor can revoke their cooperation with institutional innovations, rendering large investments from above ineffective (Mbereko et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015a</xref>; Scott 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Vervoort et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
