<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Host-associated microbial communities can have critical roles in the normal development, functioning and defence of marine organisms [
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. There is increasing evidence that disruptions of ecological interactions between hosts and their microbiomes can negatively impact host health and performance, reinforcing the idea that these biological associations (host and microorganisms) should be studied holistically, as ‘holobionts’ [
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. This is particularly important for habitat-forming holobionts that form the biogenic structure of ecosystems (e.g. trees, kelp, corals) because impacts on the interaction between these hosts and their microbiomes can affect entire ecosystems. Such habitat-forming species are in significant decline [
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], and this is likely to be exacerbated due to changes in ocean climates [
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Although we are beginning to gain a mechanistic understanding of the indirect effects of climate change via changes in ‘macrobial’ species' interactions [
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20181887C64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>], we still know very little about how host–microbiome interactions affects resilience to ocean warming and acidification. Such understanding is, however, crucial in order to provide early warning signals and conserve and manage key marine ecosystems that underpin temperate reef biodiversity and functioning.
</p>
