<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Not only can climate change affect habitat suitability and demography of ticks, it might also affect important hosts necessary for persistence of both ticks and tick-borne pathogens. Several of the models described in ยง3 &amp; 4 incorporate hosts implicitly by allowing climatic conditions to affect host-seeking activity and presumably host encounter rates (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]); given that a tick is questing, contact rates with hosts are generally assumed to be constant. However, the relevant parameters concerning host-seeking activity by ticks and impacts of climate change on the distribution and abundance of tick-hosts have rarely been incorporated into projections of the future distributions of disease risk. Because the most important hosts for 
 <italic class="italic">Ixodes</italic> ticks in areas impacted by Lyme disease and other tick-borne diseases are endotherms, the effect of climate warming is expected to be buffered by physiological temperature regulation. Nevertheless, a recent study by Roy-Dufresne 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>] indicates that the geographical range of the white-footed mouse (
 <italic class="italic">Peromyscus leucopus</italic>) has extended northward in Quebec coincident with climate warming between 1975 and the present. Roy-Dufresne 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>] project that, because this mouse is so important both to tick survival [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>] and transmission of 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">A. phagocytophilum</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">Babesia microti</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>], continued range expansion will facilitate poleward expansion of Lyme disease. Population genetic analyses of white-footed mice in Quebec suggests that, with the exception of large rivers, there are few geographical barriers to gene flow that might inhibit the ability of this species to track a warming climate and expand northward [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>]. While some models of tick range expansion in Canada indicate that long-distance dispersal on migratory birds will help ticks and 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> track suitable conditions for tick survival as the climate warms [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>], a recent projection of a 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> risk index suggests that the expansion of the Lyme disease agent will be limited by the dispersal of 
 <italic class="italic">P. leucopus</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. The degree to which climate change will alter the spatial distributions, population dynamics and physiology (especially immunology) of hosts for ticks is a poorly studied but promising area for future research.
</p>
