<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec id="sec001" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p class="p">The South-to-North Water Diversion (SNWD) project is designed to channel fresh water from the Yangtze River north to more industrialized parts of China. An important question is whether future climate change and dispersal via the SNWD may synergistically favor a northward expansion of species involved in hosting and transmitting schistosomiasis in China, specifically the intermediate host, 
   <italic class="italic">Oncomelania hupensis</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methodology/ Principal findings</title>
  <p class="p">In this study, climate spaces occupied by the four subspecies of 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> (
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic>, 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">robertsoni</italic>, 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">guangxiensis</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">tangi</italic>) were estimated, and niche conservatism tested among each pair of subspecies. Fine-tuned Maxent (
   <italic class="italic">f</italic>Maxent) and ensemble models were used to anticipate potential distributions of 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> under future climate change scenarios. We were largely unable to reject the null hypothesis that climatic niches are conserved among the four subspecies, so factors other than climate appear to account for the divergence of 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> populations across mainland China. Both model approaches indicated increased suitability and range expansion in 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> in the future; an eastward and northward shift in 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">robertsioni</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">guangxiensis</italic>, respectively; and relative distributional stability in 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">gangi</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions/Significance</title>
  <p class="p">The southern parts of the Central Route of SNWD will coincide with suitable areas for 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> in 2050–2060; its suitable areas will also expand northward along the southern parts of the Eastern Route by 2080–2090. Our results call for rigorous monitoring and surveillance of schistosomiasis along the southern Central Route and Eastern Route of the SNWD in a future, warmer China.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
