<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Framework and Theory</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main proposition is that the global change driven by the anthropogenic climate change is influencing entire cultures of the indigenous populations in the Artic (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). We conceptualized the complex causal web schematically in Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a is an extension of the framework of the Center for Environmental and Respiratory Health Research multidisciplinary research program established in 2009 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. In the present form, “public health” appearing in the center was replaced with “culture, well-being, and health”. The arrows from Global change illustrate how the effects of global change are hypothesized to be mediated through climate, air, water, and soil pollution, housing, and life style. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a explains the multi-dimensional, direct and indirect effects of climate change to culture, well-being, and health.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Flowchart of the systematic literature search</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40572_2018_211_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">a</span> Conceptual framework of the study. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Main factors influencing the health and well-being of Saami individual in reindeer-herding community
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40572_2018_211_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Local observations on the effects of climate change in Sápmi region based on the present systematic literature research and complementary fieldwork by Dr. Näkkäläjärvi</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40572_2018_211_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We apply the proposition of Butler and Harley to divide the health effects of climate change into the primary, secondary, and tertiary effects. The primary effects arise from the direct changes and impacts of the physical system. The secondary effects arise due to alternations in the ecology of vectors, parasites, and host animals, and effects mediated by the allergens and air pollutants are included in this category. The tertiary effects refer to wider scale of effects caused by intersection of climate, politics, and ecology, both human and non-human [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>••]. Our framework in the Saami context is expanded to cover cultural and social effects of climate change. Cultural and social effects are likely to influence health and well-being.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a, b describes the different methodological approaches to understand the factors effecting Saami health and cultural well-being in a changing climate and the main forces driving the global change.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a describes the central research disciplines and research methods that applied to study the holistic effects of climate change on Saami culture. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>b describes the ethno-ecological niche [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>] of Saami people and the changing framework of their culture. The niche includes the individual and the 
  <span class="italic">siida</span> that is kinship-based Saami communal structure that manages reindeer work in its own area. Each siida has its own pasture areas, but the siida system is very flexible [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The cultural ecological framework of the niche consists of the 
  <span class="italic">eallu</span> (the reindeer) and biodiversity. Saami people and culture are not isolated but part of larger Saami community and national society with its legislation, practices, education system, and jurisprudence. Climate change has been identified as a new framework for Saami culture and livelihoods due to its far-reaching and holistic influences [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>••, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>•].
 </p>
</sec>
