<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the present time, the rate and magnitude of warming may be comparable to that of postglacial warming (Solomon, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Willis &amp; MacDonald, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Climate warming can reduce genetic richness by indirectly reducing landscape and species diversity (Chapin III et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). Understanding among and within genetic diversity indices will help identifying the genetic diversity “hotspots” and unique haplotypes. Moreover, identifying climate factors which contribute to the distribution of genetic diversity may provide ideas for genetic conservation under climate change. In light of the present study, genetic “hotspot” conservation is the most efficient way to protect the yellowhorn's genetic diversity (i.e., the identified six wild yellowhorn populations harboring higher haplotype diversity). Climate variables TD (temperature difference between MWMT (mean warmest month temperature) and MCMT (mean coldest month temperature)) and EMT (extreme minimum temperature over 30 years) in the identified haplotype diversity “hotspots” are expected to increase by 3–5°C in the following 50 years (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34944-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>). TD showed the difference between mean warmest month temperature (MWMT) and mean coldest month temperature (MCMT) is increasing, while the extreme minimum temperature over 30 years (EMT) is increasing, which indicate that extreme weather conditions may occur more than contemporary observed. While yellowhorn is adapted to warm climate as its original distribution is in tropical region; however, the observed and predicted climate change are expected to cause greater challenges. Surprisingly, all moisture‐related climatic variables were nonsignificant indicating that temperature alone plays a major role in the species contemporary and future distributions and confirming the species drought resistance (An et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
