<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To achieve Aichi Biodiversity Targets (Goal A) in Convention on Biological Diversity (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cbd.int/sp/targets/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cbd.int/sp/targets/</ext-link>), the Chinese National Natural Conservation Areas program is providing the most restrictive laws to protect wild plant and animal species (Wang, Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Wang, Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), and this prompted the establishment of the Sanjiangyuan National Park in 2017, the first National Park in China. According to condition 2 of the regulations of the People's Republic of China on Nature Reserves (2017 version: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.forestry.gov.cn/main/3950/content-459882.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.forestry.gov.cn/main/3950/content-459882.html</ext-link>), the natural distribution areas of rare or endangered species are considered as locations for the establishment of new protect area (national parks, nature reserves, and wilderness areas). Our yellowhorn previous research showed that the total distribution area of wild yellowhorn is expected to decline by 10%–17% (≈210,000–330,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) in the next 30–50 years by the impact of global warming and identified the species as endangered in its wild populations (Wang, Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Wang, Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Thus, we suggest the establishment of yellowhorn protected areas in the identified six genetic diversity “hotspots,” and this initiative could help conserving the existing genetic diversity within these unique gene pools (Jenkins &amp; Joppa, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Maxted, Dulloo, Ford‐Lloyd, Iriondo, &amp; Jarvis, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Additionally, maintaining and conserving the yellowhorn ecosystem will aid in the conservation and protection of those animals associated with the species seeds dispersal. Furthermore, while efforts are dedicated to the in situ conservation of yellowhorn in its wild estate within protected ecosystems, a complementary ex situ conservation efforts such as gene banks are also advocated (Cohen, Williams, Plucknett, &amp; Shands, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>; Vavilov, 
 <xref rid="ece34944-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1927</xref>).
</p>
