<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Bioclimatology or 
 <italic class="italic">bioclimatics</italic>, which includes phenology, is an ancient science that investigates the relationship between living organisms and climates. According to historical records, China was the first country to conduct bioclimatic observation approximately 3,000 years ago. Bioclimatology is referred to as 
 <italic class="italic">Wuhou</italic> (物候) in Chinese, a word that originated from the classic 
 <italic class="italic">Ch’un</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">ch’iu Tso Chuan</italic> (春秋左傳). Western bioclimatology was established in approximately 1753 by Linnaeus, a Swedish botanist, who is known as the father of phenology. The term phenology was first introduced by the Belgian botanist Morren in 1853. One hundred years before the term was coined during Linnaeus’ time, phenology was focused on the seasonal and periodic phenomena that organisms exhibit and is referred to as classic or seasonal bioclimatology. In Japan, phenology is referred to as the study of seasons and organisms. Scientists have since identified that changes in living organisms follow periodic changes in climates. Thus, the scope and definition of phenology vary constantly as new bioclimatic findings are obtained. Consequently, the early definition of phenology has become inapplicable. Although numerous scientists have attempted to redefine phenology and create linguistically specific technical terms, many people prefer to use the established term phenology, which has been used continuously since it was coined. Bioclimatology, including phenology, now involves investigations of the correlations between climates and organisms (Chu and Wan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">1999</xref>; Hopkins 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">1938</xref>; Hsieh and Chiou 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2013</xref>; Lieth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">1974</xref>; Schnelle 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" class="xref">1955</xref>; Zou 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" class="xref">1983</xref>). To avoid confusion caused by different definitions, this article defines all types of model that have both biological and climatic variables as bioclimatic models.
</p>
