<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29" class="p">EHPs highlighted several adaptation measures, such as providing access to air conditioning in public buildings as effective factors for controlling heat-related stresses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. They also recommended heat emergency plans detailing the human and material resources needed to reduce or manage risks associated with weather-related disasters [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. For EHPs to fully realize their potential to help communities adapt to climate change, there needs to be an inclusive discussion on the nature of the role they might play, and the essential resources needed to support their efforts. Inspiration might be taken from some encouraging initiatives currently underway. For example, the City of Rustenburg, in partnership with the South African Medical Research Council, is currently in the process of developing a Heat and Health Plan for its citizens. The effort was prompted by the designation of Rustenburg as a vulnerable location [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>] when, in 2016, during a single heatwave tens of people died in the North-West province. The climate and health adaptation measures suggested during a consultative workshop in Rustenburg echo those mentioned in the current study in which EHPs rated most highly tree planting, vegetable gardening, strengthening of policies and standards for storm water drainage, strengthening climate and health research programmes, and developing community early warning systems. On the other hand, the provision of cool spaces (air conditioning at schools and churches for example) and swimming pools, as well as cycling facilities, were given the lowest ratings. These adaptation mechanisms may have received the lowest ratings because they are uncommon occurrences in informal rural and low socio-economic settlements and may not be perceived as viable and affordable options.
</p>
