<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Duration of Precipitation Extremes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of changes in precipitation extremes depends on the duration of precipitation considered (i.e., the accumulation period). In a recent climate-model study, intensity-duration-frequency curves were calculated for accumulation periods from 6 h to 10 days, and the curves were found to shift upwards in intensity on a logarithmic scale in a relatively simple way as the climate warms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>•]. However, it is not clear that global climate models can be relied on for subdaily extremes, because of the potential importance of convective processes. Indeed, for regional simulations of midlatitudes in summer, changing from a model with convective parameterization to a CRM has been found to lead to a marked improvement in the intensity distribution of hourly precipitation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>•] and to significantly alter the simulated response of hourly precipitation extremes to climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term observational records of subdaily precipitation are relatively sparse, which makes it difficult to give a general assessment of trends in subdaily extremes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>]. Many recent observational studies have instead focussed on the relationship between short-duration precipitation rates and the local surface temperature in variability within the current climate. In the first of these studies, a high-resolution record from the Netherlands was found to give a sensitivity of 7 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for daily precipitation as compared to 14 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for hourly precipitation over a range of temperatures [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>]. Similar behavior was found in some but not all subsequent studies in different regions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>]; see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>] for an in-depth discussion. Factors such as relative humidity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>], large-scale dynamics and temperature gradients [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>], and transitions from stratiform to convective precipitation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>] are thought to be important for the scaling of precipitation extremes with temperature in the current climate, and some of these factors may have a different effect on hourly and daily precipitation. While the sensitivity of precipitation extremes for long-term climate change need not be the same as for variability in a given climate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>], understanding the sensitivity of subdaily precipitation extremes in the present-day climate is an important starting point.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Idealized CRM studies suggest that changes in both dynamics and precipitation efficiency could contribute to the scaling of subdaily convective precipitation extremes with temperature. Convective precipitation extremes have been found to increase with warming considerably faster than implied by Clausius-Clapeyron scaling in some cases when a temperature increase is imposed that is constant in the vertical [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>]. This is not surprising because a vertically uniform temperature increase makes a moist atmosphere less statically stable and leads to faster updrafts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>•], but it does demonstrate that changes in the static stability associated with subdaily extreme precipitation events are worthy of further study. In a related result, temperature changes in climate-change simulations were found to be close to constant in the vertical for high-CAPE composites in the midlatitudes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>•].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As discussed in the “
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Theory</a>” section, updrafts do become somewhat faster with warming when lapse rates are allowed to equilibrate (rather than being imposed) in simulations of RCE, although the dynamical contribution to changes in precipitation extremes is still relatively small [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>]. Nonetheless, large deviations from Clausius-Clapeyron scaling have been found in a study of RCE because of changes in precipitation efficiency at mean surface temperatures below 295 K [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>]. The 99.99th percentile of precipitation from this study is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a> for durations from instantaneous to daily.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4" href="#Fn4">4</a> Warming shifts the percentile curves upwards in intensity in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>, but the rate at which they shift upwards varies with duration and temperature. As shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>, the precipitation extremes follow Clausius-Clapeyron scaling at roughly 6–7 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for temperatures above 295 K. However, for temperatures below 295 K, the sensitivity varies widely depending on temperature and accumulation period in a manner that is not fully understood. Instantaneous precipitation extremes increase at close to double the Clausius-Clapeyron rate for temperatures below 295 K, and this has been shown to be due to increases in precipitation efficiency with warming, related in part to increases in hydrometeor fall speed as more of the precipitation in the column changes from solid to liquid [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>]. Such changes in precipitation efficiency might be expected to occur for variability within a climate as well as for longer term climate change, but in the simulations, they depend strongly on the choice of cloud microphysics scheme, and it remains to be seen if they are relevant for observed precipitation extremes.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">a</span> The 99.99th percentile of precipitation for different durations (instantaneous, 1 h, 3 h, 6 h, and daily) in simulations of radiative-convective equilibrium with a cloud-system resolving model at selected mean surface-air temperatures as given in the legend. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> The sensitivity of the 99.99th percentile of precipitation to mean surface air temperature changes for the same temperatures shown in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>). The natural logarithm of the 99.99th percentile of precipitation as a function of mean surface-air temperature from ten simulations is linearly interpolated to a uniform grid in temperature and sensitivities (% K
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) are calculated as the change for a 3-K warming
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40641_2015_9_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
