<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The response of precipitation extremes (heavy precipitation events) to climate change has been the subject of extensive study because of the potential impacts on human society and ecosystems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. An early study using a four-level general circulation model found that heavy daily precipitation events become more frequent in response to elevated atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. Numerous model studies since then have also found an intensification of precipitation extremes with climate warming (with important regional variations), and this has been confirmed in the available historical record over land, as will be discussed in detail in later sections.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding of changes in precipitation extremes is better than for changes in other extremes such as tornadoes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>], but large uncertainties and research challenges remain. If changes in dynamics and precipitation efficiency are negligible, precipitation extremes increase with warming because of increases in the saturation vapor pressure of water [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>]; this will be made more precise in the “
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Theory</a>” section. However, dynamical contributions and changes in precipitation efficiency may also play an important role. Mesoscale convective organization is important for the dynamics of precipitation extremes in the tropics (and seasonally in the midlatitudes) but it is not resolved in global models, while at the same time, there are relatively few observational records of tropical precipitation extremes for estimating long-term trends and sensitivities. At higher latitudes, the effect of climate change on snowfall extremes and freezing rain will be different from its effect on rainfall extremes and requires further study. In terms of impacts, the duration of extreme precipitation events and the response of orographic precipitation extremes are both important and are only now receiving substantial research attention.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper reviews and elaborates on some of the recent research on how climate change affects precipitation extremes, including observed changes in the historical record (“
  <a rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec2">Observed Changes in Precipitation Extremes</a>”), physical theory (“
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Theory</a>”), climate-model projections (“
  <a rid="Sec4" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec4">Climate-Model Projections</a>”), orographic precipitation extremes (“
  <a rid="Sec7" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec7">Orographic Precipitation Extremes</a>”), snowfall extremes (“
  <a rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec8">Snowfall Extremes</a>”), and the duration of precipitation extremes (“
  <a rid="Sec9" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec9">Duration of Precipitation Extremes</a>”). The primary focus is on the physical factors that control the intensity of precipitation extremes in different climates. Open questions are discussed throughout and in the “
  <a rid="Sec10" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec10">Conclusions and Open Questions</a>” section.
 </p>
</sec>
