<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed Changes in Precipitation Extremes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Records of precipitation that are sufficient to detect long-term trends in extremes are primarily from rain gauges over land. Over the available record, there are regions with both increasing and decreasing trends in precipitation extremes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>], as might be expected given large internal variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>], but the grid boxes or stations with significant increasing trends outnumber those with significant decreasing trends [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>•]. Anthropogenic forcing has been shown to have contributed to the intensification of precipitation extremes over northern hemisphere land [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>••, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>]. Assessments have also been made of the effect of anthropogenic forcing on the probability of specific extreme precipitation or flooding events using ensembles of climate-model simulations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>•].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One approach that reduces the influence of unforced variability while still distinguishing large-scale variations is to analyze the sensitivity of precipitation extremes averaged over all stations or grid boxes in a latitude band [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>•]. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> shows an example of this type of analysis in which annual-maximum daily precipitation rates over land from the HadEX2-gridded dataset [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>] have been regressed over the period 1901 to 2010 against temperature anomalies from NOAA’s Merged Land-Ocean Surface Temperature Analysis (MLOST) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>]. The precipitation rates are over land only, but precipitation extremes do not necessarily scale with the local land mean temperature because of advection of water vapor from over the ocean such as in atmospheric rivers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>], and the temperatures used here are over both land and ocean. For each grid box with at least 30 years of data, the annual-maximum daily precipitation rates are regressed against the global-mean surface temperature anomalies using the Theil-Sen estimator, and the regression coefficient is divided by the mean of the annual-maximum daily precipitation rate at the grid box to give a sensitivity that is expressed in units of percent per kelvin. The median of the sensitivities is then calculated for all grid boxes in 15° latitude bands.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1" href="#Fn1">1</a> The resulting sensitivity is positive for most latitude bands, the 90 % confidence interval is above zero for all latitude bands in the northern hemisphere, and the global sensitivity (averaging over latitude bands with area weighting) is 8 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> with a 90 % confidence interval of 5 to 10 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. These results, similar to those obtained previously [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>•], provide evidence for an intensification of annual-maximum daily precipitation as the global-mean temperature has risen over the last century and at a rate that is roughly consistent with what might be expected from theory. However, the meridional structure of the sensitivities within the tropics is sensitive to the details of the analysis (cf. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>•]).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Sensitivities of observed annual-maximum daily precipitation over land (
     <span class="italic">solid lines with circles</span>; 
     <span class="italic">dotted lines</span> show the 90 % confidence interval) in 15° latitude bands relative to 
     <span class="bold">a</span> global-mean surface temperature or 
     <span class="bold">b</span> mean surface temperature over the 15° latitude band. Precipitation is from HadEX2, sensitivities are calculated for grid boxes with at least 30 annual values, and the median sensitivity is plotted for each 15° latitude band. Temperatures are over land and ocean from NOAA MLOST, and for 
     <span class="bold">b</span> the temperature time series were smoothed with a 9-year running-mean filter
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40641_2015_9_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extratropical precipitation extremes at a given latitude occur when the atmosphere is warmer than average and are more closely tied to mean temperatures somewhat further equatorward [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>•, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>]. However, they are still expected to respond primarily to changes in mean temperatures in the extratropics rather than the tropics, and recent warming has been greater in the northern extratropics than the tropics. The sensitivities shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> are based on global-mean surface temperature and do not account for the variation in warming with latitude. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a> shows an alternative analysis in which the annual-maximum daily precipitation rates at each grid box are regressed against the area-weighted mean temperature anomaly for the 15° latitude band that contains the grid box. The latitude-band temperature time series are filtered using a 9-year running mean prior to performing the regression. This filtering reduces the influence of short-term variability in regional temperatures which has previously been found to give a different sensitivity of precipitation extremes than long-term climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. The results in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a> show a higher sensitivity of precipitation extremes in the tropics compared to the extratropics, although the uncertainty in the tropics is large reflecting the sparse data there. The sensitivity for the tropics (30S to 30N) is 9 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (90 % confidence interval 6–14 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), while for the extratropics, it is 4 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (90 % confidence interval 2–5 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). The choice of filter for the temperature time series affects the overall magnitudes of the sensitivities but not whether sensitivities are higher in the tropics than the extratropics. Interestingly, higher sensitivities in the tropics are also found when projections from global climate models are constrained by satellite observations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>] as discussed in the “
  <a rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec6">Tropical Precipitation Extremes</a>” section.
 </p>
</sec>
