<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we provide the evidence of a long-term relationship between masting in trees and inter-annual variation and decadal trends of a climate teleconnection. Several seasonal indices of NAO are jointly responsible for synchronizing beech and spruce masting in Central-Northern Europe. Although previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> focused on specific seasonal NAO series and regions (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), our results show that NAO acts over multiple seasons and years synchronizing beech and spruce masting over a large part of their distribution, extending from 44°N–3.5°W to 58°N–26°E and 46°N–3.5°W to 61°N–30°E for beech and spruce, respectively. As a further step in comparison with previous studies, we tested the contribution of both the high- (inter-annual) and low- (decadal) frequency components of seasonal NAO indices. The group of significant high-frequency seasonal NAO predictors and the direction of their influence were consistent with previous findings based on raw seasonal NAO series. Negative NAO in the summer 2 years before fruit ripening, followed by a positive summer-NAO in the subsequent year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span> and by a positive spring-NAO during flowering
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, promotes beech masting. Spruce masting seems to be driven by the same high-frequency NAO components as for beech, except for a lack of influence of the summer two years before fruit ripening. Masting intensity of the previous year had a negative effect on both beech and spruce masting, which confirms that masting series display negative autocorrelation—indicative of resource depletion after large fruit crops
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>—even at a sub-continental scale, such as in the widespread masting failure in 1996, 1 year after the large masting event in 1995 (highlighted in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Our models failed to predict poor masting in 1997; such overprediction decreased when we included an autoregressive term with a lag of −2 years in both models (−29 and −28% for beech and spruce, respectively). This term had a negative significant effect (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05, two-sided test) in both models, suggesting a long-lasting resource depletion after the large mast of 1995.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among low-frequency components, only winter-NAO was significant, but displayed a strong positive effect on both beech and spruce masting in the frequency domain from 7 to 16 years. This shows that during prolonged periods of positive winter NAO, the occurrence of widespread masting events on beech and spruce increases. Although the model for beech performed better in comparison with the model for spruce, it is notable that disentangling the high-frequency (i.e., inter-annual) and the low-frequency (i.e., decadal) NAO components markedly improved the spruce model when compared to testing the raw NAO series (pseudo-
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> of 0.42 vs. 0.27).
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many studies have discussed both the seasonal effects of NAO on Central-Northern European weather
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> and the effect of seasonal weather patterns on proximate causes of masting in the 
  <span class="italic">Fagaceae</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Pinaceae</span> families
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. Our results highlight the link between seasonal NAO and weather patterns known to determine seed masting. Negative summer-NAO is associated with cool-wet summers in Central-Northern Europe (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, see also Folland et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> and Bladé et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>), a weather pattern strongly correlated with beech masting when occurring 2 years before fruiting
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, and commonly interpreted as increasing available resources by enhancing litter mass loss and nutrient uptake due to high soil moisture
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. In contrast, positive summer-NAO is associated with warm-dry summers in Central-Northern Europe (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). This weather pattern is also correlated with both beech
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> and spruce
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> masting when occurring the year before fruit ripening, as it induces hormonal translocation for flower primordial differentiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. Finally, positive spring-NAO is associated with mild-dry weather (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), which favours wind pollination and the related fruit-set in the seed production year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. With regards to the low-frequency component of winter-NAO, prolonged positive winter-NAO phases are associated with warm-wet winters (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) with delayed positive effects on growing season temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Positive NAO in winter causes an earlier leafing out of beech in Central-Northern Europe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, which lengthens the growing season. Moreover, positive winter-NAO enhances the primary production of Central-Northern European forests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, which is indicative of available resources for reproduction in temperate trees
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Consequently, we speculate that during prolonged positive phases of the winter-NAO, such as in the early ‘50s and in ‘90s of the twentieth century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, more resources were consistently available for beech and spruce masting throughout Central-Northern Europe.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the positive and significant interaction between the high-frequency component of summer-NAO of the year before masting and the low-frequency component of winter-NAO we found in the beech model could be interpreted as a higher sensitivity of the species to high temperatures inducing flowering during periods of increased resources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. However, the low ΔAIC of the interaction factor in the regression model, and the fact the interaction was not significant in the spruce model, advocates caution in interpreting this result. Indeed, few previous studies found such interaction, either in 
  <span class="italic">Fagaceae</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> or in other taxonomic groups
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. In addition, in our study this interaction could be explained by a lagged effect of the winter-NAO on summer temperatures. Previous studies report that summer heat waves in Central-Northern Europe are strong and wide-ranging when positive summer-NAO occurs in years of positive winter-NAO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. For example, this was the case in 1994 before the beech masting in 1995, the largest event in the period 1952–2015 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Interestingly, model residuals for year 1995 were reduced by including the interaction factor among predictors.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whichever way this interaction is interpreted, our results show that seasonal and annual variations, and decadal trends in the NAO affect both short- and long-term patterns of tree masting in Central-Northern Europe, although these relationships are weak in some years and periods (i.e., non-stationary through time). Indeed, the NAO is the leading climate mode in Europe, but the Euro-North Atlantic region is also influenced by other large-scale atmospheric modes of variability, which oscillate at both inter-annual and decadal time scales replacing NAO influence on European weather patterns. This could explain model errors in given years, i.e., when the NAO-based models of both species had a lower explanative power (e.g., 1958, 2004). Here, weather patterns inducing masting might have been influenced by other broad-scale climate modes, such as the Scandinavian Pattern or the East-Atlantic and West Russian pattern
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, particularly in summer. For example, the summer 1957 was characterized by a severe heat wave in Central-Northern Europe, with locally record-breaking temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Although, generally, positive summer-NAO values are associated with high temperature in this region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), the 1957 temperature-positive anomaly coincided with a below-average summer-NAO. The atmospheric patterns associated with the 1957-heatwave are instead attributed to two clusters of geopotential anomaly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, a first extending over most of the Scandinavian Peninsula and the second centred mostly over France and linked to the European summer blocking
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Similarly, the heatwave in summer 2003 coincided with a low summer-NAO index, and was attributed to tropical Atlantic forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> in conjunction with a marked soil water deficit throughout the European continent
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 1850 to 1900 and from 1960 to 2000, decadal winter-NAO and beech masting showed a significant coherence within a frequency domain of 7–16 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), and a similar pattern was observed for the spring-NAO after 1985 (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a> right). However, even the low-frequency components of winter- and spring-NAO were not always coherent with beech masting in the past two centuries. This is consistent with previous findings of a non-stationary influence of NAO over European weather patterns
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> and related ecological processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Our analyses confirm that in the long-term beech masting alternates between periods of frequent large-scale events and periods when such events are rare, thus generalizing the results of a previous study in Sweden
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. We suggest this could be partly due to variability in the strength of NAO influence on the synchronization of weather patterns determining masting at the continental scale, which themselves appear to be largely stable through time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we showed a non-stationary influence of NAO on tree masting at both inter-annual and decadal time scales, we also highlighted that NAO components have synchronized masting across Central-Northern Europe for long periods. According to our interpretation, NAO synchronizes the proximate causes of masting over large areas (Moran effect) at multiple stages of the reproductive cycle, such as resource accumulation, flower differentiation, and cross-pollination. This raises the question of the ecological meaning of the link between synchronous seed production and NAO patterns: is large-scale masting just a coincidental consequence of NAO controlling proximate causes, or does such synchronization also provide competitive advantages due to one or more economies of scale, hinting at the evolutionary factors of masting? Recently, Pearse et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> theorised a complementarity between proximate (i.e., mechanism driving masting) and ultimate causes (i.e., evolutionary drivers) of masting. Several evolutionary hypotheses have been proposed as ultimate causes of masting in beech and spruce, including the following: (i) pollination efficiency: percent of seed set is higher in high-flowering years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>; (ii) predator-dispersal: seed predators are attracted to a large fruit crop increasing dispersal-related fitness benefits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, particularly by birds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>; and (iii) environmental prediction: masting anticipates favourable conditions for seedling establishment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. Notably, seasonal NAO patterns identified by this and other studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> are consistent with all these ultimate causes. Influences of positive spring-NAO on the pollination efficiency were already discussed by Fernández-Martínez et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Regarding the predator-dispersal hypothesis, some studies found a positive relationship between winter-NAO and peaks in population dynamics of beech nuts dispersers such as 
  <span class="italic">Columba palumbus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Fringilla coelebs</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pica pica</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, and spruce dispersers such as 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis spinus</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. Interestingly, a study in North America found that antiphased climate anomalies (i.e., dipoles such as NAO) modulate consistently both broad-scale seed-eating bird irruptions and widespread masting
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> resulting in birds anticipating the resource pulse, and this might be relevant also for beech and spruce seed dispersers.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A coherent picture can also be set for the environmental prediction hypothesis, although this theory has received less support, particularly when dealing with the prediction of future climate conditions favouring seedlings (e.g. wet seasons)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>. Many studies demonstrated beech and spruce recruitment failure after a mast year because of thick litter or a closed tree canopy, typical of undisturbed stands
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. However, regeneration is highly favored in both species by mixed severity disturbances
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>, particularly when masting closely follows the disturbance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. Notably, periods of positive winter-NAO are associated with major damaging storms in Central-Northern Europe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>, whereas pressure patterns indicative of positive summer-NAO favor drought
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> and have been associated with fire activity in Southern Sweden
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> and Southern England
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Consequently, the teleconnection patterns that we show in this study to favour masting may also be associated with disturbance events that create conditions favoring seedling establishment. This is a different interpretation of the environmental prediction hypothesis, which does not require the prediction of future weather conditions criticised by previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After Pearse et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, we suggest a coherent ecological-evolutionary theory using teleconnections as a bridge linking proximate and ultimate causes of masting. Previous studies used teleconnection indices to interpret the adaptive functioning of some ecological processes linked to climate oscillations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span> and this was proposed also for masting
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. We do not imply that NAO has been the sole driver exerting a selective pressure on tree masting in Central-Northern Europe, as we found a non-stationary link between NAO and masting. Moreover, masting in the 
  <span class="italic">Fagaceae</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Pinaceae</span> families probably evolved before European weather and NAO relationships established. However, alternating large-scale features of atmospheric circulation with a significant impact on ecological and geophysical processes (e.g., resource cycles, animal populations, and natural disturbances) at any place and time might have exerted a selective pressure by influencing both the proximate and ultimate causes of masting.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, our findings can improve the ability to predict masting based on NAO forecasts
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>, particularly for beech, assuming that the non-stationarity in the NAO-masting relationships can be taken in consideration. To this extent, we suggest that studies linking climate change to tree masting should focus on how climate change affects NAO patterns
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span> and their relationships with proximate causes of masting.
 </p>
</sec>
