<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High- and low-frequency NAO vs. masting index model</div>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To discriminate between low- and high-frequencies NAO components for the period 1952–2015, we fitted each of the three raw seasonal NAO series (i.e., winter-, summer-, and spring-NAO) with a running line smoother using the 
  <span class="italic">supsmu</span> function of the 
  <span class="italic">stats</span> R package. The span of all smoothers was set to the mean frequency domain at which wavelet coherence of raw seasonal NAO series against beech and spruce masting was significant (considering all NAO data sources and seasons). The corresponding high-frequency components were calculated by subtracting the smoothed series from the raw seasonal NAO index (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). For the summer season, two high-frequency summer-NAO components were calculated (i.e., for both 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−2</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−1</sub>). We then fitted M_index as a function of the three low-frequency components (winter-, summer-, and spring-NAO), the four high-frequency components (summer-NAO 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−2</sub>, winter-NAO 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−1</sub>, summer-NAO 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−1</sub>, and spring-NAO 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M</sub>), and an autoregressive term with a lag of − 1 year. All predictors were standardized and checked for collinearity (pairwise Pearson's correlation &lt; 0.4). The period of analysis was limited to 1952–2015 and 1959–2014 for beech and spruce, respectively, the response was assumed to be 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-distributed, and the model was fitted via maximum likelihood using the 
  <span class="italic">betareg</span> package for R
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When testing for interactions between all high- and low-frequency NAO predictors, we needed to limit overfitting, due to the large number of possible bivariate interactions relative to the number of observations. Following Quinn and Keough
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, we computed the residuals of the “null” model (without interactions), and fitted them as a linear function of each possible two-way interaction among standardized predictors. Only interactions producing a significant (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) fit against null model residuals were added to the final model. The pseudo
  <span class="italic">-R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> of the model was computed as the squared correlation between the linear predictor for the mean and the link-transformed response
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assessed the importance of each (standardized) predictor in the final model by calculating the difference between the AIC of the models with and without the concerned predictor (ΔAIC)—the higher ΔAIC, the larger the importance of the predictor in the model. The final model was validated by LOOCV.</p>
</sec>
