<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Masting, the synchronous and highly variable production of seeds by a population of plants, may periodically synchronize over large portions of a species distribution range
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, with major cascading effects on ecosystems functioning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. Large-scale masting events rely on the spatial synchronization (Moran effect) of proximate mechanisms of masting (here after “proximate causes”)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, such as those promoting resource accumulation and floral induction in the previous 1–2 years, and cross-pollination in the mast year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. Over longer timescales, several studies report periods with frequent large masting events that alternate with periods of rare masting and attribute this fluctuation to decadal trends in broad climate patterns
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Indeed, the interplay of proximate causes leading to masting may occur at both annual and longer time scales, e.g., by increasing the sensitivity of trees to a flowering–inducing cue during extended periods of higher resource availability due to a favorable climate trend
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Disentangling the effects of climate oscillations on masting at high (inter-annual) vs. low (decadal) frequencies would therefore result in an improved understanding of masting as an ecosystem process and its causes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Teleconnections are broad climate patterns that produce spatially correlated weather conditions at both inter-annual and decadal time scales
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Indices describing the phase of a teleconnected climate system integrate several weather variables
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, which makes them good candidates for explaining the large-scale synchronization of ecological processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>, including masting
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several teleconnection indices were found to correlate to tree masting and its proximate causes, such as the El Niño Southern Oscillation in East Asia and Oceania
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, the North Pacific Index in North America
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, and the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) in Europe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. However, due to limitations of masting data in time and/or space, none of these studies tested for the effect of the low-frequency component of the teleconnection. Likewise, no assessment was made on whether the effects were consistent through time.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we take advantage of long-term masting observations (the MASTREE database)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, covering most of the 
  <span class="italic">Fagus sylvatica</span> L. (European beech) and 
  <span class="italic">Picea abies</span> (L.) H. Karst (Norway spruce) distribution. We used MASTREE to assess the effect of inter-annual and decadal variations of the NAO on large-scale masting in both species, and the stability of such effects through time.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beech and spruce may display synchronized reproduction over a large portion of their distribution area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Previous studies found a relationship between NAO and beech masting in some regions of Central-Northern Europe, but uncertainties emerge regarding the timing and direction of this relationship (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Positive NAO in the winter of the year before fruit ripening (
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−1</sub>) favoured beech masting in Southern England
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. Negative NAO in the summer 2 years before fruit ripening (
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−2</sub>), followed by a positive summer-NAO in year 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−1</sub>, enhanced beech masting in Southern Sweden
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, whereas positive NAO in the spring during flowering (
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M</sub>) synchronized masting in Germany, France, and Luxemburg
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. This final relationship is also reported for spruce
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Hence, no strong evidence of a spatially and temporally consistent influence of NAO on beech and spruce masting has emerged at the continental scale. We argue that inconsistencies in previous studies arise from the following: (a) failure to analyze the whole period during which climate affects proximate causes of masting in beech (three years from 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M−2</sub> to 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M</sub>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> and spruce (2 years from 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M</sub>
  <sub>−</sub>
  <sub>1</sub> to 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>M</sub>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>; (b) inability to test the effects of decadal NAO components as a potential common influence on masting; and (c) disregarding that the relationship between masting and NAO may have changed through time.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Previous findings on the relationship between seasonal NAO indices and beech and spruce masting</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Year before masting</th>
      <th>
       <span class="italic">Y</span>
       <sub>M−2</sub>
      </th>
      <th>
       <span class="italic">Y</span>
       <sub>M−1</sub>
      </th>
      <th>
       <span class="italic">Y</span>
       <sub>M</sub>
       <sub>−1</sub>
      </th>
      <th>
       <span class="italic">Y</span>
       <sub>M</sub>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Species</span>
      </td>
      <td>Beech</td>
      <td>Beech</td>
      <td>Beech</td>
      <td>Beech–Spruce</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">NAO season</span>
      </td>
      <td>Summer</td>
      <td>Winter</td>
      <td>Summer</td>
      <td>Spring</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Correlation sign NAO season vs. masting</span>
      </td>
      <td>Negative</td>
      <td>Positive</td>
      <td>Positive</td>
      <td>Positive</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">NAO phase (− or +) and weather in Europe</span>
      </td>
      <td>Summer-NAO−Weather: Cool-Wet</td>
      <td>Winter-NAO+Weather: Warm-Wet</td>
      <td>Summer-NAO+Weather: Warm-Dry</td>
      <td>Spring-NAO+Weather: Warm-Dry</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Previous study</span>
      </td>
      <td>Drobyshev et al. 2014</td>
      <td>Piovesan &amp; Adams 2001</td>
      <td>Drobyshev et al. 2014</td>
      <td>Fernández-M. et al. 2016</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Geographical area</span>
      </td>
      <td>Southern Sweden</td>
      <td>Southern England</td>
      <td>Southern Sweden</td>
      <td>France, Germany, Luxemburg</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Studied period</span>
      </td>
      <td>1871–2006</td>
      <td>1981–1995</td>
      <td>1871–2006</td>
      <td>2002–2010</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Previous findings on the relationship between seasonal NAO indices (winter-NAO; summer-NAO; spring-NAO), and beech and spruce masting in different European regions. 
     <span class="italic">Y</span>
     <sub>M</sub>: year of masting; 
     <span class="italic">Y</span>
     <sub>M−1</sub> and 
     <span class="italic">Y</span>
     <sub>M−2</sub>: 1 and 2 years before masting, respectively.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to get a broader understanding in the relationship between masting and NAO, we address the following questions: (1) Do all seasonal NAO indices reported as relevant for masting in previous studies (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) exert a significant effect on beech and spruce synchronous seed production at the European scale? (2) Do both inter-annual and decadal variations of NAO affect beech and spruce masting? (3) Are NAO–masting relationships consistent with weather patterns known to determine masting in both species? (4) Are these relationships stationary through time?
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We show that in the last 60 years the inter-annual variation of NAO in summer and spring, as well as decadal trends in the winter NAO, are highly correlated to continent-wide masting in beech and spruce. This finding highlights the role of teleconnections in affecting large-scale synchronization of tree masting and provides insights on its evolutionary drivers.</p>
</sec>
