<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Low-frequency domain of NAO and masting relationships</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wavelet analysis showed that all seasonal NAO indices exhibited coherence with beech and spruce masting at similar low-frequency domains, although relationships displayed a different level of significance for different seasonal indices. In the second half of the twentieth century, all winter-NAO indices (National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) for 1950–2015, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>; Hurrell 1899–2015, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>; Jones 1826–2015, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>) showed significantly positive coherence with beech masting in the frequency domain of 7 to 16 years. A similar wavelet coherence existed between the winter-NAO using the NOAA index (1950–2015) and the spruce M_index (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5a</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Wavelet coherence between the standardized beech M_index and winter-NAO indices. Wavelet coherence between the standardized beech M_index and winter-NAO indices. Winter-NAO indices used: Climate Prediction Centre-NOAA 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, Hurrell
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
     </span>
     <span class="bold">b</span> and Jones et al.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
     </span>
     <span class="bold">c</span>. 
     <span class="italic">X</span>-axes: years of analysis. 
     <span class="italic">Y</span>-axes: frequency domain of the NAO-masting relationship in years. Note that the 
     <span class="italic">x</span>- and 
     <span class="italic">y</span>-axes vary between plots. Arrows pointing up-right show in-phase behavior and 
     <span class="italic">y</span> leading 
     <span class="italic">x</span>, i.e., NAO leading M_index. Black contour designates frequencies of significant coherence (
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.1, two-sided test); the white cone of influence shows the data space immune from distortion by edge effects. The white squares show the period of strong coherence between 1960 and 2000
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2017_2348_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e958" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term analyses (&gt; 50 years) on beech data revealed that coherence between the beech M_index and winter-NAO varied through time. In the first half of the twentieth century, both the Hurrell (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>) and the Jones (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>) indices did not show any significant coherence with M_index, and only in the second half of the nineteenth century an in-phase influence of winter-NAO on the beech M_index emerged, again with a frequency domain of 7 to 16 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>). Summer-NAO and M_index of both species were significantly coherent for a short period around 1980 (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5b</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6a</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6c</a>), but for beech the signal in the domain of 7 to 16 years remained throughout the 20
  <span class="sup">th</span> century (albeit weakly). Finally, a significant coherence between spring-NAO and beech M_index was found using both NOAA, and Hurrell indices since 1985 at frequencies of about 8 to 16 years, but this was mostly out of the cone of influence (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6b</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6d</a>). For spruce, a coherence with spring-NAO remained weak around 11 years for the second half of the twentieth century (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5c</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite major differences in significance and stationarity between the winter-NAO and the summer- and spring-NAO, we opted for further testing of the low-frequency component of all seasonal NAO indices. In the final regression models, low-frequency indices with a periodicity of 11 years (i.e., the midpoint between 7 and 16 years) were included for both species.</p>
</sec>
