<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Masting index</div>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To analyse the response of beech and spruce masting at the sub-continental scale we computed an annual masting index for both species representing how much of the species distribution range displays a heavy seed crop in each year. We used the MASTREE database
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, which contains the longest available masting record for European beech and Norway spruce covering most of both species distribution and including annually resolved observations of beech and spruce seed production or related proxies (e.g., flowering, airborne pollen, fruiting, and dendrochronological reconstruction). We truncated the data to 2015 and 2014, and excluded the pollen and flowering proxies for beech and spruce respectively. We limited our analysis to the Central-Northern European regions, i.e., the core area of beech and spruce distribution where climate is most influenced by NAO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, and where all previous studies were focused (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). In total, we selected 5774 yearly observations from 337 series in 40 NUTS-1 (Nomenclature of Territorial Units for Statistics) for beech, and 5119 yearly observations from 191 series in 37 NUTS-1 for spruce (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). For each series, we extracted the five class ordinal masting index (from 1: very poor, to 5: very abundant) provided by MASTREE (column ORDmast). To avoid oversampling in regions with multiple data-series, we aggregated individual masting series into NUTS-1 chronologies by using the modal masting class for each year and NUTS-1. This produced long masting series with a minimum amount of missing data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. We then computed the annual masting index (M_index) for both species as the difference between the proportion of NUTS-1 displaying a good masting (classes 4 and 5, 
  <span class="italic">NC-45</span>) and a poor masting (classes 1 and 2, 
  <span class="italic">NC-12</span>) in any given year. M_index varies from − 1, when all NUTS-1 are in class 1 and 2 (broad masting failure), to + 1 when all NUTS-1 are in masting classes 4 and 5 synchronously. Intermediate (zero) values indicate a prevalence of class-3 masting, or a balanced distribution of 
  <span class="italic">NC-45</span> and 
  <span class="italic">NC-12</span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). M_index was computed on a different number of NUTS-1 each year, but covered a continuous period from 1760 to 2015 and 1800 to 2014 for beech and spruce, respectively (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
