<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NAO–masting relationships and weather patterns</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlation between seasonal NAO indices and temperature and precipitation anomalies in Central-Northern Europe (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) were consistent with weather patterns described in previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Positive winter-NAO was correlated to positive anomalies in both temperature and precipitation. Positive spring-NAO corresponded to mild temperatures and dry weather, whereas positive summer-NAO to positive anomalies in temperature and negative anomalies in precipitation throughout Central-Northern Europe.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>NAO and related weather patterns in temperature and precipitation. Correlation between NAO and temperature anomalies (first row), and between NAO and precipitation anomalies (second row) for the seasons winter, spring, summer (columns from left to right). Regions with significant correlations are denoted by black dots. Monthly precipitation and temperature have been obtained from the CRU database (version TS4.00). We aggregated these time series into seasonal time-series and the NAO indices according to our experiment design: winter (December–January–February–March, DJFM), spring (April–May, AM), and summer (June–July–August–September, JJAS). The period between 1950 and 2015 was considered for the correlation analysis. Figure created using ggplot2 package for R
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2017_2348_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1510" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
