<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> presents the trends of rainfall in the Ashanti region of Ghana. As shown in 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>a, the major and minor rainfall seasons show an increasing trends in rainfall, even though, the minor season shows a higher magnitude of increase (3.32mm) in rainfall than the major season (1.59mm). Similarly, there is an increase in annual rainfall in the region as revealed by the trend line in 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>b, with an even higher magnitude of 5.08mm. The oscillatory pattern of rainfall shows that the highest rainfall over the past 30 years was received in 2007 (1794.9mm), indicating the wettest year, while 1996 was the driest year over the same period with a rainfall of 1040.9mm (see 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>b). For seasonal trends (see Figure 2a), 2002 and 2007 received the highest rainfall of 990.4mm and 740.1mm, respectively, for major and minor rainfall seasons. According to the Ministry of Environment, Science, Technology and Innovation (MESTI) (2013), Ghana observed decreasing rainfall pattern from 1960s. However, as posited by 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">IPCC (2007)</xref>, a unit increase in temperature may account for 1–3% increase in precipitation. Rising temperature in Ghana may therefore be responsible for the increasing rainfall trends observed in this study. Studies have also projected increasing rainfall across West Africa (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Bindoff et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">IPCC, 2007</xref>). Increasing rainfall offers opportunity for smallholder farmers to increase agriculture production. For instance, increasing rainfall in the minor raining season will be suitable for the cultivation of early maturing crops, due to brevity of the minor rainfall season. Nevertheless, excessive rainfall leads to flood and erosion, which affects crop production (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">IPCC, 2018</xref>).
</p>
