<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plant secondary compounds (PSCs) have high chemical diversity with an estimated 200,000 compounds (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dixon and Strack, 2003</xref>). In higher plants, terpenoids (approximately 30,000 known compounds, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lämke and Unsicker, 2018</xref>), alkaloids (21,000) (
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wink, 2010</xref>), and phenolic compounds (8,000) (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Munné-Bosch, 2012</xref>) are the most diverse PSC groups. The majority of PSCs are related to plant chemical defense and herbivore pressure, which are considered the main drivers of PSC diversification (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lämke and Unsicker, 2018</xref>). Terpenoids originate directly from glycolysis of glucose via the mevalonate pathway or the methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathway (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bartram et al., 2006</xref>). Phenolic compounds originate from the shikimic acid pathway, which is related to the metabolism of carbohydrates and aromatic amino acids (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seigler, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lindroth, 2012</xref>). Most of the alkaloids are derived from amino acid precursors (
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wink, 2010</xref>), but coniferous alkaloids are synthesized via the polyketide pathway (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seigler, 1998</xref>). Terpenes and phenolics are the most extensively studied PSCs in forest trees (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lindroth, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lämke and Unsicker, 2018</xref>), while alkaloids have been considered in relatively few studies (
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Virjamo et al., 2014</xref>). Alkaloids and phenolics may compete more with protein synthesis than terpenoids (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Koricheva, 2002</xref>). Up to 10% of recently fixed carbon can be allocated to volatile organic compounds (VOCs) in stressed plants (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Peñuelas and Staudt, 2010</xref>), while stored terpenoids typically require secretory structures such as resin canals and glandular trichomes to avoid autotoxicity (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Goodger et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
