<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The only way yields could increase from HISTORIC in the model simulations would be for a combination of increasing temperature and increasing precipitation to result in an environment more favorable for maize growth. While this happened in some simulations in the Ummenhofer et al. study, and yields increased from 8 Mg ha
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>, our shifting of the HISTORIC time period to produce an average yield of 11 Mg ha
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> appears to be near a peak, as yields only decreased from this value in almost all model simulations. There is some other evidence for yields reaching a peak near the turn of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century (see for example [
 <xref rid="pone.0156083.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0156083.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]). Challinor et al. compare findings from a meta-analysis for the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC AR4; [
 <xref rid="pone.0156083.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]) that suggested that global cereal yields could continue to increase with up to 2°C of warming, before declining, with their new results that showed both increases and decreases for wheat yield and overall greater risk of cereal yield reductions than reported in AR4 [
 <xref rid="pone.0156083.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. They also suggested that because greater yield declines are predicted for the latter half of the century, that earlier in the century farmer adaptation could mitigate yield loss, but that more transformational strategies will be needed later. Our results support this statement as the strong correlation in simulation results between shortened growing period and increasing temperature in the near future, coupled with a weakening of this relationship later in the century, suggest that yields might be maintained in the near future by alleviating moisture stress and by using warmer season cultivars, but breeding for extreme heat tolerance along with other adaptations might be required to maintain yields by the end of the century.
</p>
