<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Meeting the physical survival needs of children during a disaster is not sufficient to ensure that their experience of the disaster does not continue to impair their mental, social and emotional development. Children are particularly vulnerable to emotional trauma from sudden changes in their daily lives, social networks and sense of security [
 <xref rid="B9-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Mental and emotional distress is commonly reported in children and adolescents following natural disasters, including post-traumatic stress disorders, sleep disturbance, aggressive behaviour, depression and anxiety, and substance abuse [
 <xref rid="B14-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. But adverse mental health impacts of stress and trauma may not be immediately apparent, and can persist for extended periods post-disaster [
 <xref rid="B29-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. There is already clear evidence that traumatic events during the childhood years can have lasting effects on mental health and cognitive development [
 <xref rid="B26-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The risks are particularly high for children without strong social support networks (such as those in displaced or fragmented families) [
 <xref rid="B25-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], for those with a family history of psychological distress [
 <xref rid="B30-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], for those with low family incomes [
 <xref rid="B30-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] and for those who experience subsequent traumatic events during childhood [
 <xref rid="B29-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Parental stress also has an important impact on child health outcomes following a disaster. Studies have shown that rates of child maltreatment, abuse and inflicted traumatic brain injuries increase in the 6 months following natural disasters [
 <xref rid="B33-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-children-01-00461" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], which is thought to be related to parental stress associated with the loss of resources and/or livelihoods, and the disruption of social support structures.
</p>
