<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract abstract-type="summary" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Author summary</title>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Why was this study done?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Diarrheal disease remains a persistent global health threat for children under 5 years of age, particularly in Africa.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">In river—floodplain systems, annual floods or flood pulses can occur, with extreme flooding and drought a common threat to local populations. We do not know how surface water dynamics influence diarrheal disease and human health or how climate change will affect populations dependent on surface water resources in these regions.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <title class="title">What did the researchers do and find?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We conducted a study on the Chobe River floodplain system in northern Botswana, a system that floods annually and is the source of drinking water for 8 villages included in the study.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We evaluated diarrheal outbreak patterns in children under 5 years of age (weekly, 2007–2017) and individuals of all ages (monthly, 1998–2017) reporting diarrheal disease at government health facilities (
     <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 10).
    </p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Using multimodel inference approaches, we assessed how meteorology, river height, and water quality characteristics (2011–2017) were associated with reports of diarrheal disease in children under 5 years of age.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Across individuals of all ages, diarrheal outbreaks occurred regularly in the wet and dry seasons.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Season had an important influence on the type of diarrhea and age group of the patient.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Increases in diarrheal case reports were closely tied to meteorology, flood recession, and decreases in surface water quality, with the highest number of cases occurring in the dry season.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <title class="title">What do these findings mean?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">In flood pulse river—floodplain systems, rapid changes in surface water quality may influence the ability of water treatment plants to provide safe drinking water.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Climate change is expected to increase hydrological variability, further influencing the vulnerability of populations in this region.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">There is an urgent need to strengthen water infrastructure to address current and future environmental impacts that can influence the production of safe water.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">In populations with high HIV infection levels, public health focus may need to be extended to include other at-risk groups beyond children under five, such as HIV-infected individuals and others that may also be immunocompromised.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">As distant weather patterns influence local flood dynamics, use of country-level data may not be adequate to predict climate impacts on human health in these types of systems.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</abstract>
