<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">If projections in this study question the future relevance of the current ecological classification of the forest landscape, they also raise important issues regarding the forest management regime, especially under the assumption that an ecosystem is defined by a relatively stable climate and substrate. The ecological principles that underlie current ecosystem-based management emphasize the need to reduce the differences between natural and managed landscapes (
 <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gauthier et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). They imply that sustainable forest management practices should aim for a desired composition and age structure. This becomes quite a challenge if the target composition is moving fast under a new climate regime (
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dhital et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mori et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Therefore, the greatest challenges in coming years will be to manage rapid transitions of forests towards other, largely unknown, steady-states. As a result, the adaptation literature has repeatedly highlighted the need to move from a paradigm of preserving current conditions or restoring ‘historical fidelity’ to one of managing for novel ecosystems that may differ in composition, structure, and/or function (
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hobbs, Higgs &amp; Harris</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Models provide some indications of where the challenges could be the greatest, and whether or not species at risk are worth maintaining at specific locations under a shifting climate. Publicly managed forests in the study area, for instance, are restored to production largely by prioritizing practices that protect the established regeneration. Where regeneration is insufficient, as may increasingly be the case on sites that we identified as ‘at risk’, reforestation may be carried out. However, the choice of species is for the most part still made under the assumption that suitable conditions in this century will be similar to the ones in recent history. New practices are being tested to maximize forest resiliency while taking into account transition states, for instance by helping shift composition (including genetic variability) towards species or individuals adapted to the new climate regime (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Breed et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Koralewski et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Park Williams et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). As well, maintaining biodiverse (both in terms of composition and age structure) forests and landscapes could provide some insurance against instability (
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Churchill et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thompson et al.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>).
</p>
