<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Findings on the negative impacts of climate change on pastures and livestock health concur with those by Hopping et al. [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>] who reported that pastoralists in the Tibetan rangelands, China, have the same opinion that changing climate is driving undesirable trends in grassland and livestock health. Rose et al. [
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] also noted cases of decline in pastures due to low and erratic rainfall. Other authors have also noted that livestock production faces the problem of poor and variable rangeland productivity and desertification processes [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Generally, reduction in fresh water resources affects natural resource and climate-dependent sectors such as forestry, agriculture, water, and fisheries [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Findings from this study indicate that local communities use LEK to detect changes in water resources due to climate change and variability. Respondents indicated that frequent extreme events such as drought and increasing temperatures affect soil moisture and surface water availability for both domestic use and agriculture. This is in line with United Nations Framework on Climate Change [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>] assertion that Africa faces challenges related to water availability and spatial variations in the location and need for water resources. Observations from this study are also similar to those by Taylor et al. [
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] who noticed that more frequent and intense climate extremes such as droughts and floods increase variability in soil moisture and surface water. Observations in this study related to drying up of rivers and poor water quality in surface and groundwater systems coincide with findings by Urama and Ozor [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>] who reported that impacts on water resources act in conjunction with other factors to affect ecosystem health and socioeconomic well-being of human communities. For example, Mburu Gathuru and Kaguna [
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] also noticed that, in Kenya, climate change interacts with anthropogenic activities along rivers to contribute to reduction of river water volume over time and weakening of critical ecosystems like forest watersheds.
</p>
