<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study we investigated the climatic suitability for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada. The objective was to quantitatively assess the current and future climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission under two greenhouse gas emissions scenarios (RCP4.5 and RCP8.5) using simulations from RCM to provide insight into where, when and for how long local transmission of CHIKV might occur in Canada. To achieve this, we assessed the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M177" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">0</mn>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) and combined this with the climatic suitability for the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> (
 <xref rid="c68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ogden et al. 2015</xref>), on the assumption that for autochthonous transmission to occur, there must be climatic suitability for both pathogen transmission for a minimum of 1 month, and for the vector over a sustained period (
 <xref rid="c32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fischer et al. 2013</xref>). Clearly with a minimum EIP duration of approximately 6 days at 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M178" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">28</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> for CHIKV (
 <xref rid="c46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>), autochthonous transmission could occur in locations where temperature conditions suitable for transmission occur for periods shorter than 1 month. However, in Canada, temperatures are not frequently 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M179" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mo class="mo">≥</mo>
    <mn class="mn">28</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> for sustained periods. The mean monthly temperature for the warmest month of the year for Canada south of 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M180" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">60</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">N</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> under recent climate was 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M181" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">15.7</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> with a range of 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M182" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">3.5</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> to 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M183" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">23.4</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>. The mean EIP from 50,000 iterations in the 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M184" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">0</mn>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> model was approximately 14.4 days when temperature was held at 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M185" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">23.4</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, suggesting monthly values are appropriate to explore the CHIKV transmission cycle period in Canada. There may be a slight underestimate of risk of autochthonous transmission were endemic mosquito species to be competent vectors but as 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> population persistence depends on year-round temperature conditions it should have a lesser effect on risk of transmission by this species. Most of the areas that were identified as climatically suitable for CHIKV transmission were not suitable for 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> due to the latter having requirements for generally warmer climate. The climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential is driven by temperature, in particular the temperature-dependent EIP of CHIKV in the vector population and vector survival beyond the duration of the EIP (
 <xref rid="c46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>), while climatic suitability for the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> is dependent on bioclimatic conditions that are known to influence the vector’s ecology including the ability of eggs to overwinter, precipitation to initiate egg hatching and warm summer temperature for mosquitoes to reach a viable reproducing population over a sustained period for successive transmission cycles (
 <xref rid="c11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Caminade et al. 2012</xref>).
</p>
