<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">The velocities of climate change (km/year for all variables) were calculated for 1951–2015 following the methods of Loarie 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> and Burrows 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> as ratios of Sen’s slope estimators for temporal trends and absolute values of spatial gradients (°C/km for temperature and mm/km for precipitation), with the direction of the velocity oriented along the direction of spatial gradient. To be consistent with our approach to temporal trends, we calculated median instead of the mean long-term spatial gradients (see Supplementary Information for more details). Climate change velocities calculated by this method are often named “local” as they consider spatial variability within the immediate neighbourhood of a location
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> and, when combined with a fine spatial resolution of data, they give fine grain estimates of residence times and velocities of climates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. On the other side, as pointed out in
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>, the values can approach infinity in areas of small spatial gradients, such as flat terrain, and underestimate values in mountainous terrain where spatial gradients can be several orders of magnitude larger (constraining near-zero values of spatial gradients is described in Supplementary Information
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>). Hence species in large topographically homogenous areas would have to move at high speed to keep pace with climate change, whereas in mountain regions the calculated migration rate might be lower than is actually required.
</p>
