<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The present commentary builds on earlier reviews (
 <xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McMichael et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Patz et al. 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Perera 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schwartz 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sheffield and Landrigan 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al. 2012</xref>) to summarize the current scientific evidence regarding the array of current and projected health and economic impacts in children from air pollution and climate change resulting from the burning of fossil fuels. The data alone provide a powerful argument for an integrated and child-centered air pollution and energy policy. However, going beyond the scientific and economic arguments, as Pope Francis has reminded us in his recent Encyclical “Laudato Si’” (
 <xref rid="r69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pope Francis 2015</xref>), is the powerful moral imperative to protect children and the less fortunate from toxic pollution and climate change. The pope’s message that global capitalism, based on the burning of fossil fuels, has created unsustainable consumption and shocking inequities within and between countries was also sounded in the recent report of the Lancet Commission (
 <xref rid="r108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Watts et al. 2015</xref>). By highlighting the disproportionately heavy burden that falls on the very young, and especially the poor, who are most vulnerable to toxic air pollutants, as well as CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-driven climate change from the combustion of coal, oil, and natural gas, the large body of evidence reviewed here calls for urgent and coordinated action to protect children. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Figures 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">2</xref> show the multiple combustion-related emissions and their associated impacts on the health of children, and hence the scope of the benefits that would result from decarbonization of the economy.
</p>
