<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural Disasters</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural disasters such as hurricanes and tornados have the potential to focus society’s collective attention and spark conversations about climate change. A person’s belief in climate change is often correlated with the weather on the day the question is asked [
  <a rid="pone.0136092.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136092.ref040">40</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0136092.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136092.ref042">42</a>]. A study using “climate change” and “global warming” tweets showed that both weather and mass media coverage heavily influence belief in anthropogenic climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0136092.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136092.ref043">43</a>]. In this section, we analyze tweets during three natural disasters: Hurricane Irene, Hurricane Sandy, and a midwest tornado outbreak that damaged many towns including Moore, Oklahoma and Rozel, Kansas. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g007" href="#pone.0136092.g007">Fig 7</a> gives the frequencies of the words “hurricane” and “tornado” within tweets that contain the word “climate”. Each plot labels several of the spikes with the names of the hurricanes (top) or the locations (state abbreviations) of the tornado outbreaks (bottom). This figure indicates that before Hurricane Irene in August 2011, hurricanes were not commonly referenced alongside climate, and before the April 2011 tornado outbreak in Alabama and Mississippi, tornados were not commonly referenced alongside climate.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0136092.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136092.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Frequency of the word “hurricane” (top) and “tornado” (bottom) within tweets containing the word “climate”.</div>
   <p>Several spikes have been identified with the hurricane or tornado that took place during that time period.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136092.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This analysis, however, will not capture every hurricane or tornado mentioned on Twitter, only those that were referenced alongside the word “climate”. Hurricane Arthur, for example, occurred in early July, 2014 and does not appear as a spike in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g007" href="#pone.0136092.g007">Fig 7</a>. This particular hurricane did not cause nearly as much damage or as many fatalities as the hurricanes that do appear in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g007" href="#pone.0136092.g007">Fig 7</a>, and perhaps did not draw enough attention to highlight a link between hurricanes and climate change on Twitter. Additionally, a large tornado outbreak in Kentucky, Alabama, Indiana, and Ohio occurred in early March 2012 and does not appear as a spike in our analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g007" href="#pone.0136092.g007">Fig 7</a> shows that the largest peak in the word “hurricane” occurred during Hurricane Sandy in October 2012. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g008" href="#pone.0136092.g008">Fig 8</a> provides a deeper analysis for the climate time series during Hurricane Sandy. The time series of the words “hurricane” and “climate” as a fraction of all tweets before, during, and after Hurricane Sandy hit are given in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g008" href="#pone.0136092.g008">Fig 8(a) and 8(c)</a>. Spikes in the frequency of usage of these words is evident in these plots. The decay of each word is fitted with a power law in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g008" href="#pone.0136092.g008">Fig 8(b) and 8(d)</a>. A power law is a functional relationship of the following form: 
  <div id="pone.0136092.e001" class="disp-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0136092.e001.jpg" id="pone.0136092.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">f</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mi">t</span>
       <span class="mo">-</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">t</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">e</span>
         <span class="mi">v</span>
         <span class="mi">e</span>
         <span class="mi">n</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mi">α</span>
      <div class="msup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <span class="mi">t</span>
        <span class="mo">-</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <span class="mi">t</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">e</span>
          <span class="mi">v</span>
          <span class="mi">e</span>
          <span class="mi">n</span>
          <span class="mi">t</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">-</span>
        <span class="mi">γ</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="label">(1)</span>
  </div> Here, 
  <span class="italic">t</span> is measured in days, and 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">event</span>
  </sub> is the day Hurricane Sandy made landfall. 
  <span class="italic">f</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) represents the relative frequency of the word “hurricane” (top) or “climate” (bottom), and 
  <span class="italic">α</span> and 
  <span class="italic">γ</span> are constants.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0136092.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136092.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Decay rates of the words “hurricane” (top) and “climate” (bottom).</div>
   <p>The left plots gives the time series of each word during hurricane Sandy. The right plots gives the power law fit for the decay in relative frequency, x-axes are spaced logarithmically. The power law exponents are given in the titles of the figures.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136092.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the power law fit, we calculate the first three half lives of the decay. Letting 
  <span class="italic">M</span> equal the maximum relative frequency, the time at which the first half life of the power law relationship occurs is calculated by 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0136092.e002" href="#pone.0136092.e002">Eq 2</a>: 
  <div id="pone.0136092.e002" class="disp-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0136092.e002.jpg" id="pone.0136092.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M2" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">t</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="mfrac">
         <span class="mn">1</span>
         <span class="mn">2</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="msup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">(</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="mfrac">
           <span class="mi">M</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span class="mn">2</span>
            <span class="mi">α</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">−</span>
        <div class="mfrac">
         <span class="mn">1</span>
         <span class="mi">γ</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="label">(2)</span>
  </div> The first three half lives of the decay in the frequency of the word “hurricane” during hurricane Sandy are 1.57, 0.96, and 1.56 additional days. Since the decay is not exponential, these half lives are not constant. The first half life indicates that after about a day and a half, “hurricane” was already tweeted only half as often. The second half life indicates that after one more day, “hurricane” was tweeted only one fourth as often, and so on. Thus, it did not take long for the discussion of the hurricane to decrease. The half lives, however, of the word “climate” are much larger at 8.19, 22.58, and 84.85 days.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0136092.g009" href="#pone.0136092.g009">Fig 9</a> gives happiness time series plots for three natural disasters occurring in the United States. These plots show that there is a dip in happiness on the day that the disasters hit the affected areas, offering additional evidence that sentiment is depressed by natural disasters [
  <a rid="pone.0136092.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0136092.ref024">24</a>]. The word shift graphs indicate which words contributed to the dip in happiness. The circles on the bottom right of the word shift plots indicate that for all three disasters, the dip in happiness is due to an increase in negative words, more so than a decrease in positive words. During a natural disaster, tweets mentioning the word “climate” use more negative words than tweets not mentioning the word “climate”.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0136092.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0136092.g009</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Happiness time series plots for tweets containing the word “climate” one week before and one week after three natural disasters in the United States (top) and word shift graphs indicating what words contributed most to the drop in happiness during the natural disasters (bottom).</div>
   <p>The word shift graphs compare the climate tweets to unfiltered tweets on the day of the natural disaster.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0136092.g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
