<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animal models</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential for evolutionary change in a population facing a drastic environmental modification such as climate change is related to the amount of standing genetic variation for important adaptive traits, and also to the strength of selection acting on these traits. Indeed, in a quantitative genetics framework, two key models have been used to predict the evolution of selected traits. First, the so-called ‘breeder's equation’ predicts the response to selection (
  <span class="italic">R</span>) based on estimations of heritability (
  <span class="italic">h</span>²) and the strength of selection (
  <span class="italic">S</span>, Falconer and Mackay 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">1996</a>): 
  <span class="italic">R</span> = 
  <span class="italic">h²S</span>. Ideally, this approach should be applied in a multivariate framework (the multivariate ‘Lande equation’), where the vector 
  <span class="italic">R</span> of responses in a set of traits depends on the 
  <span class="italic">G</span> matrix of additive genetic (co)variances for these traits and the selection gradients 
  <span class="italic">β</span>: 
  <span class="italic">R = G β</span> (Lande 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">1979</a>). Second, the Robertson-Price Identity relates the evolutionary change (
  <span class="italic">R)</span> to the genetic covariance of the focal trait (
  <span class="italic">z</span>) with relative fitness (
  <span class="italic">w</span>): 
  <span class="italic">R = σ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">a</span>
  </sub>
  <span class="italic">(z,w)</span> (Robertson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b102" href="#b102">1966</a>; Price 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b90" href="#b90">1970</a>). Data on individual phenotypes, individual fitness, and relatedness between individuals in the focal population (i.e. a pedigree) are essential prerequisites for these estimations. Quantitative genetic analyses such as the animal model rely on phenotypic resemblance among relatives to estimate quantitative genetic parameters, such as heritability or genetic correlations (Falconer and Mackay 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">1996</a>; Lynch and Walsh 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b70" href="#b70">1998</a>). When studying wild bird populations, controlled breeding is usually impossible, hence quantitative genetic analyses rely on observing or reconstructing relatedness between phenotyped individuals. ‘Classical’ approaches are parent–offspring regression or full- or half-sib analyses where the degree of phenotypic similarity between offspring and parents or sibling groups is used to estimate additive genetic (co)variances. Animal models are better-suited for the study of natural populations as they can make use of the phenotypic information of relatives via the pedigree (Wilson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b129" href="#b129">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to obtain individual data and assess heritability and selection, it is necessary to uniquely mark individuals, to follow them through their life-time (or at least a substantial part of it) and to reliably record the desired phenotypes, such as dates of initiation of breeding or dates of migration. Furthermore, it is also essential to link parents to their offspring to construct the pedigree. As birds can be easily individually marked by metal and coloured plastic leg-rings, and many avian species have extended brood care, in which often both parents take part, the necessary data for quantitative genetic analyses are comparably easily collected in birds. Several long-term studies have collected such data in some cases already for decades and they now offer a wealth of high-quality individual data suitable for sophisticated quantitative genetic analyses (Collins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">2001</a>; Postma and Charmantier 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b89" href="#b89">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In theory, the best way to test for microevolution in real time is to estimate the individual genetic values, or breeding values, for the studied trait, and explore the changes in the mean breeding values over time (example in Garant et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">2004</a>; review in Kruuk 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">2004</a>). In practice, however, the use of breeding values predicted from animal models can introduce serious biases in the analyses and conclusions reached regarding microevolution, because they do not always adequately reflect true breeding values. First, trends in predicted breeding values can mimic the observed phenotypic trend, even in the absence of a genetic change, if the phenotypic change over time is environmentally induced and this temporal variation is inadequately modelled (Postma 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b88" href="#b88">2006</a>). Second, predicted values are always associated with (often large) standard errors, and they are non-independent for individuals of the same population, hence statistical care should be invested in controlling for this uncertainty and non-independence (Hadfield et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">2010</a>). Overall, the use of breeding values to test for microevolution requires special statistical attention and caution (see e.g. Milot et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b75" href="#b75">2011</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
