<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Are the changes adaptive in the face of climate change?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation is ultimately necessary for population persistence as sustained maladaptation can lead to extinction (Kopp and Hendry this issue; Gonzalez et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">2013</a>) unless counteracted by density dependence (Chevin and Lande 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">2010</a>; Reed et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b100" href="#b100">2013a</a>). Phenotypic plasticity can allow a rapid adjustment to novel environmental conditions and even if this does not always allow a perfect tracking of the changing environment, as pointed out above, it could allow populations to persist in the short-term and ‘buy time’ for evolutionary adaptation in the long term (Chevin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">2010</a>; Kovach-Orr and Fussmann 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">2013</a>). Alternatively, plasticity can also hamper adaptation, in particular when new stressful environmental conditions trigger non-adaptive plasticity (Ghalambor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">2007</a>). Hence, a better understanding of adaptive and non-adaptive phenotypic plasticity and genetic variation in natural populations is important to predict adaptation to climate change. As only adaptation will allow populations to persist, such predictions will allow a better assessment of possible threats of climate change to biodiversity. However, information about whether an observed response is due to plasticity or evolution will yield limited information towards this ultimate goal. Showing that a population is adjusting through phenotypic plasticity, for example, by demonstrating the absence of genetic change in the presence of phenotypic change, does not directly show that the observed phenotypic plasticity is ‘adaptive’, hence it does not guarantee that the population is ‘demographically safe’. The same applies for evolutionary responses: Evolutionary responses to environmental change may be too slow to rescue a population under sustained environmental change (Bürger and Lynch 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">1995</a>; Chevin and Lande 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">2010</a>; Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">2013</a>). Besides disentangling phenotypically plastic and evolutionary responses to environmental change, we also need to know to what extent these responses are ‘fully adaptive’, that is, how much selection is acting on the trait under consideration.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the particular case of responses to climate change, it is important to mention that many studies have documented selection favouring earlier breeding pairs before climate change was a recognized issue (Perrins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">1965</a>; Lack 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b62" href="#b62">1968</a>; Price et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b91" href="#b91">1988</a>). Hence, demonstrating that earlier breeding is an adaptive response to climate change requires showing that selection for earlier breeding is stronger with (as opposed to without) climate change, in the absence of a less-than-perfect plastic response. This task involves a comparison of selection across years with differing climates or (preferably) identifying the factor(s) causing selection and showing that it is driven by climatic factors. The above cited studies on great tits provide such analyses. The study of Dutch great tits in Hoge Veluwe demonstrates that selection is driven by the temporal mismatch with the caterpillar food supply and that caterpillar phenology has advanced due to increasing spring temperatures (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>, Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b125" href="#b125">2006</a>; Reed et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b101" href="#b101">2013b</a>). In the British tit study of Wytham woods, only warm springs show a strong directional selection for earlier breeding (see fig. 2A in Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">2008</a>). Another example comes from pied flycatchers 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span> where selection on breeding time is driven by spring temperatures during the arrival period of offspring and where these spring temperatures change due to climate change (M.E. Visser, P. Gienapp, A. Husby, M. Morrissey, I. de la Hera, F. Pulido, and C. Both, unpublished data). Studies demonstrating such statistical links between the strength of selection and the presence of climate change are unfortunately still scarce. The take-home message here is that we should be careful when inferring adaptive responses to climate change from the fact that selection and observed phenotypic change are in the same direction unless we are sure that selection is driven by a changing climate.
 </p>
</sec>
