<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolutionary potential of breeding and migration timing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many long-term individual monitoring studies of birds have offered the possibility to estimate the heritability of timing of breeding, and it is now well known that egg-laying dates are commonly heritable [e.g. 
  <span class="italic">h</span>² = 0.192 (SE = 0.036) in the collared flycatcher 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicollis</span>, Sheldon et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b111" href="#b111">2003</a>; 
  <span class="italic">h</span>² = 0.159 (SD = 0.059) in the great tit 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>, McCleery et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b72" href="#b72">2004</a>; and 
  <span class="italic">h</span>² = 0.145 in the common gull 
  <span class="italic">Larus canus</span>, Brommer and Rattiste 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">2008</a>] although two case studies have shown no significant heritability for female egg-laying dates (in the mute swan 
  <span class="italic">Cygnus olor</span>, Charmantier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">2006</a>; and in the red-billed gull 
  <span class="italic">Larus novaehollandiae scopulinus</span>, Teplitsky et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b117" href="#b117">2010</a>). Similarly, a review of 12 avian studies (mostly laboratory based) showed that traits related to the timing of migration are commonly heritable, with a mean heritability of 0.34 (SD = 0.24) (Pulido 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b93" href="#b93">2007a</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b94" href="#b94">b</a>). More strikingly, experiments inducing artificial directional selection on migratory activity in the blackcap 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span> induced a significant delay in the mean autumn departure date by the same order of magnitude than that predicted by the breeder's equation (Pulido et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" href="#b97">2001</a>), thereby confirming strong evolutionary potential for the timing of migration.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, previous investigations in avian populations show that timing of breeding and timing of migration are heritable in many species, and in the face of climate change they are classically under strong negative directional selection. However, demonstrating that an avian phenological trait is heritable and is under directional selection only suggests that there is potential for adaptive evolution, but is insufficient to conclude that an advance of the average population laying date or arrival date from migration can be attributed to evolutionary adaptation (e.g. Teplitsky et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b117" href="#b117">2010</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
