<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other approaches</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Merilä and Hendry (this issue) have listed other approaches that allow plasticity and microevolution to be disentangled as processes underlying the observed changes attributable to climate change, yet several of these are difficult if not impossible to implement when focusing on avian phenology. Laboratory studies on avian breeding time are possible and have been conducted in temperature- and/or photoperiod-controlled aviaries to identify environmental cues on the timing of egg-laying (Lambrechts et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" href="#b63">1997</a>; Visser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b123" href="#b123">2008</a>), as well as underlying physiological pathways involved (Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b126" href="#b126">2010</a>). However, using temperature effects from such laboratory experiments to make predictions about phenotypically plastic responses to temperature in the wild is problematic due to the highly artificial conditions in the laboratory, such as 
  <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food or confinement stress. Studying true timing of migration in the laboratory is obviously impossible but proxies for this, for example migratory restlessness, have been used in artificial selection experiments in the blackcap 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla,</span> providing important insight in the potential for adaptive evolution in the timing of autumn migration (Pulido et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" href="#b97">2001</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Common garden experiments are a powerful tool to test for genetic differentiation across space, and have, for example, been used in birds to test whether populations vary in their response to photoperiod (e.g. Berthold and Querner 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">1981</a>; Silverin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b112" href="#b112">1993</a>; Lambrechts et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" href="#b63">1997</a>). While common garden experiments are in theory equally well suited to test for genetic differentiation across time, by repeatedly testing the same population, this either requires long-term studies started a long time ago, or if started now, considerable long-term planning and effort. Consequently, contrarily to other taxa reviewed in this special issue (see in particular Collins et al., 2013) very few studies have used this approach in birds to test for genetic changes over time (but see an example in Pulido and Berthold 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b96" href="#b96">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most obvious and direct way to test for genetic change is to assess changes at the molecular genetic level. This however requires good knowledge of the molecular genetic architecture of the avian migration and breeding traits. Important progress has been made recently in understanding the molecular basis for the circadian clock regulating daily rhythms in invertebrates and vertebrates (including birds, see e.g. Johnsen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">2007</a>). However, attempts to relate breeding phenology (Liedvogel and Sheldon 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b67" href="#b67">2010</a>; Caprioli et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">2012</a>; Liedvogel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b68" href="#b68">2012</a>) or migration phenology (Dor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2011</a>; Mueller et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" href="#b79">2011</a>) to 
  <span class="italic">Clock gene</span> polymorphism or other candidate genes have so far yielded little. Undoubtedly, genomic approaches provide exciting opportunities to test for evolutionary responses of phenology to climate change, yet at present the lack of consistent relationships across species prevents any generalization. Note also that although identifying candidate genes may be the most direct route to documenting genetic change, it might not contribute to determining how much of the change in phenotype through time was the result of genetic change (Merilä &amp; Hendry, this issue).
 </p>
</sec>
