<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The pioneering British malacologist, William Henry Benson, brought a pair of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> to India from Mauritius, and handed them to a friend and neighbor before leaving the country. It was this friend who released the snails in his garden in Kolkata, eastern India [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Later, in 1858, Benson reported that 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> had become well established in Kolkata [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> has been considered as a serious pest to small-scale agriculture, horticulture and home gardens [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. In India, the spread of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> was primarily mediated by humans. For example, a farmer has introduced it from Orissa to his farm in Araku valley in Andhra Pradesh in 1996 [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]; a blacksmith was believed to have brought 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> as a pet from Kolkata to north Bihar some time during 60s [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Since then it has invaded many parts of both the states. This could be the case for many other sites. The snail being large in size and attractive might have fascinated pet keepers and hence got transported to many parts of the country from Kolkata. By mid-20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> century, 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> attained serious pest status in India and caused severe damage to agricultural crops [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Many studies in India have reported the impact of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> invasion on horticultural and agricultural crops; however, none have quantified the exact economic loss [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. In the late 1970s, this snail was reported to damage ornamental and vegetable crops in Bangalore [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Since then, several reports have shown that 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> causes serious damage to variety of horticultural and agricultural crops viz., mulberry [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>], betel-vine, capsicum, areca, banana, tomato [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], vanilla [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] and vegetable crops such as potato, spinach, radish and tomato [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Raut &amp; Ghose [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] stated that nearly 90% plants cultivated in India were eaten by 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic>. The pest generally feeds on the succulent parts of the plants and damages the small and tender parts and seedlings completely. They feed not only on leaves but also on flowers, buds, tender shoots and fruits. Given the broad spectrum of food choice and increased precipitation in Southern India due to climate change, the invasion of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> might exacerbate the situation. At present, the range has extended through much of India, Nepal, Bhutan, Bangladesh and Sri Lanka [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. A recent genetic study showed that all 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fulica</italic> now occurring throughout South Asia, Southeast Asia and the Pacific Region are derived from a single haplotype [
 <xref rid="pone.0143724.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>].
</p>
