<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.3 Low Latitudes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global SAT response to deforestation of 15% and higher is a general increase followed by cooling (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g010" href="#pone.0153357.g010">Fig 10</a>). The magnitude and rate of initial warming tends to be proportional to the deforested area fraction and higher deforestation fractions tend to reach their peak positive anomaly sooner. Similar to the mid-latitude experiments, albedo effects start to overcome the initial CO
  <sub>2</sub> driven warming but not to the point of generating negative anomalies (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g010" href="#pone.0153357.g010">Fig 10</a>). For the 5% scenario there is relatively constant warming associated with the progressive loss of forested area and addition of CO
  <sub>2</sub> to the atmosphere seen in this experiment (see Carbon Cycle results below). SAT change over deforested bins is eventually dominated by the local increase in albedo and differs significantly from what is seen globally. At the end of the simulation all scenarions show negative local anomalies. As in the global case, the relative importance of albedo effects tend to be increase with deforested area (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g010" href="#pone.0153357.g010">Fig 10</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153357.g010" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153357.g010</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 10</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Annually averaged global air surface temperature anomalies for low latitude deforestation (Top). Annually averaged air surface temperature anomalies over deforested areas for low latitude deforestation (Middle). Air surface temperature anomalies at 2100 for the 100% low latitude deforestation simulation (Bottom). All anomalies are shown in K.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153357.g010" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The globally averaged time series of soil temperature response to deforestation exhibit a pattern similar to that of the global SAT but anomalies remain positive (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g011" href="#pone.0153357.g011">Fig 11</a>). The pattern of local soil temperature response over deforested bins is similar to the global response for the 5%-45% simulations. The 75% and 100% scenarios, similarly to what is observed at mid latitudes, show positive anomalies that decrease during to 21
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">st</span>
  </span> century resulting in soil temperatures that are still higher than the control but lower than those observed in the 15%-45% simulations.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153357.g011" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153357.g011</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 11</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Annually averaged global soil temperature anomalies for low latitude deforestation (Top). Annually averaged soil temperature anomalies over deforested areas for low latitude deforestation (Middle). Soil temperature anomalies at 2100 for the 100% low latitude deforestation simulation (Bottom). All anomalies are shown in K.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153357.g011" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global moisture response over land over the low latitudes is less consistent between simulations than that of the high and mid latitude simulations, with most deforestation fractions changing between drier and wetter conditions during the experiment (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g012" href="#pone.0153357.g012">Fig 12</a>). In all experiments, conditions become drier over deforested bins and the P-E anomalies over these areas are an order of magnitude larger than those registered in the global response (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g012" href="#pone.0153357.g012">Fig 12</a>). Both ET and precipitation increase over deforested bins and drying occurs because the increase in ET overtakes the increase in precipitation. It is interesting to note that the local drying is usually more intense in the mid latitudes than in the low latitude simulations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g012" href="#pone.0153357.g012">Fig 12</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153357.g012" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153357.g012</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 12</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Annually averaged global precipitation minus evapotranspiration (ET) anomalies over land for low latitude deforestation (Top). Annually averaged precipitation minus ET anomalies over deforested areas for low latitude deforestation (Middle). Precipitation minus ET anomalies at 2100 for the 100% low latitude deforestation simulation (Bottom). All anomalies are shown in kg m
    <span class="sup">−2</span> s
    <span class="sup">−1</span>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153357.g012" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the mean local response is drying, some areas in equatorial Africa and the Amazon become wetter after deforestation. Our simulations indicate that contrary to the areas that become wetter in the mid latitudes simulations, the positive P-E anomalies in the low latitude deforested bins are caused by an increase in precipitation and not decreased ET.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared to the mid latitudes, where the wetter conditions occur in areas of mixed warming and cooling soil temperatures, low latitude bins with positive P-E show no significant variation in soil temperature (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g011" href="#pone.0153357.g011">Fig 11</a>). From 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g012" href="#pone.0153357.g012">Fig 12</a> (bottom) it can be seen that there is an increase in P-E outside the deforested areas. This increase is not exclusive to the 100% deforestation shown, being seen in all scenarios. It is this increase in moisture in non-deforested areas, as well as the less pronounced decrease in moisture in the deforested areas for the 5%-45% simulations, that leads to an average global increase of moisture over land at various times in the simulations for the 15%-45% scenarios.
 </p>
</sec>
