<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.2 Mid Latitudes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all scenarios, deforestation produces a rapid increase in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> (2 to 47 ppmv) as the carbon lost by vegetation due to deforestation makes its way into the atmosphere (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g013" href="#pone.0153357.g013">13</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g014" href="#pone.0153357.g014">14</a>). This is followed again, in all scenarios, by a decrease in CO
  <sub>2</sub> values. After this initial pulse, the behaviour of the simulations differs. The 5%-25% scenarios show increases relative to the initial post pulse value up to year 2100. CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations remain near the post-pulse value for 45% experiment while the 75% and 100% scenarios, in similar fashion to the high latitude case, exhibit continuos reductions in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> after the initial peak. Contrary to the high latitudes simulations these reductions in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> are not large enough to generate negative anomalies by the end of the century.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All simulations experience a global increase in soil carbon that offsets a portion of the losses in land carbon caused by deforestation and dieback. Following a brief (about four years) initial decrease in soil carbon, all experiments show a relatively rapid increase of carbon in this pool up to about 2040 to 2060. The magnitude of the increase is dependent on the deforestation fraction and in all experiments this is accompanied by a reduction in atmospheric carbon (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g014" href="#pone.0153357.g014">Fig 14</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all experiments, both forested and non-forested bins contribute to the initial increase in soil carbon. Due to changes in climate and enhanced NPP caused by increased atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref047">47</a>], non-deforested bins maintain positive soil carbon anomalies over the duration of all experiments. As simulations progress, some scenarios experience eventual reductions in soil carbon, associated with loss of carbon in deforested bins. These losses are larger for the 15%-25% scenarios, (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g014" href="#pone.0153357.g014">Fig 14</a>) and are associated with increased respiration, due to warmer soil temperatures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g008" href="#pone.0153357.g008">Fig 8</a>) and wetter conditions over their deforested bins when compared to those of the other scenarios (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g006" href="#pone.0153357.g006">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g009" href="#pone.0153357.g009">9</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g012" href="#pone.0153357.g012">12</a>). The increase in NPP, as well as the enhanced drying and cooler temperatures over the deforested bins of the 75% and 100% experiments causes these areas to gain soil carbon continuously during the experiments. The large increase of soil carbon in the higher deforestation fraction experiments leads to the larger atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> drawdown seen in these scenarios.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean carbon stocks are responding to atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g014" href="#pone.0153357.g014">Fig 14</a>) as ocean carbon increases and decreases with the fluctuating CO
  <sub>2</sub> values.
 </p>
</sec>
