<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1 Model Description</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The University of Victoria Earth System Climate Model (UVic ESCM) version 2.9 is an intermediate complexity climate model with horizontal resolution of 1.8° (meridional) 
  <span class="italic">X</span> 3.6° (zonal). It is composed of a vertically integrated energy-moisture balance atmospheric model, a dynamic-thermodynamic sea-ice model, a continental ice dynamics model, and version 2.2 of the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (GFDL) Modular Ocean Model (MOM2). The MOM2 is a general circulation ocean model with 19 vertical layers. The terrestrial carbon model is a modified version of the MOSES2 land surface model and the TRIFFID dynamic vegetation model [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref032">32</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref033">33</a>]. Ocean inorganic carbon is based on the OCMIP abiotic protocol. Ocean biology is simulated by an ecosystem model of nitrogen cycling [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref034">34</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref035">35</a>]. Water, heat and carbon are conserved between model components with no flux adjustments. Cloud cover is set at a constant in the UVic ESCM. It has been shown that that large-scale deforestation may influence cloud cover and have an effect on the climate [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref012">12</a>], however uncertainties exist in the change of cloud cover due to deforestation [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref029">29</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref036">36</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref037">37</a>]. Precipitation is a function of relative humidity and not influenced by the fixed cloud cover. A full description of the atmospheric, oceanic, and sea ice models are in [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref038">38</a>], while the land surface scheme and dynamic vegetation model are described in [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref032">32</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref033">33</a>].
 </p>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.1 Vegetation Model and Land Surface Scheme</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TRIFFID defines the state of the terrestrial biosphere in terms of soil carbon, and the structure and coverage of five plant functional types (PFT), broadleaf trees, needleleaf trees, C
   <sub>3</sub> grasses, C
   <sub>4</sub> grasses and shrubs within each grid cell [
   <a rid="pone.0153357.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref032">32</a>]. Using a carbon balance approach, TRIFFID determines the change in areal coverage, leaf area index and canopy height, as a result of net carbon fluxes calculated by the MOSES 2 land surface scheme. MOSES 2 recognizes the five PFTs used by TRIFFID, plus four non-vegetation types, bare soil, urban areas, land ice and inland water. Based on a photosynthesis-stomatal conductance model, plant respiration and photosynthesis are dependent upon climate and atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> [
   <a rid="pone.0153357.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref039">39</a>]. Through this, the response of vegetation to climate occurs via climate-induced changes in the vegetation to atmospheric fluxes of carbon [
   <a rid="pone.0153357.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref032">32</a>]. In each 1.8°
   <span class="italic">X</span> 3.6° grid cell, changes to land coverage through time is determined by a dynamic competition between the different PFTs. This is based on the Lotka-Volterra approach and a tree-shrub-grass dominance hierarchy. TRIFFID also allows agricultural areas to exist. These areas are defined as croplands and are treated as grass PFTs for determining their biogeochemical and biophysical behaviors.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the non-linear character of the Lotka-Volterra equations used for the competition algorithm, there exists a possibility for rapid loss of vegetation species if the land-use disturbance is large enough to trigger the requisite scenario. This scenario can produce rapid increases or decreases in the abundance of a species [
   <a rid="pone.0153357.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref040">40</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil carbon pools are increased through litterfall, and reduced by heterotrophic respiration Litterfall is calculated as an area weighted sum from each PFT, and is dependent upon the degree of the land disturbance and competition between PFTs. Respiration is determined by the soil carbon content, a q
   <sub>10</sub> soil temperature equation, and a piecewise linear soil moisture function [
   <a rid="pone.0153357.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref032">32</a>]. In general terms this means that higher NPP results in an increase in the rate with which carbon is added to the soil with higher soil temperatures and moisture resulting in increases in respiration and hence in the rate of soil carbon decrease. Soil temperature, moisture and carbon content represent values from the model’s single one meter deep layer.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
