<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2 Experiments</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all experiments, the model is integrated from equilibrium at year 1800 to year 2000 forced by historical CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions from combustion of fossil fuels and land-use change [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref041">41</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref042">42</a>]. For the period between 2001 and 2100 simulations are forced by CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions from the IPCC A2 scenario [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref031">31</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deforestation experiments cover the period between 2010 and 2100. Deforestation is simulated separately in three bands: the area northward of 40°N (high latitudes), the areas between 20°N to 40°N, and 20°S to 40°S (mid latitudes) and the area between 20°S to 20°N (low latitudes) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g001" href="#pone.0153357.g001">Fig 1</a>). While the adoption of latitudinal bands is our best attempt to represent impacts of deforestation on different environments, it must be noted that, as TRIFFID only contains five PFTS, the type of vegetation cover present in each latitude band is a very simple and incomplete representations of existing biomes, which are not only more complex but also distributed over the landscape space in complex patterns dictated by many other factors in addition to latitude.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153357.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153357.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">2010 Forest Coverage.</div>
   <p>Coverage is represented as fractional amount of broadleaf and needleleaf trees in each grid cell. Latitude bands designated by black lines. 40°N and above for the high latitudes, 20-40°N and 20-40°S for the mid latitudes and 20°S to 20°N for the low latitudes.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153357.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the start of 2010, all experiments have the same crop area distribution based on [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref002">2</a>]. The vegetation is specified by a land cover data set [
  <a rid="pone.0153357.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153357.ref043">43</a>]. All results are compared to a control run where the crop area fraction remained fixed at the 2010 distribution. In the deforestation experiments crop area fraction is increased by different amounts in order to generate arbitrary deforestation ranging from 5% to 100% of the total forested area of the three different latitudes at 2010. The land cover change is performed in a single step at the start of 2011 by substituting trees with crops.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all but the 100% deforestation scenario only grid cells that contain both crops and forests are defined as eligible for deforestation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g002" href="#pone.0153357.g002">Fig 2</a>). In these simulations deforestation is performed by reducing the forest cover by a fixed amount in all eligible grid cells. The rationale is that experiments should simulate, as well as the coarse spatial scale of the model allows, land cover change resulting from an expansion in agricultural areas. In the 100% scenario, any grid cell with forests was deemed eligible for deforestation. There is no 75% deforestation simulation for the high latitudes, as the requirements for deforestation did not allow sufficient grid cells to be used to reach the required forest loss.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153357.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153357.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Grid cells eligible for deforestation in the high (top row), mid (middle row) and low latitudes (bottom row) in the non 100% simulations (left column) and 100% simulations (right column).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153357.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The expansion of croplands in the model follows a hierarchy where grasslands are converted to crops, before shrubs and trees. The result is that eligible grid cells that contain grasslands and shrubs prior to deforestation have these fractions converted to crops as well at the start of 2011. It should be noted that in TRIFFID crops and grasslands have identical biogeochemical and biogeophysical characteristics. The only difference is that grasslands can be outcompeted by other plant functional types while the crop distribution is prescribed. This means that all areas converted to crops in 2011 remain as such until the end of the experiments.</p>
</sec>
