<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As our compilation is dominated by low- to mid-latitude SST data, we test whether the scaling of SSTs in our compilation is representative of the climate system by comparing our data with the timespan-dependant scaling of more than 1.6 million temperature changes in an ensemble of 27 single-site multiproxy SST records spanning the past ∼13 Myr (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>; see Methods and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). We find a broad match between the two data sets, with maximum magnitudes of SST change in our compilation tracking the maxima attained in the ensembled empirical records, particularly between 10
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> and ∼10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> years (the extreme magnitudes of the Permian–Triassic boundary event notwithstanding, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). Between timespans of 10
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> and ∼10
 <sup class="sup">4</sup> years, maximum SST magnitudes in our compilation follow closely the scaling of maximum magnitudes in the ensembled SST records (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>), with 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>∼0.16, implying a 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic> of 1.32. This estimate is close to the known average spectral scaling exponent of the climatic continuum inferred from low latitude SST records over the same timespan range (1.29, ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>). For comparison, the maximum magnitudes of atmospheric temperature changes from polar latitudes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref> (not included in our compilation) have higher values, and exhibit distinct scaling patterns (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>, see also ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>). Within our compilation, data are from latitudes &lt;66°, and the correlation between SST magnitude and latitude/palaeolatitude is not significant (
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic>=0.14, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> value=0.11, see also 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 1a</xref>). The scaling is thus not influenced by known latitudinal controls on climate energy distribution
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>.
</p>
