<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation to stressful conditions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The abundant genetic variation of many natural populations explains why they can often respond rapidly to changed conditions of growth. Field studies collated by 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">Endler (1986)</a> reported average selection coefficients of 0.33 for undisturbed environments and 0.30 for situations involving recent anthropogenic disturbance. The modal selection coefficient calculated from more recent selection gradient studies collated by 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">Hoekstra et al. (2001)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">Kingsolver et al. (2001)</a> is between 0.15 and 0.35. These values may be inflated by reporting bias, but 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">Hendry and Kinnison (1999)</a> and 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b75" href="#b75">Reznick and Ghalambor (2001)</a> have emphasized that populations can often adapt successfully to abrupt environmental degradation. In the laboratory, artificial selection of a quantitative character over 30–50 generations can readily shift the population mean by 10 σ
  <sub>P</sub> or more (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">Hill and Bünger 2004</a>), and the response increases with population size (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" href="#b97">Weber 2004</a>). Moreover, many instances of evolutionary rescue have been reported, especially the evolution of antibiotic resistance in microbes, pesticide resistance in insects, and herbicide resistance in plants (see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b69" href="#b69">Palumbi 2001</a>). This gives some reason to hope that many organisms will be able to adapt successfully to the relatively mild stresses imposed by global change (see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">Frankham and Kingsolver 2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of these example, however, involve rather mild stresses, very large populations of individuals or meristems, or experimental situations in which the propagation of the line is assured. When severe stress is encountered, one route to evolutionary rescue is the high mutation supply rate provided by a large population. As a crude rule of thumb, intended to be no more than a stimulus for more exact analyses, a substantial probability of adaptation may require at least one rescue mutation per generation, independently of the severity of the stress. Although we do not yet have good estimates of this rate, some unintentional natural experiments suggest that it may often be very low. Elm and chestnut trees have failed to evolve substantial resistance to introduced fungal pathogens, despite populations of billions of trees. Vultures in India have failed to adapt to diclofenac, and will surely become extinct unless conservation efforts are successful, despite an initial population size of 2–3 × 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> individuals (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">Green et al. 2004</a>). In the first systematic discussion of adaptation to global change, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">Bradshaw and McNeilly (1991)</a> were skeptical that selection will often succeed in rescuing stressed populations from extinction. They drew on their extensive experience with heavy-metal tolerance in plants to point out that tolerance readily evolves in a minority of species, but seldom, if ever, in most. Hundreds of species grow next to stressful environments such as salt marshes or serpentine soils without ever becoming adapted to them. Changing climates often cause shifts in plant distribution, such that species remain within the same range of conditions, with little evidence for adaptation 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span>. The sporadic occurrence of adaptation to particular kinds of stressful conditions suggests that it may often depend on idiosyncratic properties of particular species, which either preadapt them to survive or make it more likely that adaptation will often occur. Any given stress would then sort the existing community and lead to the emergence of a less diverse group of the luckiest species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even very large population size is not necessarily an effective prophylactic against extinction. For example, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">Kwiatkowski and Roff (1976)</a> reported high rates of extinction among the phytoplankton of a group of acidified oligotrophic lakes on the northern shore of Lake Huron. A nonacidified lake with low concentrations of heavy metals supported 55 species of eukaryotic algae. Only 34 species remained in Carlyle Lake, which had a mean pH of about 5 and elevated levels of heavy metals. It had a chlorophyll a concentration of about 1 μg L
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, equivalent to 50 μg L
  <span class="sup">−1</span> of algae, or about 5 × 10
  <span class="sup">4</span> cells L
  <span class="sup">−1</span> of algae the size of 
  <span class="italic">Chlamydomonas</span>. This amounts to a whole-lake population of 2.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">11</span> cells, or roughly 10
  <span class="sup">10</span> cells per species on average. The time period of acidification is not known, but is unlikely to have been &lt;20 years, so the total number of cells exposed to mutation is likely to have been at least 10
  <span class="sup">12</span> on average per species. Nevertheless, about one-third of species became extinct. A more severely affected lake nearby, with pH 4–4.6 had only 12 species remaining. Baby Lake, close to a big nickel smelter at Sudbury, was almost devoid of eukaryotic life in 1972 except for a sparse population of 
  <span class="italic">Chlorella</span>. This was attributable to its pH of 4 and very high heavy metal concentrations (Ni 3.2 ppm, Cu 0.7 ppm), and when isolates of 
  <span class="italic">Chlorella</span> from the lake were tested in laboratory media they were found to have evolved tolerance to high levels of Ni and Cu (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b89" href="#b89">Stokes et al. 1973</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Scenedesmus</span> from a nearby lake was likewise tolerant of high levels of Cu. Hence, microbes can become adapted even to very stressful conditions, but even microbes are likely to become extinct as stress becomes more severe, until only the most abundant (or the luckiest) survive.
 </p>
</sec>
