<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolutionary rescue</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The outlook is much less benign, however, if lower mean fitness leads to a reduction in population size and thereby in the mutation supply rate. This will happen if environmental deterioration causes the growth rate of the current wild type to become negative, 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub> &lt; 0, so that population size begins to decline from its initial carrying capacity of 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>0</sub> individuals. This tendency is opposed by rescue mutations, all with growth rate 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>1</sub> &gt; 0, which comprise a fraction Φ of the overall genomic mutation rate 
  <span class="italic">U</span>. The number of new rescue mutations appearing before the population becomes extinct depends on the total number of individuals that live during its period of decline, which will be −
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>0</sub>/
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub>. The probability that a new rescue mutation will spread is about 2(
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>1</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub>). Hence, the expected number of fixed rescue mutations is 
  <span class="italic">B</span> = 2
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>0</sub>
  <span class="italic">U</span>Φ(
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>1</sub>)/
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub>, and the Poisson probability that at least one will spread is 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 1 − exp(−
  <span class="italic">B</span>). Evolutionary rescue therefore requires that the frequency of rescue mutations is sufficiently high, Φ &gt; −[
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub>/(
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>1</sub>)][ln (1–
  <span class="italic">P</span>)]/(2
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>0</sub>
  <span class="italic">U</span>). For example, to attain 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 1/2 in a small population (
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>0</sub> = 1000) with genomic mutation rate 
  <span class="italic">U</span> = 1, moderately rapid decline (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub> = −0.1) and moderately strong selection (r
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.1) requires Φ &gt; 0.0002 approximately.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolutionary rescue in an extreme-value model is illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>. A single severe depression of fitness (
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub> = −0.5) is countered by an extreme-value series of beneficial mutations of which the top three are rescue alleles with 
  <span class="italic">r</span> &gt; 0. The initial decline of the population is buffered by the increase in frequency of alleles with growth 
  <span class="italic">r</span>
  <sub>0</sub> &lt; 
  <span class="italic">r</span> &lt; 0, but this effect is slight. The third-ranking allele appears at about generation 10 and rapidly spreads, rescuing the population. When it has nearly reached fixation the population is invaded first by the second-ranking and shortly afterwards by the top allele, which contribute to adaptation but were not responsible for rescue. Once the population has become abundant, a shifting spectrum of low-frequency mutations appears as mutation-selection balance is restored. The diagram shows a successful rescue; in most replicate simulations the population swiftly collapses.
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Dynamics of evolutionary rescue. The population has 
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>0</sub> = 1000, 
    <span class="italic">U</span> = 1, Δ
    <sub>1</sub> = 0.25 and 
    <span class="italic">r</span>
    <sub>0</sub>
    <sub>=</sub> −0.5. The lines show the flux in frequency of a fixed series of 20 alleles, of which the top three have 
    <span class="italic">r</span> &gt; 0. The diamonds are overall population size.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0001-0003-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The probability that a population will adapt to an abrupt stress depends on the severity of the stress and on the supply of beneficial mutations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a>). The two are linked, because for a given value of Δ
  <sub>1</sub> rescue mutations will be more frequent when the stress is less severe. These simulations suggest that there will be a substantial probability of adaptation (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.2 or so) only if the number of rescue mutants appearing exceeds one per generation. This condition might be difficult to meet, especially for small populations.
 </p>
 <div id="fig04" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The probability of evolutionary rescue in relation to the severity of environmental deterioration and the mutation supply rate. Output of extreme-value model with 20 alleles, Δ
    <sub>1</sub> = 0.25, 
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>0</sub> = 1000; plotted points each based on 100 simulations.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0001-0003-f4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
