<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative variation in sexual populations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These ideas stem from thinking about microbial populations, which are typically large, asexual and highly resistant to extinction. Small sexual populations where the response to selection depends on standing genetic variance are more directly related to conservation issues. Suppose that viability in such a population with λ = 
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <span class="sup">r</span> &gt; 1 is governed by some quantitative character with phenotypic variance 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="eva0001-0003-mu1.jpg" mimetype="image" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> subject to stabilizing selection under a Gaussian fitness function with width ω
  <span class="sup">2</span>. The population mean phenotype is close to its current optimum, but this optimal value now begins to change over time at a rate 
  <span class="italic">k</span> per generation. This induces a response to selection 
  <span class="italic">R</span> that shifts the population mean closer to the new optimum. Consequently, the population shadows the moving optimum, changing at a corresponding rate 
  <span class="italic">k</span> per generation but lagging behind the current optimum by a quantity 
  <span class="italic">k</span>/
  <span class="italic">R</span> (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">Charlesworth 1993</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">Lynch and Lande 1993</a>). The disparity between the population mean and the optimum reduces λ, however, and if the rate of environmental change exceeds some critical value 
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>crit</sub> then λ &lt; 1 and the population will decline in abundance and eventually become extinct. Provided that the environment changes rather smoothly, with little stochastic variation around its expected value, this critical value is given approximately by 
  <span class="italic">k</span>
  <sub>crit</sub> ≍ 
  <span class="italic">R</span> (2 V
  <sub>λ</sub> ln λ*)
  <span class="sup">0.5</span>, where 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="eva0001-0003-mu2.jpg" mimetype="image" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> and λ* is the maximal rate of increase attained when the population mean phenotype matches the optimal value (cf equation 10 of 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">Burger and Lynch 1995</a>). Hence, the population is most likely to escape extinction through adaptation if genetic variance is large (
  <span class="italic">R</span> and 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="eva0001-0003-mu3.jpg" mimetype="image" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> large), selection is weak (ω
  <span class="sup">2</span> and 
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>λ</sub> large), and fecundity is high (λ* large). 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">Gomulkiewicz and Holt (1995)</a> present a similar analysis in which environmental change reduces the population rate of increase below replacement level. This will eventually be restored by selection, but the population is likely to become extinct through demographic stochasticity if it remains rare for too long. The analytical theory does not yet handle the evolution of the genetic variance over time, but simulations show that large population size, high fecundity and an abundant supply of genetic variation through mutation facilitate escape from extinction by adaptation (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">Holt and Gomulkiewicz 2004</a>). Although the microbial and quantitative-genetic models are constructed in very different ways they give broadly concordant results, and hold out the hope that a general theory of adaptation in relation to extinction can be constructed. This would also imply that microbial models can be used to calibrate and test theories of evolutionary rescue. No such experiments have yet been reported, although we expect that they will become an important item on the agenda of evolutionary biology in the first decade of 
  <span class="italic">Evolutionary Applications</span>. All we can do is to put forward some guesses to be tested by experience.
 </p>
</sec>
