<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rescue from extinction by adaptation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most individuals are sufficiently versatile to accommodate the mundane level of variability experienced within a lifetime. Offspring will encounter conditions different from their parents but will adjust to them through phenotypic plasticity. The perpetual increase of environmental variance, however, may eventually lead to a change in conditions too great for individuals to survive or reproduce successfully, so that the population begins to decline. Lineages can still persist by migrating or dispersing to new sites. If neither plasticity nor dispersal will serve, however, they must either adapt or die out. Natural selection may succeed in restoring adaptedness if types capable of growing in the new conditions exist in the population or arise before it becomes extinct. It is most likely to do so when the change is modest and the amount of genetic variance (or the mutation supply rate) is high. Although this notion dates back at least to the ‘lag load’ of 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b87" href="#b87">Stenseth and Maynard Smith (1984)</a> it seems not to have been explored very thoroughly (but see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">Martin and Lenormand 2006</a>, whose parameter 
  <span class="italic">s</span>
  <sub>o</sub> is a lag load), with the exceptions that we discuss below. Although selection lines in the laboratory sometimes die out through excessive stress or high levels of inbreeding, this is normally regarded as a nuisance, and we are unaware of any experimental literature demonstrating the conditions in which evolutionary rescue does and does not occur. The closest approach to experimental evidence was described by 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">Bradshaw (1991)</a>, who pointed out that some species of plant consistently adapt to heavy metal pollution whereas others do not, and attributed the failures to ‘genostasis’, the chronic and insuperable lack of appropriate genetic variation.
 </p>
</sec>
