<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> on community composition
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There have been several attempts to investigate how high CO
  <sub>2</sub> levels may affect community composition. Some studies have tested the hypothesis that an important response to CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment will be species succession, based on competition between two or more species with different resource requirements (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">Burkhardt et al. 2001</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b77" href="#b77">Rost et al. 2003</a>). The findings from short-term enrichment studies on natural phytoplankton assemblages have been equivocal, depending on the initial assemblage used and the duration of the study (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b91" href="#b91">Tortell et al. 2000</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b92" href="#b92">2002</a>). While there is still debate about whether phytoplankton will respond to CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment by increasing growth or photosynthesis rates, phytoplankton usually have some other response to elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, such as changes in calcification, nitrogen use, or the productions of extracellular polymers (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">Beardall et al. 1998</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">Clark and Flynn 2000</a>). Here, microcosm studies can be used to ask how increasing CO
  <sub>2</sub> may change more complex community dynamics. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">Shikano and Kawabata (2000)</a> investigated the effect of elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> and nutrient levels on a model community made up of 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> (bacteria), 
  <span class="italic">Tetrahymena thermophila</span> (ciliate) and 
  <span class="italic">Euglena gracilis</span> (green flagellate). This work showed differences in community composition that were both directly and indirectly attributable to elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>. The main effect of CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment in this system was an increase in algal biomass. This was correlated with several indirect effects, most notably a reduction in bacterial biomass, which is the opposite effect from CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment in pure cultures of 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>. Interestingly, the indirect effects of CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment were not observed to the same extent, or even in the same direction, if concentrations of other nutrients were not also increased. This shows how elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> and nutrient levels may affect dynamics in a specific community.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent studies in experimental evolution have begun to address the effects of ecological processes on evolutionary outcomes. For example, natural enemies retarded the diversification of microbial systems whose diversity was high in the absence of the enemy by reducing population size (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b66" href="#b66">Morgan and Buckling 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b65" href="#b65">Meyer and Kassen 2007</a>). However, the opposite effect occurred in cases where diversity was low in the absence of an enemy (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">Gallet et al. 2007</a>). These sorts of studies can help to establish general principles that will help to reconcile the apparent contradictions between studies documenting community-level responses to environmental change, including elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
</sec>
