<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oceanic carbon sink</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the potential for adaptation to atmospheric change is an interesting issue, and one that will surely be used as a model system to make advances in general theory, the main reason for our interest in phytoplankton responses to elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> is pragmatic: there is a potential carbon sink in the ocean, and we would like to be able to make predictions about it. About one-half of all photosynthetic carbon fixation on the planet occurs in oceans (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">Falkowski 1994</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">Beardall and Raven 2004</a>). Phytoplankton have the potential to absorb a portion of anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> as fixed organic carbon and trap it in deep ocean sediments (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" href="#b79">Sarmiento and Toggweiler 1984</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b73" href="#b73">Raven and Falkowski 1999</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">Schippers et al. 2004</a>), although debate exists over the size of such a sink. The biological carbon sink has generated interest in terms of its possible role in slowing global CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment, and has given rise to large-scale experiments designed to increase phytoplankton blooms and subsequent C sinking by adding iron dust to sections of ocean (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">Boyd et al. 2000</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">Buesseler et al. 2004</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">Coale et al. 2004</a>). Although some increase in phytoplankton biomass has been observed, it has been difficult to assess how much carbon was exported to deeper waters, and in the two cases where carbon export was reported, it was modest compared with expected levels (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">de Baar et al. 2005</a>). Experiments like this show continued interest in the idea that phytoplankton may have the potential to help manage global CO
  <sub>2</sub> enrichment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental evolution will enable us to make predictions about the carbon cycle that have clear ecological and economic value. To study a simple version of this in terms of the biological carbon pump, we need two pieces of information: which species will be present, and how much carbon will they sink? In other words, what will be the future composition of phytoplankton communities, and will descendents of individual species (or functional groups) continue to take up carbon at the same rate as contemporary taxa?</p>
</sec>
