<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variable and fluctuating selection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental variability will cause the strength and direction of selection to change over time. Studies of natural populations have shown that selection is often strong (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">Hereford et al. 2004</a>) and that heritability is often high (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b67" href="#b67">Mousseau and Roff 1987</a>). One explanation of these apparently contradictory generalizations is that selection often changes direction, because offspring grow up in a different place and at a different time from their parents. The variability of selection among isozyme genotypes in 
  <span class="italic">Daphnia</span> populations was documented by 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b58" href="#b58">Lynch (1987)</a>, who found that the standard deviation of the selection coefficient over time was at least 0.1. There are many detailed case studies of selection that varies widely in time (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">Grant and Grant 2002</a>) or space (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" href="#b86">Snaydon and Davies 1982</a>), even in within a few square metres of natural environment (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b88" href="#b88">Stewart and Schoen 1987</a>). Hence, populations might often be rather imprecisely adapted to local conditions of growth. This can be evaluated by measuring the selection gradient (partial regression of fitness on character state) and calculating the distance between the optimal phenotype and the population mean, in units of phenotypic standard deviations. For the studies of stabilizing selection collated by 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">Kingsolver et al. (2001)</a> this distance is exponentially distributed with mean 3.9; that is, the population was further than one phenotypic standard deviation from the optimum in about one-half of all cases, and further than 2 SD in one-third. It can also be evaluated by reciprocal transplant experiments. Where these involve clearly distinct ecotypes or species they usually show that residents are markedly superior to incomers (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b81" href="#b81">Schluter 2000</a>; Table 5.1). When morphologically undifferentiated populations are transplanted, however, there is little tendency for residents to be superior except at very large distances or between clearly distinct habitats (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">Bell 2008</a>, Table 5). These facts are consistent with the view that conditions often vary widely in time and space, generating strong but fluctuating selection.
 </p>
</sec>
