<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Health adaptation to climate change in Canada varies significantly by jurisdiction. Federal adaptation initiatives are primarily groundwork initiatives emphasizing capacity building and generating and sharing knowledge to support sub-national adaptation. This approach is congruent with the strategy outlined in Canada’s Federal Adaptation Policy Framework [
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-12-00623" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-12-00623">17</a>] and with Canada’s constitution which devolves responsibility for health and environment to the provinces and territories [
  <a rid="B78-ijerph-12-00623" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78-ijerph-12-00623">78</a>]. Sub-national adaptation focuses progressively less (between provincial/territorial and local adaptation) on information and capacity building initiatives, and progressively more on warning or observing systems and initiatives changing practice and behavior. Management, planning and policy is most heavily emphasized at the provincial and territorial jurisdiction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The level of health adaptation also varies strongly within levels of jurisdiction. The province of Quebec reports online more than five times as many health adaptation initiatives as the next province or territory, addresses to some degree almost all identified health risks in the province and has a comprehensive adaptation plan. Meanwhile, the rest of Canada’s provinces and territories are still in the early stages of adaptation, based on publically available information. Similarly, the cities of Toronto and Vancouver both show commitment to adaptation and a long-term vision, while Canada’s next four largest municipalities report little to no evidence of health adaptation. Though not explored in this study, rural Canadian communities will face challenges distinct from those of their urban counterparts, including adaptive capacity, risk perception, and dependence on natural resources [
  <a rid="B102-ijerph-12-00623" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102-ijerph-12-00623">102</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in health adaptation between provinces and territories and between municipalities is inconsistent with risks posed to varying jurisdictions. Recent extreme events such as the Alberta floods in 2013, for instance, which caused the evacuation of over 100,000 people, demonstrate the magnitude of risks facing provinces and municipalities. The Alberta provincial government, Calgary and other municipal governments have been criticized for a lack of preparation and planning for climatic extremes [
  <a rid="B103-ijerph-12-00623" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103-ijerph-12-00623">103</a>,
  <a rid="B104-ijerph-12-00623" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104-ijerph-12-00623">104</a>]. Unaddressed, these jurisdictional differences may contribute to regional differences in the health impacts of climate change on populations. Federal guidance to assist such provinces and territories is important in this context.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Canada has the capacity to adapt, with the necessary wealth, technology, institutions, social organizations and skills. However, as Burton [
  <a rid="B105-ijerph-12-00623" ref-type="bibr" href="#B105-ijerph-12-00623">105</a>] notes in his concluding chapter to the Canadian National Assessment on climate change impacts and adaptation a spontaneous or 
  <span class="italic">laissez faire</span> approach is unlikely to be sufficient for Canadian adaptation to the impacts of climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
