<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although our simulations attempt to integrate habitat and demographic information, we did not present landscape-based population viability models (
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]), mostly because the detailed and critical demographic information needed in such models (i.e., survival rates and dispersion/colonization rates per habitat types) are not available for BBWO–a problem typical for most boreal bird species. For instance, we did not take into account climatically-driven physiological, behavioural or phenological processes that may modify species’ life history traits and vital rates [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref099" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>]. In this context, changes in habitat could only provide, as a proxy, a partial assessment of the potential changes in BBWO vital rates through changes in specific resources related to these habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Likewise, we did not take into account demographic processes such as density dependence, local abundance, productivity, and dispersal, or complex interactions among birds and their prey, that could further help determine the future abundance of BBWO in conjunction with habitat projections. It is currently unknown how the insectivorous BBWO will be affected by potential climate-induced disruptions to the distribution of its prey species. As ectotherms, it is considered that insects will respond rapidly to shifts in climate conditions (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>]), although some species may be subject to resource/habitat constraints (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>]). Furthermore, bird species may exhibit adaptation to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>], although species’ plasticity has been little studied in birds [
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191645.ref104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>].
</p>
