<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34876-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PREDICTED WOODPECKER RESPONSES TO CLIMATE CHANGE</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, geographic forecasts indicate a north–northeast shift of eastern U.S. avifauna species by 2100 (Matthews, Iverson, Prasad, &amp; Peters, 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0068">2011</a>) and a concurrent change in community composition (Langham, Schuetz, Distler, Soykan, &amp; Wilsey, 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>; Stralberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0104">2009</a>). By 2080, breeding bird assemblages of northern Canada and Alaska may gain as many as 80 species, while the greatest species loss is predicted along the Canadian–U.S. border and through the Rocky Mountains (Langham et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>). Model results show that the resulting dissimilarity to contemporary species composition will be greatest throughout Canada and the Rockies. These trends will downscale to regional extents; for example, upwards of 57% of California may have novel breeding bird species assemblages by 2070 with no current analogs (Stralberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0104">2009</a>). In addition, central and southern California are areas of peak losses of species in the nonbreeding season (Langham et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the models reviewed, the model of Langham et al. (
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>) is the most comprehensive in relation to the greatest number of species and spatial extents modeled. The authors predict distributional changes to 2100 and compare these to species distributions in 2000 using bioclimatic modeling under a range of climate change scenarios for North American avifauna, including 20 North American woodpecker species. They used 13 combinations of emissions scenarios and general circulation models over three time periods to produce 39 different climate futures. All woodpeckers’ contemporary breeding and winter geographic ranges are predicted to contract due to climate change (Figures 
  <a rid="ece34876-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34876-fig-0001">1</a> and 
  <a rid="ece34876-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34876-fig-0002">2</a>), and 13 of the 20 woodpecker species evaluated are predicted to be climate endangered or threatened due to loss of breeding and/or wintering range by the end of the century (Supporting information Table 
  <a rid="ece34876-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece34876-sup-0003">S1</a>). Some of the range losses will be mitigated by climatically suitable range expansions. This results in an overall 53% and 23% of the woodpecker species breeding and nonbreeding ranges to exhibit net contractions by 2080, respectively (Figures 
  <a rid="ece34876-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34876-fig-0001">1</a> and 
  <a rid="ece34876-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34876-fig-0002">2</a>). Overall, all woodpecker species will lose climatically suitable habitat by the end of the century, and even with net gains, a majority are labeled as climate threatened or endangered based on climatic range changes (Supporting information Table 
  <a rid="ece34876-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece34876-sup-0003">S1</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34876-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The mean proportion of North American contemporary woodpecker breeding range retained by the end of the century based on the ensemble global climate model emissions scenarios (B2, A1B, and A2: listed from low to high emissions). The overall proportional change of the breeding range by 2080 compared to 2000 based on the high emissions climate model scenario (A2) and emissions scenario ensemble means (B2, A1B, and A2). Values &lt;1 represent a decline. Data from Langham et al. (
    <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-2305-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34876-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The mean proportion of North American contemporary woodpecker nonbreeding range retained by the end of the century based on the ensemble global climate model emissions scenarios (B2, A1B, and A2: listed from low to high emissions). The overall proportional change of the wintering range by 2080 compared to 2000 based on the high emissions climate model scenario (A2) and emissions scenario ensemble means (B2, A1B, and A2). Values &lt;1 represent a decline. Data from Langham et al. (
    <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-9-2305-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In comparison, a trait‐based assessment of climate change vulnerability via assessment of sensitivity, exposure, and adaptability found a mixed response among woodpeckers to those metrics. Most North American woodpecker species are sensitive to climate change. However, all are ranked as low vulnerability because of exposure (“the extent of the species’ environment that will change”) and/or high adaptive capacity (“the species’ ability to avoid the negative impacts of climate change through dispersal and/or micro‐evolutionary change”; Supporting information Table 
  <a rid="ece34876-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece34876-sup-0003">S1</a>; Foden et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0031">2013</a>). This discrepancy between the bioclimatic niche predictions (Langham et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>) and climate vulnerability assessments (trait‐based assessment; Foden et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0031">2013</a>) may be explained by the inclusion of measures of sensitivity and adaptability in the trait‐based evaluation. Though a qualitative assessment, the trait‐based vulnerability metric exposure to climate change (the quantified metric in bioclimatic niche models) is further modulated by a species’ sensitivity and adaptability to derive vulnerability. Bioclimatic niche models quantitatively assess the exposure of a species with minimal inclusion of the other measures of climate vulnerability (i.e., sensitivity and adaptability). Hence, a species may be exposed to shifts in climatically suitable habitat but may have adaptability potential via phenotypic plasticity or not be sensitive to the degree of climate change represented in the bioclimatic niche model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatially, there is an emergent pattern of predictions among woodpeckers relative to their contemporary distributions. The climatically suitable ranges of species with contemporary northern or western distribution centroids (i.e., those associated with conifer/boreal forests) are projected to contract (Langham et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>). This is in concordance with other model results of climate‐induced declines in avifauna abundance and species richness in conifer/boreal habitats of North America (Stralberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0105">2015</a>) and Europe (Virkkala, Heikkinen, Leikola, &amp; Luoto, 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0115">2008</a>). Most avian species with breeding range distributions that are associated with eastern deciduous woodlands/forests and southern mixed pine forest are predicted to be climate stable. This includes projections of the Red‐headed Woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Melanerpes erythrocephalus</span>), Red‐bellied Woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Melanerpes carolinus</span>), Downy Woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Picoides pubescens</span>), and Pileated Woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Hylatomus pileatus</span>; Langham et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0058">2015</a>; Matthews et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0068">2011</a>; Rodenhouse et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0088">2008</a>). However, species at the southern edge of their range within this region (e.g., American Three‐toed Woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Picoides dorsalis</span>) and Black‐backed Woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Picoides arcticus</span>)) may diminish because of the encroachment of hardwoods from lower elevations into their primary habitat (spruce‐fir; Rodenhouse et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0088">2008</a>). Nevertheless, coastal and southern regions of the United States are predicted to provide climates amenable to many wintering species (Schuetz et al., 
  <a rid="ece34876-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34876-bib-0099">2015</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
