<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-sensors-19-01118" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. XCO
  <sub>2</sub> Retrievals and Mapping XCO
  <sub>2</sub> Dataset
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">XCO
  <sub>2</sub> retrieval data products from January 2010 to December 2015 are collected from GOSAT Atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> Observations from Space (ACOS v7.3). This dataset was produced by the Orbiting Carbon Observatory (OCO) team of the US National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) using a full physics algorithm to retrieve XCO
  <sub>2</sub> from GOSAT’s Spectrometer (TANSO-FTS) calibrated spectra measurements (Level 1B) [
  <a rid="B19-sensors-19-01118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-sensors-19-01118">19</a>]. In order to ensure high reliability of the data, only those data over land with high gain are used after screening and correction of systematic bias as described in the ACOS Level 2 Standard Product and Lite Data Product Data User’s Guide, v7.3 [
  <a rid="B20-sensors-19-01118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-sensors-19-01118">20</a>]. ACOS XCO
  <sub>2</sub> retrievals have a standard deviation of error of 1.48 ppm when comparing with ground-based measures of Total Carbon Column Observing Network (TCCON) [
  <a rid="B21-sensors-19-01118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-sensors-19-01118">21</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-01118-f001" href="#sensors-19-01118-f001">Figure 1</a> shows the total counts of XCO
  <sub>2</sub> data points during 6 years from January 2010 to December 2015, and their temporal variation in the study area. An annual increase of XCO
  <sub>2</sub> and the seasonal variation can be clearly seen. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, XCO
  <sub>2</sub> data are irregularly distributed and have many gaps in space and time as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-01118-f001" href="#sensors-19-01118-f001">Figure 1</a>a because of the limitation of GOSAT observation mode, cloudy and data screening. To investigate the space-time changes of XCO
  <sub>2</sub>, we generate a mapping XCO
  <sub>2</sub> dataset in which those gaps are filled using the kriging interpolation method based on the spatio-temporal geo-statistics model [
  <a rid="B22-sensors-19-01118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-sensors-19-01118">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-sensors-19-01118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-sensors-19-01118">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-sensors-19-01118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-sensors-19-01118">24</a>]. The mapping XCO
  <sub>2</sub> dataset is generated mainly in Chinese mainland area from 18° N to 57° N and from 65° E to 148° E with 0.5° × 0.5° grid cells and 3-day interval in time from 1 January 2010 to 31 December 2015. In order to match with collected ODIAC emission dataset in 1° × 1°, we resampled the spatial resolution of data we used in this paper to 1° × 1°. This mapping dataset is hereafter referred to as Mapping-XCO
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
</sec>
