<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Experimental measurements have technical drawbacks. The acetylene reduction assay (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Capone, 1993</xref>), a proxy measurement of both incorporated and exuded (gross) fixed N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, measures the rate of ethylene production from added acetylene. Microbial activity repression (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fulweiler et al., 2015</xref>), low sensitivity and highly variable conversion factors for C
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>H
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>:N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wilson et al., 2012</xref>), limit the robustness of this technique. The more widely (∼75% of the measurements) applied method involves adding 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> gas to a water sample and measuring the net incorporation of 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> into plankton biomass after filtration (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Montoya et al., 1996</xref>). This method may result in significant underestimation of N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fixation rates if the added 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> gas is not equilibrated before the start of the incubation (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mohr et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wilson et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wannicke et al., 2018</xref>). The degree of underestimation is variable and dependent on the experimental conditions (incubation time, size of bottle, shaking vigor), making the correction of historical data with a constant factor arbitrary. The 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> gas stock contamination by 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> or 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub>, may result in N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fixation overestimate (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dabundo et al., 2014</xref>). Fixation rates may be underestimated if small cells (&lt;2 μm) are lost during filtration, particularly affecting rates where small diazotrophs may dominate the N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-fixing community (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bombar et al., 2018</xref>). Robust quantification of low rates is currently limited by the low sensitivity and high potential errors of present methods (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gradoville et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moisander et al., 2017</xref>). Inadequate consideration of experimental biases must be warned against. Community efforts are being made toward a consensus on methods and protocols refinement
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> for yielding more accurate and comparable fixation rates.
</p>
