<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The comparison is favourable with an overall agreement level for the historical time period of 0.89±0.07 (mean±s.d. among 7 GCM-SOILWAT comparisons) as well as for the future time period under RCP8.5 of 0.92±0.04 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 10</xref>). Regional agreement is mostly similarly high. GCM-SOILWAT agreement, however, was low for Eastern Asia in the historic time period with 0.37±0.21, which increased to 0.67±0.09 for the future period under the RCP8.5 scenario. Our simulations for the historic time period were run with observation-based weather data, whereas the GCM output represents hindcasts. For the future time periods, the representation of climate conditions for our simulations were based on GCM output. Thus, we expected a higher agreement between our simulation results and those from GCMs for the future time periods than for the historic period. Freedman 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" class="xref">83</xref> compared GRACE satellite observations of terrestrial water storage with GCM predictions for 2003–2012 for the Mississippi River Basin and found good agreement in overall aggregated values, but considerable GCM deviations spatially and in water flux partitioning. In a similar exercise, Wu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref> compared GRACE data to GCM predictions to select GCMs for a hydrological impact assessment and found noticeable variation among GCM soil moisture predictions including GCMs with cycles that do not match the seasonal variation. It is not surprising that we found modest deviations between SOILWAT and GCM soil moisture values as well (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 10</xref>), particularly across Eastern Asia, which is a region where several GCMs demonstrate difficulties in representing the monsoonal precipitation regime
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" class="xref">84</xref>.
</p>
