<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The public health sector’s 
 <italic class="italic">approach</italic> to climate change adaptation has also been debated in the literature. Hess et al. identify two contrasting views on how climate change will impact health and how public health should respond to climate change [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. The first view suggests that climate change will amplify existing public health threats, but increased investments to existing extensive public health infrastructure (e.g., program expansion) alongside adequate funding and support will be sufficient to manage the projected health impacts of climate change [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. The argument here is that the public health field is relatively well equipped to adapt to climate change due to its similarity to conventional health care and public health practices [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Meanwhile, the second view argues climate change may also impact health through entirely distinct pathways, for instance by destabilizing systems supporting public health or threatening infrastructure, thus necessitating new and innovative responses [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. While the two are not mutually exclusive, they can be contradictory, as too much confidence in conventional health care systems could increase ignorance of climate risks and reduce willingness to explore the alternative discourse. The prevailing argument taken in a particular context will impact funding priorities, prioritization of adaptation, infrastructure and preparedness decisions, and adherence to long-term approaches to public health [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>].
</p>
