<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Firstly, previous research has demonstrated that the overall infectious disease surveillance infrastructure was underfunded in China, especially in poor and rural areas [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Although China has risen to become one of the largest economic powers in the world over recent decades, its health care investment is out of pace with its rapid economic growth [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Compared with other countries in the world, China ranks among the poorest in terms of public financing for health care [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Consequently, the lack of funding in public health has resulted in limitations in technical capacity and insufficient human resources in disease control and prevention to meet the challenge of potential emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Whilst China’s comprehensive county-to-national level network CDC surveillance and reporting system has been reported as being one of the best in the world [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], greater effort is required to improve the infectious disease surveillance infrastructure. In urban areas infectious disease surveillance infrastructure has received, and continues to receive, financial support from local governments. However, maintenance and update of disease surveillance in county-level rural areas has relatively been neglected, leading to a regional imbalance between urban and rural areas [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Furthermore, despite the relative supremacy of urban disease surveillance infrastructure over its rural counterpart, it still has some limitations. In urban areas, for instance, most public health resources are concentrated in tertiary hospitals and central public health departments, while disease surveillance infrastructure in community-level health service centers needs to be strengthened. Better pathogen-based surveillance infrastructure for disease detection in urban areas and a more rapid response to infectious disease outbreaks is needed to ensure the risks of transmission are minimized in areas of high population density [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-12-11025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. It is imperative, therefore, that initiatives and actions to maintain and update rural disease surveillance infrastructure be taken, whilst concomitantly reinforcing and optimizing urban disease surveillance infrastructure.
</p>
