<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change and non-communicable diseases are global crises that threaten life as we know it and require a global response. The United Nations’ sustainable development goals (SDGs) highlight the need for a multifaceted, coordinated effort to limit global temperature rise to 1.5–2 degrees Celsius and prevent the catastrophic effects of climate change [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Among the stated objectives for health, the SDGs include increasing control and comprehensive treatment of high-burden non-communicable disease through both individual healthy life choices and public policies. The report specifically identifies the need for improved nutrition, healthy cities, and lower pollution, among other factors, in order to obtain health goals, including combating the ever increasing global obesity epidemic [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Importantly, there are opportunities to improve both greenhouse gas emissions (GHGE) and health outcomes through climate change mitigation action. This collateral beneficial relationship is termed “co-benefits”. To date, the health co-benefits of several climate change mitigation strategies have been explored extensively. Much attention has been given to large-scale projects pursued at a country or municipal level, such as adoption of cleaner burning fuels, increased resources for reproductive health, and building sustainable infrastructure [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-14-00468" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. However, relatively little attention has been paid to lifestyle co-benefits choices made at the individual level. As individuals and communities strive to design and participate in healthier more sustainable lifestyles, increased research scrutiny is needed to inform decision making lifestyle-related mitigation strategies, which for the purpose of this article, include increased active transport (i.e., cycling and walking) and climate-conscious diet modification (i.e., consuming food stuffs with relatively low GHGE). 
</p>
