<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis reveals consistent global patterns in the climate shifts of future major cities around the world over the next 30 years. Despite our use of a highly optimistic climate change scenario (i.e. RCP 4.5), we show that the climate conditions of over 77% of world’s major cities will change to such a great extent that they will resemble more closely the conditions of another major city. The projected shifts showed consistent biogeographic trends, with all city climates (both southern and northern hemisphere) generally shifting towards the conditions in warmer, low-latitude regions. The extent and consistency of these patterns provides a stark reminder of the global scale of this climate change threat and associated risks for human health. In contrast to previous analyses, our analysis also reveals that 22% of the world’s cities are likely to exist in a climatic regime that does not current exist on the planet today. These trends highlight the extreme vulnerability of tropical and sub-tropical cities, 30% of which will experience shifts into entirely novel climate regimes with no existing analogues across the world’s major cities. This lends support to the idea of novel climates, which are expected to emerge in many tropical and sub-tropical regions [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref029">29</a>]. It should be noted that, by defining the climate envelope using a convex-hull (i.e. by defining a volume from simplices (“triangles”) that form the smallest convex simplicial complex of a set of input points in 4-dimensional space), we applied a conservative method for evaluating future change. Indeed, because it includes the smallest level of extrapolation and generating the smallest possible shapes, this approach has a low-risk of incorrectly identifying novel climate conditions, relative to a concave-hull approach [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref031">31</a>]. However, this approach necessarily comes with the high likelihood of missing some novel climates. The 22% of cities experiencing a novel climate must therefore be seen as a highly conservative estimate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings also support previous studies conducted in Europe [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref011">11</a>] and north America [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref013">13</a>], stressing the current trend of north-to-south geographical shift across the northern hemisphere. Yet, using an optimistic climate change scenario, we found that the velocity (i.e. the speed of geographical shift) risks to be higher in the near future than in the second half of the 21th century [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref010">10</a>] passing from 15 km year
  <span class="sup">-1</span> to 20 km year
  <span class="sup">-1</span>. Our study also allows the extension of such observations to the global scale, showing that observations for Europe can be generalized for the entire Northern Hemisphere and for a part of the southern hemisphere (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217592.g002" href="#pone.0217592.g002">Fig 2B</a>). At the global scale, our study reveals that geographical shift tend to converge towards the subtropics (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217592.g004" href="#pone.0217592.g004">Fig 4</a>), going to warmer climate conditions from boreal and temperate regions and to drier conditions from tropical regions. While this lends support to previous observations of a “tropical belt widening” due to the expected warmer conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref008">8</a>], it also shows that tropical biomes tend to shrink in many areas due to drier conditions. We therefore suggest here to refer to a “sub-tropical widening” compared to the previous “tropical widening” due to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While our findings are necessarily dependent on the methodology used to identify the climatic shifts, it is widely recognized that the choice of the metric to assess the similarity-dissimilarity of the climate conditions between cities has an extremely minor effect, compared to the choice of the climate model and scenario[
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref032">32</a>]. That is, our results are unlikely to be affected whatever method we use to calculate dissimilarity, as the variation between climate projections is far greater. Nonetheless, Mahony and colleagues [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref031">31</a>] highlighted the need to standardize the contribution of each climate variable to the dissimilarity matrix and to account for correlation between them to avoid any bias[
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref031">31</a>]. In the present study, we address this using a scaled principal component analysis to summarize the main bioclimatic variations among the 520 major cities. This approach simply follows classic dissimilarity analysis recommendations for ecological studies[
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref027">27</a>], applying an Euclidean distance matrix on the main dimensions of the principal component analysis to assess the similarity between cities. This method was preferred to the sigma-dissimilarity developed by Mahony and colleagues[
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref031">31</a>] for its simplicity and it broad use in ecological sciences.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis allows us to visualize a tangible climate future of the world’s major cities. These results enable decision makers from all sectors of society, to envision changes that are likely to occur in their own city, within their own lifetime. Londoners, for example, can start to consider how their 2050 equivalents (e.g. Barcelona today) have taken action to combat their own environmental challenges. In 2008, Barcelona experienced extreme drought conditions, which required the importation of €22m of drinking water. Since then, the municipal government has implemented a series of ‘
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.libelium.com/saving-water-with-smart-irrigation-system-in-barcelona/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">smart initiatives</span>‘ to manage the city’s water resources (including the control of park irrigation and water fountain levels). The Mayor of London has factored drought considerations into his Environment Strategy aims for 2050 [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref033">33</a>], but this study can provide the context to facilitate the development of more targeted climate strategies. In addition, this information can also empower local citizens to evaluate proposed environmental policies. By allowing people to visualize their own climate futures, we hope that this information can facilitate efforts to mitigate and adapt to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study is not a novel model revealing updated climate projections or expectations by 2050. Instead, our analysis is intended to illustrate how complex climate data can be effectively summarized into tangible information that can be easily interpreted by anyone. Of course, the climate scenarios that we have used are based on predictions from a few climate models, run under a single (business as usual) climate scenario. We recognize that these models are characterized by huge amounts of uncertainty [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref034">34</a>], and the predicted Future Cities may change as these Earth System Models are refined, in particular in light of urban climate specificities [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref035">35</a>]. However, our results are likely to reflect the qualitative direction of climate changes within cities and so meet our primary goal, which is to communicate predicted climate changes to a non-specialist audience in order to motivate action. When model projections are updated, we would recommend communicating any new results with this goal in mind.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our knowledge, our study represents the first global analysis of the shifts in climate conditions of the world’s major cities under climate change. Our analysis revealed that over 77% of the world’s cities are likely to experience a shift towards the climate conditions of another major city by 2050, while 22% will shift to climate conditions that are not currently present for any major cities on the planet. Across the globe, the direction of movement is generally trending towards the subtropics, providing unifying patterns that support trends observed in Europe and North America. In addition, this analysis revealed new insights for cities in equatorial regions, many of which are likely to move to entirely new climate conditions that are not currently experienced by any of the other global cities today. These city analogues, and the data we openly share, can help land managers and city planners to visualize the climate futures of their respective cities, facilitating efforts to establish targeted climate response strategies. As well as facilitating our basic understanding of climate change effects, our analysis highlights the value of using cities to visualize the tangible effects of climate change across the globe.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
