<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summarizing the current climate among the major cities through a principal component analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 19 current and future bioclimatic variables were extracted from the coordinates of the 520 major cities (i.e., the city centroids), meaning each city had two sets of bioclimatic metrics: the current climate data for the world’s major cities (Current Cities) and the equivalent 2050 projection (Future Cities) according to the average of the three RCP 4.5 GCMs.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A scaled principal components analysis (PCA) was performed on current bioclimatic data in order to account for correlation between climate variables and to standardize their contributions to the subsequent dissimilarity analysis [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref027">27</a>]. As the first four principal components accounted for more than 85% of the total variation of climate data (40.2%, 26.9%, 10.5% and 7.6%, respectively), the remaining principal components were dropped from later analyses. The main contributing variables to the four components are the temperature seasonality (axis 1), the minimum temperature of the coldest month (axis 1), the maximum temperature of the warmest month (axis 2), the precipitation seasonality (axis 2), the precipitation of the driest (axis 4) and of the wettest (axis 3) month, and the temperature diurnal range (axis 4, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217592.g001" href="#pone.0217592.g001">Fig 1</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217592.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217592.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Distribution of current and future cities along the first 4 principal component axes.</div>
   <p>The seven major climate variables contributing to the Principal Component Analysis (PCA) are superposed on each figure. The figure at the top (a) shows the distribution of current (blue) and future (red) cities on the space defined by the first two principal components. The first two axes explain, respectively, 40.2 and 26.9% of climate variations. The first axis is mainly driven by differences in temperature seasonality and in minimum temperature of the coldest month, while the second axis is mainly driven by differences in precipitation seasonality. The figure at the bottom (b) shows the same current (green) and future (orange) cities on the space defined by the third and fourth principal components. They explain respectively 10.5 and 7.6% of climate variations. The third axis is mainly driven by changes in precipitation of the wet season, while the fourth axis is mainly driven by changes in the mean diurnal temperature range. Boxplots illustrates the distribution of the points along each of the 4 axes. The continuous line in the boxes represents the median of the distribution, the extremities of the boxes the 1
    <span class="sup">st</span> and the 3
    <span class="sup">rd</span> quartile and the continuous lines go up to 1.5 times the difference between the 3
    <span class="sup">st</span> and the 1
    <span class="sup">rd</span> quartile.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217592.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
