<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The gap between the scientific and public understanding of climate change, referred to as the “Consensus Gap”, is largely attributed to failures in climate change communication[
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref001">1</a>]. Often limited to ad-hoc reporting of extreme weather events or intangible, long-term climate impacts (e.g. changes in average temperature by 2100). Despite an exhaustive list of risks associated to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref002">2</a>] (e.g. heat stress, air and water quality, food supply, distribution of vectors of diseases, social factors), the intangible nature of reporting on climate change fails to adequately convey the urgency of this issue to a public audience on a consistent basis[
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref003">3</a>]. It is hard for most people to envision how an additional 2°C of warming might affect daily life. This ineffective communication of climate change facts, compounded by uncertainty about the extent of expected changes, has left the door open for widespread misinterpretation about the existence of this global phenomenon.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">History has repeatedly shown us that data and facts alone do not inspire humans to change their beliefs or act [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref003">3</a>]. Increased scientific literacy has no correlation with the acceptance of climate change facts [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref004">4</a>]. A growing body of research demonstrates that visualization—the ability to create a mental image of the problem—is the most effective approach for motivating behavior change [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref006">6</a>]. Several studies have analyzed ‘geographic shifts’ to better illustrate climate change. For example, Seidel and colleagues (2008) [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref008">8</a>] showed that climate change has driven a widening of the tropical belt, by ~2 to 4.8 latitudinal degrees in recent decades. Similarly, the changing conditions of cities around the world provides another tangible example of shifting climate regimes. Given that over 50% of the global population exists within cities [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref009">9</a>], these urban environments potentially valuable tool to visualize the impact of climate change at a global scale. As iconic locations, cities are associated with distinct sets of environmental conditions. As such, shifts in the climate conditions of these urban areas could provide a unique opportunity for people to visualize the impacts of climate change, and to establish effective response strategies to address the effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref010">10</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref015">15</a>] and press reports [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref017">17</a>] have shown that the use of ‘cities geographic shift’ or “city analogues” can help to understand and visualize the effects of climate change. In particular, cities can serve as useful climate analog, enabling people to visualize their own climate future via comparison with other cities that currently experience those climate conditions. However, until now, existing research have been focused on regional- or continent-scale analyses in North America or Europe [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref010">10</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref015">15</a>], and we lack a unifying global perspective. These regional trends suggest that cities are likely to resemble those at lower latitudes as the climate continues to warm. However, it remains unclear if this trend holds at a global scale, as other climate drivers such as changing precipitation regimes may obscure these latitudinal trends. As such, Southern Hemisphere or tropical cities, which already exist in warm conditions and are likely to experience considerable changes in precipitation and extreme climate variation, may show independent geographic shifts under changing climate conditions. Generating a unified understanding of the shifts in the climate conditions of the world’s cities is critical if we are going to visualize the impacts of climate change in any biogeographic region. Generating this understanding requires a global perspective and the use of a full range of climate variables to represent the entire climate regime of those regions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we evaluate the global shifts in the climate conditions of cities by taking current climate data for the world’s 520 major cities (Current Cities), and project what they will most closely resemble in 2050 (Future Cities). Rather than describing the quantitative changes in climate variables [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref018">18</a>], we propose to quantify city climate analogs at a global scale [
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref010">10</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217592.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217592.ref012">12</a>], i.e. assessing which Current Cities will most closely resemble the climate conditions of Future Cities. To tackle previous limitations, we explore these patterns at a global scale using 19 bioclimatic variables, to include climate variability and seasonality in addition to climate averages.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Specifically, we aim to test three questions: (i) What proportion of the world’s major cities of the future most closely resemble their own current climate conditions 
  <span class="italic">vs</span>. the climate conditions of other cities in different geographic regions? (ii) What proportion of cities will experience novel climate conditions that are outside the range experiences by cities today? (iii) If cities do shift their climate conditions, is this spatial shift uniform in direction across the planet?
 </p>
</sec>
