<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Anthropogenic climate change represents a major threat to global biodiversity (Urban 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) and is causing strong ecological responses in many taxonomic groups across broad geographic areas (Parmesan 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Species can avoid climate‐driven extinctions through three principle mechanisms: (1) individuals of a species can acclimate to changes in climate; (2) species can adapt to changing climatic conditions in situ; and/or (3) species can shift their ranges to follow the geographic displacement of suitable climate conditions (Feeley et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). For many taxa, acclimation seems unlikely given that the rapid pace and large‐magnitude of current climate change will quickly push climatic conditions beyond tolerable limits (Jump and Peñuelas 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). The remaining two options, species migration and adaptation, are not mutually exclusive and have occurred simultaneously in many species during past episodes of climate change (Davis and Shaw 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). However, given the inability of many species to evolve at the extremely rapid rates required to keep pace with contemporary climate change (Quintero and Wiens 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), the future of many species, and especially long‐lived species such as trees, will depend largely on their ability to shift their geographic ranges (Gienapp et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Visser 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Hanski 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref> but see Skelly et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0501" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Hoffmann and Sgro 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0500" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Indeed, many species are already responding to climate change through geographic range shifts (Parmesan 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31645-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
