<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0080" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beef GHG emissions in wider context</div>
 <p id="p0240" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although GHG emissions were the focus of this study, the wider impacts and broader context of beef production must also be acknowledged (
  <a rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0180">McClelland et al., 2018</a>). Additional negative environmental consequences beyond GHG emissions are also associated with beef systems, including risks of acidification and eutrophication of local water bodies and land degradation (
  <a rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0075">de Vries et al., 2015</a>). At the same time, benefits beyond meat production may also be conferred, including ecosystem service provision and rural employment (
  <a rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0285">Smith et al., 2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0245" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standardising all emissions per kg of generic meat output is also a potentially reductive approach. Meat differs in a large range of attributes of potential consumer importance (
  <a rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0135">Henchion et al., 2014</a>). These other attributes can depend upon system type, with evidence that grass-fed beef may be nutritionally superior (
  <a rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0065">Daley et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0170">McAfee et al., 2011</a>), for example. Different meat attributes and a range of potential benefits or disbenefits of beef production must therefore be considered in order to fully appraise the relative value of different systems and the net impact of beef production. Assessing these multifaceted concerns can be complex, but provides important insight into the potential for agricultural sustainable intensification and how we might achieve healthy and sustainable diets. Improving our assessment of the climate impacts of different food products and production systems will provide an essential contribution to these topics.
 </p>
</sec>
