<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0015" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon dioxide equivalence metrics</div>
 <p id="p0050" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GHG footprints are typically expressed as a CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalent (CO
  <sub>2</sub>e) that equates different GHGs to CO
  <sub>2</sub>. Emissions of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> gases are multiplied by metric values that describe the amount of CO
  <sub>2</sub> that would result in an equivalent climate impact. For multi-gas footprints, the CO
  <sub>2</sub>e values of each gas can then be summed to give a single combined CO
  <sub>2</sub>e footprint. As these metrics are relative to CO
  <sub>2</sub>, CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions are added without conversion. However, there are multiple CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence metrics that can be expressed over different timescales, resulting in significant variation in conversion factors for the same GHG (e.g. 
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). Metric choice can thus have a large impact on agricultural GHG footprints, and especially those associated with ruminant livestock, due to the extent of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions.
  <div position="float" id="t0005" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Twenty- and 100-year Global Warming Potential (GWP) and Global Temperature Potential (GTP) values for biogenic methane (CH
     <sub>4</sub>) and nitrous oxide (N
     <sub>2</sub>O) (without carbon cycle feedbacks). From 
     <a rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0200">Myhre et al. (2013)</a>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="al0050" class="alt-text">Table 1</span>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>GWP
       <sub>20</sub>
      </th>
      <th>GWP
       <sub>100</sub>
      </th>
      <th>GTP
       <sub>20</sub>
      </th>
      <th>GTP
       <sub>100</sub>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>CH
       <sub>4</sub>
      </td>
      <td>84</td>
      <td>28</td>
      <td>67</td>
      <td>4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>N
       <sub>2</sub>O
      </td>
      <td>264</td>
      <td>265</td>
      <td>277</td>
      <td>234</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0055" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alternative metrics differ markedly due to the distinct physical properties of individual GHGs. GHGs differ in their atmospheric lifespan and radiative efficiency (RE), the amount by which they alter the Earth's energy balance (measured as the change in radiative energy balance per change in atmospheric concentration of a given GHG). CO
  <sub>2</sub> has a relatively low RE, but can persist for millennia (
  <a rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0025">Archer and Brovkin, 2008</a>). CH
  <sub>4</sub> has a greater RE, but an average atmospheric lifetime of only around 12.4 years, while N
  <sub>2</sub>O has an even larger RE, and a lifetime of approximately 121 years (
  <a rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0200">Myhre et al., 2013</a>). The net energy balance perturbation resulting from a given change in the concentration of a GHG (generally over a specified time period) is defined as its radiative forcing (RF), and the total RF from all climate pollutants ultimately leads to warming as the Earth system adjusts (
  <a rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0200">Myhre et al., 2013</a>). CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence metrics typically collapse differences in both atmospheric lifespan and RE into a single value by modelling the RF (or alternative consequential impact such as temperature change) that would result from a specified emission scenario. The RF (or other output measure) for a given GHG is then scaled relative to the value for CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the same reference scenario. Such approaches, however, can mask important dynamics (
  <a rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0240">Pierrehumbert, 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0060" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most commonly used CO
  <sub>2</sub>e metric, the 100-year global warming potential (GWP
  <sub>100</sub>), is the integrated RF for 100 years following a one-off pulse emission of a gas, relative to CO
  <sub>2</sub>, and could be considered as representing “the total energy added to the climate system by a component in question relative to that added by CO
  <sub>2</sub>” (
  <a rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0200">Myhre et al., 2013</a>) over this period. Due to the differing atmospheric lifespans of different gases, this ‘addition of energy’ relative to CO
  <sub>2</sub> is not temporally uniform, and so the effect of changing the time horizon depends on the GHG. For a short-lived GHG such as methane, the increased atmospheric concentrations and hence elevated RF that result from a pulse emission will dissipate after a few decades, and so increasing the time-horizon beyond this increases the CO
  <sub>2</sub> reference denominator (as the emitted CO
  <sub>2</sub> and hence its resultant radiative forcing persist) while the methane numerator is unchanged, thus reducing its CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence value. For longer-lived GHGs such as nitrous oxide, the impact of emissions remains relatively uniform over time, and so their CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence values are less sensitive to changing the time-horizon (for time-horizons shorter than the lifetime of the gas).
 </p>
 <p id="p0065" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most prominent alternative metric, the Global Temperature change Potential (GTP, also described in the most recent IPCC Assessment Report), is based on the modelled temperature impact of different gases relative to CO
  <sub>2</sub> at a specified time following an emission pulse (GTP
  <sub>100</sub> for the temperature response 100 years following an emission). Here the time refers to a specific endpoint, rather than integrating over an increasing period, and so GTP is even more sensitive to changing time horizon than GWP. As it relates to a final modelled impact, it can be slightly easier to intuit the meaning of GTP changing over time than GWP: if the same quantities of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and methane are released into the atmosphere, after 20 years the methane will cause a temperature increase 67 times greater than the CO
  <sub>2</sub>, but after 100 years that same methane emission will be responsible for a temperature increase only 4 times that of the emission of CO
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). The CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence for a given GHG is thus only defined by the specific aspect of the climate response described by the chosen metric, at the specific time horizon used. If only a single combined CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalent footprint is provided, dynamics outside of these specifications cannot be inferred. For example, if we know that an activity has a total GTP
  <sub>20</sub> footprint of 67 kg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e, it could be 1 kg of methane (0 kg CO
  <sub>2</sub>), in which case 100 years after this activity the temperature impact would decline to the equivalent of 4 kg CO
  <sub>2</sub>, or the footprint could be 67 kg CO
  <sub>2</sub> (0 kg methane), which would, by definition, still have the impact of 67 kg CO
  <sub>2</sub> after 100 years.
 </p>
 <p id="p0070" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Neither metric is more physically accurate than the other, as they are both derived from the same atmospheric behaviours, but incorporate different aspects of the climate response. In going further towards modelling climate responses, rather than just the processes that eventually result in temperature change, GTP is subject to more uncertainty than GWP, but it has been argued that this is also an important element in anticipating the climate response, and hence does not necessarily represent a disadvantage (
  <a rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0015">Allen et al., 2016</a>). Other metrics have also been suggested, but this paper demonstrates the fixed time-horizon GWP and GTP variants above taken from the most recent IPCC report (
  <a rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0200">Myhre et al., 2013</a>), as they remain the most widely used. The 20- and 100-year variants have been suggested as revealing shorter- and longer-term impacts of different GHGs respectively (
  <a rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0210">Ocko et al., 2017</a>, but see discussion below).
 </p>
 <p id="p0075" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While GWP
  <sub>100</sub> CO
  <sub>2</sub>e has become the standard metric used in emissions reporting and climate policy, it has been criticised (e.g. 
  <a rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0215">O'Neill, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0105">Fuglestvedt et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0275">Shine, 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0240">Pierrehumbert, 2014</a>), and the IPCC assessment reports remain cautious not to suggest any one metric is inherently superior: “All choices of metric contain implicit value-related judgements such as type of effect considered and weighting of effects over time” (
  <a rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0200">Myhre et al., 2013</a>). Comparing multiple climate metrics for a single footprint has been proposed as a means of better incorporating the differences between GHGs and acknowledging the impact of metric choice on any conclusions drawn (
  <a rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0165">Levasseur et al., 2016</a>), and recently recommended in new global guidance on environmental life cycle impact assessment indicators from the United Nations Environmental Programme and Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry (
  <a rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0150">Jolliet et al., 2018</a>). Metric comparisons are only possible if GHG footprints are provided as separate emissions of individual gases: as noted above, it is not possible to work backwards or infer these effects from a single aggregated CO
  <sub>2</sub>e footprint.
 </p>
 <p id="p0080" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that significant amounts of methane are emitted by cattle production, aggregated CO
  <sub>2</sub>e footprints for the activity will vary greatly depending on the metric used. As well as changing the apparent climate impacts of beef production relative to other activities, there may be important implications for the appraisal of different types of beef production. On-going debate surrounds the relative emissions efficiency of cattle fed diets of either predominantly grass or higher energy feeds (
  <a rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0040">Capper, 2012</a>). Higher energy feeds (e.g. grains or soy) result in reduced CH
  <sub>4</sub> emissions, as they are more digestible and energy-dense (
  <a rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0160">Knapp et al., 2014</a>), and a number of recent reviews have illustrated, based on comparisons of total GWP
  <sub>100</sub> CO
  <sub>2</sub>e footprints, that grass-fed cattle are generally less emissions efficient (
  <a rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0075">de Vries et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0055">Clark and Tilman, 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0125">Gerssen-Gondelach et al., 2017</a>). However, if these lower GWP
  <sub>100</sub> footprints are a result of lower animal CH
  <sub>4</sub> but come at the expense of higher CO
  <sub>2</sub> and N
  <sub>2</sub>O emissions incurred in producing feeds, this conclusion may only hold under metrics that value CH
  <sub>4</sub> relatively highly. This adds important nuance to the types of system we should prioritise for climate sustainability, and links with wider concerns such as avoiding the consumption of human-edible foodstuffs by ruminant livestock (
  <a rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0090">Eisler et al., 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="p0085" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The complexities in cattle emissions and their resulting climate impacts make it essential that GHG footprints are available as separate emissions of individual gases. Despite this, there is a general focus on GWP
  <sub>100</sub> as a reporting metric that has resulted in many footprinting papers (and reviews thereof) only publishing a single aggregated CO
  <sub>2</sub>e value. This paper presents a systematic review of bottom-up beef footprint studies, the primary purpose of which is simply to establish how GHG footprints are reported, and how readily available disaggregated emissions data are in the current literature. The consequences of alternative metric choices are explored, and illustrated with a simple example comparing grass fed and non-grass fed production systems.
 </p>
</sec>
