<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0085" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="p0250" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Greenhouse gas emissions should not overshadow the other impacts of beef systems, whether wider negative externalities, or potential benefits beyond food provision. However, beef production is frequently highlighted as an especially emissions intensive activity, and so it is important to interrogate this topic specifically. This study suggests that relevant data are not as widespread or robust as they may first appear. Very high levels of beef consumption are climatically unsustainable, regardless of carbon dioxide equivalence metric (
  <a rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0245">Pierrehumbert and Eshel, 2015</a>). However, there are important details that we cannot reliably ascertain from the current literature. The standard reporting of GHG emissions as only a total GWP
  <sub>100</sub> CO
  <sub>2</sub>e footprint results in a significant loss of information, and the main aim of this review is to draw attention to this and encourage researchers and practitioners to publish any emissions in a disaggregated form. Without this data, the inferred climate impacts of a given GHG footprint are not clear, and limiting reporting to total GWP
  <sub>100</sub> CO
  <sub>2</sub>e can have significant implications for the apparent emissions efficiency of, for example, different types of beef production system, or the relative climate impact of beef production compared to other GHG-emitting activities. Even if using only a single climate metric, results cannot be standardised over time unless emissions of individual gases are known. Adding this data, even if just as a supplementary note, could immediately benefit research into the climate impacts of agricultural activity, and should be a straightforward addition, as individual studies or LCA databases must, at some point, have dealt with disaggregated emissions data before converting and summing to a total CO
  <sub>2</sub>e footprint. A greater awareness of debates surrounding carbon dioxide equivalence metrics and more consideration given to metric choice or the incorporation of climate modelling approaches can significantly improve the assessment of agricultural emissions.
 </p>
</sec>
