<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Greenhouse gas emissions associated with beef production</div>
 <p id="p0035" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beef production includes a number of processes that generate GHG emissions (
  <a rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#bb0080">Desjardins et al., 2012</a>). Methane (CH
  <sub>4</sub>) from enteric fermentation, part of the digestive process of ruminant animals in which carbohydrates are broken down by microbial activity, is generally the largest emissions source from beef production (under the most commonly used metric – see below). Animal excreta generate further emissions, with a proportion of organic content lost as additional CH
  <sub>4</sub>, and nitrogen lost as nitrous oxide (N
  <sub>2</sub>O). Nitrogen inputs to agricultural soils, including (but not limited to) fertiliser application, result in further N
  <sub>2</sub>O emissions, while urea and lime application result in carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) emissions. CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions are also generated by on-farm energy use, either in the form of electricity or fuel. Land-use and land-use change greenhouse gas fluxes can also result from beef production, with CO
  <sub>2</sub> either emitted to or sequestered from the atmosphere depending upon changes in plant biomass and soil organic content.
 </p>
 <p id="p0040" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The emissions described above cover typical on-farm (‘within farm gate’) GHGs. To give a complete account of the emissions that are generated as a result of beef production, i.e. a life-cycle assessment (LCA), the system boundaries must be expanded beyond this to include the impacts incurred in the production of farm inputs (‘pre-farm gate’). These include, for example, any agricultural and land use emissions from the production of feedstuffs grown elsewhere, and the energy used to manufacture fertilisers and other inputs. Including these emissions then covers the production process from initial inputs (‘cradle’) to the point at which finished animals leave the farm, often referred to as ‘cradle-to-gate’.</p>
 <p id="p0045" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">System boundaries can be expanded further still, including downstream (post-farm gate) emissions resulting from, for example, transport of animals, abattoir energy and resource use, refrigeration and cooking (for a complete ‘cradle-to-fork’ LCA). This study focuses on cradle-to-gate emissions, as a commonly used system boundary for agricultural production LCAs. The greenhouse gas emissions component of an LCA is often referred to as the ‘carbon footprint’ of a product (here, the term ‘GHG footprint’ is preferred).</p>
</sec>
