<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Database</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We employed two long-term datasets for use in our analysis. One is a dataset containing 30 years of data from DBR (Dinghushan Biosphere Reserve, Guangdong province, China); the other contains approximately 25 years of data from BCI (Barro Colorado Island, Panama). DBR has a subtropical climate, and BCI has a tropical climate. Rare species were not included in this study, because they are more sensitive to disturbance and the variations of their numbers are more stochastic.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DBR (23°10′N, 112°35′E) has a monsoon climate and is located in a subtropical, moist forest life zone. The annual mean temperature is 22.3°C and the annual mean rainfall is 1678 mm with a distinct seasonal pattern. Monthly average air temperature and precipitation, representing DBR's climatic regime, were obtained from the Gaoyao weather station [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref034">34</a>]. The reserve is dominated by regional climax, evergreen broadleaf forest represented by the 
  <span class="italic">Cryptocarya</span> community, which is dominated by 
  <span class="italic">Cryptocarya chinensis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cryptocarya concinna</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Castanopsis chinensis</span>. Abundance of the 3 dominant species in two communities was investigated 9 times from 1955 to 1985. One community was 
  <span class="italic">Cryptocarya</span> community, which was at the relatively stable stage; the other community was 
  <span class="italic">Pinus-Castanopsis-Schima</span> community, which was at a relatively early stage of succession. There were very few human activities in the study area until 1980s and there was no big pest outbreak before 1985[
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref035">35</a>]. More than twelve 10×10 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> quadrates were investigated in each of the communities. The average abundance (number of individuals) of 3 species in 2 communities for every investigation was recorded [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref036">36</a>] (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0126228.s003">S1 Table</a>). The climate data for monthly temperature and precipitation in DBR were provided by Guoyi Zhou (2012, pers. comm., 5 September).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The BCI plot (9°9'N, 79°51'W) covers an area of 50 ha; it was the first plot established by the CTFS (Center for Tropical Forest Science) and is undoubtedly one of the best-studied forests in the world [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref021">21</a>]. The island receives an average of 2634 mm of rain per year, with a pronounced four-month dry season from mid-December through mid-April [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref037">37</a>]. Daytime temperatures reach an average of 32°C, with night-time lows of approximately 23°C. This island has 1500 ha of diverse, moist, lowland, tropical forest, and has been protected from human disturbance for 70 years [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref038">38</a>]. Abundance data collected from 1981 to 2005 on the 50 ha plot were obtained from the Center for Tropical Forest Science (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ctfs.si.edu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ctfs.si.edu/</span>) and monthly climate data were provided by Steven Paton (2012, pers. comm., 23 October). There were 319 species recorded for woody stems ≥ 10 mm diameter at breast height. Among these species, only species with an average of at least 10 individuals per ha for 6 censuses were included in our analysis because large percentage changes in abundance of rare species could be caused by minor, chance events [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref039">39</a>]. Consequently, we finalised a list of 77 species for analysis (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0126228.s004">S2 Table</a>). The total abundance of 77 species accounted for 91 percent of the total individuals on the plot.
 </p>
</sec>
