<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts of climate change on community composition change rate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Altered population growth of dominant species could have profound effects on community structure and ecosystem function [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref049">49</a>]. Most previous studies on succession rate only considered the species composition change of a community [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref051">51</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref053">53</a>], but did not take population dynamics into account. In fact, community change not only indicates the species composition change but also implies a proportional change of each species relative to one another [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref054">54</a>]. One could not say a community is unchanged when no old species disappears and no new species established over years because the community composition often changes with different proportions of each species. Therefore, using the index Slnλ is more precise for detecting the rate of community change. Slnλ is determined by population growth rates of dominant species of a community, which can be predicted by environmental and temporal factors. Thus, community composition change rate, Slnλ, in a relatively short time period is predictable.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The community composition change rate, Slnλ, is determined by population growth rates of all species in a community. Accordingly, it can be inferred that at the stages when vast species replacement takes place, Slnλ should be very high. This new index can be very useful when we want to compare the stability of different communities during a time period or different stages of community changing process.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used linear regression analysis to detect the relationship between climate and community change rate, Slnλ (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g006">Fig 6</a>). Because species respond to climate individually, it is very difficult to predict the collective response. Our results suggest that a positive relationship exists between increasing temperature and increasing community change rate. Although decreasing precipitation has a positive effect on population growth rate for most populations, the overall effect on the community composition change rate seems complicated in our study. As we know, changes in precipitation can affect community composition by altering germination, seedling establishment, growth, and survival [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref055">55</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref056">56</a>]. In some studies, changes in the timing of rainfall have a greater influence on community composition than the amount of rainfall [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref057">57</a>]. Another experimental study found that drought and warming treatments slowed down secondary succession in a Mediterranean climate, and indicated that future drier and warmer conditions may severely affect plant succession due to the existence of both abundance-dependent and species-specific responses [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref058">58</a>]. For the BCI plot in our analysis, the impact of El Niño event in early 1983 caused immediate increases in tree mortality, and since then there has been a persistent directional change in the flora toward and increased abundance of drought-tolerant species[
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref021">21</a>]. These changes in composition were reflected by the community composition change rate Slnλ, which was extremely high in the 1980~1985 interval (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g005">Fig 5E</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a long-term perspective, range shifts due to global warming will alter the structure and composition of communities and change the function of ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref059">59</a>]. As different species respond to climate change in various ways, species previously regarded as aliens will begin to appear in new communities. Species that can quickly adapt to new environmental conditions will outpace those that cannot [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref060">60</a>]. Studies in Siberia revealed that a warmer climate will likely convert deciduous larch to evergreen conifer forests [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref061">61</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref062">62</a>]. When species diversity and abundance increase, community composition change rate generally will be accelerated. However, in a relatively short time period of 20 to 30 decades, species composition will not change significantly. Although climate changes influence population growth of each species, these changes will not fundamentally affect community change rate within a few decades.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To detect the community composition change rate over decades, we propose a relatively more concise index, Slnλ, which refers to an overall population growth rate based on the dominant species in a community. The variation of Slnλ over time is mainly determined by community development. Climate factors can influence the population growth rate and accordingly affect the community composition change rate. The present study indicates that increasing temperature has a positive effect on population growth rate and community change rate. Decreasing precipitation has a positive effect on population growth, but shows a complex effect on community change. As global warming will bring more precipitation to high latitudes in both winter and summer and less precipitation to low latitudes [
  <a rid="pone.0126228.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0126228.ref063">63</a>], further study is needed to reveal the relationships between the historical variations in climate and population dynamics in broader areas.
 </p>
</sec>
