<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Mepraia gajardoi</italic> is currently detected on the northern coastal zones where the arid climate is common, whilst 
 <italic class="italic">M. spinolai</italic> can be found in valleys in the Mediterranean-semiarid climate zones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. The domestic vectorial transmission by the domestic vector 
 <italic class="italic">T. infestans</italic> was declared interrupted in 1999; however, wild vectors are still a problem in rural areas of Chile [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>]. The sylvatic 
 <italic class="italic">M. spinolai</italic> is very abundant in stone quarries of periurban zones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>] where it feeds on wild rodents, goats, dogs, cats, rabbits and humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>], and several home invasion complaints are notified to the authorities every year (data requested from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.portaltransparencia.cl" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.portaltransparencia.cl</ext-link>). 
 <italic class="italic">Mepraia gajardoi</italic> is abundant near seaweed collector settlements, where it preferably feeds on sea birds, marine mammals, lizards, dogs, cats and humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. These situations are epidemiologically relevant, especially considering that the prevalence of 
 <italic class="italic">T. cruzi</italic> in 
 <italic class="italic">M. spinolai</italic> populations can reach up to 76.1% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>] and 27.0% for 
 <italic class="italic">M. gajardoi</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. Under this scenario, it is necessary to explore potential areas where these species can be detected, increasing information on habitat preferences, niche requirements and geographical distributions.
</p>
