<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Gateway Belief Model (GBM)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived expert consensus plays an important role in the formation of public attitudes towards and the acceptance of general scientific principles, including climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0118489.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0118489.ref015">15</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0118489.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0118489.ref016">16</a>]. In fact, misperceptions of the scientific consensus can be highly consequential, as even a small amount of perceived scientific dissent can undermine public support [
  <a rid="pone.0118489.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0118489.ref017">17</a>]. For example, a recent nationally representative study [
  <a rid="pone.0118489.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0118489.ref018">18</a>] found that the degree of perceived scientific agreement influences key beliefs about global warming, which in turn, drive public support for climate change policies. McCright, Dunlap &amp; Xiao [
  <a rid="pone.0118489.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0118489.ref019">19</a>] successfully replicated these results in a recent independent study and similarly point to the robust role of perceived scientific agreement in generating public support for climate change policies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yet, past research in this area suffers from one major short-coming: the bulk of these findings are based on cross-sectional survey data and thus correlational in nature. To date, there have been no controlled representative experiments (or longitudinal studies) investigating the proposed causal relationship between public perceptions of the scientific consensus on climate change and support for public action. This study builds upon and extends prior research in a novel direction by directly testing the “gateway belief” model experimentally. We posit that belief or disbelief in the scientific consensus on human-caused climate change plays an important role in the formation of public opinion on the issue. This is consistent with prior research, which has found that highlighting scientific consensus increases belief in human-caused climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0118489.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0118489.ref015">15</a>]. More specifically, we posit perceived scientific agreement as a “gateway belief” that either supports or undermines other key beliefs about climate change, which in turn, influence support for public action. A schematic overview of the “gateway belief model” is presented in 
  <a rid="pone.0118489.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0118489.g001">Fig. 1</a>. Specifically, we hypothesize that an experimentally induced 
  <span class="italic">change</span> in the level of perceived consensus is causally associated with a subsequent 
  <span class="italic">change</span> in the belief that climate change is (a) happening, (b) human-caused, and (c) how much people worry about the issue (
  <span class="italic">H1</span>). In turn, a change in these key beliefs is subsequently expected to lead to a 
  <span class="italic">change</span> in respondents’ support for societal action on climate change (
  <span class="italic">H2</span>). Thus, while the model predicts that the perceived level of scientific agreement acts as a key psychological motivator, its effect on support for action is assumed to be fully mediated by key beliefs about climate change (
  <span class="italic">H3</span>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0118489.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0118489.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The Gateway Belief Model (GBM).</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0118489.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
