<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper we have investigated tipping phenomena due to parameter drifts in typical dynamical systems exhibiting permanent or transient chaotic motion (due to topological complexity) in the frozen-in case. Because the rates of the parameter drifts are on the same order of magnitudes as the time scales of the internal dynamics, no bifurcation-induced tipping can occur.</p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chaotic nature of the dynamics requires the consideration of ensembles of trajectories instead of single trajectories. Surprisingly, in spite of the deterministic nature of the problem, we find that transitions take place with a certain likelihood. Associated 
  <span class="italic">tipping probabilities</span> are shown to be a powerful quantitative measure to characterize the tipping process. The tipping probabilities depend smoothly (but not necessarily monotonously) on the drift scenario. In contrast to traditional tippings related to a critical rate for the parameter drift, we find no sharp transitions but a rather gradual vanishing of tipping probabilities which we still consider as a type of rate-induced tipping.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We argue, that 
  <span class="italic">scenario-dependent basins of attraction</span> containing all initial conditions converging to a particular attractor in the ramped system are the key to understanding the different tipping transitions. We explored the following novel types of tipping (for more details, see Supplementary Information).
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par45">(i): 
     <span class="italic">Tipping into a chaotic attractor</span> occurs when the system starts from a periodic attractor but ends up on a chaotic one, allowing a plethora of permitted states.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par46">(ii): 
     <span class="italic">Tipping from or through a chaotic attractor</span> is closely related to losing the predictability of which trajectories tip and which do not. As a result of the unpredictability of the dynamics on chaotic attractors, tipping is random from the perspective of the individual trajectory.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par47">(iii): 
     <span class="italic">Fractality induced tipping</span> happens when the scenario-dependent basins exhibit fractal structures. These lead to non-monotonicities of tipping probabilites.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par48">(iv): 
     <span class="italic">Transient-reduced tipping</span> is found when the observation time of a tipping process is short, and observations of natural and technical processes always face this problem, tipping probabilities will be underestimated. This effect is found to be strongest if the transients are chaotic and long-lived.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the novel phenomena found are due to the topological complexity underlying typical dynamical systems. Therefore we expect these to appear in all four disciplines mentioned in the introduction: climate science, ecology, disease spreading, and engineering applications. Since chaotic transients are known to possibly have very long lifetimes in high-dimensional systems as e.g. spatio-temporal systems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> and/or systems possessing a large multitude of coexisting attractors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>, the tipping phenomena described here might play a relevant role in such cases, too. Finally, we emphasize that the essence of these novel types of tipping phenomena can best be understood in terms of snapshot attractors associated with the drifting dynamics determined by the scenario in question.
 </p>
</sec>
