<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snapshot attractors</div>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The traditional view on tipping is based on cases where the system dwells on a single (regular) attractor and ends on another attractor. Tipping in this view means that there exists in the ramped system at least one trajectory that starts on one attractor and ends outside the continuation of this attractor at the end of the parameter drift. In typical systems, however, one has to allow for a broader picture, in which snapshot attractors play an important role.</p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature on the investigation of chaotic-like systems with parameter drifts indicates the need of the use of 
  <span class="italic">ensemble</span> approaches
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span> because individual trajectories prove to be not representative. This view has also been applied to many-degrees-of-freedom systems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>, and to experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>. The unifying concept beyond these approaches is that of snapshot attractors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span> (also called pullback attractors in the mathematics and climate-related literature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>
  </span>). Loosely speaking, a snapshot attractor is an object belonging to a given time instant that is traced out by an 
  <span class="italic">ensemble</span> of trajectories initialized in some chosen region of the state space in the past, with all of the ensemble members governed by the same equation of motion. Due to dissipation, the ensemble rapidly forgets the initial conditions, and the snapshot attractor is reached, from a practical point of view, after a typically short period of time. The case where two or more snapshot attractors coexist (multistability of snapshot attractors) is of special interest. The investigations of Pierini 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span> provide the first example for the coexistence of a chaotic and a periodic snapshot attractor. In this problem, however, the parameter scenario is that of an irregular temporal oscillation about a mean, and the phenomenon of tipping has not been investigated.
 </p>
</sec>
