<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">With our simulation experiments, we want to test how sensitive the model outcomes in Cobben and Van Noordwijk (
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) are to different model starting conditions (initializations) and abrupt changes in environmental conditions during the model run, inspired by projected conditions under climate change. Table 
 <xref rid="ece33357-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref> summarizes all relevant model parameters, their meanings, and the standard values used for the simulations. We investigated different climate change scenarios, first by different model initializations, both regarding number and location of individuals, and the genetic threshold values 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. The initialization with individuals at low 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic>‐values simulates a range expansion across the landscape starting from migratory populations only, while initialization at high 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic>‐values investigates an expanding range from residential populations. A lack of genetic diversity for threshold values 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> could potentially change the model outcome, so we contrasted situations where diversity at initialization was either maximum or zero, with zero genetic diversity divided into two sets: 
 <italic class="italic">T </italic>=
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.5 and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> is fitted. Fitted 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> means 
 <italic class="italic">T </italic>=
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.1 for residents and 
 <italic class="italic">T </italic>=
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.9 for migrants. In these fitted 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> scenarios, the species’ range expanded from either side of the landscape, with the initial 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> being strongly adapted to the local conditions at the extreme ends of the landscape. In addition, we investigated several abruptly changing environmental conditions after model initialization, leading to either changing survival or reproduction probabilities. Such changes could cause disruptions in previous model outcome by selecting for a different equilibrium, which we tested by subjecting residential individuals to 20% increased survival, assuming warmer winters, or 20% decreased survival assuming changes in timing of peak food causing a phenotypic mismatch with timing of breeding. Migratory individuals experienced 20% decreased reproductive success, assuming mistiming of arrival at the breeding grounds after spring migration. Table 
 <xref rid="ece33357-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">2</xref> summarizes all the different scenario options. From these, we constructed a set of relevant combinations, resulting in 24 different scenarios (for a full scenario overview see Table 
 <xref rid="ece33357-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>). Changing survival and reproduction conditions were implemented 300 years after the start of the model run, when demographic equilibrium was reached. The only exceptions to this are the scenarios implemented with populations initialized across the landscape in combination with zero genetic diversity, in order to prevent genetic diversity from increasing before changing conditions were applied. For each scenario, we performed 100 replicate simulations.
</p>
