<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb12978-sec-0012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Advancing ocean change research</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study of ocean change is a rapidly growing field. We set out to review differences in approaches across marine disciplines that affect the collective interpretation of climate‐associated changes in the ocean. Our review specifically focuses on literature that is most frequently cited to identify research that shapes the current discourse on ocean change. We highlight a rich body of literature that indicates a suite of biological responses accompany several signals of physical and chemical changes occurring in the global ocean. By looking across disciplinary distinctions in sampling approaches for ocean change, we simultaneously emphasize previously identified issues as well as distinguish avenues for future research in both abiotic and biological realms. Our key results suggest that the current discourse on ocean change is sparser for: Southern Hemisphere ocean basins (notably the Indian, South Pacific, and South Atlantic basins), understudied marine taxa (archaea, bacteria, viruses, mangroves and turtles) and oceanographic properties (OA and dissolved oxygen, especially outside of laboratory manipulations), specific physical and chemical stressor effects on biota (dissolved oxygen, salinity, and upwelling), and biological responses of climate‐driven ocean change (evolutionary adaptation). We have shown that it is imperative to consider the statistical limitations associated with relatively short duration, small‐scale, and low‐resolution datasets when inferring broadscale signals of change, but also which datasets are applicable to the life history and population dynamics of target species. We invite future ocean change researchers studying biological systems to consider carefully the temporal (sampling duration and frequency) and spatial scales (study area) required to detect change beyond the level of an individual and establish critical baseline data. While broader‐scale studies are expected to have greater statistical power and confidence, we also urge biological researchers to consider and standardize measures of species generation times and proportion of the home range studied to enable comparable investigations at biologically relevant scales. Identification of disciplinary distinctions, similarities, and areas lacking scientific research with respect to climate‐mediated ocean change should facilitate cohesive research approaches and syntheses of observed impacts on the global ocean as well as more accurate forecasts for the future.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Calls for adaptive, ecosystem‐based, and interdisciplinary approaches in marine sciences are now commonplace (e.g., Edwards 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0023">2010</a>; Lester 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0051">2010</a>; Lubchenco &amp; Sutley, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0054">2010</a>), yet best practices for integrative studies have been elusive (Samhouri 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0084">2013</a>). The comparative cross‐disciplinary approach taken in this paper and our ability to identify the associated effects on the interpretation of climate impacts in marine systems were possible because of an interdisciplinary early‐career training program. Syntheses, such as this one, that consider biotic and abiotic marine disciplines in concert are rare. The institutional structure to train interdisciplinary students in the conduct and design of crosscutting studies remains deficient and requires increased, continuing support (Christie, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0010">2011</a>). As noted in Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>), we have yet to fully understand how single‐species or ocean processes will reorganize ecosystems and communities under climate change. Concerted efforts to improve interdisciplinary education at early‐career stages will provide future researchers with a necessary foundation for integrating and comparing disciplinary differences, and funding of early‐career interdisciplinary training should be continued and strengthened. Our study provides a novel example of how cross‐disciplinary research allowed for a comprehensive assessment of contemporary ocean change research that highlighted new research gaps and recommendations for future comparative research.
 </p>
</sec>
