<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb12978-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological responses to physical and chemical stressors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our review indicates a strong reliance on laboratory experimentation to estimate biological responses to physical and chemical marine changes that occur in the field. This is particularly true for plankton and benthic invertebrates that are more easily cultivated and maintained in laboratory settings compared to large or highly mobile vertebrates. Laboratory studies typically are performed at small spatial and temporal scales and under controlled conditions that are not capable of mimicking the complexity of natural environments. For instance, over half of the biological papers considering OA effects on organisms were conducted in the laboratory because seawater chemistry can be manipulated more easily in a controlled environment. However, OA expresses complicated natural patterns of variability (Hofmann 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0040">2011</a>) and is poorly replicated in experimental biological response studies due to covariation with factors like temperature, oxygen, and salinity (Reum 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0076">2014</a>). Short‐term controlled studies of biological responses to chemical changes can provide direct measures of organismal responses; however, these studies are not easily scaled up or extrapolated to long‐term or ecosystem‐level effects (Wahl 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0089">2015</a>), and there is generally low‐to‐medium confidence in assessing the tolerance of many marine taxa to future CO
  <sub>2</sub> levels (Pörtner 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature was also frequently studied as a stressor under laboratory examination: 19% of biological responses considered temperature a primary stressor. Temperature in the ocean has been sampled widely for extended durations, and our results suggest that it is a readily available covariate in biological response studies. Despite being easy to sample, temperature may not always be the most ecologically meaningful stressor affecting a given marine species (Robinson 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0080">2011</a>). Instead, the physical or chemical factors most relevant to an organism or system of interest may be the best focus of examination. For example, changing temperature regimes may have little direct impact on warm‐blooded marine mammals, seabirds, and fish (e.g., tuna and some sharks) that maintain body temperatures above ambient conditions. On the other hand, marine reptiles like sea turtles have temperature‐dependent sex determination, such that increased nesting temperatures could bias sex ratios within populations (Hawkes 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0032">2009</a>). Thus, temperature was not surprisingly the most frequently studied stressor and, most appropriate, for marine turtle reproductive studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature may be a key factor interacting with other important abiotic mechanisms that warrant simultaneous investigation. Sensitivity to changing thermal regimes may set the physiological limits for responses by some marine species, but other factors like oxygen, acidity, upwelling, and salinity can also complicate predictions of climate impacts (Pörtner 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). For example, a recent study demonstrated the importance of modeling interacting forces of acidification, temperature, and deoxygenation in understanding impacts on aerobic metabolic rates for teleost fishes (Del Raye &amp; Weng, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0014">2015</a>). Dissolved oxygen was rarely studied as a primary stressor in biological response studies despite being an important ecophysiological factor affecting many marine organisms (e.g., Dodds 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0016">2007</a>; Pörtner &amp; Knust, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0072">2007</a>; Froehlich 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0025">2015</a>) that is susceptible to climate variations (Deutsch 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0015">2011</a>). Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>) suggest that understanding the effects of declining oxygen concentrations is an emerging research need. Our study indicates that long‐term, high‐resolution data on dissolved oxygen are less available to researchers compared to data on temperature, which may contribute to the apparent lack of dissolved oxygen as a stressor in biological response studies. Similarly, climate‐related changes in salinity and upwelling can strongly influence primary productivity, as well as the abundance and distributions of marine organisms (Hays 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0033">2005</a>; Doney 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0020">2012</a>). Understanding changes in surface winds may be critical to understanding regional upwelling processes and how upwelling contributes to hypoxia at varying depths or other important ecosystem effects of ocean–atmosphere interactions (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Despite their regulatory influence on marine biota, salinity and upwelling were also poorly represented as primary stressors in our review of biological responses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is wide recognition in the literature of the importance of studying climate‐related responses to multiple stressors and their cumulative or synergistic impacts (e.g., Richardson &amp; Poloczanska, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0079">2008</a>; Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>; Pörtner 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). Nonetheless, few biological response studies considered the effects of more than two stressors, even though several environmental factors may covary in time or space. In addition, several nonclimate factors (e.g., commercial fishing, anthropogenic disturbance, pollution) may interact with and compound the effects of climate stressors. Distinguishing climate impacts from inherent variability and other drivers of change in marine systems can be complicated (Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0004">2011</a>; Doney &amp; Sailley, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0018">2013</a>), especially in the absence of long‐term records of physical or chemical variability (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Biological researchers should carefully consider other potential nonclimate factors (Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0004">2011</a>; Doney 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0020">2012</a>). Incorporation of alternative mechanisms can also improve confidence in the attribution of climate impacts on biological responses in marine environments (O'Connor 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0063">2015</a>). Despite increasing interest in ecosystem‐based management addressing interactions among multiple factors (e.g., Lester 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0051">2010</a>; Lubchenco &amp; Sutley, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0054">2010</a>), our findings suggest that, to date, the most highly cited ocean change research does not address multiple interacting stressors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Range and phenological shifts are among the most commonly cited effects of climate change on global biodiversity (e.g., Parmesan &amp; Yohe, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0066">2003</a>; Root 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0082">2003</a>; Chen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0008">2011</a>), but our review indicates that these types of biological responses are less frequently cited for the marine environment. Instead, our review of the highly cited contemporary literature and those of others (e.g., Wassmann 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0090">2011</a>; Poloczanska 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>) found that researchers most frequently studied changes in abundance or demography. Studies of marine range and phenological shifts have historically been disregarded and received lesser funding than those in terrestrial systems, the effects of which were amplified because marine ecologists did not always adopt the principles and standardizations used by terrestrial ecologists (Richardson &amp; Poloczanska, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0079">2008</a>). Our current understanding of marine range shifts is largely consistent with climate change (e.g., Pinsky 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0070">2013</a>; Poloczanska 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>; Wisz 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0093">2015</a>), but uncertainty remains regarding which species are shifting and the resulting impacts to ecosystems and communities (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Strict selection criteria, such as the exclusion of single‐species studies that could impose positive publication bias, can also impact the strength of conclusions about marine range shifts and changes in phenology (Parmesan, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0065">2007</a>; Przeslawski 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0074">2012</a>). Range shifts must also be put into the context of localized climate changes, which may not necessarily be consistent with global patterns and could be multidimensional (e.g., latitude and depth), to consider overall species persistence (Lenoir &amp; Svenning, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0050">2015</a>). Although projections for future distributions of marine species exist (e.g., Cheung 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0009">2009</a>; Hazen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0034">2013</a>; Jones &amp; Cheung, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0043">2014</a>), long‐term, corroborating observations necessary to detect contemporary shifts in species distribution appear to be rare in marine ecosystems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physiological responses were also frequently studied by the papers in our review, often in the laboratory and particularly for benthic communities. Of the 168 articles considering physiological responses, 63% investigated how OA was affecting processes like nutrient uptake or metabolism (phytoplankton, fish, seagrasses, kelp), tissue damage (fish), and calcification (rocky shore invertebrates, corals). Our findings suggest this focus on physiological effects is related to the recent proliferation of research on the effects of OA on marine species, especially calcifying organisms or those reliant on calcifiers (Orr 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0064">2005</a>; Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0038">2007</a>; Fabry 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0024">2008</a>; Doney 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0019">2009</a>). Despite this focus on physiological responses, research on how other stressors interact with OA and potentially nonlinear biological responses is still needed (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our review of highly cited marine biological responses yielded only one paper (i.e., Lohbeck 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0053">2012</a>) explicitly studying evolutionary implications of ocean change. Changes in gene frequency, via processes such as evolutionary or genetic rescue, are an increasingly recognized response to climate change (Carlson 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0006">2014</a>). The persistence of populations experiencing environmental change has been linked to individual performance regarding phenotypic plasticity, dispersal, and/or adaptive evolution (Merilä &amp; Hendry, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0061">2014</a>), which can be categorized as acclimatization, colonization, adaptation, or extinction (O'Connor 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0062">2012</a>). We documented population‐level responses corresponding to acclimatization (i.e., phenological, behavioral, diet, and physiological responses), colonization (i.e., distribution shifts), and avoidance of extinction (i.e., via reproductive or demographic responses) in the highly cited marine literature. In contrast, we found a general lack of studies on adaptations (i.e., changes in gene frequency), except for a selection study conducted on multiple generations of a coccolithophore in the laboratory (Lohbeck 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0053">2012</a>). However, we reviewed no studies confirming adaptive evolution in the wild. Attribution of genetic changes to climate forcing requires intensive common‐garden experiments or genetic time series that are rarely done or available, especially for long‐lived or large‐bodied species. The evidence for adaptive evolution in response to climate change, whether marine or terrestrial, is actually quite rare (Gienapp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0027">2008</a>). Rather, phenotypic plasticity is more apparent than adaptation (Hendry 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0035">2008</a>) and has been investigated for marine species (e.g., Reed 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0075">2009</a>; Kelly 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0044">2011a</a>). Ultimately, future marine research could more acutely focus on the adaptive abilities of marine species to cope with changing conditions in order to better understand future population viability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social science disciplines also warrant focus in studies of ocean change and are highly relevant to considerations of current and future changes in the marine environment. Although beyond the scope of our review, marine climate change clearly affects social systems and how individuals and communities are responding to ocean change (e.g., McCay 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0059">2011</a>; Pinsky &amp; Fogarty, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0069">2012</a>; Lauer 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0049">2013</a>). A growing body of literature is developing to assess the effects of ocean changes on social–ecological systems. Like the other papers reviewed here, this literature varies greatly in terms of temporal and spatial scales and themes addressed. A notable difference between the social–ecological literature and the papers reviewed in this study is that the former tends to focus on projected responses and how ocean change will influence human society in the future (e.g., Cooley &amp; Doney, 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0012">2009</a>; Kelly 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0045">2011b</a>), whereas the latter tends to address changes that have already occurred. Thus, these social–ecological studies introduce another set of spatial and temporal scales as well as levels of complexity, moving beyond climate change impacts to marine biodiversity but also to human societies associated with the ocean.
 </p>
</sec>
