<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we presented for the first time the local impact assessment and adaptation study of climate change on a plant disease epidemic using the integrated modeling approach with multiple models. The resulting high-resolution maps for future KBB epidemics, in particular, will ensure and enhance the usability of our results in the development of local government policies and adaptation strategies for local communities (
 <xref rid="b40-ppj-35-459" ref-type="bibr">Roberts, 2008</xref>). Using the Climate Suitability Model for kiwifruit, we found that suitable areas for kiwifruit cultivation in Jeonnam province gradually increase over future periods. Through adoption of the Pss-KBB Risk Model and linking it with the Chill-day Model, we also revealed that as the flowering dates of kiwifruit became earlier through 2100, the potential risk of severe epidemics of KBB resulted in location-specific, periodic fluctuations in future periods. Notably, KBB risks throughout Jeonnam province continued to increase and peaked in the 2060s, then drastically decreased in the 2080s, a shift that was highly correlated with corresponding climatic conditions. To relieve future KBB pressures, a potential, scientifically-informed, long-term adaptation strategy using a cultivar of kiwifruit with a different maturity period was investigated using the integrated modeling solution, resulting in the identification of the Haegeum cultivar as an alternative kiwifruit vine that will experience less KBB pressure over the coming decades. As this kind of integrated modeling platforms are developed and continuously improved with more quality-controlled data and more reliable modeling algorithms, local policymakers and stakeholders will be able to prepare more realistic, rational adaptation strategies to cope with the upcoming threats of climate change based on the evidence-based scientific results. To ensure this, there are many follow-up researches necessary in the near future, as our results directly point that urgent necessity.
</p>
