<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="ijerph-16-04594-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijerph-16-04594-t002_Table 2</object-id>
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Content of the focus group discussion and in-depth interview.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area of Discussion</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Types of Prompts Used</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perception on the occurrence of maternal death and natural disaster</td>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Did any maternal deaths occur here? 
     <break/>Why and when did the maternal deaths occur in this area? 
     <break/>Were any natural disasters observed? 
     <break/>When did the disasters occur here? 
     <break/>What types of disaster occur here? 
     <break/>Does the disaster occur regularly, and what is the duration of the disaster?
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Practices of maternal healthcare during natural disaster</td>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How is maternal healthcare provided during a disaster? 
     <break/>What preparation is there during pregnancy and delivery complications at the time of a disaster?
     <break/>What do the community people do during complication at a disaster?
     <break/>Where do they go during maternal complications, and how? 
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barrier of the marginalized community to practices on maternal care during disaster</td>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What are the challenges for maternal care during a disaster?
     <break/>What are the types of obstacles faced during the referral of a risky mother? 
     <break/>Was the referral of a mother ever delayed, and why?
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relation of maternal death with natural disaster</td>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is maternal death influenced by natural disaster? 
     <break/>How does natural disaster cause maternal death (with example)?
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recommendation and initiatives to prevent maternal death during disaster</td>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">How can maternal deaths during natural disasters be prevented? 
     <break/>What initiatives can be taken by the community people to overcome such a situation? 
     <break/>What are the recommendations to increase maternal healthcare during a disaster?
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
