<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">West Nile Virus (WNV), which infects birds, humans, horses, and other mammals, is the most widely distributed encephalitic flavivirus. WNV is mainly transmitted by 
 <italic class="italic">Culex</italic> mosquitoes in all continents, except Antarctica. Many studies have already discussed the importance of weather and climate in driving WNV epidemics.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" class="xref">140</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0141" ref-type="ref" class="xref">141</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0142" ref-type="ref" class="xref">142</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" class="xref">143</xref> WNV has circulated in Africa since the 1930s and first appeared in New York City in the United States in 1999. WNV rapidly spread to four northeastern U.S. states, finally reaching California during summer 2003.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" class="xref">144</xref> Circulation in humans and horses was reported in the western Mediterranean region and southern Russia in the early 1960s, Belarus and Ukraine in the 1970s and 1980s, and a large WNV outbreak was reported in 1996–97 in Romania, followed by another epidemic wave in Russia in 1999.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0145" ref-type="ref" class="xref">145</xref> Large WNV epidemics were subsequently reported in Russia during the late 2000s
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0146" ref-type="ref" class="xref">146</xref> and in the Balkan area in the early 2010s. Milder winter conditions, combined with droughts during the boreal spring season, were associated with increased risk of WNV transmission by urban mosquitoes in the United States.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0141" ref-type="ref" class="xref">141</xref> Extreme rainfall events were also associated with increased risk of WNV transmission. Given that the extrinsic incubation period of WNV in 
 <italic class="italic">Culex</italic> mosquitoes shortens significantly when temperature increases,
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">14</xref> climate change will undoubtedly impact future WNV epidemics.
</p>
