<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Second, abiotic and biotic differences among areas also may contribute to differential performance under drought. In particular, smaller amounts of precipitation in drought years may be more available in coarse cinder soils where infiltration is rapid (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Looney et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Peterman et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kolb, 2015</xref>). Supplemental watering during drought had a larger positive impact on 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> growing in young, coarse volcanic soil than in older soils derived from the same parent material (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Looney et al., 2012</xref>). These data, and ours, are consistent with the “inverse texture hypothesis” of 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Noy-Meir (1973)</xref> which proposes that plants growing in coarse-textured soil experience less water stress than plants growing in fine-textured soil because precipitation is more readily lost from the surface of fine-textured soils via evaporation and/or runoff. 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sala et al. (1989)</xref> suggested a cut-off for reversal of the soil texture effect at 370 mm of precipitation per year that suggests the potential for year-to-year changes in the effects of soil texture on performance. Interactions with soil microbes also vary with soils, drought, and stress in 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring and Whitham, 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring et al., 1998</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Swaty et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gordon and Gehring, 2011</xref>) and can have important effects on tree performance (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Ectomycorrhizal fungi of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Geopora</italic> promoted drought tolerance in 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>) and dominated on cinder soils both prior to and during drought (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gordon and Gehring, 2011</xref>), but were uncommon in non-cinder soils, including area two (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring et al., 1998</xref>). Thus, variation across the landscape in mycorrhizal symbiont interactions could contribute to variation in drought tolerance, alone or in conjunction with pinyon genetic variation and soil moisture properties.
</p>
