<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7" class="p">Although some of the SU presented in this study have been observed in the Karoo Basin by previous workers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>, they were interpreted as having a purely tectonic origin as uplift leads to increased stream gradients, sediment input, and accommodation proximal to the source area
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. However, climatic, and tectonic signatures are shown to overprint one another during the onset and aftermath of the Permo-Triassic mass extinction event (PTME)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup>. This study provides some evidence that climatic changes associated with the PTME were occurring much lower in the stratigraphy than previously documented. Thus it is concluded the third-order tectonic SU could be overprinted by these palaeoclimatic changes. This is supported by a newly identified faunal turnover and abundance changes marked by the appearance of 
 <italic class="italic">Lystrosaurus maccaigi</italic> and disappearance of 
 <italic class="italic">Dicynodon lacerticeps</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Theriognathus microps</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Procynosuchus delaharpeae</italic> in this SU. Palaeoclimatic changes at the point of the third-order SU in the 
 <italic class="italic">Daptocephalus</italic> Assemblage Zone are identified by a decrease in the occurrence of subaqueous environments in the overbank facies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, distal attenuation of the Balfour Formation towards the north indicates there was more accommodation for sediment proximally, and point to more non-deposition distally during the Late Permian
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. Although this faunal turnover is not identified at the base of the SU in the Beaufort West field site, it implies that the third-order SU is diachronous. Diachroneity has been identified at major lithostratigraphic boundaries of the Karoo Supergroup, such as the Ecca-Beaufort contact, Katberg-Burgersdorp contact, and Burgersdorp-Molteno contact
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup> and is evidence of tectonic influences controlling sediment distribution in the foredeep.
</p>
