<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Finally, although management responses can more than offset the projected direct effects of climate change on fisheries to create a more prosperous global future, there are three important qualifiers to this optimistic note. First, there are other potential direct (for example, acidification and other challenges to ocean productivity) and indirect (for example, novel species interactions) impacts of climate change that are not addressed by this analysis. These impacts will be important for assessing climate effects on fisheries at the local scale. Second, not everyone will share in these benefits. Globally, profits, yields, and biomass could increase, but for about half of the world’s individual fisheries, this better future appears unattainable. Even under the most optimistic scenario for human responses, roughly half of the world’s fisheries are projected to decline under a moderate climate change scenario (RCP 6.0). Most latitudes in the tropics are not expected to obtain higher profits in the future compared to today under RCP 6.0 even with fully adaptive management (fig. S9). The distribution of winners and losers warrants considerably more attention to anticipate and potentially offset the likely food and livelihood losses that could ensue. Finally, future outcomes depend critically on the pace and magnitude of climate change. Under the most extreme scenario, RCP 8.5, both profit and harvest decline relative to today even under the most optimistic assumptions about global fisheries management reforms. This result highlights the fact that the future of fisheries will depend largely on activities that occur outside of the fishing industry and the importance of greenhouse gas emission mitigation (
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">28</italic>
 </xref>). For fisheries to realize their potential, it is critical for the global community to reduce global greenhouse gas emissions; otherwise, even the most ambitious fishery reforms will fall short. Therefore, a more prosperous future for fisheries depends on both mitigation of climate change and proactive fisheries management reforms.
</p>
