<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To guide effective management, climate adaptation actions must be tailored to individual or multiple vulnerability factors. It is not enough to know that a species or region is vulnerable to climate change, we must know why it is vulnerable to derive a sensible on-ground management strategy. Mapping the spatial distribution of the species affected by the various climate change vulnerability factors, as we have done here, is a crucial first step in designing effective actions. Our results revealed enormous variation in the spatial distribution of species affected by different climate change vulnerability factors, as well as substantial taxonomic heterogeneity in climate change vulnerability and its drivers.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nearly half of the threatened species comprising our sample were vulnerable to climate change. The most vulnerable was the mountain pygmy possum, and consideration of its life history reveals a series of complex interacting factors. It is a specialist species, with low genetic variation in some populations, having undergone a significant range contraction since the last glacial maximum when it occurred throughout most of south-eastern Australia [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref039">39</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref040">40</a>], and is now further threatened by habitat loss with the ongoing development of ski resorts, in addition to a variety of other threats. The only Australian mammal confined to the Australian Alps bioregion, the species is dependent on winter snow cover and cool temperatures [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref041">41</a>]. Mountain pygmy possums are already responding to climate change by waking earlier from hibernation, which has led to food shortages through temporal uncoupling with the emergence of bogong moths (
  <span class="italic">Agrotis infusa</span>), a key post-winter food source [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref041">41</a>]. Alpine species and habitats in general may be more at risk because of the limited options for adjustment of the geographic distribution in response to a changing climate [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref042">42</a>]. Using bioclimatic modelling, Brereton et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref001">1</a>] predicted that the mountain pygmy possum would be driven extinct by a 1°C rise in temperature, and given the species current restricted distribution, it remains to be seen whether the species will survive the coming decades.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the other end of the vulnerability scale was the western quoll, a generalist species in its dietary and habitat requirements. Despite a severe range contraction because of habitat clearance and predation from feral species, the western quoll has a high dispersal capacity and the greatest genetic variation of all quoll species [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref043">43</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref044">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change vulnerability increases strongly as geographic range size declines. This could arise in part because threatened species that have already been heavily affected by habitat loss and fragmentation are now at increased climate change vulnerability through low genetic variation (due to population declines) or specific habitat requirements forcing the species into small fragments of their former range [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref045">45</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref047">47</a>]. Another explanation is that some life history traits associated with high climate change vulnerability are also related to narrow geographic range size, for example habitat specialists that survive only in naturally uncommon landscapes or microhabitats [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref048">48</a>]. Regardless of the mechanism, our finding that the most narrowly distributed species are also the most vulnerable to climate change suggests that urgent actions are needed to help these species in particular adapt to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In agreement with other studies [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref049">49</a>], we found that amphibians were the most climate change vulnerable group, with heavy reliance on local moisture regimes and aquatic habitats that are likely to be negatively impacted by climate change. Altered interactions with chytrid fungus (
  <span class="italic">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</span>) and cane toads (
  <span class="italic">Bufo marinus</span>) due to rising temperatures are listed as key threats to Australian amphibians, where cane toads may further expand their range and the distribution of chytrid fungus may shift to new areas [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref014">14</a>]. Plants were the second most vulnerable taxon out of the sample of species we assessed, often constrained in their distribution by physiological factors such as a reliance on a particular soil type, relatively poor dispersal ability and low genetic variation through small population size [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref047">47</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref050">50</a>]. Unlike plants, many birds are excellent dispersers and often with less restrictive habitat requirements, rendering them the least vulnerable taxonomic group in this analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results revealed great spatial variation in the proportion of species affected by each of the major factors driving climate change vulnerability among our sample of threatened species. Species in each region were affected by different numbers and types of factors, and groups of factors appeared to operate in concert among species in different regions. The results from this study also suggest that the indices need to be decomposed into their constituent elements before they can usefully guide management actions. Comparing two different regions illustrates this point clearly. The predominant factors driving the climate change vulnerability of species along the south-east coastline of Australia are a reliance on particular disturbance regimes and low genetic variation, they are also exposed to sea level rise, anthropogenic barriers, and natural barriers comprising the ocean and the Great Dividing Range. In contrast, upper Northern Territory is predominantly impacted by reliance on particular disturbance regimes, low genetic variation, reliance on particular moisture regimes and reliance on other species for pollination. These regions will require a suite of actions that target different factors driving vulnerability to climate change. On a species level, management can become even more complicated, with some species having multiple factors contributing to their climate change vulnerability, highlighting the need to decompose vulnerability to explore the contributing factors. A good example of this is the Nielsen Park she-oak (
  <span class="italic">Allocasuarina portuensis</span>), which only exists as a tiny reintroduced population in Sydney’s eastern suburbs. As well as by its extremely small global population size of only a few dozen individuals, this species is affected by five different climate change vulnerability factors: limited dispersal ability, reliance on a particular soil type, low genetic variation, is surrounded by natural and anthropogenic barriers and is an obligate seed regenerator, i.e. dependent on fire to kill the adult tree and release new seed, therefore careful management of all these factors is required [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref051">51</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Management can also be targeted towards specific factors. For example amphibian species richness is largely concentrated along the south-east coastline of Australia, which makes reliance on particular moisture regimes or habitats a significant vulnerability factor there. Species affected by low genetic variation or recent population bottlenecks are prevalent along the coastline of south and south-east Australia, in both fragmented and undisturbed areas (
  <a rid="pone.0124766.g003" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0124766.g003">Fig 3h</a>). Many species in these regions have undergone major range contractions through habitat destruction and the introduction of invasive species, though their distributions once extended much further north [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref014">14</a>]. For example, the South Australian glossy black-cockatoo (
  <span class="italic">Calyptorhynchus lathami halmaturinus</span>) once occurred in mainland South Australia, but is now restricted to Kangaroo Island owing to mainland habitat clearance [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref052">52</a>]. Numbers dropped to as low as 158 birds in 1995, though the population had recovered to around 320 birds in 2006, which is suggestive of a recent bottleneck [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref052">52</a>] potentially increasing its vulnerability to climate change. More generally, dependence on a particular disturbance regime that is likely to change with climate (e.g. fire), is driving climate change vulnerability throughout eastern South Australia, Victoria, western New South Wales and the south coast of Western Australia. In Australia, many species are reliant on appropriate fire regimes for reproduction and habitat. For example, the abundance of the Pilliga mouse (
  <span class="italic">Pseudomys pilligaensis</span>) increases fivefold in fire-induced regrowth forest (18–24 months post fire) in comparison with mature forest (&gt;20years) and 28-fold in the intermediate growth stage [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref053">53</a>]. Studies have found that populations peak 20–24 months post fire and following an above average rainfall year, though as with many opportunistic breeders, the population then declines rapidly [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref054">54</a>]. However, mature forest is required for breeding habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref053">53</a>]. Fires are expected to become more frequent, intense and erratic as a result of climate change in Australia [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref043">43</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref055">55</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref057">57</a>]. Reliance on specific moisture regimes is a major factor in north-eastern Queensland and in upper Western Australia and Northern Territory. For example, the western partridge pigeon (
  <span class="italic">Geophaps smithii blaauwi</span>) depends on a reliable water source for survival during the late dry season [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref058">58</a>], and reductions in rainfall and increasing temperatures as a result of climate change could pose a serious risk.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once the drivers of climate change vulnerability are known for species, management actions can be derived (
  <a rid="pone.0124766.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0124766.s005">S4 Table</a>). Actions associated with reducing vulnerability for small bodied species such as amphibians include the installation of microhabitat refuges and restoration and manipulation of moisture levels at breeding sites [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref059">59</a>]. Artificially changing the habitat and local microclimate to be more suitable for amphibians may give them the best chance of surviving climate change. Often dispersal limited, some species may be best assisted by translocation and, in the case of plants, by replanting of seedlings at new climatically suitable sites [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref060">60</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref061">61</a>]. In some cases, it may be most cost effective to establish captive populations, as has recently been attempted for orange-bellied parrots [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref062">62</a>]. It is also important to consider whether these actions will take place in protected areas, where because of shelter from other threats, there is a stronger chance of success [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref063">63</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis has revealed multiple drivers of climate change vulnerability for many of Australia’s threatened species and in many regions of Australia, suggesting that different actions will be needed in different areas and highlighting the need for a spatial prioritisation of conservation actions and focal areas. Though this sample provides a good reflection of many of Australia’s threatened flora and fauna, a full assessment of all threatened species would be worth pursuing. It is critical that recovery and management plans for threatened species are updated to include climate change vulnerability and its implications. Spatially linking actions to climate change vulnerability factors is the most direct way to improve the chance of species surviving climate change, because understanding the spatial distribution of each factor helps to spatially prioritise actions to benefit the largest number of species, making it more cost effective than considering only single species. For example, introducing a specific pollinator will only help conserve a single dependent species and is likely to be expensive, could cause unintended side effects, and might have low feasibility. On the other hand, an action such as restoration of a major vegetation type could provide benefits for multiple species. Formal analyses based on decision science will be necessary to choose among the many possible climate adaptation actions, and it will be important to consider the costs and benefits of particular actions, and how human adaptation to climate change drives future habitat loss through land use change. Given the accelerating rate of climate change and habitat loss in the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century, no time should be spared in planning and implementing on-ground actions to get threatened species ready to face climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
