<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exposure</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a proxy for species’ direct exposure to climate change we used projections of mean annual temperature and mean annual moisture index under the IPCC A1F1 scenario, in which the world remains heavily reliant on fossil fuels [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref031">31</a>] for the time horizon 2050 (
  <a rid="pone.0124766.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0124766.s002">S1 Table</a>). Climatic layers were generated using the software package ANUCLIM (v6.1), based on a 9-second digital elevation model for Australia. Adapting the scheme given in Young et al [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref026">26</a>] for an Australian context, we categorised projected change in annual mean temperature and change in mean annual moisture index according to the categories in 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0124766.s002">S1 Table</a>. A change of 0–1°C was scored as category 1, whereas a change greater than 2.25°C was scored as category 5. We then calculated the proportion of each species’ current distribution that would be affected by the different magnitudes of climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indirect exposure was assessed by estimating the extent to which each species’ current geographic distribution overlaps natural and anthropogenic barriers, or regions affected by sea level rise (
  <a rid="pone.0124766.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0124766.s003">S2 Table</a>). As some species are expected to track suitable climatic conditions beyond their current distribution through dispersal, it is anticipated that species surrounded by natural and anthropogenic barriers will have greater difficulty tracking a changing climate [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref032">32</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref033">33</a>]. Natural barriers were major water bodies (oceans and inland lakes), areas devoid of vegetation, and highlands across the continent. We extracted features categorised as ‘water’ or ‘bare ground’ from the United States Geological Survey Global Land Cover 2000 dataset (v.1; [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref034">34</a>]), and combined these with the distribution of land greater than 700m above sea level, based on a global digital elevation model at 30m spatial resolution from the National Geophysical Data Center of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref035">35</a>]. Anthropogenic barriers were approximated by mapping the distribution of urban, cultivated and managed land uses from the Global Land Cover 2000 dataset [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref034">34</a>]. These features represent land converted in cities, urban areas and farmland, which will act as dispersal barriers for many threatened species. Proximity to natural and anthropogenic barriers was calculated by defining a 50km buffer [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref026">26</a>] around each species’ current geographic distribution and overlaying this onto the distributions of the barriers to calculate the proportion of the buffer that overlaps with barriers (
  <a rid="pone.0124766.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0124766.s003">S2 Table</a>). Species for which anthropogenic barriers were unlikely to represent a dispersal barrier (e.g. many birds, such as the Tasmanian wedge-tailed eagle 
  <span class="italic">Aquila audax fleayi</span>) were scored as neutral (N) for this factor.
 </p>
</sec>
