<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial distribution of climate change vulnerability</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We mapped separately the distribution of the species that are affected by each factor driving climate change vulnerability. A species was considered to be affected by a particular sensitivity factor if it was scored as ‘somewhat increased vulnerability’ (SIV) or higher for that factor, indicating that this factor is contributing to the species overall vulnerability. For indirect exposure factors, the species was only considered affected if it was scored as ‘increased vulnerability’ (IV) or higher. The rationale behind this is that indirect exposure factors (eg. sea level rise or natural barriers) generally affect a species only in some parts of its range and are not range-wide. Only including those species that were scored as at least IV, ensured that a large portion of their range was affected by an indirect exposure factor.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The distribution of species affected by the vulnerability factors were mapped using the bioregions of the Interim Biogeographic Regionalisation of Australia (IBRA, v6.1), the landscape divisions used for national conservation planning in Australia [
  <a rid="pone.0124766.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0124766.ref037">37</a>]. A factor was considered to be present in a given bioregion if 10% or more of the range of a species affected by that factor fell within it. Each factor was mapped separately showing the percentage of species affected by it in each bioregion, thus accounting for the different number of species present in the different bioregions. Because a species is only scored for either ‘genetic variation’ or ‘signs of recent bottlenecks’ (see 
  <a rid="pone.0124766.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0124766.t001">Table 1</a>) these were merged for spatial analysis under ‘low genetic variation’. The major factor driving vulnerability for any given bioregion was the one that affected the largest percentage of species.
 </p>
</sec>
