<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23" class="p">The Interior West Forest Inventory and Analysis (IW-FIA) Program encompasses the states of Arizona, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Utah, and Wyoming, U.S.A. Tree-ring data used in this study originated from two inventory designs, periodic (late-1980s – 2001), in which a state was typically inventoried over a period of a few years and not revisited again for a decade or more, and annual (2000 to present), in which the systematic grid of plots is divided into equal, interpenetrating panels of plots that are measured on a continuous 10-year rotation in the interior western states. While periodic FIA inventories covered all forest types in the Interior West at high spatial density (i.e., generally no spatial bias), they were not temporally balanced. Different parts of a given state were measured over the course of a periodic inventory, and different states were inventoried at different times. The current and ongoing FIA annual design is also geographically unbiased, but the interpenetrating panel design simultaneously creates a temporally unbiased sample
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup> across the United States. This sampling approach is designed to infer population-level estimates of the Nation’s forests
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> through the use of statistical estimators (e.g., forest area, tree volume, or trees per area) applied to plot-level representation, which is approximately one plot per 2428 ha
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. As part of the IW-FIA data collection program, a single increment core per tree was collected from a subset of trees on plots for the purpose of determining stand age, periodic growth rates, and potential productivity (see ref. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> for details). Cored trees represented the dominant species on the plot in terms of size (i.e., diameter) and forest type at each location. The number of trees cored per plot across the Interior West varied from one to as many as 14. For the three species in this study, the average number of cored trees per plot was 1.4. While the tree-ring data in this study have extraordinary spatial representation, our analysis is limited to series that were crossdatable (i.e., some samples were either too complacent or had too many missing rings for year assignments to be made with confidence), and this introduces some (but only minor) filtering of the original sample. We did not include cores from New Mexico in our analysis, because the processing (crossdating and measuring) of those samples is ongoing and cannot yet be considered representative. In total, we included 1670 Douglas-fir samples from 1239 plots, 1830 ponderosa pine samples from 1156 plots, and 717 common pinyon samples from 603 plots.
</p>
