<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mountain pine beetle (MPB) (
 <italic class="italic">Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic>) is a highly selective insect that chooses hosts based on a complex array of chemical cues whose production by the tree is influenced by both tree condition and genotype (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Emerick et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blomquist et al., 2010</xref>). Secondary metabolic chemicals produced by the tree are used by MPBs to distinguish among tree species as well as to assess the relative strength of defenses of individuals (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blomquist et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raffa et al., 2017</xref>). Such chemicals also likely signal adequacy of nutritional content for brood production given that beetles avoid hosts of very poor quality (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taylor et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dooley et al., 2015</xref>). Using such cues, a MPB will decide whether or not to enter a particular tree and initiate a mass attack. Once in the tree, the insect converts some terpenes to pheromones important in initiating and sustaining the mass attack required to kill the tree (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blomquist et al., 2010</xref>). When MPB populations are low to moderate in size, weakened trees with poor defenses that require fewer beetles to overcome defenses are most often attacked (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boone et al., 2011</xref>). However, during outbreaks, MPBs may switch to attacking healthier trees that, although better defended, possess thicker phloem and higher nutritional contents for brood development (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boone et al., 2011</xref>). Interestingly, some trees escape attack even when MPB populations are present in high numbers and suitable hosts become increasingly scarce.
</p>
