<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">MPB outbreaks are triggered by extended periods of warm weather and drought (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meddens et al., 2012</xref>). The recent MPB outbreak in western North America was a magnitude larger than any recorded in the past and affected millions of hectares of pine forest (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meddens et al., 2012</xref>). The outbreak was primarily driven by climate although its severity was intensified in some areas by past logging practices and fire suppression (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taylor et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Creeden et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Buotte et al., 2017</xref>). Climate change also supported movement of MPB further north in British Columbia and eastward across Alberta into naïve forests (those with no prior history of MPB) of lodgepole pine and jack pine (
 <italic class="italic">P. banksiana</italic>, a novel species for MPB) (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burke et al., 2017</xref>). While the size and extent of the recent outbreak was far outside the historic norm, outbreaks of MPB are not unusual and have likely occurred for millennia. Selection by MPB during outbreaks, as well as persistent low-level activity during non-outbreak periods, are believed to have been a major force shaping constitutive and induced defenses in host pines (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raffa and Berryman, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Franceschi et al., 2005</xref>). MPB activity in naïve forests can be expected to exert especially rapid and strong selection for host resistance because of high levels of susceptibility. Indeed, naïve lodgepole and jack pine forests exhibit lower defenses to MPB attack than those with a co-evolutionary history with the beetle (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clark et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cudmore et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raffa et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burke et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
