<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0035" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we captured and processed 53 species of birds, five were chosen for complete analysis because these species were most frequently captured and their life histories varied which may have altered exposure to vectors (e.g. foraging guild, migratory status) (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). These target species were the Northern Cardinal (
  <span class="italic">Cardinalis cardinalis</span>), Tufted Titmouse (
  <span class="italic">Baeolophus bicolor</span>), White-throated Sparrow (
  <span class="italic">Zonotrichia albicollis</span>), Carolina Wren (
  <span class="italic">Thryothorus ludovicianus</span>) and Indigo Bunting (
  <span class="italic">Passerina cyanea</span>). For measures in which the covariate “species” was not statistically important, we ran the analysis with the total number of species that were captured. All analyses were performed using the statistical software SAS/STAT, Version 9.3 (
  <a rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0260">SAS Institute, Inc., 2011</a>). Due to insufficient sample size of hatch-year and after-hatch-year birds, these two age classes were grouped together and compared to adults. Birds were also placed in three different foraging guilds: ground, low-middle and middle-upper canopy according to 
  <a rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0405">Sibley (2003)</a>. A significance level of 0.05 was used for all analyses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Logistic regression was used to model the probability of infection from particular parasites based on all available information (e.g., species, age, sex, capture location, BMI and breeding season). All haemoparasites included in the study were used individually as dependent variables in separate logistic regression models. Polychromasia and PCV were not included in this analysis because of large number of missing values for these variables. An ordinal logistic regression was used to model the probability of different levels of infection. The response variable in this case is number of infections, with 3 categories: 0 for no infection, 1 for only one parasite present, and 2 for more than one parasite present. We used an ordinal logistic regression in order to model the ordinal response variable of infection, which records the number of infections of a single bird as 0, 1, or greater than 1. Two models are then created in this type of analysis (one for predicting the probability of having infections with two or more groups of parasites, and a second for predicting the probability of having infection with at least one parasite type). We worked under the proportional odds assumption that the odds ratio of having a higher level of infection for any particular predictor is the same for each of the two models.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine if there was any significant association between prevalence of infection with a particular haemoparasite and bird species (which includes migratory status and foraging guild), to test the association between prevalence of infection with each type of haemoparasite and breeding season, and to identify associations between prevalence of infection and the sites in which birds were sampled, we performed a Fisher’s exact test. Comparison of number of haplotypes by site location (North vs. South), migratory status (Resident vs. Migratory), and foraging guild was done using Fisher’s exact.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine if there was any significant relationship between the prevalence of infection with a particular haemoparasite and the PCV and polychromasia, and, whenever possible, whether age or gender influenced PCV or polychromasia, we performed 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-tests. Before each 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test was run, a test of equal variances of the two groups (those with and without infection) was performed using a Folded 
  <span class="italic">F</span>-test. Then, a method for the 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test (Pooled or Satterthwaite) was determined based on the outcome of the 
  <span class="italic">F</span>-test. The pooled method for the 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test was used for the equal variance assumption, whereas the Satterthwaite method was used when unequal variances occurred (
  <span class="italic">p</span>-value of the Folded 
  <span class="italic">F</span>-test &lt;0.05).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine if there was any relationship between the species of the bird and PCV and polychromasia, we performed an ANOVA 
  <span class="italic">F</span>-test as a preliminary test. If differences were noted, we conducted a multiple comparison test (Tukey’s test). We used a 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test to assess the associations between PCV, polychromasia, and BMI with breeding season and separately, with location. 
  <span class="italic">T</span>-tests were also used to identify a relationship between prevalence of infection and BMI.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, we were interested in knowing whether there was any correlation between PCV and polychromasia, thus we utilized a Pearson correlation to examine this relationship.</p>
</sec>
