<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0090" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.8</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall predictors for haemoparasite infections</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two predictors, species and breeding season, were significant in the final model for 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> spp., whereas for 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spp., only the breeding season was significant (
  <a rid="t0025" ref-type="table" href="#t0025">Table 5</a>). In regards of 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp., only the bird species was a significant predictor. Three variables (species, location and breeding season) were significantly associated with infection with 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma</span> spp. (
  <a rid="t0025" ref-type="table" href="#t0025">Table 5</a>). Low prevalences precluded comparisons for microfilaria.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After comparing breeding and non-breeding seasons with respect to the probability of infection with 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> spp., we determined that the odds of a bird being infected during the breeding season were 2.275 times than during the non-breeding season (
  <a rid="t0030" ref-type="table" href="#t0030">Table 6</a>). The odds of a bird being infected with 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> during the breeding season were 2.882 times that of being infected during the non-breeding season. With respect to 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp., the odds of Northern Cardinals being infected were 0.278 times those of White-throated Sparrows.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since location (North vs. South) and breeding season were important factors for 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma</span> prevalence, we determined the probability of infection with this haemoparasite between North and South Georgia, during breeding and non-breeding periods. The odds of a bird being infected with 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma</span> in North Georgia were 10.522 times those of being infected in South Georgia and the odds of a bird being infected with 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma</span> spp. during the breeding season were 7.408 times those of being infected during the non-breeding season (
  <a rid="t0030" ref-type="table" href="#t0030">Table 6</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
