<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We also note that our analysis of cumulative emissions windows within transient climate model simulations is likely to yield conservative estimates of the ultimate climate response, because further regional climate change is likely to occur after emissions are terminated (
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">36</italic>
 </xref>). The occurrence frequencies of the maximum/minimum HistoricalNat value in the CMIP5 Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) simulations (figs. S3 to S6) provide a test of the sensitivity to the pathway of cumulative emissions. For example, the cumulative emissions are similar in RCP8.5 and RCP2.6 in the first three decades of the 21st century, after which they diverge sharply, with the mid-21st century cumulative emissions of RCP8.5 exceeding the late-21st century cumulative emissions of RCP2.6 (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>). The rapid decline in annual emissions in RCP2.6 means that the global temperature remains approximately between 1° and 2.5°C above the pre-industrial for the second half of the 21st century of RCP2.6 (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">33</italic>
 </xref>). Therefore, comparison of the mid-century of RCP2.6 with the late century of RCP2.6 provides an approximation of the sensitivity of the event probability to changes in regional climate that occur after near stabilization of the global temperature. We find that the changes in occurrence between the mid- and late-century of RCP2.6 are broadly similar (figs. S3 to S6). However, a comprehensive quantification of the sensitivity of event probabilities to cumulative emissions pathway will require multiple simulations of multiple stabilization trajectories using multiple climate models.
</p>
