<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The World Climate Research Program (WCRP) designated the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) to store and distribute the output of participating GCMs obtained under a standardized set of scenarios. The majority of existing flood risk studies use the GCM projections obtained from the CMIP-3 project, which was released for the Working Group I contribution to the IPCC’s Fourth Report (
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Solomon et al., 2007</xref>). Meanwhile, an updated ensemble of GCM projections, labeled CMIP-5, has been prepared for the fifth IPCC report (
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stocker et al., 2013</xref>). CMIP-5 models have a higher spatial resolution and improved physical representation and integration of the processes in the atmosphere, ocean, and land (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flato et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Knutti &amp; Sedláček, 2013</xref>). One of the major advancements in CMIP-5 over CMIP-3 is the inclusion of the effects of land use changes associated with agriculture, urbanization and deforestation that impacts climate through the alteration of albedo, aerodynamic roughness, and water-holding capacity (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Flato et al., 2013</xref>), which makes them more relevant for the decision-making process. However, uncertainties related to aerosol-cloud dynamics (
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stanfield et al., 2014</xref>), and a lack of improvement in capturing the North American monsoon system and North Atlantic subtropical high as compared to the CMIP-3 models (
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Geil, Serra &amp; Zeng, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wuebbles et al., 2014</xref>) existed in CMIP-5 GCMs. 
 <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wuebbles et al. (2014)</xref> analyzed CMIP-5 models and found no significant changes in the overall magnitude of projected temperature and precipitation over the continental US as compared to the CMIP-3 projections.
</p>
