<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The agro-morphologic variability of citrus is very large. Several sources of tolerance to abiotic stresses have been identified (
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Krueger and Navarro, 2007</xref>): tolerance to salinity of Rangpur lime (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus limonia</italic> Osb.), 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus macrophylla</italic> Wester and Cleopatra mandarin (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus reshni</italic> Hort. Ex Tan.); tolerance to water deficit of Rangpur lime (
 <italic class="italic">C. limonia</italic> Osbeck) and the 
 <italic class="italic">Microcitrus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Eremocitrus</italic> species; tolerance to iron chlorosis of Rough lemon (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus jambhiri</italic> Lush), 
 <italic class="italic">C. macrophylla</italic> Wester, Volkamer lemon (
 <italic class="italic">C. limonia</italic> Osbeck), and 
 <italic class="italic">C. amblycarpa</italic> (Hassk.) Ochse, cold tolerance of satsuma mandarins (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus unshiu</italic> Marc.), Kumquats (
 <italic class="italic">Fortunella</italic> sp.) and trifoliate orange, 
 <italic class="italic">Poncirus trifoliata</italic> (L.) Raf. This variability opens very broad prospects for the exploitation of citrus genetic resources for adaptation breeding particularly at the rootstock level (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cimen and Yesiloglu, 2016</xref>). The facultative apomixes of many citrus species allow clonal rootstock propagation by seed and contributed to the generalization of grafting in the citrus industry. Sexual breeding programs carried out in Florida by the end of the 19th century provided several intergeneric (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">Poncirus</italic>) hybrids, still used nowadays as rootstocks in many countries. These include some citrumelos (
 <italic class="italic">C. paradisi</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">P. trifoliata</italic> cvs. Swingle, Sacaton and 4475) and, particularly, the citranges (
 <italic class="italic">C. sinensis</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">P. trifoliata</italic> cvs. Troyer, Carrizo and C-35). However, most of them present some susceptibility to adverse abiotic conditions (alkalinity, salt), urging the development of a new range of intergeneric (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus × Poncirus</italic>) hybrids. Crosses between mandarins and trifoliate orange appear very promising to combine tolerances to abiotic and biotic constraints both by sexual breeding or somatic hybridization (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dambier et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
