<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our analysis indicates that not only will blue crab overwintering behavior become more unpredictable, but also the probability of overwinter survival will increase by at least 20% by the year 2100, nearing 100% overwinter survival under RCP8.5 by the end of the century. These changes will bring about an increase in the length of the growing season, and a higher level of population productivity, with potential consequences to the management of blue crab in Chesapeake Bay [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Currently, crabbing is prohibited during the overwintering period (December-March) in all three management jurisdictions in the Chesapeake Bay. This creates a 
 <italic class="italic">de facto</italic> closed season for crab during the winter. The positive response of the population to the closure of a winter fishing in the lower Chesapeake Bay in 2008 shows the role of this closed season in maintaining the Chesapeake Bay crab population at sustainable levels [
 <xref rid="pone.0219555.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. However, the increase in temperature and subsequent increase in wintertime crab activity may encourage a lengthening of crabbing season, as is currently the practice in the lower latitude states where crabs are active year-round. Although it is possible that the increases in growth rate and survival resulting from increased temperature could sustain a longer crab fishery, the interannual variability in overwintering behavior in the Maryland portion of the Chesapeake Bay in the future complicates the wintertime management of this species. Reductions to, or elimination of, the wintertime closure in response to increases in average wintertime activity might drastically reduce population levels during cold years when crab will likely still overwinter. Therefore, despite the warming trends observed in this study, until crabs are consistently active year-round, the elimination of the wintertime dredge fishery closure may put immobile, overwintering individuals at greater risk of mortality during cold years.
</p>
