<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The environmental impact of the OP industry primarily concerns the conversion of tropical rainforests into plantations. Most of the area for expansion of the OP industry was supplied through forests where the emissions from conversion exceed the potential carbon fixing of OP (Germer &amp; Sauerborn, 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Paterson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Global production of palm oil was ca. 50 million metric tons per year in 2012 which is more than double that of 2000, of which a considerable amount involved deforestation. The highest carbon emitter countries from forest cover loss for (1) Latin America and the Caribbean, (2) Sub Sarah Africa, and (3) South and South‐East Asia were (1) Brazil, (2) Democratic Republic of the Congo, and (3) Indonesia, respectively, at values of 340, 23, and 105 (Teragrams (Tg) C/year) respectively. Malaysia was third highest at 41 Tg C/year (Harris et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Indonesia and Malaysia account for high C emissions from deforestation as they are the first and second highest producers of OP. Substantial palm oil production is also already undertaken in Columbia and Nigeria (Paterson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Emissions from OP cultivation in Indonesia accounted for ca. 2%–9% of all tropical land use from 2000 to 2010 (Carlson &amp; Curran, 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Indonesia was the world's seventh‐largest emitter of global warming pollution in 2009, and deforestation accounted for about 30% of these emissions (Union of Concerned Scientists, 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Also, plantation expansion in Kalimantan, Indonesia, is projected to contribute 18%–22% of the country's 2020 CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions (Carlson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). OP production involving deforestation releases global anthropogenic emissions of 6%–17% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Baccini et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33610-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
