<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Globally, the prevalence of mental health issues is extremely high even without considering the added mental health consequences of a changing climate. Based on a 10-year systematic analysis of global burden of disease from 1990 to 2010, Murray et al. find that mental illness comprises 7.8% of the global burden of disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. Mental and behavioural disorders also account for the greatest global burden of years lived with a disability (YLDs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>]. Vigo et al. contend that these figures are actually much higher if co-morbidities related to mental illness are considered within burden of illness studies and if a more accurate definition of mental illness is used, a definition that includes health behaviours like self-harm and suicide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. The failure of global investment in mental health care to address the consequences and impacts of rapidly escalating levels of mental illness has been described as a “global tragedy” reflecting a long “legacy of the neglect and marginalization of mental health” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>]. Similarly, authors from the 2016 Lancet report on sustainable development and global mental health describe the state of mental health as the “most neglected of all human health conditions” and a “failure of humanity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>]. The inattention to mental health is of particular concern in the field of climate change and mental health given the evidence that psychological impacts from any form of disaster exceed physical injury by 40–1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>], and that since 2000 the frequency of climate change-related weather disasters has increased by 46% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>]. Crucially, it is the most marginalized who are especially vulnerable to climate change’s impacts on mental health. As McMichael notes, climate change acts as a health “threat amplifier”, compounding existing social injustices [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. There is, therefore, a strong case for continuing to explore and communicate research and policy learning about the relationship between climate change and mental health—especially as the topic area pertains to health equity.
</p>
