<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Some studies have shown that climatic niches are conserved between the native and invasive regions (Petitpierre et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). This observation is the basis for the use of ENMs calibrated in the native range to assess the invasion risk of invasive plant species in the invasive range (Broennimann, Mráz, Petitpierre, Guisan, &amp; Müller‐Schärer, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Guisan, Petitpierre, Broennimann, Daehler, &amp; Kueffer, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Petitpierre et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Climatic niche conservatism predicts that invasive plant species are likely to grow and survive in environments that strongly resemble their native ranges (Broennimann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Guisan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Petitpierre et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Indeed, Petitpierre et al. (
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) have shown that climatic niche shifts are rare among 50 terrestrial plant invaders between Eurasia, North America, and Australia based on principal component analysis (PCA) and found that fewer than 15% of species have the shifts between their native and invasive climatic niche spaces. However, there is no consensus on this question given that in other studies, niche divergence has been shown to occur between native and invasive ranges along a gradient of temperature and precipitation for 22 plant species endemic or near endemic to Europe that have been naturalized in the USA (Early &amp; Sax, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Shifts in climatic niches are relatively frequent among European species invading North America (Dellinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). This may be because climate niche divergence can occur as a result of nonclimatic factors, such as seed dispersal, human activities, and sexual reproduction (Prentis et al. 2008; Donoghue &amp; Edwards, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Dellinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). For instance, if biotic factors, abiotic factors other than the climate, or dispersal barriers limit the distribution in either the native or the invasive range, then the breadth of climatic tolerances of the species is likely to be underestimated (Alexander &amp; Edwards, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Guisan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Sax et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Such climatic niche divergence may result in uncertainties in the use of ENMs to predict the habitat suitability of AIWs.
</p>
