<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lizards of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> comprise a group of northern forms of Laurasian origin with a diversification in North America; therefore, they are considered as one of the oldest groups of lizards (Macey et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>; Bhullar, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34200-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Currently, distribution of the 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> species is associated with mountain chains that occur from northeastern Mexico to Alta Verapaz, Guatemala (Bhullar, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Species of 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> occur in a broad altitudinal range of approximately 500–2,360 m, and they can be found in a wide variety of habitats, ranging from xerophytic tropical scrub to tropical montane cloud forest, and tropical rain forest (King &amp; Thompson, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1968</xref>). Most species of the genus share behavioral and physiological characteristics, such as being thermoconformists and thigmotherms with preferences for relatively low temperatures (García‐Rico, Díaz de la Vega‐Pérez, Smith, Lemos‐Espinal, &amp; Woolrich‐Piña, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Some authors have suggested that the entire genus 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> might be very susceptible to rapid environmental changes (Nieto‐Montes de Oca, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>; Sinervo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), which could be supported by the fact that most of these species are microendemic and have restricted dispersal abilities (Zamora‐Abrego &amp; Ortega‐León, 
 <xref rid="ece34200-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). No study, however, has properly evaluated how climate changes might influence this group of lizards; therefore, the following question becomes relevant: how would lizard species of 
 <italic class="italic">Xenosaurus</italic> respond if the conditions of their climatic niche are modified because of climate change?
</p>
