<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0080" class="p">The phyllochron (
 <italic class="italic">P
  <sub class="sub">h</sub>
 </italic>) is the thermal time required for the appearance of successive leaves, and day length response (
 <italic class="italic">P
  <sub class="sub">p</sub>
 </italic>) is the response of the final leaf number to day length (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brooking et al., 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jamieson et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1998a</xref>, 1998b). An optimal flowering time and anthesis in relation to seasonal variations of temperature, solar radiation, day length and water availability are critical factors in maximizing grain yield (Akkaya et al., 2006; 
 <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Richards, 2006</xref>). The rate of crop development and, consequently, the timing of anthesis and maturity could be altered by modifying 
 <italic class="italic">P
  <sub class="sub">h</sub>
 </italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P
  <sub class="sub">p</sub>
 </italic> in plants (
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jamieson et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov et al., 2014</xref>). The duration of grain filling (
 <italic class="italic">G
  <sub class="sub">f</sub>
 </italic>) is an important trait for increasing grain yield in wheat (
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Evans and Fischer, 1999</xref>). In Sirius, 
 <italic class="italic">G
  <sub class="sub">f</sub>
 </italic> is defined as the cultivar-specific thermal time that needs to be accumulated to complete grain filling. During grain filling, assimilates for the grain are available from two sources, 
 <italic class="italic">viz</italic>. new photosynthates produced from intercepted radiation and water-soluble carbohydrates stored mostly in the stem before anthesis. In Sirius, the labile carbohydrate pool is calculated as a fixed 25% of biomass at anthesis and is translocated to the grain during grain filling. Increasing 
 <italic class="italic">G
  <sub class="sub">f</sub>
 </italic> will increase the amount of radiation intercepted by the crop and, consequently, grain yield. Under stress conditions, when grain growth could be terminated early as a result of leaves dying before the end of grain filling due to water or heat stress, grain yield will decrease not only because of the reduction in intercepted radiation, but also because not all of the labile carbohydrate pool will be translocated to the grain due to the shortage of time (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brooks et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Halford, 2009</xref>).
</p>
