<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Force to detach kelp from turf and rock</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations that kelp were commonly recruited onto turf-forming macroalgae prompted a study to examine the attachment strength of kelp attached to rocky substrate versus turf to determine the risk of detachment by wave forces for these 2 groups of kelp. We predicted that kelp attached to turf would require less force to detach than kelp attached to rocky substrate, as kelp appeared loosely attached to the turf. On 20 Dec 2017 (n = 15 rock, and 12 turf), 9 Feb 2018 (n = 5 rock, and 6 turf), and 22 May 2018 (n = 8 rock, and 9 turf), divers used a resettable modified dynamometer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> consisting of a spring scale attached to an elastic nylon cord (to avoid tearing the holdfast) to test attachment strength of kelp attached to rock and turf. Kelp were selected haphazardly within an ~200 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> area of reef at 4 m depth at Fort Wetherill. The scale was attached to kelp by threading the nylon through the holdfast (attached to rock or turf) and secured with a loose knot. Kelp were then pulled perpendicular to the substrate until the kelp (including holdfast) was dislodged or holdfast failure occurred (cord pulls through the material of the holdfast). The indicator deflection distance on the spring scale was measured with calipers and the attachment strength was determined by multiplying the indicator deflection distance by the known spring constant
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blade lengths of kelp detached from the substrate on 20 Dec 2017 were significantly different among turf- and rock-attached individuals, with turf-attached individuals having a significantly smaller mean blade length (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). To ensure that force to detach measurements were not biased by kelp blade length (i.e. kelp age/size), we plotted the force to detach as a function of the length of individuals within each group (turf- and rock-attached). We found no relationship between force to detach and blade length (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
