<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The developing fetus and young child are more biologically and psychologically vulnerable than adults to the many adverse effects of toxic air pollutants and physical trauma, psychosocial stress, nutritional deprivation, infectious agents, and heat waves associated with climate change from fossil fuel combustion. Contributing factors include children’s rapid growth, dynamic developmental programming vulnerable to dysregulation, immature detoxification, immune, and thermoregulatory systems, and their dependence on adult caretakers (reviewed by 
 <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bateson and Schwartz 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sheffield and Landrigan 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al. 2012</xref>). The importance of protection during these early windows of development is indicated by the fact that most of the 86 billion neurons of the brain are formed during the prenatal period (
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Crelin 1973</xref>), and the brain, lungs, and immune system continue to develop during infancy through age 6 years and beyond (
 <xref rid="r110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">WHO 2006</xref>). In addition to their increased developmental vulnerability, children have greater exposure to toxic air pollutants than do adults (
 <xref rid="r110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">WHO 2006</xref>) and require three to four times the amount of food on a body weight basis than adults (
 <xref rid="r116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al. 2012</xref>). Recent studies demonstrate that the fetal period and early childhood represent windows of susceptibility both to genetic damage (
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Perera et al. 2004</xref>) and epigenetic dysregulation from exposure to xenobiotics and stress (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dolinoy et al. 2007</xref>), with potential lifelong and transgenerational consequences (
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Heindel 2005</xref>).
</p>
