<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Wheat accounts for 30% of global grain production and for 45% of cereal food, and therefore represents the major food plant. Grain filling depends on assimilate supply. Increased assimilate partitioning to developing spikes and grains had the greatest impact on improving yield potential in wheat in the past (
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foulkes 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>). Grain yield is predominantly sink limited and grains grow under saturated source supply (
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Borrás 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2004
 </xref>). Thus, improved assimilate uptake capacity and partitioning towards the grains can improve yield potential in wheat. Due to anthropogenic activities, the atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) concentration is projected to increase to 550 ppm by 2050, accompanied by higher global temperatures and increasing extreme weather events such as heat waves (
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Barriopedro 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>). Many studies also report observed increases in frequency, intensity, and/or longevity of heat waves, which can strongly impact plant growth (
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">De Boeck 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>). While CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment frequently improves carbon (C) assimilation and increases plant biomass in many species (
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taub 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>), sink limitation often occurs, leading to photosynthetic feed-back inhibition (
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">White 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). This suggests that photosynthesis is only optimal at non-limiting sink capacity and therefore insufficient assimilate translocation could be critical (
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aranjuelo 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>).
</p>
