<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">We obtained occurrence data for Qfly from four main sources: the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ala.org.au" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ala.org.au</ext-link>), the Australian Plant Pest Database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.planthealthaustralia.com.au/resources/australian-plant-pest-database" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.planthealthaustralia.com.au/resources/australian-plant-pest-database</ext-link>), existing literature, and trap data. ALA is Australia’s largest digital database of species occurrence records, containing information from a wide array of data providers including Australia’s major museums and government departments. Before downloading data from ALA, we applied filters to restrict records to those that were resolved to species-level, dated after 1 January 1950, contained geographic coordinates, and were not flagged as ‘environmental outliers’. APPD is a national, secure database of pest and plant pathogen specimens held within herbaria and insect collections across Australia. Records from ALA and APPD primarily represent ad hoc collections, and so were supplemented with records from specimens collected in fruit fly traps managed by various state government departments (New South Wales Regional Pest Management, Biosecurity and Food Safety; Biosecurity Queensland and the Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries; Department of Economic Development, Jobs, Transport and Resources, Victoria; and Primary Industries and Regions South Australia (PIRSA)). Trap data from these sources were collected at different periods from 1996 to 2017. To reduce environmental bias due to spatially autocorrelated sampling, we reduced trap data such that pairs of points were separated by at least 10 km. We also obtained occurrence data from previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup> including state government databases. After filtering/thinning, a total of 1057 unique localities (i.e. 1 × 1 km grid cells) remained.
</p>
