<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P9" class="p">The spatial distribution of anomalous energy fluxes indicates that the Southern Ocean is a key region responsible for producing the ↓N variability that enhances GMST variability in the preindustrial control run. The dynamics of this Southern Ocean variability appear to be consistent with those expounded upon in previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>–
  <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. Specifically, it has been shown that southward flowing North Atlantic Deep Water can deposit relatively warm, salty water at intermediate depths in the Southern Ocean. A large reservoir of heat can build up if convection is initially inhibited due to a relatively fresh surface layer and/or the presence of surface sea ice that obstructs air-sea heat exchange. Eventually, stochastic forcing via wind stress or surface salinity anomalies can cause the onset of convection (represented by deepening of the mixed layer; 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 4e</xref>). During convection, saltier water from mid-depth is transported to the surface where a rise in salinity occurs (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 4f</xref>). As convection continues, substantial anomalous surface heat flux from the high-latitude Southern Ocean to the atmosphere occurs (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 5b</xref>) due primarily to the sensible and latent heat flux components (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 5c and 5d</xref>). The excess energy is not damped to space locally, as a large reduction in sea ice extent causes a positive anomalous ↓clear SW flux (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 6c</xref>), especially in the summer (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 6i</xref>), and a net positive ↓N over the Southern Ocean (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 6b</xref>).
</p>
