<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In recent years, about 130 million seedlings have been used for reforestation in Québec and around 20% of these are white spruce (
 <italic class="italic">Picea glauca</italic> [Moench] Voss). In terms of its climatic distribution, white spruce is a species whose natural range extends east to west across continental North America from the tree line to the northern United States (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nienstaedt and Zasada, 1990</xref>). The species harbors extensive genetic variation in quantitative traits compared to many other commercial conifer species (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beaulieu et al., 2009</xref>), which is in part related to geography and climatic gradients (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Andalo et al., 2005</xref>). Genetic variation at many genes has further been shown to be tightly related to climatic factors (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hornoy et al., 2015</xref>). In 2012, 98% of the seeds used to produce white spruce seedlings were from improved sources (first- and second-generation seed orchards) that exhibited a genetic gain of 10 to 15% in height compared to unimproved plantation stock (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rainville et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beaulieu et al., 2009</xref>). The production of multiple clones by somatic embryogenesis is currently integrated into the operational chain for rooted cuttings and processes for their characterization and selection have been developed both in nurseries (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lamhamedi et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wahid et al., 2012a</xref>) and on reforestation sites (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Grossnickle, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lamhamedi and Gravel-Grenier, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wahid et al., 2012b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Association genetics and genomic selection approaches have also been developed for different traits related to growth and wood quality of this species (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beaulieu et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>).
</p>
