<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone.0159909.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0159909.g004</object-id>
 <label class="label">Fig 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Alternative outcomes of identifying potential climate change refugia from observed and projected climate data using physical or ecological definitions.</title>
  <p class="p">Observed climate data (e.g., Annual Temperature and Annual Precipitation) from occupied sites (blue squares mapped in geographic space; A) are extracted and plotted (blue squares; B and C). From these same sites, projected climate values are extracted and plotted in climatic space on the same axes (circles; C) to determine the amount of change expected; for a physical perspective, only sites that are expected to change less than a given threshold (green circles) are designated as climate change refugia. For an ecological perspective, information regarding the species environmental limits is modeled or experimentally determined (dotted line; B). Sites that are within this envelope after projected change are considered climate change refugia (green and orange circles; D). Thus, from both the physical and ecological perspectives, green circles are identified as climate change refugia and red circles are not, whereas orange circles are not identified as climate change refugia by the physical definition because they exceed the threshold of change but are designated as such by the ecological definition. Additionally, although currently unoccupied, gray circles represent sites that might be identified as climate change refugia as they are expected to represent suitable environmental conditions under both definitions. The spatial arrangement of climate change refugia and non-refugia (depending upon definition) are mapped in E.</p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0159909.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
