<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aim, design and setting of the study</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study aimed to evaluate the impact of SDM communication skills training for physicians treating patients with asthma on the SDM behaviors of physicians measured from three different perspectives (observer, physician, patient). Additionally, this study aimed to analyze physician views on the training, including their perceptions of intrapersonal change after the training, and their suggestions for improvement of the training. To meet these aims, a mixed methods study with a partially mixed sequential equal status design was conducted.</p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study was undertaken with the cooperation of Mundipharma GmbH [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. It was conducted following a partially mixed sequential equal status design, [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>] in line with the guidelines for conducting and reporting mixed analysis studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The study design included a quantitative evaluation phase using a pre-post design with no control group and a qualitative evaluation phase, as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Study subjects were physicians treating asthma patients in outpatient care in Germany. Cooperating partners of Mundipharma GmbH invited physicians nationwide, organized their training, and were present at the training sites in Berlin, Hamburg, and Munich in Germany. Authors who were members of the study team conducted the physician training (EM, IS, MH and AB), and the coaching interviews (EM). The training sessions were independent of study participation. Non-probability sequential sampling was used with a parallel study design that included a convenience sample of physicians who were willing to participate in the study. All participating physicians signed an informed consent form including permission for pseudonymized data analysis. The study was conducted in accordance with the Code of Ethics of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Medical Association of Hamburg, Germany (Registration No: PV4973). 
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Study design. SDM = shared decision-making</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12913_2019_4445_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
