<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative evaluation phase</div>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were collected from May 2015 until December 2016. Demographic and professional characteristics of the participating physicians were collected at the beginning of the training program. Further quantitative data were collected at the beginning of the training (t0) and after the training at the physician’s practice site (t1). Data collection was equivalent at both measurement points. Due to the design of the study, blinding was not feasible.</p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before the training, four asthma patient case vignettes with identical airflow parameters. They were developed by study team members (EM, AB) experienced in the design of medical case vignettes, and revised by an experienced pulmonologist. Two vignettes were used in simulated patient consultations at t0 and another two were used at t1. Simulated patients were psychology and health sciences students who had received 2 h of training. Consultations with simulated patients were videotaped and transcribed verbatim. Two trained team members independently evaluated the videotapes and transcripts with the OPTION
  <span class="sup">5</span> scale (primary outcome) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Training in the application of the OPTION
  <span class="sup">5</span> consisted of independent rating of ten audiotapes and transcribed patient and physician consultations and subsequent comparison and discussion of the results, until consensus was reached. The OPTION
  <span class="sup">5</span> scale is a psychometrically tested five-item observer-based instrument measuring the physician’s efforts to involve the patient in the SDM process using a five-point Likert scale (0 = not observed; 4 = executed to a high standard). Simulated patients were included to measure SDM from the patient’s point of view. Directly after the consultations, the simulated patients completed the patient version of the nine-item Shared Decision Making Questionnaire (SDM-Q-9) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>] and physicians completed the physician version of the nine-item Shared Decision Making Questionnaire (SDM-Q-Doc) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] (secondary outcomes). The SDM-Q-Doc and the SDM-Q-9 are both psychometrically tested nine-item self-reporting instruments measuring the physician and patient perspective on the decision-making process using a six-point Likert scale (0 = completely disagree; 5 = completely agree).
 </p>
</sec>
