<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sample</div>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A questionnaire survey was conducted in the autumn of 2017 (14th of September–5th of November) in Finland. Information was obtained from Valvira’s (the National Supervisory Authority for Welfare and Health) Terhikki central register. All the physicians born after 1944 who had completed their medical education outside of Finland and who had received a license to practice medicine in Finland (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1564) were included to the sample. Email addresses (provided by the Finnish Medical Association) or postal addresses (provided by the Population Register Centre) were obtained for 1012 physicians. Living abroad or not having a permanent address in Finland and non-disclosure for purposes such as direct advertising or for personal safety reasons were the most important reasons for not getting the postal addresses. The physicians whose mother tongue was one of the two official language in Finland (Finnish or Swedish; 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 203) were excluded to rule out native Finns who had studied abroad. Consequently, the questionnaire was sent to 809 physicians.
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used webropol questionnaire service and sent an email invitation with a link to the electronic survey for those whose email addresses we had. For others, a postal invitation to participate in the electronic survey was sent to their home addresses. Two reminders in 3 weeks interval were sent to those who had not responded. Additional postal paper version of the questionnaire (only in Finnish) was sent with the second reminder. Altogether 375 (46% of those who the questionnaire was sent to) physicians responded to the survey. The electronic questionnaire was available in Finnish, Swedish, Estonian, Russian and English languages; 153 of the respondents answered the electronic version in Finnish, two in Swedish, 64 in Estonian, 60 in Russian and 22 in English. Seventy-four responded by the postal questionnaire, which was only available in Finnish. We asked the country of birth in the questionnaire, thus we were able to identify those who were actually foreign-born. Of the respondents, we excluded two respondents who had studied abroad and whose mother tongue was other than Finnish or Swedish but who reported being born in Finland. Moreover, two respondents were excluded because they did not provide us with the information about their country of birth. Thus, the final study sample included 371 foreign-born physicians aged between 26 and 65 (mean age: 39.1; 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 9.09; 65% women).
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethical approval was obtained from the ethics committee of the National Institute for Health and Welfare in Finland.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the measures used in the present study have already been tested in our previous data gathering among Finnish foreign-born physicians in 2010/2011 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. The questionnaire can be found from the Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Turnover intentions</span> were measured with a question asking whether the respondent had planned changing employment. The response options were: 1) 
   <span class="italic">no</span>, 2) 
   <span class="italic">possibly</span>, 3) 
   <span class="italic">yes</span>. For the analyses the measure was coded as 0 = 
   <span class="italic">no</span> and 1 = 
   <span class="italic">yes</span> and 
   <span class="italic">possibly</span>. 
   <span class="italic">Intentions to move country</span> was measured with a question asking whether the respondent had plans to move to work in another country during the next 12 months. The response options and coding were the same as in the question for turnover intentions. Binary coding was chosen for these variables because the amount of “yes” answers was rather low especially for intention to leave the country (4,3%) and binary coding allowed us to conduct logistic regression analyses (with odds ratios and easy interpretation of the results).
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Discrimination</span> was measured with a mean of three items (α = 0.72) that have previously been used among foreign-born physicians in Finland [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>] to assess whether a person had experienced personal discrimination at work during the last 12 months coming from 1) superiors and management, 2) colleagues and fellow employees and 3) patients/clients. The items were rated on a five-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (
   <span class="italic">hardly ever</span>) to 5 (
   <span class="italic">very often</span> or 
   <span class="italic">continuously</span>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Language problems</span> were measured with the mean of seven items (α = 0.96) that have previously been used among foreign-born physicians in Finland [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>] to ask how often the respondent experienced work-related communication challenges in using Finnish language in a) face-to-face communication with patients, b) face-to-face communication with co-workers, c) workplace meetings, d) keeping up with professional literature, e) recording data in patient information systems, f) electronic communication and g) communication over the phone. The items were rated on a five-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (
   <span class="italic">hardly ever</span>) to 5 (
   <span class="italic">very often</span> or 
   <span class="italic">continuously</span>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Employment barriers</span> were measured with the mean of four items (α = 0.70) that asked whether employer attitudes, difficulties in finding information about job vacancies, insufficient relationships with people of Finnish origin and one’s uncertainty had prevented the respondent from getting a job she or he wanted in Finland during the past 2 years (1 = 
   <span class="italic">not at all</span>, 2 = 
   <span class="italic">to some extent</span> and 3 = 
   <span class="italic">a lot</span>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Satisfaction with living in Finland</span> was assessed by a asking how satisfied or dissatisfied the respondent was overall with his or her life in Finland. The response options ranged between 0 (
   <span class="italic">very dissatisfied</span>) and 10 (
   <span class="italic">very satisfied</span>). For the statistical analyses, the measure was coded as 
   <span class="italic">low</span> = 0–7 (26% of the respondents) and 
   <span class="italic">high</span> = 8–10 (74%) (this was done because the measure included only one item).
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Team climate</span> was measured with the mean of four items (α = 0.90) from the Team Climate Inventory (TCI) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>] which measures team participation, such as interaction frequency and information sharing. The items were rated on a five-point Likert scale, ranging from 1 (
   <span class="italic">fully disagree</span>) to 5 (
   <span class="italic">fully agree</span>), with higher scores indicating a better team climate.
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Job satisfaction</span> was measured with one item from Job Diagnostic Survey’s [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>] scale for overall satisfaction with the job (‘Generally speaking I am very satisfied with this job’). The item was rated on a five-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (
   <span class="italic">fully disagree</span>) to 5 (
   <span class="italic">fully agree</span>). Because this measure included only one item this measure was coded as 
   <span class="italic">low</span> = 1–4 (54% of the respondents) and 
   <span class="italic">high</span> = 5 (46%) for the analyses.
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Patient-related stress</span> was measured by the mean of three items (α = 0.82) that asked participants how often the situation described in the statement had disturbed them, worried them or caused them stress during last half-year period using a five-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (
   <span class="italic">hardly ever</span>) to 5 (
   <span class="italic">very often</span> or 
   <span class="italic">continuously</span>) with higher scores indicating higher stress. The items were: a) ‘Patients’ expectations frequently differ from those of health care personnel’, b) ‘Difficult patients who complain, blame and criticize’ and c) ‘Patients who are unwilling to co-operate and passive’. These items have been developed based on earlier studies carried out in the health care sector [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. The measure has been used previously among foreign-born physicians [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">The employment sector</span> was categorised into three groups: the municipal sector (e.g. primary care), the state sector (e.g. hospitals) and the private sector. 
   <span class="italic">The country of birth</span> was asked about in the questionnaire with an open-ended question and categorised as a) Estonia, b) the Russian Federation / former Soviet Union, c) EU/EEA countries other than Estonia and d) other countries not covered by a–c.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of independent variables on turnover intentions and intentions to leave the country were examined with binary logistic regression analyses (in separate analyses). The analyses were conducted in two steps. First, the effects of gender, age, employment sector, country of birth and the number of years from getting a practicing license in Finland were examined (Model A). In the second step, discrimination, language problems, employment barriers, satisfaction with living in Finland, team climate, job satisfaction and patient-related stress were added to the former model (Model B). A multi-collinearity analysis of the study variables was performed. The variance inflation factors (VIF) associated with the variables were all below 1.5, showing that multi-collinearity is not a concern in this study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analyses were performed using SPSS software, version 25.0.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
