<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microhabitat selection and its influence on physiology can have important ramifications for individual fitness (
  <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Huey, 1991</a>). Our research suggests that pygmy rabbits acclimatize seasonally by reducing energy expenditure at cold temperatures in winter relative to summer, and they have lower than expected thermal conductance. These qualities confer important thermoregulatory cost savings during the winter. Even so, the burrow is an important thermal refuge, particularly in winter when thermoregulatory costs can be reduced by resting in thermally buffered microsites below ground. However, reductions in snow cover are associated with increased thermoregulatory costs for burrow users (
  <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Geiser &amp; Turbill, 2009</a>) and are predicted under most climate change scenarios (
  <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Pauli et al., 2013</a>). Although substantial efforts have focused on effects of climate change-induced shifts in precipitation and temperature on hot-acclimated animals, associated changes in winter ecology may have greater implications for individual fitness and population persistence for animals such as pygmy rabbits (
  <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Pauli et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-80">Williams, Henry &amp; Sinclair, 2014</a>). Climate and land-use changes in the future will undoubtedly continue to modify the thermal environment for numerous species through changes to vegetation composition and structure and shifts in large-scale weather patterns. Understanding the extent to which such changes can influence the value of below-ground refuges, however, begins with understanding the functional relationship between the physiology of an organism and the microhabitats it exploits.
 </p>
</sec>
