<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microsite temperature</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the thermal environment in above-ground microsites and burrows available to pygmy rabbits in sagebrush steppe habitat in the Lemhi Valley of east-central Idaho, USA. The valley is high-desert shrub-steppe (elevation = 1,880–2,020 masl) and receives on average &lt;25 cm precipitation annually (
  <a rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-77">Western Regional Climate Center, 2016</a>), most of which falls as rain during late spring. Average temperatures range from a daytime low of −15.7 °C to a high of −1.2 °C in January and 5.4–29 °C in July (
  <a rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-77">Western Regional Climate Center, 2016</a>). The study site is characterized by mounded microtopography known as mima-mounds (
  <a rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-73">Tullis, 1995</a>). These mounds tend to have deeper soils and support taller shrubs than the surrounding matrix, and they are where most pygmy rabbit burrow systems are located. Wyoming big sagebrush (
  <span class="italic">Artemisia tridentata wyomingensis</span>) is the dominant shrub species, with black sagebrush (
  <span class="italic">A. nova</span>), three-tip sagebrush (
  <span class="italic">A. tripartita</span>), green rabbitbrush (
  <span class="italic">Chrysothamnus viscidiflorus</span>), and rubber rabbitbrush (
  <span class="italic">Ericameria nauseosa</span>) occurring less frequently. The matrix between clusters of sagebrush supports a highly variable mix of low-growing shrubs, forbs, and bare ground in the lowest elevations, and more continuous grass and forb cover at higher elevations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used operative environmental temperature (
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub>) to characterize the thermal environment of above-ground sites available to pygmy rabbits (
  <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Bakken, 1980</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Coleman &amp; Downs, 2010</a>). 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> integrates heat transfer from radiative, conductive, and convective sources into a single index that specifies the equilibrium temperature an animal lacking metabolic heat production or evaporative heat loss would attain in a given combination of air temperature, wind, and sunlight. To measure 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub>, we built 10 models of the approximate size and shape of a resting pygmy rabbit (
  <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Bakken, 1992</a>). Models were hollow copper ovoids (12.7 × 10.2 cm) painted a matte dark gray. Copper models have been shown to more precisely measure the above-ground thermal environment experienced by small, diurnal mammals and capture the thermal heterogeneity of habitat better than direct measures of temperature (
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Coleman &amp; Downs, 2010</a>). We attached two 8 cm segments of pipe to the bottom of the ovoids to prevent the devices from resting directly on the ground and to anchor them to the substrate. A calibrated iButton® attached to a wooden dowel was inserted into one end of each model and sealed in place by a rubber stopper (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). The iButton® recorded temperature every 30 min for one month (31 days) in the winter (20 January–19 February, 2015) and summer (5 July–4 August, 2015) to capture the coldest and hottest times of the year in the valley.
 </p>
 <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.4511/fig-1</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Cross-section of an operative temperature model (A) and an intact model (B) used to characterize the thermal environment in pygmy rabbit (
    <span class="italic">Brachylagus idahoensis</span>) habitat in eastern Idaho, USA.
   </div>
   <p>Photo credit: Charles Peterson.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pygmy rabbit burrow systems were surveyed on foot during October 2014 according to methods described in 
  <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Price &amp; Rachlow (2011)</a>. Ten active burrow systems were randomly selected for temperature monitoring using ArcMAP 10.2 (ESRI, Redlands, CA, USA). Operative temperature models were placed at random locations on active burrow systems by identifying a random direction (cardinal or intercardinal) and distance (0–3 m, at 0.5 m increments) from the center of the mima mound. If the random point landed in a location where a pygmy rabbit could not reasonably be expected to rest (e.g., above ground on the trunk of a sagebrush plant), the model was placed adjacent to the obstruction as close to the random point as possible. The mean diameter of mima mounds at our study site was 10.6 m (range: 6.6–15.0 m; 
  <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">Parsons et al., 2016</a>), and an entire burrow system was typically encompassed by the boundary of discrete mima mounds (
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">McMahon et al., 2017</a>). Pygmy rabbits at this site predominantly use mima mounds with burrow systems (
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">McMahon et al., 2017</a>) and rest close to burrow openings (
  <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Milling et al., 2017</a>). Thus, the orientation of 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> models on the mound allowed us to capture a range of above-ground microclimates available to pygmy rabbits, and although the 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> model locations do not represent rest sites where rabbits were observed, they were located on active burrow systems and we often noted fresh fecal pellets within 0.5 m of the sensor locations. We identified 10 additional active burrow systems at which we monitored temperature within burrows; we included only burrows with a minimum of two openings because pygmy rabbits typically construct burrow systems with multiple openings (
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Green &amp; Flinders, 1980</a>). Because the thermal environment inside the burrow is not directly influenced by short wave radiation, and we assumed minimal influence of convection, we measured burrow temperature using Onset Stowaway TBI32 Tidbit temperature loggers (hereafter, tidbit; Onset Computer Corp., Bourne, MA, USA). We deployed one tidbit to a depth of 1 m (the average maximum depth of a pygmy rabbit burrow; 
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Green &amp; Flinders, 1980</a>) within a randomly selected opening for each burrow by attaching the tidbit to stiff wire nailed at the burrow entrance. This inhibited removal by animals. Tidbits recorded temperature every 10 min for one month in winter (20 January–19 February, 2015) and summer (5 July–4 August, 2015). Of 10 tidbits deployed, one tidbit failed during winter, resulting in nine winter-monitored burrows, and two tidbits failed during summer, resulting in eight summer-monitored burrows. We calculated the mean temperature recorded by all tidbits and also by all operative temperature models per hour to estimate below- and above-ground temperatures with the same temporal resolution.
 </p>
</sec>
