<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respirometry data were analyzed using mixed-effects segmented regression to evaluate the relationship between 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i007.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <span id="M8" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="mml-ieqn-7" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <span class="mi">V</span>
       <span class="mo">˙</span>
      </div>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mtext">O</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> and temperature during summer and winter (
  <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">Gallant &amp; Fuller, 1973</a>). We used season and 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>c</sub> as predictor variables with body mass as a covariate, and we included a random effect for individual identity. The model parameterizes the segments of the relationship between 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i008.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <span id="M9" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="mml-ieqn-8" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <span class="mi">V</span>
       <span class="mo">˙</span>
      </div>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mtext">O</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> and temperature below and within the TNZ, determines the breakpoint between segments, and estimates the influence of season and mass on the height of the function. From this output, we quantified the slope of the relationship below the 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>lc</sub> in both seasons, determined the value of the 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>lc</sub> (the breakpoint), and estimated summer RMR
  <sub>T</sub>. We tested for a seasonal difference in thermal conductance using a mixed-effects model with fixed effects for season and mass and a random effect for individual identity. Analyses were conducted using the “nlme” and “lme4” packages in R (
  <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">R Core Team, 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Bates et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">Pinheiro et al., 2016</a>), and results were deemed significant if 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 or if a 95% confidence interval on the parameter estimate did not capture zero. Values are reported as mean ± SE, unless otherwise specified.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used results of the regression analyses to estimate approximate seasonal energetic costs of thermoregulation for animals at rest in burrows and in above-ground microsites. We set mass to the mean of our study animals and populated our temperature predictor variable (
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>c</sub>) using measurements of mean 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> and mean burrow temperature. We calculated the proportion of time in each season that the burrow could serve as a thermal refuge for a resting pygmy rabbit. In winter, this was defined as the amount of time that mean 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> &lt; 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>lc</sub>, but the burrow was warmer than mean 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> and therefore had lower associated thermoregulatory costs. In summer, it was calculated as the amount of time that 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> &gt; 35 °C (the average 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>uc</sub> of pygmy rabbit-size eutherian mammals; see 
  <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Araujo et al., 2013</a>) and the burrow was cooler than 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub>. Additionally, we calculated the amount of energy (in kJ, where 20.1 J is equal to 1 mL O
  <sub>2</sub>; 
  <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">Schmidt-Nielsen, 1997</a>) required to thermoregulate for the entire month in burrows exclusively, in above-ground microsites exclusively, and in a combination of the two habitats. For the winter data, we summed the hourly energy expenditure predicted by the regression for the mean burrow temperature and the mean 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> for the entire month. We followed the same procedure for estimating the energy expenditure in the burrow for one month during summer, but because pygmy rabbits demonstrated high capacity for behavioral thermoregulation through above-ground rest site selection during summer (
  <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Milling et al., 2017</a>), we used the lowest measured hourly 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> in the regression for instances when the mean 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>e</sub> exceeded the estimated 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>uc</sub> of pygmy rabbits. To estimate energy expenditure above 35 °C during summer, we assumed that 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span xlink:href="peerj-06-4511-i009.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <span id="M10" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}$\dot V{{\rm{O}}_2}$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="mml-ieqn-9" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <span class="mi">V</span>
       <span class="mo">˙</span>
      </div>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mtext">O</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> increased at the same rate above the TNZ as it did with increasing cold below the TNZ, which is an assumption that is supported in at least two other species of leporid (
  <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">Hinds, 1973</a>, 
  <a rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-29">1977</a>). Because model uncertainty propagates to the predicted estimates of thermoregulatory costs, we used a simulation-based approach described by 
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Mandel (2013)</a> to estimate the standard errors of the expected cost for each season and microhabitat using the measured temperature values. This method relies on a parametric bootstrap approach using the estimated sampling distribution of the model parameters instead of analytical or numerical derivatives.
 </p>
</sec>
