<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fischer and Wood (1979)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mitchell et al. (1996)</xref> have suggested reducing the confounding effect of phenology to explore other mechanisms of drought avoidance and tolerance. Despite these early efforts, looking at the literature, a very large number of published research studies (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Araki et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kirigwi et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kuchel et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Honsdorf et al., 2014</xref>) related to responses to drought or heat (both phenotyping and genetics) completely ignored the effect of phenology that Fischer took into consideration in his early work to improve screening methodologies for drought adaptation (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fischer and Maurer, 1978</xref>). This oversight is unfortunate and at least partially hampers our progress to increase GYs under low rainfall and warm environments. Fortunately, there have been a few significant efforts to remove the confounding effects of phenology in various wheat populations for gene discovery at the International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center (CIMMYT; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Olivares-Villegas et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pinto et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lopes et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). The removal of confounding effects of phenology must be fully encouraged when developing new populations for gene discovery or other purposes related to studies of drought or heat adaptation (the evident exception would be for populations developed for the discovery of new phenology genes or related studies). In a scenario of increased temperatures in dry areas, as projected in the last IPCC report (available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipcc.ch/ipccreports/tar/wg2/index.php?idp=378" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ipcc.ch/ipccreports/tar/wg2/index.php?idp=378</ext-link>), these considerations become even more relevant due to the increased difficulty of breeding for a combination of stresses.
</p>
