<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="ijerph-11-07347-box001" position="float" class="boxed-text">
 <label class="label">Box 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">IPCC, Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) key findings for human health, 2014.</title>
 </caption>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Human health</bold>
 </p>
 <p class="p">Until mid-century, projected climate change will impact human health mainly by exacerbating health problems that already exist (very high confidence). Throughout the 21st century, climate change is expected to lead to increases in ill-health in many regions and especially in developing countries with low income, as compared to a baseline without climate change (high confidence). Examples include greater likelihood of injury, disease, and death due to more intense heat waves and fires (very high confidence); increased likelihood of under-nutrition resulting from diminished food production in poor regions (high confidence); risks from lost work capacity and reduced labor productivity in vulnerable populations; and increased risks from food- and water-borne diseases (very high confidence) and vector-borne diseases (medium confidence). Positive effects are expected to include modest reductions in cold related mortality and morbidity in some areas due to fewer cold extremes (low confidence), geographical shifts in food production (medium confidence), and reduced capacity of vectors to transmit some diseases. But globally over the 21st century, the magnitude and severity of negative impacts are projected to increasingly outweigh positive impacts (high confidence). The most effective vulnerability reduction measures for health in the near-term are programs that implement and improve basic public health measures such as provision of clean water and sanitation, secure essential health care including vaccination and child health services, increase capacity for disaster preparedness and response, and alleviate poverty (very high confidence). By 2100 for the high-emission scenario RCP8.5, the combination of high temperature and humidity in some areas for parts of the year is projected to compromise normal human activities, including growing food or working outdoors (high confidence).</p>
 <attrib class="attrib">Source: [
  <xref rid="B1-ijerph-11-07347" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]
 </attrib>
</boxed-text>
