<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many recent studies have investigated the influence of climate change on tick-borne disease upturn in different parts of the world. For instance, 
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Parola et al. (2008)</xref> correlated a cluster of Mediterranean spotted fever cases to a warming-mediated increase in the aggressiveness of brown dog ticks. Climate change has been implicated as an important driving force for the expansion of the taiga tick 
 <italic class="italic">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> habitat and the incidence of tick-borne encephalitis in the north of European Russia (
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tokarevich et al., 2011</xref>). It is also recognized that 
 <italic class="italic">I. ricinus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> sensu lato are spreading to northern latitudes and to higher altitudes as a result of the effects of climate change on host populations and on tick development, survival and seasonal activity (
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mannelli et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Léger et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Medlock et al., 2013</xref>). Nonetheless, the relationship between climate change and tick-borne diseases is not uniform across all regions and tick species. For instance, 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feria-Arroyo et al. (2014)</xref> used a maximum entropy approach to forecast the present and future distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic>-infected 
 <italic class="italic">I. scapularis</italic> in the Texas–Mexico transboundary region by correlating geographic data with climatic variables. According to this modelling approach, habitat suitable for the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">I. scapularis</italic> in the Texas–Mexico transboundary region will remain relatively stable until 2050. In the same way, the increased incidence of tick-borne encephalitis in Sweden during 2011–2012 is apparently more correlated to host population dynamics than to climate factors (
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Palo, 2014</xref>).
</p>
