<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">i</span>) Expand Measurement Networks to Include More Proxies for Methane Source Partitioning.
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiocarbon (
  <span class="sup">14</span>C; e.g., ref. 
  <a rid="r113" ref-type="bibr" href="#r113">113</a>), deuterium (i.e., 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i68" class="math">
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
   </div>
  </div>D), and “clumped” isotopologue measurements (molecules multiply substituted with rarer isotopes, such as 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CH
  <sub>3</sub>D or 
  <span class="sup">12</span>CH
  <sub>2</sub>D
  <sub>2</sub>; ref. 
  <a rid="r114" ref-type="bibr" href="#r114">114</a>) could provide additional leverage on partitioning the global budget because they would help isolate changes due to the most uncertain sectors (e.g., wetlands and OH). Specifically, radiocarbon measurements would help to separate fossil and nonfossil methane emissions [Petrenko et al. (
  <a rid="r113" ref-type="bibr" href="#r113">113</a>)] while clumped isotopologue measurements can constrain biogenic/thermogenic emissions [Stolper et al. (
  <a rid="r114" ref-type="bibr" href="#r114">114</a>)] or the loss via reaction with OH [Haghnegahdar et al. (
  <a rid="r115" ref-type="bibr" href="#r115">115</a>)]. However, both of these measurements will require advances in the analytical techniques before they could be used in ambient conditions. 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i71" class="math">
    <span class="mi">δ</span>
   </div>
  </div>D measurements, on the other hand, are less useful than radiocarbon or clumped isotopologues but the measurements are substantially easier to make. All of these isotopic measurements could help to constrain the most uncertain sectors in the methane budget, but there is a trade-off between added value and cost. Expanded studies of source signatures would be required for these isotope-driven approaches to provide maximum value. Radiocarbon shows potential with a less extensive source signature study requirement, as this tracer provides a cleaner delineation between fossil and contemporary methane sources. We encourage more observing-system simulation studies that quantify the added values of different proxies as well as redundancies, at the local to regional and global scales. In the interim, archiving of air samples [such as those at Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO), ref. 
  <a rid="r116" ref-type="bibr" href="#r116">116</a>] would provide an affordable strategic approach for enabling future measurements of attributive tracers that are infeasible with current technology or have not yet been recognized. As such, expansion of the air archive would enable the community to work backward in future years and address the most uncertain aspects of the methane budget.
 </p>
</sec>
