<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">ii</span>) Targeted Measurement and Modeling Programs Focused on Tropical Wetlands and Global OH.
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These sectors are currently the largest uncertainties in interpreting trends in methane and moving forward will continue to present a challenge unless we can improve the observational constraints and our ability to represent emissions/uptake with process-driven models. Development of high-resolution inventories that resolve, for example, wetland and lake emissions without double counting [e.g., Thornton et al. (
  <a rid="r117" ref-type="bibr" href="#r117">117</a>)] and spatially resolved isotopic source signatures [e.g., Ganesan et al. (
  <a rid="r118" ref-type="bibr" href="#r118">118</a>)] will be crucial to help reduce uncertainties in the use of isotopologue measurements. Dense observations (ground, airborne or space-borne, campaign or sustained) coupled with methane wetland model development for multiple tropical regions could provide a pathway toward more accurate representation and understanding of emissions from this sector. A similar observational approach was applied to the US oil and gas sector [Alvarez et al. (
  <a rid="r119" ref-type="bibr" href="#r119">119</a>)] that led to substantial improvements in the representation of methane sources [Zavala-Araiza et al. (
  <a rid="r120" ref-type="bibr" href="#r120">120</a>)]. Such a campaign could help improve the dynamics of methane emissions in wetland models (including regionally relevant isotopic source signatures) and their sensitivity to changes in temperature and inundation. Global OH presents a different challenge, as point measurements of OH are unlikely to adequately sample the variability in OH to the precision needed for methane trends (better than 3%). Further, the methyl chloroform constraints on OH are degrading with time as the ambient concentrations of methyl chloroform are now 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i72" class="math">
    <span class="mo">∼</span>
   </div>
  </div>2 parts per trillion (a 50-fold decrease from the 1990s) (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>); alternate strategies need to be developed [Liang et al. (
  <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>)]. Recent work from Zhang et al. (
  <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>) suggests that satellite observations of midtropospheric methane could be used for this purpose. Additional work using existing measurements, such as those from AirCore [Karion et al. (
  <a rid="r90" ref-type="bibr" href="#r90">90</a>)] or the Atmospheric Tomography Experiment (ATom) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://espo.nasa.gov/atom/content/ATom" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://espo.nasa.gov/atom/content/ATom</span>), and future campaigns should further investigate the possibility of inferring OH with midtropospheric measurements from satellites.
 </p>
</sec>
