<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for Emissions Mitigation</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While uncertainties in the methane budget exist, they should not detract from the key points discussed here. Namely, reducing anthropogenic methane emissions will slow or reverse the rise in atmospheric concentrations; however, depending on the timescale and magnitude of reduction, it may take decades before atmospheric levels decline. When considering recent decades, the stabilization period is emerging as anomalous due in part to fluctuations in natural sources/sinks, whereas the last decade of growth continues the long-term, increasing trend that is due to human activities.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even with present uncertainties on global methane trends, there have been a a number of recent advances in measurement technology that have tremendous potential for opportunistic mitigation (i.e., reducing emissions at no net cost). A few notable examples include identifying large fugitive leaks in oil and gas infrastructure and changing the diet of livestock. Specifically, remote sensing has demonstrated the ability to identify anomalous, large emitters and focused programs to use aircraft- or space-based observations to identify and mitigate emissions could prove cost efficient and effective (
  <a rid="r82" ref-type="bibr" href="#r82">82</a>, 
  <a rid="r121" ref-type="bibr" href="#r121">121</a>
  <a href="#r122">*</a>
  <a href="#r123">*</a>
  <a href="#r124">*</a>–
  <a rid="r125" ref-type="bibr" href="#r125">125</a>). Recent advances in frequency-comb spectrometers (
  <a rid="r126" ref-type="bibr" href="#r126">126</a>, 
  <a rid="r127" ref-type="bibr" href="#r127">127</a>) and affordable, small ground-based sensors may also provide a mitigation opportunity for superemitters in oil/gas basins (
  <a rid="r128" ref-type="bibr" href="#r128">128</a>). Changes in the diet of livestock could reduce the production of methane in dairy cattle without reducing milk production and, as such, could be an opportunity to reduce methane emissions from livestock (
  <a rid="r129" ref-type="bibr" href="#r129">129</a>, 
  <a rid="r130" ref-type="bibr" href="#r130">130</a>). Implementation of these or other mitigation strategies could help to curb future increases in atmospheric methane and provide detectable changes in the global methane burden within decades.
 </p>
</sec>
