<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The underlying driver of atmospheric energy redistribution</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our above analysis of the mechanisms of surface pattern correlation demonstrates that the atmospheric circulation is an efficient homogenizer of heterogeneous forcings, even under fixed-SST conditions. Indeed, a simple energy balance analysis, based on energetic constraints alone, illuminates why this atmospheric homogenization must occur (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Because land surface and atmospheric energy perturbations rapidly equilibrate to zero, the total ocean surface energy perturbation (Δ
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">O</span>
  <sub>surf</sub> + Δ
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <span class="sup">O</span>
  <sub>surf</sub>, with Δ
  <span class="italic">R</span> and Δ
  <span class="italic">H</span> denoting the radiative and heat components, respectively) must equal the TOA ERF over oceans (ERF
  <span class="sup">O</span>) plus that over land (ERF
  <span class="sup">L</span>) in the global mean: Δ
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">O</span>
  <sub>surf</sub> + Δ
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <span class="sup">O</span>
  <sub>surf</sub> = ERF
  <span class="sup">O</span> + ERF
  <span class="sup">L</span>. Vertical longwave and shortwave radiative energy conservation dictates that the TOA ERF must equal the sum of the surface radiative perturbation (Δ
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>surf</sub>
  <span class="italic">)</span> and any net (i.e., absorption less emission) atmospheric absorption change (ERF = Δ
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>surf</sub> + ΔAA). Thus, the surface heat flux perturbation over ocean will be equal to the total atmospheric absorption change over land and ocean plus the land surface radiative perturbation (Δ
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <span class="sup">O</span>
  <sub>surf</sub> = ΔAA
  <span class="sup">O+L</span> + Δ
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">L</span>
  <sub>surf</sub>), a balance that is evident in our simulations (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). This coupling between the atmospheric and surface energetics over the land and the ocean dictates that most of the spatial heterogeneity in the initial TOA forcing cannot be maintained in the response and must be rapidly transformed (from radiation to heat) and redistributed (from the land surface and atmosphere to the ocean surface) by the atmospheric circulation. This circulation adjustment process is fundamentally responsible for the similar ocean heat flux perturbation patterns between GHGs and aerosols.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Energy balance constraints on surface heat flux patterns. The top-of-atmosphere (TOA) effective radiative forcings (ERF) over land and ocean (ERF
     <span class="sup">L/O</span>) must equal the surface radiative perturbation (∆
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">L/O</span>
     <sub>surf</sub>) plus any atmospheric absorption (∆AA
     <span class="sup">L/O</span>) by vertical radiative energy conservation. Because the atmosphere and land surface cannot store energy long-term (
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">L</span>
     <sub>surf</sub> + 
     <span class="italic">H</span>
     <span class="sup">L</span>
     <sub>surf</sub> = 0, assuming positive downward sign convention), the TOA ERFs must be balanced through the ocean surface energy perturbation (
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">O</span>
     <sub>surf</sub> + 
     <span class="italic">H</span>
     <span class="sup">O</span>
     <sub>surf</sub>). The ocean heat flux perturbation (
     <span class="italic">H</span>
     <span class="sup">O</span>
     <sub>surf</sub>) will, therefore, be responsible for balancing the total atmospheric absorption change plus the land surface radiative perturbation
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5735_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e828" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Annual mean energy balance perturbations</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Perturbation</th>
      <th>Greenhouse gas</th>
      <th>Aerosol</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Ocean surf. heat flux (Δ
       <span class="italic">H</span>
       <span class="sup">O</span>
       <sub>surf</sub>)
      </td>
      <td>0.73 (1.4)</td>
      <td>−0.019 (−0.037)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Global atmos. abs. (ΔAA
       <span class="sup">O+L</span>)
      </td>
      <td>0.64 (1.2)</td>
      <td>0.41 (0.80)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Land surf. radiative flux (Δ
       <span class="italic">R</span>
       <span class="sup">L</span>
       <sub>surf</sub>)
      </td>
      <td>0.092 (0.18)</td>
      <td>−0.42 (−0.83)</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Annual-mean perturbations to energy balance terms in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> due to present-day greenhouse gases and aerosols in 10
     <span class="sup">15</span> W are shown quantitatively (globally averaged in W/m
     <span class="sup">2</span>). Heat flux and radiative flux terms are positive downward, and atmospheric absorption terms are positive into the atmosphere
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Notably, the fast homogenization described in this work operates primarily within a single hemisphere. The ratio of Northern Hemisphere to Southern Hemisphere TOA ERF does not differ significantly from that of the surface energy perturbation (1.0 and 1.1, respectively, for GHGs and 3.2 and 3.3, respectively, for aerosols). Under fixed-SST conditions, the Hadley circulation, the main mode of atmospheric cross-equatorial transport, cannot readily respond to perturbations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, constraining homogenization to within a given hemisphere.
 </p>
</sec>
