<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p content-type="flushleft" class="p">Ecosystems of the Himalayan region are especially vulnerable to climate change (
 <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>). Their high biodiversity supports a large commercial trade in wild-harvested medicinal species (
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>). Among these, caterpillar fungus (
 <italic class="italic">Ophiocordyceps sinensis</italic>, formerly called 
 <italic class="italic">Cordyceps sinensis</italic>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>), an entomopathogenic fungus that parasitizes over 50 species of 
 <italic class="italic">Thitarodes</italic> (Hepialidae) moth larvae in the Himalayan region (
 <xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>), has become one of the most valuable biological niche commodities in the world (
 <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>). Although it has been used in Tibetan and Chinese medicine for centuries, this fungus has experienced a surge in demand in recent decades, primarily among urban Chinese consumers (
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>). Used to treat a growing list of ailments, including cancer (
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>), its price increased by 20% per year on average from 1997–2012 (
 <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>). By 2017, high-quality pieces sold for more than 140,000 USD per kilogram in Beijing, more than three times the price of gold (caterpillar fungus prices from Tong Ren Tang Pharmaceutical Co. in Beijing on May 20, 2017; gold prices for May 2017 from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://goldprice.org/" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://goldprice.org/</ext-link>). For Bhutan, despite producing far less caterpillar fungus than its larger neighbors, the hundreds of kilograms that it sells each year make this niche commodity one of its most valuable exports (
 <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>). Consequently, caterpillar fungus sale generates a substantial proportion of regional gross domestic product (
 <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>), and harvesting has become a primary source of income for hundreds of thousands of collectors (
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>).
</p>
