<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Datasets</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We sourced monthly time series from 1950 to 2014 from the Center Research Unit (CRU V3.23; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://crudata.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://crudata.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/</span>) at a 0.5° resolution for air temperature (AT) and from the Met Office Hadley Center (HadISST; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst/</span>) at a 1° resolution for sea surface temperature (SST). These raster maps are composed of 67325 and 32619 monthly observations time series for AT and SST, respectively. The number reported for the latter excludes pixels that were mostly composed of ice as those pixels are not temperature time series and can’t be analyzed with EWIs.
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine whether some ecoregions were more likely to approach a critical transition than others, as already shown for other facets of change
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
   </span>, we extracted terrestrial biomes from the Köppen-Geiger climatic classification (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://koeppen-geiger.vu-wien.ac.at" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://koeppen-geiger.vu-wien.ac.at</span>) whereas for sea surface temperature we compiled biomes from the World Wildlife Fund (WWF) Marine Ecoregions Of the World (MEOW; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldwildlife.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldwildlife.org/</span>). The year band used for the Köppen-Geiger classification was 1986–2010. Note that we haven’t used the WWF classification for the terrestrial system because ecoregions were not comparable to the marine ecoregions. We nonetheless report result for this classification in the supplementary material (Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simple and composite EWI</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature time series were analyzed separately after removing the seasonal component. For this purpose, we decomposed the times series into seasonal, trend, and irregular components using a moving average procedure
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
   </span> and only conserved the last two components for the remaining analyses. We then filtered out long-term trends in the time series to achieve stationarity using a Gaussian kernel smoother with a fixed bandwidth of 50
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>. We chose a bandwidth of 50 because preliminary analyses performed on several pixels revealed that this value was appropriate. From the resulting time series, we compiled eight EWIs using a sliding window of half the length of the original time series using the package earlywarnings
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
   </span> within the R environment software
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
   </span>. However, we did not conserve all EWIs as some of them were highly correlated (ρ &gt; 0.99; p &lt; 0.001) and thus redundant (Supplementary Material Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). Consequently, our study is based on five EWIs: the first order autoregressive coefficient (i.e. a measure of temporal autocorrelation at first lag), the standard deviation, the coefficient of variation, the skewness, and the kurtosis. Although the first three EWIs are all expected to increase when approaching a critical transition, trends in skewness and kurtosis depend on whether the transition is toward an alternative state that is larger or smaller than the present state
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>. Nonetheless, given the global warming context, changes in the temperature regime, if any, are likely to be toward a warmer state and we therefore expect a rise in both indicators
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. This is because an increase in the frequency of extreme warm temperatures is expected to create an asymmetry towards the right hand of the distribution while, at the same time, the distribution is expected to become more “leptokurtic” with an increase in the frequency of rare values.
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the five above-mentioned EWIs, we computed a composite metric to determine whether it can reinforce evidence of an approaching transition relative to individual EWI. As a first step, we normalized each of the five EWIs by subtracting the long-run average of that indicator from the value of that indicator at time t, and divided it by the long-run standard deviation (i.e. z-score transformation)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
   </span>. To obtain the composite EWI, we then summed the normalized values of individual EWIs at each time step for each pixel, providing us time series for the composite EWI. For all EWIs (individuals and composite), we used Kendall’s τ rank correlation coefficient as a measure of their tendency to increase or decrease over time in each pixel, as classically done and recommended
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>. From the trends obtained, we generated “risk evaluation maps” for each EWI using the packages rworldmap
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
   </span> and rasterVis
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
   </span> to highlight spatial variations in the trends obtained for the different EWIs. We do not report negative trends because they are non-informative of approaching a critical transition and might rather indicate “critical speeding-up” whereby resilience to perturbations increases after the system has crossed a tipping point
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
   </span>. To evaluate the contribution of the five EWIs to the trends estimated with the composite EWI, we used a cross-validation approach where we (i) recalculated the composite EWI by removing one of the five EWIs, (ii) re-estimated the trend, and (iii) calculated the absolute difference between the new trend and the original trend. To determine how trends in the composite indicator varied with latitude, we focused on positive trends (i.e. positive Kendall’s τ coefficient) and calculated the average value of trends for each latitudinal band. Given that skewness and kurtosis have mixed support from the theoretical literature
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>, we also generated “risk evaluation maps” using a composite metric computed without these two EWIs (see Supplementary Material Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because trends in EWIs can be sensitive to the choice of sliding window and detrending bandwidth
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>, we repeated our analyses for different combinations of these parameters. We calculated the coefficient of variation of the trends obtained from the different combinations and used this as a measure of sensitivity of our results to the choice of sliding window and detrending bandwidth. A high value indicated a strong influence of these parameters on the estimated trend and thus a low robustness of our results.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying false positives</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For EWIs to be ecologically meaningful, one has to test whether the observed trends are different from the ones that would have been obtained by chance. To test whether trends computed for the composite EWI in each pixel were true positives, we generated 1,000 surrogate time series with the same length and autocorrelation structure as the original residual time series i.e. after the seasonal component and the long-term trend have been removed
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. The autocorrelation structure of the surrogate time series was set to the value estimated from the best linear autoregressive moving average model (ARMA) fitted to the original time series and identified using a stepwise selection procedure based on AIC. For each surrogate time series we then computed the composite EWI and calculated its long-term trend, as explained above. As a result we obtained a distribution of Kendall’s τ coefficients under the null hypothesis that there is no temporal trend in the composite EWI. Significance was defined as the percentage of simulated trends showing higher values than the observed trend with a threshold fixed to 10%. Because the overall procedure was very time-consuming, we only tested the significance of trends for the composite EWI.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data availability statement</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the data used in this manuscript are freely available on the web at the following addresses: - 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://crudata.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://crudata.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/</span>. - 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst/</span>. - 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://koeppen-geiger.vu-wien.ac.at/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://koeppen-geiger.vu-wien.ac.at/</span>. - 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldwildlife.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldwildlife.org/</span>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
