<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42" class="p">County-level crop yield datasets were obtained for maize, sorghum, and soybean for the period of 1968–2013 from the United States Department of Agriculture-National Agricultural Statistics Service (USDA-NASS). The beginning date of the study period (1968) was based on the start of the state level crop yield records. The earliest year with crop yield records available for all nine states studied was 1968 and, hence was chosen as the beginning of the study period. The USDA-NASS obtained yield data were reported in bushels per acre of wet weight. To make the data convenient for our use as well as for the greater scientific community, conversions were made to kilogram per hectare on a dry weight basis (adjusting to standard 15.5% grain moisture content), by using conversion factors of 62.77 for maize and 67.25 for soybean. The analysis on crop yield variability was limited to counties with data available for least 60% of the study period. It should be noted that the sorghum yield dataset was highly discontinuous prior to 1972 and following 2007 for majority of the counties, hence all analysis for sorghum was conducted for a 36-year period instead (1972–2007). Daily weather dataset consisting of maximum air temperature, minimum air temperature, and precipitation were obtained from the Global Historical Climatology Network (GHCN) provided through the National Climatic Data Centre of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NCDC-NOAA). The GHCN datasets are subjected to rigorous quality assurance reviews. Historical daily weather datasets for the period 1968–2013 were obtained for over 800 weather stations distributed over the study area. The selection is performed so that all the weather stations selected possess regular data during the temporal span of 46 years. Out of these sites, 672 sites are geographically located in nine states studied. The remainder of the sites was selected from the surrounding states along the boundaries of the study area, specifically Arkansas, Idaho, Illinois, Louisiana, Missouri, Montana, Minnesota, New Mexico, Utah, and Wisconsin to perform accurate and continuous interpolation of various variables along the edges of the study area. Lastly, the boundary datasets for various governmental units such as states and counties that were used to aid in the analysis and representation in the GIS environment were obtained from the USDA-Geospatial Data Gateway.</p>
