<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Respondents are known to often use scales of measurement that are non-linear and that differ between individuals when rating values [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. In our study the individuals' valuations were optimally scaled to maximize the sum of the largest eigenvalues [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], the number of which was determined using scree plots. The optimally scaled transformations (&gt;0) were then used to co-cluster the values and respondents/locations using the machine-learning technique of non-negative matrix factorization (NMF), to identify clusters of value items and show how the respondents' valuations were loaded on these, as described in [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s001" class="xref">S1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s002" class="xref">S2</xref> Figs) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s011" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>). To enable consideration of different value strengths, the respondents' loadings on the identified clusters of values were used to cluster respondents/locations into groups representing different value profiles using the Affinity Propagation Clustering methodology [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210426.g003" class="xref">Fig 3</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s003" class="xref">S3 Fig</xref>). To handle missing data in modelling, the questions were used as variables to impute five complete data sets (n = 302) using maximum likelihood methodology [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Conditional random forest methodology for ordinal data [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] was then applied to all five datasets to estimate the importance in terms of the ranked probability score [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] of value profiles and socio-demographic variables used as predictors of the two belief variables, respectively. This modelling methodology accounts for potential collinearity between predictor variables. The Student’s t-test was used to test for differences between groups described by numeric data, Pearson's χ
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>-test with simulated p value was used to test for differences between groups of categorical data [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], Wilcoxon rank-sum test with continuity correction was used to test for differences between groups described by data at ordinal level, and Kendall's rank correlation tau was used to test for correlations involving data at ordinal level. Average test results were computed over the imputed data sets. All tests were two-tailed and made at α = 0.05. All analyses were conducted using the R Project for Statistical Computing packages v3.3.1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], and in particular by applying the libraries Amelia II for multiple imputation [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>], "APCluster" for Affinity Propagation Clustering [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], "Aspect" for optimal scaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], "party" for conditional random forest modeling [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], "vcd" for visualizing categorical data [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>], and "NMF" for nonnegative matrix factorization [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>].
</p>
