<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The maintenance of genetic, species or functional diversity within ecosystems (see Folke 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref> for a detailed review), has also been advocated, primarily for the purpose of bet‐hedging: more diverse systems are better positioned to withstand climate change. For example, the effects of extreme drought on plant communities are patchy, affecting some species more than others (Buckland 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>). Consequently, maintaining the diversity of these plant communities ‘bet hedges’ that those species that are more tolerant or resistant to drought will be conserved (Di'az &amp; Cabido 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). The same principle has also been proposed at the genetic level, where populations with more genetic diversity are often found to be more resistant or resilient to extreme climatic events (Jump &amp; Peñuelas 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). While the general applicability of the ‘maintaining diversity’ approach is at least partially supported by evidence that management to improve diversity in one particular taxon or group often benefits diversity in other groups (Maskell 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), the underlying rationale is at best equivocal. One of the key reasons why increased diversity has been suggested to increase resilience is based on the concept of functional redundancy: more diverse ecosystems are assumed to be better able to maintain function even when some species are lost. Nonetheless, even in diverse systems, the loss of a single species can lead to major changes in ecosystem function (Di'az &amp; Cabido 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). The opposing side of this argument is that protecting the natural function of ecosystems, species and communities will enhance their capacity to cope with climate change. These processes can be biological (e.g. pollination, dispersal, succession of vegetation) or physical (e.g. erosion and deposition, river migration). A good example of the benefits of maintaining natural processes is the managed realignment of coasts already discussed. However, the approach has been applied more widely and often has multiple benefits. The retention of deadwood and/or debris in forests, for example, both improves the diversity of saproxylic invertebrates (Pawson 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and offers greater diversity of microhabitats for other potential occupants (Hobson &amp; Mickleburgh 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). This serves to illustrate a more general point: some (e.g. Bellard 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12602-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) have argued that our current knowledge of the impacts of climate change is highly disparate and uncertain. In such situations, ‘no regrets’ techniques are likely to be the most sensible to adopt.
</p>
