<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To model seabird energy requirements at a point in time and space, we used the mechanistic model Niche Mapper™, which evaluates the daily energy requirements of an individual using the biophysical properties of seabird bodies exposed to specific microclimatic conditions [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Niche Mapper consists of two submodels: a microclimate model and an animal model. The microclimate model uses macroclimate data (sea surface temperature (SST), air temperature, cloud cover, relative humidity and wind speed), substrate properties, geographic location and time of year to calculate hourly environmental conditions at the animal's height. Microclimate model calculations are detailed in [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The animal model uses the outputs from the microclimate model to iteratively solve a heat balance equation to find the metabolic rate needed for the animal to maintain its body temperature, accounting for convective, radiative, evaporative and solar heat fluxes with its microenvironment. Heat balance calculations are detailed in [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Little auks were modelled as a series of simple shapes that have well-understood heat transfer properties that enable surface temperature calculations—and thus heat flux calculations—given a certain core temperature to maintain: two ellipsoids for the head and torso and two cylinders for the featherless parts of the legs. Legs were modelled to allow heat loss, with possible changes in peripheral blood flow as a function of bird heat balance and external temperature. For time not spent diving or flying, little auks were modelled as floating on the ocean surface with legs and 25% of torso submerged in the water (electronic supplementary material, file S2). Auks were modelled as diving 24% of each day and flying 9% of each day (electronic supplementary material, file S2, [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]). All model input values are detailed in electronic supplementary material, file S2. Monthly average environmental input data were downloaded from the International Comprehensive Ocean-Atmosphere Data Set (ICOADS, 
 <uri xlink:href="http://icoads.noaa.gov/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://icoads.noaa.gov/</uri>, observed data, 1° × 1° resolution). The model was run to predict little auk daily energy requirements during the winter months (November, December, January and February) between 30° N to 80° N and 70° W to 15° E with a 1° × 1° grid size. A sensitivity analysis was performed to identify input variables which had the strongest influence upon modelled energy requirements (electronic supplementary material, file S3).
</p>
