<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">This study has compared and evaluated the composite indicators aggregated by the three additive and the three multiplicative utility functions for the IPCC’s vulnerability assessment components. The selection of aggregation frameworks needs to be carefully determined according to the purpose of vulnerability assessments and the characteristics of assessment components, and compensability is one of the basic selection criteria in various aggregation schemes, each with its own benefits and limitations. As an example case, the Unite Nations Development Programme (UNDP) revised the Human Development Index (HDI) by a multiplicative composite scheme, since the additive structure of the original HDI had been criticized for its drawback that allowed for perfect substitution across the three assessment components of health, education, and income
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. Although both additive and multiplicative aggregation schemes are compensatory schemes, the latter offers lesser compensation for low value components compared with the former with constant trade-offs across all components. In addition, the multiplicative aggregation scheme requires that all components have the same directional elasticity to a composite indicator in order to avoid undesirable ranking reversal problems. As selected for the coastal flood vulnerability to climate change in this study, the multiplicative scheme can provide a better solution to avoid full compensability. Under certain circumstances, however, it would be a partial solution still with some degree of compensability. When it should be interpreted as symmetrical importance of components, it can be solved by a non-compensatory multi-criteria approach
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. All studies on vulnerability assessments may have limitations and drawbacks in processes for constructing composite indicators. This study employs the min-max normalization method where proxy variables are transformed into a common scale between 1 to 100 and also adopts an equal weighting assumption, the possible weighting systems in lack of a statistical or an empirical basis on causal relationships or consensus of assessment components. Therefore, this comparative case study for various composite indicators needs further investigation on several important processes affecting composite indicator outcomes, particularly for the selection and uncertainty in representative proxy variables for each attribute component, normalization methods for transforming variables measured at different units or scales into a common domain, and weighting schemes for variables and components to contribute to the analysis in different scales.
</p>
