<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We carried out live-trapping at nine sites across Carlo Station, Tobermorey Station, Cravens Peak and Ethabuka Reserves, an 8000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> region in the Simpson Desert, southwestern Queensland, Australia (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS170384F1" class="xref">figure 1</xref>). Small mammals (native rodents, 
 <italic class="italic">Notomys alexis, Pseudomys hermannsburgensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Rattus villosissimus</italic>, and dasyurid marsupials, including 
 <italic class="italic">Sminthopsis youngsoni</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Sminthopsis hirtipes</italic> and the predatory mulgara 
 <italic class="italic">Dasycercus blythi</italic>) and reptiles were live-trapped using pitfall traps (16 cm diameter PVC pipe dug 60 cm deep into the ground), each equipped with a 5 m drift fence of aluminium flywire to increase trap efficiency [
 <xref rid="RSOS170384C37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Pitfall traps were arranged on 1 ha grids comprising six lines of six pitfall traps spaced 20 m apart (i.e. 36 pitfall traps per grid). Sites contained 2--12 grids and were spaced at least 10 km apart. Grids within sites were set 0.5–2 km apart in randomly chosen positions along access tracks. We opened traps two to six times a year from 1990 to 2012 for two to six nights at one site (Main Camp), and from 1995 to 2012 at eight more sites (Shitty Site, Field River South, Field River North, South Site, Kunnamuka Swamp East, Carlo, Tobermorey East and Tobermorey West). We conducted trapping sessions in both the Austral summer and winter each year to maximize species captures due to seasonal changes, such as rainfall and temperature. Each animal was given a unique individual identification mark. Long-term (17–22 years; up to 130 sampling trips per site) live-trapping (205 524 trap nights) yielded 21 202 captures of 11 species of small mammals and 17 681 captures of 58 species of reptiles [
 <xref rid="RSOS170384C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. We pooled animal captures per grid at each site per trip (sampling period; electronic supplementary material, table S1) and calculated the minimum numbers of animals known to be alive (i.e. total captures per grid–recaptures). Appropriate permissions and licences to conduct the fieldwork were obtained from the Queensland Government (Permits WITK15192514 and WISP15192514).
</p>
