<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species Occurrence Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The known distribution of 
  <span class="italic">P. japonica</span> was assembled from the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (
  <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">GBIF.org 2018</a>), the European and Mediterranean Plant Protection Organization global database (
  <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">EPPO 2018</a>), the Center for Environmental and Research Information Systems (
  <a rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0008">CERIS 2018</a>), and the literature (
  <a rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0012">Clausen et al. 1927</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0021">Fleming 1976</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0009">Chebanov 1977</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0058">Simões et al. 1993</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0038">Krell 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0048">Pavesi 2014</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0015">EPPO 2017</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0066">Urban 2018</a>; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>). Occurrences were verified where possible through either validated photos or specimen records. Records with incomplete locality information were omitted. Reports of this species in portions of China and North Korea are unreliable, and the species has yet to be confirmed on the mainland of Asia (
  <a rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0021">Fleming 1976</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0054">Reed et al. 1991</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0001">Allsopp 1996</a>, 
  <a rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0052">Potter and Held 2002</a>). In total, 1,028 occurrence localities were found with 40 in Asia (e.g., Japan and Russia), 6 in Europe, and 981 in North America and 1 in Central America.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Known global (A) and North American (B) distribution of 
    <span class="italic">Popillia japonica</span>. Blue circles represent established populations, green triangles indicate locations where 
    <span class="italic">P. japonica</span> has been detected, and red triangles represent locations where 
    <span class="italic">P. japonica</span> has been eradicated. Pink areas represent national or subnational administrative units where the species has been recorded as established, dashed areas indicate national or subnational administrative units that are partially infested, and blue areas represent national or subnational administrative units currently under annual surveillance and chemical control programs.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="iez023f0001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
