<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Applied within localized agrarian settings, intersectional approaches offer ways of understanding how social dimensions of identity (encompassing gender) are bound up in systems of power and social institutions (both formal and informal) to shape situation-specific interactions between individual farmers, households, and agroecosystems. These intersections result in unique and dynamic adaptation needs. At this (or any other) scale, there is no one approach or defined set of methods that represent best practices for seeking intersectional understandings of vulnerability relating to climate change. We agree with Davis (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2008</xref>), Lykke (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">2011</xref>), and Kaijser and Kronsell (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2014</xref>) who stress that the complexity of intersectionality demands a multiplicity of disciplinary perspectives and should not be boxed in by any one set of priorities or uses. That being said, there are novel approaches and methods that support intersectional understandings and are applicable to issues that link climate change, livelihood strategies, and agroecosystem management. One such approach is based on the 
 <italic class="italic">Livelihoods as Intimate Government</italic> (LIG) framework and methodological approach (Carr 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2013</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2014</xref>). LIG encompasses non-material factors (for example, societal norms and other informal institutions that shape and are embodied through livelihoods decisions) that influence the exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity of certain groups and individuals facing uncertain climate futures. In so doing, LIG offers an explicit method for gathering empirical data needed to support an intersectional framing. The method is composed of a four-step approach for capturing the various motivations for livelihoods decisions, from material provisioning to the maintenance of social status, without making a priori assumptions as to which motivation is of highest importance (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>; Carr 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2014</xref>). 
</p>
