<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34838-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Elevational range of breeding birds and its trend over time</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we assessed the presence of a temporal trend in the species’ reference points. To this aim, we fitted a weighted linear regression using the elevation value of each reference point as dependent variable, the year as independent variable, and the number of sampling units as weight. The analysis was performed using the 
  <span class="italic">nlme</span> package (Pinheiro, Bates, DebRoy, &amp; Sarkar, 
  <a rid="ece34838-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34838-bib-0055">2017</a>) in R. Then, we classified the patterns of elevational range change for all species showing a significant trend in at least one of their reference points as: (a) “contraction” when the changes of the reference points brought to a distance reduction between the extreme reference points; (b) “expansion” when the changes of the reference points brought to an increase of the distance between extreme reference points; (c) “shift” when the changes of the reference points were consistent between each other. Depending on which reference points changed, we referred the observed change to the lower (OBL and CBL) or upper (CBR and OBR) reference points. If the slopes of the year pertaining to the two extreme reference points showed a significant trend with same sign but were significantly different between them, we evaluated if their change caused either a contraction or an expansion of species' range.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have to acknowledge that reference points’ estimation using unlimited‐distance point count technique may be less accurate for open habitat species, since individuals observed at large distances (and different elevations) could be associated to the elevation of the point where observations were performed. Thus, due to the higher variance in observed elevation for open habitat species and the consequent estimation of their reference points, the long‐term changes in elevational distribution could result not significant (type II error). Moreover, the same kind of error could arise from the impossibility to take into account the imperfect detection that, however, should be quite limited according to Fuller and Langslow (
  <a rid="ece34838-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34838-bib-0028">1984</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
