<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To model the effects of forest harvest, we comprehensively assessed information from recent forest harvest studies in the region. We used a conservative scenario of changes in magnitude and timing of stream temperature and flow. Accordingly, our forest harvest scenario represented a composite of current practices that include riparian buffers and a 40-year rotation. More generally, the literature suggested increased summer temperatures, increased summer flows, and increased flow from winter storm events for 1–2 decades following each harvest. Hence, for each cutting, we elevated stream temperatures for 15 years, with the first five years having daily mean stream temperature increased by 0.37°C [
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] uniformly, followed by a gradual, linear decrease in daily mean stream temperature by 0.037°C each year for 10 years until recovery of baseline conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Therefore, baseline temperature values were restored in year 16 and again in year 57 because that is when the forest canopy would be expected to be restored, providing shade to the stream. Responses of flow regimes to forest harvest are variable, but in the Coast Range of Oregon, alterations to flow regimes can last for 20 years with changes to storm events and seasonal low flows [
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. We increased daily water yield by 20% on the days when a storm event occurred that generated flow &gt; 2 standard deviations above the annual mean, because although water yield increases from forest harvest are highly variable, they generally increase by approximately 20% [
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. We increased summer (July-September) daily mean flows by 45% above baseline for five years [
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0135334.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], then decreased summer mean flows by 2.25% per year for 15 years until baseline was reached in year 20 post-harvest and again in year 60, because as the forest regrows, more water is used by trees.
</p>
