<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSIONS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study provides the first comprehensive distribution map of tree mycorrhizal association in the contiguous United States. We provide empirical evidence based on national forest inventory data to suggest how global changes may have affected the shift of mycorrhizal associations at the continental scale. We found that AM tree dominance was positively associated with both soil C and N stocks, particularly for temperate forests, which challenges the prevailing idea that EM tree dominant ecosystems store more C than AM tree dominant ecosystems (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>). We note, however, that soil C:N ratio was negatively associated with AM tree dominance, supporting recent findings that showed a positive association between soil C:N ratio and EM tree dominance driven by low soil N instead of by high C stock in EM tree dominant ecosystems (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>). Our results suggest that increases in AM tree dominance in the eastern United States may increase soil N stocks, inducing a positive feedback of nutrient acceleration, at least in the upper surface soils. A better understanding of the role of dominant forest mycorrhizal association type in ecosystem processes at global scales and the mechanisms responsible for forest soil C storage is critical for improving ecosystem models to predict forest ecosystem processes and functions in global climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
