<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distribution and drivers of tree mycorrhizal association patterns</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using FIA vegetation data and tree mycorrhizal type information, we mapped the relative abundance of more than 3 million AM and EM trees across the conterminous United States (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). While patterns of mycorrhizal associations and associated drivers have been reported previously, these studies were based on species occurrence data (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>), and they covered lesser spatial extent (
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>) and examined fewer vegetation survey plots than our study (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>). Our results indicate that AM trees are more dominant in dry and warm ecoregions, while EM trees are more dominant in humid and cold ecoregions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>, A and B). In the western United States, AM trees are dominant in the subtropical desert and steppe regions, while EM trees are dominant in the northwestern and intermountain west regions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a> and fig. S1). AM and EM trees are well mixed in the eastern United States, with more AM trees in the hot continental region and more EM trees in the western portion of the warm continental region (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> and fig. S1). Using a mixed-effects model that accounts for the spatial heterogeneity between plots in different subecoregions, we found that climate is an important driver of tree mycorrhizal association patterns at the continental scale (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>). Overall, AM tree dominance was negatively associated with mean annual precipitation (MAP) and positively associated with mean annual temperature (MAT) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>), although the magnitude and direction of effect sizes differed in some ecoregions. Forest tree basal area, which was used as an indicator of forest successional stage, had smaller effects on AM tree dominance compared with climatic factors, implying that climate is a more important driver of the continental tree mycorrhizal association patterns than successional stage (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Distribution of forest tree mycorrhizal types and their associated factors in forests of the contiguous United States.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Geographical distribution of AM tree dominance. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Distribution of AM tree dominance in climatic space. MAP, mean annual precipitation; MAT, mean annual temperature. (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Relative effects of MAP, MAT, and tree basal area on AM tree dominance. Each dot in (A) and (B) represents a plot and is colored on the basis of the associated AM-EM tree dominance. Boundaries of ecoregions (solid line) and nested subecoregions (dashed lines) in (A) are based on Cleland 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">
     <span class="italic">58</span>
    </a>). Circles in (B) indicate ecoregion-level mean MAT and MAP values with the associated SDs. The circle is colored on the basis of the mean AM tree dominance, and the size is proportional to the number of plots (log scale). Effects of MAP, MAT, and basal area on AM tree dominance across ecoregions in the contiguous United States (C) were tested using generalized mixed-effects models with subecoregions included as a random effect in each model. Significant coefficient estimates are plotted in (C) as solid circles, and nonsignificant ones are plotted as open circles. Circle size is proportional to the number of plots (log scale). The number beside each dot in (B) and (C) represents the associated ecoregion in (A). Error bars in (C) are SEs.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav6358-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
