<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relationships between tree mycorrhizal associations and soil C and N</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the potential consequences of mycorrhizal association shifts on C and N dynamics, we analyzed the relationships between AM tree dominance and soil C and N stocks (litter layer and 0- to 20-cm depth of the mineral soil) on plots where both soil attributes and associated vegetation were measured (2113 plots) using linear regression models. In general, the associations between AM tree dominance and soil C and N stocks were positive in mesic temperate ecoregions but negative in dry ecoregions; however, most ecoregions had a negative relationship between soil C:N ratio and AM tree dominance (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, A to C). Across the study area, AM-dominated forests had 28% more soil N and 8% more soil C than EM-dominated forests (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, A and B, and table S2). The higher increase in soil N stocks (relative to soil C stocks) in mesic ecoregions and the lower decrease in soil N stocks (relative to soil C stocks) in dry ecoregions resulted in a negative relationship between soil C:N ratio and AM tree dominance along the continental AM tree dominance gradient (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, A to C).
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Associations between forest soil C and N with forest tree mycorrhizal type and environmental factors in forest ecosystems in the United States.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span> to 
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Relationships between AM tree dominance and soil (A) C stock, (B) N stock, and (C) C:N ratio (based on 0- to 20-cm depth mineral soil and litter layer). Linear regression lines were fitted by ecoregion (solid line, 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05; dotted line, 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.05; red, positive slope; blue, negative slope). Inset shows coefficient (slope) estimate of the fitted line for each ecoregion (colored bars indicate significant relationship at 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05; red, positive; blue, negative). (
    <span class="bold">D</span> to 
    <span class="bold">F</span>) Effects of AM tree dominance and environmental factors on soil (D) C stock, (E) N stock, and (F) C:N ratio across ecoregions of the United States. Coefficient estimates in (D) to (F) are based on mixed-effect models at ecoregion level with subecoregions as a random effect. Significant coefficient estimates are plotted as solid circles, and nonsignificant ones are plotted as open circles. Circle size is proportional to the number of plots (log scale). Error bars are SEs. The number beside each bar in (A) to (C) and each dot in (D) to (F) represents the associated ecoregion in (A). Soil data summary is available in table S2.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav6358-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using mixed-effects models, we further tested how forest mycorrhizal association and environmental factors are related to soil attributes for each ecoregion after accounting for the spatial heterogeneity between plots in different subecoregions by adding subecoregions as random intercepts in the models. We found that AM tree dominance, climate, and soil texture had significant associations with soil C and N stocks and C:N ratio, although with different effect sizes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, D to F). Overall, AM tree dominance was positively associated with soil C and N stocks and negatively with C:N ratio across the ecoregions, consistent with site-based patterns recently reported (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>). Among the climatic factors, MAP tended to have positive associations with soil C and N stocks, while MAT have negative associations. Soil C and N stocks were similar between the top 20 cm of the mineral soil and the top 20 cm plus litter layer (fig. S4) owing to the much smaller size of the litter C and N pools.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observational nature of our data precludes us from determining whether AM trees are causing elevated N levels in soil (as opposed to merely responding to them). It is possible that AM trees can elevate soil N (pool sizes and transformation rates) by releasing high chemical quality litter to soil. Several studies of temperate trees have shown that AM litters generally decay faster than EM litters in common garden studies (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) and meta-analyses (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>). Given that higher chemical quality litter leads to both greater rates of N transformations (
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>) and the formation of more protected (i.e., stable) soil organic matter [sensu the MEMS (Microbial Efficiency-Matrix Stabilization) hypothesis] (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>), increasing AM dominance may lead to elevated N levels in soil (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>). Contemporary theory on soil organic matter stabilization and turnover predicts that changes in AM versus EM dominance can alter C and N cycling in 30 to 45 years (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>), well within the time frame of changes detected in the FIA dataset. Thus, our contention that AM trees may be contributing, in part, to N accumulation is a testable hypothesis but requires further inquiry.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last, separating cause and effect in this instance may be of limited importance given that tree species often modify soils in ways that tend to exacerbate or enhance the preexisting biogeochemical condition (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>). Thus, while we cannot rule out that the species are merely responding to the high N soils, both processes likely contribute to the maintenance of the biogeochemical syndromes observed. More experiments and/or long-term repeated measures of soil stocks are needed to test the mechanisms of these associations. Nevertheless, the consistent large-scale patterns in forests across multiple ecoregions suggest that dominant tree mycorrhizal type could be an important driver of nutrient and C dynamics in forests through positive/negative feedbacks associated with AM/EM plant traits (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that AM-dominated forests tend to be underlain by soils with lower C:N than EM-dominated soils [(
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>); 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4C</a>], the increasing dominance of AM trees could have consequences for forest ecosystem functions and services. Low or small ratios are often used as proxies for rates of microbial N transformations in soils such as nitrification and nitrate leaching losses (
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>), as well as for ecosystem sensitivity to N deposition (
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>). Thus, forests of the eastern United States may be experiencing an acceleration of N cycling—owing to the shifts in AM dominance. The consequences of nutrient acceleration would likely be profound for water quality if, for example, elevated nitrification rates enhance nitrate export to lakes and rivers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The consequences of nutrient acceleration may be most profound for forest productivity, which can feed back to affect climate change. Most AM-dominated ecosystems cannot sustain a high level of productivity under elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> unless the availability of soil N is high (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>). Thus, if increases in AM tree dominance lead to an acceleration of N cycling, then AM-dominated forests in the eastern United States may be strong sinks for atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub>. However, if the AM-induced acceleration of N cycling leads to substantial ecosystem N losses (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>) or results in N stabilization in soil organic matter (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>), then there may be little stimulation of forest productivity. In addition, shifting the balance of AM-EM vegetation could also be influenced by N-induced phosphorus (P) limitation and more severe drought periods (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>). While N-induced P limitation has long been considered as something that would only occur in forests south of the Last Glacial Maximum (where mineral P levels are extremely low), recent evidence from northern ecosystems challenges that paradigm (
  <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
   <span class="italic">42</span>
  </a>). Either way, our results indicate that changes in N cycling owing to increasing AM tree dominance could have profound consequences for C and N retention and loss in forests and hence, the degree to which forests feedback to climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
