<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">The Tien Shan-Pamir-Karakoram (TPK) mountain complex is the “water tower” of the Central Asian countries east of the Aral Sea (Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Uzbekistan, Kazakhstan, and Turkmenistan), and the Xinjiang province of western China (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) that was generated from the DEM data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://earthexplorer.usgs.gov/</ext-link>) on ArcGIS 9 ArcMap 9.3 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esri.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esri.com</ext-link>). Along the Western slope of the divide, the major rivers Amu Darya (WAM), Syr Darya (WSY), and Chu River (WCH) flow to Central Asian countries, Tajikistan, Kyrgyzstan, Uzbekistan and Turkmenistan, supplying over 90% of the water resources for 22 million people in Central Asia
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. The Ili River (WIL) originates in Xinjiang China and flows to the lake Balkhash in Kazakhstan. Along the Eastern slope of the divide, the Junagr river system (EJG) includes rivers originating from northern side of the eastern Tian Shan and flowing into the Jungar Basin; the Kaidu River (EKD) flows into the Boston Lake, and the Weigan River (EWG), Tailan River (ETL), Tarim River (ETR) and Kashgar River (EKG) flow into the Tarim Basin. The ETR consists of the Aksu River originating from the middle Tien Shan, the Yarkant River from Karakoram, and the Hotan River from the western Kunlun mountain. These rivers from the eastern TPK contributes to the water supply for 20 million people in the Xinjiang province, and sustains downstream ecosystems, which are currently degraded
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. Changes in the magnitude or seasonality of runoff may thus have important consequences downstream to both human society and ecosystems. From inventories (see Supplementary Information), the study area is covered 27,101 glaciers with a total area of 36,539 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (see Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>) for six main rivers on the eastern slope of the TPK mountains and four main rivers on the western slope (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Glacier runoff plays an important role in regulating the streamflow and is also sensitive to climate change.
</p>
