<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The complexity of models resultant in MAXENT environment is primarily driven by the following two factors; feature type and regularization parameter (Moreno-Amat et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Maxent offers a range of five function forms known as “feature types” to explain the relationship between predictor variables and the probability of species occurrence. These feature types are labeled as Linear (L), Quadratic (Q), Hinge (H), Product (P), and Threshold (T) (see Phillips et al., 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Elith et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref> for details). Maxent allows users to select and combine different function forms manually or picks functions or their combinations automatically when left in the default “Auto Feature” mode. Most of the published MAXENT-based studies rely on the default options of feature type and regularization parameters, which means that model complexity and the risk of over-fitting is completely ignored by the researchers (Muscarella et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). The second key factor that determines the complexity of MAXENT models is the regularization parameter. As part of the modeling process, MAXENT pushes or modifies the predictor values (such as variance and mean) of environmental variables as close as possible to the values describing actual presence points, which frequently leads to over-fitting of the model. To counter over-fitting, MAXENT uses the regularization parameter to control the complexity of models (the default value is 1). The regularization parameter limits the number of “features” in the model, depending on the number of presence records (fewer records allow for fewer features to be included). A higher value of the regularization parameter penalizes the number of features and thus leads to less complex models (Merow et al., 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Various studies have confirmed that calibrating MAXENT models with default settings frequently leads to highly complex models, a species-specific tuning of the model is thus recommended (Moreno-Amat et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). In this study, we generated all possible combinations of features types in combination with a range of regularization parameter values; 0.1, and then 1–10 with an increment of 1. We then used ENMeval R package to select the model with the lowest AICc (corrected Akaike Information Criterion) value which was then used as the most appropriate (least over-fitted model) out of the whole suite of models (Warren and Seifert, 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Muscarella et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
