<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-02724" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sickle cell disease (SCD) is one of the most common genetic disorders in the world. The main clinical manifestations of this disease, which vary from person to person and change over time, include intermittent and recurrent acute severe pain episodes, as a result of vaso-occlusion. These painful crises frequently require hospital admissions and can lead to serious complications [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02724">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02724">2</a>]. Vaso-occlusive crisis (VOC) is caused by a complex series of processes that are initiated by the polymerization of deoxygenated sickle hemoglobin (HbS) [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02724">3</a>]. There is a great variability in the expression of the disease. Some people have no painful crises, while others may have six or more per year [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-02724">4</a>]. Several factors that may promote VOC have been identified, but there are still many unknown factors. Among these factors, the environment might play a role in the occurrence of VOC [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02724">5</a>]. Indeed, several studies have already identified climate and infectious diseases as factors associated with painful crises [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02724">3</a>,
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02724">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02724">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-02724">7</a>]. French Guiana is the French territory most affected by sickle cell disease. The population, of African ancestry, consists mainly of three groups: Guianese Creoles, Maroons (descendants of runaway slaves), and, more recently, Haitian immigrants [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-02724">8</a>]. The estimated incidence at birth is one in 227, and the overall frequency of hemoglobin AS (HbAS, made up of normal hemoglobin A and sickle hemoglobin S) carriers is 10% [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-02724">9</a>]. The major SCD groups include the three main genetic forms that combine different structural hemoglobin variants or thalassemia syndromes (hemoglobin S HbS, hemoglobin C HbC, β-thalassemia): HbSS (68%), HbSC (25%), and Sβ thalassemia (7%) [
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02724">10</a>]. Identifying a link between environmental factors and VOC hospital admissions would improve patient care and patient management in the hospital, and aid in more targeted prevention and therapeutic education for patients with SCD in French Guiana. This study investigates the associations between different environmental factors, such as: climate, infectious outbreaks, and weekly emergency visits and hospital admissions for VOC.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethical Approval: This study was presented at the Cayenne General Hospital Ethical Committee (Number 1-2017-V2) and the database was declared at the Commission Nationale Informatique et Liberté (CNIL, Number 2087477). Patients were informed of the utilization of their data with an informative poster in the medical units concerned with sickle cell disease.</p>
</sec>
