<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-ijerph-16-02724" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study shows the temporal variability of the frequency of vaso-occlusive crises among SCD patients, which could be partially explained by environmental factors. Indeed, emergency visits for VOC were influenced by climatic factors, with a decrease in humidity leading to an increase in emergency visits for VOC. This link has already been described in the literature and is explained by a greater risk of dehydration [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-02724">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02724">13</a>]. Furthermore, this decrease in humidity occurs mainly in the dry season when the sun is stronger. This is because the skin is exposed and sweating, and therefore, can be more vulnerable to sudden changes in temperature (air conditioner wind, etc.) [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-02724">12</a>]. A decrease in mean temperature was also associated with an increase in emergency visits for VOC in our study. This association was already described elsewhere and lies in the fact that a decrease in temperature leads to skin cooling, followed by vasoconstriction of the peripherical vessels, and reduction in the velocity of blood circulation [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-02724">14</a>]. The red blood cells then spend a longer time in a deoxygenated circulation zone, which causes the polymerization of hemoglobin S and the occurrence of a VOC [
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-16-02724">15</a>]. Although climatic variations are apparently not as marked in tropical environments as in temperate zones, they are sufficient to increase the number of painful crises leading to an emergency visit. In our tropical context where temperatures are mostly hot throughout the year, this may be overlooked by patients and sometimes by their physicians. Intuitively, the rainy season would be the riskier season because it can be cooler when the sky is cloudy and the rainfall is abundant. Indeed, there is a link with this rainy season and VOC. However, counter-intuitively what we show is that the dry season may also be associated with a higher risk of VOC. The present results suggest that this message should be reemphasized for patients and health care professionals, and that patients should remain vigilant in the hotter dry season.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When looking more specifically at severe painful crises that required hospitalization (with or without prior emergency visit), the associated factors were different and influenza was the only explanatory series that correlated significantly with VOC in the multivariate analysis. This association has already been mentioned in the literature, but is rarely tested [
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-16-02724">16</a>]. The fact that flu causes more serious and frequent complications among SCD patients (severe pain crisis, pneumonia, acute chest syndrome, etc.) explains, in part, the increase in hospitalizations for VOC during influenza epidemics [
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-16-02724">16</a>]. The question of vaccination also arises here. Protection against infections is a major goal of any care program for patients with SCD. The seasonal flu vaccine is reimbursed by health insurance in France. The vaccine coverage of SCD patients against influenza in France is not exactly known, but it is estimated to be around 30% in French Guiana according to an informal survey of physicians. A study in the UK showed an immunization against viral influenza of 12% in adults and 8% in children [
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-02724">17</a>]. In addition, influenza, by altering the bronchial mucosa, often paves the way for subsequent pneumococcal infections [
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-02724">18</a>]. Patients with sickle cell disease are normally vaccinated, but vaccine valences do no cover all pneumococcal serotypes. Thus, maximizing pneumococcal vaccine coverage should be ensured for all patients.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study has several limitations. First of all, the data about VOC were retrospectively collected from medical files that are not intended to be analyzed in a research context, which implies caution should be taken when regarding data quality. For this reason, we started from the year 2010 because the data collection was more complete thereafter. The study period was correct for this type of analysis, but ideally could have been a little longer. The study did not have access to more detailed clinical data in order to attempt to better understand the most likely chain of events leading to VOC. Future studies should aim to improve the description of context, and clinical signs and symptoms in the medical records, in order to conduct more detailed analyses.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some explanatory series could have been added, in particular pollution measures. It has already been demonstrated that the exposure to air pollution can increase complications and hospitalizations among patients with SCD [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02724">3</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02724">6</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-16-02724" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-16-02724">19</a>]. However, these parameters could not be tested in our study because the quality of the data was not good enough to be integrated into the model. The amount of missing data related either to a failure of the measuring device or to defective measures was substantial. The integration of chikungunya and Zika epidemics as explanatory series of VOC would probably have been consistent and relevant. Indeed, graphically, the link between hospitalization for VOC series and these outbreaks is quite clear, but so far there has been only one chikungunya epidemic and one Zika epidemic in French Guiana, which does not allow a time series analysis. The impact of dengue fever should also be tested, but so far the two outbreaks, one in 2010 and the other in 2013, do not provide enough data for analysis. It seemed, however, that graphically there were no correlations between the dengue fever series and the two VOC series.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, patients should be aware of increased risks during flu epidemics, low temperature episodes, and low humidity episodes. Therapeutic patient education should enable people with SCD to manage the increased risk of VOC in the presence of aggravating factors. Home prevention measures, such as maintaining good hydration and averting excessive temperature differences, even in the tropical context of French Guiana, could avoid some painful crises. Moreover, physicians should encourage patients to get immunized for influenza vaccine every year. Improving the influenza vaccine coverage and optimizing pneumococcal vaccine coverage could reduce the number of hospitalizations and admissions for VOC during the flu outbreaks. It is essential that patients know their disease, as well as the mechanisms that underlie it, in order to better adapt their behaviors. This is the central principle of therapeutic patient education. It therefore seems important to communicate these results to patients, but also to their entourage and to physicians, to improve knowledge about the sickle cell disease and its management.</p>
</sec>
