<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The site selectivity of protein nitration is influenced by the molecular structure of the protein, the nitrating agent, and the reaction conditions. For example, different preferred reaction sites were observed for the birch pollen allergen Bet v 1, the egg allergen ovalbumin, and bovine serum albumin.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref304" class="xref">304</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref328" class="xref">328</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref333" class="xref">333</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref354" class="xref">354</xref>
 </sup> Upon exposure of Bet v 1 to atmospherically relevant concentrations of O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>/NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and physiologically relevant concentrations of ONOO
 <sup class="sup">–</sup>, the preferred sites of nitration were tyrosine residues with high solvent accessibility and within a hydrophobic environment. Accordingly, nitrated tyrosine residues occurred mainly in the C-terminal helix and in the hydrophobic cavity (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.6b04908/suppl_file/es6b04908_si_001.pdf" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Figure S4</ext-link>).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref328" class="xref">328</xref>
 </sup> Both are key positions for the binding of specific IgE,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref369" class="xref">369</xref>
 </sup> as well as ligands like fatty acids, cytokines, and flavonoids.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref370" class="xref">370</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref372" class="xref">372</xref>
 </sup> The binding of such ligands may be involved in allergic and inflammatory immune responses by stabilizing Bet v 1 against endo/lysosomal degradation.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref373" class="xref">373</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, nitration-related changes in ligand-binding capacity might influence the interaction of allergenic proteins like Bet v 1 with adjuvant substances like lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and induce a shift from Th1 to Th2 responses, thus resulting in increased allergenicity.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref306" class="xref">306</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
