<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Indeed, several studies showed enhanced allergenic potentials for nitrated pollen allergens,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref229" class="xref">229</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref305" class="xref">305</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref306" class="xref">306</xref>
 </sup> nitrated fungal allergens,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref237" class="xref">237</xref>
 </sup> and nitrated food allergens.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref304" class="xref">304</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref345" class="xref">345</xref>
 </sup> For example, the most efficiently nitrated tyrosine residue in the food allergen ovalbumin (OVA) is part of human and murine IgE epitopes and also belongs to a human T cell epitope.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref304" class="xref">304</xref>
 </sup> Recent studies suggest that nitration may also affect the allergenic potential and adjuvant activity of α-amylase/trypsin inhibitors (ATIs) from wheat and other gluten-containing grains, which act as aeroallergens in baker’s asthma and are involved in hypersensitivities and chronic inflammation of the gastrointestinal tract.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref346" class="xref">346</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref351" class="xref">351</xref>
 </sup> Nitrated variants of the major birch pollen allergen Bet v 1 induced enhanced levels of specific IgE in murine models, possibly because of the formation of neo-epitopes.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref229" class="xref">229</xref>
 </sup> Nitration of Bet v 1 also increased the presentation of allergen-derived peptides by antigen presenting cells (APC).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref305" class="xref">305</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, increased proteolytic stability, up-regulation of CCL17 (Th2-associated chemokine secreted by dendritic cells, DC), and alterations of T cell proliferation and stimulatory capacities have been observed for nitrated Bet v 1.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref306" class="xref">306</xref>
 </sup> Nitrated proteins also have been observed to modulate the antioxidant levels in murine pneumocytes.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref352" class="xref">352</xref>
 </sup> In a recent study, in vivo fumigation of ragweed pollen with NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> resulted in an altered proteomic pattern including nitrosylation products and the treated pollen showed higher IgE recognition in immunoblots.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref239" class="xref">239</xref>
 </sup> Enhanced allergenic potential was also observed for 
 <italic class="italic">Betula pendula</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Ostrya carpinifolia</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Carpinus betulus</italic> pollen after NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> exposure (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acs.est.6b04908/suppl_file/es6b04908_si_001.pdf" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Table S1</ext-link>).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref236" class="xref">236</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
