<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We modified the Faben's (
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0501" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1965</xref>) capture–recapture formulation of the von Bertalanffy growth model to estimate individual growth rates of SVL for each color morph (Schofield, Barker, &amp; Taylor, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Snout‐to‐vent length is a standard measurement of growth (Leclair, Levasseur, &amp; Leclair, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>), as salamanders can gain or lose mass rapidly depending on water availability. These models estimate two parameters: a growth coefficient, 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>, and an asymptotic maximum size, 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>
 <sub class="sub">inf</sub>. We allowed growth coefficients to differ by a season by morph interaction (autumn, winter, spring, and summer; Table 
 <xref rid="ece32573-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">2</xref>). We would expect the rate of growth in summer and autumn to be higher for lead‐backed morphs and rate of growth in winter and spring is to be higher for striped morphs (prediction 7; Table 
 <xref rid="ece32573-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). We defined seasons the same across all 4 years, where spring (March 2–May 16) and autumn (September 6–December 4) contained all field surveys. Summer and winter were periods when no surveys occurred and when most salamanders were expected to be underground. To test prediction 8, we examined the relationship of growth rate during the surface‐active seasons, autumn and spring, to the previous summer's or previous winter's mean temperature, respectively. Winter and summer growth rates were related to the current season's mean temperature. This allowed us to measure impacts during the hottest and coldest periods of the year and to account for the thermal inertia that carries over into the next season. We predicted that lead‐backed morphs would grow faster under hotter conditions and that striped morphs would grow faster under cooler conditions. We fit growth models using program R and package “runjags” to call program JAGS (Denwood, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Plummer, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; R Core Team, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). See Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece32573-app-0003" ref-type="app" class="xref">C</xref> for model description and JAGS code.
</p>
