<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We ran multiple simulations of the model with and without acclimatization of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub>. The values of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> were empirically derived estimates based on the seasonal variation of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> that coincided with changes in VPD (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) and plasticity of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> in the laboratory (fig. S3). We modeled physiological plasticity using changes in the mean value of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> between simulations. By using the mean, our simulations estimated the full potential for physiological plasticity to minimize the effect of warming. Simulations with acclimatization incorporated the maximum value of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> (7 s/cm), and simulations without acclimatization incorporated the average value of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> (4 s/cm). We also tested the extent to which behavioral avoidance buffers extinction risk. In simulations with avoidance, salamanders retreated underground to a depth of 30 cm when net energetic costs were higher while foraging relative to remaining inactive underground. This avoidance behavior was used to simulate the potential for individuals to limit exposure to high energetic costs. We selected a depth of 30 cm in simulations with avoidance due to the negligible dampening of temperature beyond this depth. Therefore, this depth represents the maximum depth that behavioral strategies might minimize energetic costs. We used a depth of 2.5 cm in simulations without avoidance to identify the full potential of avoidance to minimize energetic costs. These depths also represented the range of depths that terrestrial salamanders behaviorally selected while underground (
 <xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">59</italic>
 </xref>). Comparisons between these depths indicated the greatest extent to which behavioral choices of depth might influence energy balance and extinction.
</p>
