<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Studies have shown that individuals with high degrees of food neophobia purchase some types of foods (e.g., poultry and fish) at a lower frequency and others (e.g., pork) at a higher frequency [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. A study by Jaeger et al. [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] confirms that the eating habits of adult New Zealanders are subject to the varying influences of different degrees of food neophobia. Adults with high degrees of food neophobia have lower intake frequencies and selection norms for foods such as fruits, vegetables, protein, seasonings, beverages, and dairy products when compared to those with low degrees of food neophobia. According to this analysis and the definitions and topics of this study, food neophobia is defined as the degree to which consumers are unwilling to consume insect foods when they experience dislike or fear [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. This study also uses the FNS to measure the degree of food neophobia, which reveals that when consumers have higher degrees of food neophobia, stronger negative emotions result, refusals to eat certain foods become more intense, and purchase intention decreases. Previous studies have also stated that in some Western countries, people’s dislike toward and refusal to eat insects is a kind of food neophobia [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-16-01606" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. As such, this study argues that because insect foods are a relatively unfamiliar food product for Taiwanese consumers, they may experience fear or disgust when they see insect foods. On this basis, we present hypothesis 5: 
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis 5 (H5).</bold> 
  </label>
  <p class="p">Consumers’ food neophobia negatively and significantly affects their purchase intention toward insect foods.</p>
 </statement>
</p>
