<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Erosion of sedimentary organic matter and fluxes downstream</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Glacial erosion may lead to some OM removal or re-distribution over time beneath ice sheets. Indeed, where ice is warm at the bed and exhibits high rates of flow (e.g., close to the ice sheet margins), erosion rates could be considerable. For example, erosion rates of up to 0.6 mm a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> have been plausibly modelled for Antarctic ice stream tributaries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>
  </span> and rates of up to 5 mm a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> are inferred at the margins of the Greenland Ice Sheet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>. However, erosion rates in inland regions of ice sheets must be much smaller to be compatible with the preservation of sedimentary basins, such as those found in Antarctica even after 30 Ma of glaciation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>
  </span>. Consistent with this are calculated erosion rates in East Antarctica of 0.04 mm a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Slessor Glacier
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>
  </span>) and 0.001 mm a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Lambert Basin
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>
  </span>). The erosion and export of organic carbon from the polar ice sheets has recently become pertinent to the global carbon cycle, because of the potential for this material to become buried in long term geological carbon sinks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>
  </span>, such as the dark, oxygen-starved bottom waters of fjords
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>
  </span>. The global rate of carbon burial in fjords is estimated to be 18 Tg a
  <span class="sup">−1</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>, but at many sites the proportions of old vs. newly produced OM are unknown. It is notable that the percentage organic carbon contents reported in Greenland fjord sediments (1.6%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>
  </span> are orders of magnitude higher than those recorded in suspended particulate material exported in runoff from large Greenland outlet glaciers (&lt;0.1%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The annual flux of DOC and POC in ice sheet meltwater and ice discharge is relatively small (present day total flux ~6 Tg C a
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, including ice-rafted debris (IRD)) compared to the total reserve held in ice or sediments (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) and is equivalent to approximately 10% of the DOC and POC export from Arctic rivers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" href="#CR107">107</a>
  </span>. Since erosion rates beneath ice sheets are generally low, material remaining under the ice is often old
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>
  </span>. For example, if we assume a subglacial POC store in Greenland of 27 Pg C (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), it would take some tens of thousands of years to export all of this organic carbon via runoff (assuming meltwater export of POC and DOC at &lt;1 Tg a
  <span class="sup">−1</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">,</span>). This is consistent with the observation that the 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C radiocarbon ages of bulk POC associated with suspended particulate material in Greenland runoff are old (5–9 kyr) and become progressively older through a melt season as the snowline retreats inland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>
  </span>. We estimate that the amount of OC liberated via Antarctic subglacial meltwater discharge, is 0.17 Tg C a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> as DOC and 0.33 Tg C a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> as POC (using new data from Subglacial Lake Whillans for Antarctic DOC concentrations), which is comparable to previous estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> (see 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Supplementary Methods</a>). DOC/POC release via Antarctic ice discharge is an order of magnitude higher at 4 Tg a
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although fluxes of DOC and POC are relatively small on a global scale (&lt;1% global land-ocean fluxes), a growing number of studies have observed that glacier derived DOC and POC are highly bioavailable
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>
  </span>, and thus could be important in fuelling bacterial respiration in receiving aquatic ecosystems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Observation of radiocarbon depleted (i.e., pre-aged) organic carbon on glacier surfaces and in glacial runoff also suggests that glacially exported DOC is also paradoxically ancient
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">108</a>
  </span>. The source of this ancient DOC has been debated, as has the reason for its high bioavailability in comparison with non-glacial sources of DOC. Ice core data demonstrate a significant contribution of anthropogenic-derived carbon in glacier ice, concurrent with the onset of the industrial era
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" href="#CR109">109</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">110</a>
  </span>. The molecular composition of OM within Alaskan and Tibetan glaciers indicates high relative contributions of condensed aromatics, which is consistent with the presence of combustion derived OM (i.e., black carbon)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>. Other studies have suggested an alternative explanation for aged DOC in glacial runoff (but not the glacier surface), arguing that it reflects cycling of overridden subglacial material (e.g., paleosols)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">108</a>
  </span> or glacial erosion and associated reactivation of ancient OM in bedrock
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">111</a>
  </span>. The high bioavailability of DOC emanating from glacial surfaces (and hence runoff) has been hypothesised to reflect OM sourced from the incomplete combustion of fossil fuels enriched in high abundances of nitrogen-rich aliphatic compounds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. However, more recent work also shows the potential role of microorganisms in cycling organic carbon to more bioavailable forms, giving rise to bioavailable DOC both on the glacier surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">112</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>
  </span> and at the glacier bed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">114</a>
  </span>. Future projections indicate that the total magnitude of DOC exported in glacier runoff between now and 2050 will be approximately 48 Tg C as annual glacier mass loss increases, particularly from mountain glaciers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. This increasing flux of glacier DOC provides a subsidy of bioavailable carbon to receiving streams, rivers, estuaries and coastal systems and will be disproportionally impactful in heavily glaciated coastal systems (e.g., Greenland, Gulf of Alaska, Patagonia) that are home to commercially important fisheries.
 </p>
</sec>
