<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fertilisation impacts of ice sheets</div>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate warming over the last glacial-interglacial transition was accompanied by the disappearance of ice sheets over much of northern Europe and America
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" href="#CR130">130</a>
  </span> and marginal retreat of the Antarctic Ice Sheet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" href="#CR131">131</a>
  </span>. If indeed ice sheet freshwater export is a key source of nutrients for the world’s oceans, then the geological record should hint at shifts in the productivity of ocean basins bordering ice sheets synchronous with changes in ice sheet freshwater inputs (e.g., meltwater, icebergs). To introduce this idea and to provide some testable hypotheses for future work, we turn our attention to the Fe-limited
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span> Southern Ocean over the last glacial-interglacial transition. Here, the productivity of phytoplankton is limited primarily by the availability of Fe in surface ocean waters, and variations in the Fe supply over glacial-interglacial cycles has been argued as a plausible driver for CO
  <sub>2</sub> drawdown
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">132</a>
  </span>, via its influence upon the strength of the biological pump which controls carbon export to the deep ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">133</a>
  </span>. Specifically, enhanced Fe supply to the Sub-Antarctic zone of the Southern Ocean, and associated changes in export production, has been linked to the step decreases in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> recorded in ice cores during the last glacial period, particularly during Marine Isotope Stages (MIS) 4/5 transition (c. 70 kyr B.P.) and around the LGM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" href="#CR134">134</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are a number of potential Fe sources in the Southern Ocean fertilisation game, all with their own spatial and temporal complexities. These include aeolian dust
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">132</a>
  </span>, coastal sediments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138" href="#CR138">138</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141" href="#CR141">141</a>
  </span>, hydrothermal inputs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142" href="#CR142">142</a>
  </span> and more recently, iceberg rafted debris (IRD)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143" href="#CR143">143</a>
  </span> and meltwater from the Antarctic Ice Sheet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144" href="#CR144">144</a>
  </span>. Inferring the precise mechanism(s) driving Southern Ocean fertilisation at key periods of Earth’s history is challenging, in part due to the overlapping geographical impacts of different Fe sources. For example, inputs of Fe from dust, coastal sediments or icebergs are often concentrated in the Atlantic Sector of the Southern Ocean, via transport off Patagonia (dust
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145" href="#CR145">145</a>
  </span>, including remobilised fine glacial sediments from Patagonian glaciers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146" href="#CR146">146</a>
  </span>) and via ocean currents along the so called iceberg alley adjacent to the Antarctic Peninsula. In general, discerning the importance of each of these potential Fe sources involves correlating past CO
  <sub>2</sub> variations to reconstructions of iron/nutrient supply via elevated Fe inputs (the iron hypothesis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">132</a>
  </span>) and associated proxies for export production (e.g., opal accumulation)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147" href="#CR147">147</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation in aeolian dust supply to the Southern Ocean has attracted perhaps the greatest historical interest as an explanation for Fe fertilisation-driven changes in Southern Ocean productivity during the last glacial period, when enhanced inputs of wind-blown dust reflected changes in source area, as well as the strength and position of southern hemisphere westerlies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148" href="#CR148">148</a>
  </span>. Supporting the dust hypothesis for Southern Ocean fertilisation is the existence of excellent temporal records of past lithogenic fluxes (inferred to reflect dust inputs) to both the ice sheet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149" href="#CR149">149</a>
  </span> and to marine sediments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" href="#CR136">136</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150" href="#CR150">150</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152" href="#CR152">152</a>
  </span>, which lend themselves well to correlation with palaeo records of export production and atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149" href="#CR149">149</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). For example, the EPICA Dome C ice core dust flux
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149" href="#CR149">149</a>
  </span> record highlights the last glacial period as a period of enhanced dust transport (14 mg m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>), and therefore, of potential Fe fertilisation of the Southern Ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149" href="#CR149">149</a>
  </span>. The fertilisation impacts of this Fe-bearing dust have been inferred in the SE Pacific and Atlantic (sub-Antarctic) sectors of the Southern Ocean at the LGM and have been linked to elevated rates of opal accumulation and overall export production
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" href="#CR136">136</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148" href="#CR148">148</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150" href="#CR150">150</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153" href="#CR153">153</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154" href="#CR154">154</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). They indicate Fe fertilisation of a northerly displaced opal belt–a zone of siliceous oozes and muds located between the Polar Front and the northern limit of seasonal sea ice which is associated with the upwelling of silica and nutrient-rich waters and relief of light limitation along the Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC) frontal system. In contrast, the Antarctic Zone of the Southern Ocean shows decreased opal export around the LGM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155" href="#CR155">155</a>
  </span>. A dusty source for core-bound lithogenic material in marine cores is implied by presence of terrestrial n-alkanes in the same cores, ascribed to the input of plant leaf waxes associated with terrestrial inputs of dust
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156" href="#CR156">156</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Temporal variability in the Southern Ocean. Temporal variation in atmospheric CO
     <sub>2</sub>, marine opal accumulation, Ice-rafted debris (IRD) and total lithogenic inputs to the Southern Ocean over the past 25 ka: 
     <span class="bold">a</span> atmospheric CO
     <sub>2</sub> concentrations (EPICA Dome C, dark grey line) and opal accumulation in sub-Antarctic cores 1090/PS2498-1174 (blue line)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151" href="#CR151">151</a>
     </span>, (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) IRD in core 1090
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159" href="#CR159">159</a>
     </span>, (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) IRD in core PS282-1 where the IRD data are from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
     </span> and the Depth/Age model is from Ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR175" href="#CR175">175</a>
     </span>, (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) IRD in core PS2498-1 where the IRD data are from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
     </span> and the Depth/Age model is from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151" href="#CR151">151</a>
     </span>, (
     <span class="bold">e</span>) IRD core PS1778-5, where the IRD data are from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
     </span> and the Depth/Age model is from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR176" href="#CR176">176</a>
     </span>, (
     <span class="bold">f</span>), IRD in core PS1752, where the IRD data are from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
     </span> and the Depth/Age model is from ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR177" href="#CR177">177</a>
     </span>. 
     <span class="bold">g</span> IRD in cores SK200-22A and SK200-27 from the Indian Ocean sector of the Southern Ocean
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161" href="#CR161">161</a>
     </span>. 
     <span class="bold">h</span> Lithogenic fluxes to the Southern Ocean for marine cores 1090
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>
     </span>, PS2498-1
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151" href="#CR151">151</a>
     </span> and PS75-059/2
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152" href="#CR152">152</a>
     </span> alongside the EPICA Dome C dust flux record. The shaded area indicates the period of maximum CO
     <sub>2</sub> increase during deglaciation. See Supplementary Fig. 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a> for core locations
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11394_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2960" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A new player on the field of Southern Ocean Fe fertilisation is the Antarctic Ice Sheet. Early work on ice sheet contributions focussed upon iceberg rafted debris, which contains bioavailable Fe (oxy)hydroxide nanoparticles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>
  </span> which are released from melting bergs as they drift often far offshore from the Antarctic continent
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143" href="#CR143">143</a>
  </span>. Estimates of the potential bioavailable (ascorbic acid extractable) Fe fluxes associated with Antarctic IRD at the present day (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>) are c. 600 Gg Fe a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (range: 100– 2900Gg Fe a
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). These compare with Antarctic bioavailable Fe fluxes associated with dust which are several orders of magnitude lower at 0.56 Gg Fe a
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for the present day
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. More recently, ice shelf basal melt
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157" href="#CR157">157</a>
  </span>, surface melt
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>, and subglacial meltwaters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144" href="#CR144">144</a>
  </span> from the ice sheet have been proposed as potential sources of Fe to the Southern Ocean, but these melt (and Fe) inputs are likely limited to the coastal zone
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examination of records of IRD in several sub-Antarctic marine cores over the last glacial-interglacial transition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158" href="#CR158">158</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>) suggest that Fe delivered by icebergs to the Southern Ocean could be an important segment of the deglacial Southern Ocean fertilisation, export production and CO
  <sub>2</sub> story. In particular, elevated IRD deposition is recorded in sub-Antarctic cores between 22 kyr and 17 kyr B.P. when Antarctic ice volume was at its highest
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161" href="#CR161">161</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). There is insufficient confidence in past iceberg flux estimates from the Antarctic Ice Sheet to calculate LGM fluxes of iceberg hosted Fe. However, we know from marine cores that IRD fluxes to the Atlantic sector of the sub-Antarctic Southern Ocean around the LGM were x10–20 present day fluxes, which is consistent with more intense IRD fertilisation of sub-Antarctic waters at this time (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Together, these findings suggest that a combination of high ice discharge and slower iceberg melting due to colder sea surface temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158" href="#CR158">158</a>
  </span> increased the supply of Fe-rich terrigenous material to sub-Antarctic waters during this interval, incidentally in a similar time frame to peak dust fluxes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Later during deglaciation, we hypothesise that warmer ocean waters reduced iceberg transport offshore, such that Fe fertilisation of the sub-Antarctic zone substantially decreased and that of the Antarctic zone likely increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is difficult with the current data available to conclusively evaluate the role of iceberg-associated Fe in fertilising the Southern Ocean during the last glacial period alongside the more widely acclaimed dust. Certainly, the magnitude of present day IRD–Fe fluxes, when combined with the similarity in temporal and spatial patterns of IRD export and those for dust (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>), suggest that IRD may play a role in the Southern Ocean fertilisation story and warrants investigation. Unequivocally solving this mystery, however, requires a multi-pronged approach. First, it requires parallel study of a range of marine cores over a wide geographical area of the Southern Ocean to tease out the temporally variable contributions of both dust and IRD to the lithogenic flux record. Traditionally, IRD is assumed to account for the coarser fraction of lithogenic material in marine cores, which is variably defined (e.g., 250 μm−2 mm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158" href="#CR158">158</a>
  </span>, &gt;1 mm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162" href="#CR162">162</a>
  </span>, &gt;125 μm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">160</a>
  </span>). However, research on the grain size distribution of debris of glacial sediments, including those entombed in icebergs, often have an important fine (i.e., silt/clay) fraction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR163" href="#CR163">163</a>
  </span>. Thus, while the presence of larger particles (e.g., sand) in marine cores might point towards IRD rather than dust inputs, the presence of silt/clays could reflect inputs from either IRD or dust. Geochemical provenance studies may help elucidate the precise origin of the lithogenic fraction in marine cores
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150" href="#CR150">150</a>
  </span>, as may the use of biomarkers. The presence of n-alkanes derived from leaf waxes in the lithogenic material in marine cores is often interpreted as indicative of a dusty source
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156" href="#CR156">156</a>
  </span>. While it seems unlikely that leaf waxes are present in sediments beneath the Antarctic Ice Sheet, the presence of these biomarkers in Antarctic IRD has not been evaluated. Finally, biogeochemical models have strong potential to reveal the magnitude of fertilisation impacts that could be possible in a glacial ocean via various Fe inputs, including dust and IRD. Model simulation of dust and ice sheet-sourced Fe impacts on Southern Ocean fertilisation and thus, productivity, have been attempted for a modern ocean and suggest strong influences by ice sheet Fe inputs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
  </span>. However, these simulations have not been conducted for an LGM ocean. Part of the challenge of conducting such model studies is the grave uncertainty regarding potential Fe fluxes from the ice sheet to the ocean, which need to be better constrained. In summary, determining the role of iceberg-borne Fe in fertilising the Southern Ocean is no simple task, but has the potential to reveal powerful insights regarding the relationship between Fe export from the ice sheet (via melt and icebergs) and export production in the Southern Ocean, which may become more pertinent in a future warming world.
 </p>
</sec>
