<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrate stability</div>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Turning our attention to potential direct effects of ice sheets upon the global carbon cycle, we examine the geological record for past periods of methane hydrate destabilisation beneath ice sheets, and associated CH
  <sub>4</sub> release. Ice sheet thinning or retreat has the potential to dramatically alter in situ temperature and pressure conditions in sub-ice sheet sediments, triggering methane hydrate destabilisation and release of the resultant CH
  <sub>4</sub> gas to the atmosphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). Non-linear changes in Greenland and Antarctic Ice Sheet extent and thickness, due to marine ice sheet instability have the potential to trigger such a response, but are difficult to predict
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129" href="#CR129">129</a>
  </span>. There is some evidence in marine sediments located close to the former margin of former Eurasian Ice Sheets that past phases of ice sheet retreat have been associated with methane hydrate destabilisation in subglacial sediments. Abundant pockmarks and authigenic carbonate crusts aligned to the position of the former LGM Scandinavian Ice Sheet margin are observed both in the Barents Sea and off the coast of Norway
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122" href="#CR122">122</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164" href="#CR164">164</a>
  </span>. The former were interpreted to reflect fluid escape at the seafloor during (thermogenic) methane hydrate dissociation at depth, and the latter arise from AOM-driven saturation of sediment porewaters with respect to calcite. These features are contended to reflect CH
  <sub>4</sub> release as the ice overburden was removed during the last deglaciation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122" href="#CR122">122</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164" href="#CR164">164</a>
  </span> and provide compelling evidence that hydrate forms beneath ice sheets and is destabilised as the ice thins and retreats, in this case over a period of ~10 kyr
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164" href="#CR164">164</a>
  </span>. Similar evidence has yet to be uncovered from the Antarctic Ice Sheet, where hydrate reservoirs are predicted at the present day
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span>. Ice thickness reductions in marginal areas of the Antarctic Ice Sheet during the last deglaciation were significant (e.g., 300–800 m in East Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165" href="#CR165">165</a>
  </span>) and sufficient to destabilise potential subglacial hydrate reserves in these areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span>. The potential impacts of such release events on atmospheric CH
  <sub>4</sub> concentrations are unclear, and are complicated by the uncertainty regarding the fate of CH
  <sub>4</sub> in marine waters (e.g., oxidation to the less potent greenhouse gas, CO
  <sub>2</sub>). For example, recent work off the coast of Svalbard has indicated that high CH
  <sub>4</sub> gas fluxes from the seafloor instead stimulate enhanced marine productivity, likely due to indirect transportation of nutrient-rich water and CO
  <sub>2</sub> (from dissociated CH
  <sub>4</sub>) from depth. In this case, the negative radiative forcing exceeded positive radiative forcing associated with CH
  <sub>4</sub> release
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166" href="#CR166">166</a>
  </span>. Resolving the influence of these opposing influences is important in determining the net impact of subglacial CH
  <sub>4</sub> hydrate destabilisation on atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub>. If the CH
  <sub>4</sub> is released to the atmosphere during non-linear ice retreat, it could impact the effectiveness of the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change emissions-based agreements to keep climate warming to a minimum of 2 °C by 2100.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Model of ice sheet ice sheet impacts on hydrate reserves. A conceptual model illustrates the impact of ice sheet retreat and thinning on hydrate reserves beneath ice sheets, via their impact on the Gas Hydrate Stability Zone (GHSZ). (
     <span class="bold">a)</span> Conditions at peak glaciation, and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) conditions after substantial ice sheet retreat. Following ice sheet retreat, relict features of hydrate destabilisation (e.g., authigenic carbonates, pock marks and relict cold seeps) may be evident on the formerly glaciated continental shelf
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11394_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e3210" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
