<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a component of the Earth’s system to impact the global carbon cycle, and potentially influence atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide or methane, it must either directly sequester and/or release carbon, or indirectly influence carbon uptake/release in other parts of the Earth system. The notion that ice sheets contain significant carbon stores has its roots in the early 2000s–the great ice sheets were hypothesised to advance over soil and vegetation carbon during glacial periods, with this fossil carbon being released back to the atmosphere once exposed by retreating ice during deglaciation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. More recent work has highlighted the capacity of glacier surfaces to act as sinks for carbon-containing aerosols from anthropogenic or natural sources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. However, both these mechanisms represent passive processes of carbon storage and release by glaciers. Only in the last 15 years have glacial systems started to be considered as active cyclers of carbon, arising from the discovery that they include a range of aquatic environments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> which host abundant and diverse populations of microorganisms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> and are hot spots for biogeochemical weathering
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. These processes create the potential for ice sheets to directly or indirectly impact the global carbon cycle (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Direct impacts include the release of greenhouse gases (carbon dioxide, CO
  <sub>2</sub> and methane, CH
  <sub>4</sub>) during the microbial respiration of organic matter (OM) stored within ice sheets. Examples of indirect impacts include the fertilisation of downstream ecosystems, promoted by either the release of nutrient-rich glacial meltwaters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> or by subglacial meltwater-induced upwelling of nutrient replete marine water at tidewater glacier margins
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Ocean fertilisation by glaciers may be accompanied by significant CO
  <sub>2</sub> drawdown by phytoplankton, intensifying the biological pump
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Conceptual diagram of ice sheets in the global carbon cycle. The diagram indicates the potential direct and indirect impacts of ice sheets. (1) direct sequestration or emission of CO
     <sub>2</sub>/CH
     <sub>4</sub> by microbial activity in ice sheets, (2) burial of terrestrial OM exported from ice sheets by rivers, (3) emission of CO
     <sub>2</sub> by respiration or uptake by primary production in the oceans (4) export production–OM produced by primary production which is not recycled before it sinks to the ocean floor
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11394_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e454" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The size of the carbon stores entombed in ice sheets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> and magnitude of nutrient supply to surface ocean waters by meltwaters and icebergs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> make it crucial to evaluate the role of ice sheets as open systems in regulating the global carbon cycle via the direct and indirect mechanisms identified in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Here, we draw upon advances over the last two decades to address the hypothesis that ice sheets have important direct and indirect impacts on the global carbon cycle (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) at the present day, which are accentuated during periods of enhanced melt or ice discharge. In this Review, we first identify the key biogeochemical processes in ice sheets, and then go on to highlight in further discussions important indirect and direct impacts. We conclude this synthesis by evaluating the suggestion that ice sheets play a role in regulating the global carbon cycle with a novel analysis of the geological record over the last glacial-interglacial transition.
 </p>
</sec>
