<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par62" class="p">Several themes that were top barriers across landscapes were also top opportunities, including funding, political support and leadership, and using climate change data to identify management actions. This finding is congruent with other studies showing that certain factors may serve as either drivers or barriers (Engle 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2012</xref>; Uittenbroek et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2012</xref>; Lemieux et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2015</xref>). The presence of particular factors as both barriers and opportunities may indicate that individuals or organizations in our study have been able to transform barriers into opportunities through creativity, learning, leadership, and/or use of varied approaches. In the Transboundary Rockies and Adirondacks, for example, organizations have been able to circumvent political and community wariness of climate change by framing climate change adaptation in terms of key regional resource issues. In the Rockies, framing climate change as a water management issue has garnered support from natural resource management agencies and the ranching community who have implemented actions to address declining snowmelt inputs to streams, such as the installation of low-cost and low-tech structures constructed from willow branches and other local vegetation. These structures mimic beaver activity and restore the natural water storage capacity of riparian and wetland ecosystems. In the Adirondacks, framing of the issue in terms of protecting winter recreation opportunities, a major economic driver in the area, has motivated groups to work together on addressing climate-related issues. For instance, three New York state-owned ski resorts (two based in the Adirondacks) have pledged to be powered by 100 percent renewable energy by 2030 and invest millions of dollars into making the resorts year-round destinations with ample non-snow related activities. Other landscapes and organizations may be able to incorporate similar approaches in their own efforts, corroborating the importance of sharing insights and expertize across regions and between organizations.
</p>
