<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we analyze climate change impacts on agricultural welfare on a global and regional scale, which are measured as changes in “consumer surplus” and “producer surplus.” The impacts are dynamically assessed for the period from 1995 to 2095 using the agro-economic land use optimization model MAgPIE (Model of Agricultural Production and its Impacts on the Environment; see Materials and Methods and the Supplementary Materials) (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">17</italic>
 </xref>). Although there is a considerable amount of literature on climate impacts on crop yields (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>), few studies have analyzed the subsequent economic welfare effects (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">19</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">20</italic>
 </xref>). MAgPIE is well suited to translate biophysical into economic impacts because crop yield patterns and water availability that are directly affected by climate change enter the economic model as spatially explicit biophysical constraints. The surplus concepts are standard analytical tools in welfare economics (
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">21</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>). Under agricultural welfare, we consider economic surplus from agricultural activities related only to plant cultivation and livestock production. Other agricultural subsectors, such as forestry and fishery, are not studied here. Producer surplus is equivalent to the production profit, that is, the difference between total revenues and production-associated costs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>, A and B, red area). Consumer surplus is the difference between a consumer’s willingness to pay for a certain good and the amount he or she actually pays for it at the market price (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>, A and B, blue area). Consumer behavior is fully deterministic in MAgPIE by exogenously defined demand trajectories for agricultural products (
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">23</italic>
 </xref>), which implies an unbounded willingness of consumers to purchase at the market. In the case of a negative impact on the production side, the supply curve shifts upward (or leftward), and the equilibrium price increases to a new level, implying shifts in surpluses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1B</xref>). Climate change–induced welfare impacts for food producers and consumers are calculated in this analysis based on these differences in surpluses. Three indicators are considered: change in consumer surplus, change in producer surplus, and change in total agricultural welfare (the last indicator being the sum of the first two) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1C</xref>). The economic valuation of climate change impacts in agriculture is measured by chosen indicators as a percentage change with respect to the value of future total GDP [provided by selected economic projections from the Special Report on Emissions Scenarios (SRES) (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>)], thereby implying the effect of agricultural sector on total economic welfare. Details on economic surplus in MAgPIE are provided in the Supplementary Materials.
</p>
