<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The market response to a climate shock is obtained through the comparison of results from a scenario with climate effect on crop yields with a reference scenario where climate conditions are fixed at the initial level in 1995. Here, we focus on high-end impacts, driving the MAgPIE model with high population growth and high greenhouse gas (GHG) emission scenario [SRES A2 (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>)] and assuming no beneficial effects from the highly debated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">25</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">26</italic>
 </xref>) in the underlying crop yield simulations with the gridded global crop model LPJmL (Lund-Potsdam-Jena with managed Land) [figs. S1 and S2; (
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">27</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">28</italic>
 </xref>)]. In this setting, we explore the effects of high-end climate change on agricultural welfare indicators, explicitly addressing uncertainties in patterns of climate change and the importance of trade regimes. For this, we use 19 different general circulation models (GCMs) of climate change projections that are implemented in SRES A2 and for which changes in crop yield patterns are computed, and analyze two trade regimes. Acknowledging different aspects of biophysical and socioeconomic uncertainties, we assess the sensitivity of our results to central assumptions made, including (i) the uncertainty in CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization, (ii) additional analyses with different crop growth models as studied by Nelson 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">29</italic>
 </xref>), (iii) two alternative population and GHG emission scenarios [SRES B1 and A1B (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">24</italic>
 </xref>)], and (iv) agricultural demand elasticity.
</p>
