<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diarrhea is an example of a global health problem that will not likely be solved by future economic development (
 <xref rid="c50" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2014</xref>). In 2015, an estimated 526,000 deaths due to diarrhea occurred among children younger than 5 years of age (
 <xref rid="c26" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. 2016</xref>). A recent study estimated that in 2016, diarrhea cases and deaths were responsible for more than 40 million disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) among children younger than 5 years of age (
 <xref rid="c43" ref-type="bibr">Troeger et al. 2018</xref>). Although the incidence of diarrheal disease may be undermined by environmental changes such as climate change, which damage urban infrastructure and reduce the overall availability of water (
 <xref rid="c50" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2014</xref>), diarrheal disease transmission is complex and depends on a number of factors (
 <xref rid="c37" ref-type="bibr">Prüss et al. 2002</xref>), comprising both host susceptibility and environmental components (
 <xref rid="c14" ref-type="bibr">Guerrant et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c47" ref-type="bibr">Walker et al. 2013</xref>). Additionally, infectious diarrhea can arise as a result of a variety of pathogens whose relative importance varies regionally (
 <xref rid="c22" ref-type="bibr">Kotloff et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c47" ref-type="bibr">Walker et al. 2013</xref>). Therefore, previous studies that have aimed to quantify the burden of diarrhea have encountered problems with data quality and model specificity (
 <xref rid="c26" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c43" ref-type="bibr">Troeger et al. 2018</xref>). Nevertheless, as diarrhea is a leading cause of death and illness globally among children younger than 5 years of age (
 <xref rid="c43" ref-type="bibr">Troeger et al. 2018</xref>), studies on diarrhea are paramount for improving prediction estimates and aiding in the prioritization of mitigation and adaptation policies in the future.
</p>
