<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">All events within 5° × 5° boxes are pooled together to assess the statistical strength of the mean metric value, which is determined by assessing whether the differences between the event and control samples are significantly larger (or smaller) than those generated by chance as follows: First, the climatology of the individual locations within the 5° boxes is removed by subtracting the long‐term mean of the values within the control and the event samples (pooled together from both samples for each location). Second, the difference between the averages of the event sample and the corresponding control sample (
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">δ</styled-content>(
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</styled-content>) = mean(
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</styled-content>
 <sub class="sub">
  <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">e</styled-content>
 </sub>) − mean(
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</styled-content>
 <sub class="sub">
  <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">c</styled-content>
 </sub>)) is computed, and its strength is determined by the corresponding quantile of the distribution of the same difference in each of 1,000 random samples. These samples consist of 
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">n</styled-content> values (where 
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">n</styled-content> is the size of the event sample) randomly selected from all values of the event and control samples pooled together (as a substitute for the event sample) and the remaining values within this pool (as a substitute for the control sample). Statistical significance of a positive (negative) feedback is claimed if the strength of 
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">δ</styled-content>(
 <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Y</styled-content>) is greater (smaller) than 0.9 (0.1). 5° boxes with less than 25 event samples were masked out as they cannot provide robust results.
</p>
