<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38" class="p">These agricultural damage functions are then incorporated into a sectorally and regionally disaggregated SCC damage module based on the FUND model, keeping the rest of the impact sectors unchanged
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. Damage functions in the module use the central parameter estimates of FUND. The full FUND model includes probability distributions over many parameters and is designed to be run in a Monte Carlo mode
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. This uncertainty is not dealt with in this paper, meaning uncertainty reported in the SCC reflects only the uncertainty in the yield response derived from the meta-analysis. The damage module is driven by a standardized socio-economic and emissions pathway and climate model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. We use a business-as-usual emissions scenario (Scenario 2 in ref. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>), paired with the DICE climate module
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. This produces a warming of 4 °C of warming above preindustrial by 2100. The SCC is calculated by adding a 1 Gt pulse of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions to this reference emissions path in 2020 and comparing the time path of damages along the perturbed pathway to the reference case. Then these incremental damages (or benefits) are discounted back to 2020 at a 3% discount rate and normalized by the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> pulse volume to give the SCC. Results using alternative discount rates are given in Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">5</xref>. As the SCC is additive, it can be decomposed by sector and region, allowing a detailed comparison of the regional impacts in agriculture between FUND and the revised regional damage functions.
</p>
