<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35383-sec-0015" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSIONS AND NEXT STEPS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Widespread mortality of tree species due to changing climate is a major concern in forests worldwide, but the potential for resilience is rarely assessed during an ongoing mortality event, a gap we have attempted to fill here. Species’ responses to climate change‐induced mortality will vary widely based on species‐specific traits, sensitivity to climatic extremes, biotic stressors, and abiotic conditions of the establishment environment, thus requiring autecological studies on factors limiting versus promoting success. In 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> forests, there is no increase in 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> regeneration abundances to offset canopy mortality. As a result, this forest type is not resilient to mortality associated with ongoing snow loss, and a type change appears to be underway. This example of climate change‐driven mortality in a single species highlights how species‐specific sensitivity can lead to shifts in community composition and stand dynamics following canopy mortality via the same mechanism—death of mature seed trees.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Few strategies or solutions exist for forests vulnerable to ecosystem type conversion due to mature tree mortality and associated loss of seed source, and numerous knowledge gaps remain. In the case of 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis,</span> common garden studies using seed sources from across the species’ range could allow for identification of genotypes with fine‐root frost tolerance. Planting gardens across decline severity gradients would also allow for targeted research on regeneration response to concurrent canopy mortality and associated establishment conditions. Given the potential for a wave of transitional mortality across the 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> range (Buma, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>), however, survival of local versus foreign seed source is hard to predict. Long‐term monitoring in our plot network will allow us to track forest response to the predicted transitional mortality phenomenon and provide demographic information on the impacts of climate on different size classes as well as on the growth and survival rates of regeneration across the decline severity gradient. Demographic studies will also resolve the confounding effects of seed availability, canopy mortality, and establishment conditions on regeneration. Simultaneously investigating climate‐induced tree mortality and subsequent postmortality resilience gives a clearer view of the long‐term consequences of climate change on forest health, and this observational study has just scratched the surface of filling the critical knowledge gaps essential to understanding and predicting long‐term forest resilience to climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
