<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="ece35383-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the climate changes, successful tree regeneration is threatened by novel climate and disturbance conditions and associated shifts in canopy community composition. Our study highlights how species‐specific sensitivity to climate change can lead to restructuring of the forest community following canopy mortality. We demonstrate that reductions in both mature tree and regeneration abundances after single‐species mortality events occur via the same mechanism—death of mature, seed‐producing trees. In the case of 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span>, our work suggests that climate‐induced forest mortality is driving alternate successional pathways in forests where 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> was once a major component, which is likely to lead to long‐term shifts in community composition and stand dynamics. As suitable habitat conditions shift with ongoing global climate change, both mature trees and regeneration will be increasingly exposed to novel conditions, and identifying the autecological factors contributing to successful regeneration, or lack thereof, is an essential first step toward predicting forest response and resilience to climate change.
 </p>
 <sec id="ece35383-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate impacts on mortality and regeneration in Callitropsis nootkatensis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the NPCTR, climate change‐induced canopy mortality is restricted to a single species, 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis,</span> allowing for a focused examination of the effects of climate, seed source, and local conditions on regenerating community response and subsequent stand dynamics. Mature tree mortality across the study area corresponded with a reduction in 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> regeneration (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0006">6</a>) and a shift to surviving canopy species, predominantly 
   <span class="italic">Tsuga</span> (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0003">3</a>), a widespread species known to dominate the regenerating community following disturbance (Alaback and Tappeiner II (
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0003">1991</a>); Deal &amp; Farr, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0023">1994</a>). 
   <span class="italic">Callitropsis nootkatensis</span> regeneration constituted less than 20% of the regenerating community in decline areas (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0003">3</a>) and appears to be limited by a lack of available seed and vegetative source, although drainage conditions, as determined by slope, and maximum winter temperatures also contribute to structuring regenerating community composition (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0007">7</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Local hydrologic regime and associated ecosystem productivity are key factors in both species’ distributions (Bisbing et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0010">2016</a>) and in the extent of 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> decline (D'Amore &amp; Hennon, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0022">2006</a>). Mortality across this plot network was most extensive on wetter, lower‐productivity peatlands; however, proportional mortality was greatest in productive upland forests. The apparent lack of congruity between these results and previous research, which reports higher mortality on lower slopes (D'Amore &amp; Hennon, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0022">2006</a>), is explained by our use of proportional mortality rather than total. Although mortality is most extreme on saturated peatlands, it is likely that surviving individuals will allow for ongoing perpetuation of the species on lower‐productivity peatlands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nonetheless, the loss of 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> from both the canopy and the regenerating community across the extent of decline in southeast Alaska indicates that canopy trees and regeneration are in sync in their responses to climate change. Cold, low‐snow winters have led to widespread mortality over our study area (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0004">4</a>) and across the species’ range (Buma et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0017">2017</a>), and local drainage conditions (i.e., slope, hydrologic regime) amplify or mitigate response of the canopy (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0004">4</a>) and regenerating community (Figures 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0005">5</a> and 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0007">7</a>). While this study cannot conclusively determine the mechanism for the lack of regeneration, the close correspondence between the canopy and regenerating communities is striking. These plot‐level findings are consistent with recent modeling work on drivers of canopy mortality that identified winter temperatures and slope as conditions leading to decline at broad scales (Buma et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0017">2017</a>). Mortality is predicted to be ongoing in areas above the winter snow threshold, and up to 50% of current suitable habitat is expected to experience climate conditions favorable to decline (Buma et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0017">2017</a>). Continued mortality of this conifer is likely to lead to more widespread shifts in community composition (Oakes et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>; data presented here). The close relationship between seed source and composition of the regenerating community suggests that no compensation in the form of increased recruitment will make up for the loss of the 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> canopy.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35383-sec-0013" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Single versus multiple species decline</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mortality events specifically attributed to climate change (Breshears et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0014">2005</a>; Van Mantgem &amp; Stephenson, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0066">2007</a>; Williams et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0070">2010</a>) do not typically discriminate but, instead, lead to decline or mortality of multiple species in the affected ecosystem. Sierra Nevada mixed‐conifer forests have, for example, seen concurrent declines in shade tolerant 
   <span class="italic">Abies</span> and shade‐intolerant 
   <span class="italic">Pinus</span> following years of temperature‐driven drought stress (Van Mantgem &amp; Stephenson, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0066">2007</a>), while extreme droughts in the arid southwest led to mortality in 
   <span class="italic">Pinus edulis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Juniperus monosperma</span> (Mueller et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0049">2005</a>). In both cases, no immediate impacts on regenerating community composition were evident, although higher 
   <span class="italic">P. edulis</span> mortality indicated that long‐term shifts are likely (Mueller et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0049">2005</a>). The climate change‐induced 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> mortality in the NPCTR is unique in its isolated effect on a single species but also in its observable, and now documented, postdecline shift in species dominance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regenerating community response in other single‐species mortality events has been highly variable and largely driven by the severity of a biotic disturbance, such as insect attack (Burr &amp; McCullough, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0019">2014</a>), on the canopy community and variability in local establishment conditions (Kayes &amp; Tinker, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0044">2012</a>). In some cases, regeneration proceeds successfully following the loss of canopy species (Diskin, Rocca, Nelson, Aoki, &amp; Romme, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0028">2011</a>; Macek et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0046">2017</a>), while, in others, species experience loss of dominance (Pelz &amp; Smith, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0054">2012</a>), increasing the probability of ecosystem type conversions (Burr &amp; McCullough, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0019">2014</a>; Klooster et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0045">2014</a>). Self‐replacement of a single species following canopy morality has been documented following extreme drought (Suarez &amp; Lloret, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0062">2018</a>) and bark beetle attack (Diskin et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0028">2011</a>), where co‐occurring species established but failed to dominate. These instances of ongoing success, however, occurred in forest types where the impacted species dominated the canopy prior to the disturbance and either did not experience wholesale mortality, as is the case in 
   <span class="italic">Nothofagus</span> drought mortality (Suarez &amp; Lloret, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0062">2018</a>), or possessed a canopy seed bank, as occurs with 
   <span class="italic">Pinus contorta</span> ssp. 
   <span class="italic">latifolia</span> forests (Diskin et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0028">2011</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regeneration declines or failures have also been documented in cases of single‐species mortality (Burr &amp; McCullough, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0019">2014</a>; DeRose &amp; Long, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0027">2007</a>; Klooster et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0045">2014</a>; Pelz &amp; Smith, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0054">2012</a>). Laminated root rot in the Northwest has led to similar compositional changes as seen in 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> forests, where 
   <span class="italic">T. heterophylla</span> assumes dominance as canopy mortality of 
   <span class="italic">Pseudotsuga menziesii</span> proceeds (Hansen &amp; Goheen, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0034">2000</a>). Additionally, the 1990s 
   <span class="italic">Dendroctonus rufipennis</span> attack on 
   <span class="italic">Picea engelmannii</span> led to 
   <span class="italic">Abies lasiocarpa</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Populus tremuloides</span> dominance in the regenerating community, precluding 
   <span class="italic">P. engelmannii</span> from returning to dominance (DeRose &amp; Long, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0027">2007</a>). As with 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> response to canopy mortality, the primary limiting factor in all cases is an available seed source.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regenerating community response to canopy mortality is clearly influenced by a number of factors, such as establishment environment conditions, postdisturbance climate, seed availability, and herbivory—but available seed source is regularly identified as a primary limiting factor, regardless of disturbance type (e.g., fire vs. beetle attack) and magnitude (e.g., single vs. multiple species). Consistent with studies in other forest types and under different climate‐induced disturbances, our findings suggest that seed source (DeRose &amp; Long, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0027">2007</a>; Redmond et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0059">2018</a>; Urza &amp; Sibold, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0065">2017</a>) and microsite/establishment environments (Harvey, Donato, &amp; Turner, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0035">2016</a>; Redmond et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0059">2018</a>; Urza &amp; Sibold, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0065">2017</a>) are the most important factors in regenerating community response. Species tolerant of postdecline conditions will have a higher likelihood of future dominance, further reducing available seed and vegetative source of the declining species.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Documenting changes in communities following canopy mortality will be crucial to identifying the ecological, and potentially economic, consequences of these losses. Identifying successional trajectories, in particular, will reduce the large uncertainty around the long‐term impacts of climate change‐driven forest mortality events. Forest response to novel disturbance conditions will be hard to predict, and the lessons learned from these cases can help shift our expectations of postdisturbance stand dynamics, particularly in climate‐impacted systems.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35383-sec-0014" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystem resilience and transition to alternate stable states</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The consequences of rapid climate change on forest resilience remain uncertain and are likely to be highly variable, based on a particular forest's ecological memory (i.e., information legacies of ecological adaptations to disturbance; Johnstone et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0043">2016</a>). For forests to be resilient and resist transitions to alternate states, there must be synchrony between both information legacies (i.e., genetic adaptations to disturbance, like sprouting in avalanche‐prone ecosystems) and material legacies (i.e., the physical legacies, such as seedbanks, that are present after a disturbance event; Johnstone et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0043">2016</a>). Historically, 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis’</span> shallow root system and early response to spring warming were beneficial, allowing for early, rapid growth each growing season (Hennon et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0039">2016</a>); however, this once advantageous legacy is now a deleterious adaptation. Mortality in mature trees limits the potential for biological inertia (Young et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0072">2019</a>) due to a lack of available seed. Instead, advanced regeneration via vegetative reproduction remains a successful strategy even in areas of severe decline (unpublished data/personal observation). This may help the species maintain a presence on the landscape during periods of mature tree mortality until periods more favorable for sexual reproduction, similar to the “orphaned cohort” example of 
   <span class="italic">Fraxinus</span> in response to 
   <span class="italic">Agrilus planipennis</span> invasion (Klooster et al., 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0045">2014</a>). The immediate loss of seed‐producing trees and seedlings (Figures 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0002">2</a> and 
   <a rid="ece35383-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0003">3</a>), as well as competition from faster growing species, means these forests are lacking the biological inertia needed for resilience and are likely to transition to 
   <span class="italic">T. heterophylla</span>‐dominated forests even if 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> maintains some temporary or disjunct presence on the landscape. For species or forest types undergoing similar climate‐induced mortality events, ecologists will need to determine which legacies contribute to ecosystem resilience, or if novel climate or disturbance will remove these legacies that were historically critical.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystem resilience may also vary as a function of regional climate fluctuations over space and time, known as transitional climate mortality (Buma, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>), where mortality is highest within a particular range of climatic conditions but decreases above or below this range. Currently, the mid‐range of the 
   <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis’</span> distribution is experiencing mortality, but, if emissions scenarios continue toward worst‐case trajectories, it is possible that the mortality “donut‐hole” will be relatively short‐lived (Buma, 
   <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>). Short, intense climate fluctuations may therefore be less deleterious to ecosystem resilience if there are deep enough ecological legacies to sustain species over time.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
