<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35383-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is altering the conditions for tree recruitment, growth, and survival, and range shifts are a widely anticipated consequence of novel temperature and precipitation regimes. Local adaptation to historical climate is already creating mismatches between species’ current distributions and suitable habitat conditions (Aitken &amp; Bemmels, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0001">2015</a>; Aitken, Yeaman, Holliday, Wang, &amp; Curtis‐McLane, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0002">2008</a>), and these disparities are likely to be most extreme for seedlings, which have a narrower range of tolerance to climate conditions than mature individuals (Niinemets, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0051">2010</a>). As climate regimes shift, habitat suitable for survival of mature trees and the conditions necessary for germination and establishment may no longer correspond with each other, potentially leading to simultaneous canopy mortality and declines in regeneration, and, ultimately, shifts in species distributions (Walck, Hidayati, Dixon, Thompson, &amp; Poschlod, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0067">2011</a>). The key to regeneration success and long‐term survival will be continued synchronization of tree germination, establishment, and growth with local climate (Aitken &amp; Bemmels, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0001">2015</a>). In contrast, asynchronization will likely lead to restructuring of forest communities through dieback (Oakes, Hennon, O'Hara, &amp; Dirzo, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>), regeneration failures (Holz, Wood, Veblen, &amp; Bowman, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0042">2015</a>), or both (Anderegg, Kane, &amp; Anderegg, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0007">2013</a>). Inhibition of conifer regeneration, for example, could lead to ecosystem type conversions (Allen &amp; Breshears, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0004">1998</a>; Holz et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0042">2015</a>) and long‐term changes in stand dynamics (Turner, Dale, &amp; Everham, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0064">1997</a>). Thus, understanding the relative climatic tolerances of the mature and regeneration life phases of species is critical to predicting their response to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the driving processes are difficult to disentangle, species range contractions consist of concurrent or sequential canopy mortality and regeneration failures. Climate change‐induced canopy mortality is already a globally documented phenomenon (Allen, Breshears, &amp; McDowell, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0005">2015</a>; Allen et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0006">2010</a>). Altered precipitation regimes (i.e., change in timing, amount, frequency, type) combined with simultaneous increases in temperature are leading to both drought mortality (Guarín &amp; Taylor, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0033">2005</a>; Peng et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0055">2011</a>) and, at the other extreme, mortality attributed to earlier snowmelt and spring freezing events (Bourque, Cox, Allen, Arp, &amp; Meng, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0012">2005</a>). Drought‐induced canopy mortality is well‐established (Allen et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0005">2015</a>; Anderegg et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0007">2013</a>), and recent studies have quantified the impacts of prolonged drought (Redmond, Weisberg, Cobb, &amp; Clifford, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0059">2018</a>) and postfire drought conditions (Stevens‐Rumann et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0061">2017</a>; Young et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0072">2019</a>) on regeneration. However, relatively little is known about the consequences of reduced snowpack and early season frost damage on canopy mortality and regeneration response, although these phenomena may become more common as the climate warms (Woldendorp, Hill, Doran, &amp; Ball, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0071">2008</a>)—leading to root mortality and nutrient loss (Decker, Wang, Waite, &amp; Scherbatskoy, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0025">2003</a>), needle and bud injury (Man, Kayahara, Dang, &amp; Rice, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0047">2009</a>), canopy mortality (Buma, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>), and seedling mortality (Camarero &amp; Gutiérrez, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0020">2004</a>). Regardless of the climatic stressor, widespread canopy mortality is likely to be ongoing under the more extreme conditions predicted for the future, and under such conditions, range contraction potential will be governed by regeneration success or failure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not all climate‐driven mortality will result in a range contraction, as regeneration after extensive mortality is dependent upon two conditions: (a) available sources of seed and/or vegetative reproduction and (b) the establishment environment (climatic, abiotic, and biotic). Seed supply generally decreases with a loss of mature trees (Tepley, Veblen, Perry, Stewart, &amp; Naficy, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0063">2016</a>), and this loss can result in reductions in seedling abundances, lower recruitment into mature tree size classes, and the potential for local extirpation due to competition with nondecline‐affected species (Oakes et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>). Mortality of mature trees may, conversely, create more favorable establishment conditions by increasing available light and releasing advanced regeneration (Macek et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0046">2017</a>; Zeppenfeld et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0073">2015</a>) or leading to more successful germination and subsequent survival (Whitmore, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0069">1989</a>). Such increases in favorable microsites may partially offset canopy declines; under such conditions, regeneration of species declining in the canopy may increase despite a reduction in available seed—similar to pulses of recruitment following windthrow events (Dunn, Guntenspergen, &amp; Dorney, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0030">1983</a>; Peterson &amp; Pickett, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0056">1995</a>). Comparing the relative strength of seed source versus community competition and abiotic changes is therefore important in predicting the net effects of mortality and the potential for range shifts at broader scales—thus, resilience.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of canopy mortality on regeneration are, however, difficult to isolate, as climate change‐induced canopy mortality often leads to concurrent decline of multiple species. Concurrent declines challenge our ability to identify the factors driving reductions in suitable habitat for mature tree survival versus those leading to regeneration failures for individual species, as a variety of interspecific relationships are changing simultaneously. Simplified systems in which a single species undergoes climate‐related mortality in isolation of climate effects on co‐occurring species provide a means of parsing out the effects of climate change on mortality, regeneration, and the resultant ecological community.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Across the North Pacific coastal temperate rainforest (NPCTR) of southeast Alaska, USA, and British Columbia, Canada, 
  <span class="italic">Callitropsis nootkatensis,</span> D. Don, Oesrt. Ex D.P. Little (Alaska yellow‐cedar) is experiencing extensive, climate change‐driven mortality over more than 400,000 ha and ten degrees of latitude (Buma et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0017">2017</a>). Regional wintertime temperatures average 0°C; thus, a slight warming results in significant snow loss (Buma, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>). Subfreezing weather events following snowmelt in late winter and early spring kills fine roots of mature 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> (Hennon et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0039">2016</a>; Schaberg, Hennon, D'amore, &amp; Hawley, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0060">2008</a>), and this phenomenon has been ongoing for several decades (Beier, Sink, Hennon, D'Amore, &amp; Juday, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0009">2008</a>; Hennon, D'Amore, Schaberg, Wittwer, &amp; Shanley, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0036">2012</a>). Mortality drivers in this complex pathway include the limited cold tolerance of roots, a reduction in insulating snowpack due to warmer winters, soil freezing due to lack of insulation, and a positive feedback loop in which canopy gaps in declining forests lead to further reductions in springtime snowpack (Beier et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0009">2008</a>; Schaberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0060">2008</a>). Given predicted future climate conditions, 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> is likely to experience continued decline over most of its range (Buma, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>) and be replaced by other regionally dominant conifers (Oakes et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>). Co‐occurring 
  <span class="italic">Tsuga heterophylla</span> Raf. (Sarg) (western hemlock) and 
  <span class="italic">Picea sitchensis</span> Bong. (Carr) (Sitka spruce) are not considered sensitive to snow loss (Buma &amp; Barrett, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0016">2015</a>) and may increase in dominance when 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> fails to regenerate (Oakes et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>). Yet, despite extensive research on the drivers of decline (Barrett, Latta, Hennon, &amp; Eskelson, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0008">2012</a>; Buma et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0017">2017</a>; Hennon et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0036">2012</a>; Hennon, Hansen, &amp; Shaw, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0037">1990</a>; Hennon &amp; Shaw, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0040">1997</a>; Hennon, Shaw, &amp; Hansen, 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0041">1990</a>; Schaberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0060">2008</a>), little is known about 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> regeneration following canopy mortality, and the fate of 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> and long‐term dynamics of affected forests remain unknown.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address these knowledge gaps and isolate the conditions differentiating habitat suitable for mature tree survival versus those key to successful regeneration in a climate mortality‐affected system, we sampled declining 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> forests over a five‐degree latitude range in the NPCTR of southeast Alaska to ask the following: (a) “Does climate‐induced mortality occur across all size classes of the affected species, and, specifically, does regeneration response correspond with the same climate conditions driving mortality?”, (b) “If response is differential, what climatic and community factors drive tree mortality versus postdecline composition of the regenerating community?”, and (c) “Is community composition stable or in the process of a decline‐induced shift?”. Our analysis provides new insight into stand dynamics in a changing climate by increasing understanding of forest ecosystem response and rearrangement following the decline of a single species. Obtaining information on life stage response to climate‐induced mortality, postdecline community composition, and stand dynamics in the NPCTR and beyond will be essential to scientifically based forest management and vital to supporting conservation efforts in the face of climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
