<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35383-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plot design and sampling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 67 plots were compiled from published (Oakes et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>) and ongoing research by the authors in the perhumid NPCTR subregion of southeast Alaska (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35383-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0001">1</a>). This plot network represents all compatible studies in the region, with compatible defined as those including both regeneration and canopy community data, precise locations, comparable methodologies, and comparable scales. Due to aggregating across sources and studies, each with their own goals, plots were not randomly distributed across the region. However, the data products were compatible and collectively allowed for analysis of regeneration response to the canopy decline severity gradient.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece35383-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Map of 
    <span class="italic">Callitropsis nootkatensis</span> plot network distributed across southeast Alaska. Previously established plots were installed by Oakes and colleagues in 2011 and 2012 in Glacier Bay National Park (GBNP) and Chichagof Island (CHICH), and additional plots were installed by the authors in 2015 and 2016 on Kupreanof Island (KUP) and Prince of Wales Island (POW). Inset plots for illustration of the numerical distribution of plots only (scale varies). For a complete range and decline map, see Buma et al. (
    <a rid="ece35383-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0017">2017</a>) or Buma (
    <a rid="ece35383-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0015">2018</a>)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-8157-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plots installed by Oakes and colleagues (
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a>, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 50) were randomly selected from areas stratified by 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> status—live forests (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 20) and three time‐since‐mortality classes (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 10 each in recent, mid‐range, and old) on Chichagof Island and in Glacier Bay National Park (installed in 2011–2012, Figure 
  <a rid="ece35383-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0001">1</a>). These plots represent the northernmost extent of the contiguous species distribution while also approaching the northernmost extent of documented decline. Data were collected in nested, fixed‐radius plots: (a) 10.3m radius (~333 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) for mature trees (&gt;25 cm diameter at breast height, DBH) and (b) 6m radius (~113 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) for saplings (&lt;2.5 cm DBH and &gt;1 m in height), treelets (2.5–9.9 cm DBH), and small trees (10–24.9 cm DBH, see Oakes et al., 
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0052">2014</a> for details). In addition, conifer germinants and seedlings (&lt;10 cm height) were sampled using eight one‐m
  <span class="sup">2</span> quadrats (8m
  <span class="sup">2</span> total area sampled) installed in the cardinal directions at five and eight meters from plot center.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To extend inference across 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span>' distribution in southeast Alaska, we leveraged 17 additional nested, fixed‐radius plots on Kupreanof and Prince of Wales Islands (installed 2015–2016, Figure 
  <a rid="ece35383-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35383-fig-0001">1</a>). Mature and small trees (&gt;10 cm DBH) were sampled over a 400‐m
  <span class="sup">2</span> plot. Treelets, saplings, and advanced regeneration (&gt;10 cm but &lt;1.37m in height) were sampled in a nested 100‐m
  <span class="sup">2</span> plot. Germinants and seedlings (&lt;10 cm height) were tallied by species in four one‐m
  <span class="sup">2</span> quadrats at the corners of the 400‐m
  <span class="sup">2</span> plot (16 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> total area sampled). Hereafter, the term regeneration refers to the combined germinant and seedling classes, including all recently emerged germinants (i.e., cotyledons still visible) to seedlings less than 10cm in height and, presumably, &lt;2 years of age.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Across all plots, species, DBH, tree status (live/dead), live crown condition, and snag class were sampled for all trees. Snags were identified to species, if possible, and 
  <span class="italic">C. nootkatensis</span> snags classified into time‐since‐mortality classes according to Hennon, Shaw, et al. (
  <a rid="ece35383-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35383-bib-0041">1990</a>). Unidentifiable snags were classified as unknown species. Additionally, regeneration was identified to the genus for 
  <span class="italic">Tsuga</span> germinants (
  <span class="italic">heterophylla</span> and 
  <span class="italic">mertensiana</span>) but to the species for all other species and size classes. Disturbed areas (e.g., windthrow, landslides) were eliminated from plot selection to avoid the confounding influence of disturbance on community composition.
 </p>
</sec>
