<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">Heuristic frameworks and maps typically rely on predictions of multivariate climate change without explicit regard for specific impacts to particular ecosystems or species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. Instead, heuristics rely on assumptions that evaluations of changes in multiple dimensions of climate may provide useful guidance on the relative vulnerability of species and ecosystems
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. Climate vulnerability has been described as a function of climate exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, though we focus here on climate exposure (i.e. the degree of climate change likely to be experienced by a species or locale). Climate exposure metrics include predictions of changes in individual climate variables
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>, geographic displacement of climate analogues (i.e., climate velocity)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>, and multivariate shifts in climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. Various metrics of predicted exposure suggest that different regions may experience relatively high degrees of climate change depending on which metric is evaluated
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. These differences may reflect various ‘dimensions’ of climate change. Evaluating regions where high or low degrees of different exposure metrics coincide may be an important step in evaluating potential future impacts to complex ecosystems.
</p>
