<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">During the last decades, there have been substantial phenological changes in a large number of animal and plant species (Walther et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2002</xref>; Menzel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2006</xref>; Parmesan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">2007</xref>). As the typical direction of change has been an advancement of phenological events, it has been causally linked to recent climate change and in particular the global increase in temperatures (Sparks and Yates 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">1997</xref>; Stefanescu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2003</xref>). The results presented here add to this literature. More interestingly, this study and that of Karlsson (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2013</xref>) found that the rate of phenological change over time was correlated with the phenological changes across latitudes. This suggests that species of butterflies that show strong latitudinal variation in phenology, presumably due to spatial variation in climate, also tend to show strong effects of changes in climate over time. This correspondence is expected if the adaptations that control butterfly life cycles and phenology include response to aspects of climate that changes in a similar way over time and space, and that populations along the latitudinal gradient respond in similar ways to climatic cues. While temperature is one obvious and important aspect of climate, other cues, such as the photoperiod, will not show this type of parallel change in time and space, i.e., the photoperiod at a given time of year varies with latitude while it is not influenced by temporal changes in climate at any given location. For our particular study system, this pattern suggests that it is reasonable to use the “space for time” paradigm to get a rough idea of how climate is likely to affect the phenology of 
 <italic class="italic">A. cardamines</italic> and how this might influence its host utilization (Hodgson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2011</xref>). Indeed, it seems likely that both temporal and spatial changes in the phenology of 
 <italic class="italic">A. cardamines</italic> are reflecting strong effects of thermal conditions on the hatching of adults in comparison with other butterfly species. In support of this idea, the flight date of 
 <italic class="italic">A. cardamines</italic> shows a strong response to ambient spring temperature during pupal development where an increase of 1°C advances flight date with 6.4 days. Mean value for other univoltine butterflies overwintering in the pupal stage is an advancement of 3.3 days/°C (cf. Karlsson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
