<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33032-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The blue tit</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Along with the temperatures, the air pressure has a profound influence on the blue tit's song trait variability. There is not much known about how air pressure modulates sounds and thus birdsong, but it is known that with decreasing air pressure also the oxygen partial pressure decreases, that is, the lower the air pressure, the less oxygen in the air. Considering the lower oxygen partial pressure in the air, one might hypothesize that birds experiencing low air pressure would have a simpler song to ensure oxygen supply. The blue tit has a narrower bandwidth of the element with the maximum bandwidth within a verse, when the air pressure is low. Hence, our findings would support this conclusion.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There have been studies on bird song along elevational gradients, but they did not investigate the effect of the air pressure, and they did not compare within‐species variability but compared congeneric species, or species within a subfamily (Caro, Caycedo‐Rosales, Bowie, Slabbekoorn, &amp; Cadena, 
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0009">2013</a>; Jankowski, Robinson, &amp; Levey, 
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0033">2010</a>; Snell‐Rood &amp; Badyaev, 
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0049">2008</a>). At this stage, there is no simple explanation why the three species in our study react differently to changes in air pressure. Therefore, there is a need for further investigation to better understand how air pressure modulates sound and which effect it has on different song traits and their transmission and if species with similar song characteristics show similar changes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of the blue tit, hypothesis 3, that the bandwidth of the song widens with increasing air temperature, can be rejected. The bandwidth of their song is not influenced by air temperature, but by other weather parameters such as atmospheric humidity and average soil temperature.</p>
</sec>
