<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33032-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The blackbird</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimal linear models for each song parameter of the blackbird mostly contained weather parameters and only few urbanity parameters with significant 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values. The soil temperature parameters were the variables with the lowest 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values in most of the minimal models (Table 
  <a rid="ece33032-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#ece33032-tbl-0003">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The explanatory variables which stayed most often in the minimal models of the song parameters with significant 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values were the average soil temperature and the daytime. Variables which also remained quite often in the minimal models were the wind speed, the minimum soil temperature, and the number of hours of sunlight per day. Urbanity parameters rarely remained in the minimal models with significant 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average soil temperature and the daytime remained almost equally often in the minimal models of frequency and structure song parameters. The wind speed mainly remained in the minimal models for the structure song parameters.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pairwise correlation between the most important variables of a model and the corresponding song parameter showed, for example, a significant positive correlation between the mean soil temperature and the bandwidth of the verse (Pearson's rank correlation: 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = .37, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>* = .03) (Figure 
  <a rid="ece33032-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33032-fig-0004">4</a>). The bandwidth of the verse increased with the mean soil temperature.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33032-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Correlation plot for the blackbird. Increasing bandwidth of a verse with rising average soil temperature 5 cm below the ground surface (
    <span class="italic">r</span> = .37, 
    <span class="italic">p</span>* = .03, 
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 71)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-7-4868-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
