<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33032-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great tit</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimal linear models for each song parameter of the great tit contained urbanity and weather parameters with significant 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values. The variables with the lowest 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values in the different models mostly were weather parameters such as air and soil temperatures but also the amount of sunlight per day and the atmospheric humidity (Table 
  <a rid="ece33032-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#ece33032-tbl-0003">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The explanatory variables which stayed most often in the minimal models of the song parameters with significant 
  <span class="italic">p</span>‐values were the atmospheric humidity, the maximum soil temperature, and the minimum air temperature. Variables which also remained quite often in the minimal models were the soil and air temperatures as well as the building density and the number of hours of sunshine per day.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The maximum soil and minimum air temperature remained most often in the minimal models of frequency song parameters. Mostly, the atmospheric humidity remained in the minimal models for the structure song parameters.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In only one model among all species, an urbanity parameter was the most important variable: The building height explained most of the variation of the number of elements in a verse of the great tit's song (
  <span class="italic">b</span> = 2.16, 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 3.35, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = .002). This relationship was not significant when performing a pairwise correlation (Pearson's rank correlation: 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = .23, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>* = 2.75) (Figure 
  <a rid="ece33032-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33032-fig-0003">3</a>a).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33032-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Correlation plots for the great tit. (a) Non‐significant correlation of the building height with the number of elements within a verse (
    <span class="italic">r</span> = .23, 
    <span class="italic">p</span>* = 2.75, 
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 50). (b) Rising duration of the shortest element within a verse with increasing average atmospheric humidity per day (
    <span class="italic">r</span> = .57, 
    <span class="italic">p</span>* &lt; .001, 
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 50)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-7-4868-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pairwise correlation between the other most important variables of a model and the corresponding song parameter showed, for example, a highly significant correlation between the atmospheric humidity and the duration of the shortest element within a verse (Pearson's rank correlation: 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = .57, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>* &lt; .001) (Figure 
  <a rid="ece33032-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33032-fig-0003">3</a>b). The duration of the shortest element within a verse increased with the mean atmospheric humidity.
 </p>
</sec>
