<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33032-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great tit</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The atmospheric humidity is one of the most important variables in the minimal models for the great tit along with soil and air temperature variables and the amount of sunlight per day. The atmospheric humidity plays a more important role in the models of the structure parameters as in the minimal model for the duration of the shortest element within a verse. Briefly, with increasing atmospheric humidity, the elements become longer.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Harris (
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0030">1966</a>) and Gomez‐Augustina, Dance, and Shield (
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0029">2014</a>) describe the effects of air temperature and atmospheric humidity on sound attenuation and reverberation times. In general, high frequencies are absorbed the most and even more so when atmospheric humidity is low. Reverberation time is low when frequencies are high and when atmospheric humidity is low. The great tit, which has a mean frequency of about 4.6 kHz (Table 
  <a rid="ece33032-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece33032-sup-0001">S1</a>), is situated in a medium frequency range and therefore less affected by sound attenuation. But as reverberation time increases with lower frequencies along the atmospheric humidity, it might be an explanation for the importance of the atmospheric humidity in the minimal models of the great tit as well as the highly significant correlation of the duration of the shortest elements within a verse with the humidity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great tit has longer elements within a verse when humidity is high, and hence, the elements have high reverberation times (for graphics see Harris (
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0030">1966</a>) and Gomez‐Augustina et al. (
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0029">2014</a>)). The high reverberation time might favor the sound transmission and might facilitate song perception by females (Slabbekoorn, Ellers, &amp; Smith, 
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0046">2002</a>). Some of the great tit's song types might be defined as narrow frequency bandwidth notes as described by Slabbekoorn et al. (
  <a rid="ece33032-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33032-bib-0046">2002</a>) and might show these benefits from reverberation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of the great tit, hypothesis 3—increasing air temperatures supposedly leading to a wider bandwidth of the song—can be rejected. The minimum air temperature stays in the minimal model for the bandwidth of the song; nevertheless, the direct correlation is not significant. The bandwidth of the song might not be an appropriate song parameter for identifying the influence of weather parameters on the great tit's song. This might be due to the fact that the latter is grouped into motifs that are repeated, but mostly stay within a certain frequency range in contrast to, for example, the versatile song of the blackbird.</p>
</sec>
