<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Speleothems P09-H1b, P10-H2 and P10-H5 were collected from Huagapo Cave in the central Peruvian Andes. The study site has mean annual rainfall of 690 mm, with about 65% falling during the austral summer (Peruvian Meteorological Service, SENAMHI, unpublished data, 1919–1999). Seasonal temperature variation is small, average summer temperatures in the central Peruvian Andes at 3750 m are 11 °C compared to winter temperatures of 9 °C at the same elevation (SENAMHI). Cave air temperatures at the time of sampling were 12 °C, relative humidity was not measured. Huagapo Cave is 2,844 meters in length and was formed within a Triassic dolomitic limestone massif
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Stalagmites P09-H1b, P10-H2 and P10-H5 are 13.5, 22 and 109 cm tall, respectively. All samples are 100% calcite as confirmed by X-ray diffraction analysis. Each stalagmite was cut into halves along the growth axis and polished. Subsamples of approximately 100 milligrams were milled parallel to growth layers for radiometric dating. For stable oxygen and carbon isotope analysis, subsamples of approximately 200 micrograms were taken as along the center of the growth with a 0.6 mm drill bit.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The radiometric dates (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) were measured using a multi-collector, inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (MC-ICPMS) on a Thermo-Finnigan Neptune at the Minnesota Isotope Laboratory with procedures similar to those described in
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. The stable isotopic analyses were performed at the University of Massachusetts using an on-line carbonate preparation system linked to a Finnigan Delta Plus XL ratio mass spectrometer. Results are reported as the per mil difference between sample and the Vienna Pee Dee Belemnite standard in delta notation where δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O = (R
  <sub>sample</sub>/R
  <sub>standard</sub> − 1) ∗ 1000, and R is the ratio of the minor to the major isotope. Reproducibility of the standard materials is better than 0.08‰. Values are reported relative to the VPDB standard.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A time-series analysis of the oxygen isotope record was conducted on an equally spaced fifty-year composite record filtered to remove orbital scale variability. The composite was created by taking an annual interpolation using a piecewise cubic hermite interpolating polynomial, then averaging to fifty-year bins. A 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> order Butterworth high pass filter with a frequency of 5000 years was then applied to remove the first order orbital scale signal.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two time-series analyses were then conducted on the filtered composite record. First, an autocorrelation, with significance-level calculations including red-noise of the composite record was done. Butterworth and autocorrelation calculations were conducting using MATLAB functions created by Dave Heslop, now at The Australian National University. Second, a continuous wavelet transform using a Morelet wavelet to determine spectral relationships in the time-frequency space
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All data will be made available online through the NOAA National Centers for Environmental Information (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/data-access/paleoclimatology-data/datasets" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/data-access/paleoclimatology-data/datasets</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
