<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Site and core collection</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ice-rich peat cores were collected from a peatland we refer to as DHP174 (65.21°N, 138.32°W; Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a–f</a>), situated in the continuous permafrost zone. The peatland is dominated by 
   <span class="italic">Sphagnum</span> spp. moss, and includes sparse forb and lichen groundcover, and an open canopy of 
   <span class="italic">Picea mariana</span> trees. DHP174 is a soligenous peatland, sustained by precipitation and seasonal runoff from a south-flanking hillslope. There is ~15–20 m of relief across the ~100–150 m peatland surface, measured from the bottom of the hillslope to the northern edge of the peatland
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. The slope ensures continuous drainage of surface and active layer runoff throughout the thaw season, and well-drained conditions in the uppermost 20–30 cm of peat. Saturated conditions during the summer occur below 20–30 cm depth and are maintained by elevated summer precipitation totals (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>) and low saturated hydraulic conductivities (e.g. ~ 1 m day
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) that are typical below 30 cm depth in northern peat plateaus
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. The DHP174 peatland sits on an alluvial terrace in a valley that drains into Engineer Creek (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) and is underlain by permafrost, which limits runoff to the seasonally thawed active layer.
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the water isotope analysis presented in this study, we collected two 10 cm diameter core profiles using a portable permafrost drilling system
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>. The first core profile (DHP174-13, 3.83 m long) is from the ‘undisturbed’ upper surface, and the second core profile (DHP174-13L, 3.32 m long) was collected from an ‘excavated’ lower surface (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>); the cores overlap stratigraphically, and the lower core includes the basal peats and underlying strata. The lower surface was excavated by the highway maintenance authority before 2007 (Google Earth time stamp) to thermally erode the underlying permafrost in order to expand the roadside quarry shown in the satellite images (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d, e</a>). At the time of coring (June 2013), frozen ground was encountered 16 and 24 cm below ground at the upper and lower coring sites, respectively, which are also the starting depths of the cores.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pore ice sampling and water isotope analysis</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The frozen cores were split along their long axis with a bandsaw. The two core profiles were sub-sampled into 1 cm increments. For the DHP174-13 core, every tenth centimetre increment of pore ice was analysed for water isotopes starting from the core top (16 cm below the surface) to core bottom (382 cm composite depth); the only exception being DHP174-13 core depths 16–76 cm, which were analysed at near 1 cm resolution to allow for a more detailed analysis of pore ice in the active layer and across the active layer–permafrost interface. For the DHP174-13L core, every tenth centimetre increment of pore ice was analysed for water isotopes starting at a depth of 30 cm below the lower coring surface (230 cm composite depth; see Methods—chronology) down to the basal sediments at 530 cm composite depth). In total, 104 pore ice samples were analysed for water isotope ratios, 43 of which are active layer or transient layer pore ice, and 71 of which are relict pore ice.</p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The frozen samples were thawed at ~4 °C in plastic bags and the liquid was filtered into 2 mL autosampler vials. δD and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O ratios of the water were measured at the University of Alberta using a Picarro L2130-
   <span class="italic">i</span> analyser. Unknowns and standards were injected eight times, and mean raw values were calculated from the last four injections. Raw isotope ratios were corrected for inter-sample memory effects that are common to cavity ring-down spectroscopy systems
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
   </span>. We used certified water reference standards (USGS-45 and USGS-46) to normalise raw isotope ratios to the Vienna Standard Mean Ocean Water-Standard Light Antarctic Precipitation (VSMOW-SLAP) scale. Analytical error is 0.6‰ for δD and 0.1‰ for δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O based on routine analysis of an internal deionised water standard.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Peat-sediment age-depth model</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A composite Bayesian age-depth model for the peat-sediment sequence was produced using radiocarbon (
   <span class="sup">14</span>C) dates and cryptotephra isochrons (see Davies
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span> for full details of the composite chronology). Depths are reported as core composite depths (ccd). The Bayesian age-depth model (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>) was constructed using the OxCal Poisson process model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seventeen macrofossil samples were picked for 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C dating from the upper monolith and core profiles (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This includes three dates from a previously collected core that was not used for pore ice analysis (DHP174-12, cored within 1.5 m of DHP174-13), but is included in the age model as it has precise modern cryptotephra and post-bomb 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C dates for its surface peat. Dates from all three cores were included in a composite profile where cryptotephra tie-points were used to correlate between the individual core profiles.
  </p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where possible, 
   <span class="italic">Sphagnum</span> remains were preferred as they can provide reliable 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C dates
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
   </span>. In the mineragenic, non-peat core sections at the base of the DHP174-13L profile, terrestrial plant macrofossils (twigs and leaves) were used for 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C dating. Samples were pre-treated at the University of Alberta following standard procedures
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>, and analysed for 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C content at the W. M. Keck Carbon Cycle AMS Laboratory (University of California, Irvine, CA, USA). Two secondary standards were pre-treated concurrently (a last interglacial non-finite-age wood, AVR-PAL-07; and a middle Holocene wood, FIRI-F) and the 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C results were within expected ranges. The unknown 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C dates were calibrated as appropriate using Bomb13NH1
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
   </span> and IntCal13
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span> calibration curves with Oxcal v4.3.2
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Glass shard concentration profiles for cryptotephra were produced at 1 cm resolution using standard methods
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
   </span>. Three samples geochemically correlated with known eruptions using major element EPMA glass analyses (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>; see Davies
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span>) were included in the composite age-depth model to improve model accuracy. Katmai-Novarupta (10 ccd) is a historic eruption with an observed occurrence date of 1912 CE. The Aniakchak CFE II (116 ccd) and Hayes set H unit F2 (133 ccd) eruptions are widely reported in Alaska and beyond, and have well-constrained Bayesian age estimates
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chronology of relict pore ice</div>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meteoric waters that reach the maximum thaw depth of ~58 cm (see maximum active layer thickness or ALT
   <sub>max</sub> in Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) will eventually freeze in situ as pore ice during the fall freezeback and become ‘relict’ as permafrost aggradation occurs. Since permafrost aggradation is paced by the accumulation of materials at the surface (peat or sediment), the age of relict pore ice at any given depth below the permafrost table can be referenced from the peat-sediment age-depth model by accounting for the 58 cm offset between relict pore ice and its contemporaneous surface. For example, ca. modern relict pore ice at 58 cm composite depth is age-equivalent to the modern surface (i.e. –63 cal yr BP in the age-depth model); likewise, relict pore ice at 530 cm composite depth is age-equivalent to a paleosurface at a composite depth of 472 cm (13,585 cal yr BP in our age-depth model). We assume a static ALT
   <sub>max</sub> of 58 cm through time. Although ALT
   <sub>max</sub> potentially did vary throughout the Holocene due to changes in summer climate, it likely remained within 3–6 cm of the modern ALT
   <sub>max</sub> value and does not significantly influence our pore ice chronology or conclusions (Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">LMWL and local temperature-δ
   <sub>precip</sub> calibration
  </div>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The δ
   <sub>precip</sub> isoscape of northern Canada is spatially complex due to regional differences in mean weather system trajectories, continentality, local orographic effects and varying degrees of continental moisture recycling
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
   </span>. Because each study area has its own potentially unique set of boundary conditions, δ
   <sub>precip</sub> signals preserved in ground ice are best interpreted in the context of local δ
   <sub>precip</sub> systematics
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>. We demonstrate the meteoric origins and seasonality of DHP174 pore ice by comparison with monthly δD and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
   </span> from the nearest GNIP station at Mayo, Yukon, ~210 km south of DHP174 (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). Mayo and DHP174 are situated at similar elevations (600 and 720 m, respectively) in central Yukon in the western foothills of the Ogilvie Mountains. The Mayo data were used to constrain the LMWL (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>), and the temperature-δ
   <sub>precip</sub> regression lines (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>; Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Three Mayo records that plotted far below the LMWL (see Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) were excluded from the regressions because of suspected evaporative enrichment. Extreme leverage points (&gt;3
   <span class="italic">σ</span> Cook’s distance) were given a weight of zero in the calibration to avoid undue bias on the regression lines. By comparison with monthly GNIP data from Whitehorse (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>), a site that is ~325 km south of Mayo and has a similar LMWL
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>, the Mayo temperature-δ
   <sub>precip</sub> regressions are found to be skilful in predicting δ
   <sub>precip</sub> at other continental sites in Yukon (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which supports their application to more proximal sites such as DHP174.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seawater correction</div>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Precipitation isotope ratios over long timescales reflect climatic signals and changes in the isotopic composition of marine source waters (δ
   <sub>seawater</sub>). To isolate local climate signals in δ
   <sub>precip (pore ice)</sub>, which are unrelated to changes in seawater, the composite pore ice record was corrected for long-term δ
   <sub>seawater</sub> changes following the general equation [
   <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>] from Stenni et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
   </span>:
   <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">1</span>
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\mathrm{\delta }}_{{\mathrm{corrected}}} = {\mathrm{\delta }}_{{\mathrm{ice}}} - {\mathrm{\delta }}_{{\mathrm{seawater}}} \times \left( {{\mathrm{1}} + {\mathrm{\delta }}_{{\mathrm{ice}}}{\mathrm{/1000}}} \right){\mathrm{/}}\left( {{\mathrm{1}} + {\mathrm{\delta }}_{{\mathrm{seawater}}}{\mathrm{/1000}}} \right).$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">δ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">corrected</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">δ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">ice</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">-</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">δ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">seawater</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">1</span>
        <span class="mo">+</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">δ</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">ice</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">∕1000</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">∕</span>
      <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">1</span>
        <span class="mo">+</span>
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">δ</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">seawater</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">∕1000</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">.</span>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9622_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assume the δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>seawater</sub> reconstruction by Rohling et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
   </span> and that δD
   <sub>seawater</sub> changes were ~8× larger than δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>seawater</sub>, as supported by data from Late Pleistocene marine pore waters
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
   </span> and as assumed by others
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature reconstruction</div>
  <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two types of temperature estimates were made based on the pore ice record—mean temperatures for the modern era (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>) and a full Holocene reconstruction of temperature anomalies (Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5d</a>). The first was calculated based on δD
   <sub>pore ice</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pore ice</sub> of ca. modern relict pore ice (58–61 cm, uppermost 3 cm of permafrost from the DHP174-13 core), and was used as a line of evidence to validate the proposed summer seasonality of pore ice. Mean temperature estimates depend on the slope (
   <span class="italic">m</span>) and intercept (
   <span class="italic">b</span>) of the δ
   <sub>precip</sub>-temperature regression line, and δ
   <sub>pore ice</sub> values corrected for the first ice enrichment effect (ε
   <sub>ice-water</sub>; 5.8‰ and 0.8‰ for δD
   <sub>pore ice</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pore ice</sub>, respectively; Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). Uncertainties in the mean temperature estimates take into account the 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span> error in δD
   <sub>pore ice</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O
   <sub>pore ice</sub> measurements, and 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span> uncertainties in the regression slope and intercept. The general formula used to calculate mean temperatures based on either isotope is: 
   <span class="italic">T</span> = ([δ
   <sub>pore ice</sub> ± 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span>] –  
   <span class="italic">ε</span>
   <sub>ice-water</sub> – [
   <span class="italic">b</span> ± 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span>])/[
   <span class="italic">m</span> ± 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature anomalies (Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>) were reconstructed for the full Holocene based on δD
   <sub>pore ice</sub> anomalies (ΔδD
   <sub>pore ice</sub>, relative to Holocene mean) and the δD
   <sub>precip</sub>–temperature slope (
   <span class="italic">m</span>). Since ε
   <sub>ice-water</sub> is assumed to be a constant (Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>), ΔδD
   <sub>pore ice</sub> and ΔδD
   <sub>precip</sub> are equal. The formula used for estimating Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span> is: Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span> = [ΔδD
   <sub>pore ice</sub> ± 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span>]/[
   <span class="italic">m</span> ± 1
   <span class="italic">σ</span>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
