<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantification of radiative forcing by anthropogenic well-mixed greenhouse gases (WMGHGs) is required to detect and attribute the historical impacts of these agents on the climate since industrialization and to project their future impacts on Earth’s system. The primary role of WMGHGs is to enhance the atmospheric greenhouse effect through absorption and re-emission of terrestrial infrared, or longwave, radiation (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). However, a significant secondary role of the WMGHGs CO
  <sub>2</sub>, CH
  <sub>4</sub>, and N
  <sub>2</sub>O is to absorb incoming solar radiation, thereby heating the atmosphere while simultaneously reducing the surface insolation (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>). The shortwave effects of methane have been omitted from the radiative forcing formulae used in past assessments by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). While the forcing formulae have recently been updated to correct this omission (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>), those findings raise questions about whether estimates of the forcing by methane will continue to evolve and, if so, by how much. Any overlooked aspects of CH
  <sub>4</sub> absorption could lead to revised radiative forcing estimates with potentially significant ramifications for the relative prioritization both of scientific investigations and of mitigation strategies for anthropogenic WMGHGs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper concerns quantifying two significant uncertainties in the shortwave effects of CH
  <sub>4</sub> and the implications for the estimation of anthropogenic methane radiative forcing. The global uncertainties are associated with the rapidly evolving scientific understanding of CH
  <sub>4</sub> spectroscopy and the regional uncertainties with existing parameterizations of forcing based on limited numbers of radiative transfer calculations. Our incomplete knowledge of methane’s absorption features, and hence the uncertainties in our calculations of CH
  <sub>4</sub> shortwave forcing, is due to the remarkable complexity of methane spectroscopic line data (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>). Its current derivation from laboratory measurements and theory is known to be seriously incomplete (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>). Astronomical observations indicate that methane is a broadband solar absorber with absorption bands of widely varying strengths across the visible and near-infrared spectrum, extending to violet light wavelengths at 25,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>). However, current spectroscopic databases informed by laboratory and detailed theoretical calculations, such as the High-Resolution Transmission (HITRAN) (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) and the Gestion et Étude des Informations Spectroscopiques Atmosphériques (GEISA) (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>), exhibit shortwave coverage over just the near-infrared absorption features between 3000 and 11,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. There are at least three orders of magnitude more absorption lines than are currently tabulated in these databases (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>). As these spectroscopic data are the basis for all existing calculations of CH
  <sub>4</sub> shortwave forcing using reference line-by-line (LBL) models (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) and for every shortwave parameterization used in global climate models (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>), these calculations and parameterizations all omit the absorption of sunlight by methane at wave numbers greater than 11,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In principle, this omitted absorption could systematically increase the radiative forcing by CH
  <sub>4</sub>. Over 64% (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>) of solar insolation occurs at wave numbers ν &gt; 11,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, and hence there is 1.78 times more energy to absorb in this portion of the solar spectrum than at ν ≤ 11,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. In addition, several processes including greater Rayleigh scattering (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>) and higher cloud and land surface albedos (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>) act to increase path lengths traversed by photons with ν &gt; 11,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> relative to longer wavelengths. The resulting increase in tropospheric absorption path lengths from increased atmospheric and surface scattering (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>) at ν &gt; 11,000 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> reduces the flux of upwelling diffuse solar radiation at the tropopause, thereby potentially increasing the net direct radiative forcing by methane.
 </p>
</sec>
