<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone.0197689.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0197689.g004</object-id>
 <label class="label">Fig 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Effect of province of origin, education, and political view as predictors of perceptions on impacts of climate change across the Canadian forest sector.</title>
  <p class="p">Conditional Inference (CI) classification trees split the dataset into different groups based on certain values of the explanatory variables. At each intermediate mode, dataset is split into two groups based on the values of the explanatory variable indicated in the branches under the node. For statement 1.4, the first node splits the sample into liberals (political view (≤ 3, in a scale from 1 to 7) and moderates and conservatives. Liberal respondents are further split as a function of their province of orgin. Those respondents from westernmost provinces (British Columbia, BC; and Alberta, AB) were more likely than those from Ontario (ON), Québec (QC) or New Brunswick (NB) to consider climate change as a threat to them (a) and already having a significant impact on forest ecosystems (b). In the latter, this distinction was only observed among respondents holding a Bachelor in Sciences (BSc) or a higher degree, whereas those with lower degrees were the most unsure about the impacts on forest ecosystems. Stacked bar plot at each terminal node indicates the proportion of respondents that disagreed (dark gray), agreed (light gray) or were unsure (gray) about the statement. Total sample size depends on the statement, and can be calculated adding the sample size of the terminal nodes (indicated by brackets). Each tree only shows statistically significant variables at p &lt; 0.05. The classification accuracy for each conditional inference tree is also provided. The CI trees for the all the statements included in the survey can be found at 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0197689.s004" class="xref">S4 File</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0197689.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
