<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">There have been two types of assessments of prediction skill of the PDO index; one, correlation coefficient between observed and predicted indices or area-average SSTs over several decades, and two, prediction skill of specific warm or cold events. An example of the former type is a skill assessment of decadal hindcasts of the PDO index in five CMIP5 ESMs by Kim et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2012</xref>) who found that there was a reasonably significant prediction skill for up to five years after prediction initialization, but that this skill was less than that derived from persistance of the PDO index. An example of the latter type of skill assessment is the improved prediction skill of the mid-to-late 1970s change in the PDO phase from negative (cold) to positive (warm) in combined initial and boundary value experiments with several CMIP5 and other ESMs by Meehl and Teng (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2012</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2014</xref>) compared to uninitialized experiments or simulations as boundary value experiments. As mentioned earlier and described in detail by Meehl et al. (2014), reasonably high skill of area-average North Atlantic SSTs is shown by several ESMs [see, for example, Keenlyside et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2008</xref>), Pohlmann et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2009</xref>), van Oldenborgh et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2012</xref>), Yang et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2012</xref>), Hazeleger et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2013</xref>), Ham et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2014</xref>), and others]. Using decadal hindcast data from four CMIP5 ESMs, Mehta et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2013b</xref>) found that there was significant, but variable, decadal hindcast skill of global- and tropical ocean basin-average SSTs during 1961 to 2010. The skill varied by averaging region and decade. It was also found that low-latitude volcanic eruptions can be one of the sources of decadal SST hindcast skill when major eruptions occurred. In the four ESMs, decadal hindcast skills of SST anomalies over ocean basin size averaging regions generally improved due to model initialization with observed data. Kirtman et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2013</xref>) summarize conclusions about decadal prediction that “Predictions for averages of temperature, over large regions of the planet and for the global mean, exhibit positive skill when verified against observations for forecast periods up to ten years.” Thus, there is slow and incremental, but definite, progress in making skillful decadal climate predictions.
</p>
