<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">To expand the potential for applying decadal climate predictions to societal impacts adaptation, new prediction approaches need to be evolved from the points of view of users of decadal climate information—farmers, water managers, and other stakeholders and policymakers—if the predicted information is to be useful for application. Although impacts of quantitative changes in DCV indices on hydro-meteorology (and, consequently, on water resources and agriculture) have not attracted much attention from researchers, impacts of DCV phases—positive and negative—are known much better via analyses of empirical data and via experiments with numerical models of the global atmosphere [see, for example, Schubert et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2004a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">b</xref>)]. Therefore, data and information such as phase (positive or negative) of average anomaly in precipitation and temperature, river flow, drought index, and other quantities over the next 2–10 years can be very useful for management decisions in water and agriculture sectors if the data and information are provided at the spatial resolution required for each sector (Mehta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2013a</xref>; Mehta 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2017</xref>). A study of the value of decadal climate information to the agriculture sector in the Missouri River Basin—the largest river basin in the U.S. and a major “bread basket” of the world - with a water and crop choices model showed that the correct prediction of important DCV phenomena one year in advance can be worth approximately $80 million per year (Fernandez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2016</xref>). This study also showed that the correct prediction of even the phase of the DCV phenomena one year in advance can realize a sizeable fraction of this monetary value. Therefore, accurate prediction of DCV phase transitions sustained for several months to a year or longer can be useful in the adaptation of worldwide agriculture and water resources to DCV-related hydro-meteorological conditions, with important consequences for water and food securities. Since decision processes in these sectors utilize probabilistic information, accurate predictions of DCV phase transition probabilities would be very useful to these sectors. Understanding and prediction of DCV phases is also important for attribution of DCV phase transitions to internal ocean–atmosphere processes or changes in external forcings.
</p>
