<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fast ice, icebergs and benthic blue carbon</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Southern Ocean sea surface features striking contrasts in albedo between open water and sea ice, and as such remote sensing is an ideal tool to detect trends in sea-ice spatial and temporal extent [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C2">2</a>]. Satellite data can be enhanced (when cloud obscures satellite image capture) and ground-truthed by 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> manually operated or remote image capture. Around Antarctica these have proved to be complex, in terms of extent, geography and drivers of change. Overall, there have been marginal increases in Southern Ocean sea ice to date, but there have also been considerable losses around West Antarctic continental shelves and even larger gains, mainly over deeper water, in the Weddell and Ross Seas [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C1">1</a>]. The consequences of sea-ice losses and gains remain poorly understood but strongly influence local physical characteristics such as heat and gas exchange, biological activity such as phytoplankton bloom timing, duration and composition [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C20">20</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C21">21</a>], and iceberg scouring rates [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C22">22</a>]. Research has identified diverse and far-reaching secondary consequences to fauna such as habitat and food provision, impacting breeding of higher predators to feeding and composition of zooplankton [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C23">23</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C24">24</a>]. Near-coast sea-ice losses and responses of benthic organisms to such sea-ice losses are hard to monitor as station-based direct observation is crucial [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C6">6</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C25">25</a>]. Such work is both time- and labour-intensive and only yields small spatial coverage (rarely more than square kilometres), so collaborative efforts are needed to increase coverage and analyse resulting data [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C26">26</a>]. To date few locations maintain ‘long-term’ observations of sea-ice status (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F1" href="#RSTA20170176F1">figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>) to ground-truth coastal remote-sensed data, and even fewer are monitoring benthos responses (red circles, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F1" href="#RSTA20170176F1">figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>). Circumpolar satellite-derived data have revealed that the WAP particularly is a hotspot for sea-ice losses. Iceberg scour can be very frequent in the shallows if the area above it is free of fast ice (because there is less obstruction to wind-driven travel) [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C22">22</a>]. New data from seabed-ice scour monitoring adjacent to Carlini station [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C25">25</a>] (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F1" href="#RSTA20170176F1">figure 1</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>) shows even higher rates than at Rothera. As at Rothera, the site (at Carlini) closest to a glacier terminus showed some very high scouring rates, suggesting that local iceberg production as well as fast ice are important factors for seabed disturbance. We suggest that climate forcing has made the WAP a hotspot for coastal iceberg scouring. Results from the longest running (2003 onwards) iceberg scour-monitoring experiment near Rothera research station [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>] showed that ice scouring can reduce by half the carbon held by shallow benthos in a single year. Scaled up to the area of the WAP shallows, this may annually recycle an estimated 8 × 10
  <span class="sup">4</span> tonnes of carbon per year [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>] that otherwise could have been buried—and represents a major source of previously unaccounted variability in carbon capture and storage. That study showed that blue carbon standing stock recovery took 4–6 years in the shallows. This is hard to test at typical shelf depths but we reanalysed 36 samples of benthic images with matched trawl specimens from Barnes &amp; Sands [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C26">26</a>] collected in 2011 from site 12 (at which Polarview showed an iceberg was grounded in 2004, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F2" href="#RSTA20170176F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>), and sites 11 and 13 (which showed no evidence of having been scoured in the remote-sensing era). We found no significant difference between scoured and unscoured samples with respect to blue carbon stock mass (ANOVA, df1, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> = 1.69, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.2), suggesting recovery is at least possible within approximately 7 years even at a 200 m depth on the South Georgia shelf. Part of the problem and complexity of analyses of iceberg blue carbon impact, at least coastally, is the confounding effects of sea ice and phytoplankton blooms. In shallow coastal waters, sea-ice losses drive both blue carbon decreases by increased scour probability, and increases through longer phytoplankton blooms sustaining benthic growth. To examine the relationship between sea ice and benthic biomass, we reanalysed data presented in Barnes [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C6">6</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>] from Marguerite Bay (1997–2016) and examined the relationship between benthic biomass (blue carbon storage) and fast-ice duration, and how this changes with depth from the shallows down to 1000 m (data from 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F2" href="#RSTA20170176F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). We found that, in the top approximately 10 m, there was a positive correlation between blue carbon and sea-ice duration (zone A, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F2" href="#RSTA20170176F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). We interpret this as longer sea-ice durations reduce ice scour chances, which outweighs slower growth from the shorter phytoplankton blooms. There was no relationship between benthic blue carbon and sea-ice duration from 10–40 m depth (zone B, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F2" href="#RSTA20170176F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>), which is probably explained by the reduction in ice scour chances due to longer sea-ice durations approximately balancing slower growth from the shorter phytoplankton blooms. At typical continental shelf depths (200–500 m), there were negative correlations between blue carbon and sea-ice duration (zone C, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F2" href="#RSTA20170176F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). Ice scour chances are so rare in deep water (because few icebergs are big enough to have keels hundreds of metres deep) that longer sea-ice durations have little impact on this, so the main effect is slower growth from shorter phytoplankton blooms. Between 40 and 200 m is a zone of very little benthic sampling, perhaps often too shallow or geographically close to shallows for safe ship operation but too deep for self-contained underwater breathing apparatus (SCUBA)—a data-poor zone that we need to address (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTA20170176F2" href="#RSTA20170176F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). 
  <div id="RSTA20170176F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Monitoring sea ice and iceberg activity in West Antarctica. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) Monitoring sites, using automated cameras (black circles) and manual observations (white circle), of sea-ice extent in time and space. Monitoring sites of both sea-ice extent and annual iceberg scouring (red circles) at Rothera (bottom red circle) and Carlini (top red circle) [
     <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>,
     <a rid="RSTA20170176C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C21">21</a>]. (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) Relationship between duration of fast-ice cover each year and ice scouring on the seabed at Rothera and Carlini (inner bay in orange, outer bay in red) stations. The 
     <span class="italic">y</span>-axis shows the proportion of the monitored seabed from a 5–25 m depth hit by icebergs. Pearson's correlation line (−0.86, 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) drawn through Rothera data only. 
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsta20170176-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="RSTA20170176F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Iceberg impacts on seabed blue carbon. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) Iceberg grounded at South Georgia in 2004; photo courtesy of US National Ice Center. Sites 11, 12 and 13 are benthic image and trawl samples. The island in the image (left) is South Georgia and iceberg size is 75 × 41 km. (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) Correlation between sea-ice duration and blue carbon storage on the seabed around southern Adelaide Island, West Antarctic Peninsula (from data in Barnes [
     <a rid="RSTA20170176C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C6">6</a>,
     <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>] ). Zones are zoobenthic carbon; significant increase with increased fast-ice duration (A), no significant change (B,D), significant decrease with increased fast-ice duration (C) and depth zone where there is too little known for meaningful analysis (zone of ignorance).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsta20170176-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
