<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strongest measured and most visible impact of climate change in the polar regions has been the drastic shift in sea-ice extent. Over the last four decades, the seasonal sea-ice maximum area and duration have decreased considerably over the Arctic and West Antarctica [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C1">1</a>]. By contrast, around parts of East Antarctica, such as the Weddell and Ross Seas, there have been ever stronger sea-ice gains [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C2">2</a>]. Alongside this, there have been other important marine-ice changes, including increases in the number of marine glaciers in retreat and their retreat rate, as well as major ice shelf disintegrations [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C3">3</a>]. Reductions in West Antarctic sea ice, particularly the winter fast ice (here defined as the seasonal frozen sea surface, which is connected to land), have already seen pronounced responses from pagophilic (ice-associated) higher predators and the highly productive pelagic zooplankton, such as Antarctic krill [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C4">4</a>]. In our work, we focus on marine-ice interactions with life on the Southern Ocean seabed (benthos) for several reasons: (i) it is less well known and understood; (ii) the vast majority of Antarctica's species live there and nearly all are endemic (live only there); and perhaps most importantly (iii) benthos perform a key ecosystem service of carbon storage and burial, known as blue carbon [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C5">5</a>]. Blue carbon (carbon in organisms) in polar waters has been little considered to date, with scientific attention mainly focusing at lower latitudes on kelp forests, seagrass beds, salt marshes and mangrove swamps (which are contracting due to anthropogenic habitat use, pollution and other disturbance). However, benthic blue carbon around Antarctica has been found to strongly interact with sea-ice losses to make it a globally significant negative (mitigating) feedback on climate change. Indeed, there is recent evidence that polar benthic blue carbon stocks, and thus their potential for mitigating impact, have increased [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C6">6</a>]. The biggest factor limiting build-up, longevity and blue carbon storage potential of benthic communities is the scouring of icebergs (originating from glaciers or ice shelves) when they run aground on the seabed [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C7">7</a>]. This smashes up and grinds carbonate bioconstruction, providing feasts for scavengers [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C8">8</a>] and reducing burial, but scour decreases rapidly in frequency with depth [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C9">9</a>]. While being locally catastrophic, iceberg scour promotes regional biodiversity by making the seabed a patchwork, with each location at a varying state of recovery since it was last scoured, across the Arctic [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C10">10</a>] and Antarctic [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C7">7</a>] continental shelves. While studying iceberg frequency and impact is easiest on the shore and in the shallows [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C11">11</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C12">12</a>], giant icebergs, several kilometres in length, are big enough to effectively track using remote sensing. In this paper, we provide evidence to support the inclusion of (fast ice and) icebergs as an important component of a holistic Southern Ocean Observing System (SOOS) because, apart from marine traffic and installation safety, icebergs have a profound impact on blue carbon ecosystem services.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Periodic disintegration of polar ice shelves to form giant icebergs is a normal process during warmer interglacial phases, such as the current time. However, seabed scour patterns suggest that the most recent past deglaciation mainly formed smaller icebergs (with V-shaped keels) than current ice shelf losses, which are producing giant tabular icebergs [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C13">13</a>]. The rapidity and extent of recent ice shelf collapses into giant icebergs has been increasingly linked to anthropogenic enhancement of climate change through fossil fuel use. Giant icebergs (greater than 30 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) are not uncommon, currently numbering 47 larger than 30 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in March 2017, including six that exceeded 1000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in area (see US National Ice Center iceberg data available at 
  <span xlink:href="http://www.polarview.aq/antarctic" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.polarview.aq/antarctic</span>). Duprat 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C14">14</a>] were able to study some effects of 17 recently calved giants in detail and begin a viewpoint of positive climate feedback contributions. Ice shelf fragility has been recently highlighted by the recent giant iceberg (A68) breakout of Larsen C and the long, rapidly growing fissure in the Brunt ice shelves in the East Antarctic—the latter forcing temporary evacuation of the Halley VI UK Antarctic research station. The consequences of such calving can be severe, including changing albedo (and thus heat absorption) and increasing the seaward flow of land-based ice by up to a factor of 8, at least initially [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C15">15</a>]. The change in macro-coastline and the (indirect) potential for sea-level rise consequences of ice shelf losses have gathered considerable public and scientific attention, particularly since the collapses of more northerly parts of Larsen in 1995 and 2002. Ice shelf disintegrations and calving have formed icebergs up to 32 000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, the passage and fate of which have also captured widespread concern, from collisions with rich life on the seabed or anthropogenic installations (such as oil rigs [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C16">16</a>]) to indirect impacts on penguin mortality [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C17">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The positive feedback on climate change and potential for serious societal impacts of increased ice shelf losses are considerable but these are by no means the only important effects. The continental shelves part-covered by ice shelves are biologically unproductive but their collapse may open up vast new bays to generate new primary productivity [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C18">18</a>], secondary productivity [
  <a rid="RSTA20170176C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20170176C19">19</a>] and thus major benthic carbon capture and storage opportunities. The giant icebergs fertilize the otherwise poorly productive ocean away from the shelf as they drift northwards, likewise generating new primary and secondary productivity, which if converted into long-term blue carbon stores will produce a negative feedback on climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we consider recent progress in measuring and understanding more general relationships between sea ice, icebergs and blue carbon on the Southern Ocean's seabed. Our aim is to better understand what we know and do not know about sea ice and iceberg impacts on blue carbon around the Southern Ocean. From published papers we analysed recent (2014–2017) benthic blue carbon data from (i) the relationship between fast-ice duration and the frequency of ice scouring in shallow waters at Rothera and Carlini stations on the West Antarctic Peninsula (WAP), (ii) iceberg impacted and non-impacted sites on South Georgia's north shelf and (iii) how correlation changes with depth between sea ice and benthic blue carbon around Marguerite Bay. Fourthly, we also analysed US National Ice Center circumpolar data of giant iceberg status (e.g. fasted, grounded and roaming), grounding hotspots and tracks to assess the trade-offs of giant iceberg formation with respect to effects on benthic ecosystem services of blue carbon (e.g. enhanced growth; carbon storage and its fate; potential for sequestration). Finally, we used these findings and literature to construct a polar projection map (based on 3° × 3° grid cells) of data illustrating benthic blue carbon change where we completely lack data.</p>
</sec>
