<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040" class="p">We performed a Pearson's correlation test for the 19 climatic variables (
 <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Table S2</xref>) and the variables with correlation coefficients above 0.90 were removed to reduce the effect of multicollinearity. After this procedure, eight bioclimatic variables remained in our analyses, among which four variables were associated with temperature (bio1, bio2, bio3, bio4) and another four variables were associated with precipitation (bio12, bio14, bio15, bio18). Additional static environmental variables previously shown to contribute to model performance were used in the analysis (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stanton et al., 2012</xref>), including a land-cover layer (resolution of 10 arc-seconds) downloaded from the European Space Agency (ESA: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://due.esrin.esa.int/page_globcover.php" id="intref0020" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://due.esrin.esa.int/page_globcover.php</ext-link>), a soil layer (resolution of 30 arc-seconds) downloaded from the International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webarchive.iiasa.ac.at/Research/LUC/External-World-soil-database/HTML/index.html?sb=1" id="intref0025" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://webarchive.iiasa.ac.at/Research/LUC/External-World-soil-database/HTML/index.html?sb=1</ext-link>), and an elevation layer (resolution of 30 arc-seconds) downloaded from the Geospatial Information Authority of Japan (GIAJ: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://globalmaps.github.io/el.html" id="intref0030" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://globalmaps.github.io/el.html</ext-link>). These variables were assumed to be constant under current and future scenarios. All layers were cut to restrict the projection area to the HHM, standardized to the same resolution as the climatic layers (30 arc-seconds) with the same coordinate system (WGS1984), and transferred to ASCII format to be prepared for modeling operations.
</p>
