<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hypothesized learning model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We seek to test whether 
  <span class="italic">World Climate</span> helps people learn about climate change science while motivating them to learn more and increasing their intent to take action. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0202877.g004" href="#pone.0202877.g004">Fig 4</a> summarizes prior theory showing how gains in knowledge, affect, desire to learn more, and intent to take action relate to one another. If the information deficit model of learning [
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref009">9</a>] were correct, then outcomes such as a desire to learn more and intent to take action (“Desire to Learn” and “Intent to Act,” respectively) would arise from gains in knowledge resulting from exposure to information about climate change. However, knowledge may neither function alone nor be sufficient to drive action. For example, knowledge about the causes and impacts of climate change is positively correlated with concern, an affective response [
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref036">36</a>]. Further, climate change knowledge and affect are thought to have a bidirectional, reinforcing relationship [
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref037">37</a>] (shown as links between “Knowledge” and “Affect,” 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0202877.g004" href="#pone.0202877.g004">Fig 4</a>). Affect is also important in risk perception and support for climate action [
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref038">38</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref039">39</a>], suggesting that changes in “Intent to Act” and “Desire to Learn” may be affected more strongly by affect than knowledge.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0202877.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0202877.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Theoretical model of learning for action through the 
    <span class="italic">World Climate</span> simulation.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0202877.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To gain insight into these issues we collected open-ended responses from participants in 
  <span class="italic">World Climate</span> sessions (see below for description of the sample and data collection protocol). While a comprehensive analysis of these responses is beyond the scope of the current study, these examples illustrate common themes expressed by participants in the study sample. We report examples from sessions that were a required component of courses or programs unrelated to climate change to avoid potential selection bias that might arise in sessions that participants joined voluntarily, as such participants could be predisposed to favor action to address climate change. These sessions include a program for low-income high school students (Upward Bound, Boston University); a required activity for high school students in Miami, Florida; an Honors Seminar for undergraduate students at UMass Lowell; undergraduate and graduate business students at Reutlingen University, Germany; and the Executive MBA program at MIT. Typical responses to the question, “How has participating in the 
  <span class="italic">World Climate</span> simulation affected your understanding of climate change, if at all?” include:
 </p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>“Now I know the facts, causes, and effects.”–High school student, Boston University Upward Bound.</p>
  <p>“I have an increased understanding of the urgency and level of effort required to make a positive impact.”–Undergraduate student, UMass Lowell.</p>
  <p>“It was very eye-opening. Current issues regarding climate change are very clear and the time-pressure understood.”–Business student, Reutlingen University.</p>
  <p>“It changed my mental model dramatically.”—Executive MBA participant, MIT.</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other comments illustrate gains in affective engagement (and, in some cases, their link to gains in knowledge resulting from the role-play), e.g.:</p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>“I was surprised how angry I became.”—Undergraduate student, UMass Lowell.</p>
  <p>“Alarmed but hopeful.”–High school student, Miami, Florida.</p>
  <p>“Empowered because I'm a part [of] something bigger than me.”–High school student, Boston University Upward Bound.</p>
  <p>“I am much more concerned now about the climate change, and much more aware about the specific actions each of us has to take to make a contribution into and have an impact on saving this world for our children.”—Executive MBA participant, MIT.</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses also suggest that gains in affect and knowledge were associated with both gains in intent to act and desire to learn more. Responses to the question, “Has participating in 
  <span class="italic">World Climate</span> affected how motivated you are to address climate change? If so, what do you plan to do?” included:
 </p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>“I want to do more research into possible solutions for climate change.”—Undergraduate student, UMass Lowell.</p>
  <p>“Yes, I am more motivated to learn more and contribute to change.”—Undergraduate student, UMass Lowell.</p>
  <p>“It has motivated me to inform others who may not be aware of what climate change is.”–High school student, Boston University Upward Bound.</p>
  <p>“I plan to take more action to decrease my carbon footprint. I could walk more, use LED lights, turn off lights + also most importantly inform other people about climate change so they are also aware.”–High school student, Boston University Upward Bound.</p>
  <p>“Stronger desire to learn more and have the tools to change my peers’ minds.”—Executive MBA participant, MIT.</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses to open-ended questions suggest participants experienced increases in their affective engagement, desire to learn more about climate change and their intention to take action. Several responses also point to interactions among knowledge, affect, and intent (e.g., “
  <span class="italic">I have an increased understanding of the urgency</span>,
  <span class="italic">”</span> and “
  <span class="italic">I am much more concerned now about the climate change</span>, 
  <span class="italic">and much more aware about the specific actions each of us has to take…”</span>). Together with prior research on climate change communication [
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref009">9</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref013">13</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0202877.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202877.ref015">15</a>], these responses suggest gains in participants’ climate change knowledge and affect, not knowledge alone, contribute to gains in their desire to learn more and their intent act.
 </p>
</sec>
