<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Controlling calibration area, novel climates, model complexity, and model transference to ensure robust predictions, we developed forecasts of geographic shifts in the potential range under future climates for 14 important disease vectors in Ecuador, finding consistent predictions of reductions in the vector’s potential ranges and the number of people exposed for most of the species studied. Our modeling experiments were developed based on a detailed design supported by ecological theories while outputs were evaluated carefully
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>. The overall patterns suggest that vectors of arboviruses and leishmaniasis will experience geographic range reductions by 2100 under future climate conditions, while chagas vectors had mixed results with some species increasing (
 <italic class="italic">T. dimidata</italic>) and others reducing (
 <italic class="italic">T. carrioni, T. dispar, R. ecuadoriensis</italic>) their geographic distribution (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>). A similar situation was observed for malaria vectors where one species (i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">An. darlingi</italic>) was predicted to increase in the geographic range while the other species were forecasted to experience range reductions. Therefore, 
 <italic class="italic">An. darlingi</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T. dimidata</italic> are of particular public health concern as such vectors could expand their range under future climate conditions, which could impact the epidemiology of malaria and chagas disease in Ecuador respectively. Climate change was even forecasted to possibly extirpate important vectors such as 
 <italic class="italic">Triatoma dispar</italic>, a vector of chagas disease. A reliable extinction would require ecological niche conservatism with no adaptation of vectors to warming climates; adaptation of species to warming climate is, however, restrained by high temperatures
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>. In other words, there is a physiological upper limit that cannot be exceeded easily by species, providing some confidence to our estimation. Our results show a benefit of climate change in terms of plausible extinction and range reduction for some vectors and consequent decrease in exposure risk for people, contrasting with the proposed negative effects of climate change on human health
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>. Our findings support other mathematical modeling and laboratory experiments proposing potential benefits of climate change in terms of limiting the burden of malaria and dengue vectors
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>, mitigating potential overinterpretation of other studies suffering incorrect study designs and thus proposing dramatic impacts of future climate on the epidemiology of infectious diseases which could fail to inform decision makers with realistic scenarios. Studies showing the attenuated negative impacts on the epidemiology of some vector species may help to reduce focus on the effects of climate change on the burden of vector-borne diseases of likely reduced future importance, and may encourage scientists to instead focus on the effects of other equally or more important factors for future human health, such as land use change, to help in the design and implementation of effective public health policies. We argue that a mature understanding of climate change effects on health could be achieved if and only if the research communities moves to a broader interpretation of climate effects, covering plausible negative and positive effects of such changes across ecosystems and taxa.
</p>
