<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We have assumed static patterns of human density in Ecuador in face of climate change, in other words, given that we based our estimation on values of human density, we assume that the present-day patterns of low and high will remain in the future. However, human displacement as a result of climate change is a complex factor that deserves further exploration. Further, topographic steepness limits the potential for upslope human migrations in the region, with most non-steep upland areas already densely occupied. While there is consensus that vectors are sensitive to weather and climate
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>, there is still uncertainty on the various impacts of climate variability on fine-scale transmission dynamics and socioeconomic variables
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>. We mitigated uncertainty in our forecasts by tuning model parameters for biologically realistic predictions by capturing the environmental tolerances of vectors from their entire geographic range and assessing model fit with available data. Our present-day predictions highlight areas of vector suitability at high spatial resolution for all the species included in this study. These areas suitable for vectors occurrence should be considered into account by public health authorities given the plausible disease underreporting in Ecuador (i.e., epidemiological silence
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>). The areas predicted to be of present-day risk may be of special interest for testing control measures and for identifying currently neglected human populations. The areas found suitable via remote sensing data could be also useful to guide local studies aiming to understand the distributional ecology of vectors, considering their interaction with other vector species, prey, variations in microclimate, availability of breeding sites, and the effects of socio-economic factors facilitating vectors’ occurrence
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>. Such local-scale factors were not considered in this study, but would provide valuable information to better understand fine-scale patterns in the ecology of vectors across different geographic and temporal scales
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>. An inter-sectoral approach should be implemented at the municipality level to address issues of sanitation, safe water availability, and preventive health care in areas predicted of present-day risk (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>).
</p>
