<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here we present a 19-year database of physical, chemical, and biological data that span primary producers to secondary consumers measured during summers in 28 lakes in the Adirondack Park in New York State, USA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). The Adirondack Park is a protected state park in northeastern New York that encompasses c. 26,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of public and private land, and nearly 3000 lakes (&gt; 0.4 ha)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. These lakes are poorly buffered due to surficial and bedrock geology, making them highly susceptible to acidification
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. Due to the proximity to industrial centers in the mid-western US and prevailing winds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>, the region received elevated atmospheric sulfur and nitrogen deposition, which has decreased in recent years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. This unique combination of geology and geography of the Adirondacks resulted in widespread and severe acidification of surface waters, which are now undergoing recovery. Concurrently, the northeastern U.S. has experienced substantial increases in temperature and precipitation and extreme events associated with changing climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. These stressors individually may have contrasting impacts on aquatic ecosystems. For example, warming surface temperatures and increased thermal stability are predicted to decrease zooplankton species richness
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>, while recovery from acidification is associated with increases in zooplankton richness
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
