<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering the carbon storage effect of HWPs derived from domestic forests according to the production approach, under the future scenarios of conservation of domestic forest resources and of business as usual as regards and HWP usage, the carbon storage effect will not be obtained over the span of time until 2050. However, under the future scenarios whereby domestic roundwood production and HWP usage is promoted, the carbon storage effect is consistently expected up until 2050, with an anticipated nationwide maximum of 2.9 MtC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2030.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As regards the material substitution effect, in the future scenarios in which HWP usage is promoted, the maximum nationwide carbon emissions reduction volume is estimated at 2.9 MtC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2050. In addition, the substitution of wooden building construction for non-wooden building construction could be expected to prompt a large reduction and could prove to be an effective mitigation strategy.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As regards the energy substitution effect, under future scenarios in which domestic roundwood production, HWP usage, and energy use are all promoted, a maximum nationwide carbon emissions reduction volume of 4.3 MtC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> is obtained by 2050, with the greatest contribution coming from increased use of logging residue. In addition, upwards of 50 % of the reduction volume is derived from east and west Japan, influenced by the fact that these regions have a large volume of roundwood production, which is a source of logging residue.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taken together, the carbon storage effect, the material substitution effect, and the energy substitution effect for HWPs derived from domestic forests under future scenarios that promote domestic roundwood production, HWP usage, and energy use, a maximum nationwide climate change mitigation effect of 8.4 MtC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> can be achieved in 2050, which is equivalent to 2.4 % of Japan’s total carbon dioxide emissions volume in 2013. In this case, the volume of the climate change mitigation effect of HWPs is comparable to the volume of the carbon removal effect of Japanese forests.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the overall climate change mitigation effect attributable to HWPs in each region of Japan was clarified, and future projected changes until 2050 were explored. A major issue for the future entails the integrated investigation of the carbon balance of HWPs and forests and relevant changes, together with a consideration of their trade-off relationships [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. Furthermore, it is also important to consider the leakage of the international HWP trade on each country’s forests [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>], where declining carbon storage in forests in countries, which export HWP to Japan, is balanced with limited domestic wood harvesting and conservation of Japanese forests.
 </p>
</sec>
