<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and discussion</div>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon storage effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows carbon storage volume attributable to HWPs derived from domestic forests by region. Under the BAU and BAU scenario, it is assumed that the future carbon storage volume for the whole of Japan declines compared to the actual value of 48 MtC in 2013 to the equivalent of 98 % of this level in 2030, and the equivalent of 96 %, or 46 MtC, in 2050. This decline is influenced by the downward trend in demand for wood, and is in line with declines in population and building construction up until 2013. However, under the scenarios whereby domestic roundwood production and HWP usage is promoted (the Mod &amp; Mod, the Plan &amp; Agg, and the Int &amp; Agg scenarios), we assume an increasing trend until 2050. In 2050, the highest carbon storage volume occurs under the Int &amp; Agg scenario, at a value of 125 MtC and equivalent to 262 % of the 2013 level. Focusing on regional distribution, although results vary according to the scenario and timescale, 16–20 % of the nationwide carbon storage volume is assumed to be in east Japan, 56–62 % in central Japan, and 21–24 % in west Japan, with the carbon storage volume high in central Japan, which includes the Tokyo metropolitan area. In addition, our breakdown of the carbon storage volume by application is as follows: building construction 68–88 %, civil engineering 0–12 %, furniture production 4–12 %, and paper making 7–13 %.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Carbon storage for HWPs derived from domestic forests, by region</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig4_HTML" id="MO5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> shows annual changes in the nationwide carbon storage volume attributable to HWPs derived from domestic forests. Under the Con &amp; BAU and the BAU &amp; BAU scenarios, as a result of a decline in carbon storage volume, the annual change has a negative value up until 2050, and a carbon storage effect cannot be expected. However, under the Mod &amp; Mod, the Plan &amp; Agg, and the Int &amp; Agg scenarios, the annual change has a positive value until 2050, and a carbon storage effect can be anticipated. In particular, under the Int &amp; Agg scenario, 2.9 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> is estimated for 2030, the biggest effect among the scenarios, which is in line with the trend in the volume of domestic roundwood production (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). There is significant scope for growth in the HWP stock derived from domestic forests. However, because the volume of domestic roundwood production reduces thereafter, until 2050, the carbon storage effect decreases.
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Annual change in nationwide carbon storage for HWPs derived from domestic forests</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig5_HTML" id="MO6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material substitution effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The volume of annual carbon emissions reduction due to material substitution in each region compared to the BAU scenario is illustrated in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> and the nationwide annual reduction volume is shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>. It was evident that, compared to the BAU scenario, a nationwide material substitution effect of 0.6 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2030 and of 1.3 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2050 could be expected under the Mod scenario, and an effect of 1.4 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2030 and 2.9 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2050 under the Agg scenario. Under all scenarios, the regional breakdown of the volume of annual emissions reduction was 17 % derived from east Japan, 63 % derived from central Japan, and 20 % derived from west Japan. In addition, the breakdown by application was 88 % derived from building construction, 8 % derived from civil engineering, and 4 % derived from furniture making, emphasizing the significance of the reduction effect attributable to the substitution of wooden building construction for non-wooden building construction.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to material substitution, by region (difference from the BAU scenario)</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig6_HTML" id="MO7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Nationwide annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to material substitution (difference from the BAU scenario)</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig7_HTML" id="MO8" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy substitution effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The volume of annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to energy substitution for each region is shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a> and the nationwide annual reduction is shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig9">9</a>. Under the Con &amp; BAU and the BAU &amp; BAU scenarios, the annual carbon emissions reduction remained more or less flat through 2050 with little visible change. However, under the three scenarios of the Mod &amp; Mod, the Plan &amp; Agg and the Int &amp; Agg, an increase in the annual carbon emissions reduction was seen, mainly as a result of a large increase in the volume of energy generation from logging residue. For 2050, a nationwide annual emissions reduction volume of 4.0 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> was obtained under the Plan &amp; Agg scenario, and of 4.3 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> under the Int &amp; Agg scenario, the latter figure being equivalent to 279 % of that for 2013. The regional breakdown of the actual figure for nationwide annual carbon emissions reduction in 2013 was 17, 61, and 22 % for east, central, and west Japan, respectively. Under the Plan &amp; Agg and the Int &amp; Agg scenarios, the proportion of reduction volume derived from central Japan declined to 43 and 49 %, while the proportions from east and west Japan increased. Under these scenarios, as a result of the aforementioned increase in energy-use volume of logging residue, the annual emissions reduction volume rose in east and west Japan, where there is a high volume of roundwood production, which generates logging residue. Within the carbon emissions reduction volume, the proportion derived from logging residue was high, at 43 % in 2050 under the Plan &amp; Agg scenario, and 46 % under the Int &amp; Agg scenario.
   <div id="Fig8" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 8</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to energy substitution, by region</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig8_HTML" id="MO9" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig9" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 9</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Nationwide annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to energy substitution</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig9_HTML" id="MO10" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the term “logging residue” refers to items such as branches and leaves generated after tree harvesting; it does not refer to items such as unused thinning wood. If we also take into account the residue resulting from thinning standing trees, the volume of residue available for energy use is likely to be greater. The degree to which such logging residue, seldom used in Japan and often left on the forest floor, is used in the future will have a significant impact on the energy substitution effect. At the same time, removing logging residue from the forest floor decreases the carbon storage in dead organic matter and soil in forests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. A future study needs to investigate a trade-off relationship between the energy use of logging residue and carbon storage in forests.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change mitigation effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nationwide total of the carbon storage effect, the material substitution effect, and the energy substitution effect attributable to HWPs derived from domestic forests (the annual change in carbon storage relates to HWPs derived from domestic forests, and the annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to material and energy substitution) is shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig10">10</a>. The mitigation effect under the Con &amp; BAU scenario was the smallest at 1.3 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2050. The mitigation effect under the Int &amp; Agg scenario was the largest at 8.4 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2050, equivalent to 2.4 % of the nationwide carbon dioxide emissions volume in 2013 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Looking at the breakdown of three effects, under the same scenario, 15 % is seen as derived from carbon storage, 34 % from material substitution, and 51 % from energy substitution.
   <div id="Fig10" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 10</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Nationwide HWP climate change mitigation effect (annual change in carbon storage relates to HWPs derived from domestic forests and annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to material and energy substitution)</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig10_HTML" id="MO11" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because the decline of the forestry and wood industries in Japan is currently an issue [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>], it is imperative to promote the use of HWPs derived from domestic forests to contribute toward revitalizing these industries. Therefore, the aggressive usage scenarios have the potential to produce the combined effect of both revitalizing the domestic forestry and wood industries and achieving carbon emissions reduction related to HWPs. On the other hand, the volume of the usage of HWP derived from domestic forests has a trade-off relationship with the volume of carbon storage in domestic forests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. According to the results estimated from a carbon balance model for Japanese forests (including both vegetation and soil) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], carbon removals (annual changes in carbon storage) by domestic forests declined from around 20 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> under the BAU scenario to around 10 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (approximately 50 % decrease) under the aggressive wood harvesting scenario in 2050. Our estimated results showed that the volume of the overall climate change mitigation effect of HWPs could be expected to be over 8 MtC year
   <span class="sup">−1</span> in 2050 under these aggressive usage scenarios, and mostly compensate for the decrease in domestic forests. An important future consideration is an integrated investigation of the carbon balance for both HWPs and forests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
