<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy substitution effect</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The volume of annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to energy substitution for each region is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a> and the nationwide annual reduction is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig9">9</a>. Under the Con &amp; BAU and the BAU &amp; BAU scenarios, the annual carbon emissions reduction remained more or less flat through 2050 with little visible change. However, under the three scenarios of the Mod &amp; Mod, the Plan &amp; Agg and the Int &amp; Agg, an increase in the annual carbon emissions reduction was seen, mainly as a result of a large increase in the volume of energy generation from logging residue. For 2050, a nationwide annual emissions reduction volume of 4.0 MtC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> was obtained under the Plan &amp; Agg scenario, and of 4.3 MtC year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> under the Int &amp; Agg scenario, the latter figure being equivalent to 279 % of that for 2013. The regional breakdown of the actual figure for nationwide annual carbon emissions reduction in 2013 was 17, 61, and 22 % for east, central, and west Japan, respectively. Under the Plan &amp; Agg and the Int &amp; Agg scenarios, the proportion of reduction volume derived from central Japan declined to 43 and 49 %, while the proportions from east and west Japan increased. Under these scenarios, as a result of the aforementioned increase in energy-use volume of logging residue, the annual emissions reduction volume rose in east and west Japan, where there is a high volume of roundwood production, which generates logging residue. Within the carbon emissions reduction volume, the proportion derived from logging residue was high, at 43 % in 2050 under the Plan &amp; Agg scenario, and 46 % under the Int &amp; Agg scenario.
  <div id="Fig8" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 8</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to energy substitution, by region</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig8_HTML" id="MO9" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig9" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 9</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Nationwide annual carbon emissions reduction attributable to energy substitution</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig9_HTML" id="MO10" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the term “logging residue” refers to items such as branches and leaves generated after tree harvesting; it does not refer to items such as unused thinning wood. If we also take into account the residue resulting from thinning standing trees, the volume of residue available for energy use is likely to be greater. The degree to which such logging residue, seldom used in Japan and often left on the forest floor, is used in the future will have a significant impact on the energy substitution effect. At the same time, removing logging residue from the forest floor decreases the carbon storage in dead organic matter and soil in forests [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. A future study needs to investigate a trade-off relationship between the energy use of logging residue and carbon storage in forests.
 </p>
</sec>
