<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future scenarios</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the previous model, there were two future scenarios focusing only on HWP consumption volume. However, in the new model, several scenarios were investigated relating to domestic roundwood production, HWP consumption volume, and the volume of energy use. These combinations are shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Combinations of future scenarios</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Tab1_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As regards the domestic roundwood production volume, we explored five future scenarios [in ascending order of volume: resource conservation (Con), business as usual (BAU), moderate increase in harvesting (Mod), in accordance with the Basic Plan for Forest and Forestry of Japanese government (Plan), in accordance with the forest owners’ intentions (Int)] created by Forestry and Forest Products Research Institute [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. In the resource conservation scenario, the volume of roundwood production declines in the future, and forest resources are conserved, with only limited harvesting of wood. In the BAU scenario, even if the future composition of forests increases, the harvesting area and the afforestation area remain unchanged at their actual recent-year level, and the forests continue to age. In the moderate harvesting increase scenario, older trees are harvested, and roundwood production volume is at least double its current level by 2050. In the government plan scenario the future production of roundwood is aggressively pursued in line with the Japanese government’s Basic Plan for Forest and Forestry. In the forest owners’ intentions scenario, which relies upon the results of a survey on the intentions of the forest owners affiliated with the forestry cooperatives, 15–30 % of planted trees are harvested in the 20-year period 2011–2030, and 25–30 % during 2031–2050. Roundwood production volume under these scenarios was estimated for each prefecture and the three regions; the national production is presented in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Japanese nationwide domestic roundwood production</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13021_2015_36_Fig3_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three scenarios were considered for HWP consumption volume, namely business as usual (BAU), moderate promotion of usage (Mod), and aggressive promotion of usage (Agg). Under the BAU scenario, the proportion of wood used in building construction, the proportion of wood used in furniture, and the volume of HWPs consumed in civil engineering projects all remain unchanged at the current level until 2050. Under the moderate usage promotion scenario, the proportion of wood used in building construction and in furniture making increases from 35 to 50 % by 2050 and the volume of HWPs consumed in civil engineering projects increases to 3 Mm
  <span class="sup">3</span> by 2050 from the current 1 Mm
  <span class="sup">3</span>. Under the aggressive usage promotion scenario, the proportion of wood used in building construction and in furniture making increases to 70 % by 2050, and the volume of HWPs consumed in civil engineering projects increases to 6 Mm
  <span class="sup">3</span> by 2050. No distinction was made between scenarios for the volume of paper consumption, with no change in per-person paper consumption anticipated through 2050. Details on HWP consumption volume are explained in the “
  <a rid="Sec11" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec11">Methods</a>” section.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three similar scenarios were also assumed for the volume of energy usage, namely business as usual (BAU), moderate promotion of usage (Mod), and aggressive promotion of usage (Agg). The BAU scenario entails no change in energy usage until 2050 with the current proportion of logging residue, processing residue, and waste wood. In the moderate usage promotion scenario, in 2050, in addition to the current energy-usage proportion, half of the unutilized proportion is used. In the aggressive usage promotion scenario, in 2050, in addition to the current energy-usage proportion, the whole of the unutilized proportion is used. Details of the volume of energy usage are explained in the “
  <a rid="Sec11" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec11">Methods</a>” section.
 </p>
</sec>
