<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35452-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global climate projection models suggest that spatial and temporal patterns of temperature and precipitation will become increasingly heterogeneous, with arid areas in the lower latitudes seeing more frequent and severe droughts. Warm and dry climates are increasingly prevalent across much of China (Tan et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0050">2017</a>) and have seriously affected the terrestrial ecosystem and food security (Lesk, Rowhani, &amp; Ramankutty, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0025">2016</a>; Reichstein et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0042">2013</a>; Sun et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0049">2017</a>). Studies have revealed a greater frequency of droughts in the semiarid areas of northern China (Wu, Dijkstra, Koch, Peñuelas, &amp; Hungate, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0056">2011</a>), which will become even more common in the future as a result of climate change (Battisti &amp; Naylor, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0004">2009</a>; Ma, Zhou, Angélil, &amp; Shiogama, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0031">2017</a>). Steppe has an important strategic position for ecological security in China, covering an area of about 4 × 108 ha, or about 41.67% of the territory of China. Steppes in Inner Mongolia account for nearly 67% of the total area of temperate steppe in China (Kang, Han, Zhang, &amp; Sun, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0021">2007</a>) and are highly affected by climate change (Sui, Zhou, &amp; Zhuang, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0048">2013</a>). Decreases in water availability have led to the migration of steppe vegetation and a reduction in steppe area, with additional changes to the structure and productivity of steppe plant communities (Wertin, Reed, &amp; Belnap, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0053">2015</a>; Wilcox, Fischer, Muscha, Petersen, &amp; Knapp, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0054">2015</a>). These impacts have been exacerbated by increasing ambient temperatures (Castagneri, Regev, Boaretto, &amp; Carrer, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0008">2017</a>; Li et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0028">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant functional traits are the internal or external adaptive characters formed by the interaction of plants and environment (Salgado‐Negret, Canessa, Valladares, Armesto, &amp; Perez, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0043">2015</a>). Previous studies have revealed that mild decreases in precipitation do not significantly affect plant growth; however, extreme drought significantly reduces plant height, leaf area, and photosynthetic capacity, negatively impacting the production capacity of the plants (Bret‐Harte et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0005">2001</a>; Cowling et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0011">2015</a>; Munson et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0035">2013</a>; Phillips et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0040">2009</a>; Shi, Zhou, Jiang, Wang, &amp; Xu, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0046">2016</a>; Xu et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0058">2014</a>). For the scientific management of plant resources in our changing climate, a detailed comparison of the responses of functional traits to precipitation variability in different steppe grasses is needed. This will help to guide the application of drought control and resistance methods in a timely manner (Nepstad et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0037">2004</a>). Biomass reflects the growth and resource utilization of plants and is an important research focus of steppe ecology (Manea, Sloane, &amp; Leishman, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0032">2016</a>). Plants respond to reduced precipitation mainly by inhibiting gas exchange while concurrently adjusting their physiological characteristics, thereby altering plant functions such as net primary production or biomass (Brodribb, Bowman, Nichols, Delzon, &amp; Burlett, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0006">2010</a>; Li, Zhao, &amp; Liu, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0026">2015</a>; Shafran‐Nathan, Svoray, &amp; Perevolotsky, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0045">2013</a>). In addition, differences in the functional traits to precipitation variability mean that the final total biomass of a plant is not necessarily altered, which reflects the adaptive strategies of the plant species to changing environments (Brunner, Herzog, Dawes, Arend, &amp; Sperisen, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0007">2015</a>; Chapin, Bloom, Field, &amp; Waring, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0010">1987</a>). However, quantitatively assessing the contribution of various functional traits to biomass has drawn little attention to date.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In response to precipitation variability, plants are either adaptive or stressed; however, even resilient plants have a limited capability to adapt to reduced precipitation, and the growth and survival of plants are inhibited by prolonged or extreme changes in precipitation that exceed their adaptation and recovery abilities (Barkaoui, Navas, Roumet, Cruz, &amp; Volaire, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0003">2017</a>; Sankaran et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0044">2005</a>). The determination of these limits confirms the drought threshold of plant and is essential for the application of drought control and resistance methods. Especially, the response range of the dominate plant species to precipitation variability is particularly representative of the adaptability of the natural ecosystem (Cavin, Mountford, Peterken, &amp; Jump, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0009">2013</a>; Waddington et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0052">2015</a>). Identifying critical precipitation thresholds of biomass in dominant steppe species to precipitation variability is therefore important for the evaluation of the effects of climate change on these ecosystems (IPCC, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0020">2014</a>; Palumbi, Barshis, Traylor‐Knowles, &amp; Bay, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0038">2014</a>). A recent study revealed that a linear model was not applied to describe temporal precipitation—aboveground net primary production (ANPP) relationships, but a nonlinear form of the temporal precipitation—ANPP relationship would better predict responses of ANPP to changing precipitation regimes because the precipitation variability and extreme precipitation were forecast to increase with climate change (Knapp, Ciais, &amp; Smith, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0022">2017</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Leymus chinensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. grandis</span> reached their peak biomass when the relative soil moisture was 66% and 54.7%, respectively, via a simulated experiment (Xu &amp; Zhou, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0059">2011</a>); thus, the biomass decreased with decreasing precipitation and there existed the response threshold to drought. But warming strengthened the negative effects of drought to plant biomass (Hoover, Knapp, &amp; Smith, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0017">2016</a>; Yang, Wang, Yang, &amp; Guo, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0060">2013</a>). These studies showed that biomass responded differently to precipitation in different species and more focused on the responding extent of plants to precipitation variability. Few studies have reported the critical precipitation threshold of biomass at different warming levels.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Stipa</span> L. dominates the zonal steppe communities of Inner Mongolia, presenting a regular zonal distribution from east to west in the steppes (Shi et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0046">2016</a>; Song, Wang, &amp; Lv, 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0047">2016</a>). Among them, 
  <span class="italic">S. baicalensis</span> dominates in semiarid and semihumid meadow steppes, 
  <span class="italic">S. bungeana</span> grows in the semiarid warm temperate typical steppes, 
  <span class="italic">S. grandis</span> grows in the semiarid typical steppe, and 
  <span class="italic">S. breviflora</span> dominates in the arid and semiarid desert steppes (Qi et al., 
  <a rid="ece35452-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35452-bib-0041">2010</a>). Here, these four representative 
  <span class="italic">Stipa</span> species as subjects in climate simulation experiments under ambient and warming conditions with precipitation variability. The main objectives of this study were to identify difference in responses of functional traits and drought threshold to precipitation variability at different warming levels. Three hypotheses were tested as follows: (a) Among the functional traits, the growth strategy traits (root/shoot ratio, R/S) may be more sensitive to precipitation than the other traits and warming may improve the responses of those traits; (b) warming may lead to higher optimum water requirements for total biomass and critical water threshold may differ in the four 
  <span class="italic">Stipa</span> species; (c) 
  <span class="italic">Stipa</span> species may be able to adapt better to drought when temperatures were increased by 1.5°C rather than 2.0°C. These results will help to identify and monitor the impacts of drought, and provide evidence for dealing with drought in Inner Mongolia steppe.
 </p>
</sec>
