<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In Zvimba, women and girls tend to be impacted more by climate variability. The notion that climate change presents a significant threat to human security especially women is no longer debatable and within the studied area, 40 of the respondents agreed to that. Participants indicated that in time of a drought, women stay at home with their families whilst men move away to look for other alternatives. It is within this period that women, presented with few options, find ways to earn a living. Participants from the Ministry of Environment, Water and Climate Change indicated that climate change is and will continue to exacerbate the gender dimensions of vulnerability. What makes women to be more vulnerable is the fact that they constitute the majority of peasant farmers who depend heavily on rain-fed agriculture, which is sensitive to the changing climate. Madzwamuse (
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) supports this as he argues that 70% of women in Zimbabwe are smallholder farmers who depend on rain-fed agriculture and climate-sensitive resources. This study noted that women are not periodically involved in household’s decisions. Therefore, women are left without cash savings or any other assets to sell in order to restock or buy basic food items during a crisis. Like it is in many African countries, climate change is impacting negatively the livelihoods of women and it is reducing their economic base and opportunities. Interesting to note is that women are vulnerable to climate change (because they perform house chores, i.e. collecting of water and feeding the family) yet they are not fully represented and given a space in decision-making process on issues related to the changing climate. The planning and management measures should ensure that women are given space to be champions in the planning of climate change and disaster risk management. Women must be captains in managing environmental protection programmes and should be given maximum support. Future planning must incorporate a gender-sensitive perspective, which requires an understanding of the ways in which climate change can intensify pre-existing inequalities between men and women (Chagutah 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
