<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a) Capture and handling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was carried out within the Forêt d’Enseignement et de Recherche Macpès, Québec, Canada (48° 30’ N, 68° 52 W) between January and March 2010 (n = 56) and from October 2010 to March 2011 (n = 149). Data from summer individuals were collected in August 2010 (n = 12) and 2011 (n = 11). To attract chickadees and facilitate capture, 18 feeding stations were set up within the forest with an average distance between stations of 1.9 km (see 30,32 for a description of the stations). Feeders were regularly filled with black sunflower seeds. On capture days, feeders were removed and homemade potter traps (15 cm x 15 cm x 15 cm) baited with seeds were placed on a tray installed on a wooden fence pole. All birds were caught during morning (between 08:00 and 13:00) and removed from traps within one minute of capture. Weather stations in the forest [
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>] recorded temperature data allowing us to track ambient temperatures over the two years of the study.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds caught for the first time were banded with a USGS numbered metal band as well as a unique combination of three plastic color bands to allow further identification from a distance. For each capture, birds were first weighed then had the length of their beak, head plus beak, tarsus, tail and wing measured [
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>]. Following these measurements and depending on capture success, up to four birds per day were brought to the field station for metabolic measurement.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b) Ethics statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All bird manipulations were approved by the animal care committee of the Université du Québec à Rimouski (CPA-37-09-68) and have been conducted under scientific and banding permits from Environment Canada - Canadian Wildlife Service (Permit Number: 10704H).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c) Respirometry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once at the field station, birds were maintained in separate cages (39 cm x 43 cm x 31 cm) supplied with food (sunflower seed) and water 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> until measurements were made. Cages were kept in a room receiving natural light through a window and maintained quiet to avoid disturbance. At around 13: 00, we began M
   <sub>SUM</sub> trials by measuring two birds in parallel using Fox, Box oxygen analyzers (Sable Systems, Las Vegas, NV, USA). This was followed by a second trial on the remaining two birds, which began before 15: 00. Briefly, birds were first weighed (± 0.1 g) and body temperature was measured with a thermocouple reader (Omega model HH-25KC, NIST-traceable, Omega, Montréal, Qc, Canada) using a copper-constantan thermocouple inserted into the cloacae approximately 10 mm deep. Then, birds were put in a stainless steel metabolic chamber fitted with a perch and were exposed to helox gas (21% oxygen, 79% helium) using an average flow rate of 1109 ml.min
   <span class="sup">-1</span> controlled by mass flow valves (Sierra Instruments, Side-Trak® Model 840 (Monterey, CA, USA)). We recorded oxygen consumption of each bird using a sliding cold exposure protocol [
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>] with a decrease in ambient temperature of 3°C every 20 minutes, starting at 0°C in winter and at 6°C in summer. We ended the trials when birds became hypothermic, which was easily identifiable in real time as a steady decline in oxygen consumption for several minutes. Body temperature was measured again immediately after taking birds out of their chambers. We assumed a bird had reached its M
   <sub>SUM</sub> when body temperature after a trial was ≤ 38°C [
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>] (mean body temperature after M
   <sub>SUM</sub> measurement = 33.6 ± 0.2°C). Data from individuals showing a body temperature above this threshold were discarded. Birds were weighed again after measurements and the average body mass was used for the M
   <sub>SUM</sub> analysis. Birds were then brought back to their cage with food and water 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> until BMR measurement starting at 19: 00.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each day, all four birds had their BMR measured simultaneously overnight (from 19: 00 to 06:00). Individuals were maintained at 30°C throughout the trial (within the thermoneutral zone for this species [
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>]) and received a constant flow of air. Birds were weighed before and after measurements and average mass was used in BMR analyses.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oxygen analyzers were adjusted each day to 20.95% using CO
   <sub>2</sub>-free dry air and mass flow valves were carefully calibrated for air and helox using a bubble-O-meter (Dublin, OH, USA) once per winter. Metabolic rate calculations were done with ExpeData software, v 1.2.6 (Sable Systems, Las Vegas, NV, USA). M
   <sub>SUM</sub> and BMR calculations were based respectively on the highest and lowest averaged 10 minutes of oxygen consumption per measurement sequence according to Lighton’s equation 10.1 [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>]. The instantaneous measurement technique [
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>] was used for M
   <sub>SUM</sub> while BMR was calculated using the steady state approach. The duration of BMR trials (around 11 hours) insured that birds were post-absorptive at time of BMR measurement (which was obtained after 6 h 40 min ± 8 min of recording on average). Since wintering birds use mostly lipids as substrate for shivering [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>,
   <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>,
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>], we estimated energy consumption using a constant equivalent of 19.8 kJ.L
   <span class="sup">-1</span> O
   <sub>2</sub> and converted to Watts [
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>]. After BMR measurements, birds were put back in their cage with access to food and water until release at capture site around 2 hours later.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(d) Sexing individuals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">130 individuals (56 females and 74 males) caught for this study were sexed by PCR [
   <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>] or dissection. We determined sex of the remaining 98 birds using their morphometric data in a discriminant analysis [
   <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>]. Overall, 85 individuals were identified as females, 107 as males and 36 birds remained undetermined.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(e) Statistical analysis</div>
  <sec id="s2.5.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inter-seasonal variation</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We first studied inter-seasonal variation in body mass and metabolic performance. To do so, we used a linear mixed effect model (LME) to test for effects of “year”, “season” (winter or summer), “sex” (male, female or undetermined) and interaction term “year*season”, using bird ID as random parameter, on whole BMR, M
    <sub>SUM</sub> and ME. We also included the variable “relative time of capture” (time since sunrise / day length, hereafter “time of capture”) for body mass analyses. We then used the same model including body mass as a covariate to analyse variations in mass-independent metabolic performance.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s2.5.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intra-seasonal variation</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To study intra-seasonal variation (i.e. within winter) in parameters of metabolic performance, we used the same model but this time testing for the effects of “year”, “month”, “sex” and the interaction term “year*month”, again using bird ID as random parameter. “Time of capture” was also considered when analysing variations in body mass. To study effects on mass-independent variables we repeated the analyses including body mass as a covariate.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We saved residuals from those LMEs to study relationships between whole and mass-independent winter BMR and M
    <sub>SUM</sub>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variables were removed from models when non-significant and results from final models are presented. In cases where the interaction term year*month was significant, we ran separate analyses by year. We used Tukey tests to investigate differences between months and between sexes. Analyses on metabolic parameters showed the same final patterns whether or not body mass was included as a covariate. We therefore present results for mass-independent BMR, M
    <sub>SUM</sub> and ME. Data for these variables without mass corrections are available in the Supporting Information files (
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0068292.s001" href="#pone.0068292.s001">table S1</a>-S2). In all cases, residuals were tested for normality using the one sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Population data are presented as least square means ± s.e.m., and intra-individual data are shown as predicted values (original values corrected for the effects that were found significant at the population level).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
