<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study is the first to document, with an extensive dataset, intra-seasonal and intra-individual patterns of change (e.g. reaction norm [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]) in metabolic performance of free-living birds wintering at northern latitudes. As expected, both BMR and M
  <sub>SUM</sub> were higher in winter relative to summer and increased during the coldest months of winter. However, average BMR and average M
  <sub>SUM</sub> followed dissimilar paths with BMR declining to summer level in the spring while M
  <sub>SUM</sub> tended to remain high, resulting in the highest metabolic expansibility being recorded in March. Variations in metabolic performance observed at the population level reflected that observed within individuals.
 </p>
 <sec id="s4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a) Inter-seasonal variation in metabolic performance</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mass-independent basal metabolic rate, interpreted here as the energy expenditure of physiological systems remaining active in a resting bird, peaked at 0.27 W in wintering black-capped chickadees. This is comparable to values measured in wintering chickadees from Ohio (0.26 W) and Wisconsin (0.27W) [
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>] but lower than the ones measured in birds spending their winter in New York (0.29) [
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>], South Dakota (0.30 W) [
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>] and Alaska (0.42 W) [
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>]. It is therefore not surprising to find that the 6% seasonal increase in mass-independent BMR observed here is much lower than the +14% found by Cooper and Swanson in birds from South Dakota [
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>]. This seasonal variation is, however, in the relatively large range of seasonal changes observed in other temperate free-living resident passerines (from -4.3% in 
   <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
    <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
     <span class="italic">Carpodacus</span>
    </div>
    <span class="italic">
     <div content-type="species" class="named-content">mexicanus</div>
    </span>
   </div> [
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>] to +36.3% in 
   <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
    <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
     <span class="italic">Passer</span>
    </div>
    <span class="italic">
     <div content-type="species" class="named-content">montanus</div>
    </span>
   </div> [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]). Assuming the seasonal elevation in BMR reflects an increase in maintenance costs [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>,
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>], it therefore appears that black-capped chickadees from our study site only face a moderate rise in maintenance energy demand in association with seasonal cold acclimatization relative to other populations. If temperature is one of the drivers of winter metabolic performance [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>,
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>], it is likely that differences between populations reflect physiological responses to local conditions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As for BMR, the seasonal increase in M
   <sub>SUM</sub> (+34%) was in the range of previously reported observations. Seasonal changes in mass-independent M
   <sub>SUM</sub> range from +16.2% in 
   <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
    <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
     <span class="italic">Sitta</span>
    </div>
    <span class="italic">
     <div content-type="species" class="named-content">carolinensis</div>
    </span>
   </div> [
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>,
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>] to +42.4% in 
   <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
    <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
     <span class="italic">Picoides</span>
    </div>
    <span class="italic">
     <div content-type="species" class="named-content">pubescens</div>
    </span>
   </div> [
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>], with black-capped chickadees from South Dakota showing a 26.3% increase in winter mass-independent M
   <sub>SUM</sub> relative to summer [
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b) Intra-seasonal variation in metabolic performance and the uncoupling of BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature has been suggested as one of the drivers of winter metabolic performance [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>,
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>,
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>,
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>] and this led us to predict a gradual increase in BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub> during winter where a peak would be observed during the coldest months of the season. Seasonal variations in BMR were of lower amplitude than expected but changes in average values were consistent with our prediction. Although significant differences were only clear when comparing February with October, November and March, BMR clearly tended to be higher during December, January and February, the coldest months of winter (both years combined, 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">table 1)</a>. However, BMR declined rapidly in March, when ambient temperatures were still relatively cold (-16°C and -27°C mean minimum temperature in 2010 and 2011 respectively), which suggests that temperature may not be the sole driver of winter BMR phenotype in chickadees.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, intra-seasonal changes in average M
   <sub>SUM</sub> differed between years. During the first winter, M
   <sub>SUM</sub> peaked in February and declined in March while in the second year M
   <sub>SUM</sub> increased until the end of our measurements in March. M
   <sub>SUM</sub> variations were therefore consistent with our predictions for the first year, where February was the coldest month based on minimal temperature, but were counterintuitive for the second year where no decline in M
   <sub>SUM</sub> were observed. It must be noted, however, that cold energy-demanding temperatures lasted much longer during the second winter since, although daily temperatures were already warming by March, minimal temperatures were as cold in March as in January. It is therefore likely that birds maintained their thermogenic capacity to its maximal level as long as days with very cold temperature prevailed. As metabolic expansibility is the ratio of M
   <sub>SUM</sub> on BMR, and given the differences in range of intra-seasonal changes in BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>, variations in ME were inevitably affected by changes in M
   <sub>SUM</sub>. It was therefore of no surprise to find similar variation when comparing ME and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contrast in BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub> patterns goes in hand with the hypothesis that these components of metabolic performance respond to different sets of environmental constraints [
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>,
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>,
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. Comparing intra-seasonal patterns of change in BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub> relative to summer values also suggests a certain level of independence between these parameters. Although it was moderate, the increase in mass-independent BMR between seasons (+5.9% comparing August and February) was the same as that detected between October and February (+5.9%). In fact, the increase in BMR started after November, when birds began to face minimal temperatures below -10°C (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">table 1)</a>, and remained relatively steady until February (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g004" href="#pone-0068292-g004">Figure 4A)</a>. In contrast, the inter-seasonal change in mass-independent M
   <sub>SUM</sub> (+34.2% between August and February) was higher than that measured within season (+25.0% between October and February). In fact, M
   <sub>SUM</sub> had already achieved 21.8% of its inter-seasonal increase when we began our measurements in October (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g004" href="#pone-0068292-g004">Figure 4B)</a> meaning that, although the largest change in M
   <sub>SUM</sub> appeared between January and February (+45.4% of total inter-seasonal increase, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g004" href="#pone-0068292-g004">Figure 4B)</a>, this parameter began to change well before the beginning of sub-zero mean ambient temperatures (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">table 1)</a>. These results therefore suggest that flexible adjustments in thermogenic capacity appear relatively early in autumn (before October) while physiological components reflected in BMR only begin to change later (from November).
  </p>
  <div id="pone-0068292-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0068292.g004</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Visual representation of the monthly winter increment in metabolic performance.</div>
    <p>Increment in mass-independent BMR (A) and M
     <sub>SUM</sub> (B) relative to summer values. Data measured in August are used as the summer phenotype reference point (August = 0%, black star, dashed line) while maximal levels of BMR and M
     <sub>SUM</sub> recorded in winter are considered representative of the “peak” winter phenotype (February = 100%). Monthly changes in metabolic performance (values above lines) are presented in percent of total inter-seasonal difference. Dotted lines represent BMR variations below the summer reference point.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0068292.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why would BMR begin to increase later in autumn and decline earlier in the spring than M
   <sub>SUM</sub>? The reasons for the uncoupling of these variables are not clear. However, if one considers M
   <sub>SUM</sub> as a variable mainly influenced by the size of shivering muscles [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>,
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>,
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>,
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>] and BMR as reflecting changes in size and activity of the main digestive organs in response to cold acclimatization [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>,
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>,
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>] then it is likely that those metabolic parameters reflect different sets of physiological constraints acting relatively independently, both being associated with winter [
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. Pectoral muscles would start changing early in the season in association with the appearance of cold ambient temperatures (note that sub-zero minimal temperatures were already recorded in October), whereas winter BMR variations would likely reflect changes in diet and in the amounts of food consumed (to sustain an increasing daily energy expenditure, DEE). Chickadees feed mainly on insects during summer but eat up to 50% vegetal matter during winter [
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>] while food supplementation by feeders may represent only up to 21% of their daily energy intake [
   <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>]. Snow typically starts to fall in November at our field site while insects are already visible by March. Therefore, it could be that the combination of a winter increase in DEE and changes in natural diet digestibility and energy content leads to a restructuring of the digestive apparatus, and in turn changes in BMR, appearing independently from those observed in M
   <sub>SUM</sub>. The proximal effect of cold ambient temperature on parameters of metabolic performance [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>,
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>,
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>] would therefore be much more influential for M
   <sub>SUM</sub> than for BMR. Experimental research is needed to test this “metabolic uncoupling” hypothesis and to determine what biotic and/or abiotic factors trigger seasonal changes in parameters of metabolic performance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the seasonal mismatch in variations of BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>, it is therefore of no surprise to find a lack of significant correlation between these parameters when controlling for body mass in regression analyses. Independence of BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub> has also been observed by others [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>,
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>,
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>,
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>], but findings remains conflicting [
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>,
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. Experimental manipulations of BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>, for example by combining diet and temperature treatments, should therefore be conducted to confirm findings.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c) Intra-individual variation in winter metabolic performance</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies on seasonal variation of avian metabolic performance are typically conducted at the population level [
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>,
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>,
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>,
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>] and, although it is rarely stated, they generally assume that population patterns are reflective of those observable within individuals. As far as we know, this is the first study to document with an extensive dataset seasonal variation of metabolism at both the population and individual levels in a resident bird species. Our findings support the common assumption; patterns observed at the population level reflected intra-individual variation in body mass, mass-independent BMR, M
   <sub>SUM</sub> and ME (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0068292-g003" href="#pone-0068292-g003">Figure 3A–C)</a> and are therefore representative of average individual phenotypic flexibility.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(d) Is metabolic expansibility a meaningful variable?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we considered metabolic expansibility as an indicator of the capacity of an organism to produce heat (because it was based on M
   <sub>SUM</sub>) for a given size of metabolic machinery (which would be reflected by BMR) [
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>,
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>,
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>,
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>]. However, the lack of correlation between BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>, as observed by others [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>,
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>,
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>,
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>], as well as the temporal mismatch in these parameters during seasonal acclimatization suggest a lack of a functional relationship between BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub>. Although BMR includes the resting energy consumption of physiolgical components involved in active thermogenesis (i.e. muscles), evidences suggest that, in the context of cold acclimatization, its variations are mainly influenced by activity and size of organ systems involved in energy acquisition and digestion [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>,
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>,
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>], while M
   <sub>SUM</sub> would mostly reflect active energy consumption of shivering muscles [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>,
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>,
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>]. It therefore becomes apparent to us that metabolic expansibility, as we defined it earlier, may lead to misleading conclusions about machinery adjustments. We therefore suggest caution with the interpretation of this variable and recommend interpreting variations in BMR and M
   <sub>SUM</sub> separately to infer on animals metabolic capacity.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
