<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With global changes comes a higher frequency of unpredictable weather events [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. These short-term environmental fluctuations can affect animal species through changes in demography, phenology [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>] and genetic variability [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>], for example by disturbing the timing of reproduction [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>] or by favouring genotypes that produce flexible rather than stable phenotypes [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. This may be particularly important for northern latitude species where warming is accelerated relative to lower latitudes [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>], especially in winter [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>], and where the occurrence and amplitude of short term stochastic events are predicted to increase [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. Phenotypic flexibility, the rapid and reversible transformations of phenotypic traits that allow individuals to adjust their behaviour and physiology to predictable or stochastic changes in the environment [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>], should provide a certain capacity to buffer these variations [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. However, in natural settings, little is known on how animals adjust their phenotype to intra-seasonal changes in ecological conditions [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Winter at northern latitudes is typically considered a challenging season for resident bird species [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. Since they remain active throughout the cold season, low ambient temperatures force these animals to increase energy expenditure for thermoregulation [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>] while short days, snow and ice cover may reduce foraging time and food availability [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. In small bodied species, thermoregulatory constraints are exacerbated because of their large surface area relative to volume, which increases heat loss [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>], in addition to their limited ability to carry thick insulative plumage. Small birds therefore use physiological adjustments to improve cold tolerance [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>] and their chances of survival. Seasonal acclimatization is typically associated with a winter increase in metabolism visible in parameters such as basal metabolic rate (BMR; physiological maintenance cost) and summit metabolic rate (M
  <sub>SUM</sub>; maximal thermogenic capacity) [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]. However, although cold acclimatization has been investigated for decades [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>], most field studies lack the required temporal resolution to address questions regarding individual physiological adjustments in response to intra-seasonal variations in ambient conditions [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>,
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. Studies typically compare phenotypic traits such as BMR and M
  <sub>SUM</sub> on a seasonal basis, comparing values from individuals captured in winter with data collected on different individuals captured in summer [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>,
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>,
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To face stochastic winter conditions, small birds could use two mutually non-exclusive strategies. First, they could maintain a constant and elevated winter metabolism. This strategy would increase survival during extreme thermal events but it would also presumably be associated with high and often unnecessary maintenance costs. Second, birds could use phenotypic flexibility to rapidly adjust their physiology to prevailing conditions. In this situation, however, individuals may have to invest considerable resources in physiological readjustments (e.g. adjustment in organ size [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]). As far as we know, only two studies have provided data on intra-seasonal metabolic changes in response to winter climate variations in small free-living birds [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>,
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]; both of these reflected a phenotypic flexibility strategy. Swanson and Olmstead [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>] observed that cold ambient temperature was associated with elevated metabolic performance in dark-eyed juncos (
  <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
    <span class="italic">Junco</span>
   </div>
   <span class="italic">
    <div content-type="species" class="named-content">hyemalis</div>
   </span>
  </div>), black-capped chickadees (
  <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
    <span class="italic">Poecile</span>
   </div>
   <span class="italic">
    <div content-type="species" class="named-content">atricapillus</div>
   </span>
  </div>) and American tree sparrows (
  <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
    <span class="italic">Spizella</span>
   </div>
   <span class="italic">
    <div content-type="species" class="named-content">arborea</div>
   </span>
  </div>). This was visible at the population level on a between-year timescale for BMR and M
  <sub>SUM</sub> and on a between-month (i.e. intra-seasonal) timescale for M
  <sub>SUM</sub> (there were not enough data for testing the effect on BMR). Furthermore, ambient temperature preceding measurements appeared to affect metabolic performance within relatively short periods, between one and 30 days, depending on the species. Similar findings were reported by Broggi et al. [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>] in great tits (
  <div content-type="genus-species" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="genus" class="named-content">
    <span class="italic">Parus</span>
   </div>
   <span class="italic">
    <div content-type="species" class="named-content">major</div>
   </span>
  </div>) where BMR changed throughout winter and responded to ambient temperature averaged over the preceding week.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If ambient temperature exerts such a proximal effect on winter metabolic performance, one would therefore expect adjustments in metabolic parameters over the course of the season, with peak capacity observable at the coldest time of winter. However, data on the shape of metabolic transformations within seasons are lacking, albeit being called for [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>,
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. Furthermore, although seasonal changes in metabolic performance are interpreted as a clear and evident example of phenotypic flexibility in response to winter constraints [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>], within individual data to support this statement are still lacking for free-living wintering birds. Our understanding of intra-seasonal and intra-individual variation in metabolic performance of birds wintering at northern latitudes therefore remains poor.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we report results of a study where we followed intra-seasonal changes in metabolic performance over two consecutive winters in a population of black-capped chickadees from eastern Canada. We measured changes in BMR to assess variations in physiological maintenance costs and we measured changes in M
  <sub>SUM</sub> to follow adjustments in winter thermogenic capacity. These measurements were also performed in August of each year to obtain a summer reference point for comparison. Our first objective for this part of the study was to determine patterns of variation in BMR and M
  <sub>SUM</sub> within winter. We expected a gradual increase in metabolic performance beginning in autumn to reach a peak at the coldest of winter (i.e. January–February), followed by a gradual decline to reach summer values [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. Our second objective was to confirm that these patterns were also visible within individuals and therefore confirm that observations at the population level reflect individual phenotypic flexibility.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies suggested a functional link between BMR and M
  <sub>SUM</sub> [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>,
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>] but some evidence rather suggests that these variables reflect physiological systems acting independently [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>,
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. BMR would mainly reflect energy requirements of internal organs [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>,
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>] while M
  <sub>SUM</sub> would reflect the size of muscles involved in active shivering [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>,
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>]. Given recent contrasting findings, including in our own model species [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>,
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>], we also had an interest in testing the relationship between BMR and M
  <sub>SUM</sub> with an extensive dataset.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metabolic expansibility (ME), the ratio of maximal over minimal metabolic rates (M
  <sub>SUM</sub> / BMR) [
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>,
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>,
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>], is interpreted as the capacity of an organism to increase its level of heat production for a given size of metabolic machinery [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>]. Therefore, variations in ME should also be a useful variable to evaluate co-adjustment of physiological maintenance costs and thermogenic capacity. We thus report inter- and intra-individual variation in ME throughout winter.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To meet our objectives, 228 individuals were captured during winters 2010 and 2010-11 and had their metabolic performance measured within the following 24h. Of this number, 56 individuals were recaptured and remeasured between one and five times within a same winter.</p>
</sec>
