<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Indices of sub-organismal performance of Delta Smelt were sensitive to warming and elevated salinity regimes in the current study. Delta Smelt showed physiological sensitivity to the Warm/Sal regime in particular, as evident by increased hematocrit and decreased muscle tissue water content compared to the control fish (Table 
 <xref rid="coy076TB2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). Elevated hematocrit (i.e. an increase in red blood cells) after 2 weeks of warming indicates additional oxygen carrying capacity may have been needed to support elevated metabolic demands of warming and/or increase in salinity. In a previous study, when exposed to 20°C, Delta Smelt larvae responded by elevating aerobic metabolism and upregulating heat stress repair genes (
 <xref rid="coy076C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jeffries 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>), while adults had a reduced capacity to regulate cellular repair mechanisms under warming (
 <xref rid="coy076C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>). While it is unclear if changes in hematocrit and muscle tissue water content were in response to warming or the subsequent salinity stressor, previous studies have shown Delta Smelt are relatively insensitive to salinity increases to 12 ppt (
 <xref rid="coy076C39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kammerer 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammock 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). Given the relative insensitivity to elevated salinity, the elevated hematocrit levels in juvenile Delta Smelt in Warm/Sal were likely a heightened response to warming and not salinity. Lastly, Delta Smelt showed stable body condition following the series of exposures to elevated temperature and salinity after 25 days, similar to previous studies in juveniles and adults (
 <xref rid="coy076C39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kammerer 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). Delta Smelt in this study were likely able to maintain energy allocation required for maintenance mechanisms and body growth when fed to satiation. Under natural conditions, if food resources are low, the physiological adjustments required to maintain homeostasis under warming and changes in salinity may be energy limited. Although all species irrespective of origin (native versus non-native) require sufficient resources to maintain homeostatic mechanisms, species with greater thermal sensitivity and lower tolerance, such as Delta Smelt, may be more susceptible to a mismatch in the energy supply required to meet increased energetic demands at lower temperatures in a low food environment compared to eurythermal non-native species.
</p>
