<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Physiological sensitivity of Mississippi Silversides was not affected by multiple stressors of warming and increased salinity, whereas Largemouth Bass had altered physiology indicating sensitivity to stressor regimes. Silversides have been described previously as extremely eurythermal (10–38°C, 
 <xref rid="coy076C4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beitinger 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2000
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Interagency Ecological Program 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2018a
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="coy076C31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>) and euryhaline (0–35 ppt, 
 <xref rid="coy076C45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mahardja 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). Our findings of unaltered hematocrit and muscle tissue water content, as well as increased growth suggest elevated salinity and warming may enhance physiological optima of Mississippi Silversides. Similarly, growth capacity of Atlantic Silversides (
 <italic class="italic">Menidia menidia</italic>) has been shown to increase with warming (
 <xref rid="coy076C2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Baumann and Conover, 2011</xref>). In contrast, Largemouth Bass in the present study did not experience increased growth from warming and/or elevated salinity (potentially due to a lower feeding rate, 
 <xref rid="coy076C54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Niimi and Beamish, 1974</xref>), and alterations in hematocrit and plasma osmolality were evident following the multiple stressors. Hematocrit decreased in the multiple stressor regime with the initial salinity increase (Sal/Warm), whereas plasma osmolality increased in both serial stressor regimes of high temperature and salinity by the end of the experiment (Day 25, Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="coy076F5" class="xref">5</xref>), suggesting some degree of osmoregulatory imbalance (
 <xref rid="coy076C49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meador and Kelso, 1990</xref>). Largemouth Bass osmolality in this present study was 291–301 mOsm kg
 <sup class="sup">–1</sup> (baseline), which is roughly isosmotic to 8 ppt. Many invasive species in the SFE have been shown to predate on Delta Smelt (although in low numbers, likely due to the rarity of the species; 
 <xref rid="coy076C62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schreier 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>); however, if Delta Smelt have greater performance in higher salinities, the threat of predation may be reduced due to species-specific differences in osmotic tolerance, at least for Largemouth Bass predators. More research investigating osmoregulation mechanisms of non-native species, particularly predators in the SFE, is warranted to determine osmotic limitations and therefore the influence on native fish populations (including Delta Smelt) through predator–prey interactions.
</p>
