<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model evaluation and time of emergence</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mechanisms that we identify above are in line with previous studies that have usually focused on temperature extremes (extreme compared to current climate) and on shorter time scales (
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). When comparing the occurrence of such extreme events between models and observation-based data sets, previous studies have usually found good agreement regarding their frequency and trend patterns (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>). Here, we briefly compare the modeled variability of monthly mean temperatures with four reanalysis data sets (see Materials and Methods for more detail): ERA-Interim (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>), NOAA-CIRES 20th Century Reanalysis V2c (
  <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
   <span class="italic">42</span>
  </a>), NCEP/DOE Reanalysis 2 (
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>), and MERRA2 (
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>). Although locally constrained by observations, these reanalysis data sets allow a global and temporally complete coverage. We calculate the temperature SD in the period 1980–2010 for all models and the four reanalyses by linear detrending for each month and computing the SD of the residuals. Overall, our comparison confirms that the current temperature SD of the CMIP5 models is within the observational range (fig. S6). Regional biases occur mostly in high latitudes over areas of substantial variability in sea-ice cover and over some tropical land regions (fig. S6A). However, these model mean biases are comparable in magnitude with the typical differences between models (fig. S6B) and, over some regions, are also comparable to the differences between reanalysis data sets (fig. S6C).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CMIP5 models are particularly uncertain and biased in the Amazon. Although most models show a pronounced hotspot of future temperature SD increase, this is also the region where the magnitude of this increase is most uncertain. Overall, the regions that the models identify as hotspots of future temperature SD increase tend to have a positive bias, that is, the model average shows larger present-day variability than reanalyses (fig. S6A). However, selecting groups of models based on their overall sign of biases hardly affects the general pattern of changing temperature variability. Although there is a tendency for models with positive bias to also show larger increases in temperature SD in many places, this bias is relatively small compared to the predicted changes in most hotspot areas, and the position of hotspots and the relative magnitude of temperature variability changes in these regions are not substantially affected.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Donat 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>) recently raised the question whether the predictions of the models are reliable or whether they share common biases in their predictions of temperature extremes, despite the overall agreement regarding the magnitude of observed variability. In the case that the model predictions are correct, the question arises whether the anthropogenic fingerprint is already apparent in observations of temperature variability. We therefore recalculate the changes in temperature SD for the period from 1958 to 2017 and compare the result to two observational data sets based on in situ measurements from meteorological stations: HadCRUT4 (
  <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">
   <span class="italic">45</span>
  </a>) and the GISS (NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies) Surface Temperature Analysis (GISTEMP) (see Materials and Methods) (
  <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
   <span class="italic">46</span>
  </a>). These data sets report temperatures whose mean and variance have been standardized with a reference period. This procedure is known to introduce biases in variance changes (
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
   <span class="italic">47</span>
  </a>), although the effect is likely small here because the trends that we find in the observational data sets tend to also show up in the reanalyses that have no such bias (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At first sight, the observations do not agree well with the signal in the model predictions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). The most apparent features in observations are an increase in temperature SD in the Mediterranean region and a decrease in some parts of North America and Northern Europe (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, A and B). In contrast, the tendencies of changes in temperature SD in the models already show the overall pattern that we analyzed above when all models are considered (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4C</a>). However, the model agreement is still relatively low, and the characteristic contrast between high and low latitudes is not apparent in individual models with very few exceptions. If we assume that each model is one realization of climate variability in the real world, then this means that we cannot expect to see the anthropogenic signal in recent observations. It is only during the 21st century that the signal emerges in the large majority of the models, with more than 80% of the models agreeing on the sign until 2100 over subtropical land and the mid- and high latitudes (fig. S1). Although the sign of variability change in observations can be very clear at places (indicated by a large absolute Kendall τ value), these observations still provide only one realization.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Trends in temperature variability in the period 1958–2017 in observations and models.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Observations from HadCRUT4, (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) observations from GISTEMP, and (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) CMIP5 models. (A) and (B) show Kendall τ values, whereas (C) shows the number of models agreeing on the sign of the Kendall τ value. The window size for removing the annual cycle was 15 years, and the window to compute the Kendall τ value for the change in SD was 20 years.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aar5809-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a recent companion study (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>), we have shown that the sign of the observed temperature trends substantially depends on the choice of the time period, which confirms that the observed changes are largely related to internal climate variability and not a forced trend. The relatively robust decrease of observed variability over high northern latitudes in the North Atlantic region, however, might already be part of the anthropogenic signal (associated with sea-ice loss). Unfortunately, the regions with the largest model agreement in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4C</a> (tropical land areas and high latitudes)—where the anthropogenic signal can be expected to emerge the earliest—are also among the regions with the fewest observations. It is therefore hard to conclude whether current observations confirm or refute the predictions of models regarding trends in monthly temperature variability.
 </p>
</sec>
