<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unequal regional changes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We loosely define hotspots as regions of relatively large variability changes that also show a large model agreement on the sign of the change. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a> shows the projected relative changes in SD of monthly temperature anomalies until the end of the 21st century, averaged over all 37 models (see fig. S1 for model agreement). Several hotspots of increases in SD are revealed over (sub)tropical land, namely, Amazonia, Southern Africa, Australia, the Sahel, the Arabian Peninsula, India, and Southeast Asia. In boreal summer, large increases occur over Europe, North America, and near the Arctic coast (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). In all other seasons, SD decreases over northern mid-latitudes (fig. S2). Several of the identified hotspots are consistent with previous modeling studies (
   <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
    <span class="italic">21</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
    <span class="italic">23</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Relative changes of SD of monthly temperature anomalies until the end of the 21st century.</div>
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Boreal summer [June, July, and August (JJA)], (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) austral summer [December, January, and February (DJF)], and (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) the whole year, averaged over 37 climate models. In hatched areas, at least 30 of the 37 models agree on the sign of change from 1850 to 2100 expressed in the Kendall τ value [for example, see fig. S1A for the model agreement in (C)].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aar5809-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Absolute changes in variability are greatest in mid- and high latitudes in boreal autumn and winter (fig. S2), but these are also regions with the largest background levels of temperature variability. In relative terms, the largest changes in SD are increases of up to 40% in Amazonia and Southern Africa in austral spring and summer. Using temperature anomalies from all months of the year, Amazonia stands out as a region with a particularly large relative SD increase (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>) because increases occur in all seasons. Although the models agree on the sign of change, the magnitude differs substantially between the models, with some models showing a doubling of SD in the tropical hotspots, especially in central and northern Amazonia. The changes continue in the nine models extended beyond 2100 and scale approximately with global warming. In the model average, each degree of global warming leads to an ~15% increase in SD in Amazonia, Southern Africa, and the Arctic coast during the local summer season, and a 10% increase in the subtropical hotspots of the Northern Hemisphere (fig. S3).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have isolated the role of selected mechanisms in individual models by suppressing certain sources of variability (
   <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
    <span class="italic">24</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
    <span class="italic">26</span>
   </a>). This is not feasible across all of the CMIP5 models; hence, we take a different approach and analyze the changes in the terms contributing to the surface energy balance in the model mean, and identify important regional differences. In high latitudes, decreases in temperature SD are particularly pronounced over regions with sea-ice loss because the exposed ocean introduces a much larger heat capacity. This leads to more persistent but damped anomalies (
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
    <span class="italic">12</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
    <span class="italic">15</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
    <span class="italic">27</span>
   </a>), in other words, SD decreases. Reductions in SD in mid-latitudes are not directly related to Arctic sea-ice loss. The largest SD decrease in the Arctic occurs in autumn [September, October, and November (SON)], the season with the largest sea-ice loss until 2100, whereas the SD decrease in mid-latitudes is most pronounced during Northern Hemisphere winter (DJF), the season where Arctic amplification is largest (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> and fig. S2). This amplification of mean warming in high northern latitudes leads to a reduced meridional temperature gradient (fig. S4). If one assumes that typical wind patterns do not change, then incoming air from the North or South is less different in temperature than it was when the temperature gradient weakens, leading to smaller local temperature anomalies. Calculating the monthly anomalies of advection (the local temperature tendencies due to horizontal wind) indeed reveals a decrease of the advection-induced temperature variability (fig. S4). We thereby confirm previous studies showing that the decreased temperature variability in mid-latitudes is associated with a decreased meridional temperature gradient due to the polar amplification of global warming (
   <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
    <span class="italic">13</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
    <span class="italic">27</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
    <span class="italic">28</span>
   </a>). The CMIP5 models do not support the alternative hypothesis that Arctic amplification causes increased meandering of the mid-latitude westerlies and, hence, greater variance and persistence of mid-latitude weather conditions (
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
    <span class="italic">29</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increases of temperature variability that we find are largest in the season of maximum insolation (fig. S2). In the following, we therefore focus on the summer season. In the Southern Hemisphere, the results are qualitatively similar in all seasons. In the Northern Hemisphere, the summer season is the only season with an increased SD of temperature anomalies, whereas SD decreases in all other seasons (for the reasons described above). The large increases in SD over tropical land are particularly striking and have not been explained in previous analyses.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in the Southern Hemisphere</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although sea surface temperature (SST) anomalies are known to affect temperature over land (
   <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
    <span class="italic">24</span>
   </a>), SST variability appears not to be responsible for the increased variability on land, because of the low model agreement over the oceans in contrast to the large agreement in the identified land hotspots (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> and fig. S1). Furthermore, in the Southern Hemisphere summer, advection only plays a minor role (fig. S4C). We therefore focus on the local energy balance over land.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a local perspective, fluctuations in the downwelling radiation (short-wave plus long-wave fluxes) at the surface, 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>, can be seen as a direct atmospheric driver of temperature changes, which determines how much energy is available at the surface. We do not consider changes in surface albedo here because its contribution to monthly variability is likely small. We recognize that local conditions can feed back to the atmosphere (for example, via changes in cloud cover) to affect 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>, but note that 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> is also determined by processes on larger scales. A second important parameter is the evaporative fraction (EF) (the part of the available energy at the surface used to evaporate water), here calculated as 
   <span class="italic">EF</span> = 
   <span class="italic">LH</span>/(
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>u</sub> + 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>), with upwelling radiation 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>u</sub> and latent heat flux (LH). Because an increase in sensible heat flux is associated with temperature increase, whereas increased LH is not, EF determines by how much a change in atmospheric forcing translates into temperature change. The smaller the EF becomes, the greater the effect of variations in available net radiation on temperature, because more radiation is converted into sensible instead of latent heat.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have shown that changes in soil moisture affect the partitioning of surface fluxes mostly in intermediate moisture regimes (
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
    <span class="italic">30</span>
   </a>). Where evapotranspiration is limited by moisture but still has a substantial contribution to the energy balance, soil moisture has the largest effect on LH or temperature (and hence their variability). In this context, it is striking that regions with substantial increases in temperature variability coincide with regions identified as hotspots of strong soil moisture temperature coupling in previous studies (
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
    <span class="italic">30</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
    <span class="italic">31</span>
   </a>). We therefore analyze how increases in temperature variability are related to changes in soil moisture and EF, in comparison to variations in downwelling radiation 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2A</a> shows that the grid cells where temperature variability increases (red on the color scale) tend to have decreasing soil moisture (horizontal axis) as well as increasing variability in 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> (vertical axis). The same relation emerges when plotting EF instead of soil moisture (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>). Therefore, the changes in the Southern Hemisphere hotspots are consistent with the explanation that soil moisture loss leads to smaller EF and thus larger temperature variability. Even in the humid climate of Amazonia where evapotranspiration is limited by radiation in many places, the large future drying brings the region closer to a soil moisture–limited regime, which is associated with a large reduction in the positive correlation between evapotranspiration and incoming radiation (fig. S5).
  </p>
  <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Changes in variability of the surface energy balance until the end of the 21st century.</div>
    <p>The horizontal axes in (
     <span class="bold">A</span>), (
     <span class="bold">B</span>), (
     <span class="bold">D</span>), and (
     <span class="bold">E</span>) show changes in the mean, whereas all other axes and the color bar show changes in SD. Each dot represents the difference between the periods 1875–1904 and 2055–2084 at a particular land grid cell in the Southern Hemisphere without Antarctica (A to 
     <span class="bold">C</span>) and the Northern Hemisphere without Greenland (D to 
     <span class="bold">F</span>) for the multimodel average. All figures show summer conditions (DJF in the Southern Hemisphere, JJA in the Northern Hemisphere). The blue coordinate system in (C) and (F) defines the index shown in 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>, with negative values indicating larger increases in LH variability and positive values indicating larger radiative variability.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aar5809-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Such a transition from a wet to a moisture-limited regime is associated with an increase in the sensitivity of LH to soil moisture fluctuations (even in the absence of any changes in available radiation) (
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
    <span class="italic">30</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
    <span class="italic">32</span>
   </a>). The variability changes in 
   <span class="italic">LH</span> and 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> can therefore potentially reveal information on the mechanisms behind changes in variability. In agreement with the soil moisture hypothesis, increased temperature variability is associated with substantial increases in the variability of LH (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>). The SD of 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> and LH both increase to a similar extent, and thus, both contribute to increased temperature variability. However, as the changes in EF and soil moisture show, 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> cannot be the sole driver of the increased temperature variability because there is no clear reason why the increased SD of 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> would systematically deplete the mean soil moisture. Instead, we suggest that the SD increase in downwelling radiation in these areas is at least partly associated with land-atmosphere feedbacks. For example, surface drying can affect cloud distribution and, hence, the variability of 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>. To separate these effects quantitatively, specific additional model simulations would be needed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in Northern Hemisphere summer</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Northern Hemisphere shows a very different pattern (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>, D to F). There, soil moisture is not a good explanatory variable in general (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>). This occurs because soil moisture does not limit EF in many places, so that decreases in soil moisture do not necessarily cause increased temperature variability. Moreover, changes in EF alone cannot explain the increased temperature variability in the Northern Hemisphere (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>), and increases in 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> variability are needed as an explanatory variable at many places. The few exceptions with decreased temperature SD in the range of +4 to 6 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span> of downwelling radiation SD (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>) occur at grid boxes in very high northern latitudes (mainly Northeast Canada) where the fluctuations in available energy are often compensated by phase changes (melting snow and water, or freezing water) instead of temperature fluctuations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This pattern suggests that changes in the atmosphere on a regional scale are an important driver of the changes in variability at the surface. When we compare changes in the variability of 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> and LH in the Northern Hemisphere summer, we find two distinct regimes (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>). The horizontal (bottom-right) branch with substantial increases in LH variability is consistent with the soil-drying mechanism explained above. Because 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> variability does not increase or even decreases, the soil moisture loss must be solely responsible for the enhanced temperature variability. In contrast, the vertical (upper) branch in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a> consists of dry regions where other mechanisms dominate, whereas changes in LH variability are small.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To illustrate the geographical distribution of these differences, we quantify the relation between SD changes in LH and net downwelling surface radiation (
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>) as an index (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). This index (
   <span class="italic">I</span>) is proportional to the angle in the diagram spanned by the two properties (blue coordinate system in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>, C and F)
   <div class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">I</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
       <span class="mo">/</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">π</span>
       <span class="mo"> </span>
       <span class="mtext">atan</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">[</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
       <span class="mtext">SD</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">R</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">d</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
       <span class="mo">,</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
       <span class="mtext">SD</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">L</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">H</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">]</span>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <span class="mn">0.5</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>where ΔSD(
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>) and ΔSD(LH) stand for the changes in the SD of 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> and LH. The factor 2/π and the shift by 0.5 transform this angle in such a way to obtain a value of −1 if the increase in LH SD equals the decrease in 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> SD, 0 if both increase by the same amount (most points in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a> lie in this direction), and +1 if 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub> SD increases as much as LH SD decreases. In 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>, all clearly negative values (blue areas) are associated with variability increases in the latent heat flux, which cannot be explained with radiation alone. All clearly positive values (red areas) are associated with an increased variability of the downwelling radiation 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <sub>d</sub>, which cannot be explained with local hydrological changes. For example, heat waves in European summer (
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
    <span class="italic">33</span>
   </a>) show up as dominated by soil moisture loss (the horizontal branch in the scatter cloud of 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>), whereas, in the subtropics of the Northern Hemisphere (mostly the Sahel, Arabia, and India), radiation often dominates over LH changes (vertical branch in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>). The latter indicates that local changes in hydrology are too small to explain the radiative changes and that processes other than soil moisture loss are causing increased temperature fluctuations.
  </p>
  <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Index related to the changes in the SD of LH versus downwelling net radiation.</div>
    <p>See main text and 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> (C and F). Negative values indicate that changes are driven by soil drying, whereas positive values indicate a larger contribution of atmospheric variability. Ice sheets and locations where changes in temperature SD are smaller than 0.1K have been masked out (white areas). Each hemisphere shows summer conditions (JJA in the North, DJF in the South). All changes are calculated from the multimodel average and the period 1875–1904 versus 2055–2084.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aar5809-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because model agreement tends to be lower in India and the Sahel than in other hotspots (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> and fig. S1), we also calculate model averages for only the models showing an increase in temperature SD in a given region. In India, the SD of rainfall, soil moisture, cloud cover, and LH all increase despite little changes in mean soil moisture. This indicates that the Indian summer monsoon in the models is becoming more variable under greenhouse forcing, a result that is confirmed by other studies (
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
    <span class="italic">34</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>). A similar effect occurs in Southeast Asia (
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
    <span class="italic">36</span>
   </a>), in combination with a mean soil moisture decrease, causing an additional SD increase in temperature. In the Sahel, summer rainfall protrudes further north in those models showing a clear increase in temperature SD. Where the preindustrial climate has been almost permanently dry, an increased occurrence of cloudier and wetter months promotes increased variability in both radiation and LH. Moreover, because the Sahara warms more than the vegetated regions to the South, the meridional temperature gradient in the Sahel region is enhanced (fig. S4B). This enhancement of variability due to the increased spatial temperature contrast is hence the reversed mechanism of the decreased variability in mid-latitudes. An increased temperature gradient is also the reason for the zone of large SD increase surrounding the Arctic Ocean (fig. S4A), which warms much less than the land.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
