<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time periods and multimodel averages</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate geographic maps (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> and figs. S2 and S3) and scatter plots (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>) with changes in variability, we selected two time periods (1875–1904 and 2055–2084 to assess changes until 2100) from the anomaly time series mentioned above in each model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When calculating seasonal changes, we only selected the anomalies from the specific months belonging to a season (hence removing all other months from the time series). For each model, season, and time period, we then calculated the SD of the anomaly time series for the variable under consideration and took the absolute and relative difference between the two periods for each season and model. Because the historical simulation from 1850–2005 includes the radiative forcing from volcanic eruptions (in particular the strong eruption of Mt. Krakatoa in 1883), whereas the future scenario does not, we verified the robustness of our results. For example, when using a base period from 1888 to 1917 (that is, excluding the Krakatoa eruption) or the preindustrial control simulations (which do not contain volcanic eruptions), our results remain essentially the same.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thereafter, we averaged the resulting maps over all models. To do so, we brought the data on the same grid by interpolating each map to the grid of the model with the highest resolution (CCSM4), using a bilinear interpolation (CMCC-CM has even higher resolution but not all variables that we analyzed were available in that model, see above). The same method and grid were also used for interpolating the four reanalysis data sets. All multimodel averages are based on the same time period in each model.</p>
</sec>
