<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the twentieth century, the northern hemisphere experienced high rates of climate warming primarily before 1940 and after 1980, but there were regional deviations from this trend (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2013</a>). In northern Sweden, 1930–1960 was the first particularly warm period. This review suggests that the faunal community changed substantially at this time. Climate warming should primarily favor southern species. For the twentieth century as a whole, this was supported by changes in the bird community. Likewise, southern mammals increased and expanded (red fox, pine marten, badger, lynx, moose, and roe deer), while northern mammals retreated and declined (gray-sided vole, arctic fox, and wolverine). These observations are in line with the hypothesis that climate warming alters northern ecosystems. However, several of these changes have been suggested to be caused by drivers such as land-use change, anthropogenic food subsidies, and hunting. It is possible that the potential effects of climate warming were overlooked until recently, when the research focus shifted toward this driver. For example, recent findings show that the abundance composition of the Swedish bird community has tracked the temperature trend since the 1960s (Lindström et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2013</a>), and several birds have changed their phenology in the last century, although this pattern appears stronger in southern than in northern Sweden (Kullberg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2015</a>). Furthermore, out of 14 investigated alpine bird species, 9 declined significantly in 2002–2012, concurrent with increasing summer temperature and precipitation (Lehikoinen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2014</a>). Likewise, one-third of the alpine specialists, i.e., species that primarily breed in alpine areas, declined over the last 30 years (Ottvall et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2009</a>). Nevertheless, we suggest that the information in this review, taken together, indicates that climate warming worked in synergy with other factors, and that all these drivers primarily favored southern species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although there is substantial local variation, the altitudinal treeline in Sweden has advanced by an average 70–90 m in the twentieth century, and forest densification and increased shrub cover have been observed in some forest-to-tundra borderlands (Kullman and Öberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2009</a>; Callaghan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2013</a>). In the Arctic tundra, large herbivores in particular may escape predator regulation. However, with increasing summer temperature, the strength of herbivory decreases while that of predation increases, suggesting that the climate warming may cause a shift from bottom-up to top-down regulation of herbivores (Legagneux et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2014</a>). In Sweden, reindeer grazing has remained strong in alpine habitat, favoring graminoids, suppressing dwarf shrubs, and at least locally buffering against climate-driven treeline rise (Olofsson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2004</a>; Van Bogaert et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2011</a>). In Canada, most caribou (i.e., reindeer) populations are declining at present. Unfavorable weather conditions have had a negative effect on one caribou population, but land-use changes which indirectly favor large carnivores and increase the predation pressure on caribou are the main driver of these declines (Festa-Bianchet et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2011</a>). In Sweden, feeding of semi-domesticated reindeer during adverse winters and management of large predators may have prevented such change. Small rodent grazing can also have strong effects on the alpine plant community (Olofsson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2012</a>), but grazing effects should have weakened during periods without high-amplitude population peaks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The small rodent cycle, and associated cycles in rodent predators and alternative prey, is a key characteristic of northern ecosystems (Ims and Fuglei 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2005</a>; Krebs 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2011</a>). However, temporary release from top-down control is necessary for rodents to reach high-amplitude peaks (Ims et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2011</a>; Legagneux et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2012</a>). Hence, although fading cycles have been related to direct effects of snow characteristics (Kausrud et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2008</a>), climate change should also entail northern advancement of generalist predators that should stabilize the rodent cycle (Hanski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">1991</a>). Fading rodent cycles could also have positive feedback effects on generalist predators. Non-cyclic dynamics provide a more stable food resource, allowing some reproduction in all years (Hörnfeldt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2005</a>). Specialist rodent predators, which rely on high-amplitude peaks for breeding, could suffer from this development or be outcompeted by generalists (Ims and Fuglei 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2005</a>; Henden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2009</a>). Similarly, the recent expansion of kestrels in some boreal–alpine borderlands may be facilitated by declines in larger competitors in the rodent specialist guild, e.g., the rough-legged buzzard (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). However, this trend can also partly be explained by an increase in foraging habitat related to clear-cutting practices, and higher availability of nest sites caused by large-scale nest box programs (e.g., Saurola 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We suggest that climate warming has worked synergistically with other long-term anthropogenic drivers. For example, historical land use might have allowed some northern birds to expand into marginal southern habitats (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>), but they could be highly sensitive to climate change in these localities. Likewise, resource subsidies, such as alternative habitat or food, can increase and stabilize the dynamics of southern species in marginal northern habitat, providing a buffer against adverse periods (Henden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2009</a>). In Fennoscandia, Karelia retains a relatively large proportion of old-growth boreal forest (Lindén et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2000</a>). Roe deer was absent in the relatively cold period 1700–1900, but recolonized along rivers in the early 1900s. However, it remains restricted to watersides, agricultural land, and clear-cuts (Danilov 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2010</a>). Expansion of agriculture, forestry, built-up areas, and other infrastructure in Sweden likely provided southern species with dispersal corridors and suitable habitat, as well as refugia during adverse times. Thus, the northern advance in southern species that we observed in the 1900s could be seen as classic habitat tracking (Darwin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">1859</a>). Land-use change increased the structural and functional connectivity for southern generalists, as well as the temporal connectivity by providing refugia during less-favorable climate periods (Auffret et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2015</a>). This should have facilitated and reinforced northern expansions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While synergistic negative effects of multiple drivers of change are a common problem for threatened and declining species (Brook et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2008</a>), synergistic positive effects of climate and land-use change can favor invasive species. It has also been suggested that positive synergies may facilitate the expansion of temperate species to higher altitudes (Bellard et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2013</a>). Outside Fennoscandia, land-use change has so far had relatively little impact on the northern boreal and tundra biome, as these remain relatively unexploited in large parts of Russia and Canada (Brooks et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2006</a>). However, our study highlights that positive and negative synergies between climate warming and land-use change may be wide-spread in northern biomes experiencing both forms of change. Climate and land-use change are both projected to become strong drivers of biodiversity change in the boreal biome over the next century (Sala et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2000</a>), suggesting that the impact of these synergies will increase substantially in the northern hemisphere.
 </p>
</sec>
