<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We focused primarily on species that have a distribution limit in the boreal or alpine biome, as range shifts can be observed only in these species. Furthermore, because we reviewed observed changes since the nineteenth century, some information sources were qualitative and/or anecdotal. We assumed that such sources were more likely to report substantial changes such as range shifts, although we also included information on population trends. We defined species as ‘southern’ or ‘northern’ depending on their distribution relative to their distribution limit. Southern species had a northern and/or high altitudinal distribution limit in the boreal forest or alpine tundra in Fennoscandia (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), while northern species had a southern and/or low altitudinal distribution limit in boreal or alpine Sweden. Regarding the northern distribution limit, we used the Fennoscandian distribution limit to not exclude southern species that presently have a distribution limit slightly north of Sweden, as these might have advanced north within Sweden since the nineteenth century.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We did a two-part review. The first part was an overview of known changes in southern and northern bird species. Of 196 species regularly breeding in boreal or alpine Sweden, 118 (60 %) were classified as either southern or northern (Table 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13280-014-0606-8" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">S1</span> in Electronic Supplementary Material). The remaining species had, for example, eastern or scattered distributions (Table 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13280-014-0606-8" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">S2</span> in Electronic Supplementary Material). Svensson et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>) compiled information on long-term trends in Swedish bird species since the nineteenth century. For each southern or northern bird species, we used this source to find out whether the distribution limit had changed, or if not, whether there was another long-term population trend (Electronic Supplementary Material). Differences between southern and northern species were tested with Fisher’s exact test. For species that had shown range shifts or a long-term population trend, we also noted suggested drivers of change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second part of the review, we focused on northern and southern mammals, as well as bird species that interact strongly with these mammals. From a functional perspective, these bird species belong to the same wildlife community as the mammals, and we present the results with all species grouped according to their primary trophic function (herbivore/prey or predator) as well as body size (small, medium-sized, large). We excluded mammalian insectivores because they are not known to substantially interact with the community delineated above, and due to information deficiency regarding long-term change in the main taxa, shrews (
  <span class="italic">Soricidae</span>), and bats (
  <span class="italic">Chiroptera</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
