<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Medium-sized herbivores/prey</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The medium-sized herbivore/prey community is dominated by mountain hare (
  <span class="italic">Lepus timidus</span>) and grouse (capercaillie 
  <span class="italic">Tetrao urogallus</span>, black grouse 
  <span class="italic">Lyrurus tetrix</span>, hazel grouse 
  <span class="italic">Tetrastes bonasia</span>, willow ptarmigan 
  <span class="italic">Lagopus lagopus</span>, and rock ptarmigan 
  <span class="italic">Lagopus muta</span>). Although grouse also feed on insects, they are primarily herbivorous. Northern grouse and hare populations generally fluctuate or cycle (Angelstam et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">1985</a>). In the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, the period of these fluctuations appeared to largely reflect the small rodent cycle, although mountain hare also showed a tendency for longer periods of approximately 10 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). However, peak abundances seemed to decline in the 1900s in grouse, and after 1930 in hare, possibly with some recovery after 1960. Alternatively, the dynamics may have stabilized temporarily in 1930–1960 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>; Sweden’s Official Statistics 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">1870–1966</a>). Similarly, other sources suggest that rock ptarmigan has declined since the nineteenth century, while capercaillie and black grouse began declining in the 1930s to recover somewhat in the 1960s (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>). Both ptarmigan species declined in alpine habitat in the last decade (Lehikoinen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2014</a>). The medium-sized herbivore/prey community also includes some migratory geese. The lesser white-fronted goose (
  <span class="italic">Anser erythropus</span>) began declining in alpine Sweden in the 1930s, locally to extinction (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>). In at least one site, extirpation occurred within a few years in the 1940s (Ryd 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early reports attribute low abundance of hare and grouse to unfavorable weather and disease, but increased fox predation is mentioned twice in the 1920s (Sweden’s Official Statistics 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">1870–1966</a>). At present, the dominant hypothesis suggests that 3–5-year cycles in medium-size herbivores are caused by medium-sized predators, which switch from rodent prey to medium-sized prey in the decrease phase of the rodent cycle (Angelstam et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">1985</a>; Kausrud et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2008</a>). The tendency for 10-year fluctuations in mountain hare might be caused by interactions with larger predators, similar to present-day mountain hare populations in Russian Karelia which fluctuate with an approximate 11-year period tracked by the Eurasian lynx (
  <span class="italic">Lynx lynx</span>; Danilov 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2010</a>). In Sweden, strong suppression of medium-sized herbivores by red fox predation is supported by a temporary increase in hare and boreal grouse in the 1980s when a mange epizootic reduced the fox population (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>; Danell and Hörnfeldt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">1987</a>; Lindström et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">1994</a>). Red fox expansion in alpine Sweden is one potential cause of decline in white-fronted goose (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>). In Finland, boreal grouse is negatively affected by forestry, climate change, and fox predation (Ludwig 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2007</a>). In southern Sweden, the mountain hare has declined due to interference with introduced brown hares (
  <span class="italic">Lepus europaeus</span>). Since 1980, the brown hare has advanced north into boreal Sweden, likely in response to mild winters (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>; Jansson and Pehrson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2007</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Northern expansion of four southern species (
     <span class="italic">red</span>) in the northernmost Swedish counties (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">c</span>), indicated by hunting bags for 1960–2010, compared to similar northern or already established species (
     <span class="italic">gray</span>). The western jackdaw (
     <span class="italic">Corvus monedula</span>) was one of the expanding southern bird species (Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Hunting bag data were provided by the Swedish Association for Hunting and Wildlife Management
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2014_606_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
