<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small herbivores/prey</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The small herbivore/prey community is dominated by rodents, in particular bank vole (
  <span class="italic">Myodes glareolus</span>), gray-sided vole (
  <span class="italic">Myodes rufocanus</span>), field vole (
  <span class="italic">Microtus agrestis</span>), and Norwegian lemming (
  <span class="italic">Lemmus lemmus</span>). The bank vole is a southern species and field vole is omnipresent, while gray-sided vole and Norwegian lemming are northern species. Their dynamics have been described as generally cyclic with high-amplitude peaks every 3–5 years (Hansson and Henttonen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1985</a>; Angerbjörn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2001</a>). In the twentieth century, however, high-amplitude lemming peaks failed to appear in northern Sweden in 1941–1960 and 1982–2001 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>; Angerbjörn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2001</a>). Although an absence of conspicuous high-amplitude peaks does not exclude the possibility that cycles persist, but with inconspicuous low-amplitude peaks, analyses of the dynamics of rodent-dependent predators in 1960–2008 suggest that regular cycles were absent for some time in the 1980s and 1990s in both alpine and boreal rodent communities (Elmhagen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2011</a>). Small mammal trapping data show that cycle amplitude and period declined in boreal voles in 1971–2002, while a pattern with seasonal fluctuations with low spring densities and high autumn densities strengthened (Hörnfeldt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2004</a>). High-amplitude cycles reappeared in 2001, with the exception for gray-sided voles in boreal forests that remained at low population density (Ecke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2010</a>; Elmhagen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the 1970s, cycle amplitude and spring densities in particular have declined in the majority of the studied populations in Europe. The proximate mechanisms causing cycles to fade may vary within Europe as bioclimatic conditions differ. However, climate change is likely to be involved, as cycle amplitude is connected to winter conditions (Cornulier et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2013</a>). Substantial snow cover and specific snow characteristics appear to be a prerequisite for high-amplitude peaks in Fennoscandia (Hansson and Henttonen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1985</a>; Kausrud et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2008</a>). High-quality snow provides a subnivean space where small rodents can feed and be relatively protected from predators, allowing winter reproduction in lemmings, release from predator control, and rapid population growth (Kausrud et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2008</a>; Ims et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2011</a>). In the Swedish boreal forest, however, the gray-sided vole also suffers from fragmentation of mature forest (Ecke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2010</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
