<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small and medium-sized predators</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are three southern mammalian predators: badger (
  <span class="italic">Meles meles</span>), red fox, and pine marten (
  <span class="italic">Martes martes</span>). They have all increased or advanced since the nineteenth century. Pine marten was probably absent for some time between the seventeenth and nineteenth century, but increased in the late nineteenth century and in 1930–1960 (Helldin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2000</a>). The badger had its northern distribution limit in southern boreal Sweden in 1850–1900, but advanced north to the Arctic Circle during the 1900s (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>; Sweden’s Official Statistics 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">1870–1966</a>; Bevanger and Lindström 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1995</a>). The red fox was repeatedly described as increasing in northern Sweden in 1892–1895, 1914–1920, and 1937–1945. In 1945, it was specifically pointed out that it was spreading to new areas (Sweden’s Official Statistics 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">1870–1966</a>). The red fox also increased in Norway in 1891–1920, with further increases in 1930–1950 (Selås and Vik 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A large number of birds of prey, as well as the omnivorous gulls, are predators on small rodents (Krebs 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2011</a>). The common gull (
  <span class="italic">Larus canus</span>) and black-headed gull (
  <span class="italic">Chroicocephalus ridibundus</span>) expanded in inland northern Sweden in 1930–1950. The common gull also established in the alpine tundra in the 1960s (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>). The Eurasian kestrel (
  <span class="italic">Falco tinnunculus</span>) was a rare breeder in at least some mountain regions during the 1970s, but is now at least locally abundant in birch forest and alpine tundra (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). In boreal and alpine Sweden, rodent specialists such as northern harrier (
  <span class="italic">Circus cyaneus</span>) and rough-legged buzzard (
  <span class="italic">Buteo lagopus</span>) declined in 1940–1960 and 1980–2000 (Kjellén and Roos 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2000</a>). Likewise, boreal owl (
  <span class="italic">Aegolius funereus</span>), short-eared owl (
  <span class="italic">Asio flammeus</span>), and long-eared owl (
  <span class="italic">A. otus</span>) declined in 1980–2000 (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>; Hörnfeldt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2005</a>). The snowy owl (
  <span class="italic">Bubo scandiaca</span>) breeds only in alpine tundra. It was probably more common in the southern alpine tundra in the nineteenth century and did not breed at all in Sweden in 1982–2001 (Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>; Ottvall et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2009</a>). The only northern mammalian predator, the arctic fox, was abundant in the alpine tundra until the population plummeted in the early 1900s. Excessive hunting was suggested to cause the decline (Lönnberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">1927</a>), but the arctic fox did not recover despite protection in 1928. The population declined further in 1982–2001 (Angerbjörn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1995</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>).
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Density of breeding pairs of common kestrel and rough-legged buzzard in Stora Sjöfallet National Park 1970–1978 and 2001–2011. Density estimates include breeders only, i.e., nests where egg clutches were initiated. Both species are rodent specialists at this site, and short-term variation in breeding density is largely explained by numerical responses to small mammal fluctuations. Thus, the density of breeding pairs during rodent peaks is the most reliable population estimate. The rough-legged buzzard declined in Sweden in 1980–2000 (Kjellén and Roos 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2000</a>). In Stora Sjöfallet National Park, the average rough-legged buzzard breeding density in rodent peak years was lower in 2001–2011 compared to that in 1970–1978 (this figure)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2014_606_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are several suggested drivers of change in the southern species. Pine marten appears sensitive to harvest and the increase in 1930–1960 has been attributed to protection, while the species may have been suppressed by forestry and red fox interactions in the late twentieth century (Helldin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2000</a>). Badger expansion has been suggested to be associated with climate warming, land use promoting young forest stages, reduced hunting pressure, and wolf (
  <span class="italic">Canis lupus</span>) extirpation (Bevanger and Lindström 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1995</a>). The red fox is favored by climate warming, young forest stages, agricultural land, and anthropogenic infrastructure which provides food sources such as garbage and road kills (Hersteinsson and Macdonald 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1992</a>; Kurki et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1998</a>; Selås and Vik 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2006</a>; Selås et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2010</a>). In alpine tundra, the red fox is locally favored by changed reindeer herding practices, where reindeer are kept in the tundra throughout winter which increases the abundance of reindeer carcasses (Killengreen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2011</a>). In southern Sweden, red fox increased in the nineteenth century following large carnivore extirpation, but this effect appeared weak in northern Sweden, potentially due to strong effects of resource limitation (Elmhagen and Rushton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Declines in specialist rodent predators in northern Sweden in 1982–2001 are linked to poor reproduction due to disrupted rodent dynamics (Angerbjörn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1995</a>; Svensson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1999</a>; Kjellén and Roos 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2000</a>; Hörnfeldt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2005</a>; Ottvall et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2009</a>). In addition, increased competition with the red fox likely contributed to the decline of the arctic fox in the early 1900s and prevented its recovery (Hersteinsson and Macdonald 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1992</a>). The arctic fox has retreated to high-altitude habitats where red fox interactions are least likely to occur (Herfindal et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2010</a>). Since 2000, the arctic fox has increased in two Swedish areas with intense conservation efforts, red fox culling, and supplemental feeding, while the number of arctic foxes has remained low in Scandinavian areas without intense actions (Angerbjörn et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>). The positive effect of increased food availability relies on a relative absence of red foxes, as red foxes can monopolize productive habitats and food resources such as carcasses (Killengreen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2007</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2011</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
