<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heat acclimation (HA) involves a series of beneficial physiological adaptations resulting from repeated exposure to heat stress that facilitate a greater ability to deal with subsequent heat exposure. Considering children are vulnerable to heat illness under extreme conditions, employing HA strategies provides a feasible risk reduction strategy in the face of climate change. Differing HA regimens may be utilized, with conditions closest to the anticipated exposure environment, typically lasting 7–14 days [
 <xref rid="B108-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>] and often incorporating exercise to elicit a maximally heat acclimated phenotype [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Physiological adaptations to HA have been extensively documented in adults [
 <xref rid="B104-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>], including reduced cardiovascular strain (heart rate (HR) and Q) at a given workload, a lower 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> threshold for sweating, increased thermosensitivity resulting in a higher SR for a given 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic>, and greater maximal SRs [
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. Children acclimate similarly to adults yet do so more slowly, requiring several more days of exposure for complete HA [
 <xref rid="B72-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The reduced sweating onset threshold and HA-associated increases in SR are highly beneficial during subsequent exposure to high ambient temperatures in a population that has significantly lower sweating responses compared to adults. Children display lower sweat NaCl concentrations compared to adults [
 <xref rid="B107-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>], with reductions in sweat Na
 <sup>+</sup> and Cl
 <sup>−</sup> concentrations in both groups following HA [
 <xref rid="B126-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Further acclimation increases the responsiveness of the duct to aldosterone in adults [
 <xref rid="B128-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>], but this mechanism has not been investigated in children.
</p>
