<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec9.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">9.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assemblages</div>
 <sec id="sec9.2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biozone 1: 15.87–11.25 m</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This lowermost zone extends from the sandy clays to the shelly silts (sub-units 2a–2c). The sandy clays below 14.00 m yielded a sparse ostracod fauna dominated by juveniles of the euryhaline species 
   <span class="italic">Cyprideis torosa</span> (Jones). Many of the specimens of 
   <span class="italic">C. torosa</span> showed signs of nodal development, a characteristic that has been attributed to salinities (&lt;6‰) at the lowest limit of the species' range (cf. 
   <a rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib75">Meisch, 2000</a>). Freshwater species increase in frequency and become more diverse in the clay-rich sediments at 13.00 m. These include the bottom-burrowing 
   <span class="italic">Candona neglecta</span> Sars and 
   <span class="italic">Pseudocandona marchica</span> Hartwig and the plant-crawling 
   <span class="italic">Ilyocypris gibba</span> (Ramdohr) and 
   <span class="italic">Limnocythere inopinata</span> (Baird). Two of these, 
   <span class="italic">C. neglecta</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I. gibba</span>, show particularly large increases in abundance at 13.00 m (
   <a rid="fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#fig9">Fig. 9</a>). Noded valves of 
   <span class="italic">C. torosa</span> also increase at this level.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec9.2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biozone 2: 11.25–7.90 m</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This upper zone extends from the middle of sub-unit 2c to Unit 3 and is characterized by fluctuations in the frequencies of both brackish and freshwater taxa. At 10.63 m, for example, numbers of smooth-valved 
   <span class="italic">C. torosa</span> increase dramatically, whilst the diversity and frequency of freshwater species decline. Numbers of 
   <span class="italic">C. torosa</span> fall, however, at 9.50 m, with a corresponding rise in the frequencies of freshwater taxa. 
   <span class="italic">C. neglecta</span> dominates the latter, with well-balanced numbers of adults and juveniles and males and females (
   <a rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98">Roe, 1994</a>). The free-swimming 
   <span class="italic">Sarscypridopsis aculeata</span> (Lilljeborg) also occurs. 
   <span class="italic">C. torosa</span> valve frequencies rise again near the upper part of the unit. The thin detritus muds overlying the silty clays (Unit 3) yielded only a few noded 
   <span class="italic">C. torosa</span> and the occasional broken valve of 
   <span class="italic">C. neglecta</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
