<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lithostratigraphy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the exception of the sands and gravels exposed in the cliffs, which extend for several kilometres along the coast of Mersea Island (
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Fig. 3</a>), the entire Pleistocene sequence at Cudmore Grove fills a steep-walled, channel-like depression cut into the London Clay, the ‘Cudmore Grove Channel’ (
  <a rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98">Roe, 1994</a>) (
  <a rid="fig3 fig4 fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3 fig4 fig5">Figs. 3–5</a>). This feature is at least 0.28 km wide and 0.25 km long and is aligned in a northwest–southeast direction. The southern edge of the channel is well exposed at the base of the cliffs near Cudmore Grove wood and on the foreshore (
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Fig. 3</a>). Its maximum observed depth was recorded in borehole CG1 at −10.40 m O.D. (
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>). The depth further to the east is unknown, where the Pleistocene beds are truncated by Holocene sediment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Pleistocene sequence at Cudmore Grove can be divided into six units:</p>
 <sec id="sec4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 1: Basal sands and gravels (Cudmore Grove Channel Gravel)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The floor of the channel is lined with sands and gravels that form the basal member of the Pleistocene sequence and directly overlie London Clay. These reach a maximum recorded thickness (3.10 m) in borehole CG1 (
   <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>), then thin progressively south-westwards towards the channel margin, where they taper into a 1–2 cm pebble lag (
   <a rid="fig4 fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4 fig5">Figs. 4 and 5</a>), the ‘Cudmore Grove Channel lag’ (
   <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">Bridgland et al., 1988</a>). The persistence of Unit 1 to the northeast of borehole CG1 is unknown.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 2: Silty clays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The basal gravels grade upwards into a thick sequence of silts and clays, which occupy most of the channel and are exposed over wide areas of the foreshore. This unit can be divided into four sub-units:</p>
  <sec id="sec4.2.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a. Sandy clays</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Massive, dark grey sandy clays occupy the basal 0.5–1 m. These reach maximum thickness (1.2 m) in borehole CG1, and thin towards the channel margin (
    <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>). They can also be traced at the eastern end of the site below −5 m O.D. The continuity of the sub-unit beyond this point is unknown.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4.2.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">b. Lower silty clays</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sandy clays pass gradually upwards into brown-grey silty clays (Munsell: 10YR 4/1), commonly interbedded with thin, horizontal and gently inclined sand bands. Shell fragments occur occasionally. The lower silty clays reach maximum thickness (ca 3 m) between boreholes CG1 and MM5 and can be traced as far north as the sea wall (
    <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4.2.3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">c. Shelly silts</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lower silty clays grade upwards into a thick sequence of massive, dark grey silts with scattered shell debris. These vary in thickness, from ca 5 m near borehole MM5 to &lt;1 m in the southwest. The shelly silts can also be traced to the end of the sea wall in the northeast, where they extend from −3 m to 2 m O.D. (
    <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>). The sub-unit is truncated further to the east by Holocene estuarine sediment.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4.2.4" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">d. Upper silty clays</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Green-grey silty clays, (ca 0.5 m) with occasional horizontal sand beds form the uppermost member of this unit, which contains occasional scattered wood fragments and shell debris.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 3: Detritus muds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The silty clays are truncated at the southwestern part of the site by a thin bed of shelly detritus muds, composed of abundant shell debris in a matrix of dark brown (7.5YR 2/0) silty clay. This deposit, which when sampled in the early 1990s was only a few centimetres thick, is richly fossiliferous and has yielded a wealth of faunal remains (
   <a rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib57">Holman et al., 1990</a>; see below). The detritus muds were formerly more extensive and up to 30 cm thick (
   <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">Bridgland et al., 1988</a>) but have been eroded significantly by ongoing cliff retreat. The contact between the detritus muds and the silty clays of Unit 2 is sharp and is marked by a thin bed of coarse sand. The maximum thickness of the detritus muds (15 cm) was recorded near borehole MM3 (
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a>). From here the unit thins rapidly westwards, grading into 2–3 cm layer of grey sand and eventually disappearing near borehole MM5.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 4: Organic clays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Organic clays with abundant wood fragments overlie the detritus muds. The contact between the two units is abrupt and is marked by the sudden disappearance of shell debris. Like the detritus muds, the organic clays achieve maximum thickness (2.5 m) in the southwestern part of the site, where two facies can be recognised, a lower ca 20–50 cm bed of highly compressed wood interbedded with organic clay, and an upper 1–2 m bed of massive, organic clay with occasional wood fragments. The lower deposit is the more heterogeneous and is partly laminated. Three tree trunks have been exhumed from this horizon, one with its roots still intact (
   <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>, Fig. 5.26). Both beds show signs of compaction and local deformation. The organic clays thin steadily south-westwards, where they finally meet the rising surface of the London Clay. They also thin north-eastwards and eventually become truncated by the Upper sands and gravels (Unit 6) (Figs. 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
   <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">6</a>A).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 5: Grey clays</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Massive, grey clays, 5–30 cm thick, form the uppermost member of the channel-fill sequence (
   <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">Fig. 6</a>B). The contact between the two deposits is variable, sometimes it is marked by a transitional zone of brown-grey clay, but elsewhere it is abrupt. The unit extends laterally towards the eastern part of the site where it rests directly above Unit 2. It finally disappears near borehole 25 (
   <a rid="fig4 fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4 fig5">Figs. 4 and 5</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Units 1–5 together complete the infill sequence of the Cudmore Grove Channel, which we formally define here as the ‘Cudmore Grove Member’ of the Lower Thames Formation (cf. 
   <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">Gibbard, 1999</a>). Borehole CG1, which includes the thickest representation of most of the sedimentary units, is proposed as the stratotype [TM 0681 1456].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 6: Upper sands and gravels (Mersea Island Member, Lower Thames Formation)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fine-grained beds are capped by 4–5 m of sands and gravels, which are exposed in the Cudmore Grove cliffs (Figs. 
   <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">4</a>, 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
   <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">6</a>A). These were originally assigned to the ‘Mersea Island Gravel’ of the Low-level East Essex Gravel Formation (
   <a rid="bib12 bib13 bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12 bib13 bib14">Bridgland, 1983, 1988, 1994</a>), which comprised all the diverted Thames gravel aggradations in eastern Essex. This has since been re-termed the ‘Mersea Island Member’ of the Lower Thames Formation (
   <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">Gibbard, 1999</a>) with Cudmore Grove the designated type locality. Accelerated cliff erosion in recent years has provided excellent exposures of the sands and gravels that comprise two main facies: a lower 2–3 m suite of cross-bedded sands (Unit 6a); and an upper 3 m of mainly clast-supported gravels (Unit 6b) (
   <a rid="fig4 fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4 fig5">Figs. 4 and 5</a>). The lower unit, which forms a sharp contact with the underlying grey clays and organic clays, is best developed in the western part of the cliff exposure, where it comprises large-scale, gently dipping foresets of sand and subsidiary gravel. Individual foresets are 15–50 cm thick and dip at angles of 5–20°. Palaeocurrent measurements show that the prevailing flow direction was towards the north-north-east (
   <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>c). In the lower part of this unit the sand-rich facies are locally interbedded with a series of thin (1–5 cm) grey clay horizons (
   <a rid="fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#fig6">Fig. 6</a>B).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sandy beds are truncated by the clast-rich facies of Unit 6b, which thicken progressively towards the sea wall. These too are cross-stratified, particularly in the lower 2 m, although the foresets are smaller than in Unit 6a. In contrast to the lower facies, palaeocurrent measurements show that flow was towards the southeast (
   <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>c).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unit 6b shows several signs of periglacial deformation, including a number of ice-wedge casts. At the southwestern end of the exposure the gravelly facies are also interbedded with large lobes of massive, heavily oxidized silty clay (‘brickearth’) (
   <a rid="bib12 bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12 bib18">Bridgland, 1983; Bridgland et al., 1988</a>; 
   <a rid="fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#fig5">Fig. 5</a>), thought to comprise soliflucted London Clay (
   <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
