<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec15" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">15</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amino acid geochronology</div>
 <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec15.1" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">15.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A new technique of amino acid analysis has been developed for geochronological purposes (
   <a rid="bib83 bib84 bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib83 bib84 bib86">Penkman, 2005; Penkman et al., 2007a, 2008a</a>), combining a reverse-phase high-pressure liquid chromatography (RP-HPLC) method of analysis (
   <a rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib60">Kaufman and Manley, 1998</a>) with the isolation of an ‘intra-crystalline’ fraction of amino acids by bleach treatment (
   <a rid="bib127" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib127">Sykes et al., 1995</a>). This combination of techniques results in the analysis of D/L (dextro- and laevo-rotatory optical isomers) values of multiple amino acids from the chemically protected protein within the biomineral, thereby enabling both decreased sample sizes and increased reliability of the analysis.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amino acid racemization (AAR) analyses were undertaken on shells and opercula from bulk samples from Unit 3: four shells of 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> (NEaar 0859, 0888–0890; published in 
   <a rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84">Penkman et al., 2007a</a>), four shells of 
   <span class="italic">V. piscinalis</span> (NEaar 0855–0858; published in 
   <a rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84">Penkman et al., 2007a</a>) and four opercula of 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> (NEaar 0891–0894). Seven 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> opercula (NEaar 2407–8, 3728–3730, 3820–2821) have also been analysed from the neighbouring ‘East Mersea Restaurant Site’ (Sample 3) (
   <a rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>); five previously published by 
   <a rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib85">Penkman et al. (2007b)</a> (NEaar 3728–3730, 3820–3821) and two new analyses (NEaar 2407–8). All samples were prepared using the procedures of 
   <a rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib83">Penkman (2005)</a> and 
   <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Penkman et al. (2008a)</a> to isolate the intra-crystalline protein by bleaching. Two subsamples were then taken from each shell; one fraction was directly demineralised and the free amino acids analysed (referred to as the ‘Free’ amino acids, FAA, F), and the second was treated to release the peptide-bound amino acids, thus yielding the ‘total’ amino acid concentration, referred to as the ‘Total Hydrolysable amino acid fraction’ (THAA, H*). Samples were analysed in duplicate by RP-HPLC.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DL ratios of aspartic acid/asparagine, glutamic acid/glutamine, serine, alanine and valine (D/L Asx, Glx, Ser, Ala, Val) as well as the [Ser]/[Ala] value provide an overall estimate of protein decomposition (
   <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">Fig. 10</a>; 
   <a rid="appseca1" ref-type="sec" href="#appseca1">Supplementary Online Appendix 1</a>). Serine is one of the most geochemically unstable amino acids, with one of its decomposition products being alanine (
   <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">Bada et al., 1978</a>). This enables the ratio of the concentration of serine ([Ser]) to the concentration of alanine ([Ala]) to be used as a useful indication of the extent of protein decomposition. The D/L of an amino acid will increase with increasing time, whilst the [Ser]/[Ala] value will decrease. The D/L of Ser is less useful as a geochronological tool for samples of this age, but is presented here as aberrant values are useful indications of contamination.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="results" id="sec15.2" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">15.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a closed system, the amino acid ratios of the FAA and the THAA subsamples should be highly correlated, enabling the recognition of compromised samples. The extent of protein decomposition in both the FAA and THAA increases with time, with increased levels of protein breakdown during warm stages and decreased rates of degradation in cold stages. Data from British interglacial deposits using the intra-crystalline fraction of these three biominerals (
   <span class="italic">V. piscinalis</span> shell, 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> shell and opercula) tend to fall into clusters of amino acid ratios (
   <a rid="bib83 bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib83 bib84">Penkman, 2005; Penkman et al., 2007a</a>). Given a similar temperature history, this then allows a regional aminostratigraphic framework to be developed, with independent geochronology allowing correlation with marine Oxygen Isotope Stages (
   <a rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib83">Penkman, 2005</a>). The extent of protein degradation in the 
   <span class="italic">V. piscinalis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> shells indicates an age for the Cudmore Grove shells between MIS 7 and MIS 11 (
   <a rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84">Penkman et al., 2007a</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has become apparent that the protein fraction within gastropod shells has greater variability in samples of this age, resulting in difficulties in discrimination between different interglacial warm stages (
   <a rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84">Penkman et al., 2007a</a>). Amino acid data obtained from the intra-crystalline fraction of the calcitic 
   <span class="italic">Bithynia</span> opercula indicate that this biomineral is a particularly robust repository for the original protein (
   <a rid="bib84 bib86 bib88" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84 bib86 bib88">Penkman et al., 2007a, 2008a, in press</a>). The 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> opercula from Cudmore Grove (
   <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">Fig. 10</a>) have protein that is significantly more degraded than that from Aveley and Lion Pit, which are in the Mucking Formation of the Thames, correlated with MIS 7 (
   <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>). Aveley also has OSL dates consistent with an age within MIS 7 (E. Rhodes, personal communication). The opercula protein from Cudmore Grove is also less degraded than that from sites correlated with MIS 11, such as Hoxne (
   <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Ashton et al., 2008</a>), Swanscombe, Clacton (
   <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">Bridgland et al., 1999</a>), Barnham (
   <a rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib93">Preece and Penkman, 2005</a>), Elveden (
   <a rid="bib146" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib146">Ashton et al., 2005</a>) and Beeches Pit (
   <a rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib95">Preece et al., 2007</a>). Both Hoxne (
   <a rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib49">Grün and Schwarcz, 2000</a>) and Beeches Pit (
   <a rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib95">Preece et al., 2007</a>) have independent geochronology (U series/ESR and TL) confirming attribution to MIS 11. The opercula show similar levels of protein degradation to sites correlated with MIS 9, including Hackney (
   <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">Green et al., 2006</a>), Barling (
   <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Bridgland et al., 2001</a>) Grays (
   <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>) and Purfleet (
   <a rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib112">Schreve et al., 2002</a>). Purfleet also has OSL data consistent with an MIS 9 age (E. Rhodes, personal communication). The intra-crystalline protein decomposition is slightly lower than that observed at Purfleet, which is consistent with an age within a later part of MIS 9.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the low levels of degradation with cold stages and because of the natural variability in biological samples, there is a potential difficulty of discriminating between the end of one warm stage and the beginning of the next, particularly with some amino acids. We have therefore used statistical tests on the 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> opercula to establish whether it is possible to use the extent of protein breakdown to discriminate between Cudmore Grove and selected sites that have multiple lines of evidence correlating them with either MIS 11, MIS 9 or MIS 7. Together with the problem of small sample sizes, amino acid data have upper and lower limits (0 and 1) and therefore statistical tests must be applied with caution. However, they can provide useful insights alongside interpretations based on the graphical data alone. For each amino acid within each fraction (FAA and THAA), a 2-tailed 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-test (assuming normally distributed data, as shown to be usual in 
   <a rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib84">Penkman et al., 2007a</a>) was performed on the data. If the result of the 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-test produces a 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05, this enables discrimination between the two groups tested at a 95% confidence level. The 2-tailed 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-test assumes no prior knowledge of the stratigraphy and therefore provides a useful guide of the resolving power of this technique when applied to sites of unknown age. The results are presented in 
   <a rid="appseca1" ref-type="sec" href="#appseca1">Supplementary Online Appendix 2</a> but are also summarised in 
   <a rid="tbl6" ref-type="table" href="#tbl6">Table 6</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amino acid data from 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> and 
   <span class="italic">V. piscinalis</span> shells and 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> opercula indicate an age for Cudmore Grove lying between MIS 7 and MIS 11 but the enhanced chronological resolution from the 
   <span class="italic">Bithynia</span> opercula data indicates a probable mid-late MIS 9 age.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span> opercula protein analysed from the East Mersea Restaurant Site (Sample 3) was significantly less degraded than those from Cudmore Grove (
   <a rid="fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#fig10">Fig. 10</a>). Although one sample has slightly lower ratios in Glx and Val (NEaar 2408), the samples have very similar values to opercula from sites correlated with the Ipswichian (MIS 5e), such as Trafalgar Square in central London and Bobbitshole, the Ipswichian type site near Ipswich (Suffolk) (
   <a rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib87">Penkman et al., 2008b</a>). The extent of protein decomposition is significantly less than that observed in opercula from sites correlated with MIS 7 (
   <a rid="appseca1" ref-type="sec" href="#appseca1">Appendix 1</a>). The amino acid data therefore support the correlation of the Restaurant Site with the Ipswichian.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
