<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec16.1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">16.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environment and climate associated with the interglacial beds: synthesis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The channel-fill sequence at Cudmore Grove has yielded an impressive suite of thermophilous plant and animal remains clearly indicative of interglacial conditions. Particularly important in this respect are the beetle assemblages, from which a temperature range 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>max</sub> 16–22 °C and 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>min</sub> −7 °C to +4 °C has been estimated, and the herpetofauna that is indicative of a climatic regime equivalent to that found today in parts of central Europe. Moreover, the Cudmore Grove channel sediments span much of the interglacial and have provided a long pollen record extending from the early-temperate stage, when oak and other thermophilous forest elements were expanding, to the late-temperate stage, when late immigrating trees such as 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus</span> were becoming established (
  <a rid="tbl7" ref-type="table" href="#tbl7">Table 7</a>). The post-temperate sub-stage, during which pollen values of 
  <span class="italic">Quercus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> decline and those of 
  <span class="italic">Pinus</span>, Poaceae and Ericales increase, may also be represented in the grey clays (Unit 5) in the upper part of the sequence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further insights into the depositional context of the interglacial beds have been provided by the diatom, ostracod, molluscan and coleopteran assemblages, which show that the channel-fill sequence accumulated in a dynamic coastal environment that underwent a number of changes through time (
  <a rid="tbl7" ref-type="table" href="#tbl7">Table 7</a>). The diatoms and ostracods together show that the silty clays (Unit 2) were deposited in a tidally-influenced river channel, which became increasingly open to marine influence as the oak-dominated early-temperate sub-stage progressed. Outer estuarine conditions prevailed by the end of this phase. Conditions changed markedly when the detritus muds (Unit 3) accumulated; this richly fossiliferous deposit was the product of high-energy riverine or coastal processes that carried shell debris, insect remains, bones and other detritus into the site from the surrounding hinterland and adjacent estuarine areas. Sheltered lagoonal conditions became established subsequently as the organic muds (Unit 4) accumulated and the site became isolated from the open estuary. The persistent presence of marine diatoms in these sediments, which date from the late-temperate sub-stage, confirms that relative sea levels remained high, with saltwater episodically penetrating the lagoon. The grey clays (Unit 5) capping the channel-fill sequence may even reflect a return to more open, estuarine or fully marine conditions towards the end of the interglacial, although the absence of diatoms or ostracods precludes confirmation.
 </p>
</sec>
