<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec12.2.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">12.2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herpetofauna</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The herpetofaunal assemblage, one of the richest reported from Britain (
  <a rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib57">Holman et al., 1990</a>), provides valuable palaeoclimatic information, since the geographical distributions of these animals are closely linked to temperature. All herpetiles are directly reliant upon external heat for their survival, and in the case of oviparous reptiles, require certain minimum temperatures for the hatching of their eggs. Six of the 14 herpetile taxa reported from Cudmore Grove by 
  <a rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib57">Holman et al. (1990)</a> are not native in Britain: water frog or edible frog (
  <span class="italic">Rana ridibunda</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Rana esculenta</span>), moor frog (
  <span class="italic">Rana arvalis</span>) tree frog (
  <span class="italic">Hyla</span> sp.), viperine or dice snake (
  <span class="italic">Natrix tessellata</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Natrix maura</span>), aesculapian snake (
  <span class="italic">Zamenis longissimus</span>) and European pond terrapin (
  <span class="italic">Emys orbicularis</span>). There is some debate over the degree of oceanicity or continentality indicated by these exotic taxa. Based upon their present-day ranges, 
  <a rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib57">Holman et al. (1990)</a> suggested that the palaeoclimate at Cudmore Grove was slightly warmer than at present in Britain, with mean July temperatures above 17–18 °C and with mild winters. Comparable modern analogues have been suggested for central or southern France (
  <a rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib57">Holman et al., 1990</a>) or northern Italy (
  <a rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib56">Holman, 1993</a>) but 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Gleed-Owen (1999)</a> proposed more continental conditions. 
  <span class="italic">Z. longissimus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">N. tessellata</span> are distributed throughout most of eastern Europe, where they experience cold continental winters (
  <a rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib36">Gasc et al., 1997</a>). Taken in association with the occurrence of 
  <span class="italic">R. arvalis</span> at Cudmore Grove, 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Gleed-Owen (1999)</a> suggested that a more realistic modern analogue would be around the southeast German border with north-east Austria and the western Czech Republic.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Cudmore Grove herpetofaunal assemblage is indicative of still or slowly flowing water with abundant aquatic vegetation, adjacent damp grassland and nearby well-vegetated, damp habitats with plenty of ground cover. Some drier, open shrub or woodland habitats are also indicated by 
  <span class="italic">Bufo bufo</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Z. longissimus</span>, whereas 
  <span class="italic">Vipera berus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Lacerta vivipara</span> occur in a wide range of open terrestrial habitats, including heaths, dunes, woodland, marshes and meadowland (
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Arnold and Burton, 1980</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
