<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec12.1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">12.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fossiliferous deposits were first reported at East Mersea in the early 1900s by 
  <a rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib29">Dalton (1908)</a>, although no specific mention was made of vertebrate remains. Later accounts by 
  <a rid="bib137 bib138" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib137 bib138">Warren (1917, 1933)</a> and 
  <a rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib27">Cornwall (1958)</a> mention bones of 
  <span class="italic">Hippopotamus</span> and therefore probably refer to the deposits of Ipswichian age that are known from the nearby ‘Hippopotamus Site’ (
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">Bridgland and Sutcliffe, 1995</a>) and the ‘East Mersea Restaurant Site’ (
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">Bridgland et al., 1995</a>) a short distance away on the foreshore (
  <a rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>). The detritus muds (Unit 3) at Cudmore Grove have yielded an extensive vertebrate assemblage including mammals, birds and herpetiles (
  <a rid="bib18 bib57" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18 bib57">Bridgland et al., 1988; Holman et al., 1990</a>) and fish. Unit 1 has yielded a fragmentary molar of an indeterminate elephant (G.R. Ward, personal communication) and a single bone of 
  <span class="italic">Bison</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Bos</span> was recovered from Unit 2 (
  <a rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98">Roe, 1994</a>). The specimens from Unit 3 are extremely well preserved, showing no significant signs of rolling or abrasion. The presence of fragile herpetile vertebrae and small mammal mandibles with the dentition still 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> suggests that there has been little post-depositional disturbance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At least 18 mammalian taxa have been recognized amongst the 1508 bones and teeth recovered from the detritus muds (Unit 3) (
  <a rid="tbl5" ref-type="table" href="#tbl5">Table 5</a>). In addition, 11 fish taxa, 14 herpetofaunal taxa (364 specimens) and 11 avian taxa (41 specimens) have been recorded.
 </p>
</sec>
