<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec7.4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">7.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pollen biostratigraphy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pollen sequence from Cudmore Grove shows two clear phases of vegetational development. The first, in biozones CG-1 and CG-2, records the regional establishment and expansion of mixed oak woodland, during the mesocratic phase of an interglacial, when closed forests developed under temperate conditions and soils became more fertile (cf. 
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">Birks and Birks, 2004</a>). Biozone CG-3 in contrast, records the local development of alder carr woodland with a peripheral expansion of 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span>. In northwest Europe the expansion of these two trees occurred in the oligocratic phase, when soils deteriorated and forest cover declined. In Britain, this broad pattern of vegetational succession has commonly been divided into four zones: the ‘pre-temperate’, ‘early-temperate’, ‘late-temperate’ and ‘post-temperate sub-stages’ (
  <a rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib133">Turner and West, 1968</a>). More complete palynological records from central and southern Europe (e.g. 
  <a rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib104">Roucoux et al., 2008</a>) indicate that some interglacials have more complex histories of forest change, but we retain these terms here in order to facilitate comparisons of the pollen records with those of other Middle Pleistocene sites and as a framework for the discussion of the relative sea-level history.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The representation of pollen spectra of both early and late-temperate sub-stage character at Cudmore Grove is highly unusual within the context of the Thames region, where interglacial pollen records are typically fragmentary. A hiatus probably occurs between biozones CG-2 and CG-3, but there are strong grounds for believing that both of these phases date from the same interglacial. There is, for example, no evidence for a period of weathering or a major unconformity between the two biozones, or any evidence for an intermediate deterioration of climate. Alder also appeared to have been expanding locally at the end of zone CG-2 and continued to expand in CG-3, suggesting that the two biozones date from the same temperate episode. The profile from Cudmore Grove thus represents one of the most complete, non-lacustrine interglacial pollen records from Britain and is arguably the most important from the Thames system. However, given the changes in pollen source area and the estuarine/lagoonal context of the sediments, correlations with other sites, particularly records from lakes, must be made with caution.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite this difficulty, a number of palaeobotanical elements strongly support correlation with a ‘Hoxnian-type’ interglacial (cf. 
  <a rid="bib115 bib128" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib115 bib128">Scourse et al., 1999; Thomas, 2001</a>). This evidence is strongest in the upper part of the sequence (biozone CG-3), where the presence of Type X and 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> pollen and megaspores of 
  <span class="italic">A. filiculoides</span> together preclude correlation with any other interglacial sequences of the British Late-, Early and Middle Pleistocene. All three floristic elements were absent, for example, in the Ipswichian (=Eemian/MIS 5e) (cf. 
  <a rid="bib143" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib143">West, 1980</a>). These elements are also absent at sites that have been correlated on the basis of their terrace stratigraphy, faunal assemblages or aminostratigraphy with MIS 7, for example, Aveley and Ilford in the Lower Thames region (
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>), although the pollen records from these sites are far less complete (
  <a rid="bib144 bib142" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib144 bib142">West et al., 1964; West, 1969</a>). Sparse 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> pollen (&lt;0.5–1% of the total land pollen) has been reported from fluvial deposits which have been correlated with MIS 7 at Stoke Goldington (
  <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">Green et al., 1996</a>) and Marsworth (
  <a rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib78">Murton et al., 2001</a>) in Buckinghamshire, although these can be attributed to long-distance inputs (cf. 
  <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">Green et al., 1996</a>). The spectra from both of these sites differ from those of Cudmore Grove in several other respects, particularly in their absence of Type X and their inclusion of greater frequencies of Poaceae pollen, which point to an incomplete regional tree cover in southern Britain at least during part of this interglacial.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More detailed correlations between the Cudmore Grove pollen assemblages and those from other ‘Hoxnian-type’ sites in Britain and continental Europe are hampered by several problems, not least the taphonomic issues outlined above, and the fact that more than one ‘Hoxnian-type’ temperate episode may have occurred with similar floristic characteristics (cf. 
  <a rid="bib115 bib128 bib113" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib115 bib128 bib113">Scourse et al., 1999; Thomas, 2001; Scourse, 2006</a>). It is nevertheless appropriate to make brief comparisons with the records from three key sites in the immediate vicinity (&lt;20 km) that have also yielded pollen assemblages of ‘Hoxnian’ character: i) the Hoxnian parastratotype succession at Marks Tey, Essex, a lacustrine sequence infilling a depression cut in Anglian till (
  <a rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib131">Turner, 1970</a>); and ii) the pollen spectra from the neighbouring channel-fill sequences at Clacton (
  <a rid="bib90 bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib90 bib21">Pike and Godwin, 1953; Bridgland et al., 1999</a>) and Tillingham (East Hyde) (
  <a rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib100">Roe, 2001</a>) (
  <a rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>). The last two channel-fills were deposited by the Thames in the interglacial that immediately followed the diversion of the river into eastern Essex during the late Anglian, i.e. the Hoxnian (cf. 
  <a rid="bib14 bib21 bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14 bib21 bib100">Bridgland, 1994; Bridgland et al., 1999; Roe, 2001</a>). The sediments at all three sites have been correlated with MIS 11 (
  <a rid="bib21 bib107" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21 bib107">Bridgland et al., 1999; Rowe et al., 1999</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Cudmore Grove pollen spectra share several attributes with those from Marks Tey, only 16 km to the northwest (
  <a rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib131">Turner, 1970</a>: p. 396; 
  <a rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#fig7">Fig. 7</a>). Biozones CG-1 and CG-2, for example, compare closely with the spectra assigned to Ho IIa at this site, which are characterized by a sharp rise in 
  <span class="italic">Quercus</span> pollen, a gradual expansion of 
  <span class="italic">Alnus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Corylus</span> and persistent presence of 
  <span class="italic">Fraxinus</span> pollen (
  <a rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib131">Turner, 1970</a>), although this sub-stage is not especially diagnostic (
  <a rid="bib128" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib128">Thomas, 2001</a>). The Cudmore Grove pollen profile differs from that of Marks Tey in the high frequencies of 
  <span class="italic">Pinus</span>, although this might be explained by taphonomic differences between the sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biozone CG-3 at Cudmore Grove is also broadly similar to the late-temperate sequence (Ho III) at Marks Tey, particularly in its record of 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus</span> and Type X pollen. However, all three taxa achieve much greater abundances at Marks Tey than at Cudmore Grove, with 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> in particular peaking at frequencies of 45%, as opposed to ca 6% at Cudmore Grove (
  <a rid="fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#fig7">Fig. 7</a>). This attribute alone does not provide sufficient basis for assuming that the sites are of different ages; the comparatively modest 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> profile at Cudmore Grove could be an artifact of the local dominance of 
  <span class="italic">Alnus</span>, which may have obscured some of the regional vegetational changes upon which zonation of this sub-stage has been based (cf. 
  <a rid="bib141 bib131" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib141 bib131">West, 1956; Turner, 1970</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> prefers drier soils and is thus unlikely to have flourished around Cudmore Grove at any time during the high 
  <span class="italic">Alnus</span> phase. Moreover, even if 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> was widespread in the hinterland, it is doubtful whether much of its pollen would have reached the site, given its low rates of pollen productivity and restricted patterns of dispersal (
  <a rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib96">Reille, 1990</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Taxus</span> pollen is also far more strongly represented at Marks Tey than at Cudmore Grove, achieving frequencies of ca 10% (
  <a rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib131">Turner, 1970</a>), although varying frequencies of yew pollen could reflect local differences in soil conditions (cf. 
  <a rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib61">Kelly, 1964</a>). Unlike Marks Tey, there is also no record of 
  <span class="italic">Pterocarya</span> in the late-temperate sub-stage at Cudmore Grove (cf. 
  <a rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib131">Turner, 1970</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pollen profiles from Clacton and East Hyde (Tillingham) also include far greater abundances of 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus</span> pollen than Cudmore Grove, although in other respects the assemblages are broadly similar, and all three sites have yielded Type X pollen and remains of 
  <span class="italic">Azolla</span>. At Clacton, 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> peaks at ca 65% (
  <a rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib90">Pike and Godwin, 1953</a>), whilst at East Hyde a peak of 40% is recorded (
  <a rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib100">Roe, 2001</a>). This difference might again reflect taphonomic variations between the sites; during the late-temperate sub-stage of the interglacial represented at Cudmore Grove a sheltered lagoon appears to have existed, whereas the channels at East Hyde and Clacton were more open to estuarine influence during the corresponding interval (
  <a rid="bib90 bib21 bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib90 bib21 bib100">Pike and Godwin, 1953; Bridgland et al., 1999; Roe, 2001</a>). This might have provided suitable conditions for the selective accumulation of bisaccate grains.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The palaeobotanical data from Cudmore Grove thus display broad similarities with the neighbouring records from Marks Tey, East Hyde and Clacton, but there are a number of subtle differences, particularly the differing proportions of 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> recorded in the late-temperate sub-stage. These may either reflect taphonomic differences between the sites, or may imply that the Cudmore Grove profile belongs to a younger interglacial also characterized by ‘Hoxnian-type’ vegetation, and possibly co-eval with MIS 9 (cf. 
  <a rid="bib115 bib128" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib115 bib128">Scourse et al., 1999; Thomas, 2001</a>). Wider comparisons between the Cudmore Grove pollen record and sites in southern Britain and elsewhere are considered further below in the light of the other bio- and aminostratigraphic data.
 </p>
</sec>
