<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec6" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional distribution of the sediment sequence</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thickness of the sand and gravel overburden in the Cudmore Grove cliffs, (
  <a rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig4">Fig. 4</a>) renders it impossible to trace the Cudmore Grove Channel or its associated infill inland or immediately beyond the foreshore area. However, sand and gravel outcrops occur elsewhere on the island, which have been correlated with the gravel in the Cudmore Grove cliffs (
  <a rid="bib12 bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12 bib13">Bridgland, 1983, 1988</a>). Compositionally these gravels are similar to those at Cudmore Grove, although they differ considerably in height. The outcrops at West Mersea, for example, have basal elevations of ca 10–13 m O.D. (
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">Bridgland, 1983</a>), some 10 m higher than the gravels at Cudmore Grove (
  <a rid="fig2 fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2 fig4">Figs. 2 and 4</a>). These outcrops rest directly on London Clay. The outcrops near East Mersea are less well documented, although 
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">Bridgland (1983)</a> established that the small outcrop to the west of the village (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>b) has a base of ca 10 m O.D. Sand and gravel outcrops at Point Clear, 4 km to the east of Cudmore Grove on the Tendring Plateau (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>), have also been assigned to the Mersea Island Member (cf. 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland (1994)</a> showed that the various outcrops of the Mersea Island Member correspond well, both in thickness and height, with the sands and gravels of the Asheldham Member (cf. 
  <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">Gibbard, 1999</a>) on the Dengie Peninsula, which he considered its upstream equivalent. The Wigborough Gravel, ca 8 km to the east in the Clacton area (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>), was thought to represent the downstream equivalent on the Tendring Plateau (see 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>: p. 294 for a full account of the correlations). Like the gravels in the Cudmore Grove cliffs these also include slightly enriched levels of exotics (
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>: p. 322).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In spite of these long profile projections, it remains difficult to establish whether all the outcrops of the Mersea Island Member represent part of a single aggradation or whether they are composite in age. It is possible, for example, that some of the more elevated outcrops are older than those in the Cudmore Grove cliffs and may even pre-date the Cudmore Grove Channel and its infill. Relative age determinations based on long profile projections are also hampered, in this instance, by the fact that at least part of the Cudmore Grove cliff gravels sequence appears to have been deposited by a tributary river or rivers (the proto-Blackwater and/or proto-Colne) and not by the Thames–Medway (
  <a rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98">Roe, 1994</a>). The stratigraphical and palaeogeographical implications of these findings are considered further below.
 </p>
</sec>
