<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional setting</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The coastal fringe of eastern Essex is dominated by a series of low-lying (&lt;ca 30 m O.D.) Pleistocene terrace gravels that extend in a north-easterly direction between Southend and Clacton (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>). These deposits are largely of Thames origin and post-date the Anglian glaciation, when the Thames was diverted by ice from an earlier, more northerly course across central and northern Essex into the valley of an existing tributary, the Essex Medway (cf. 
  <a rid="bib48 bib12 bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib48 bib12 bib14">Gruhn et al., 1974; Bridgland, 1983, 1994</a>, Fig. 5.5; 
  <a rid="bib39 bib40" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39 bib40">Gibbard, 1985, 1994</a>). Older, pre-Anglian diversion Thames deposits, assigned to the ‘Kesgrave Member’ of the Lower Thames Formation (
  <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">Gibbard, 1999</a>) occur to the north of Mersea Island in the Tendring Plateau area, whilst pre-diversion gravels of the Essex Medway, the ‘High-level East Essex Gravels’ (
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>), survive as isolated remnants in the west of the coastal region (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>). The study area lies beyond the Anglian ice limits; the nearest glacial deposits occur a few kilometres to the west of Colchester (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The terrace gravels of south-eastern Essex are locally underlain by remnants of a series of palaeo-channels cut into the London Clay (
  <a rid="bib67 bib12 bib13 bib14 bib98 bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib67 bib12 bib13 bib14 bib98 bib99">Lake et al., 1977; Bridgland, 1983, 1988, 1994; Roe, 1994, 1999</a>). Of these, the channel-fill sequence at Cudmore Grove is the best preserved and most accessible. These features represent incised river channels of the diverted Essex Thames (or ‘Thames–Medway’) and its associated tributaries as the river migrated southwards across the region during successive warm stages of the late Middle Pleistocene (
  <a rid="bib18 bib21 bib14 bib98 bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18 bib21 bib14 bib98 bib100">Bridgland et al., 1988, 1999; Bridgland, 1994; Roe, 1994, 2001</a>). Palaeontological analyses have confirmed that the southeast Essex channel deposits accumulated under fully temperate conditions at times of high relative sea level (
  <a rid="bib139 bib14 bib98 bib99 bib100 bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib139 bib14 bib98 bib99 bib100 bib21">Warren, 1955; Bridgland, 1994; Roe, 1994, 1999, 2001; Bridgland et al., 1999</a>). The terrace gravels and the channel-fill sediments are truncated locally by Holocene estuarine sediment, particularly around the east-trending estuaries of the Crouch, Blackwater and Colne (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
