<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec16.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">16.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The age of the Cudmore Grove interglacial beds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The biostratigraphical datasets have provided varying degrees of insight into the age of the interglacial beds. The pollen and plant macrofossil data are important not only for constraining the length of interglacial time recorded, but they additionally include elements that have traditionally been regarded as uniquely ‘Hoxnian’, including the presence of Type X pollen, modest levels of 
  <span class="italic">Abies</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Carpinus</span> pollen in the late-temperate sub-stage and megaspores of 
  <span class="italic">A. filiculoides</span> (
  <a rid="bib131 bib89 bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib131 bib89 bib58">Turner, 1970; Phillips, 1976; Horton et al., 1992</a>). A last interglacial (MIS 5e) or an MIS 7 age for the Cudmore Grove interglacial beds can therefore be firmly ruled out. However, given the uncertainty over the number and status of ‘Hoxnian-type’ interglacials represented in the British Pleistocene (
  <a rid="bib98 bib115 bib128" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98 bib115 bib128">Roe, 1994; Scourse et al., 1999; Thomas, 2001</a>), there are potential flaws in undertaking correlations with spectra from other ‘Hoxnian’ sites. This problem is further compounded by the fact that most of the sites that have been attributed to the younger of the two ‘Hoxnian-type’ interglacials, which was possibly co-eval with MIS 9, have only yielded fragmentary pollen records, reflecting their fluvial origin (
  <a rid="bib128 bib80" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib128 bib80">Thomas, 2001; Nitychhoruk et al., 2006</a>). Notwithstanding this, the pollen spectra from Cudmore Grove zone CG-1 show some similarities to the short pollen profiles from Hackney (
  <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">Green et al., 2006</a>) and Barling (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Bridgland et al., 2001</a>) in the Thames system, which have both been correlated with MIS 9 on the basis of their faunal biostratigraphy and position in the Thames terrace sequence. These profiles, which span part of the early-temperate sub-stage of an interglacial (cf. 
  <a rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib133">Turner and West, 1968</a>), also include a phase of 
  <span class="italic">Quercus</span>–
  <span class="italic">Pinus</span> dominance with subsidiary levels of mixed oak forest taxa, e.g., 
  <span class="italic">Ulmus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Fraxinus</span>. They have also both yielded macrofossils of 
  <span class="italic">A. filiculoides</span>. Unfortunately, like many other early-temperate sub-stage spectra (cf. 
  <a rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib133">Turner and West, 1968</a>), the observed palynological changes are biostratigraphically uninformative and do not provide independent grounds for correlation. Pollen biostratigraphical correlations with longer regional pollen records from lacustrine sequences are complicated by the fact that the Cudmore Grove pollen assemblages accumulated in a coastal environment where different taphonomic processes operate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With regard to the molluscs, the occurrence of the invasive bivalve 
  <span class="italic">C. fluminalis</span> in the early-temperate sub-stage is significant because during the Hoxnian it does not occur until the late-temperate sub-stage, at least in the Thames system (cf. 
  <a rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib74">Meijer and Preece, 2000</a>). For example, at both Swanscombe and Clacton (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>), it only appears with the so-called ‘Rhenish fauna’ in the aggradations which are attributed to Ho IIIb (
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Kerney, 1971</a>). Its early appearance at Cudmore Grove is again more consistent with its distribution at Barling (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Bridgland et al., 2001</a>) and Hackney Downs (
  <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">Green et al., 2006</a>) which both are attributed to MIS 9.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mammalian faunas and the AAR data provide the strongest insights into the age of the Cudmore Grove interglacial beds and firmly support a correlation with MIS 9. In the case of the mammalian data, this correlation is not only based on the absence of several ‘indicator’ species of Hoxnian age, but on the presence of 
  <span class="italic">U. arctos</span> (brown bear), which is unknown from the Hoxnian, and also on the ‘
  <span class="italic">Mimomys</span>’ enamel differentiation of the 
  <span class="italic">Arvicola</span> molars (cf. 
  <a rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib95">Preece et al., 2007</a>). The fact that only 4.46% of the 
  <span class="italic">Arvicola</span> specimens from Cudmore Grove display the ‘
  <span class="italic">Mimomys</span> fold’ further points to a post-Hoxnian age (cf. 
  <a rid="bib82 bib95" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib82 bib95">Parfitt, 1998; Preece et al., 2007</a>). The AAR datasets are derived from the shells of two species of molluscs (
  <span class="italic">V. piscinalis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">B. tentaculata</span>), as well as the opercula of the latter. These data independently support a correlation with MIS 9. Despite their proximity and palynological similarities, the differences in the amino acid ratios between Cudmore Grove and Clacton are particularly striking. Not surprisingly, the Cudmore Grove amino acid ratios also differ from those of the East Mersea Restaurant Site (
  <a rid="bib18 bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18 bib20">Bridgland et al., 1988, 1995</a>), which lies only 2 km to the south-west of Cudmore Grove (
  <a rid="fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>). This interglacial deposit, which comprises ca 1.2 m of silts and gravel channelled into the London Clay, has yielded a freshwater molluscan fauna and a rich vertebrate assemblage (10 species) that includes the water vole, 
  <span class="italic">A. terrestris terrestris</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Hippopotamus amphibius</span>; a combination unknown in Britain before the Late Pleistocene (cf. 
  <a rid="bib126 bib125" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib126 bib125">Sutcliffe and Kowalski, 1976; Sutcliffe, 1995</a>). The mammal assemblages compare closely with those from several other Ipswichian (MIS 5e) sites, including Joint Mintor Cave, Devon (
  <a rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib123">Sutcliffe, 1960</a>) and Trafalgar Square, London (
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">Bridgland et al., 1995</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further independent support for a separation of the Cudmore Grove interglacial beds from those at Clacton is provided by the marked differences in the sea-level histories of the two sites. The Clacton Channel deposits do not record the onset of estuarine/marine conditions until relatively late in the interglacial, during the late-temperate sub-stage (Ho IIIb), whereas the earlier part of the channel-fill sequence, representing the early-temperate sub-stage, accumulated in a freshwater environment (
  <a rid="bib132 bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib132 bib21">Turner and Kerney, 1971; Bridgland et al., 1999</a>). A similar onset of marine conditions, again during Ho IIIb, is recorded in the channel-fill sequences at East Hyde near Tillingham (
  <a rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib100">Roe, 2001</a>) (
  <a rid="fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#fig11">Fig. 11</a>) and at Swanscombe (
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Kerney, 1971</a>) and all three channels are believed to have infilled during MIS 11 (
  <a rid="bib21 bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21 bib100">Bridgland et al., 1999; Roe, 2001</a>; 
  <a rid="fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig12">Fig. 12</a>a). At Cudmore Grove, in contrast, estuarine conditions were already established in the early-temperate sub-stage of the interglacial represented, and relative sea levels remained high until at least the late-temperate sub-stage. It is difficult to reconcile the presence of outer estuarine conditions at Cudmore Grove during the early-temperate sub-stage with the freshwater conditions at Clacton; the channels lie at approximately the same height and are only 10 km apart and are thus likely to have been flooded by the sea around the same time had they formed during the same interglacial (
  <a rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98">Roe, 1994</a>). To accommodate these differences within the same temperate event requires a complex model of coastal evolution, which would have allowed the sea to penetrate the eastern part of Mersea Island, but not neighbouring Clacton (
  <a rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib99">Roe, 1999</a>). Whilst this cannot be ruled out, it is not supported by any evidence or the bio- and aminostratigraphical data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The clast lithological and palaeocurrent data presented here further re-enforce the interpretation that the Cudmore Grove Channel is not an upstream equivalent of the Clacton Channel as was once suggested (e.g. 
  <a rid="bib13 bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13 bib14">Bridgland, 1988, 1994</a>). This interpretation was based on the assumption that both interglacial channel-fills were overlain by what were assumed to be Thames–Medway gravels: the Mersea Island Member aggradation above the Cudmore Grove Channel and the Wigborough Gravel at Clacton (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>). The fine-grained channel-fills were thus thought to represent the interglacial course of the Thames–Medway during the interglacial that preceded the Mersea Island–Wigborough Gravel aggradation: the Hoxnian (
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>, Fig. 5.5). The Hoxnian correlation was based on the biostratigraphy of the Clacton deposits and their position in the Thames terrace sequence (cf. 
  <a rid="bib132 bib13 bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib132 bib13 bib14">Turner and Kerney, 1971; Bridgland, 1988, 1994</a>, Fig. 5.5). The clast lithological data presented here cannot confirm that either the basal sands and gravels lining the Cudmore Grove Channel (Unit 1) or the Unit 6 gravels in the Cudmore Grove cliffs were deposited by the Thames–Medway. Indeed, the Unit 1 gravels have a composition that is more consistent with aggradation by a smaller river, possibly the Essex Blackwater, re-working Thames–Medway deposits, local Kesgrave Member gravels and fluvio-glacial gravels from the area to the west of Cudmore Grove. Moreover, the palaeocurrent directions from Unit 6 confirm that the upper part of this aggradation (sub-unit 6b) was deposited by a river flowing from the northeast (possibly a proto-River Colne), which is inconsistent with a Thames–Medway origin. The Unit 6 gravels also display compositional differences from Thames–Medway gravels further to the south, for example, on the Dengie Peninsula (cf. 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>), which suggest that they too may have been aggraded by tributary rivers (the Colne, Blackwater or both) re-working older Thames–Medway deposits. The terrace gravels above the two channels cannot therefore be used to confirm that the underlying interglacial beds are either contemporaneous or part of the same palaeo-channel system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is therefore compelling biostratigraphical, aminostratigraphical and palaeo-sea level evidence, together with evidence from the regional terrace stratigraphy to suggest that interglacial deposits from three separate interglacials are represented in this small area of eastern Essex: i) the Clacton and Tillingham Channel deposits, which are of Hoxnian age and formed during part of MIS 11 (
  <a rid="bib21 bib100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21 bib100">Bridgland et al., 1999; Roe, 2001</a>); ii) the Cudmore Grove Channel deposits, which we suggest formed within MIS 9; and iii) the East Mersea Restaurant Site deposits, which are of last interglacial (Ipswichian) age (MIS 5e). We reject the possibility that the Cudmore Grove sequence dates from a younger temperate sub-stage within MIS 11 (for example, sub-stage 11c) because the sequence records a full interglacial forest succession and temperatures several degrees warmer than present, characteristics that are inconsistent with other records attributed to this warm interval (cf. 
  <a rid="bib97 bib31 bib95" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib97 bib31 bib95">Reille et al., 2000; Desprat et al., 2005; Preece et al., 2007</a>). The Cudmore Grove mammal faunas are also markedly different to those recorded in the upper part of the Hoxnian type-sequence at Hoxne (strata C and B), which has recently been re-assigned to a later sub-stage within MIS 11 (
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Ashton et al., 2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The palaeogeographies of eastern Essex were quite different during the two late Middle Pleistocene interglacials (
  <a rid="fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig12">Fig. 12</a>). During MIS 11, the Thames–Medway appears to have flowed north-eastwards between Tillingham and Clacton, maintaining its early post-diversion route, which had been established late in the Anglian (cf. 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">Bridgland, 1994</a>; 
  <a rid="fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig12">Fig. 12</a>a). During MIS 9, a larger fluvio-estuarine drainage network appears to have existed in the region, of which the Cudmore Grove Channel sequence was only a small remnant (cf. 
  <a rid="bib14 bib98 bib112" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14 bib98 bib112">Bridgland, 1994; Roe, 1994; Schreve et al., 2002</a>) (
  <a rid="fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig12">Fig. 12</a>b). On the basis of the clast lithological data, we assume that this section of the palaeo-estuary was associated with a southward-draining tributary system (the ‘proto-Colne or proto-Blackwater’), which may have become confluent with the Thames–Medway somewhere in the current offshore area, possibly east of the Dengie Peninsula. Interglacial deposits filling buried channels at Shoeburyness, Canewdon (
  <a rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib99">Roe, 1999</a>) and Barling (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Bridgland et al., 2001</a>) on the Southend Peninsula, and Burnham (North Wick) on the Dengie Peninsula (
  <a rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib99">Roe, 1999</a>) are all considered to have formed part of this palaeo-estuary (
  <a rid="bib99 bib112" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib99 bib112">Roe, 1999; Schreve et al., 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="fig1 fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#fig1 fig12">Figs. 1 and 12</a>). Like Cudmore Grove, all these sites have yielded brackish-water assemblages indicative of the early-temperate sub-stage of an interglacial (
  <a rid="bib98 bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib98 bib99">Roe, 1994, 1999</a>). The spectra from Shoeburyness and North Wick show striking similarities to those from zone CG-2 at Cudmore Grove, although the late-temperate sub-stage is missing at these sites (
  <a rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib99">Roe, 1999</a>). The exact geography of this palaeo-estuary is speculative, although bathymetric and seismic data from the offshore area to the east of the Dengie Peninsula confirm the existence of a buried channel system with associated submerged terrace gravels in the postulated vicinity of this inferred MIS 9 estuary (
  <a rid="bib19 bib16 bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19 bib16 bib15">Bridgland et al., 1993; Bridgland and D'Olier, 1995; Bridgland, 2002</a>). It is worth noting that the occurrence of channel-fills in close proximity that can demonstrably be shown to date from different interglacials is not unique in Britain; a similar series of channel-fills of Middle to Late Pleistocene age occur in close juxtaposition in the eastern Solent on the south coast of England, incised into the soft, Eocene Bracklesham Beds (
  <a rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib94">Preece et al., 1990</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
