<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">During the 20th century, meteorological measurements have shown significant warming during all seasons but the greatest rates have been during winter and spring. They have also revealed general increases in precipitation, although considerable decadal-scale variability is present over many regions of the country. For example, Zhang 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] determined that mean annual air temperature has increased by an average of 0.9 °C over southern Canada between 1900 and 1998 with the greatest rates seen in the West during the winter and spring (southern Canada broadly refers to south of 60N; an exception is [
 <xref rid="B314-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">314</xref>] and mention in [
 <xref rid="B315-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">315</xref>] where southern Canada refers to south of 55N. See Figure 5 in [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] for additional details. For Statistics Canada discussions, see [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] for a description of standard drainage area classifications). Subsequent analysis extending the target period to 2010 confirmed the warming has continued and even accelerated with an increase in the mean annual temperature of 1.5°C for southern Canada over this longer period [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Zhang 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] also found that annual total precipitation increased significantly from 1990–1998 over most of southern Canada with the exception of southern Alberta and Saskatchewan. Analysis expanded to the period 1900 to 2009 also found an 8.7% increase in annual rainfall for southern Canada [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Snowfall mainly increased in northern Canada while at the same time decreasing significantly in the Southwest for the period 1950–2009 [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
