<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An analysis of changes in extreme temperature indices over southern Canada from 1900–2003 and the entire country from 1950–2003 found that over most of the country, there was an increase in the number of warm days where the maximum temperature (&gt;90th percentile) and the number of warm summer days (maximum temperature &gt;25°C) during the last half century [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The number of hot days (&gt;30°C) and summer warm days (&gt;90th percentile) also increased over all of Canada, but were only significant in southwestern regions [
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. The analysis revealed little change in the number of summer warm spells. An examination of changes in extreme temperature and precipitation indices over southern Canada from 1900–2003 and the entire country from 1950–2003 found a decrease in the consecutive number of days with no measurable precipitation in British Columbia and Atlantic Canada. Trends in drought occurrence and severity in Canada are often monitored using meteorological drought indices, such as the Standardized Precipitation Index (SPI), the Palmer Drought Severity Index (PDSI), and the Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. These indices are designed to assess regional precipitation anomalies (the SPI), or a region’s water balance using both precipitation and temperature data (PDSI and SPEI), to account for evapotranspiration effects. Results from trend investigations incorporating these various drought indices have shown variable results over Canada, often being dependent on the time period used in the trend calculation (mainly due to the aforementioned decadal-scale variability in precipitation). However, an increase in drought (i.e., a decreasing Palmer Drought Severity Index (PDSI) trend) over most of the country was observed between 1950 and 2002 [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>].
</p>
