<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and sampling sites</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The eastern Himalayan mountain region occupies western and north-western Yunnan, western Sichuan, south-eastern Tibet, southern Qinghai and south-western Gansu. Steep mountain ranges and major rivers in deep valleys divide this region into several distinct eco-subregions [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>] (see Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a>). Tang [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>] and Zhang [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] described diverse floristic constitution of these subregions. The northern subregion, which is comprised a part of the Tibetan plateau, is dominated by a plateau cold and dry climatic condition [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>]. The vegetation type is characterized by alpine meadows and grasslands. This northern subregion is considered as 'Plateau avifauna' with the endemic avian species as 
   <span class="italic">Pseudopodoces humilis, Montifringilla adamsi, Pyrgilauda ruficollis, Urocynchramus pylzowi </span>and 
   <span class="italic">Kozlowia roborowskii </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B31" href="#B31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">32</a>]. The southern subregion, on the other hand, is influenced by much warmer and wetter climatic condition, and the vegetation is characterized by tropical, or subtropical, broadleaved forests with a mixture of evergreen and deciduous species. This subregion is represented by Himalaya-Hengduanshan Mountain avifauna with many endemics babbles (Timallinae) and pheasants [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>]. The eastern subregion consists of a cluster of mountains including of Qinling, Min, Mang and Daba mountains. The vegetation is dominated by temperate evergreen coniferous and broadleaved mixed forests. Endemic avian species include 
   <span class="italic">Chrysolophus pictus, Spizixos semitorques, Garrulax sukatschewi, G. davidi, Yuhina diademata, Paradoxornis przewalskii, P. paradoxus </span>and 
   <span class="italic">Parus davidi </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B31" href="#B31">31</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>]. Subregion-specific species have also been observed for other taxa, such as plants [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>], ants [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>], fishes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B36" href="#B36">36</a>], reptiles [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>] and mammals [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B38" href="#B38">38</a>].
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Topographic map of the eastern Himalayan region including all elevations between 2 000 and 4 000 m.a.s.l.; the altitudinal range of Elliot's laughing thrush (
      <span class="italic">Garrulax elliotii</span>)
     </span>. The species' range is indicated by the thin dashed line as in [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B110" href="#B110">110</a>]. Sampling locations are indicated by the abbreviation of each population's name (Table 1). The bold dashed line represents the boundary between recognized ecological subregions of the eastern Himalayan mountain range [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]. Insert: The shaded area represents the study region.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1471-2148-11-174-1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These three subregions are further divided into thirteen biogeographic sectors corresponding to clusters of mountains [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]. The sites from which samples of 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>were obtained are shown in Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a> and Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>. These sample sites were distributed across the range of the species, and grouped into ten populations according to the biogeographic sectors described in Li [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>].
  </p>
  <div id="T1" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Nucleotide polymorphism in each population; S, number of segregating sites; Nhap, number of haplotypes; Hd, haplotype diversity; π, nucleotide diversity</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="center">Subregion division</th>
      <th align="center">
       <span class="bold">Biogeographic sectors in Li </span>[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]
      </th>
      <th align="center">Sampling locations</th>
      <th align="center">
       <span class="italic">n</span>
      </th>
      <th align="center">S</th>
      <th align="center">Nhap</th>
      <th align="center">Hd</th>
      <th align="center">π</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="center">Southern subregion</td>
      <td align="center">Southwest Yunnan mountains</td>
      <td align="center">DL</td>
      <td align="center">11</td>
      <td align="center">39</td>
      <td align="center">10</td>
      <td align="center">0.982</td>
      <td align="center">0.00338</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td align="center">Yulong mountains</td>
      <td align="center">ZD</td>
      <td align="center">14</td>
      <td align="center">58</td>
      <td align="center">13</td>
      <td align="center">0.989</td>
      <td align="center">0.00385</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center">Eastern</td>
      <td align="center">Motianling mountains</td>
      <td align="center">WX</td>
      <td align="center">7</td>
      <td align="center">27</td>
      <td align="center">5</td>
      <td align="center">0.905</td>
      <td align="center">0.00279</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center">subregion</td>
      <td align="center">Qinlin mountains</td>
      <td align="center">QL</td>
      <td align="center">5</td>
      <td align="center">26</td>
      <td align="center">5</td>
      <td align="center">1</td>
      <td align="center">0.00318</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td align="center">Shenlongjia mountains</td>
      <td align="center">HB</td>
      <td align="center">5</td>
      <td align="center">33</td>
      <td align="center">5</td>
      <td align="center">1</td>
      <td align="center">0.00338</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td align="center">Minshan mountains</td>
      <td align="center">BC</td>
      <td align="center">7</td>
      <td align="center">28</td>
      <td align="center">7</td>
      <td align="center">1</td>
      <td align="center">0.00298</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td align="center">Wuxia mountains</td>
      <td align="center">YA</td>
      <td align="center">8</td>
      <td align="center">7</td>
      <td align="center">34</td>
      <td align="center">0.964</td>
      <td align="center">0.00355</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center">Northern</td>
      <td align="center">Gongga mountains</td>
      <td align="center">MK</td>
      <td align="center">14</td>
      <td align="center">45</td>
      <td align="center">10</td>
      <td align="center">0.923</td>
      <td align="center">0.00297</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center">subregion</td>
      <td align="center">Ningjing mountains</td>
      <td align="center">CD</td>
      <td align="center">7</td>
      <td align="center">55</td>
      <td align="center">6</td>
      <td align="center">0.952</td>
      <td align="center">0.00451</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td align="center">North Shaluli mountains</td>
      <td align="center">RT</td>
      <td align="center">2</td>
      <td align="center">20</td>
      <td align="center">2</td>
      <td align="center">1</td>
      <td align="center">0.00496</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitochondrial DNA amplification and sequencing</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA was extracted from tissue samples using the DNeasy Tissue kit (QIAGEN). The cytochrome 
   <span class="italic">b </span>(cyt-
   <span class="italic">b</span>), cytochrome 
   <span class="italic">c </span>oxidase subunit I and II (COI and COII), NADH dehydrogenase subunit 2 and 6 (ND
   <sub>2 </sub>and ND
   <sub>6</sub>), ATP synthetase subunit 8 (ATP
   <sub>8</sub>) and control region (CR) genes were amplified via the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B39" href="#B39">39</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>]. The same primers were used for amplification and sequencing reactions. Methods of purification and sequencing were as described in Qu et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>]. All sequences are accessible at GenBank (Accession nos: 
   <span ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="HM601543" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">HM601543</span>-
   <span ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="602022" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">602022</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microsatellite genotyping</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PCR amplifications were achieved in a 10 ul reaction volume containing 10-30 ng DNA, 0.5 U Taq DNA polymerase, 0.2 nmol dNTPs, 1-3 nmol MgCl
   <sub>2 </sub>and 5 pmol primers. These loci were originally developed for the following passerine species: 
   <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica </span>(HrU
   <sub>5</sub>-A) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B46" href="#B46">46</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Loxia scotica </span>(LOX
   <sub>1</sub>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B47" href="#B47">47</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Catharus ustulatus </span>(Cum
   <sub>02</sub>, Cum
   <sub>10</sub>, Cum
   <sub>28 </sub>and Cum
   <sub>32</sub>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B48" href="#B48">48</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Poecile atricapillus </span>(Pat
   <sub>43</sub>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B49" href="#B49">49</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopus occipitalis </span>(Pocc
   <sub>6 </sub>and Pocc
   <sub>8</sub>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>] and 
   <span class="italic">Dendroica petechia </span>(Dpu
   <sub>16</sub>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B51" href="#B51">51</a>]. Original PCR conditions were optimized with variable MgCl
   <sub>2</sub>, template DNA concentrations and annealing temperatures. Microsatellites were amplified with fluorescently labelled forward primers (FAM and HEX dyes). Fragment lengths were analyzed with the internal size marker GENESCAN-500 ROX (Applied Biosystems), and scored with GENEMARKER 3.7 (SoftGenetics).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic polymorphism</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For mitochondrial data, we calculated the number of segregating sites, haplotype diversity and nucleotide diversity for each population and all populations combined using DnaSP 4.0 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B52" href="#B52">52</a>]. McDonald &amp; Kreitman's [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>] test was used to examine the selective neutrality of the mitochondrial DNA protein-coding fragments. Two additional neutrality tests, Fu's 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>S </sub>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B54" href="#B54">54</a>] and Fu &amp; Li's [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]
   <span class="italic">D </span>were used to detect departures from the mutation-drift equilibrium that would be indicative of changes in historical demography and natural selection. All three tests were implemented in DnaSP.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For microsatellite data, parameters such as the number of alleles per locus (
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>A</sub>), average allelic richness (
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>R</sub>), observed heterozygosity (
   <span class="italic">H</span>
   <sub>O</sub>), heterozygosity expected from the Hardy-Weinberg assumption (
   <span class="italic">H</span>
   <sub>E</sub>) and exact tests of linkage disequilibrium (LD) between pairs of loci for each population were calculated with ARLEQUIN 3.5 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B56" href="#B56">56</a>] and FSTAT 2.9.4 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B57" href="#B57">57</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogeography and population structure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The maximum-likelihood algorithm implemented in PHYML 2.4.4 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B58" href="#B58">58</a>] was used to reconstruct phylogenetic relationships among mitochondrial haplotypes. Based on the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B59" href="#B59">59</a>], we used the model GTR+I+G as suggested by Modeltest 3.7 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">60</a>]. We set the proportion of invariant sites and the shape of Gamma distribution as 0.43 and 1.048, respectively (estimated by Modeltest). The base frequency and ratio of transition/transversion were optimized by the maximum-likelihood criterion in PHYML. Outgroups were the black-faced laughing thrush (
   <span class="italic">G. affinis</span>), exquisite laughing thrush (
   <span class="italic">G. formosus</span>) and streaked laughing thrush (
   <span class="italic">G. lineatus</span>), which are considered closely related to 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B61" href="#B61">61</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used two methods to identify genetically distinct groups among microsatellite genotypes. First, genetic relationships between individual samples were quantified using Nei's standard genetic distance in GENETIX 4.05 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>]. The resultant matrix was then converted into a dendrogram using the Neighbour-Joining algorithm [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">63</a>] provided with PHYLIP 3.5 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B64" href="#B64">64</a>] and graphically displayed with TREEVIEW 1.6 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>]. Second, we used STRUCTURE 2.3.2 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>] with a burn-in of 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">7 </span>and 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8 </span>iterations without prior population information and following the admixture model. We conducted ten replicate runs for each value of 
   <span class="italic">K </span>(most likely number of populations) from 1 to 10. The most likely 
   <span class="italic">K </span>was identified using the maximal values of Pr(
   <span class="italic">X</span>/
   <span class="italic">K</span>), typically used for STRUCTURE analysis [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>] and Δ
   <span class="italic">K </span>based on the rate of change in the posterior probability of data between successive 
   <span class="italic">K</span>-values [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B67" href="#B67">67</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape genetics and environmental variables correlation analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Suitable habitats for 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>were identified in order to investigate whether intraspecific lineages were separated by areas of unsuitable environmental conditions. The habitat-mapping model was developed in ARCGIS 9.0 (Environmental Systems Research Institute) using vegetation, topographic layers and the known distribution range of 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii</span>. Shrublands were identified as suitable vegetation types [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>]. We consider an area suitable if these vegetation types are intersected by suitable altitude distribution (2 000 to 4 000 m.a.s.l.). These constructed areas were then projected onto the current distribution of 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>to generate a map of suitable habitats. Gaps between patches of suitable habitat were considered habitat gaps. GENELAND 1.0.5 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>], a computer program in the R-PACKAGE [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>], was implemented to verify our definition of 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>populations and locate areas of genetic discontinuity. GENELAND used microsatellite genotype data together with geographic information (the locations from which individuals were sampled) to estimate population structure. Areas of genetic discontinuity were detected as geographic areas with low posterior probability of membership. Following the approach of Coulon et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">70</a>], we allowed 
   <span class="italic">K </span>to vary (from 1 to 10) and inferred the most probable 
   <span class="italic">K </span>using five replicate runs with 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">5 </span>Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) iterations. For these analyses the maximum rate of the Poisson process was fixed at 100 with no uncertainty in the spatial coordinates, and the maximum number of nuclei in the Poisson-Voronoi tessellation was fixed at 300. The Dirichlet model was used to estimate allele frequencies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, a distance-based redundancy analysis [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B72" href="#B72">72</a>] was used to examine whether environmental factors might explain genetic diversification among populations. In the case of mitochondrial data, we used ten locations as spatial units and the uncorrected p distance and pairwise Φ
   <sub>ST </sub>as the measures of genetic differentiation. In the case of microsatellite data, genetic distance was measured as the 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>ST </sub>and Nei's 
   <span class="italic">D</span>s. An array of predictor variables was grouped into six sets: (i) coordinate (latitude and longitude); (ii) vegetation (alpine steppe; Tibet alpine meadow &amp; shrublands; subalpine grassland &amp; shrublands; temperate grasslands &amp; shrublands and subtropical shrublands); (iii) subregion (southern; northern and eastern); (iv) elevation; (v) temperature (mean annual temperature; mean January temperature and mean July temperature); (vi) mean annual rainfall. All predictor variables except vegetation and subregion were continuous, therefore these were treated as categorical variables with two states; 1 if a sample was located in a given vegetation type or subregion, and 0 if it was located in another vegetation type or subregion. Thus, each vegetation type or subregion was regarded as a vector corresponding to five vegetation types and three subregions, respectively. Vegetation or subregion was analyzed as a set, i.e. these variables were combined in a single test.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental variables were taken from the WWF Terrestrial Ecoregion and WorldClimate (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclimate.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclimate.com</span>) databases. Subregions were defined according to Li [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]. In order to identify variables correlated with genetic distance, individual sets of predictor variables were analyzed with the marginal test in DISTLM 5.0 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B73" href="#B73">73</a>]. The 
   <span class="italic">P </span>values in these analyses were obtained using 9 999 simultaneous permutations of the rows and columns of the distance matrix. To examine which subset of predictor variables provided the best model explaining genetic differentiations among 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>populations, the forward selection procedure in the program DISTLM forward [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B74" href="#B74">74</a>] was performed on all sets of variables. The forward selection procedure consists of sequential tests, fitting each set of variables one at a time, conditional on the variables already included in the model. To examine whether the tested variables were correlated, output files also included information on the correlations among all pairs of explanatory variables. This provided a further check on potential multi-collinearity issue. As in the previous analysis, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>values were obtained using 9 999 permutations of the rows and columns of the multivariate residual matrix under the reduced model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Divergence time estimate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to overcome the limitations of conventional estimates of divergence time based on 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>ST </sub>values (e.g. estimation of divergence time assuming isolation without gene flow) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B75" href="#B75">75</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B77" href="#B77">77</a>], we employed a coalescent-based MCMC simulation to estimate the divergence times for the main mitochondrial lineages in the program IM [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B78" href="#B78">78</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B79" href="#B79">79</a>]. As recommended by Hey &amp; Nielsen [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B78" href="#B78">78</a>] we first performed multiple runs, with an increasing number of steps and using wide priors and heating schemes to ensure that the complete posterior distribution could be obtained. We finally performed four independent runs of 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8 </span>steps with a burn-in of 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">7 </span>steps and a linear heating scheme (g1 = 0.05). IM was run under the HKY substitution model (estimated by Modeltest 3.7). Convergence on stationary distributions was assessed by monitoring the similarity of posterior distributions from independent runs and by assessing the autocorrelation parameter values over these runs [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B80" href="#B80">80</a>]. The peaks of the resulting posterior distributions were taken as estimates of parameters [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B81" href="#B81">81</a>]. Credibility intervals were recorded as the 90% highest posterior density (HPD). Because no fossil data were available to calibrate the mutation rate, we assumed a conventional molecular clock for the avian mitochondrial DNA cytochrome 
   <span class="italic">b </span>gene (1 × 10
   <span class="sup">-8 </span>per site per year) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B82" href="#B82">82</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B83" href="#B83">83</a>]. The mutation rate was modulated by multiplying the ratio of the average distance for the combined sequences versus that for cyt 
   <span class="italic">b </span>alone to deduce the mutation rate for all fragments combined. We used this modified mutation rate to convert the divergence time estimate into calendar years.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For microsatellite data, timing of population splits was estimated using the IMa2 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B81" href="#B81">81</a>] with burn-ins of 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">7 </span>and 5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8 </span>iterations under the SSM model with initial short runs to provide prior estimates. A geometric heating scheme was employed and the program run four times with different random seed numbers to ensure convergence of parameter estimates. The IMa2 output included mean values of the parameters for two sets after the burn-in period, representing the first and second half of the total generations of the post burn-in run. We ran our analyses until the peak location set values were equal for both sets. This, along with the high effective sample size and low autocorrelation estimate, suggested the Markov chains reached convergence after a sufficiently long burn-in period and were sampled from the appropriate likelihood space. A generation time of 1 year [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>] and a mutation rate of 10
   <span class="sup">-5 </span>to 10
   <span class="sup">-4 </span>per generation for birds [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B84" href="#B84">84</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B89" href="#B89">89</a>] were used to convert divergence time into calendar years. Given the uncertainty in mutation rates, the resultant estimates should be interpreted with caution.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical biogeography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine whether populations remained isolated in individual habitats (multiple refugia), or merged into a single gene pool (single refugium) during down-slope dispersal, we used coalescent simulations in MESQUITE 2.5 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B90" href="#B90">90</a>] to test three phylogeographic models of diversification. The first hypothesis posited that all populations derive from a single source population (single-refugium hypothesis). The second hypothesis postulated that populations were isolated into southern and north-eastern refugia (two-refugia hypothesis). The geographic structure was inferred from mitochondrial data. A third, three-refugia hypothesis, which was consistent with three-subregion division and inferred from microsatellite data (see RESULTS), predicted that populations derive from three independent refugia.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For coalescent simulations, we first estimated 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e </sub>for individual populations of 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>using values for θ calculated in MIGRATE 2.3.2 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B91" href="#B91">91</a>] under the following parameters: 10 short chains (500 trees used out of 10 000 sampled) and three long chains (5 000 trees used out of 100 000 sampled) with four adaptive heating chains (1, 3, 5 and 7). Maximum-likelihood estimates (MLE) were calculated under a stepping-stone model four times to ensure convergence upon similar values for θ. We converted θ to 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e </sub>using the equation for maternally inherited mitochondrial data θ = 2 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e</sub>μ, using same mutation rate in divergence time estimate. The estimates of 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e </sub>for all populations were summed to calculate Total 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e </sub>and scaled the branch widths of our hypothesized population trees using the proportion of Total 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e </sub>that each population comprised. The 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e </sub>
   </span>of the refugial population was constrained to a size proportional to the relative 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e </sub>
   </span>of the population sampled from the sites of the putative refugia. Thus, if samples from the site of the putative refugium had an effective population size of one-third that of the Total 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e</sub>, we would constrain the population size in the simulation prior to population expansion to one-third the total 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e</sub>. During coalescent simulations, both Total 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <sub>e </sub>and lower and upper bounds of the 95% CI for 
   <span class="italic">N
    <sub>e </sub>
   </span>were used as model parameters in order to encompass a wide range of potential 
   <span class="italic">N</span>e values The divergence time specified for each model corresponded to the approximate age estimated using IM and IMa2 as follows: 0.1 mya for the southern and north-eastern populations (two-refugia model), 0.015 mya for northern and eastern populations (three-refugia model). In the single refugium model, we specified divergence time as 0, which assumed a panmixia population derived from a single refugium. For converting coalescent time (in generations) to absolute time, we assumed a generation length of 1 year [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amount of discordance between a gene tree and population model was measured by 
   <span class="italic">S</span>, the minimum number of sorting events required to produce the genealogy within a given model of divergence [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B92" href="#B92">92</a>]. The 
   <span class="italic">S </span>value is a measure of the number of parsimony steps in characters for a reconstructed gene tree, such that more discordance between the population model and gene tree leads to a higher 
   <span class="italic">S </span>value. To obtain a distribution of 
   <span class="italic">S </span>values, 10 000 gene trees were simulated, constrained within each model of population divergence under a neutral coalescent process, and the amount of discordance between the simulated genealogy and population model was determined. Overall, this produced a null distribution of 10 000 
   <span class="italic">S </span>values based on reconstructed genealogy for each model of population divergence. The 
   <span class="italic">S </span>value for observed genealogy was calculated and compared to the distributions of 
   <span class="italic">S </span>values from coalescent simulations to determine whether the observed genealogy could have been generated under a given model.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also examined the ancestral area distributions for deeper nodes of the mitochondrial haplotype phylogeny with an event-based method in DIVA 1.1 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B93" href="#B93">93</a>]. Each individual in the phylogeographic analysis was coded to one of the ten biogeographic sectors. We used an equal likelihood for the rate of change among sectors for estimating ancestral areas because we had no information on the dispersal rate among sectors.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical demography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The past population dynamics of mitochondrial lineages of 
   <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>were estimated using the Bayesian skyline plot method implemented in BEAST 1.4.6 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B94" href="#B94">94</a>]. This approach incorporates uncertainty in the genealogy using MCMC integration under a coalescent model, in which the timing of dates provides information about effective population sizes through time. Chains were run for 100 million generations, and the first 10% of which were discarded as 'burn-in'. The substitution model was selected according the result of Modeltest 3.7. We applied 10 grouped coalescent intervals and constant growth rate for the skyline model. The same mutation rate in divergence time estimate was used. Pilot analyses showed that the ucld.stdev parameters were close to zero, thus a strict clock model was employed. Demographic history through time was reconstructed using Tracer 1.4 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B95" href="#B95">95</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The exponential growth rate (
   <span class="italic">g</span>) was also estimated for each mitochondrial lineage by FLUCTUATE 1.4 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B96" href="#B96">96</a>]. FLUCTUATE was initiated with a Watterson [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B97" href="#B97">97</a>] estimate of theta (θ) and a random topology, performing 10 short chains, sampled every 20 genealogies for 200 steps, and two long chains, sampled every 20 genealogies for 20 000 steps. FLUCTUATE analyses were repeated five times and the mean and standard deviation of 
   <span class="italic">g </span>calculated from the results of these separate runs. Because this genealogical method yields estimates of 
   <span class="italic">g </span>with an upward bias [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B96" href="#B96">96</a>], we corrected 
   <span class="italic">g </span>values following the conservative approach of Lessa et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B98" href="#B98">98</a>] and only considered the 
   <span class="italic">g </span>value indicative of population growth when 
   <span class="italic">g </span>&gt; 3 SD (
   <span class="italic">g</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
