<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic admixture among intraspecific lineages</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the deep phylogeographic partitions found in other sky island species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>], we only found a shallow phylogeographic division in 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii</span>. This is consistent with genetic admixture among lineages occurring during glacial periods. The two partially sympatric mitochondrial lineages show shared ancestry, and microsatellite data indicate gene flow among the three subregional populations. Furthermore, GENECLASS identified a considerable proportion of admixed individuals, most of which were assigned to the geographically intermediate populations MK, YA and BC. Interestingly, despite the relatively high degree of genetic admixture, these locations were also identified as the potential refugia that most likely defined the boundary of each genetic lineage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on these observations, it is probable that isolated populations of 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>periodically expanded to lower elevation where they mixed. Thus, the three intraspecific lineages likely established a contact zone along their boundaries. Because these lineages are geographically relatively close and are likely to have experienced repeated glacial cycles, this has resulted in multiple episodes of genetic admixture. Over time, this could have defined a centre of gene flow, such as populations YA, MK and BC. This process might cause the mixing of genetic lineages thereby obscuring the pattern of genetic variation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B42" href="#B42">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, the rather large degree of genetic separation among lineages indicates that these have been isolated from each other for a relatively long period. Although the southern and north-eastern mitochondrial lineages are intermixed, no haplotypes are shared between them. This lack of sharing suggests that the two lineages are at an intermediate stage of divergence along the continuum from complete panmixia to paraphyly and ultimately to reciprocal monophyly [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B106" href="#B106">106</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B107" href="#B107">107</a>]. In contrast, differences in microsatellite allele frequencies among the three lineages are more distinct. The discrepancy between these two markers may indicate that admixture among these lineages is relatively ancient, and hence, that the mixing signature is relatively weak.
 </p>
</sec>
