<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape genetics and environmental variables correlation analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Suitable habitats for 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>were identified in order to investigate whether intraspecific lineages were separated by areas of unsuitable environmental conditions. The habitat-mapping model was developed in ARCGIS 9.0 (Environmental Systems Research Institute) using vegetation, topographic layers and the known distribution range of 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii</span>. Shrublands were identified as suitable vegetation types [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>]. We consider an area suitable if these vegetation types are intersected by suitable altitude distribution (2 000 to 4 000 m.a.s.l.). These constructed areas were then projected onto the current distribution of 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>to generate a map of suitable habitats. Gaps between patches of suitable habitat were considered habitat gaps. GENELAND 1.0.5 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>], a computer program in the R-PACKAGE [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>], was implemented to verify our definition of 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>populations and locate areas of genetic discontinuity. GENELAND used microsatellite genotype data together with geographic information (the locations from which individuals were sampled) to estimate population structure. Areas of genetic discontinuity were detected as geographic areas with low posterior probability of membership. Following the approach of Coulon et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">70</a>], we allowed 
  <span class="italic">K </span>to vary (from 1 to 10) and inferred the most probable 
  <span class="italic">K </span>using five replicate runs with 5 × 10
  <span class="sup">5 </span>Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) iterations. For these analyses the maximum rate of the Poisson process was fixed at 100 with no uncertainty in the spatial coordinates, and the maximum number of nuclei in the Poisson-Voronoi tessellation was fixed at 300. The Dirichlet model was used to estimate allele frequencies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, a distance-based redundancy analysis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B72" href="#B72">72</a>] was used to examine whether environmental factors might explain genetic diversification among populations. In the case of mitochondrial data, we used ten locations as spatial units and the uncorrected p distance and pairwise Φ
  <sub>ST </sub>as the measures of genetic differentiation. In the case of microsatellite data, genetic distance was measured as the 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST </sub>and Nei's 
  <span class="italic">D</span>s. An array of predictor variables was grouped into six sets: (i) coordinate (latitude and longitude); (ii) vegetation (alpine steppe; Tibet alpine meadow &amp; shrublands; subalpine grassland &amp; shrublands; temperate grasslands &amp; shrublands and subtropical shrublands); (iii) subregion (southern; northern and eastern); (iv) elevation; (v) temperature (mean annual temperature; mean January temperature and mean July temperature); (vi) mean annual rainfall. All predictor variables except vegetation and subregion were continuous, therefore these were treated as categorical variables with two states; 1 if a sample was located in a given vegetation type or subregion, and 0 if it was located in another vegetation type or subregion. Thus, each vegetation type or subregion was regarded as a vector corresponding to five vegetation types and three subregions, respectively. Vegetation or subregion was analyzed as a set, i.e. these variables were combined in a single test.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental variables were taken from the WWF Terrestrial Ecoregion and WorldClimate (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclimate.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclimate.com</span>) databases. Subregions were defined according to Li [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>]. In order to identify variables correlated with genetic distance, individual sets of predictor variables were analyzed with the marginal test in DISTLM 5.0 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B73" href="#B73">73</a>]. The 
  <span class="italic">P </span>values in these analyses were obtained using 9 999 simultaneous permutations of the rows and columns of the distance matrix. To examine which subset of predictor variables provided the best model explaining genetic differentiations among 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>populations, the forward selection procedure in the program DISTLM forward [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B74" href="#B74">74</a>] was performed on all sets of variables. The forward selection procedure consists of sequential tests, fitting each set of variables one at a time, conditional on the variables already included in the model. To examine whether the tested variables were correlated, output files also included information on the correlations among all pairs of explanatory variables. This provided a further check on potential multi-collinearity issue. As in the previous analysis, 
  <span class="italic">P </span>values were obtained using 9 999 permutations of the rows and columns of the multivariate residual matrix under the reduced model.
 </p>
</sec>
