<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pattern of distribution and biogeography</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographic complexity and environmental heterogeneity are likely to have shaped the genetic structure among 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>populations. Such a landscape effect is evident in the eastern Himalayan region. Although 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>has a rather restricted geographic distribution, mitochondrial data support the separation of a southern and a north-eastern lineage with incomplete gene sorting, while microsatellites indicate a clear subdivision into three lineages, a southern, a northern and an eastern. Despite intermixing of mitochondrial haplotypes, none of the haplotypes are geographically widespread. All shared haplotypes occur within the same subregional population. In this case, the steep mountains and deep valleys of the Kangding-Muli-Baoxin Divide, recognized as a geographic barrier by Zhang et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>] and Li [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B20" href="#B20">20</a>], appear to effectively have prevented gene flow among subregional populations. Across the entire sampling area, the correlation between phylogeographic pattern and subregion division is strong. Furthermore, our regression model reveals that the general pattern of subdivision could be attributed to geographic and environmental differentiations, e.g. subregion and vegetation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mountains, like sky islands, and are separated by areas of unsuitable habitats that act as barriers to gene flow [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B15" href="#B15">15</a>]. Species restricted to sky islands commonly have high levels of interpopulation genetic divergence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B15" href="#B15">15</a>]. In the eastern Himalayas, 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>is restricted to shrublands in the three subregions separated by deep valleys. The habitat-mapping model shows that these subregions or lineages are separated by areas where the environmental conditions are unsuitable for 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii</span>. Consistent with the expectation that these valleys prevent or restrict gene flow, each subregional population represents an evolutionary lineage. Thus, the contrast in environmental conditions at high and low elevations in the eastern Himalayas may have created a "sky island situation" for 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although many sky island species in other regions show high levels of isolation in clusters of mountains [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>], our data indicate that diversification of 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>has occurred on a broader geographic scale, eco-subregions. 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>is an alpine bird found between 2 000 and 4 000 m.a.s.l. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>]. This broad altitudinal range implies large ecological plasticity. Considering that most previously studied sky island species belong to less mobile groups such as beetles and plants, this difference in scale probably reflects the fact that historical processes of isolation are more easily reconstructed in species with less dispersal capability than in highly mobile species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B1" href="#B1">1</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While our study may demonstrate newly discovered sky island diversification in a previously unstudied region, sky islands also have the extra connotation that mountain ranges are equivalent ecologically and they share the same biogeographic history. Since three eco-subregions in the eastern Himalayas present different ecological systems, our result should be considered cautiously. Whether the eastern Himalayan region is a sky island situation ultimately depends on the ecology of the organisms under study. Further research on more organisms inhabiting this region, especial the same eco-climatic subregions is required to clarify this.</p>
</sec>
