<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogeography and population structure</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The maximum-likelihood algorithm implemented in PHYML 2.4.4 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B58" href="#B58">58</a>] was used to reconstruct phylogenetic relationships among mitochondrial haplotypes. Based on the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B59" href="#B59">59</a>], we used the model GTR+I+G as suggested by Modeltest 3.7 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">60</a>]. We set the proportion of invariant sites and the shape of Gamma distribution as 0.43 and 1.048, respectively (estimated by Modeltest). The base frequency and ratio of transition/transversion were optimized by the maximum-likelihood criterion in PHYML. Outgroups were the black-faced laughing thrush (
  <span class="italic">G. affinis</span>), exquisite laughing thrush (
  <span class="italic">G. formosus</span>) and streaked laughing thrush (
  <span class="italic">G. lineatus</span>), which are considered closely related to 
  <span class="italic">G. elliotii </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B61" href="#B61">61</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used two methods to identify genetically distinct groups among microsatellite genotypes. First, genetic relationships between individual samples were quantified using Nei's standard genetic distance in GENETIX 4.05 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>]. The resultant matrix was then converted into a dendrogram using the Neighbour-Joining algorithm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">63</a>] provided with PHYLIP 3.5 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B64" href="#B64">64</a>] and graphically displayed with TREEVIEW 1.6 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>]. Second, we used STRUCTURE 2.3.2 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>] with a burn-in of 5 × 10
  <span class="sup">7 </span>and 5 × 10
  <span class="sup">8 </span>iterations without prior population information and following the admixture model. We conducted ten replicate runs for each value of 
  <span class="italic">K </span>(most likely number of populations) from 1 to 10. The most likely 
  <span class="italic">K </span>was identified using the maximal values of Pr(
  <span class="italic">X</span>/
  <span class="italic">K</span>), typically used for STRUCTURE analysis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>] and Δ
  <span class="italic">K </span>based on the rate of change in the posterior probability of data between successive 
  <span class="italic">K</span>-values [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B67" href="#B67">67</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
