<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Economic and conservation impacts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The economic costs of agriculture associated with invasions are significant due to loss of productivity and resources spent on control efforts [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref014">14</a>]. Naylor [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref081">81</a>] estimated that the total cost of 
  <span class="italic">Pomacea canaliculata</span> (apple snail) invasion to Philippine rice agriculture in 1990 was US$ 425–1200 million. This estimate does not include impacts on ecosystems and human health. The economic loss due to 
  <span class="italic">Dreissena polymorpha</span> (zebra mussel) invasion in the United States was estimated to be US$ 3.1 billion between 1993–1999 for power plants and over US$ 5 billion when other sectors are considered [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref082">82</a>] and in Canada, impact was estimated at US$ 376,000 annually per generating station estimated in 1994 [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref082">82</a>]. In the United States, management authorities took nearly a decade and US$ 1 million to completely eradicate 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> from Florida [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref083">83</a>]; however, there are several recent reports of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> occurrence in this region despite all the efforts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The invasion of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> in India is a major problem, not only in semi-urban or peri-urban areas but also increasingly in rural areas. Agriculture, particularly in India with nearly 60% being rain-fed, has been a highly risky venture with extremities in monsoon coupled with other abiotic and biotic factors. Climate change is set to compound the daunting complex challenges already being faced by the farmers. Increasing temperature will have significant negative impact on crop yield [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref084">84</a>]. This along with land use and invasive species such as 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> will have even more impact on small-scale agriculture and horticulture. The invasion is particularly high during monsoon months (June to November) when most of the small-scale farmers grow vegetables and horticultural crops. We have found here that regions with high agriculture output in India also have high invasion risk. These regions include Kerala, coastal parts of Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh, Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra and Assam [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref085">85</a>]. The slow growth regions in terms of agriculture such as Bihar and parts of Uttar Pradesh are also very economically backward regions and highly dependent on monsoon for good yield. These regions are also highly vulnerable to invasion. Increased invasion by 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> under future climate in these regions will only worsen the agriculture situation in India, thus further marginalizing the small-farming community and adversely impacting local economies. 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> not yet invaded forested regions of India. The impact of snail invasion on native snail fauna is not known. Given the high endemism in land snails in India [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref086">86</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref087">87</a>], there is urgent need to study the impact on native biodiversity.
 </p>
</sec>
