<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the greatest threats to global biodiversity, agriculture, livelihoods, human and animal health, and forestry is invasive alien species [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref003">3</a>]. Invasive alien species affect not only the environment or ecology, but also the local economy [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref003">3</a>]. Ever-growing international trade, increased transportation and deliberate introductions have facilitated invasions at an unprecedented rate across the globe [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref005">5</a>]. Another factor that has great implications for biodiversity, environment and human health is climate change. Invasive alien species acting synergistically with climate change might be expected to have much larger impact on local ecosystem than either acting alone [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref006">6</a>]. It has been hypothesized that climate change will aggravate the impacts of “non-native/exotic/alien” species naturalization and subsequent invasion across communities and ecosystems in the new ranges, thus threatening native biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref007">7</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref015">15</a>] and human well-being [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref016">16</a>]. Identifying the probable future distribution of invasive alien species is of paramount importance for early detection, prioritization of regions for conservation and effective management of invasive species [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref017">17</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref018">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The giant African snail (
  <span class="italic">Achatina fulica</span> Férussac, 1821: Achatinidae) is a highly invasive terrestrial snail native to East Africa. According to the global invasive species database, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> is the second worst invasive alien species in the world. It has now invaded most parts of the world with particular impact in tropical and subtropical regions [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref019">19</a>]. It was introduced either accidentally along with agriculture or horticulture produce or deliberately as pets, or ornamental, medicinal or food resources [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref020">20</a>]. Given the very high density of this large pest, it is likely to have a great impact on the native biodiversity and ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref020">20</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> has been recognized as a major agricultural and garden pest [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref022">22</a>]. It is known to consume more than 50 species of native plants, agricultural and horticultural crops, modify habitats and outcompete native snails [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref023">23</a>]. The species reproduces rapidly under optimal field conditions and can reach high densities and biomass in a very short time [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref024">24</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref025">25</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> spreads the spores of pathogens of a variety of cultivated plants in the introduced range [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref026">26</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref029">29</a>]. It is also a vector of the rat lungworm, 
  <span class="italic">Angiostrongylus cantonensis</span>, which causes eosinophilic meningoencephalitis in humans [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref031">31</a>]. Apart from economic loss and human health issues caused by 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span>, they are also a general nuisance to people. According to Mead [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref026">26</a>], there are reports of car accidents due to cars skidding on crushed snails on roads.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pioneering British malacologist, William Henry Benson, brought a pair of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> to India from Mauritius, and handed them to a friend and neighbor before leaving the country. It was this friend who released the snails in his garden in Kolkata, eastern India [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref032">32</a>]. Later, in 1858, Benson reported that 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> had become well established in Kolkata [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref033">33</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref034">34</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> has been considered as a serious pest to small-scale agriculture, horticulture and home gardens [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref022">22</a>]. In India, the spread of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> was primarily mediated by humans. For example, a farmer has introduced it from Orissa to his farm in Araku valley in Andhra Pradesh in 1996 [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref035">35</a>]; a blacksmith was believed to have brought 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> as a pet from Kolkata to north Bihar some time during 60s [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref036">36</a>]. Since then it has invaded many parts of both the states. This could be the case for many other sites. The snail being large in size and attractive might have fascinated pet keepers and hence got transported to many parts of the country from Kolkata. By mid-20
  <span class="sup">th</span> century, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> attained serious pest status in India and caused severe damage to agricultural crops [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref037">37</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref039">39</a>]. Many studies in India have reported the impact of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> invasion on horticultural and agricultural crops; however, none have quantified the exact economic loss [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref040">40</a>]. In the late 1970s, this snail was reported to damage ornamental and vegetable crops in Bangalore [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref038">38</a>]. Since then, several reports have shown that 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> causes serious damage to variety of horticultural and agricultural crops viz., mulberry [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref041">41</a>], betel-vine, capsicum, areca, banana, tomato [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref042">42</a>], vanilla [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref039">39</a>] and vegetable crops such as potato, spinach, radish and tomato [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref043">43</a>]. Raut &amp; Ghose [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref025">25</a>] stated that nearly 90% plants cultivated in India were eaten by 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span>. The pest generally feeds on the succulent parts of the plants and damages the small and tender parts and seedlings completely. They feed not only on leaves but also on flowers, buds, tender shoots and fruits. Given the broad spectrum of food choice and increased precipitation in Southern India due to climate change, the invasion of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> might exacerbate the situation. At present, the range has extended through much of India, Nepal, Bhutan, Bangladesh and Sri Lanka [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref044">44</a>]. A recent genetic study showed that all 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> now occurring throughout South Asia, Southeast Asia and the Pacific Region are derived from a single haplotype [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref045">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we assess the potential distribution of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> under present and future climate change scenarios using ecological niche modeling tools. The ecological niche models (ENM) integrate species occurrence records with climatic and other environmental variables and generate maps of species’ potential distribution [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref046">46</a>]. Of late, the ENM approach is being increasingly used to map potential distributions of invasive species under present and future climate change scenarios [
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref047">47</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0143724.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0143724.ref051">51</a>]. In this study, we used maximum entropy modeling (MaxEnt) to predict the invasion potential of the introduced invasive snail species, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> in India and develop a risk map of areas likely to be invaded in the future, which can be used for prioritization and effective management of this species. The specific objectives of this paper were (1) to generate a map of the potential present distribution of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span> in India, (2) to assess the impact of climate change on the potential invasion patterns and (3) to identify bioclimatic factors that contribute to invasion of 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fulica</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
