<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Response of sea-ice algae to habitat changes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assuming unchanged nutrient availability, Arctic sympagic gross primary production (GPP) in first-year ice is projected to overall increase in the future (i.e., from 2.47 to 4.02 Tg C y
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, that is, 63%; 
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a> and table S2), indicating an increased uptake of carbon dioxide and thus an overall increase of the carbon biological pump. However, the response of the biological community to quasi-linear latitudinal changes in sea-ice physical drivers of 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> is markedly nonlinear.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Latitudinal changes in sea-ice annual GPP.</div>
   <p>The percentage changes in the magnitude of sea-ice GPP are shown as a function of latitude and differences in the timing of the bloom peak. This indicator is the difference between the RCP8.5 scenario (2061–2100) and the historical simulations (1961–2005), scaled by the historical value. (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Percentage change in annual sea-ice GPP per unit area (red bubbles), i.e., integrated temporally along the ice season length. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Percentage change in annual sea-ice GPP integrated both temporally along the ice season length and spatially over the ice extent of each simulation period (yellow bubbles). The area of the bubbles is proportional to the percentage change.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav4830-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite similar latitudinal advances in projected breakup dates, the changes in timing of sea-ice algal blooms are different and grouped into two main clusters. Below 66°N, where the breakup date is projected to occur about 25 days earlier in the future climate (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>), the bloom peak develops between 45 and 70 days earlier than in the historical climate (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3A</a>). Above 66°N, the advance of the algal bloom is more in line with the advancing of the breakup dates (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>), i.e., between 15 and 40 days earlier in the future projections (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3A</a>). The number of clusters increases to three when we factor in the relative changes in GPP. For these clusters, low-latitude seasonal sea ice is expected to be up to 150% more productive (i.e., increasing from 0.48 to 1.20 g C m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> y
  <span class="sup">−1</span> at 65°N). Smaller and negative variations are expected between 68°N and 74°N (i.e., between −25 and 11% relative change), while the largest increase is expected above 74°N, with up to more than 550% increase in GPP at 77°N (i.e., from 0.05 to 0.33 g C m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> y
  <span class="sup">−1</span>; 
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3A</a> and table S2).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With inclusion of the projected latitudinal changes in ice extent (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>), the relative increase in GPP per unit area predicted below 74°N diminishes because of the large loss of seasonal sea ice, while above 74°N, it becomes more important because of first-year ice largely expanding at the expense of multiyear ice (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3B</a> and table S2). The combination of area-specific production increase and first-year ice expansion is expected to give rise to a sea-ice habitat that is more than 2500% more productive than in the recent climate for algae located northward of 80°N (i.e., from 7.48 to 199.48 Gg C y
  <span class="sup">−1</span> at 83°N). Thus, the anticipated increase in first-year ice algal production would make this region productively equivalent to what is currently simulated 10° more to the south (table S2), which is a non-negligible change. In light of the CMIP5 model bias in sea-ice extent (particularly large between 70°N and 78°N; 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>), we anticipate the relative increase in GPP found at these latitudes (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3B</a>) to be even underestimated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We searched for mechanisms linking the changes in physical drivers to the phenological differences illustrated in 
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>. We specifically investigated alterations in the timing of the peak bloom, driven by latitudinal variation in light availability. The available light in turn is a function of sea-ice and snow thicknesses, length of the biological time window, and photoperiod. We present here one latitude example for each cluster: 58°N to 66°N (lower panels), 66°N to 74°N (mid panels), and 74°N to 84°N (upper panels), representing respectively low-, mid-, and high-latitude pan-Arctic sea-ice ecosystems for historical (left) and RCP8.5 (right) scenario simulations (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Drivers and mechanisms of sea-ice algal phenology.</div>
   <p>Simulation results at three representative latitudes (61°N, 71°N, and 81°N) for the historical period (1961–2005, left) and RCP8.5 scenario (2061–2100, right), showing sea-ice season length, sea-ice/snow thickness (black), downward solar radiation [from the ERA-Interim climatology (
    <a rid="R56" ref-type="bibr" href="#R56">
     <span class="italic">56</span>
    </a>), used as the reference between historical climate scenario; red], algal chlorophyll anomaly (green), nonpermeable sea ice (gray), permeable and potentially productive sea ice [color gradient from pale blue to green is proportional to normalized GPP (0 to 1), with pale blue representing 0 and green representing 1] Dotted lines highlight changes in snow thickness (black) and biological time window (green). The chlorophyll anomaly (green) is an indicator of algal bloom phenology (
    <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
     <span class="italic">22</span>
    </a>) and is computed as the difference between the concentration and its SD over the sea-ice season (fig. S1).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav4830-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first cluster (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 61°N) is typical of regions such as the Bering Sea, the Sea of Okhotsk, the Hudson Bay, or the land-fast ice conditions found in Greenland fjords (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>) and the Baltic Sea (
  <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
   <span class="italic">42</span>
  </a>). According to our modeling results, below the Arctic Circle, sea ice is projected to become much thinner and entirely permeable. The thinner snow depth, expected to be less than 0.1 m, leads to a long productive season, with a large and sharp asymmetrical bloom that is characteristic of little light limitation (see also fig. S1C).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second cluster (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 71°N) includes basins such as the Beaufort Sea and the Mackenzie shelf in the Canadian Arctic (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>), the Chukchi Sea, the Baffin Bay, and the Kara Sea, where sea-ice production under current climate conditions is limited by thick ice and snow despite the favorable photoperiod. The latitudes of up to 74°N are currently characterized by one of the largest extents of first-year ice (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>), and these areas are projected to double by the end of the century (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>). In the RCP8.5 scenario simulation at 71°N, both sea ice and snow are expected to thin largely, although not enough to allow sufficient growth within the narrower biological time window due to earlier breakups. The resulting magnitude of sea-ice production is expected to mimic current climate conditions, but the phenology is nonetheless altered toward earlier blooms (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a> and fig. S1B).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Barents Sea deserves specific mention because it is mostly located within this cluster’s range of latitudes, but it is characterized by sea-ice conditions more similar to that of the first cluster (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 61°N). In the Barents Sea, we expect an increase in GPP similar to that seen at the lowest latitudes (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3A</a>) because of significant sea ice and snow thinning (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 61°N). However, we expect this to be modulated by the sharper photoperiod typical of these latitudes. This might reduce the length of the ice algal growing season in a way that is similar to the second cluster (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 71°N).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third cluster (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 81°N) is typical of first-year ice found in the high Arctic. An example of this cluster is the offshore Lincoln Sea north of Greenland. The area is currently characterized by first-year ice that is generally less productive than other shelf regions, with algal biomass comparable to multiyear ice conditions (
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>). At these high latitudes, sea-ice blooms are limited by low brine permeability and thick ice and snow. The climate model projections indicate a marked thinning of the sea ice to levels similar to the current-day 71°N cluster (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>). At these highest latitudes, the key factor responsible for the largest relative increase in GPP in first-year ice (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>) is the advance of the sea-ice season toward a more favorable photoperiod, which would give rise to blooms that are expected to be larger than in the adjacent southern cluster (see also fig. S1A).
 </p>
</sec>
