<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dealing with uncertainties and the impacts on the Arctic marine food web</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In spite of wide variability, the projections of the climate models consistently show that the thinning and retreat of Arctic sea ice will continue throughout this century, although at different paces in different scenarios (
   <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
    <span class="italic">3</span>
   </a>). Despite the models’ limitations (
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
    <span class="italic">33</span>
   </a>), the proposed statistical approach allowed us to extract reliable descriptors of current sea-ice conditions from coarse resolution climate models (
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>), which were used to provide a quantitative description of the impact of future sea-ice projections on the phenology and magnitude of sea-ice GPP (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Figs. 3 and 4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of 2° latitudinal bands, driven by the coarseness of climate model data, limits our ability to resolve the exact geographic boundaries of the sea-ice algal response. Our statistical methodology to include daily variability as a way to increase climate model skills in reproducing the seasonal patterns of sea-ice drivers cannot overcome the reduced regional variability, as indicated by the narrower spread of the model ensemble percentiles in 
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>. This can only be achieved with models at higher spatial resolution and more detailed sea-ice physical processes. We acknowledge the potential compromises that this approach presents with regard to ignoring variability in the local climatic conditions for the different sea-ice regions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anticipated phenological changes in GPP in a warmer Arctic indicate an overall early shift at all latitudes but large heterogeneity in the combination of bloom timing and intensity (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). These findings stress the nonlinearity of the response of the biological community to quasi-linear latitudinal changes in physical drivers, highlighting the complexity of the sympagic system. Important trade-offs are at play below 74°N; the expected increases in production are limited by the diminished seasonal areas, while blooms in areas with expanding first-year ice are limited by narrow growth windows. These are also the latitudes currently characterized by most of the coastal Arctic sea ice and where the terrestrial inputs of nutrients are most relevant.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How can we incorporate the observational and climate model uncertainties in a more comprehensive overview of the potential impacts on the Arctic marine food web? The hybrid numerical model can also provide insights on the spread of algal response to a range of uncertain factors. We focused on the role of the unconstrained changes in future nutrient distributions (
   <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
    <span class="italic">6</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>) and the wide variability of climate model projections of sea-ice season duration and snow depth (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2, A, B, and G</a>) by considering more extreme values.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is known that the final algal biomass is also determined by winter nutrient availability in the ocean (
   <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
    <span class="italic">10</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
    <span class="italic">14</span>
   </a>). The available measurements of winter dissolved silicate in the Arctic Ocean point to great heterogeneity among latitudinal bands (
   <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
    <span class="italic">44</span>
   </a>). The effects of this latitudinal variation of nutrients on sea-ice production have been tested with a sensitivity analysis to the 10th and 90th percentiles and comparison with the median value (
   <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a> and table S3), which was used in the presented standard simulations of 
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>. Overall, the different ranges of nutrients give values of sea-ice GPP and Chlorophyll-a (Chl-a) falling within the reported ranges in the Arctic Ocean (tables S2 and S3) (
   <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">
    <span class="italic">45</span>
   </a>), although within their lower limits. This is due to the fact that our results are representative of wide latitudinal bands, thus flattening the influence of possible hot spots of biological production that can be found in the literature. Little nutrient variability is currently observed below 66°N, and this has a negligible effect on current and projected sea-ice GPP (
   <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, 61°N; nutrient values are given in the legend). The largest observed nutrient heterogeneity is found between 66°N and 74°N (
   <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, 71°N), which is an indication of the diversity of oceanic and coastal conditions at this latitudinal band. The simulated algal biomass is directly proportional to nutrient availability (
   <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
    <span class="italic">14</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
    <span class="italic">24</span>
   </a>), which is an expected response given that the vernal development of sea-ice algae occurs when all nutrient replenishing mechanisms are at their optimal conditions. Above 74°N, the observed spread in nutrient distribution is between the one found in two other cases and has an expected intermediate effect on the resulted GPP (
   <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, 81°N).
  </p>
  <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Changes in GPP associated with nutrient heterogeneity along latitudinal bands.</div>
    <p>Simulation results at three representative latitudes (61°N, 71°N, and 81°N) for the historical period (1961–2005) and RCP8.5 scenario (2061–2100), showing sea-ice GPP under different levels of availability of dissolved silicate according to the calculated 10th, 50th, and 90th percentiles of measured winter silicates at a depth of 10 m between 1948 and 2000, retrieved from the Hydrochemical Atlas of the Arctic Ocean (
     <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
      <span class="italic">44</span>
     </a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav4830-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The presence of local upwelling and nutrient pulses generated by coastal features are likely to further enhance the productivity of the sea ice. South of the Arctic Circle, these events will be nevertheless confined to the strongly reduced areas of seasonal sea ice (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>), while to the north, the compensation between areal expansion and early breakup would eventually maintain the current conditions. Given the wide spread of the tested nutrient concentrations, opposite speculations can be made, considering the projected enhancement in stratification that would result in lower or suppressed levels of nutrients (
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>) and thus reduced sea-ice primary production.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This uncertainty needs to be combined with the spread of the climate models and their limitations in deriving robust estimates of the projected trends in sea-ice seasonality (
   <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
    <span class="italic">46</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">
    <span class="italic">48</span>
   </a>). In particular, CMIP5 models fail to capture the recent steepening trend in sea-ice extent (
   <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
    <span class="italic">46</span>
   </a>), and the large spread has been linked to the model’s mean sea-ice thickness of multiyear ice, which is difficult to constrain given the limited observations (
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">
    <span class="italic">48</span>
   </a>). Although this issue may not be as relevant for first-year ice projections—which are the focus of our study—we need to consider the possibility that, even within the chosen most pessimistic scenario (i.e., the RCP8.5), the ensemble medians would be too conservative.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More extreme scenarios can be assessed by considering the ensemble means of the single model 10th and 90th percentiles, which are shown in 
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6, A to D</a> for a selected set of sea-ice drivers (see table S3 for a complete overview). Two extreme cases have been selected: a model realization characterized by the shortest sea-ice seasons along all latitudes (warm extreme; see Materials and Methods for details) and a drastic reduction to bare ice conditions (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a>). The latter case aims to analyze the impact that uncertainties associated with the modeled snow depth data (
   <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">
    <span class="italic">49</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">
    <span class="italic">50</span>
   </a>) may have on algal phenology and production. The results give a quantitative overview of the anticipated shifts in the algal bloom features as the projected sea-ice season shortens with the scenarios. While the bloom peak under current sea-ice conditions is evenly distributed across latitudes (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6E</a>, circles), in the warm extreme case, it shows a rather linear response to shorter ice seasons (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6E</a>, diamonds), as envisaged in conceptual models (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>). The higher latitudes will have more pronounced, earlier blooms as the ice season becomes dramatically shorter and algal production in an extremely warm climate is ultimately constrained by the duration of the ice season at all latitudes. In the scenario driven by ensemble medians (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6E</a>, stars), ice algal phenology shows nonlinear interactions between sea-ice conditions and algal growth (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Figs. 3 and 4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This response is sensitive to the snow depth simulated by climate models, as indicated in the scenario experiment where the snow-covered surface is forced with prescribed bare ice; the bloom would advance by at least 50 days at all latitudes (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6E</a>, squares and fig. S3). We notice that the GPP of the high latitude clusters identified in 
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a> would be considerably larger (fig. S3). The smallest differences would be expected at the lowest latitudes, since there is a comparable decrease of maximum snow depth (&lt;0.1 m) in the RCP8.5 snow-covered scenario (
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 61°N, right panel). At the mid-latitudes, the little increase seen for the snow-covered RCP8.5 scenario (
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 71°N, right panel) would be replaced by a more intense increase because of the snow removal.
  </p>
  <div id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Uncertainties in the future projections of sea-ice drivers and simulated responses of algal phenology.</div>
    <p>Spread of the sea-ice driver projections and extreme cases for (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) ice season duration, (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) maximum sea-ice thickness, (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) maximum snow depth, (
     <span class="bold">D</span>) minimum near-surface air temperature. The lines are the ensemble means of empirical density distribution medians (50th percentile as in 
     <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>) for the RCP8.5 scenario (2061–2100) simulations. The shaded areas indicate the interval between the ensemble means of the 10th and 90th percentiles from the same distributions. The purple lines show the sea-ice drivers derived from the extreme warm scenario. The bare ice scenario is identical to the ensemble mean except for the snow depth set to zero [gray line in (C)]. (
     <span class="bold">E</span>) The resulting ice algae phenology, expressed as the day of bloom peak (
     <span class="italic">y</span> axis) under different scenarios (historical, ensemble RCP8.5, ensemble RCP8.5 for bare ice experiment, and RCP8.5 of the warmest extreme among models) and as a function of sea-ice season duration (
     <span class="italic">x</span> axis) for all the simulations and latitudinal bands.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav4830-F6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results, albeit constrained by the uncertainties discussed above, offer quantitative support to other paradigms linked to the loss of less-productive multiyear ice and the mismatch between the timing of primary and secondary production (
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
    <span class="italic">19</span>
   </a>). Our analysis indicates a doubling of first-year ice at the expense of multiyear ice at higher latitudes (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>). The notable increase of annual production in first-year ice (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>) would make the Arctic sea ice at these latitudes a more productive system (
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, 81°N, right panel). At the same time, observations from the central Arctic (
   <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
    <span class="italic">43</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">
    <span class="italic">51</span>
   </a>) suggest that thick ice may in fact be already more productive than initially thought; therefore, the projected thinner and more permeable multiyear ice might enhance sea-ice production even further.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the seasonal timing of the sea-ice algal bloom is critical to the successful reproduction of copepod grazers, the timing of the phytoplankton bloom is critical to the survival of copepod offspring (
   <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">
    <span class="italic">52</span>
   </a>). Disruption of the seasonality of the algal blooms by the sea-ice changes analyzed here (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Figs. 2</a> and 
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">6E</a>) has already created mismatches for the timing of zooplankton production, which has consequences for higher trophic levels (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">
    <span class="italic">51</span>
   </a>). These copepods are highly adapted to feed on ice algae, and their overwintering survival is phenologically synchronized with the availability of this food source. We have shown here that earlier breakups, associated with altered photoperiods and thinner sea ice and snow, can shorten the length of the biological time window at mid-latitudes, thus setting an upper limit for ice algal production, which is not the case at low and high latitudes (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Figs. 3</a> and 
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">4</a>). This might affect timing and amplitude of zooplankton production, which in turn might affect their main predator, Arctic cod, up to the top predators at the highest trophic levels. Because of the diverse latitudinal response of sea-ice algae (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>) to changes in climatic drivers (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>), we confirm the possibility of phenological uncoupling with secondary and tertiary consumers as described by Post (
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recent shifting paradigm toward a high level of wintering activity of plankton populations (
   <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">
    <span class="italic">53</span>
   </a>) also suggests that we should revisit our way of considering the winter Arctic marine ecosystem. The projected increase and advanced sea-ice GPP found in our simulations (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>) may also be an earlier potential pulse of energy for the active winter plankton communities in the low latitudes of the Arctic, although the large reduction in first-year ice extent would likely limit this effect.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the Arctic marine food web is short, poorly diverse, and seasonally driven by limited pulses of energy, the projected latitudinal changes in ice algal phenology have the potential of trophic cascades and phenological shifts at higher trophic levels. The phenological synchrony across trophic levels is expected to be driven by the pace of advancing sea-ice breakups (
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>) and consequent shift in algal bloom timing (this study). Thus, as supported by our results in 
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>, we might expect the strongest phenological cascades (i.e., shifts in timing) at the lowest latitudes where algal blooms are projected to occur significantly earlier, while the largest trophic cascades (i.e., changes in abundance at adjacent trophic levels) at the highest latitudes where the largest relative increase in biomass is projected.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea ice is inhabited also by other algal groups besides the dominant pennate diatoms (
   <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
    <span class="italic">40</span>
   </a>). We thus may expect the potential development of new acclimation and/or adaptation patterns or the shift in dominance of other competitive algal groups in a warmer Arctic. The modeling of these ecological dynamics would require an increase in model complexity beyond that of the present study, which was constrained by the current limited knowledge on the ecological and physiological traits of other algal groups (
   <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
    <span class="italic">39</span>
   </a>). To resolve the local features driving algal changes, we urgently need organized multidisciplinary studies of sea-ice physics, biogeochemistry, and associated biota on multiple temporal and spatial scales to achieve the proper level of details that models would need to make reliable future projections of algal phenological and trophic changes at those scales.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
