<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea-ice algae form a large fraction of sea-ice (sympagic) biomass (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). Before the onset of the seasonal phytoplankton bloom, sea ice provides critical habitat for marine algae and the upper trophic levels for whom sea-ice algae are their sole food-source during this period. Together with sub-ice phytoplankton, sea-ice algae represent the foundation of ecological interactions in the sea-ice biome (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Algal growth in sea ice is limited by the strong seasonality of light, nutrients, and brine connectivity and, in first-year ice, by the relatively narrow time window during which sea ice exists. At high latitudes, light conditions in the sea-ice habitat are subject to extreme seasonal changes. Light availability is largely regulated by the photoperiod, which depends on latitude and time of the year, and by the albedo and light attenuation of different sea-ice surfaces (e.g., snow-covered ice, bare ice, and ponded ice). Nutrients in sea ice are replenished through brine connectivity with the underlying water column and through local regeneration processes. Brine connectivity depends on brine permeability, a function of both sea-ice temperature and salinity. The warmer and less salty the ice, the greater its permeability and thus its habitable space.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We expect future higher sea-ice surface temperature (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) and thus warmer and more permeable sea ice. However, steeper temperature gradients through thinner ice/snow, together with the expected general freshening of the Arctic Ocean (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>), might have a counterbalancing effect on sea-ice permeability. Large uncertainties in future nutrient dynamics (i.e., how mixed layer depth might change and be sustained) limit our understanding of the future Arctic Ocean ecosystem (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In sea ice, the phenology of the narrow time window for biological growth is constrained by the incidence of suitable light conditions and by the length of the ice season (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>). While sea-ice freeze-up (breakup) is overall expected to occur later (earlier) in the season at all latitudes (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>), there are more uncertainties in the future timing of sympagic algal blooms (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>), with snow changes considered to be the single most important predictor of future sea-ice algal phenology (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>). A few conceptual and qualitative models have been proposed to describe the anticipated response of the seasonal ice zone biota to a warmer climate (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>), and some more quantitative works have used climate model projections and earth system models to analyze the effects of a fresher, ice-free Arctic on phytoplankton primary production (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). Melt onset trends have shown considerable advances on pan-Arctic scale with marked regional differences and the southerly regions melting earlier (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). The strongest trend since 1979 has occurred in the Barents Sea and East Greenland Sea (25 and 30 days, respectively), while less rapid trend is observed in the Baffin Bay, Kara Sea, and Hudson Bay (22, 15, and 10 days, respectively), and the weakest trend is found in the Central Arctic Sea (5 days). There is increasing consensus that these advances in melt onset, together with thinner sea ice and increased stratification, have led to conditions generally more favorable for sub-ice pelagic blooms in the last 30 years (
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>), suggesting that the advancement of the phytoplankton bloom peak has made the annual season of primary productivity overall longer as well (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, less is known of the conditions that lead to sea-ice algal blooms, which are also dependent on other factors such as brine connectivity. Changes in sea-ice nutrient concentrations are expected to affect the overall amplitude (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>) but are less likely to influence the timing of the growth of sea-ice biota (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>). Thus, sympagic and pelagic dynamics might not be directly related (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>), and the onset of seasonal primary production in the Arctic marine food web may occur in subsequent waves made of sub-ice and open-water phytoplankton blooms (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>) on top of sea-ice algal blooms. These pulses of primary production trigger higher trophic levels, from zooplankton to fish to top predators such as whales and polar bears. These phenological cascades are expected to be stronger in the Arctic Ocean where there is tight coupling between abiotic conditions and the timing of primary production and where the food chains are short (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate model projections are the only available tools that can be used to quantitatively assess potential long-term changes in sea-ice biogeochemical dynamics in a warmer Arctic. Here, we use a near-mechanistic modeling approach that combines sea-ice drivers obtained from an ensemble of 18 CMIP5 [Climate Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>)] climate models with a state-of-the-art sea-ice biogeochemical model (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>) to provide a quantitative overview of the effect of different physical drivers on the potential phenological changes in pan-Arctic first-year ice primary production. We focus our study on first-year ice, which is becoming the dominant type of sea ice in the Arctic Ocean (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). In this work, we consider the Arctic first-year ice as a single pan-Arctic physico-biogeochemical unit. This is motivated by the inherent constraints of climate projections and by the sparse availability of recurring studies on seasonal sea-ice biogeochemistry. We seek to elucidate the first-order impacts of large-scale, climate-driven ice changes on sea-ice algal production rather than considering the more local and subregional components, e.g., as done in (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>) to explain the coupling between sea ice and tundra in the Svalbard Archipelago since it would require observational efforts that are not yet available on a pan-Arctic scale.
 </p>
</sec>
