<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The biogeochemical model set-up</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sea-ice biogeochemical model (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>) allowed flexible stoichiometry in the algal composition and physiological responses (
  <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">
   <span class="italic">58</span>
  </a>); in this specific case, it also featured a nonlimiting amount of dissolved nitrogen and phosphorous and realistic historical concentrations of dissolved silicates (SiO
  <sub>4</sub>), assuming no intracellular storage and a Monod-like uptake rate (
  <a rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" href="#R59">
   <span class="italic">59</span>
  </a>) as modeled in phytoplankton. This choice was made (i) to limit the uncertainties due to the little available knowledge on sea-ice nutrient co-limitation; (ii) because of previous sensitivity studies on the role of nutrients on algal bloom timing (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>); (iii) because silica is an essential macronutrient for the generally dominant functional group of algae found in the Arctic bottom sea-ice habitat, which is pennate diatoms (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>). Pennate diatoms were characterized by three basic constituents: carbon, Chl-a, and silica. Note that the internal stoichiometric ratios were allowed to vary, particularly the Chl:C ratio, which is an emulator of light acclimation capability. Other functional groups included detritus and gases, for nine state variables in total. The simulated sea-ice biological processes were photosynthesis, respiration, mortality/excretion, and nutrient uptake. The sea-ice biogeochemical model was coupled to pelagic biogeochemistry in a simple slab ocean, representing an averaged mixed layer depth under sea ice (15 m for all latitudes and both scenarios). The ocean model was initialized in both scenarios with the zonal winter median (November to May) concentrations of dissolved silicates in the first 10 m of the Arctic Ocean between 1948 and 2000 (
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>) for every latitudinal band. 1 mg C/m
  <span class="sup">3</span> of diatoms in seawater for all latitudes and in both scenarios were used as the typical background winter value. The sea-ice model did not need initialization since the fluxes at the interface, which are a function of sea-ice growth/melt velocities and thickness of the BAL, controlled the exchanges of dissolved and particulate matter between sea ice and seawater (
  <a rid="R58" ref-type="bibr" href="#R58">
   <span class="italic">58</span>
  </a>). With this setup, we investigated the relative changes in future GPP, which, assuming unchanged nutrient dynamics in the future, are independent on the background nutrient conditions used, which are highly uncertain (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). This operative strategy thus removes the uncertainties associated with current and future nutrient dynamics, while it increases our confidence toward reliable estimates of future sea-ice GPP.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The biogeochemical prognostic variables presented are sea-ice algal Chl-a and GPP in the brine pockets and their vertical integral over the BAL, both temporally integrated over the duration of the sea-ice season. An indicator of phenology, the anomaly index of chlorophyll concentration in the brine volume has been developed (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>), where positive values represent the period of bloom activity in sea ice. This index was computed as the difference between the amplitude of the concentration and its SD over the production period.
 </p>
</sec>
