<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Element 4: Reporting, Monitoring, and Review</div>
 <sec id="sec2.4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monitor and review the H-NAP to assess progress, effectiveness, and gaps</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An objective of the H-NAP process is to strengthen national systems for monitoring and evaluating the burden of climate-sensitive health outcomes and to align those systems with international reporting.
   <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">
    <span class="sup">21</span>
   </a> Guidance on what needs to be included in a national health information system should be developed during the H-NAP process, taking into consideration the priority health outcomes of concern over the coming decades, the human and financial resources needed to augment surveillance programs, whether additional capacity needs to be built within the ministry of health and other organizations for monitoring and evaluation of climate-sensitive health risks, and the recommended indicators for monitoring the process of adaptation and the effectiveness of the products of specific adaptation programs (eg, early warning systems).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indicators for monitoring, evaluation, and learning can include the following:
   <div list-type="simple" class="list">
    <div id="u0140" class="list-item">
     <span class="label">•</span>
     <p>The number and geographic distribution of cases and deaths (and trends over time) in climate-sensitive health outcomes. Health outcome data should be at least disaggregated by age and gender to identify high-risk population subgroups and to facilitate design of tailored interventions. Other variables to consider when developing indicators depend on the health outcome of interest; for example, socioeconomic variables where income distribution is important or the prevalence of chronic diseases.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="u0145" class="list-item">
     <span class="label">•</span>
     <p>Trends in factors that increase or decrease vulnerability and exposure to the hazards associated with changing weather patterns and sea level rise, such as urbanization, access to improved water sources, and social capital.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="u0150" class="list-item">
     <span class="label">•</span>
     <p>Weather and climate variables, such as average and extreme temperature and precipitation, trends in the frequency and intensity of extreme weather and climate events, and sea level rise. Other environmental variables also may be useful, such as measures of soil moisture or stream flow.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="u0155" class="list-item">
     <span class="label">•</span>
     <p>The effectiveness of adaptation policies and programs, such as whether a particular option decreased the number of people at risk during a flood or increased the capacity of health care professionals to use weather and climate variables to forecast health risks.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="u0160" class="list-item">
     <span class="label">•</span>
     <p>The process of adaptation, including tracking the progress on identifying and scaling out lessons learned and best practices.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because the health sector has been managing the risks of climate-sensitive health outcomes for decades to centuries, there are well-established indicators for monitoring the burden of these outcomes, such as the number of children who are undernourished, the number of deaths from specific vector-borne diseases, or the proportion of a community or region with access to improved drinking water sources and sanitation.
   <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">
    <span class="sup">22</span>
   </a> In some cases, it would be helpful to increase the frequency of weekly or monthly monitoring because developing robust early warning systems generally requires daily data so that any associations between weather or climate and health variables are discernible. Where changes in the geographic range of vector-borne diseases are of concern, surveillance may need to be expanded into new regions. Working with stakeholders across local to national scales during the H-NAP will facilitate identifying where gathering additional health information would promote resilience.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative and qualitative indicators can be used to monitor trends in factors that can affect vulnerability. Indicators of important social determinants of vulnerability or exposure can include the extent to which gender is a key driver of vulnerability, metrics of the strength of social capital for promoting health adaptation or coping with extreme weather and climate events, and the effectiveness of bridging organizations in reducing vulnerability.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The H-NAP will identify the weather and climate variables associated with adverse health outcomes. These variables are generally measured by national hydrometeorologic services but may not be measured in locations important for health adaptation. Collaborating with these services will help ensure that information is available on these variables for monitoring the effectiveness of adaptation interventions.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although monitoring and evaluation of the effectiveness of adaptation options are well established in health systems, current approaches were not designed for issues such as climate change where, for example, the magnitude of the “exposure” to weather and climate events cannot be reduced until at least mid-century; where local socioeconomic and environmental conditions are key determinants of the magnitude and pattern of risks; and where upstream drivers mainly arise from sectors outside health. Monitoring and evaluation frameworks also need to be adjusted to describe explicit baselines against which the effectiveness of adaptation options can be measured over time and to inform future modification of adaptation options. Baseline variables include those describing the patterns of vulnerability, patterns of weather and climate variables important for health, the effectiveness of current health systems interventions, and the capacity of health systems to manage the health risks of climate variability and change. Low- and middle-income countries are developing baselines as they implement adaptation projects (cf 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/globalchange/projects/en/" id="intref0015" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.who.int/globalchange/projects/en/</span>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">WHO is developing summary climate change and health country profiles to provide a baseline for monitoring future progress. The profiles will include information on current weather and climate hazards and health impacts; current burdens of climate-sensitive health outcomes; future exposures and health risks under different climate change scenarios; opportunities for health gains through climate change mitigation and adaptation; and policy information related to health and climate change.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When monitoring effectiveness, it is important to capture not only best practices but also barriers and constraints and how they were overcome (if they were). Scaling out adaptation options to other regions will be easier and more effective when there is a more complete understanding of the process of adaptation.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having an adaptation strategy does not guarantee that it is implemented, and implementing a strategy may not be as effective as possible without including other sectors and nonstate actors. It is therefore important to include indicators focused on the process of adaptation and the extent to which adaptation interventions are effective. To start, annual, mid-term, and final review of the implementation of the H-NAP and of recommended adaptation programs should be considered in the list of indictors. Indicators monitoring interactions across sectors could include, for example, the frequency of intersectoral meetings and whether memoranda of understanding are actually facilitating data sharing.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The monitoring, evaluating, and learning framework should include milestones and should be designed for regular evaluation to introduce modifications when needed.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Update the health component of the NAP in an iterative manner</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The magnitude and pattern of the health risks of climate variability and change will shift as climate and development proceed, which will require revisiting the H-NAP to ensure continued relevance and effectiveness. Revisions to the H-NAP should also take into account experience gained with implementing adaptation options, knowledge gained from research, and changes in institutional structures. The updating process should be flexible, revisiting the H-NAP whenever major changes occur that could alter the previous conclusions and approaches to adaptation. An update should also be considered when the national adaptation plan is revised.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Outreach on the H-NAP process, including reporting on progress and effectiveness</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Outreach is invaluable for increasing the preparedness of communities, health services providers, and other key stakeholders. A communication strategy should be developed from the beginning of the H-NAP process.
   <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">
    <span class="sup">9</span>
   </a> Stakeholders should include management units within the ministry of health responsible for climate-sensitive health outcomes, representatives from health care providers, representatives from other sectors, community representatives, and others who could be affected by or who could affect the success of the adaptation plan.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The NAP process will define report requirements and the timeframe for doing so. To the extent possible, health data generation, compilation, analysis, synthesis, communication, and use for decision-making should be aligned with these requirements so that the H-NAP can ensure the best possible information is included in the national adaptation plan, highlighting the potential health risks of climate variability and change, and the opportunities for proactively managing these risks to reduce the current and projected burden of climate-sensitive health outcomes.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
