<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Promote coordination and synergy with the NAP process, particularly with sectors that can affect health, and with multilateral environment agreements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This step calls for including a description in the H-NAP of how it will promote the national strategies identified in the overall NAP process and how health adaptation will coordinate with other sectors in promoting human health and well-being.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because many of the upstream drivers of the health risks of climate change arise from outside the sector, multisectoral approaches are required for effective adaptation.
  <a rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib16">
   <span class="sup">16</span>
  </a> Closer partnerships across sectors and, ultimately, better governance can arise from understanding the different institutions and organizations whose decisions can affect population health. Partnering mechanisms, at local to national scales, should include sectoral collaboration, policy coordination, and increasing coherence of risk management approaches. One way to facilitate cross-sectoral coordination is to include health indicators within the national indicator framework (see the next section).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bowen et al. proposed a multilayered governance network for identifying the actual decision-making actors, their roles, and their level of influence in health adaptation options.
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">
   <span class="sup">17</span>
  </a> The network includes 4 elements: social capital, non–state-based actors, informal networks, and bridging organizations. These elements can be explicitly incorporated into implementation strategies to facilitate effective and efficient adaptation through strengthening partnerships and collaboration mechanisms.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social capital includes the capacity of a population or community to work together as a self-organizing unit to achieve particular goals.
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">
   <span class="sup">18</span>
  </a> The activities undertaken can, depending on the circumstances, facilitate adaptation. Social capital is also an important driver of some health outcomes (eg, mental health).
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">
   <span class="sup">19</span>
  </a> Greater efforts are needed to identify the enabling conditions for norms and behaviors that will support greater awareness of and actions to reduce the risks of climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It also is important to link with multilateral environmental agreements to identify opportunities for synergies across adaptation and mitigation efforts. For example, greening of the health care sector can promote adaptation, by identifying modifications to increase the resilience of facilities and infrastructure to extreme weather and climate events. Greening also can promote mitigation by identifying energy efficiency opportunities in energy intensive facilities such as hospitals.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the H-NAP is structured from the beginning to integrate with the NAP process, then this step can identify where, for example, formal memorandums of understanding or other mechanisms can institutionalize collaborations developed during the H-NAP. An example is the Republic of Indonesia climate change sectoral roadmap (ICCSR) developed in 2009 to provide input for the 5-year medium-term development plan (RPJM) 2010-2014 and for subsequent RPJMs until 2030, placing particular emphasis on the challenges emerging in 9 particular sectors, including health.
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">
   <span class="sup">20</span>
  </a> Each sector developed a roadmap that included a policy analysis, formulation of a vision on climate change, and identification of a pathway of actions to accomplish the vision. The national development planning agency is addressing challenges and opportunities across sectors through coordination of the work of all ministries, departments, and agencies. The roadmap includes prioritized recommendations that reflect the linkages across policies, programs, and plans for different sectors and donor programs/projects.
 </p>
</sec>
