<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In reality, thermal limits occur across a spectrum between the maximum environmental temperature individuals experience locally and beyond the maximum temperatures a species experiences globally (i.e. species-specific limit). That is, individuals from an established population should at least survive the environmental conditions typical of that location, but may also be able to survive in much warmer conditions. Examined across a species' geographical range, this spectrum of thermal limits creates a wedge of potential thermal safety margins (TSMs) that individuals may experience (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20180550F1">figure 1</xref>). The upper margin of the wedge represents the axis of lowest sensitivity (i.e. maximum potential TSMs), where upper thermal limits are conserved, resulting in declining TSMs between the cool-edge and warm-edge of a species' distribution, as environmental temperatures approach the species-specific thermal limit. The bottom of the wedge represents the axis of highest thermal sensitivity (i.e. minimum potential TSMs), where upper thermal limits are similar to maximum local environmental temperatures, irrespective of thermal range position. While locally adapted and acclimatized individuals are not confined to this axis, individuals and populations observed along this axis are likely to be highly adapted or acclimatized to their local thermal environment (see §3, below). Historically, the upper axis of the sensitivity wedge has been predominantly used to forecast local extirpation and species redistributions from climate change. But several studies have now highlighted how short-term warming can cause large-scale, catastrophic mortality events at temperatures well below the species-specific limit, particularly throughout central and cool-edge locations of a species distribution [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], consistent with the thermal sensitivity wedge. 
</p>
