<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">A fairly simple diagnostic that can be calculated from reanalysis and model data, and is more relevant for glacier mass balance than surface temperature, is the freezing level height (FLH). Increasing FLH in the Central Andes negatively affects the surface mass balance of glaciers, by changing the rain/snow ratio and increasingly exposing lower reaches of glaciers to rain as opposed to snow
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. Hence a rise in the FLH does not only directly affect the glacier surface mass balance through higher temperatures, leading to more melt, but also impacts accumulation and glacier surface albedo
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. The FLH increased by approximately 160 m over the last five and a half decades over the Cordillera Blanca and Cordillera Real
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, located to the north and south of QIC, respectively. The mean annual FLH in the Cordillera Vilcanota was 5010 m a.s.l. over the 1980–2015 period
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>, with a higher FLH during the warmer wet season and a lower FLH during the slightly colder dry season
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, respectively. Historically the increase in the FLH in the tropics can be empirically described as a linear response to the increase in tropical sea surface temperature (SST)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, the FLH over this region is dependent on the phase of ENSO and responds to both interannual and decadal-scale changes in tropical Pacific SST
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
