<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Independent air quality control</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All results presented above assume the level of air quality control that occurs independently of climate policy will proceed approximately as projected in the coming decades, based on current and planned policies. We systematically test the importance of this assumption by implementing an environmental Kuznets-type approach where emission intensities decrease with increasing per capita income (described in detail in the Methods section, and in particular Eqs. (
  <a rid="Equ2" ref-type="" href="#Equ2">2</a>)–(
  <a rid="Equ4" ref-type="" href="#Equ4">4</a>) and associated discussion). Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> reports results when we slow down and speed up this Kuznets-relevant income, allowing it to range between roughly 50% (
  <span class="italic">χ</span> = 0.5) and 150% (
  <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1.5) of the true (modeled) income; lower values imply less stringent air quality control and vice versa. In these model runs the true income is used in all other parts of the model.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Impact of independent air quality control. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Optimal decarbonization and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> associated global temperature rise given different levels of autonomous air quality control. The reference and RICE + AIR cases from Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, where 
     <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1, are displayed as the blue and red solid lines, respectively
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9499_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e788" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results demonstrate that although assumptions about air quality control do influence optimal mitigation levels, more decarbonization remains optimal compared to the reference case under all of these scenarios. However, the mechanisms driving the additional decarbonization vary. If the (pre-mitigation) air is dirtier than projected (
  <span class="italic">χ</span> &lt; 1), extra mitigation occurs primarily to reap the health co-benefits. If stringent air quality control occurs in the future (
  <span class="italic">χ</span> &gt; 1), more decarbonization is also optimal compared to the reference case. In part this is to capture remaining health co-benefits, but also for two other reasons. First, the potential damages associated with the substantial loss of the aerosol cooling effect requires additional CO
  <sub>2</sub> reductions as a counterbalance. And second, when the air is cleaner, each marginal reduction in CO
  <sub>2</sub> has a greater net benefit because it is not coupled to as much cooling aerosol.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another way of understanding the role of independent air quality measures on optimal climate policy is by comparing not only the different RICE + AIR cases, as in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, but also the difference between the RICE + AIR cases and their corresponding reference cases, as reported in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. The results confirm that as autonomous emission controls get stronger (represented by higher 
  <span class="italic">χ</span> values), the less health co-benefits matter for climate policy.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Impact of independent air quality control</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>2030</th>
      <th>2030</th>
      <th>2050</th>
      <th>2050</th>
      <th>Diff. in peak temp (°C)
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>Reference</th>
      <th>RICE + AIR</th>
      <th>Reference</th>
      <th>RICE + AIR</th>
      <th/>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">χ</span> = 0.5
      </td>
      <td>20%</td>
      <td>39%</td>
      <td>27%</td>
      <td>57%</td>
      <td>0.9</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">χ</span> = 0.75
      </td>
      <td>22%</td>
      <td>37%</td>
      <td>33%</td>
      <td>54%</td>
      <td>0.5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1 (main result)
      </td>
      <td>24%</td>
      <td>36%</td>
      <td>35%</td>
      <td>52%</td>
      <td>0.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1.25
      </td>
      <td>24%</td>
      <td>35%</td>
      <td>36%</td>
      <td>51%</td>
      <td>0.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1.5
      </td>
      <td>25%</td>
      <td>35%</td>
      <td>37%</td>
      <td>50%</td>
      <td>0.3</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Optimal decarbonization rates in RICE + AIR versus the corresponding reference case for different values of 
     <span class="italic">χ</span>, which represent different levels of independent air quality control. 
     <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1 represents the assumption underlying the main results, whereas higher (lower) values indicate more (less) stringent air quality control in the future. The difference in peak temperature is the difference between the highest global average temperature in the RICE + AIR optimum versus the reference case given the assumed value of 
     <span class="italic">χ</span>
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">a</span>Positive values indicate a lower peak temperature in RICE + AIR. Values are rounded
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the scenarios displayed in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> is the fully co-optimal case that selects the ideal combination of both air quality and climate policies by introducing an additional policy lever that can act directly on individual air pollutant emissions through end-of-pipe measures, rather than via CO
  <sub>2</sub> (described in Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). When this lever is added, large reductions in air pollutant emissions occur when and where associated abatement costs are low, the reductions lead to relatively large decreases in exposure, and/or they produce few climate damages. This first-best policy where climate and air pollution policies are co-optimized leads to rapid air quality improvements but still increased decarbonization relative to the reference case, albeit by a lower margin than in the standard 
  <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1 case that underlies our main results. Note that we selected 
  <span class="italic">χ</span> = 1 as the basis for the main result in order to explore the effect health co-benefits have when regions act consistently with their current and planned air pollution policies (which are suboptimal). As this section demonstrates, the magnitude of the co-benefit effect is importantly influenced by the assumed level of independent air quality control.
 </p>
</sec>
