<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In rural Bangladesh, natural disasters are identified as one of the most important factors for deaths of women, especially during pregnancy. The female to male death ratio is 3:1 during natural disasters [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. During the disaster, women are the most vulnerable for pregnancy complications including retained placenta, obstructed labor, and fetal distress. It is difficult to manage maternal health problems during disasters as healthcare facilities and providers are not available. Delivery in unsafe condition increases maternal deaths [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Disaster also impacts on reproductive health through spontaneous abortion, birth defects, and low birth weight of the baby [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. According to literature, South-East Asia is the most vulnerable region, due to global warming having significant effects on the climate changes including unprecedented heavy rain and floods [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In Pakistan, about 500,000 expecting mothers were affected by the 2010 flood while 1.5 million women needed emergency obstetric care [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Among pregnant women during the disaster, 1700 women delivered, with hundreds of them suffering from delivery complications in Pakistan. Maternal deaths are also high in the Indian sub-continent due to a lack of medicine and the absence of female healthcare providers during disasters [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Bangladesh is considered to be one of the world’s most natural hazard-prone countries, and flood is one of the most common disasters experienced regularly by the people of Bangladesh where on average, 18% of the country is affected by floods every year [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In a study by UNFPA of nine districts in Bangladesh, it was found that 1,876,636 people were affected by flood disasters, of which 32,000–33,000 were pregnant women [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Pregnant women, lactating mothers, and differently disabled women suffered the most, as they found it difficult to move during and after a disaster. Sometimes women cannot express their problems [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In Bangladesh, it is found that non-availability of transport in and around all flood-affected areas and disruption of communications seriously hindered women’s ability to access health facilities for deliveries [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Moreover, the delay in decision making and delays in transportation influence the maternal deaths in rural communities [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It is also found that some of the healthcare centers are inundated with flood water. So, access to health services becomes limited as a result of routine immunization and outpatient consultation, antenatal care become disrupted in the affected villages in Bangladesh [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-04594" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Due to climate change, Bangladesh is overexposed for natural disasters such as floods. This study explored the perception of maternal death during the flood. This study also explored the practices and challenges of the community people for emergency maternal care with complications during the flood period. The study tried to investigate the community recommendation for preventing maternal death during flood. 
</p>
