<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.2.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Develop a national health adaptation strategy that identifies priority adaptation plans</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The H-NAP should specify the priority strategies designed to address the adverse health risks of climate variability and change and include a detailed plan of action. Having a comprehensive vulnerability and adaptation assessment will facilitate developing strategies and implementation plans. Using a theory-of-change approach (eg, a process for defining how to achieve a long-term goal by identifying necessary early and immediate changes) can facilitate identification of priority strategies. Conducting a theory-of-change process includes working with stakeholders to identify the long-term change being sought; the process and sequence of change, including the socioeconomic and political conditions and the actors able to influence them; explicit statements of the assumptions about how change might happen; and a diagram and narrative summary of the process and expected outcome. The overarching strategy is generally to increase the resilience of health systems to the health risks of climate variability and change; this includes ensuring that health systems can prepare for, respond to, cope with, and recover from climate-related effects.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The H-NAP should include detailed institutional arrangements to implement and engage relevant stakeholders; immediate and medium- and long-term health adaptation goals, with a time frame for implementation; a monitoring and evaluation framework; and approaches to ensure adequate human and financial resources are available to implement the plan.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, African ministers of health and of environment have begun jointly implementing the framework for Public Health Adaptation to Climate Change.
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">
   <span class="sup">15</span>
  </a> The guiding principles are evidence-based planning, country ownership and community participation, intersectoral cooperation and collaboration, synergies with other public health initiatives, and advocacy at national and international levels. Implementation requires multisectoral Country Coordination Committees (CCCs), which are national technical and advisory entities intended to address health and environment issues—including climate change—that should include government representatives, development partners, and civil society. The proposed template for the adaptation plan includes risk and capacity assessment; capacity-building; integrated environment and health surveillance; response; research; monitoring and evaluation; and coordination and management. Following this process will put countries on pathways to become more resilient to the health risks of climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
