<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All actors in health systems, from research scientists to ministries of health staff to health care providers, are responsible for understanding, engaging in, and supporting the health component of a national adaptation plan. Most H-NAP elements and steps will be familiar; understanding and managing risks are at the core of health systems. However, climate variability and change bring new dimensions that will require training and capacity building to mainstream climate change concerns into health system strategies, policies, and programs and into research and development. Focusing on strengthening health protection systems for climate-sensitive health outcomes is important, including increasing access to vaccination, safe water, and improved sanitation. But that is only the start. Risks will evolve with climate and development, requiring proactive planning, implementation, and monitoring and evaluation if health systems are to be prepared to reduce risks to the fullest extent possible.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There also are key research gaps that need to be filled, particularly in low-income countries.
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">
   <span class="sup">4</span>
  </a> National governments and international research funders can help fill those gaps, supporting analysis of existing data sets, including projecting how health risks could change under different possible futures, and supporting the collection of additional longitudinal data where gaps exist. This research should include an explicit focus on upstream drivers of climate-sensitive health risks. This critical research's limited funding constrains the design and implementation of effective and efficient adaptation options. More methods and tools are coming online, such as early warning systems that can effectively increase resilience to some negative health outcomes. Additional efforts are required to increase their uptake and effective use.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The health risks of climate variability and change are already unacceptable, with the burden projected to increase as the climate continues to change. Proactive and efficient adaptation can reduce health burdens over coming decades but cannot eliminate all risks.
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">
   <span class="sup">4</span>
  </a> Mitigation is equally as important as adaptation; rapid and substantial reductions in greenhouse gas emissions are required to reduce risks past mid-century. But even with substantial reductions and with significant investments in adaptation, climate-sensitive health risks in excess of what countries will be able to manage will be a feature of coming decades. Conducting an H-NAP is the best opportunity for preparing for very different socioeconomic and environmental conditions that will likely challenge the ability of health systems to maintain and improve population health.
 </p>
</sec>
