<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual chick responses to treatment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our first indicator of individual chick performance, growth rate during the linear phase of growth, correlates well in shags with prefledging mass (Reed et al. 
  <a rid="b74" ref-type="bibr" href="#b74">2012</a>), which studies in a range of bird species have shown to be positively related to recruitment probability (Magrath 
  <a rid="b53" ref-type="bibr" href="#b53">1991</a>; Schwagmeyer and Mock 
  <a rid="b80" ref-type="bibr" href="#b80">2008</a>). We obtained individual growth rates during this linear growth phase by fitting a linear regression for each chick. Each chick had 3–5 measurement points (mean 4.7, 1231 measurements on 259 chicks) apart from in 2007, when only two measurements per chick were possible (at treatment and toward the end of the linear growth phase, mean age 29.3 days). The data have previously been shown to be quantitatively robust to this restricted sampling (Reed et al. 
  <a rid="b74" ref-type="bibr" href="#b74">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested whether the rank-specific effect of treatment on growth rate varied with environmental conditions by fitting a three-way interaction term between rank as a three-level factor, treatment as a two-level factor, and productivity as a covariate. We compared the fit of the three-way interaction with models containing all of its subsidiary two-way interactions in turn and simultaneously. All models also included sex to account for the faster growth rate of males, which may make them more expensive to rear and hence more sensitive to their rank, levels of parasitism, and/or prevailing conditions (Daunt et al. 
  <a rid="b22" ref-type="bibr" href="#b22">2001a</a>; Reed et al. 
  <a rid="b72" ref-type="bibr" href="#b72">2008a</a>). Therefore, we compared the fit of all models fitted to three terms: sex as a main effect, a sex-by-rank interaction, or a sex-by-rank-by-productivity interaction. We also tested whether sex affected chicks' responses to treatment in the same way as we tested the role of rank. To examine whether rank-specific treatment responses were simply a result of mass differences between siblings at treatment, we fitted mass at treatment instead of rank and undertook the same model fitting and selection procedure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also investigated whether treatment affected chick survival between treatment and fledging (age ∼50 days, Snow 
  <a rid="b85" ref-type="bibr" href="#b85">1960</a>). We used the same models as for chick growth rate, with survival modeled as a binary response with binomial errors and a logit-link function.
 </p>
</sec>
