<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Parasites play a key role in many ecological and evolutionary processes through the costs they impose on their host (Sheldon &amp; Verhulst 
  <a rid="b84" ref-type="bibr" href="#b84">1996</a>; Clayton and Moore 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">1997</a>; Norris and Evans 
  <a rid="b62" ref-type="bibr" href="#b62">2000</a>; Hudson et al. 
  <a rid="b45" ref-type="bibr" href="#b45">2002</a>; Sandland and Minchella 
  <a rid="b77" ref-type="bibr" href="#b77">2003</a>). However, in wild populations, the effect of parasitism may vary considerably with external conditions, potentially having a greater effect when conditions are poor because hosts have fewer resources to deal with infection. Many environmental factors are predicted to become more variable in the near future due to climatic change (Coumou and Rahmstorf 
  <a rid="b19" ref-type="bibr" href="#b19">2012</a>). Understanding how this extrinsic variability interacts with parasitism to influence an organism's life history is therefore critical to understanding the full impact of both factors on populations. However, in studies of wild hosts, variation in how hosts cope with infection is rarely considered explicitly in the context of prevailing environmental conditions (Sandland &amp; Minchella 
  <a rid="b77" ref-type="bibr" href="#b77">2003</a>; Wolinska &amp; King 
  <a rid="b97" ref-type="bibr" href="#b97">2009</a>; Boughton et al. 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">2011</a>). Instead, parasite manipulation studies commonly interpret environmental variability as noise to which conclusions should be robust, rather than an informative aspect of host responses to infection. Qualitative interannual differences in the effects of parasite manipulation in wild hosts have been observed (e.g., Heeb et al. 
  <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">1999</a>; Stien et al. 
  <a rid="b88" ref-type="bibr" href="#b88">2002</a>; Knowles et al. 
  <a rid="b48" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48">2010b</a>), and the importance of environment to host–parasite interactions is well acknowledged in laboratory systems (Luong and Polak 
  <a rid="b52" ref-type="bibr" href="#b52">2007</a>; Wolinska &amp; King 
  <a rid="b97" ref-type="bibr" href="#b97">2009</a>; Vale et al. 
  <a rid="b93" ref-type="bibr" href="#b93">2011</a>), yet we know of no study that incorporates quantitative measures of interannual environmental variation to examine the consequences of parasitism in a wild, free-ranging population.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals in a population are likely to vary in their response to environmental conditions, their susceptibility to parasite infection, and their subsequent ability to deal with an established infection (Schmid-Hempel &amp; Koella 
  <a rid="b79" ref-type="bibr" href="#b79">1994</a>; Shaw, Grenfell &amp; Dobson 
  <a rid="b83" ref-type="bibr" href="#b83">1998</a>; Sandland and Minchella 
  <a rid="b77" ref-type="bibr" href="#b77">2003</a>; Lewis et al. 
  <a rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" href="#b50">2009</a>). This variation among individuals is likely to be particularly pronounced in juveniles, because parental investment patterns may vary strategically with environmental conditions to maximize lifetime reproductive success (Temme &amp; Charnov 
  <a rid="b90" ref-type="bibr" href="#b90">1987</a>; Forbes 
  <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">2009</a>). For example, parents with multiple offspring may bias provisioning to ensure that core young obtain sufficient resources to survive when conditions are poor (Lack 
  <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">1947</a>; Mock and Forbes 
  <a rid="b56" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56">1995</a>; Forbes et al. 
  <a rid="b30" ref-type="bibr" href="#b30">2002</a>; Hudson and Trillmich 
  <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2007</a>; Forbes 
  <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">2009</a>). Much of the research in this area has been carried out in birds, where this bias often stems from within-brood asymmetry in size, commonly set up by asynchronous hatching of eggs and differences in the hormonal environment of offspring (Stenning 
  <a rid="b87" ref-type="bibr" href="#b87">1996</a>; Bonabeau et al. 
  <a rid="b10" ref-type="bibr" href="#b10">1998</a>; Groothuis et al. 
  <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2005</a>). Levels of maternal antibodies and nutrients may also differ in relation to laying order and offspring sex (Royle et al. 
  <a rid="b76" ref-type="bibr" href="#b76">1999</a>; Pihlaja et al. 
  <a rid="b67" ref-type="bibr" href="#b67">2006</a>; Hasselquist and Nilsson 
  <a rid="b39" ref-type="bibr" href="#b39">2009</a>; Martyka et al. 
  <a rid="b54" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54">2011</a>). Inherent differences between offspring therefore exist that could influence both their susceptibility and tolerance to parasitism, leading to complex, nonadditive effects of parasitism under different environmental conditions (Forbes 
  <a rid="b27" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27">1993</a>; Bize et al. 
  <a rid="b8" ref-type="bibr" href="#b8">2006</a>; Knowles et al. 
  <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">2010a</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, the developmental environment may also influence the value of the whole brood to parents. There may therefore be variation in the total amount of food that parents provide to the nest as well as allocation between brood members (Godfray and Johnstone 
  <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">2000</a>; Parker et al. 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2002</a>). While offspring parasitism has been shown to alter overall parental provisioning (Christe et al. 
  <a rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17">1996</a>; Tripet &amp; Richner 
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">1997</a>; Hurtrez-Boussès et al. 
  <a rid="b46" ref-type="bibr" href="#b46">1998</a>), little is yet known about whether it can influence resource allocation among a brood.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of studies that manipulate ectoparasite loads have demonstrated an impact of infection on a range of traits across family members, showing that parasitism in the nest can be detrimental to the development of individual offspring (O'Brien and Dawson 
  <a rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" href="#b64">2009</a>), to the success of the whole brood (Christe et al. 
  <a rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17">1996</a>), and to parents' future breeding success (Bize et al. 
  <a rid="b7" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7">2004</a>; Fitze et al. 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">2004</a>). These effects could be driven by various behavioral mechanisms of intrafamilial conflict. For example, ectoparasitism has been shown to influence both chick signaling and parental provisioning in great tits 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>, where removal of biting hen fleas in the nest decreased both chick begging rate and the father's provisioning rate (Christe et al. 
  <a rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17">1996</a>). However, many ectoparasites are mobile and redistribute themselves between chicks and parents to feed and disperse (Tripet &amp; Richner 
  <a rid="b92" ref-type="bibr" href="#b92">1999</a>). It is therefore difficult to completely isolate the effect of a particular individual's parasite load, as removing parasites from one family member may alter the parasite load of others (Bize et al. 
  <a rid="b7" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7">2004</a>; Fitze et al. 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">2004</a>; Gallizzi et al. 
  <a rid="b33" ref-type="bibr" href="#b33">2008</a>; Roulin et al. 
  <a rid="b75" ref-type="bibr" href="#b75">2003</a>). In contrast, endoparasites are discretely distributed between hosts, allowing the direct costs to the host and the indirect effects on other family members to be distinguished. Separating these effects would be a major step in advancing our understanding of how individual differences in responses to parasitism are affected by environmental conditions. This will be key when considering how effects of parasitism may scale to affect different populations of varying composition as they face environmental change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we examine the effect of annual population productivity (a proxy of prevailing environmental conditions) on the consequences of parasitism in juvenile European shags, 
  <span class="italic">Phalacrocorax aristotelis</span> (Fig.
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>). Individuals of this species are infected with gastrointestinal nematodes from the fish they eat (Anderson 
  <a rid="b4" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4">2000</a>; Hoberg 
  <a rid="b41" ref-type="bibr" href="#b41">2005</a>; Fagerholm and Overstreet 
  <a rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25">2008</a>), and there is a high prevalence of infection among adults and juveniles (Reed et al. 
  <a rid="b74" ref-type="bibr" href="#b74">2012</a>; Burthe et al. 
  <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2013</a>; Granroth-Wilding 
  <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2013</a>). Shag chicks hatch asynchronously, and chick survival varies considerably among years. Last-hatched chicks show lower survival on average (Amundsen and Stokland 
  <a rid="b3" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3">1988</a>) and therefore potentially more variable responses to environmental conditions. Here, we experimentally manipulate parasite loads over 5 years of variable conditions to investigate the effect of gastrointestinal nematode infection on individual chick growth rate and survival in a system where we can disentangle the confounding effects of parasite distributions between related individuals. We also investigate whether these differences arise as a result of changes in parental resource provisioning to the whole brood or to changes in how resources are allocated to different members of a brood.
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>A brood of asynchronously hatched European shags (
    <span class="italic">Phalacrocorax aristotelis</span>), aged c. 25 days, with an attending parent.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ece30004-3408-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
