<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change and health vulnerability and adaptation assessments are conducted at local, regional, or national scales by health authorities to identify and interpret information needed to prepare health systems for the impacts of climate change. These studies are participatory in nature, engaging a range of stakeholders to support efforts in preparing for climate change. They possess a common set of goals and processes, although individual studies may vary significantly in design. Key functions of assessments include [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Improving evidence and understanding of the current associations between weather/climate and health outcomes, including the health of populations most vulnerable to these risks;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Providing health and emergency management officials, stakeholders, and the public with information on the magnitude and pattern of current and future health risks associated with climate variability and change, and identifying vulnerabilities in the health system;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Identifying opportunities to incorporate climate change concerns into existing policies and programs designed to manage health risks associated with weather and climate, and to develop new programs where necessary to prevent and reduce the severity of future risks;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Serving as a baseline analysis against which future changes in risks and in associated policies and programs can be monitored;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Forging collaborations with sectors such as water and infrastructure to promote activities to improve population health in a changing climate; and</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Strengthening the case for investment in health protection.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
