<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Therefore, we developed a more advanced approach that better accounts for the shapes of the temperature distributions between two cities. We created analog city pairs based on the projected probability distribution functions (PDFs) of warm-season daily 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M60" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">A</mi>
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi class="mi">T</mi>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">max</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>. The best “match” for each city’s future climate was determined by performing a comparison of the nonparametric Kolmogorov–Smirnov (K-S) test statistic (
 <xref rid="c35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Massey 1951</xref>) between present-day and future temperature distributions. The K-S test statistic is a measure of the maximum distance between two continuous distribution functions. For 13 cities (Barcelona was excluded here because it was the only city not to use 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M61" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">A</mi>
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi class="mi">T</mi>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">max</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> in its ERF), the city whose present-day distribution that had the lowest test statistic when compared with an individual city’s future distribution was selected as a match. For example, the projected climate of London was found to be most similar to that of present-day Milan (out of the 12 possible options) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>; see also Table S1); thus, 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M62" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</mi>
    <mi class="mi">M</mi>
    <mi class="mi">o</mi>
    <mi class="mi">r</mi>
    <mi class="mi">t</mi>
    <mo class="mo">-</mo>
    <mi class="mi">C</mi>
    <mi class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> for London was computed using the London climate change projections as input to the Milan ERF.
</p>
