<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over the last decades, there has been an increasing interest in patient safety and learning from medical errors. Traditionally, these issues have to a large degree been addressed in hospital settings [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. However, during recent years, there has been a stronger emphasis on investigating factors related to patient safety in primary care as well, as the largest volume of health care is provided outside the hospitals.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Patient safety culture involves leader and staff interaction, routines, attitudes, practices and awareness that influence risks of adverse events in patient care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. The concept is developed within organizational psychology, and is regarded as a group phenomenon. The safety culture in the health service near the patients is of particular interest, as a substantial variation across wards has been shown [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. This variation is associated with risk of medical errors [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nursing homes may be among the primary care services with the highest risks of adverse events. Nursing home patients are vulnerable due to their complex multiple diseases, cognitive impairment and unclear presentation of illnesses [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. There is a risk of medication errors and fall injuries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. In nursing homes there commonly are many health care providers with short or no formal training, like auxiliary nurses and untrained assistants. There might also be challenges with staffing ratios to meet the needs of the patients. In nursing homes, physicians are usually present only a few hours per week.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared to hospitals, the patient safety culture in nursing homes has been shown to be considerably poorer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Therefore, nursing home patients might be at increased risk of harm related to medical errors. An association between patient safety culture in nursing homes and poor clinical outcomes has been reported [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Nursing home administrators and managers seem to rate the safety culture in their institutions higher than do direct caregivers, who might be more aware of safety concerns [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. For this reason, the practice of leadership walkarounds has been recommended.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessment of patient safety climate in nursing homes provides an opportunity to identify improvement targets [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. However, introducing safety projects may be challenging. An Ohio study showed that nearly half of the nursing staff found it difficult to make needed quality changes in nursing homes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. A “blame and shame” culture has also been observed in nursing homes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Patient safety climate assessment affords an opportunity to involve leadership in improving culture, as well as to set targets for improvement and divert resources if necessary [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are several instruments to measure safety attitudes among health care professionals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. These have traditionally been made for clinical settings within hospitals, like the Hospital Survey of Patient Safety Culture (HSOPSC) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Over the last years, questionnaires have also been adapted to settings outside hospitals. This includes the Nursing Home Survey on Patient Safety Culture (NHSOPSC), which was developed by the Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. A study describing the psychometric properties of the Norwegian NHSOPSC version has been published [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another commonly used instrument is the Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ). It includes six major patient safety factors: Teamwork climate, Safety climate, Job satisfaction, Perceptions of management, Working conditions, and Stress recognition [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of studies have shown an association between SAQ scores and patient outcome [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. The SAQ identifies areas with poor patient care and can motivate leaders to implement quality improvement strategies, whereby the risk of adverse events may be reduced [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The Safety Attitudes Questionnaire - Ambulatory Version (SAQ-A) has been developed and adjusted to the primary care setting [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>] (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). It provides the possibility of measuring effect of safety improvement interventions and change in safety attitudes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. The SAQ has also been used in nursing home settings [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SAQ-A has previously been adapted and validated for Norwegian General Practitioner (GP) practices and out-of-hours casualty clinics [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. As the instrument has proved to be a useful tool for measuring safety climate in these parts of Norwegian primary care, we wanted to validate it in the nursing home setting as well. This will enable safety culture comparisons across sectors of the health services.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of the present study was to develop a tool for measuring patient safety climate in nursing homes. We present the psychometric properties of the Norwegian translated version of the SAQ-A for nursing homes. We aimed to study whether the factor structure in this Norwegian version was the same as in the original questionnaire. Finally, we wanted to investigate whether the SAQ-A might be an appropriate instrument for measuring patient safety climate in the Norwegian nursing home setting.</p>
</sec>
