<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study showed that the hypothesized total factor model of six factors Teamwork climate, Safety climate, Job satisfaction, Perceptions of management, Working conditions, and Stress recognition had acceptable goodness-of-fit values to be used for climate measurements in the nursing home setting.</p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a recent study, SAQ was shown to be a reliable tool to measure safety climate also in nursing homes in the Netherlands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. The authors in that study encouraged nursing homes to avoid focusing on all safety factors at the same time. Their report showed that improving one factor may have a positive influence also on other safety climate factors.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cappelen et al. have studied the psychometric properties of the Nursing Home Survey on Patient Safety Culture (NHSOPSC) in Norwegian nursing homes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. This is an alternative instrument to measure safety climate. The authors identified ten factors: teamwork, staffing, compliance with procedures, training and skills, nonpunitive response to mistakes, handoffs, feedback and communication about incidents, communication openness, supervisor expectations, and management and organizational learning. Some of these factors overlap with the SAQ factors, but the NHSOPSC factors are described in more detail. Both instruments are useful tools for measuring patient safety in the Norwegian nursing home setting.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The degree of consensus amongst staff in a nursing home ward is a measure of the organizational climate’s strength. In order to describe the degree to which staff share perceptions within the same nursing home ward, we aimed to obtain a response rate of 70%. The response rate of 62.2% in our study was suboptimal. However, it was higher than the response rates in a Dutch nursing home study (53%) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>] and a study in Norwegian GP practices and out-of-hours clinics (52.2%) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. The large number of nursing home employees working part-time may have a higher degree of uncertainty about patient safety. This could possibly affect the willingness to participate in the study. There was no clear association between number of employees and response rates across the participating nursing homes. The actual response rates for the five nursing homes were 56.9, 60.4, 62.5, 63.3 and 72.2, respectively. This gives us the opportunity to explore the variation in organizational climate measurements across nursing home wards.
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among those responding to the questionnaire, there were moderate instances of items with missing values/not applicable, on average 9.4%. In 15 out of 62 items, the proportion of missing values/not applicable was &gt; 10%. However, only two of these 15 items belonged to any of the safety factors. These were items Q5 (Medical errors are handled appropriately in this nursing home ward) and Q20 (I am encouraged by my colleagues to report any patient safety concerns I may have), both belonging to the factor Safety climate, and with a proportion of 10.4 and 10.1% missing values/not applicable, respectively. A high proportion of missing values/not applicable may indicate that the respondents regard the specific item as being less relevant for their nursing home setting. However, 24 out of 28 items belonging to one of the six safety factors had &lt; 10% missing values/not applicable.</p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both the size and the organization of Norwegian nursing homes vary a lot, some of them being large institutions with teaching responsibilities of health profession students, others being small with limited numbers of patients and staff. For these reasons, it is not surprising that employees may have regarded some of the 62 items as being less relevant for their particular nursing home setting. This also reflects the diversity in the included nursing homes. In addition, the included health professions have different responsibilities in nursing home care. For instance, nursing assistants are not involved in test results, and health workers have no responsibility for medication. This means that certain items are highly relevant for some of the health professions and less to others.</p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our study, we chose to use the full SAQ-A version – and not the short form of SAQ. This increased the possibility of including items that staff found less appropriate – with a correspondingly larger proportion of missing responses to these items. However, this nursing home study is part of a larger patient safety climate study in different services of Norwegian primary care, and we have decided to use the full SAQ-A version in all the services.</p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have to recognize that the 17% of employees who were not Norwegian native speakers may have had difficulties understanding the statements in the questionnaire. We do not know the country of origin for these respondents; language problems would probably be less among those coming from other Scandinavian countries.</p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As far as we know, this is the first systematic study of the psychometric properties of the SAQ-A in Norwegian nursing homes. It is a strength that the study was done in both small and large nursing homes. Comparisons of safety cultures are now possible as the SAQ-A instrument has been validated and adapted to different sectors of the primary healthcare services.</p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Cronbach alphas for the total model (0.873) and for two of the six factors, Safety climate (0.700) and Job satisfaction (0.754), were considered good (≥ 0.70). For the remaining four factors, Teamwork climate (0.626), Stress recognition (0.672), Working conditions (0.673) and Perceptions of management (0.695), the Cronbach alphas were acceptable (≥0.60) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. These values demonstrate the internal consistency of the total model and the individual factors. The Norwegian translation of the SAQ-A adapted for nursing homes is an appropriate instrument for the study of patient safety climate in this setting.
 </p>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The responses in our study tended to be skewed towards the favorable side of the scale, reflecting a positive attitude to patient safety. Still, as studies have shown that safety culture in nursing homes may be poorer than in other parts of the health services [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>], and nursing home patients are particularly vulnerable to adverse events, it is important to address safety issues and medical errors also in this primary care setting. By measuring safety attitudes among the employees, it is possible to identify specific threats on the nursing home ward level.
 </p>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have previously studied the psychometric properties of the SAQ-A in Norwegian out-of-hours clinics and GP practices [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. In that study, the following five factor model was shown to have acceptable goodness-of-fit values in the confirmatory factor analysis: Teamwork climate, Safety climate, Job satisfaction, Working conditions and Perceptions of management. These five factors were also confirmed in the nursing home setting. In addition, Stress recognition had acceptable goodness-of-fit values in nursing homes, but this factor was not confirmed in the GP practice or out-of-hours settings in Norway.
 </p>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite a large degree of similarities across different health services within and between countries, important site-specific differences exist. For that reason, it is important to investigate the psychometric properties of the SAQ instrument, both in different countries and in different clinical settings in hospital and primary care.</p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although authors state a correlation between patient safety culture and risk of adverse events [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>], there are studies in which an association was not found [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>]. This underlines the need of further studies to investigate whether such an association applies to the nursing home setting. This was, however, beyond the scope of the present study.
 </p>
 <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SAQ may be used to compare results before and after interventions. It also gives the possibility of comparing the relative prevalence of wards with good patient safety climate scores across institutions. This may help leaders to support health professionals in reducing the risk of medical errors. Nursing home leaders have the responsibility to encourage employees to be open about possible risks and adverse events by cultivating a “no-blame no-shame” culture. It is also important to compare safety climate across the varying services in primary and hospital care, in order to identify safety improvement strategies that can be used in different clinical settings.</p>
</sec>
