<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oceans provide enormous benefits to people (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). Each year, more than 80 million metric tons of seafood is harvested, providing more than 20% of needed animal protein to nearly 3 billion people and livelihood to 10% of the global population (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). However, climate change is already compromising these benefits through changes in both stock productivity and location (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). Previous estimates of climate change impacts on the world’s fisheries have focused on the direct effects of ecosystem-level changes by comparing maximum potential food production today with that in the future (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). While instructive for assessing what could theoretically be possible, focusing on changes in maximum potential food production alone overlooks the effects of alternative human responses to climate change, which could either limit or exacerbate ecosystem changes. The actions of fishermen, management institutions, and markets can all influence the magnitude of fisheries benefits obtained from an ecosystem (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). Here, we ask: What are the potential benefits of adaptive fisheries management reforms that address anticipated consequences of changes in species productivity and distribution due to climate change? We examine how future global biomass, harvest, and profit of the world’s fisheries might change over time if a range of potential human responses and climate change are considered together.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considerable scope remains for increasing global fisheries yield, conservation, and profitability by improving current fishery management (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>), but climate change could compromise these potential upside benefits (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>). Although climate effects are diverse, the impacts on global fisheries can be clustered into two broad categories: changes in stock productivity, which affect potential yields and profits, and changes in stock distributions, which affect where fish can be caught and who might catch them. These changes pose distinct management challenges. Responding to changes in fisheries productivity requires harvest policies that are appropriately adaptive to changing demographics. For example, banded morwong and many other species in the Tasman Sea have already experienced noticeable changes in their population sizes driven by rapid warming (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>). Failure to adequately address these changes can further exacerbate management failures. By contrast, changes in species distributions (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>) can move stocks into and out of management jurisdictions, such as countries’ exclusive economic zones (EEZs), altering management jurisdiction and incentives for those stocks. A perceived or anticipated decline of a stock due to a range shift out of one country creates an incentive to overharvest before it leaves the nation’s waters (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>). In contrast, as a stock enters a new EEZ or the high seas, a new and potentially unmanaged fishery emerges. If left unaddressed, these range shift challenges can drive overharvesting, even in fisheries that are currently managed effectively. For example, until 2009, North East Atlantic mackerel was well managed under a trilateral agreement between Norway, the Faroe Islands, and the European Union. However, because of shifts in migration patterns, Iceland suddenly became a key contender in the fishery and maximized its newfound access to a valuable fishery. Since countries could not agree on appropriate quota allocations, management was compromised. By 2010, mackerel harvest was 40% above safe biological recommendations (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>). Solving these stock movement challenges requires the proactive development of effective transboundary institutions (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explore the potential range of human responses to climate change, we analyze four management scenarios that bound human responses to the dual challenges of range and productivity shifts: (i) Full Adaptation, (ii) Range Shift Adaptation, (iii) Productivity Adaptation, and (iv) No Adaptation. The Full Adaptation scenario assumes that management addresses both productivity and range shift challenges. Thus, we apply an economically optimal harvest policy that maximizes long-term economic benefits to each stock (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). This dynamic harvest control rule optimally adjusts fishing mortality on the basis of available biomass and is therefore naturally adaptive to climate-driven productivity changes. In this scenario, we assume that management also addresses challenges posed by shifting stocks (for example, through new proactive institutions, such as effective transboundary agreements), ensuring that effective management does not degrade because of spatial shifts. Therefore, under this management scenario, all species, including those expected to shift across management boundaries, are managed with an optimized harvest control rule. Conversely, the No Adaptation scenario assumes that neither climate challenge is addressed. In this scenario, the current fishing mortality rate is initially applied to all stocks but is only maintained for those that do not shift across EEZs. Management for those that shift gradually transitions to open access, where fishing mortality is driven by short-term profits. Both the looming departure of a stock and the emergence of a new stock motivate this shift in management. The length of this transition for each stock depends on how quickly it is expected to experience a range shift across EEZs. The Full Adaptation and No Adaptation scenarios bookend the possible future outcomes for global fisheries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two intermediate scenarios separately address one of the two challenges explored in this paper. The Range Shift Adaptation scenario assumes that management addresses challenges posed by shifting stocks but lacks a response to changes in productivity. Under this management scenario, the current fishing mortality rate is maintained for all stocks, as it ensures that current management does not degrade because of spatial shifts and does not benefit from an optimal harvest rule. Productivity Adaptation manages for fisheries productivity changes that affect population dynamics and potential yields but takes no actions to address range shift challenges. Therefore, the economically optimal harvest rule is only applied to species for which climate change is not expected to cause border crossings. For all other stocks, we apply a harvest rule that gradually shifts from the economically optimal fishing mortality rate to the rate expected under open access (see the “Policy alternatives” section in the Supplementary Materials for details on all policies). These management scenarios, while broad and, in some cases, idealistic, can provide general insights into how a range of approaches to climate challenges might affect future biomass, harvest, and profit.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We apply the appropriate harvest rates prescribed by these four management alternatives to 915 single- and mixed-species stocks across the globe that have adequate data to both assess their current status and forecast their future distributions. The majority (779) consist of stocks of individual species (species stocks). The remainder (136) are mixed-species aggregations (NEI stocks—Food and Agriculture Organization Not-Elsewhere Included fisheries). Cumulatively, these 915 species stocks or NEI stocks (hereafter collectively referred to as “stocks”) represent 67% of total current global catch (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Changes in range for each species, projected under four different greenhouse gas concentration pathways [Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs)] (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>), determine how climate change will likely affect each stock’s productivity and spatial range under several future climatic scenarios (table S1). We focus mostly on the moderately high-emission scenario, RCP 6.0, under which global mean temperature is expected to increase by 2.2°C by 2100 (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
