<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-microorganisms-07-00260" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microbes are ubiquitous on Earth and have colonized the most hostile and improbable environments, including snow [
  <a rid="B1-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-microorganisms-07-00260">1</a>], glacial ice [
  <a rid="B2-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-microorganisms-07-00260">2</a>] and permafrost [
  <a rid="B3-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-microorganisms-07-00260">3</a>]. Microbiologists have studied their adaptations and how various environments imposed them onto these small living creatures [
  <a rid="B4-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-microorganisms-07-00260">4</a>]. Interactions between various microbes and between microbes and other organisms have also been extensively studied [
  <a rid="B5-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-microorganisms-07-00260">5</a>]. However, how microbes impact the chemistry and the physics of their environment have received comparatively little attention. The case of snow chemistry is particularly interesting because changes in snow chemical composition, whether caused by photochemistry, dark chemistry, or microbes, also have the potential to affect atmospheric composition and hence climate [
  <a rid="B6-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-microorganisms-07-00260">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-microorganisms-07-00260">7</a>], as well as the carbon budget of the cryosphere [
  <a rid="B8-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-microorganisms-07-00260">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-microorganisms-07-00260">9</a>]. Regarding snow studies, microbiologists have expectedly focused on their field and have characterized microbial assemblages and quantified populations [
  <a rid="B10-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-microorganisms-07-00260">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-microorganisms-07-00260">11</a>]. They have considered the availability of nutrients but have paid little attention to the impact of microbial metabolism on snow chemical composition and reactivity. In parallel, snow chemists have likewise focused on their own field and interpreted the chemical composition and reactivity of the cryosphere in terms of chemical reactions [
  <a rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-microorganisms-07-00260">12</a>] while often ignoring the possible impact of microorganisms. Arguably, too few interactions have taken place between these two scientific communities. The purpose of this short note, which is not an exhaustive review, is to illustrate with selected examples that snow and atmospheric chemistry may be significantly dependent on microbial activity. My purpose is to stress the need for greater interactions between snow chemists and microbiologist to understand these issues, which also have implications for the climate. Indeed, in the current climate change context, the cryosphere and in particular the snow is one of the most affected media [
  <a rid="B13-microorganisms-07-00260" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-microorganisms-07-00260">13</a>]. I therefore argue that understanding how climate change will impact microorganisms and how these may in return feedback on the climate through their effect on snow and atmospheric chemistry requires highly interdisciplinary collaborations.
 </p>
</sec>
