<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a generalized additive mixed model (GAMM) with a binomial distribution to determine whether the percentage of radiocollared polar bears using land ≥21 consecutive days versus remaining on the sea ice changed over time. We chose the threshold of ≥21 consecutive days because it has been used previously [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref035">35</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref038">38</a>] to describe long-term use of land and thus allows for comparison to our study. Based on the previously described analysis of CRAWL-derived locations, we coded land use or lack thereof by individuals as a binary response variable (i.e., 1 = individual used land, 0 = individual did not use land). Year was analyzed as a fixed effect, but because some individual bears were radiocollared in multiple years, we used individual as a random factor. We also calculated the mean annual percentage of radiocollared bears with long-term land use, and used a piecewise general linear regression procedure [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref039">39</a>] with a normal distribution to determine if and when there was a discontinuity (i.e., breakpoint) in the mean annual percentage detected on shore over the 29 years of study. Parameters estimated for the piecewise regression included the intercept, change in slope prior to the breakpoint, and change in slope after the breakpoint [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref039">39</a>]. We did not include collar type (Argos and GPS) as a variable in subsequent analyses, though it is possible that improvements in satellite collar technology could represent a confounding factor. However, while the ability to accurately estimate the true day of arrival on land and departure back to ice should be better with GPS-era collars, the Argos-era data should not be biased toward estimating either longer or shorter land tenures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the relationship between the phenology of onshore use by radiocollared bears and sea ice dynamics, we used linear mixed models to examine the influence of sea ice conditions and characteristics on the annual mean timing of arrival on shore, length of stay on shore, and timing of departure from shore back to the sea ice. For this analysis, we included bears that came ashore for ≥7 consecutive days and used ordinal dates of arrival and departure, and total days spent on shore as response variables. We used the ≥7 consecutive days threshold to exclude bears that used land incidentally. Because we sampled some of the same individuals repeatedly, we included individual identity as a random factor in the models with first-order autocorrelation as a covariance structure. We used restricted maximum likelihood (REML) methods for model estimation. When modeling timing of departure, we censored individuals that entered maternity dens on land. Predictor variables included measures of &gt;15% and &gt;50% sea ice concentrations over the continental shelf (e.g., Mn&gt;15%, Mn&gt;50%), distance from the shelf of &gt;15% and &gt;50% sea ice (Mdis&gt;15%, Mdis&gt;50%), and length of the open water season defined as the periods of time when sea ice concentration remained ≤15 or ≤50% (OW15%, OW50%).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We developed, 
  <span class="italic">a priori</span>, sets of biologically plausible candidate models (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0155932.s001" href="#pone.0155932.s001">S1 Table</a>) and used Akaike’s information criterion values [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref040">40</a>] corrected for small sample bias (AIC
  <sub>c</sub>) to aid in determining top models. We used AIC
  <sub>c</sub> to rank and compare models based on ΔAIC
  <sub>c</sub> and normalized Akaike weights 
  <span class="italic">w</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> and considered models with ΔAIC
  <sub>c</sub> values &gt;2.0 to measurably differ in information content [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref041">41</a>]. When faced with model uncertainty, we calculated 85% confidence intervals (CI) for parameter estimates to avoid unnecessarily discarding variables in models supported by lower AIC
  <sub>c</sub> values [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref042">42</a>]. Following Arnold [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref042">42</a>], we considered parameters whose 85% CI overlapped zero to be uninformative. We assessed multicollinearity of predictor variables using variance inflation factors (VIF) and removed a correlated variable from a given model when VIF &gt;10 [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref043">43</a>]. We used normal probability plots and coefficients of correlation to ensure that model variables were normally distributed and assessed fit using measures of model deviance [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref044">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the paired sets of annual aerial surveys to investigate whether the availability of bowhead whale remains influenced polar bear distribution. We pooled data among years from surveys conducted before and after whale remains were placed at carcass aggregation sites (Point Barrow, Cross Island, and Barter Island). We used Moran’s I statistic to test the hypothesis that polar bear sightings were spatially autocorrelated (i.e., individuals were not randomly distributed) and an ArcGIS to determine the Euclidean distance of each bear sighting to the closest carcass aggregation site. We then used a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test to determine if the distribution of distances from carcass sites differed between survey sessions― i.e., whether the spatial distribution of bears differed prior to and after the stocking of carcass sites. Statistical significance for these tests was set at α = 0.05.</p>
</sec>
