<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical (i.e., pre-2000) use of terrestrial habitat during the open-water season by SB polar bears was relatively rare and limited to short durations [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref045">45</a>]. Recently, land-use behavior has become more prevalent, although a majority of the SB subpopulation still remains on the sea ice during summer. We detected clear trends over time of 1) an increasing percentage of polar bears coming ashore (the percentage tripled from 2000–2014), 2) earlier dates of arrival (advancing at a rate of ~ 5 days/decade), 3) later dates of departure (~7 days later/decade), and 4) longer tenure on land (increased at a rate of ~7 days/decade). Further, increased use of terrestrial habitat was related to declines in sea ice extent and changes in sea ice phenology. Since the late 1990s, the duration of the open-water season in the SB increased by an average of 32 and 36 days based on &gt;50% and &gt;15% sea ice concentrations over the continental shelf, respectively, while the amount of time spent on land increased by ~3 weeks. Our results are consistent with other recent work showing increased land use by polar bears from the adjacent Chukchi Sea subpopulation over roughly the same time period [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref038">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relatively infrequent historical use of land by SB polar bears was likely due to the persistent availability of sea ice over the continental shelf, even during the period of minimum sea ice extent in September. Since the late 1990s, the duration of the open-water season in the SB increased by an average of 66% or 82% (depending on sea ice concentration threshold), while the September average distance from shore to pack ice increased by 120%. Since the 2000s, the length of the open-water season has increased at a rate of ≈9 days/decade, which is among the largest rates of increase for the seas of the Arctic Ocean [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref014">14</a>]. From 2006 to 2014, the distance from shore to September pack ice has increased an additional 65%, which placed the leading edge of the ice an average of 450 km from the continental shelf. Polar bears prefer to forage from sea ice over shallow, biologically productive continental shelf waters [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref013">13</a>]. The lengthening period of sea ice absence over the shelf during summer equates to an increasing loss of preferred foraging habitat. Evidence suggests that displaced polar bears are increasingly coming ashore in response to this loss of sea ice habitat.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous work in the SB [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref015">15</a>] and elsewhere (e.g., WH; [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref020">20</a>]) has found that the timing of arrival of bears on shore was associated with sea ice dropping below a 50% concentration. More recently, Cherry et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref046">46</a>] evaluated multiple sea ice concentration thresholds in WH and determined that dates of arrival were best correlated with the timing of 30% sea ice concentration, while departure occurred after ice concentrations reached &gt;10%. Our findings, that the availability of sea ice concentrations &gt;15% (but &lt;50%) are best correlated with the timing of arrival, length of stay, and timing of departure of SB bears, is qualitatively similar to the findings of Cherry et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref046">46</a>]. It appears that in both subpopulations, polar bears delay the transition from ice to shore until ice drops below a concentration where its use as a reliable substrate is untenable. Interestingly, our finding of an inverse relationship between timing of arrival and concentration of &gt;15% ice over the shelf suggests that bears may come ashore before widespread disappearance of low concentration ice in order to avoid long-distance swims [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref047">47</a>]. Collectively, our findings provide important quantitative evidence of the relationship between sea ice phenology and use of terrestrial habitat by polar bears. Monitoring the timing and rate of seasonal ice disappearance may be an effective, logistically tractable way for managers and industry to prepare for the annual arrival of bears on shore.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found a notable increase in the proportion of radiocollared bears coming ashore in summer and fall beginning in the year 2000. From 2004 to 2007, there was a pronounced decline in the survival of SB polar bears, followed by two years (2008–2009) of apparent stability [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref026">26</a>]. The declines and subsequent stability of survival and abundance occurred as use of terrestrial habitat was increasing. While there is no causal link between the patterns in polar bear vital rates and increased use of terrestrial habitat, there is precedence in other species for behavioral shifts ameliorating some of the adverse effects of rapid environmental change. For example, Charmentier et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref048">48</a>] found that individual adjustment of behavior allowed a population of great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) to closely track changes in prey phenology and maintain the temporal match between clutch hatch date and peak availability of prey. This suggests that behavioral adjustments that closely track key phenological shifts may lessen some impacts of rapid environmental change, at least in the short term. The decision by some polar bears from the SB to exploit terrestrial habitat, rather than remain with the retreating pack ice, appears to be a behavioral response to the loss of sea ice habitat over the continental shelf. This behavior is not necessarily surprising since other subpopulations where the sea ice completely melts every summer (e.g., WH, southern Hudson Bay, Foxe Basin, and Davis Strait) display greater use of land along with flexibility in foraging behavior [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref049">49</a>]. In the near-term, whether bears benefit from this behavioral flexibility will likely hinge on the trade-off between the availability of food resources (and net energetic benefit), and the risks associated with accessing them, such as increased exposure to human-related activities, competition with grizzly bears (
  <span class="italic">Ursus arctos</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref050">50</a>], and increased potential for disease transmission [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref051">51</a>]. However, for polar bears to benefit over the long term, behavioral flexibility will have to result in adaptations to environmental change on a sufficiently fast time-scale to result in evolutionary rescue [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref052">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distribution data obtained from aerial surveys suggests that bowhead whale bone piles are focal attractors for bears on shore. Rogers et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref053">53</a>] found evidence of a shift in foraging behavior by some SB polar bears marked by fidelity to the nearshore region in winter and spring and consumption of bowhead whale tissue during summer and fall. It is likely that most bowhead whale tissue is consumed by bears visiting sites that have been stocked with remains following fall whaling [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref054">54</a>], though scavenging on beach-cast whales also occurs. Nevertheless, the difference in the biomass of marine mammal food resources available to bears on shore is an important distinction between the SB and the previously mentioned five subpopulations of polar bears that have historically used land in summer. For the latter, entire subpopulations come ashore when the annual ice melts completely each summer and bears enter a hypophagic state until the ice reforms in the fall [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref055">55</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref056">56</a>]. In WH, the open water season lasts upwards of 4 months (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref057">57</a>]) and model-based estimates, that assume polar bears fast while on shore, suggest that an increase beyond 5 months could trigger substantial declines in reproductive potential and survival ([
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref058">58</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref059">59</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref060">60</a>] but see [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref061">61</a>]). Currently in the SB, bears are spending upwards of 2.5 months on shore and usually have access to bowhead whale remains for the latter portion of that period. If the trends of increasing use of terrestrial habitat and lengthening open water season continue in the SB, then any relative benefits of scavenging bowhead whale remains should diminish over time (assuming biomass available to bears remains consistent).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increased use of terrestrial habitat and exploitation of human-provisioned resources by polar bears has attendant risks, including a greater potential for human-polar bear interaction and conflict. Wildlife-human conflict can have wide-ranging effects, including adversely impacting wildlife populations, causing economic losses to stakeholders, and endangering public safety [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref062">62</a>]. The north coast of Alaska includes several villages and an industrial footprint associated with oil exploration and extraction activities, all of which are in relatively close proximity to bowhead whale remains sites (particularly at Barter and Cross Islands) where the majority of bears were detected during aerial surveys. Human-wildlife conflicts are often clustered in space and time (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref063">63</a>]) due to the availability and distribution of focal attractors. Given that the extent of summer sea ice is projected to decline through the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref064">64</a>], terrestrial habitat and human-provisioned resources are likely to become increasingly important for SB polar bears. Bears that are highly motivated to obtain food appear more willing to risk interacting with humans (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref065">65</a>]), and the increased frequency of bears on land, coupled with expanding human activity due to retreating sea ice, is expected to lead to greater human-polar bear interaction and conflict. Proactive management of human-polar bear interactions will be needed to reduce the future risk of conflict.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study suggests that SB polar bears have become more reliant on terrestrial habitat. Since the mid-2000s, the estimated proportion of the SB subpopulation coming ashore [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref015">15</a>] has increased substantially and the behavior should no longer be considered trivial, even though the majority of the subpopulation still remains with the sea ice during the open-water season. Indeed, there is reason to hypothesize that use of terrestrial habitat may be adaptive, at least for the short-term. When summer sea ice persists in the SB, it is now relegated to the deep water of the polar basin which is less biologically productive than the continental shelf region. As a result, polar bears that remain with the ice may have fewer opportunities to encounter ringed (
  <span class="italic">Pusa hispida</span>) and bearded seals (
  <span class="italic">Erignathus barbatus</span>), which may explain reports of increased frequency of fasting, decreased kill rates [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref066">66</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref067">67</a>], and declining body condition [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref024">24</a>]. By contrast, polar bears that come ashore and scavenge bowhead whales may be able to maximize energy intake while minimizing energy expended, thereby reducing the likelihood of fasting and staving off declines in body condition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polar bears have evolved preferences for sea ice habitat and preying on marine mammals. In the SB, those preferences are informing two seemingly disparate strategies for coping with the loss of summer sea ice habitat: displace to shore and scavenge on predictably-available marine mammal food, or remain with the sea ice as it retracts over the polar basin and risk nutritional restriction [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref012">12</a>]. Human-induced rapid environmental change is having profound effects on the quality and quantity of Arctic sea ice [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref068">68</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref069">69</a>], which will likely make it difficult for polar bears and other ice-adapted species to reliably select suitable habitats for maintaining fitness [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref070">70</a>]. Behavioral plasticity is the initial response to dramatic environmental perturbations, followed by transmission of innovative behaviors within and across generations, eventually leading to evolution of the behavioral response over time [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref071">71</a>] and, perhaps, evolutionary rescue [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref052">52</a>]. However, behavioral plasticity may be an effective response by polar bears only if the rate of environmental change does not outpace transmission of behavioral innovations.
 </p>
</sec>
