<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The long-term persistence of polar bears (
  <span class="italic">Ursus maritimus</span>) is linked to the health of the Arctic marine ecosystem, particularly the availability of sea-ice habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref002">2</a>]. Polar bears are specialist carnivores that rely on sea ice to meet a number of life history needs including accessing prey, searching for mates, and establishing maternal dens [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref003">3</a>]. However, the Arctic region is experiencing a warming trend that is driving pronounced changes in sea ice extent and structure. Since 1979, sea ice extent and volume during summer have declined at rates of ≈14%/ and 28%/decade [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref004">4</a>], respectively, with the most pronounced change occurring over the last 15 years. Arctic warming will likely continue for several decades given the current trends in global greenhouse gas emissions [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref005">5</a>] and the lag times associated with global climate processes attaining equilibrium [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref006">6</a>]. Hence, climate-induced effects on sea ice and polar bears will continue for several decades, or longer, if global greenhouse gas emissions are not reduced.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of individuals to modify their behavior has been posited as the primary mechanism by which some animal populations have responded to climate-driven changes in their environment [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref007">7</a>]. The best documented examples of behavioral modification in response to altered physical environments have involved changes in spatial distribution and phenological shifts (i.e., the seasonal timing of animal and plant activities, sensu [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref008">8</a>]). For example, Perry et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref009">9</a>] documented northward shifts in distribution for a group of North Sea fishes in response to increased sea temperature. Parmesan and Yohe [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref010">10</a>] examined over 800 terrestrial species and detected distributional shifts in approximately half: 80% of those shifts were poleward with most being influenced by the advancement of the spring season. However, species that occur at environmental extremes, such as Arctic endemics, have little opportunity to modulate climate-warming changes to their physical environment via shifts in distribution. Rather, they must display 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> plasticity in key behaviors or traits to cope with a changing climatic envelope.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a habitat specialist with a long generation time such as the polar bear, the rapidly changing physical environment can create a situation where the species becomes “trapped” by its evolved response to cues that are suddenly occurring in a novel context (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref011">11</a>]). As a result, entrenched behaviors could become maladaptive and eventually manifest at the population level as declining vital rates—unless the species possesses sufficient phenotypic plasticity to assess and respond to highly dynamic conditions. For polar bears, there is uncertainty concerning their capacity to exhibit behavioral plasticity relative to changing sea ice phenology and availability, particularly in areas of the Arctic where bears have historically spent the entire year on the sea ice. In those areas, the decision to remain with ice as it retreats well past biologically-productive shallow waters may lead to prey scarcity and nutritional restriction [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref012">12</a>]. By contrast, the decision to displace from retreating sea ice to shore could result in attraction to habitats that function as ecological traps because they contain inadequate resources or expose bears to novel risk factors. Understanding how polar bears respond to climate-driven displacement from primary habitat, and how this overlaps with exposure to known and novel threats, is critical to forecasting how they may fare in an increasingly dynamic environment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polar bears of the southern Beaufort Sea (SB) subpopulation have historically spent the entire year on the sea ice (with the exception of individuals that den on land), even when the pack ice retreated away from the coast to its minimal extent in September [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref013">13</a>]. However, over the last 15 years, the SB has experienced a marked decline in September sea ice extent, along with a pronounced lengthening of the melt season (i.e., period of time between sea ice break-up and freeze-up; [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref014">14</a>]). The dramatic changes in the extent and phenology of sea ice habitat have coincided with evidence suggesting that use of terrestrial habitat has increased. For example, Schliebe et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref015">15</a>] estimated that between 3.7 and 8.0% of polar bears from the SB were on land in a given autumn during 2000–2005, and that percentage increased when sea ice was farthest from the coast. In contrast to the SB, polar bears of the greater Hudson Bay region [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref016">16</a>], for example, historically spent significant periods of time on land (1–5 months) when ice completely melted each year. In general, populations in the Hudson Bay region have been demographically productive [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref017">17</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref018">18</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref019">19</a>], although an increase in the length of the ice-free season has resulted in a decline in the western Hudson Bay (WH) subpopulation [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref020">20</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref021">21</a>] followed later by apparent stabilization [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref022">22</a>]. In the SB, measured declines in polar bear body condition, productivity, and abundance have also been linked to declining sea ice habitat [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref013">13</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref023">23</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref024">24</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref025">25</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref026">26</a>]. It is unknown if the decline in productivity in the SB subpopulation is linked to increased use of land or to remaining on the sea ice as it retreats away from the biologically productive water of the continental shelf.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigated polar bears from Alaska’s SB subpopulation, where rapid environmental change may be driving a divergence in space use and foraging behaviors in the form of increased land use. Specifically, our objectives were to examine (i) the long-term trend in the use of terrestrial habitat, (ii) the influence of sea ice characteristics on the phenology of movement from sea ice to terrestrial habitats and back to ice, and (iii) the spatial distribution of bears while on shore. Last, we discuss potential cascading effects of behavioral divergence and how those effects may influence population dynamics in the SB through time.</p>
</sec>
