<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenology of onshore behavior</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used location data from radiocollared adult females from 1986 to 2014 to determine if bears used terrestrial habitat during summer and, if so, to generate estimates of mean date of arrival on shore, duration of time spent on shore, and mean date of departure from shore back to the sea ice. The majority of locations prior to 2010 were derived with the Argos System, and have variable levels of accuracy from &lt; 250 m to &gt; 1500 m (see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.argos-system.org/web/en/78-faq.php#faq-theme-55" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.argos-system.org/web/en/78-faq.php#faq-theme-55</span>). We filtered locations in an attempt to remove spurious locations by first removing all designations which had a high probability of being erroneous. We then applied the Douglas Argos-Filter algorithm [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref031">31</a>] using a maximum redundancy function set at 10 km and minimum rate (“minrate”) of movement set at 10 km/hr.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To integrate the GPS and filtered Argos location data, which varied both in accuracy and the temporal scale of collection, we employed the continuous time correlated random walk (CRAWL) model [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref032">32</a>] to develop predicted paths at a regularized daily time interval based on observed locations. The CRAWL model allows predicted paths to take into account variable location quality and sampling intervals. Thus, for Argos locations, we defined location accuracy based on accuracy designations for Telonics Argos collars (i.e., L3: 150 m, L2: 350 m, L1: 1000 m, L0: 1500 m; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.telonics.com/technotes/argosintro.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.telonics.com/technotes/argosintro.php</span>). Because location accuracies are not provided for locations with LA or LB designations, we provided conservative location accuracies; LA: 5,000 m, LB: 10,000 m. We assigned locations obtained from GPS collars an accuracy of 30 m.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the observed location accuracy and land use, we used the R [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref033">33</a>] package ‘crawl’ [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref031">31</a>] to implement the CRAWL model and predict daily polar bear locations from 1 July to 31 October period. We then associated predicted locations with buffered land coverages (described below) to determine if an animal was likely to be on land at that time. Because the CRAWL model does not provide meaningful results if observed locations are too temporally dispersed [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref034">34</a>], we excluded predicted locations that occurred between observed points separated by &gt;14 days. For bears that came ashore, we noted the ordinal date of arrival and departure, and calculated the total amount of time spent on shore. We then generated indices of the earliest and mean ordinal dates of arrival on shore, mean departure back to the sea ice, and length of stay on shore.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We determined if an animal’s location occurred on land by overlaying locations on one of two land coverages. The first layer was a digital elevation model (100 m resolution; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://data.eol.ucar.edu/codiac/dss/id=106.ARCSS301" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://data.eol.ucar.edu/codiac/dss/id=106.ARCSS301</span>; accessed 12 Aug 2014) for the North Slope of Alaska. While this layer covered the majority of land used by bears in this study, it did not provide coverage for eastern Canada. Thus, to account for land use in that region, we used the default continent shapefile found in ArcGIS (version 10.1, ESRI, Redlands, CA). Because neither land coverage had sufficient resolution to detect small barrier islands, which are known to receive significant use by polar bears during summer [
  <a rid="pone.0155932.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155932.ref035">35</a>], we buffered the land coverages by 5 km. We then determined which animal locations occurred within the 5 km land buffer and categorized those as predicted land locations. While this might have resulted in some bears not on land being classified as using land, this was unlikely to occur given that landfast ice is largely absent during this period. Thus, any animal observed within this buffer would most likely have used land at some point during that day.
 </p>
</sec>
