<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Changing climate in the subarctic is expected to increase the transport and availability of elements and basal nutrients via greater runoff into freshwaters from terrestrial zones, which has a major effect on ecosystem productivity. Dissolved organic carbon (DOC) is an important source of energy for clear water ecosystems (e.g., Pace et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>) and the availability of both DOC and phosphorous control primary production in subarctic freshwaters (e.g., Benson, Wipfli, Clapcott, &amp; Hughes, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Karlsson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). DOC concentrations have a dual role in controlling primary production in food webs, firstly as a carbon source and secondly by determining the photic depth of primary producers (Karlsson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). The “shading” effect of DOC has been suggested to be more important than the availability of phosphorous in influencing primary and secondary production in oligotrophic lakes (Karlsson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Increases in DOC in subarctic lakes in both Europe and North American have been predicted with climate change (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0210" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), such as a 65% increase to 3.3 mg C/L by 2100 (Larsen, Andersen, &amp; Hessen, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0128" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Such increases in DOC are linked to higher runoff from surrounding terrestrial habitats, expanding vegetation cover (and burning) and melting of permafrost releasing carbon into freshwaters (Jaffé et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Schädel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0166" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Schuur et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0169" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Combined temperature and nutrient increases in subarctic streams with climate change culminate in increased primary production, as shown from in situ stream experiments in Iceland (Gudmundsdottir, Olafsson, Palsson, Gislason, &amp; Moss, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
