<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place and temporal effects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place-to-place variations can be substantial (
  <a rid="pone.0138208.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g001">Fig 1B</a>). Other studies have found both systematic and idiosyncratic explanations for such place effects, reflecting characteristics of the local economy, history, environment and culture.[
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref018">18</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref019">19</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref025">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal variations over the years studied here have been smaller (
  <a rid="pone.0138208.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g002">Fig 2A</a>), with only weak seasonal and daily temperature effects. The latter finding fits the mixed conclusions of previous research, in which some authors report effects from ambient conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref042">42</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref043">43</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref044">44</a>], weather [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref045">45</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref046">46</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref047">47</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref048">48</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref049">49</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref050">50</a>] or climate trends [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref024">24</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref029">29</a>]. Other studies, however, find minor or nonexistent effects from weather or climate [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref051">51</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref052">52</a>]. These inconsistent results suggests that weather or climate effects tend to be minor and contingent, in contrast to the strong, ubiquitous effects of political orientation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The New Hampshire time series was initiated to monitor possible changes in public agreement with the scientific consensus on climate change. The relative 
  <span class="italic">lack</span> of change was an early, unexpected discovery. As the series lengthens, however, we see evidence of upward drift. Overall, New Hampshire public acceptance of anthropogenic climate change moved up about five points, from 53% in 2010 to 58% in 2015. This small but statistically significant (
  <a rid="pone.0138208.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0138208.t002">Table 2</a>) drift roughly agrees with yearly nationwide results based on other survey questions [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref004">4</a>]. That agreement on trends incidentally provides further encouragement for viewing the New Hampshire series as a proxy. Despite upward movement, both New Hampshire and national public opinion falls far short of the 97% consensus among climate scientists.
 </p>
</sec>
