<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="evl391-supl-0001" class="supplementary-material">
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S1</bold>. Geographic information for the populations of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> used in this experiment.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S2</bold>. Results of generalized linear mixed effects models for the effect of local vs. foreign origin on performance of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> in common gardens.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S3</bold>. Results of generalized linear mixed effects models of the effects of absolute precipitation and temperature differences on component lifestages of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S4</bold>. Results of generalized linear mixed effects models of the effects of being a within‐population cross vs. a between‐population cross, while accounting for effects of absolute precipitation and temperature differences.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S5</bold>. Results of generalized linear mixed effects models separately testing the effects of (A) genetic differentiation, (B) absolute midparent temperature differences, and (C) absolute midparent precipitation differences on performance of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> in common gardens.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S6</bold>. Results of generalized linear mixed effects models of the effects of genetic differentiation between parental populations on performance of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> in common gardens.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table S7</bold>. Results of generalized linear mixed effects models for the effect of local vs. foreign origin on performance of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> including covariates of absolute precipitation and temperature differences (Supporting information Analysis 2).
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Figure S1</bold>. Correlation of temperature and precipitation normals calculated over the years 1951‐1980 and 1984‐2013.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Figure S2</bold>. Temperature and precipitation normals calculated over the years 1951‐1980 and 1984‐2013, shown paired by site.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Figure S3</bold>. Distribution of climate differences of within‐ vs. between‐population crosses of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> relative to conditions during the experiment.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Figure S4</bold>. Lifetime fitness (seeds produced per seed planted) from populations of 
   <italic class="italic">Clarkia pulchella</italic> with foreign vs. local parents.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Figure S5</bold>. Regression estimates and predicted lifetime fitness of local populations (black) compared to foreign populations from warmer (red) and cooler (blue) provenances (Supporting information Analysis 1).
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Figure S6</bold>. Immature ovary length (measured in the field) correlates with seed set after hand pollination (n = 596 fruits, grey points).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="EVL3-3-55-s001.pdf" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption class="caption">
   <p class="p">Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
