<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results indicate that interspecific competition plays an important role in structuring the avian community of the Eastern Himalayas by causing altitudinal stratification. Our conclusions are derived from several lines of evidence, including phylogenetic relationships, trait data and spatial occurrence data. We interpret these results as occurring on multiple timescales. On a short timescale, there is a significant effect of morphological dissimilarity on the extent of spatial co-occurrences exhibited by a species. Moreover, closely related species pairs are more spatially segregated than would be expected under a null model. Among morphologically similar species pairs, the reduced co-occurrence is generated by two seemingly different mechanisms. Some species pairs have distinctly different elevational ranges and therefore co-occur rarely, with competition presumably playing a minor proximate role. Other species pairs appear to overlap broadly in elevational space, but exclude each other at smaller spatiotemporal scales and so are rarely found together, more indicative of direct competition. Further research is required to understand what explains these different strategies. We found that phylogenetic relatedness alone cannot explain it, as the age of a species pair’s most recent common ancestor does not predict the amount of co-occurrence relative to elevational overlap.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results also suggest that competition has played a role on longer timescales. Speciation driven by adaptive divergence can produce results that look facially similar to competition in a coexistence analysis [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref037">37</a>]. We do not believe that speciation itself is responsible for the pattern we observe, as Eastern Himalayan avifauna has been built up through cycles of allopatric speciation and secondary contact, with the closest relatives of most Eastern Himalayan species located outside the region [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref022">22</a>]. However, our results indicate that competition following secondary contact is a major driver of community assembly. We believe that species pairs that segregate to a large degree in elevational space, as discussed above, have evolved their ranges in response to competition occurring over a longer timescale. Our interpretation is bolstered by our findings that species’ morphological traits and elevational ranges do not seem to have evolved at random. When considering the phylogeny as a whole, morphological traits and elevational ranges are underdispersed, indicating conservatism around favored elevations and clade-specific morphologies. However, traits are divergent (overdispersed) across clades, indicating historical niche displacement along both morphological and thermal tolerance axes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Older studies on passerine diversification in this region have emphasized the importance of interspecies competition and niche differentiation, particularly among individual clades [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref026">26</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref027">27</a>]. Moreover, a recent community-wide analysis by Srinivasan et al showed competition to be a strong force in setting altitudinal ranges in the region [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref029">29</a>]. However, another recent study by Elsen et al has called the importance of competition into question in favor of abiotic considerations such as temperature [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref030">30</a>]. Our results align strongly with the Srinivasan et al study, showing that competition plays an important, if not exclusive, role in determining altitudinal range limits and structuring the community. Additionally, we suggest that this view can be reconciled with the Elsen et al study, as we find that differences in abiotic preferences are likely to be the result of past competition leading to niche displacement. Our work further indicates that there is an evolutionary tradeoff between selection for optimal morphologies corresponding to a clade-specific fitness peak, and selection for divergent morphologies within a clade that push species away from that peak. This can be seen in the fact that morphological trait values are more similar than would be expected from phylogenetic relatedness alone across the entire phylogeny, which may be explained by a convergence on a morphology suitable for general insectivory, the most common foraging mode for birds in the region [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref022">22</a>]. Conversely, species in the same genus are more different in their functional morphological traits than would be expected from relatedness alone. The same applies to elevational ranges, which are a proxy for thermal tolerance. We observe a general preference for middle elevations, which have more abundant resources, but species are appear to have been forced away from these more favorable conditions by competitive interactions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In cases where species pairs show similar morphologies and elevational preferences, yet do not co-occur on smaller scales, further work may elucidate what mechanisms are responsible. For example, studies on Andean birds have shown that aggressive responses to heterospecific songs are important in setting elevational range limits[
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref063">63</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref065">65</a>]. Additionally, there is some evidence that certain Sino-Himalayan species may display territorial responses to heterospecific song playback [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref066">66</a>], although strength of response to different but closely related species is quite variable. Songs may also reinforce range limits of species pairs whose elevational ranges barely overlap, and in fact song traits may experience selection for this purpose [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref067">67</a>]. However, it is worth mentioned that other Sino-Himalayan species show little response to heterospecific playback, and that field observations indicate that responses to playback are often highly species-specific [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref068">68</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref069">69</a>]. Other mechanisms may include fine-scale niche partitioning within an altitudinal band as a response to structural habitat features, differential susceptibility to parasites and/or diseases, and differences in the time of daily foraging or other activity that allow for increased elevational overlap despite morphological similarity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is also worth mentioning that while our results indicate that competition plays a strong role in influencing species’ range limits in this system, it does not exclude additional contributory factors. Species’ range limits are known to be controlled by a variety of factors (see e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref038">38</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref039">39</a>]). Some of these factors may mediate the way in which competitive species interactions play out across the landscape. For example, the species in this study have similar breeding phenologies linked to the onset of the monsoon season [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref049">49</a>]. This synchrony in phenology likely exacerbates the effects of competition. Additionally, the altitudinal migrations undertaken by many species may affect the strength of competitive species interactions outside the breeding season. Further research is required to elucidate the strengths of these other mechanisms in contributing to the determination of elevational range limits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the coming century, anthropogenic climate change is expected to cause extensive perturbations to ecosystems and communities [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref070">70</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref071">71</a>]. Several attempts have been made to predict the responses of avian communities to this challenge [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref072">72</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref073">73</a>]. One of the major challenges of these efforts is predicting the plasticity of species in their abiotic tolerances. However, there is some evidence that birds in montane environments tend to track their preferred climate space over time [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref074">74</a>]. Additionally, several species in the Eastern Himalayan avian community track their preferred climate space during seasonal migration [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref029">29</a>]. Our results further indicate that thermal limits of many species are a product of continuing selection and are reinforced by interspecies competition. This suggests that many species may be challenged by climate change, as spatial range shifts may be countered by the presence of parapatric closely-related species. This may prevent species from shifting their ranges, thus subjecting them to rapid changes in their abiotic environment. Continuing selection on their abiotic preferences may hamper their ability to adapt to these changes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considerable effort has gone into the application of species distribution modelling (SDM) to estimate the change in species’ spatial ranges in the face of climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref075">75</a>]. However, these attempts are generally limited to consideration of changes in abiotic conditions alone [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref075">75</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref076">76</a>]. Our results suggest that to accurately understand the effects of climate change on Himalayan avifauna, it is necessary to incorporate interspecies competition. If these competitive species interactions are omitted, predictions regarding the response of species to climate change are likely to be inaccurate. By correctly accounting for the effects of biotic interactions, we may more accurately predict the response of this remarkable system to the next century of rapid change, thus enhancing our ability to make critically required conservation decisions and helping to preserve it for future generations of researchers.
 </p>
</sec>
