<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For our 34 congeneric sister species pairs, we found that neither the competition coefficients nor the raw degree of elevational overlap were correlated with morphological similarity. This is in part due to the fact that species with little range overlap also have low calculated competition coefficients, since they are not expected to co-occur. Additionally, species that share a large portion of the elevational range may not co-occur at the scale of individual sites if they specialize on different microhabitat features (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g002" href="#pone.0217549.g002">2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g003" href="#pone.0217549.g003">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, when we examined range overlaps relative to our null expectations, we found a significant correlation with morphological differentiation. Spatial co-occurrence (SC) was found to be significantly correlated with the morphological difference between a species pair (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g005" href="#pone.0217549.g005">Fig 5A</a>; t = 2.59, df = 32, p = 0.014, r = 0.41). Species that differed more in morphology were expected to have more co-occurrence, and vice versa. This is persuasive evidence that competition plays a role in setting the altitudinal ranges of species at short temporal scales.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217549.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217549.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between morphological difference and elevational overlaps for sympatric congeneric sister species pairs.</div>
   <p>(a) Spatial co-occurrence; t = 2.59, df = 32, p = 0.014, r
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.17. (b) Range-size corrected elevational overlap; t = 2.42, p = 0.021,r
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.15. In both cases, morphologically dissimilar species are expected to have greater overlaps in range. Open circles represent individual sympatric congeneric sister species pairs; dashed line indicates linear regression fit.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217549.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, range-size corrected elevational overlaps (RSCEO) were found to be significantly correlated with morphological differentiation, with morphologically distinct species showing greater than expected overlap (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g005" href="#pone.0217549.g005">Fig 5B</a>; t = 2.42, p = 0.021, r = 0.38). Moreover, observed elevational overlaps were significantly different from the null expectation based on elevational range size alone (paired student’s t-test; t = 2.06, df = 33, p = 0.047). It is worth noting that many species show greater than expected altitudinal overlap, i.e. a value of RSCEO greater than zero. This is likely due to the relationship between elevation and overall diversity, which peaks at mid-elevations and is thought to be driven by arthropod abundances [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref022">22</a>]. As a result, there is a significant benefit to birds residing at this elevation, causing greater elevational overlaps in species pairs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is generally thought that the strength of competition is higher amongst closely related taxa. When considering all pairwise congeneric comparisons, and not just sister taxa, corrected range overlaps were still significantly negatively correlated to morphological difference, although the correlation was lower than when only sister species were considered (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g006" href="#pone.0217549.g006">Fig 6</a>; t = 3.89, df = 153, p&lt;0.005, r = 0.29). As we examined more distantly related species, this correlation declined, providing empirical evidence to suggest that distantly related species do not appear to affect each other’s altitudinal ranges or functional traits (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g007" href="#pone.0217549.g007">Fig 7</a>); the correlation falls off quickly with divergence time.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217549.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217549.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between morphological difference and competition corrected range overlaps for all congeneric species pairs.</div>
   <p>Open circles represent individual congeneric species pairs (159 pairs); dashed line represents the best-fit linear regression. t = 3.75, df = 157,p&lt;0.005,r2 = 0.08.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217549.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0217549.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217549.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between divergence time between species, and the strength of the correlation between morphological difference and altitudinal overlaps for those species.</div>
   <p>Y-axis represents the r value for this correlation for all species pairs with a more recent MRCA than the X-axis value. As the X-axis increases, representing the inclusion of more distantly-related species pairs, the Y-axis value approaches zero. In other words, when including distantly-related species pairs, there is no correlation between morphological difference and altitudinal overlap. This implies that competition is only a factor between closely related species.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217549.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also found that when examining the entire phylogeny, there was evidence of non-random evolution of both morphological traits and central elevation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g008" href="#pone.0217549.g008">Fig 8</a>). We created a consensus tree based on our set of 1000 phylogenies. We used the PCA values for morphology to calculate a distance from centroid for each species. For the consensus tree, observed values of Moran’s I and Abouheif’s C
  <sub>mean</sub>, were significantly underdispersed when compared to 1000 randomizations for both morphology and central altitude; both measures always deviated in the same direction. We also calculated Moran’s I and Abouheif’s C
  <sub>mean</sub> for 100 randomly selected trees individual phylogenetic trees. In each case, the observed values of Moran’s I and Abouheif’s C
  <sub>mean</sub> were significantly different from values generated by randomization, indicating that phylogenetic uncertainty is insufficient to alter the overall pattern. The underdispersion of Moran’s I and Abouheif’s C
  <sub>mean</sub> indicate that related species are more similar than would be expected in the case of random noise. This pattern indicates that clades of species have evolved specialized morphologies corresponding to their ecological niches, foraging modes, etc. The observed underdispersion of the central elevation occupied by species is likely to be driven by the previously mentioned bias of species towards mid-elevations [
  <a rid="pone.0217549.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217549.ref022">22</a>], resulting in species having more similar elevational ranges than would be expected by chance alone.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217549.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217549.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Simulated and actual Moran’s I, all species, for (a) morphology and (b) elevation.</span> For morphology, the value for each species was taken to be its distance from centroid in principle component space after morphological variables. For elevation, the value for each species was taken to be the central elevation occupied by that species. Bars represent number of simulations out of a thousand resulting in a given value of Moran’s I; vertical line topped by diamond represents the observed value of Moran’s I. Positive values of Moran’s I indicate that species are more similar to their relatives than the null expectation.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217549.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taken individually, genus consensus trees with at least 3 species exhibited overdispersion of traits (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217549.g009" href="#pone.0217549.g009">Fig 9</a>). No single genus tree was significantly different from the null expectation, likely due to the relatively paltry number of species per genus. However, a sign test indicates that the median value for Moran’s I along both morphological and altitudinal axes is significantly less than zero (n = 24; for morphology, s = 2, p&lt;0.0001; for altitude, s = 2, p&lt;0.0001), providing support for the hypothesis of recent diversification in those traits. There was no indication of a tradeoff between divergence along each of these axes–in fact, there was a positive correlation between Moran’s I for morphological traits and Moran’s I for central elevation (t = 3.95, df = 22, p&lt;0.001, r
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.41). Qualitatively similar results were obtained from an analysis of a random sample of 100 individual trees; for all 100, values of Moran’s I clustered below zero for individual genera (p&lt;0.05 for all 100 sign tests for PC1 and altitude).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0217549.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0217549.g009</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between Moran’s I for PC1 and Moran’s I for central elevation.</div>
   <p>Negative values of Moran’s I indicate overdispersed traits, though all results are not significantly different from a null expectation. Open circles represent individual genera; dashed line indicates best fit linear regression (t = 3.95, df = 22, p&lt;0.001, r
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.41).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0217549.g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
