<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytochrome c oxidase</div>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">COXI,</span> complex IV, showed purifying selection in penguins, as has been observed across all Aves [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. We estimated Ka/Ks ratios close to zero for all comparison among species and genera, and similar results were obtained using both the SLAC and FEL methods. These genes from complex IV represent the terminal complex of the respiratory chain. It catalyzes electron transfer from cytochrome c to molecular oxygen, reducing the latter to water. It has been postulated that Complex IV of the OXPHOS, in which 
  <span class="italic">COX1</span> is one of the two catalytic subunits, has the property of intrinsic uncoupling [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>], through which it regulates and increases the coupling efficiency to produce ATP or heat. This mechanism is consistent with the negative selection observed for this gene, as adaptations can occur by changing the configuration of the protein, a mechanism that does not occur in complexes I and V.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further studies are required to completely understand the factors constraining the evolutionary rate of mitogenomes in penguins. Evolution of protein sequences depends on functional constraints including differential gene expression, protein folding and connectivity, functional importance, and expression breadth among tissues [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>]. Here, we discussed the implications of functionality of different mtDNA genes on the evolutionary rate of a protein. Alternatively, Zang and Yang [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>], suggest that this rate may be predominantly influenced by its expression level rather than functional importance.
 </p>
</sec>
