<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitogenomics and ecological-evolutionary hypotheses to explain selection</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are two hypotheses generally offered to explain patterns of mitochondrial genome evolution. The first is that temperature is a primary driver of selection and the evolution of mtDNA genes. For penguins, speciation and adaptation are seemingly strongly correlated with temperature differences of ocean water between the Antarctic and the tropics [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. The mitochondrial OXPHOS generates both energy and heat, with the balance of each depending on the coupling efficiency of the electron transport chain to the 
  <span class="italic">ATP</span> synthase activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Less efficient energy production and more heat production would be beneficial for survival in cold environmental conditions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. A reduced proton leak would lead to incremental cold sensitivity that effectively constrains the biogeographic distribution of species with this pattern of mtDNA variation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. Selection on mtDNA variation influencing mitochondrial bioenergetics would thus be plausible drivers of adaptation and speciation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>], and indeed we detected correlation between Ka/Ks from ND4 and sea suface water temperature which should be further investigated.
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second hypothesis is that the risk of starvation associated with restricted food availability (less abundant or less reliable food source) drives mtDNA gene evolution, since starvation can generate more efficient coupling of energy production by the OXPHOS pathway [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. Three mechanisms have been suggested for the evolution of starvation resistance and each may be influenced by mitochondrial diversity: (a) greater energy reserves (lipid stores); (b) reduced rate at which reserves are utilized; (c) and lowering of the minimal resources required for survival [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. Reducing energy requirements may occur by reducing ROS and heat production and thus increasing OXPHOS efficiency [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Chl can be considered to be a measure or correlate of primary productivity and therefore resource availability in the Antarctic marine food web. Penguins as top predators, are dependent on the productivity of lower trophic levels. Therefore, the high variation in productivity of the habitats throughout the 
  <span class="italic">Spheniscus</span> species distributional ranges may have led to the evolution of more efficient coupling in those species, compared to the stable environments of Emperor and Adélie penguins. For example, high variability in levels of Chl is observed within the range of 
  <span class="italic">S. humboldti</span>, and becomes further exacerbated during El Niño events, leading to a higher probability of mortality due to starvation. In this circumstance, selection may favor OXPHOS efficiency rather than heat production. During El Niño events, the upwelling of nutrients is interrupted, reducing food availability and increasing water temperature in Chilean-Peruvian waters [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>]. This affects fish abundance, causing increased Galapagos and Humboldt penguin mortality, nest desertion and large-scale movements [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>]. Although Chl could be an important variable for mtDNA evolution, only a weak correlation between Ka/Ks ratio of 
  <span class="italic">COXI</span> and Chl across small geographic scales was detected here. Therefore, our results should be further investigated in penguins not only at a species level, but also in populations of each penguin species across a gradient of sea surface temperatures (e.g. across latitudes) and chlorophyll levels.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although 
  <span class="italic">ATP8</span> was not correlated to SST and Chl here, the Ka/Ks ratio values were higher than in any other gene compared. Moreover, it showed a remarkable pattern for all comparisons among species distributed in extremely different environments (tropical and hot temperate climate versus polar climate). We found contrasting results for 
  <span class="italic">ATP8</span>. 
  <span class="italic">A. forsteri</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Spheniscus</span> had the lowest values for 
  <span class="italic">ATP8</span> genes in pairwise comparisons among all genera. This may be indicative of different mechanisms of adaptation among genes and species depending on their individual habitat requirements. However, we cannot discount the possibility that this gene is associated with other selective variables, which in turn are correlated with climatic and productive variations observed in the distributional ranges of penguins. Indeed, it was recently suggested that evolution of mitochondrial genes might be linked with pathogen variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An increasing number of studies have implicated mitochondria with innate immune responses, including the control of apoptotic signaling, sterile inflammation, and antibacterial and antiviral response [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Although it is uncertain what direct role mitochondrial encoded genes have in immune response, it bears further evaluation. Antarctica and the tropics differ considerably in virulence, ensemble, abundance, development and diversity of pathogens. Just recently, the influenza virus was detected in penguins in Antarctica [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>]. Antarctic wildlife is particularly susceptible to infectious agents because of its geographic isolation and extreme environment, which increases the likelihood that the fauna has evolved under low “pathogen pressure” and are thus immunologically naïve [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
