<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NADH dehydrogenase</div>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In metazoans, mitogenome complexes I through V are physically positioned relative to each other in accordance with their function, with the complex II genes residing in the nucleus [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>]. A positively selected codon was detected by SLAC model on the mitogenome of penguins in the Complex I or 
  <span class="italic">NADH</span> dehydrogenase gene (
  <span class="italic">ND4</span>). Complex I through IV generate the proton gradient in the intermembrane space of mitochondria. Complex I is the main entrance point of electrons and the largest complex of the respiratory chain. It catalyzes the transfer of two electrons from NADH to ubiquinone and translocates four protons across the inner mitochondrial membrane [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. Complex I consists of different protein subunits, with fourteen homologous subunits present in all organisms, and which constitute the enzyme.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ND1 and ND2 are situated at the connection between the peripheral and the membrane arm, whereas ND4 and ND5 are at the distal end [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>]. If ND2, ND4 and ND5 are the actual proton pumping devices [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>], mutations in these genes may alter the efficiency of the proton-pumping process. The concentration of codons under positive selection in specific domains of the mitogenome are very likely to be related to protein function [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>] and a meta-analysis of 237 vertebrates showed that most of the genes under positive selection were located in Complex I [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">NADH</span> dehydrogenase genes have also shown signatures of positive selection at a population level in birds (
  <span class="italic">Parus</span> spp.) in the 
  <span class="italic">ND2</span> gene [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>], in lineages of an Australian bird (
  <span class="italic">Eopsaltria australis</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>] in 
  <span class="italic">ND4</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ND4L</span>. Similarly the Chinese snub-nosed monkey (
  <span class="italic">Rinopithecus</span> ssp.) showed evidence of adaptive variation related with physiological hypoxia and cold stress in altitude in 
  <span class="italic">ND2</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ND6</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>]. Few studies have assessed if selection on mtDNA genes is correlated with environmental variables [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>]. In the Atlantic herring (
  <span class="italic">Clupea harengus</span>), significant positive selection was observed in 
  <span class="italic">ND2</span>, 
  <span class="italic">ND4</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ND5</span>. Correlations between genetic diversity and variation of environmental factors (temperature, salinity and latitude) were generally weak, although the authors addressed some correlation between temperature and genetic distances with 
  <span class="italic">ND3</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ND4L</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
