<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although our results show qualitatively a similar range expansion across the different climate change scenarios for this species, we caution that results from environmental niche models should be interpreted with some precaution. This is especially true for species with narrow geographical distributions or specialized habitat requirements like the velvet gecko and the quality of data use for characterizing their climate envelopes (see also 
 <xref rid="zox021-B204" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wisz et al. 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rebaudo et al. 2016</xref>). However, ENMs work on the assumption that a species is at equilibrium with its environment (i.e., a species is present in all suitable habitats and is absent from all unsuitable habitats (
 <xref rid="zox021-B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guisan and Thuiller 2005</xref>). Notwithstanding, the climatic niche at equilibrium of a species is limited by both the small-scale abiotic and biotic interactions (e.g., competition, predation, pathogens, dispersal limitations), which are rarely incorporated in ENMs (
 <xref rid="zox021-B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Le Maitre et al. 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guisan et al. 2014</xref>). Additionally, major weaknesses have been observed using WorldClim data to infer the thermal niche for small ectotherms (see 
 <xref rid="zox021-B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hannah et al. 2014</xref> and references therein). However, this topic is still highly debatable in scientific literatures as there are protagonists (
 <xref rid="zox021-B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hannah et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Storlie et al. 2014</xref>) as well as antagonists (
 <xref rid="zox021-B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bennie et al. 2014</xref>). In a recent analysis by 
 <xref rid="zox021-B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rebaudo et al. (2016)</xref>, they used 3 different climatic datasets at different spatial scales (i.e., WorldClim, weather station, and microclimatic) to calibrate species ENMs. They showed that models calibrated with microclimatic dataset predicted the observed abundance of the study species but was however less accurate than the WorldClim datasets when performed at a coarse scale. Therefore, in the absence of microclimatic datasets, WorldClim datasets are well suited for calibrating the thermal niche of small ectotherms, given that, the availability of microclimatic data sets still represents a major challenge to overcome (
 <xref rid="zox021-B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rebaudo et al. 2016</xref>). Nevertheless, we used WorldClim data to calibrate the thermal niche of the velvet gecko, but we further stress the point that ENMs provide only a probabilistic framework for a species’ potential distributions, which needs to be verified using empirical data on many factors acting in a synergetic manner to determine the realized niche of a species.
</p>
