<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conceptual Approach</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We structured this research using a vulnerability approach. Vulnerability can be defined as the “susceptibility to be harmed” (Adger 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2006</a>:269) with vulnerability research seeking to identify and characterize who is vulnerable, to what stresses, and why (Ford and Smit 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2004</a>). Contextual vulnerability considers the political, biophysical, social, and economic factors that interact to shape vulnerability and defines vulnerability as a function of exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity (O’Brien 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2007</a>; Wang 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2014</a>; Archer 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2017</a>); exposure captures the environmental changes affecting the ripening time, abundance and quality of berries; sensitivity reflects the livelihoods and other social, economic, and political characteristics of the community, and shapes the impacts of exposure, e.g., if there is a landslide caused by permafrost degradation (exposure), the effect on a community will be dependent on components of sensitivity such as the location of settlements, infrastructure, land use, and technology (Smit and Wandel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2006</a>); adaptive capacity reflects the potential ability of the community to plan for, address, or cope with exposure (Ford and Smit 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2004</a>; Smit and Wandel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2006</a>; O’Brien 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2007</a>; Bennett 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2016</a>), e.g., berry pickers may bring extra gasoline anticipating the need to visit multiple bakeapple picking grounds by boat. The response to these drivers of vulnerability in turn shapes and changes the initial conditions of vulnerability, and as a result, vulnerability is dynamic (Smit and Wandel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2006</a>; Ford 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2013</a>; Archer 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2017</a>; Fawcett 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2017</a>). Case studies are particularly important for identfiying the various factors affecting vulnerability and understanding how they interact together in particular places (Ford 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2010</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
