<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results highlight social and physical changes that impact bakeapple picking from the perspective of the Indigenous community in Cartwright, Labrador. Interviewees described changes in temperatures, vegetation, and the consequent impacts on bakeapples. The impacts of these environmental changes on families’ abilities to harvest bakeapples are magnified by socioeconomic impacts, including the closures of the inland fisheries and the resettlement program of the 1960s. However, the advent of the speedboat, the commercial market for bakeapples, the cultural and nutritional value families continue to place on bakeapples, and concerns with maintaining traditional cultural and ecological knowledge seem to reinforce families’ continued engagement in bakeapple picking.</p>
 <p id="Par65" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contextual vulnerability to climate change encompasses not only the environmental impacts associated with climate change but the concurrent social, political, and economic processes that determine how a given community experiences climate change (Ford and Smit 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2004</a>; Smit and Wandel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2006</a>; O’Brien 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2007</a>; Bennett 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2016</a>). Previous studies have described the contextual vulnerability of the land-based livelihoods of Indigenous communities in the Arctic (Ford 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2012a</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">b</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2015</a> Archer 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2017</a>), and our study also illustrates that social and physical constraints to ease of access to traditional bakeapple picking grounds can impact harvesting capacity as much as the actual ecological impacts of climate change on the resource.
 </p>
</sec>
