<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par59" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The exposures, described by Cartwright community members, parallel observations in other arctic and subarctic communities. Bakeapple pickers explained that variability in the timing and abundance of bakeapples is to be expected. Some bakeapple pickers observed that the timing of picking has been earlier in the past decade largely due to earlier warming temperatures in the spring and summer (see also Downing and Cuerrier 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2011</a>). Some interviewees described how tree and larger shrub growth has encroached on bakeapple patches. First Nation communities in the Yukon and Northwest Territories, Inuit communities in Nunavik, and Gwich’in communities have also observed new shrub and tree species at berry picking spots (Parlee 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>; Guyot 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2006</a>; Cuerrier 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2015</a>). Participants also observed that the berries ripen in a more fragmented way, are less abundant and smaller compared to when they were younger. A couple of participants attributed these changes to climate change. Climate change and vegetation growth have likely contributed to the decrease in palsas at The Big Marsh, consistent with trends seen in other permafrost-associated peatlands (Christensen 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2004</a>; Johansson 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2006</a>; Bouchard 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2014</a>). The observed fragmentation of bakeapple patches may also be related to changing permafrost conditions in bogs. From field surveys showing that vegetation types are significantly different across palsa and no permafrost plots, and from satellite imagery revealing a decrease in palsas, we can infer that with continued palsa degradation, the vegetation will change and eventually resemble the present vegetation of the surrounding no permafrost areas. One bakeapple picker from Cartwright attributed the fragmentation of bakeapple patches and less abundant bakeapples to more extremes in the weather, including precipitation. Other Indigenous communities note changes in the bakeapples themselves. First Nation communities have described precipitation that is resulting in smaller berries and less snow bringing fewer berries (Guyot 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2006</a>). In a Gitga’at community in British Colombia, residents explained that in recent years wild berries are scarce and attributed this to heavy rains (Turner and Clifton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Cartwright, bakeapple picking is tied to other harvesting activities, specifically fishing. Similarly, in Gwich’in First Nation communities the harvest of berries and fish occur at the same time (Parlee 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>). Other First Nation communities in British Colombia also harvest important plants, specifically edible seaweed, while fishing for salmon and halibut. As a result, any changes in the fishery have an impact on the harvesting of edible plants. In Cartwright resettlement impacted families’ land based livelihoods because it became more difficult for them to travel between their summer homes for fishing and berry picking and their winter homes. Similarly, resettlement programs also moved Inuit in Nunavut into permanent communities and ended their semi-nomadic way of living, which limited individuals’ ability to access hunting areas (Wenzel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2009</a>) and reduced the extent of harvesting areas and the availability of country food (Ford and Beaumier 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2011</a>). Resettlement, with subsequent sociocultural transformations, is an example of a slow variable that has resulted in a change in culture and livelihoods over the past half century in Indigenous northern communities (Chapin 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2004</a>; Ford 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">New technology has enabled Indigenous communities to continue living off the land despite social and environmental change. In Cartwright, owning a speedboat allows families to continue visiting bakeapple picking grounds. Similarly, the snowmobile allows individuals in Inuit communities in Nunavut to continue hunting despite living farther away from traditional hunting grounds (Wenzel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2009</a>). In Arctic Bay, Inuit use GPS and online sea ice reports to navigate changes in sea ice conditions (Archer 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2017</a>). Members of a Gitga’at community in British Columbia created technology to dry their seaweed and fish despite increased precipitation (Turner and Clifton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The market for bakeapples in Cartwright is a part of the adaptive capacity of the community in that it provides supplemental incomes and makes it more affordable for many families to continue bakeapple picking. Community members did not indicate that the market for bakeapples has threatened traditional sharing networks with family and friends. Similarly, Inuit communities in Greenland have had widespread positive experiences selling country food for 150 years (Ford 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2016</a>). In contrast, other Indigenous communities are concerned about the commercialization of traditional foods. For instance, in the Gwich’in settlement region, communities are concerned that commercializing wild berries will complicate traditional sharing networks (Murray 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2005</a>; Parlee 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2005</a>). Similarly, some Inuit communities in Nunavut have expressed concerns about the commoditization of country food in terms of traditional sharing networks (Ford 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2016</a>; Searles 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2016</a>; see also MacDonald 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cultural and nutritional value placed on bakeapple picking in Cartwright is also a key component of adaptive capacity. Other studies have documented the nutritional value that an Indigenous community in Alaska and an Inuit community in Nunavut also place on bakeapples (Downing and Cuerrier 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2011</a>; Kellogg 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2010</a>). However, there is concern in Cartwright that younger families spend less time or no time bakeapple picking. Other studies document similar concerns within Indigenous communities that traditional knowledge is not being passed to younger generations (Turner and Turner 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2008</a>; Beaumier 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2015</a>; Archer 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2017</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
