<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviews</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted semi-structured interviews with 18 individuals (Longhurst 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2003</a>) with an interview guide (Valentine 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">1997</a>) 
  <span class="italic">—</span> structured by the components of vulnerability (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The interviews lasted between 30 min to an hour. A purposive sampling strategy (Baxter and Eyles 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">1997</a>) was used to select participants with rich knowledge and experience of bakeapple picking and was implemented with the help of a respected and active community member and then via a snowballing strategy, in which interviewees suggested other potential participants. Interviews were conducted until a saturation of relevant information was reached.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Themes with corresponding component of vulnerability and sample questions from interview guide</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Themes</th>
      <th>Example questions</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Duration of time an individual has picked for</td>
      <td>About how many years have you been bakeapple picking?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="5">Observations of environmental changes at the bakeapple picking grounds (exposure)</td>
      <td>Have you noticed changes in the plant species where you pick bakeapples?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Have you noticed a change in the amount of surface water in the landscape?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>How much variability is there from year to year in the abundance and quality of bakeapples?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>What things have affected how good the bakeapples are in a particular year?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Has the timing of when pick bakeapples changed from your youth?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">Observations of social change related to bakeapple picking (sensitivity)</td>
      <td>What importance does bakeapple picking have to you currently as an adult and previously as a child?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>What does an average day of bakeapple picking look like now and as a child?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">Observations of economic change related to bakeapple picking (sensitivity)</td>
      <td>Do you sell the bakeapples that you pick?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Have job opportunities impacted your ability to go bakeapple picking?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Technology advances and impact on bakeapple picking (sensitivity)</td>
      <td>How do you get to the spots that you bakeapples pick now and is this different from your youth?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">The main barriers and reasons for bakeapple picking (adaptive capacity)</td>
      <td>What are your greatest barriers to go bakeapple picking? How do you deal with these barrier(s)?</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>What are the main reasons that you go bakeapple picking?</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviews were coded to identify the key components of the vulnerability of bakeapple picking to changes in the physical and social landscape. The 14 recorded interviews were transcribed (Bedford and Burgess 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2001</a>). For the four unrecorded interviews, annotations and memos related to the method or context were made on the transcriptions and on the interview notes (Dunn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2000</a>; Cope 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2003</a>; Corbin and Strauss 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2014</a>). Based on the emerging patterns, initial codes were created, and based on how they connected to the components of vulnerability secondary codes were generated (Cope 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2010</a>). Finally, we identified the emerging key themes based on the secondary codes and our knowledge of the literature (Saldaña 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2013</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
