<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coral reef ecosystems are complex aquatic systems structurally composed of scleractinian corals situated on the accumulated dead exoskeletons of their ancestors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Coral reefs are host to a diverse combination of organisms while offering a multitude of services to the population surrounding them. Each coral reef consists of the multiple base units–polyps–that over a large period of time develop into large coral reef ecosystems which often act as a magnet for both tourism and fishing.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A key asset for coral growth are zooxanthellae algae, which are unicellular organisms capable of photosynthetic processes. In coral reefs, zooxanthellae algae exist in a symbiotic relationship with coral polyps (although we note that zooxanthellae can also exist in isolation). In order to acquire nutrients, corals secrete a chemical signal causing the zooxanthellae algae in the coral tissue to release organic compounds created during photosynthetic processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. In return, zooxanthellae acquire nutrients such as nitrogen in higher densities via the coral excrement
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. This mutual feedback cycle promotes growth and development of both species.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historically, Caribbean coral reefs have been subjected to various stressors, such as coral disease and hurricane-induced destruction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. Despite the influence of these and other stressors, Caribbean coral reefs have demonstrated considerable resilience against past disturbances. For instance, Caribbean coral reefs began recovering quickly after Hurricane Allen over a 3 year period from 1980 to 1983
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. This resilience is widely attributed to the presence of its dominant grazers, the 
  <span class="italic">Diadema antillarum</span> sea urchins
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. The mutualistic relationship between the urchins and the coral reefs provided the urchin population with nourishment in the form of algal turf (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. However, the mass mortality of 
  <span class="italic">Diadema antillarum</span> in 1983, possibly on account of multiple stressors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, appears to have reduced the resilience of coral reefs and caused a period of decline in the face of stressors that reefs previously demonstrated resilience against, such as hurricanes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Parrotfish are now considered the primary grazers of the ecosystem, but overfishing of parrotfish has further reduced coral reef resilience, underscoring the need for effective conservation measures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Flowchart illustrating the basic dynamics of the coral reef ecosystem.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_20341_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e348" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Algal formations are detrimental to the integrity of coral reefs. Invasion of macroalgae is known to prevent reef growth due to their colonization of potential growth sites for new polyps. In the absence of grazing, macroalgal contact with corals have been known to cause higher levels of coral mortality and bleaching
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Multiple genera of these algae exist, but for this paper we only consider two species of macroalgae – 
  <span class="italic">Lobophora variegata</span> whose effects on the reefs induce heightened levels of coral mortality and an extended state of coral bleaching, and 
  <span class="italic">Dictyota</span> species which cause heightened coral mortality and rapid coral tissue deterioration
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mathematical modelling has been an invaluable tool for many decades, offering insight into real-world systems with applications ranging from classical predator-prey dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, to infectious disease dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Relatively detailed mathematical models with empirically-informed model structure and parameter estimates can be useful for predicting future population dynamics under various possible scenarios. However, even simple models can be useful for gaining potential insights into dynamics of ecosystems where the component species interact nonlinearly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Research on coral reef ecosystem dynamics has included mathematical models that explore the impact of various stressors on the coral reefs, including the effect of exploitation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Among other findings, these models predict that when predation/fishing of grazers is sufficiently low, the system exhibits a critical transition beyond which the growth and recovery of the ecosystem are possible
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Models typically treat human influence on coral reefs as constant and incorporate it through a fixed model parameter, such as fishing intensity. In contrast, coupled socio-ecological models (or equivalently, human-environment system models or coupled human-and-natural system models) formulate a separate dynamical equation for humans, and allow for human systems and ecological systems to influence one another. To capture the effect of dynamic human social behaviour, elements of evolutionary game theory have been previously employed in order to capture social learning dynamics, in which human opinions or strategies actively change based on the current condition of the environment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Humans are assumed to follow an imitation dynamic whereby individuals imitate more successful strategies they observe in other individuals. Models have already been established in ecosystem management
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, forestry/grasslands
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>, land-use change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> and vaccination
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> but have not been utilized modelling the dynamics of coral reef ecosystems, to our knowledge. For many systems, interactions between humans and natural systems is complex and do not need to be one-way
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. This approach of coupling human social dynamics to environmental or ecological dynamics contrasts with treating human behaviour as a fixed parameter, as in much previous research on coral reef dynamics, enabling us to model how human opinion about reef conservation and fishing restrictions responds to changes in coral reef cover.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of dynamic human behaviour on coral reef sustainability therefore requires further investigation via theoretical modelling. With evidence of various anthropogenic impacts reflected in current research together with ongoing efforts to promote reef conservation through marine protected areas and other measures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>, mathematical models of coral reef ecosystem dynamics can benefit from including a coupling to a human population with evolving opinions. By modelling human behavior as an adaptive, dynamically evolving phenomenon, a deeper and richer understanding of the anthropogenic stresses in a given system over longer time horizons–including potential surprises due to nonlinear interactions–can be achieved. With further development, this approach has the potential to assist developing more effective coral reef conservation by helping policymakers avoid counter-productive response by human populations and/or by harnessing processes like social learning to optimize conservation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we create a coupled socio-ecological coral reef model by combining an existing model of a Caribbean reef ecosystem including parrotfish fishing, with an imitation dynamic model of human opinion spread and behaviour. Our objective is to explore how adaptive human feedback influences the viability of coral reefs, and also to explore the potential dynamics that may emerge in a socio-ecological reef-opinion system that may not be recognized from studying these systems in isolation from one another. We use the model to explore the impact of social norms, sensitivity of the human population to coral loss, and social learning on the coral reef ecosystem. Through these investigations, the effect of social dynamics on the coral reefs are investigated, allowing us to explore potential conditions to improve the long-term viability of the Caribbean coral reef ecosystem.</p>
</sec>
