<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="nph14968-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Summary</title>
 <p class="p">
  <list list-type="bullet" id="nph14968-list-0001" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Local adaptation in tree species has been documented through a long history of common garden experiments where functional traits (height, bud phenology) are used as proxies for fitness. However, the ability to identify genes or genomic regions related to adaptation to climate requires the evaluation of traits that precisely reflect how and when climate exerts selective constraints.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We combine dendroecology with association genetics to establish a link between genotypes, phenotypes and interannual climatic fluctuations. We illustrate this approach by examining individual tree responses embedded in the annual rings of 233 
     <italic class="italic">Pinus strobus</italic> trees growing in a common garden experiment representing 38 populations from the majority of its range.
    </p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We found that interannual variability in growth was affected by low temperatures during spring and autumn, and by summer heat and drought. Among‐population variation in climatic sensitivity was significantly correlated with the mean annual temperature of the provenance, suggesting local adaptation. Genotype–phenotype associations using these new tree‐ring phenotypes validated nine candidate genes identified in a previous genetic–environment association study.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Combining dendroecology with association genetics allowed us to assess tree vulnerability to past climate at fine temporal scales and provides avenues for future genomic studies on functional adaptation in forest trees.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </p>
</abstract>
