<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0221057.s001" class="supplementary-material">
 <label class="label">S1 Appendix</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table A. Definition of the climate indices used</bold>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table B. Student’s t-test t-statistics for the most significantly different climate indices between the East Anglia and Mediterranean France regions in the UK and France respectively.</bold> Also shown are the t-statistics for the biology-related indices (
   <xref rid="pone.0221057.t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Indices included are significantly different at the 99% confident interval in a Student’s t-test. Refer to Table A for the description of the indices.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Table C. Student’s t-test t-statistics for the most significantly different climate indices between the East Anglia and Mediterranean France regions, in the UK and France respectively, in the baseline period and the biology-related indices (refer to 
    <xref rid="pone.0221057.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> and 
    <xref rid="pone.0221057.t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref> for more details).
   </bold> Indices included are significantly different at the 99% confident interval by the number of models shown in brackets. Refer to Table A for the description of the indices.* Note that only 4 of the 5 models reach GWL4 by 2100.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig A. Spatial distribution of percentage of month available for optimal development conditions from egg to adult (&gt;15°C) for the current climate observations, the climate model baseline and under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions</bold>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig B. Spatial distribution of percentage of month available for optimal survival conditions (&gt; = 20°C AND &lt; = 30°C) for the current climate observations, the climate model baseline and under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions</bold>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig C. Latitudinal transect showing the percentage of month (A: June, B: July, C: August) as cold as the 10</bold>
   <sup class="sup">
    <bold class="bold">th</bold>
   </sup>
   <bold class="bold">percentile cold days in Mediterranean France (under current climate conditions in the Mediterranean France region) under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions.</bold> The left-hand panels show the transects through France and the right-hand panels show the transects through the United Kingdom. The vertical shaded bars correspond to the regions for Mediterranean France and East Anglia as shown in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>. Latitudinal averages are constructed by excluding the Central Massif, the Alps, the Pyrenees, Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland from the datasets as high elevations are likely to hinder whitefly colonisation.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig D. Spatial distribution of percentage of month as cold as the 10</bold>
   <sup class="sup">
    <bold class="bold">th</bold>
   </sup>
   <bold class="bold">percentile cold days in Mediterranean France (under current climate conditions in the Mediterranean France region) for the current climate observations, the climate model baseline and under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions</bold>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig E. Latitudinal transect showing the percentage of month (A: June, B: July, C: August) as cold as the 10</bold>
   <sup class="sup">
    <bold class="bold">th</bold>
   </sup>
   <bold class="bold">percentile cold nights in Mediterranean France (under current climate conditions in the Mediterranean France region) under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions.</bold> The left-hand panels show the transects through France and the right-hand panels show the transects through the United Kingdom. The vertical shaded bars correspond to the regions for Mediterranean France and East Anglia as shown in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221057.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>. Latitudinal averages are constructed by excluding the Central Massif, the Alps, the Pyrenees, Wales, Northern Ireland and Scotland from the datasets as high elevations are likely to hinder whitefly colonisation.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig F. Spatial distribution of percentage of month as cold as the 10</bold>
   <sup class="sup">
    <bold class="bold">th</bold>
   </sup>
   <bold class="bold">percentile cold nights in Mediterranean France (under current climate conditions in the Mediterranean France region) for the current climate observations, the climate model baseline and under the three global climate warming levels (GWL) of 1.5, 2 and 4°C above preindustrial conditions</bold>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">Fig G. Spatial distribution of the number of consecutive days as cold as the 10</bold>
   <sup class="sup">
    <bold class="bold">th</bold>
   </sup>
   <bold class="bold">percentile cold days in Mediterranean France (under current climate conditions in the Mediterranean France region) for the EObs data for June, July and August</bold>.
  </p>
  <p class="p">(PDF)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="pone.0221057.s001.pdf" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption class="caption">
   <p class="p">Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
