<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The ecological niches of the four subspecies of 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> were not identical, but we were unable to reject the null hypothesis that climatic niches are similar (except 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">robertsoni</italic> versus 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tangi</italic>). Although failure to reject the null hypothesis does not assure that the climatic niche has been conserved, no evidence indicates that they have not been conserved, and broad climate spaces overlapped among the four subspecies (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006021.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0006021.s006" class="xref">S2 Fig</xref>). The relationship between niche overlap and phylogenetic relationships of the four subspecies further supports the idea that climate niches have been conserved (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006021.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0006021.s007" class="xref">S3 Fig</xref>). The signal of climate niche conservatism suggests that factors other than climate likely account for the genetic divergence of 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> populations. Li et al. suggested that genetic differentiation of 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic> in mainland China is ultimately structured by landscape ecology [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], with populations falling into four different ecological settings (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006021.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>): swamps and lakes in the Yangtze River Basin (
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hupensis</italic>); the mountainous region of Sichuan and Yunnan Provinces (
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">robertsoni</italic>); the hilly, littoral part of Fujian province (
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tangi</italic>); and the karst landscape of Guangxi Autonomous Region (
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">guangxiensis</italic>). This landscape-level segmentation of the four subspecies is generally consistent with the foundational work of Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]: indeed, clear geographic barriers separate the four subspecies (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006021.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>; [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]). Climate niche divergence between 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">robertsoni</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tangi</italic> might relate to the long geographic distance separating them.
</p>
