<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observational data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under intense harvest, the harvest to biomass ratio reflects the ability of a standing stock to produce harvestable biomass each year. We obtained harvest and biomass data from the RAM Legacy stock assessment database [
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref063">63</a>], and used them to calculate harvest to biomass ratios (H:B hereafter). Stock assessments, by their nature, target individual species in particular geographic regions. Because BOATS represents all commercial species, its results can only be compared with stock assessments when they represent a significant fraction of the total ecosystem. Analysis of the RAM Legacy stock assessment database demonstrated that there were a total of 8 LMEs where at least 40% of the of the harvest from the SAUP database were represented: Baltic Sea, Barents Sea, Patagonian Shelf, Benguela Current, North Sea, Okhotsk Sea, Gulf of Mexico, and East Bering Sea. For each of these LMEs, we calculated average harvest and biomass from the years that were common to all of the stocks represented.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We calculate peak harvest using the Sea Around Us Project (SAUP) database [
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref060">60</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref061">61</a>] aggregated over functional groups at the scale of Large Marine Ecosystems (LMEs). To estimate the peak harvest at each LME, 
  <div id="pone.0169763.e032" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0169763.e032.jpg" id="pone.0169763.e032g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M32" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow"/>
       <span class="mi">l</span>
      </div>
      <div class="msubsup">
       <span class="mi">H</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">LMEmax</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mtext">obs</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, we take the mean harvest of the 10 years with largest harvest. To compare observed LME peak harvests to those simulated by BOATS, 
  <div id="pone.0169763.e033" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0169763.e033.jpg" id="pone.0169763.e033g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M33" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow"/>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">i</span>
        <span class="mo">,</span>
        <span class="mi">l</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="msubsup">
       <span class="mi">H</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mtext">LMEmax</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mtext">sim</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> where 
  <span class="italic">i</span> is an index for the Monte Carlo simulations, we convert both to area-specific LME harvests [
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref067">67</a>], and ignore a number of high latitude Large Marine Ecosystems (LMEs) due to well-established biases in chlorophyll estimates [
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref068">68</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref069">69</a>] which carry through to estimates of net primary production. We therefore neglect the following LMEs: Antarctica, Kara Sea, Laptev Sea, East Siberian Sea, Canadian Eastern Arctic—West Greenland, Hudson Bay Complex, Beaufort Sea, Canadian High Arctic—North Greenland, Central Arctic, and Northern Bering—Chukchi Seas. Since the Black Sea is an inland sea ecosystem, and not comparable to the other LMEs, we ignore it as well [
  <a rid="pone.0169763.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0169763.ref067">67</a>]. The harvest in these 11 LMEs is a negligible fraction (&lt; 1%) of the total harvest over all LMEs, and so ignoring them has a negligible impact on our analysis. 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0169763.s008" href="#pone.0169763.s008">S3 Table</a> lists all of the LMEs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fish biomass modeled in BOATS includes three groups defined by asymptotic size: small (S), medium (M), and large (L) groups (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0169763.s009" href="#pone.0169763.s009">S4 Table</a>). One of our aims is to compare this simple size-based community structure with the SAUP observations. Although most of the SAUP functional groups clearly denote size, we define an association when this is not the case (eg. large shrimp). For cases where the size group is vague (eg. cephalopods) or there are mixed sizes in a functional group (eg. Small to medium flatfishes) we denote these as other (O). We assume the other (O) fraction of harvest follows the same size distribution as the identified groups, such that 
  <div id="pone.0169763.e034" class="disp-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0169763.e034.jpg" id="pone.0169763.e034g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M34" class="math">
     <div displaystyle="true" class="mtable">
      <div class="mtr">
       <div columnalign="right" class="mtd">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="mfrac">
          <span class="mi">G</span>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">S</span>
           <span class="mo">+</span>
           <span class="mi">M</span>
           <span class="mo">+</span>
           <span class="mi">L</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">=</span>
         <div class="mfrac">
          <div class="msub">
           <span class="mi">G</span>
           <span class="mi">a</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">S</span>
            <span class="mi">a</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">+</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">M</span>
            <span class="mi">a</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">+</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span class="mi">L</span>
            <span class="mi">a</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span width="1.em" class="mspace"/>
         <span class="mtext">and</span>
         <span width="1.em" class="mspace"/>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">S</span>
          <span class="mi">a</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">+</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">M</span>
          <span class="mi">a</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">+</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">L</span>
          <span class="mi">a</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">=</span>
         <span class="mi">S</span>
         <span class="mo">+</span>
         <span class="mi">M</span>
         <span class="mo">+</span>
         <span class="mi">L</span>
         <span class="mo">+</span>
         <span class="mi">O</span>
         <span class="mo">,</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="label">(12)</span>
  </div> where 
  <span class="italic">G</span> represents a size group (S, M, or L) and the subscript 
  <span class="italic">a</span> represents the adjusted harvest. This adjustment is usually small since the other (O) fraction of harvest is generally small.
 </p>
</sec>
