<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Feeding in 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> is characterized by bouts of tissue intake interspersed with periods of resting away from the feeding site. When disturbed, they often drop from the food plant along a silk thread, which is later used by the larvae to climb back onto the plant. However, heavy rainfall may prevent this from occurring (Kobori and Amano 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). By contrast, larvae of 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> feed gregariously during the first three instars. Moreover, 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> larvae tend to move much less between feeding bouts and produce silk beds with which they are tightly attached to the leaf. Therefore, 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> larvae are in general less affected by physical disturbance. In a previous study, we reported that caterpillars of 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> are also more strongly disturbed by wind than the caterpillars of 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> (Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). The higher mortality of 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> in response to rainfall, especially when occurring at higher frequencies (80% reduction), is even stronger than mortality caused by wind exposure (10%; this study, Chen et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Eggs and (early) first‐instar larvae of Lepidoptera are the most vulnerable life stages and mortality during each of these stages can be significant (&gt;40%; Zalucki et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). First instar caterpillars of 
 <italic>P. xylostella</italic> feed and live inside leaf tissues and are, therefore, less exposed to environmental conditions. Though females of both species lay their eggs predominantly on the underside off the leaves, it cannot be excluded that downpours affects survival of eggs, thus underestimating the effect on survival in this study.
</p>
