<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the other end of extreme weather events, periods of extended drought are also predicted to increase in frequency under conditions of climate warming. In particular, heat waves and droughts generate conditions that are very different from heavy downpours. Prolonged lack of water and exposure to extreme heat can inflict huge physiological stresses both on plants and higher trophic level organisms. For instance, drought can lead to changes in primary and secondary metabolism and the overall physiological status of the plant (Jamieson et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), which, in turn, can affect the behavior and development of insect herbivores (Huberty and Denno 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>), as well as the interaction with their natural enemies (Karban et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). In extreme cases, prolonged drought can lead to early plant estivation or even death (McDowell et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), and this, in turn, will clearly affect and entire community of organisms associated with the plant. In addition to the biotic environment, the microclimatic environment plays an important role in determining the population dynamics of insect herbivores (Dobkin et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>, Walsh 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). For instance, Walsh (
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) found that, after a serious drought event, factors influencing the microclimate better explained the population decline of an endangered butterfly species, the Karner blue butterfly (
 <italic>Lycaeides melissa samuelis</italic>) than the biotic factors. These results demonstrate the relative importance of abiotic factors on the survival of small ectothermic organisms. Moreover, it is important to note that heat waves, droughts, and intense, sudden downpours can occur in close proximity, e.g., intensive heat waves that are often broken by severe thunderstorms. These contrasting abiotic conditions may induce a range of different, and even opposite, stresses on plants and insects associated with them.
</p>
