<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study is the first attempt to utilize volunteer monitoring-based observations as resources to determine the dietary compositions of birds and their seasonal shifts. The dietary trends observed in and estimated from the monitoring data (Figs. 
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g002">2</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g004">4</a>) were largely consistent with the general food habits determined by previous studies of the focal birds. The estimates based on the volunteer monitoring data successfully detected noticeable seasonal shifts in many of the birds from plant materials to animal diets (mainly invertebrates) during spring—summer. They also appeared to reflect species-specific characteristics in terms of dietary trends. For example, the relative dietary dependency on invertebrates during spring—summer observed in three seed-eating passerines (sparrow, greenfinch, and bunting) based on the monitoring data was consistent with previous stomach analyses, i.e., buntings utilize them more frequently than sparrows [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref040">40</a>], whereas greenfinches utilize them rarely [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref041">41</a>]. The results were also consistent with empirical findings that the white-eye and bulbul depend on flower nectar during spring [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref042">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The comparison with stomach analysis data (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g005">Fig. 5</a>) supports the qualitative validity of the monitoring-based dietary information and the effectiveness of the Bayesian models in improving the estimates. It also demonstrates the advantages and disadvantages of the two different methods. Thus, one advantage of using monitoring data is the ability to detect and evaluate dietary items such as fleshy fruits, flower nectar, and vertebrates. The monitoring-based results demonstrated that the bulbul and white-eye exhibit high dependency on flowers from late winter to spring (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g002">Fig. 2</a>), which was not fully evaluated in the stomach analysis (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g005">Fig. 5D</a>). Similarly, the monitoring-based data suggests higher proportions of fleshy fruits than the stomach analysis data (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g005">Fig. 5C</a>). This is probably because ingested fleshy fruits are often digested; thus, only extracted seeds can be recorded after being separated from the fleshy pulp during stomach analysis (but see [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref019">19</a>]). The identification of dietary parts of plants is also difficult by DNA barcoding and stable isotope analysis, thus direct observation methods still have advantages for these items compared with other methods. Another difference between the monitoring data and the stomach analysis data was that the proportion of vertebrate dietary items was much higher in the monitoring data (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g005">Fig. 5F-5I</a>). One main cause for this difference was the units used for measurement by the two methods. The stomach analysis data counted the items whereas the monitoring data were based on the number of observed feeding bouts for each item. Thus, the latter may reflect the total time spent consuming an item. The stomach analysis could lead to the dominance of small items, such as seed grains, among the dietary proportions; thus, the dependency on vertebrate diets may have been underestimated in the stomach analysis data used in this study. Another possible cause of the difference is that large-sized items, such as vertebrates, could be easily observed and reported in the monitoring program, thereby overestimated in the ROPs. Given these two possibilities, the actual proportions of vertebrate diets appear to lie between the two estimates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our Bayesian modeling approach may also improve the estimation of dietary compositions to some degree. The comparison with stomach analysis data (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g005">Fig. 5</a>) showed that MOPs generally had fewer differences from the CPs in the stomach analysis than the ROPs for most of dietary items. For the items where the ROPs exceeded CPs, such as invertebrates, fleshy fruit, flowers, and vertebrates, the modeling reduced the proportions. By contrast, for the “seeds” item where the ROPs tended to be lower than the CPs, the modeling increased the proportion. Although, as mentioned above, stomach analysis data have their own potential biases, the smaller difference between MOPs and CPs can increase confidence in the MOPs. The combination and integration of stomach analysis data and monitoring-based data, as well as other methods, could provide more accurate estimates of bird diets.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some biases might not have been addressed and controlled in this monitoring-based analysis, e.g., for rare bird foraging behaviors, observers might have tended to record and report rare dietary items rather than common ones, which could have overestimated rare dietary items for a bird. We do not know how much this bias influenced the results, but such bias was shown to be small, at least for rareness of bird species, in our previous analysis [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref035">35</a>]. Variation in the levels of expertise among observers is another possible major bias that needs to be considered in citizen science-based approaches [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref043">43</a>], but we consider that this bias had little effect on our data because most of the observation records were made by veteran naturalists. Finally, similar to foraging location, the size of a dietary item can also affect detection rate and probability in a way that the item is reported as unidentified in the modeling [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref016">16</a>]. Our model could not fully deal with this potential bias. Future refinement of the method is required, including some procedure of calibrating detection rates between dietary items prior to, or during the course of monitoring.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The monitoring data analyzed in this study had unique characteristics because they comprised episode-based observations, which were reported spontaneously by motivated regional naturalists. This additional, detailed information on bird behaviors beyond bird presence/absence records or numbers facilitated our current analysis. Previously, majority of citizen science data used in ornithological studies have comprised bird abundance and/or occurrence data [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref031">31</a>], or records of specific events/behaviors such as breeding and migration [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref032">32</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref044">44</a>]. This is because the data format needs to be as simple as possible to facilitate effective data collection; thus, there is a trade-off between the complexity of the data format and effective data collection by citizens. The inclusion of additional descriptions could reduce the efficiency of data collection and complicate the data structure, but it could be an important source of knowledge related to various aspects of avian natural history, thereby facilitating further ecological research, such as identifying the patterns of interaction networks between birds and other organisms [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref033">33</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref035">35</a>]. Therefore, data collection and mining of such free description records could be important resources for bird ecology and conservation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our method is based on direct observation of bird foraging that is easily conducted by non-professional naturalists. This method is particularly suitable for threatened bird species and those with unknown feeding techniques because direct observation is less invasive than other methods such as stomach analysis (except for nesting and incubating periods), and offers information on actual foraging locations and behaviors of the birds. In addition, this method can effectively distinguish between the dietary preferences of the birds for specific plant parts (i.e., fruits, seeds, leaves, or flowers), which could not be fully determined using DNA barcoding and stable isotope analysis. Thus, this method can be used to evaluate the potential roles that the birds play within plant ecology [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref005">5</a>], particularly when detailed descriptions on foraging behavior are recorded. On the other hand, our method can successfully estimate actual dietary compositions of birds under certain conditions. First, the observation of foraging of a target bird species should cover as broad a range of locations that the bird utilizes as possible, so that observed locations are not overly biased to specific locations. Second, considerable focus of observations at each feeding location should be devoted to identifying actual diet. Unidentified dietary items at certain locations can result in excessive extrapolation from the identified items and may result in an invalid estimation. The estimates can be biased, particularly when specific modes of diet items or specific combinations of diet items and locations are expected to have low detection rates [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref024">24</a>]. Therefore, consulting and integrating results by other methods is necessary. When collected and treated appropriately, direct observation data by citizens can be an effective method for evaluating foraging ecology of birds, and a fertile source of information for studies on broad aspects of animal ecology.
 </p>
</sec>
