<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MOPs based on Bayesian modeling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used hierarchical Bayesian modeling to consider two potential biases in estimating dietary proportions: 1) variation in the identifiability of dietary items and 2) accidental data fluctuations due to low numbers of observations during some months (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0119324.g001">Fig. 1</a>). We refer to these estimated proportions as MOPs. Because our modeling details are described in 
  <a rid="pone.0119324.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0119324.s001">S1 Appendix</a>, we provide a brief explanation on MOPs in this section.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0119324.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0119324.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The structure of the Bayesian model developed to infer unidentified feeding episodes by birds.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0119324.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate MOPs, we estimated the expected foraging frequency of each dietary item while considering the existence of “unidentified items” in our data. Our approach to identifying the “unidentified items” was to utilize the relationship between dietary items and foraging locations in the feeding episodes with identified items. We assumed that bird species were observed to forage dietary items at each location randomly with the same probability (by multinomial distributions, i.e., generalization of usual binomial distributions) in both identified and unidentified items. This assumption is marginally too simple but valid because foraging locations are one of the major cause of the variation in the identifiability of dietary items.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our modeling, we also assumed that expected foraging frequencies were seasonally auto-correlated, i.e., foraging frequency in 1 month was similar to that in neighboring months for each dietary item of each bird species. Introducing the seasonal autocorrelation reduced the bias due to low numbers of observations in some months. We did not assume that the magnitudes of seasonal autocorrelation vary from month to month. Because our analysis used a coarse temporal scale, the change of magnitude of seasonal autocorrelation is likely to introduce relatively little bias to our estimation of the expected foraging frequencies.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of our Bayesian analyses were conducted using the R software suite (version 3.02 [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref037">37</a>]) and Just another Gibbs Sampler 3.3.0 [
  <a rid="pone.0119324.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0119324.ref038">38</a>]. We used informative prior for all estimated parameters (see 
  <a rid="pone.0119324.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0119324.s001">S1 Appendix</a> for details). We calculated monthly MOPs of each dietary item after rounding the estimated frequency to an integer.
 </p>
</sec>
