<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stomach analysis data from previous studies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the validity of the dietary compositions estimated from the monitoring data, we compared these results with the stomach analysis data for birds reported in previous studies of Japanese birds. We collected all the available quantitative dietary data regarding the target birds within the Japanese Archipelago using the following procedures. First, we checked all of the relevant studies in the main ornithological journals of Japan, including Tori (1915–1986), Japanese Journal of Ornithology (1986–2014), Ornithological Science (2002–2014), Strix (1982–2014), Bird Research (2005–2014), Journal of Yamashina Institute of Ornithology (1952–2014), and Bulletin of Applied Ornithology (1980–1990). We also checked agricultural bulletins published between the 1910s and 1950s by the Japanese Ministries of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries. In addition, we checked other studies in some cases by tracing citations within the literatures. Next, we selected the studies that included quantitative dietary information related to the focal birds. We focused on stomach analysis data because the selected studies were based almost exclusively on individual-based stomach analysis, apart from a very low number of studies based on direct observations or pellet analysis. In general, these stomach analysis studies used a format that listed a bird species, sample number, sampling location, detected dietary items, and their count numbers (or weights in very few studies), although some studies pooled the results from several individuals in the same month.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the comparison, we focused on the following eight bird species because abundant monitoring and literature data were available: sparrow, bulbul, two crows, greenfinch, magpie, shrike, and bunting (
  <a rid="pone.0119324.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0119324.t001">Table 1</a>). Based on published reports, we calculated the monthly count proportion (CP) for each item. The CP for an item was calculated as the total number of the item detected (pooling across bird individuals from all previous studies) in a month divided by the total number of all items in the same month. The number of parts of plant items (seeds, fruits, flowers, and leaves) and the number of individuals for animal items (invertebrate, bird, fish, amphibian and reptile, and mammal) were counted. When a detected item was uncountable (e.g., resolved or ground after heavy digestion), we counted it as one. Next, for each dietary item, we compared the monthly proportions of the item based on the ROP and the stomach analysis data. In this monthly comparison, we only used the bird—month combinations with more than four individual specimens in the stomach analysis data. To assess the fits between the two types of monitoring-based proportions and the proportions based on the stomach analysis, we calculated root mean square difference between ROPs and CPs, and that between MOPs and CPs. This statistic measures the gap between the two values; a larger value indicates a larger gap.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Note that these stomach analysis-based proportions were also biased in several ways. First, as mentioned earlier, the estimated compositions were inevitably biased due to the variation in diet mode and digestibility. Second, the selected studies only presented the number of each dietary item detected (e.g., the numbers of individual insects or animal species, and the numbers of seed grains or fruits) for each bird. Therefore, the dietary compositions obtained were considerably different from the actual compositions based on the volume, weight, or energy intake. Third, the samples for the stomach analysis were from various localities. Because these sample locations were scattered within the Japanese Archipelago for many of the target bird species, this is expected to average (and offset) the possible bias of locality, and be comparable to the monitoring-based results in Kanagawa Prefecture in central Japan. However, as for the Eurasian tree sparrow, a considerable proportion of the samples were collected from northern parts of Japan, which may cause some bias.</p>
</sec>
