<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">C4 plants such as maize are able to concentrate CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in the Rubisco-containing photosynthetic cells of the bundle sheath. The CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-concentrating mechanism of C4 photosynthesis facilitates high rates of carbon assimilation to occur even when stomata are partially or fully closed, because the C4 pathway delivers a high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration in the vicinity of rubisco limiting the oxygenation reaction and flux through the photo-respiratory pathway. Hence the C4 pathway of photosynthesis provides a competitive advantage under growth conditions that promote carbon loss through photorespiration, such as high temperatures or decreased water availability (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lopes and Foyer 2011</xref>). The transpiration rates and water status of maize leaves, particularly the older leaf ranks, are changed under conditions of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment even when plants are maintained under well-watered conditions (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prins et al. 2010</xref>). Under well-watered conditions, elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> has little effect on the photosynthesis or growth of C4 plants in controlled environment (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soares et al. 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prins et al. 2010</xref>) or in the FACE studies (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Leakey et al. 2009a</xref>, b, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manderscheid et al. 2014</xref>). Moreover, the negative impact of drought on yield is attenuated at high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> because of stomatal closure (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lopes et al. 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manderscheid et al. 2014</xref>). Such observations indicate that maize should perform better under drought stress conditions when plants are grown at high [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>]. While higher temperatures should favor C4 plants over C3 plants (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long and Ort 2010</xref>), a negative response of global yields has been projected for maize as well as wheat and barley as a result of increased temperatures (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tatsumi et al. 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Asseng et al. 2014</xref>). Elevated temperatures have been reported to exert a negative influence on a range of plant processes such as photosynthesis through decreased activation of Rubisco, stomatal closure, flower development, pollen viability and hence fertility, and fruit ripening but in many cases the precise mechanisms remain to be characterized.
</p>
