<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">By sampling 2 holobionts adapted to conditions at the extreme ends of the host species’ depth distribution we were able to assess the relative importance of light adaptation, 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> phylotype and temperature on productivity. Relative to deep/C7, shallow/A3 
 <italic class="italic">O. faveolata</italic> had twice the 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> density, but similar chla concentrations per cell (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). This suggests that photoprotective mechanisms (e.g., self-shading and host pigments for non-photochemical quenching) were upregulated at shallow depths. In comparison, deep/C7 corals were duller in appearance, and had fewer 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> with no reduction in chlorophyll per cell, which is indicative of light-limiting conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>]. As such, deep/C7 corals brought to surface light conditions had 34% more carbon assimilation than shallow/A3 corals owing to more efficient use of light, and showed no response to warming (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a</xref>). In contrast, warming caused a 14% increase in carbon assimilation in shallow/A3 corals illustrating that heat can increase photosynthesis even when photoprotective mechanisms are present. Thus, host regulation of photoprotective mechanisms appears to have a stronger influence on symbiont photosynthesis than warming alone. The host’s ability to regulate symbiont photosynthesis via protection and inhibition is a plausible negative feedback mechanism for bleaching resistance. Such mechanisms may help to explain the different bleaching tolerances observed across the diversity of coral holobionts. However, warming had no proportional benefit to the host carbon subsidy, indicating that 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> either retained their additional carbon or it was respired by the holobiont (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref>).
</p>
