<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">In contrast to carbon, 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> nitrogen assimilation was universally enhanced with warming with no proportional increase in nitrogen obtained by the coral host (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1c, d</xref>). Deep/C7 corals assimilated &gt;37% more nitrogen than their shallow conspecifics at both temperatures. This can be attributed to either (1) 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> identity, which is not mutually exclusive from, or (2) greater photosynthetic efficiency, or (3) different nitrogen exposure histories or (4) a higher nitrogen demand for PSII repair. More importantly, warming and depth/clade were equal in their effect on 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> nitrogen assimilation. Both deep/C7 and shallow/A3 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> assimilated &gt;31% more nitrogen when warmed to 31 °C. Although the coral host still benefitted from symbiont nitrogen translocation, there was no proportional increase in translocation due to either warming or depth/clade. Given that nitrate assimilation is an energy intensive process, 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> effectively lowered their cost by maintaining a fixed subsidy to the host and retaining the surplus assimilated nitrogen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. This finding has several major implications. It suggests that when nitrogen is not limiting to primary productivity that warming (1) favors the assimilation of nitrogen and thus, the proliferation of 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]; (2) nitrate increasingly “evades” host mechanisms (via passive transport, perhaps) to modulate 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> access to nitrogen, as proposed for organic nitrogen and ammonium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>], and (3) 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> either translocate a fixed nitrogen subsidy to their host, or hosts are physically or biochemically limited in the amount of nitrogen they can receive. Taken together, these data validate models that predict a synergistic effect of warming and nitrogen on selfish symbiont behavior and coral bleaching [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>].
</p>
