<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">Although this study is limited to a single coral host (
 <italic class="italic">O. faveolata</italic>), we were able to evaluate the metabolic costs and nutritional benefits of hosting 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> partners that span the continuum from a sensitive mutualist to stress-tolerant, opportunistic parasite. 
 <italic class="italic">S. fitti</italic> (ITS2 clade A3) are known for their tolerance of high light and increasing temperature, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>], while being a less beneficial partner to their hosts than clade C 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>]). Indeed, 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> within the ITS2 clade C are generally considered to be more mutualistic as they confer more fitness benefits to their hosts, including carbon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>] and growth limiting nitrogen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. C7 is one such mutualist, which is specific to and dominates 
 <italic class="italic">Orbicella</italic> in low-light habitats though is less tolerant of thermal stress [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>]. Yet, we observed enhanced symbiont resource uptake (i.e., revenue) with unchanged host translocation (costs), which led to a higher net “profit” in the form of accumulated resources that led to a concomitant increase in cell division (benefits) by both of these symbionts in hospite under thermal stress. At the same time, their hosts sustained a large increase in respiration, which was associated with a reduction in carbon content. Taken together, these observations suggest that warming can create conditions for symbiont parasitism.
</p>
