<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
 <p class="p">The authors wish to thank Amanda A. Stearns, MSPH for providing valuable research assistance for this study.</p>
 <sec id="FPar19" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Funding</title>
  <p class="p">Funding for this study was provided by the George Mason University Foundation and the Public Health Institute.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar20" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p class="p">Data will not be publicly shared because our informed consent procedures ensured respondents that only aggregated summary statistics (for the online survey) and general themes and relevant quotes (for the in-depth interviews) would be reported. We are declining to release individual responses and interview transcripts to protect respondent privacy.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar21" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Authors’ contributions</title>
  <p class="p">JK and MS designed the study. JK and KP constructed and administered the online survey and in-depth interviews. JK performed statistical analysis on survey data; JK and KP conducted qualitative analysis of in-depth interview data. JK wrote the manuscript, with written contributions and critical revisions by KP and MS. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar22" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Competing interests</title>
  <p class="p">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar23" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Consent for publication</title>
  <p class="p">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar24" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p class="p">This study received approval from the Institutional Review Board at George Mason University. Informed consent was obtained from participants immediately prior to participation in the online survey (written consent) and in-depth interviews (verbal consent).</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
