<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Past-present trajectories of vulnerability associated with demographic changes and environmental degradation have being reported as important for future adaptation among Pacific Island populations where the “desire to make money” has resulted in the development of more cash cropping which in turn has eroded the social cohesion and reduced subsistence resources [
 <xref rid="pone.0205714.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205714.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Similarly, a demographic driver related with a less mobile settlement pattern and increasing farming practices was identified as a key proximal pathway for Shawi households and community food security. The Shawi have consistently increased their population over the last half century [
 <xref rid="pone.0205714.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. Improved access to health services, particularly vaccination, and the erosion of Indigenous fertility regulations (e.g. polygyny, marriage rules, contraception), have been hypothesised as key factors in the recovery of Indigenous Amazonian populations after major population declines following encounters with Western societies [
 <xref rid="pone.0205714.ref094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205714.ref095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>]. Although we did not find updated Shawi data on infant mortality, the last Peruvian census (2007) indicates that the Shawi population was relatively young, with higher fertility rates compared to the Peruvian average (7.7 vs 2.6 children per women) [
 <xref rid="pone.0205714.ref096" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. This implies that the Shawi population may continue to increase in the future. Youth participants indicated that they intended to have fewer children and this intention may represent the potential for declining fertility rates if barriers to accessing appropriate and effective contraception planning are addressed.
</p>
