<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">
    <span class="underline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global SAT response</span>. High-latitude deforestation leads to cooling proportional to deforested area. Removing trees over the low latitudes causes warming but due to an increase in albedo and increase in the soil carbon pool (see below) this warming is reduced in experiments with large initial deforestation fraction. The SAT response of mid-latitude deforestation is small compared to the other two bands with intermediary deforestation fractions causing warming and larger fractions cooling.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">
    <span class="underline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SAT response over deforested areas</span>. Albedo driven cooling is observed for all latitude bands and all initial deforestation fractions.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">
    <span class="underline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The importance of soil carbon</span>. Atmospheric CO
    <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</sub> concentration, and consequently the global temperature response to deforestation, are greatly influenced by post-disturbance changes in soil carbon pools inside and outside deforested areas. It is in large part due to an increase in soil carbon over deforested areas that, irrespective of latitude band, larger initial deforestation scenarios show lower final atmospheric CO
    <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</sub> concentrations than intermediate scenarios. Given the large uncertainties associated with the modelled terrestrial carbon cycle [
    <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], our results also point to the need for greater understanding of how organic matter behaves in soils [
    <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] and for the adoption of this new knowledge by terrestrial models.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">
    <span class="underline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pattern and drivers of soil carbon change</span>. Larger NPP, due mostly to CO
    <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</sub> fertilization, is the cause of soil carbon increase over non-deforested areas. In the high-latitude experiments non-deforested areas also gain carbon due to colder and dryer conditions. In the mid- and low-latitude experiments deforested area soils become warmer and dryer, with moisture effects overcoming the opposing temperature impacts and leading to net soil carbon gain, particularly for the higher deforestation fraction scenarios, where local soil temperatures do not increase as much. Among experiments that end up with similar total deforested area, those with larger initial deforestation fractions tend to show larger soil carbon gains and consequently relatively cooler temperatures, an indication that the rate of land cover change is an important determinant of the model’s response to deforestation.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">
    <span class="underline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drivers of soil temperature change over deforested areas</span>. At high latitudes the tendency is for cooling due to the increase in albedo. In both mid and low latitudes the response is warming caused by a post-deforestation reduction in sensible heat flux.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">
    <span class="underline" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clouds and low-latitude deforestation</span>. The local cooling recorded by our experiments is not seen in simulations of low-latitude deforestation conducted by models that incorporate cloud dynamics. Reliable predictions of the effects of deforestation require understanding the cloud response to land cover change, a problem with yet many uncertainties.
   </p>
  </div>
 </list>
</p>
