<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another possible response to our results is to seek a unified position across religious groupings on climate change, to seek to change community attitudes. Examples of these included the 2007 and 2009 resolutions of the United Churches of Christ in the USA, which comprises predominantly Congregational churches [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], the resolution of Evangelical Christian Leaders in the USA [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], as well as the position statements of the World Council of Churches [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Similar statements have also been released in Australia. For example, the Uniting Church [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] adopted a statement called “For the Sake of the Planet and all its People” that relates to climate change, and calls on church members to reduce carbon emission and advocate for governments to reduce dependence on carbon based energy sources. Similar efforts are being promoted by the Catholic Church through Catholic Earthcare Australia [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Evidence is emerging that these sorts of strategies have led to increased local level action to reduce carbon emissions [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. However, as Ayre [
 <xref rid="pone.0134868.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] suggests, ambiguity still remains for some Australian denominations about the church’s role in being vocal about the need for responsible care for the environment, and opportunity remains to better translate stated positions about climate change into effective work on the ground. Thus there remains opportunity for religious groups to do more to support the acceptance of human induced climate change and the need for policy responses, as well as action at a local level.
</p>
