<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">Existing studies stem mostly from the gray literature acknowledging that the European part of the Arctic Ocean has a significant resource potential that could play a significant role on the global hydrocarbon markets, but come to mixed conclusions regarding the economic viability of Arctic oil and gas from European offshore sources (IEA 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2013</xref>; Aarhus et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2014</xref>; Casey 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2014</xref>; Emmerson and Lahn 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2012</xref>). Here, we focus mainly on studies published after the drop in oil and gas prices during the 2007/2008 financial crisis. From a conceptual point of view, our work relates to Harsem et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2015</xref>), who studied the impact of projected sea ice developments on oil activity in 21 Arctic oil provinces. They conclude that (Harsem et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2015</xref>, p. 101), “while certain Arctic provinces may become more attractive during the next 30 years, most provinces will still imply very high costs. Even though the Arctic is expected to lose a significant portion of its sea ice cover, this does not automatically imply that it will become a substantial oil region.” Their work, as ours, is based on USGS estimates for oil potential, but applies only one climate model and a top-down approach for estimating cost differentials between the provinces instead of bottom-up estimates of cost levels. Aarhus et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2014</xref>), in a report prepared by the Norwegian gas pipeline operator with input from the Barents Sea Gas Infrastructure Forum (BSGI), reviewed both potential technologies and potential production costs. They concede that, while acknowledging the potential of the Barents Sea, existing discoveries are not sufficient to justify investment in new gas infrastructure, which will be challenging to realize from a post-tax project robustness perspective. Casey (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2014</xref>) focused on licensing rounds in Greenland and was skeptical about economic feasibility, which, if at all, he only saw in the long term. The IEA (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2013</xref>, p. 138) concludes that exploration and production activity in the offshore Arctic is likely to increase in the coming decades, but qualifies that “realising the potential of Arctic resources will depend not only on market success and conditions in finding them, but also on technological innovation and the ability to exploit these resources in a safe and environmentally sound manner. The cost of bringing Arctic resources to markets is substantial, so projects will require a high market price and more cost-effective technology to attract investment.” Lindholt and Glomsrod (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2012</xref>) found in their scenario analysis on the entire Arctic that its relevance for international gas markets will decline and for oil markets at least not increase. Emmerson and Lahn (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2012</xref>) highlighted the importance of fluctuations in energy prices for energy developments in the Arctic and show cost estimates of 30–100 2008 USD/barrel of oil, based on IEA estimates. In the same vein, Overland et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2015</xref>) showed that oil and gas production depends crucially on price development, the level of international cooperation, and climate policy.
</p>
