<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Direction of range shifts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An example is presented to illustrate how range shifts driven by climate change can occur both towards the poles or the equator. We modelled the relative abundance (from 0 – absent, to 1 – highest abundance) of a theoretical species under two climate change scenarios. We modelled an equatorial species which is intolerant of cold stress and tolerant of heat stress. Abundance was determined as the lowest value of either ‘winter minimum’ or ‘summer 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile’ at each shore (following Liebig’s law of the minimum). To allow the comparison of both metrics (which are not equivalent in absolute terms) we normalised each metric to vary from 0 to 1, reflecting the range observed within the study region. Zero abundance occurred at shores where at least one of the metrics had a value of zero, meaning that either ‘winter minimum’ or ‘summer 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile’, or both, prevented the species from existing. Both metrics were used without any change for the initial conditions. The first climate change scenario considers climate change as a monotonic increase of both aspects of temperature, and the abundance pattern was computed using “hot” versions of both ‘winter minimum’ and ‘summer 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile’ (resulting in increased habitat suitability). The second scenario considers climate change as an increase of variability in which some metrics may actually become colder. In this case the abundance pattern was computed using the “cold” version of ‘winter minimum’ and the “hot” version ‘summer 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile’. The initial range limit was identified as the most poleward shore with abundance greater than zero. The location of the range limit was re-evaluated for both climate change scenarios to determine the direction of change (poleward or equatorward).
 </p>
</sec>
