<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aims of this perspective have been two-fold; firstly to highlight the benefits of using the measurable attributes of the plant water transport system as a tool for understanding plant distribution and the probability of forest mortality under future climatic scenarios. The development of new techniques should enable the characterization of entire forest communities as new innovations continue to improve the efficiency of measurement. Expanded sampling of hydraulic vulnerability will enable to the identification of particularly vulnerable species and will provide a mechanistic means of understanding the limits of species distributions, enabling predictions of how geographical limits can be expected to change as global temperatures rise.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second aim of this perspective has been to demonstrate why increasing global temperature poses a threat to tree species in terms of increasing the probability of mortality during periods of water shortage. Our simulation using hydraulic modelling indicates a high probability of extensive mortality in a mesic deciduous forest in France under a warming scenario characterized by increasing CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions over the century. These simulations, although preliminary, provide strong motivation to carefully evaluate the future of forests under warming climate conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With knowledge of the types of data required to understand plant hydraulic stress, and process-based models to predict species exposure to future mortality we are in a good position to implement sampling and monitoring to create a picture of how forests are likely to change in the future. This knowledge will enable those engaged in forest and ecosystem management to have an informed anticipation of inevitable change.</p>
</sec>
