<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydraulic modelling to predict future mortality</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative simplicity of plant water transport models, coupled with the causal association between xylem damage and plant death makes this an ideal approach to gauge the magnitude of the tree mortality crisis that may be approaching as global temperatures rise. Hydraulic flow models (
  <a rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref34">Sperry 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1998
  </a>) have already been used with some success to explain contemporary forest damage (
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">Anderegg 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
  </a>), but there are few cases where hydraulic models have been used to predict future forest damage. To demonstrate the potential for using mechanistic models of plant hydraulics to simulate the impacts of future climatic perturbation on tree mortality we used the recently developed model SurEau (
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">Martin-StPaul 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2017
  </a>; 
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">Cochard, 2019</a>) to predict mortality in 
  <span class="italic">Fagus sylvatica</span> forest in the centre of France. The model computes the daily and seasonal dynamics of tree transpiration, water potentials and xylem blockage by cavitation under different climatic time series (see 
  <a rid="box01" ref-type="boxed-text" href="#box01">BOX 1</a>). The simulation here uses 1960–2100 daily climatic data from climatic scenario RCP8.5 generated with the GCM MPI-ESM-LR/RCM RCA4 models. The forest was assumed to be initially composed of tree genotypes displaying a variability of vulnerability to cavitation matching the observations of Wortemann 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2013) for this species. Other traits, such a leaf area, rooting depth and stomatal behaviour, were assumed to be constant across genotypes and estimated from observations, adjusted to produce no mortality (i.e. embolism &lt; 50%) for the historical 1960–2000 time series. Tree death in the model was triggered by plants crossing a threshold of either &gt; 50%, or a more conservative &gt; 88% cavitation (
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Brodribb and Cochard, 2009</a>). For each year and each genotype, we computed a probability of mortality based on the occurrence of lethal events during the past decade. From this we derived the temporal evolution of the number trees of each genotype in the forest. The model output shows a sharp reduction in tree population starting after 2020 and a complete forest mortality by the end of the century when mortality was set at 50% cavitation (
  <a rid="f2" ref-type="fig" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). This reduction is predicted to be accompanied by an erosion of genetic diversity, the most vulnerable trees dying first (
  <a rid="f2" ref-type="fig" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a> insert). The more conservative hypothesis for mortality (i.e. embolism &gt;88%) or a more optimistic climatic scenario (RCP4.5) yielded similar results but delayed in time.
 </p>
 <div id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Output from a hydraulic model used to estimate the temporal erosions of population and genetic diversity of 
    <span class="italic">Fagus</span> trees under a future climatic scenario in central France. Depending on the amount of xylem damage expected to cause mortality two scenarios for tree decline are predicted. If 50% xylem failure is lethal (dashed line) then a collapse in adult tree number is predicted after 2020 due to xylem cavitation produced by increased transpiration and soil water deficit. A more conservative rate of tree decline is predicted if plants are able to survive up to 88% loss of xylem function (dotted line). The insert shows the distribution of tree genetic sensitivity to drought (xylem vulnerability: P
    <sub>50</sub>) at four time points in the future, showing a shift to more resistant varieties. Under this RCP8.5 scenario (continuing increase in CO
    <sub>2</sub> emissions), a dramatic collapse of tree population is predicted by the middle of this century, with most vulnerable genotypes dying first.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="coz046f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
