<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Since the Mediterranean climate is determined by the interaction between mid-latitude and sub-tropical circulation regimes and a complex morphology of mountain chains and land–sea contrasts, the Med-regions are vulnerable to climatic changes [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. In fact, the Mediterranean ecosystems are among the most vulnerable to the global warming impacts [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Recent studies show that these changes have already been observed: for instance, since the 1960s, the Mediterranean basin has become warmer with a significant increase in the frequency, intensity and duration of heat waves. It is also characterized by a reduction in the availability of potable water as a result of a decrease in the total amount of precipitation, changes in rainfall patterns and water overuse by the growing population, mainly in urban areas [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. In California the mean temperature has increased across all regions [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], and projected average temperatures are expected to rise dramatically in future decades, greatly exceeding the warming that has occurred to date since the late 19th century [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In recent years, California has experienced extreme drought [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. According to Williams 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] anthropogenic warming has intensified the recent droughts as part of a chronic drying trend that is becoming increasingly detectable and is projected to continue growing throughout the rest of this century. In the Western Cape region of South Africa significant warming trends were found and very warm days have become warmer or have occurred more regularly [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Under climate change projections, serious reductions in water supply and increases in the frequency of intense wildfires are expected for this region [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. In southwestern Australia, the mean temperature has risen by more than 1 °C since 1910 and declines in rainfall have been observed in recent decades [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-13-00438" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>].
</p>
