<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Climate change affects human health through three pathways. The direct health impacts of climate change are associated with the changing frequency and severity of extreme weather events, such as heat, drought, and heavy rain. Secondly, climate change’s effects can be mediated through natural systems, for instance, by altering the burden and pattern of distribution of vector-, water-, and food-borne diseases. Finally, climate change may impact health indirectly, via social institutions, resulting in undernutrition (for example, when climatic factors interact with global food markets), mental ill-health, and even violence and conflict [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>•]. Whilst it is widely recognised that climate change affects human health, attributing morbidity and mortality to climate change is challenging, for the attribution of individual weather events to climate change itself is difficult, even without accounting for the associated human health consequences and mediation through ecosystems and human institutions. Nonetheless, the ability to attribute events to climate change is improving, and consequently, there is growing evidence that climate change is already impacting human health. For instance, the European heatwave of 2003 killed over 70,000 people, with France being particularly badly affected; climate change exacerbated the severity of this heatwave and is estimated to have increased the risk of heat-related mortality in Paris by 70% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. Such research on the health impacts of climate change is vital to effectively addressing climate change; in particular, understanding health impacts is important in enabling the public health sector to adapt to climate change and reduce associated health burdens. Adapting to climate change is an immense challenge for public health practice, owing to the unpredictability of its impacts on health; the rapidity of changes in the climate system relative to historical stability; and that it simultaneously impacts multiple risk factors and determinants of health, thus correlating previously uncorrelated risks. Understanding how climate science can be translated into public health practice is therefore an essential first step in enabling robust adaptation to climate change.
</p>
