<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Paleontologists have long used skeletal elements from extant animals to reconstruct body mass and body shape of fossils (Christiansen, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Damuth &amp; MacFadden, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>; Gingerich, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>). Data from some bones indicate body size more accurately than others. Indices of body size in mammals, including 
 <italic class="italic">Bison,</italic> are best indicated by bones of the hind foot (elements of the ankle, calcaneum, and astragalus), and front foot (elements of the wrist, scaphoid, and magnum), along with the toes (podial digits and distal and proximal phalanges; (Damuth &amp; MacFadden, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>)). The bulk of the foot bones precisely reflects body mass because they bear the weight of the animal, whereas the shape of the bones reflects the functional anatomy for locomotion through the attachment of tendons and muscle (Scott, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>). Longer bones of limbs (femora and humeri) are also good proxies for reconstructing body size. Unfortunately, long bones in the fossil record are typically broken, whereas the calcanea, astragali, and phalanges are commonly well preserved, likely because these dense elements resist degradation. Consequently, podial elements are well studied within Bovinae, which includes cattle (
 <italic class="italic">Bos taurus</italic>, (Lawrence, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1951</xref>; Olsen, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1960</xref>; Balkwill &amp; Cumbaa, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1992</xref>)), and Antilopinae, mountain goats (
 <italic class="italic">Oreamnos</italic> sp., (Carpenter, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>)), bighorn sheep (
 <italic class="italic">Ovis</italic> sp., (Todd &amp; Rapson, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1988</xref>; Rothschild &amp; Martin, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>), among others). However, it is difficult to distinguish taxa using podial elements. 
 <italic class="italic">Bison</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bos</italic> can be resolved from traits of podial elements by the methods of Balkwill and Cumbaa (
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1992</xref>) but we cannot resolve 
 <italic class="italic">Bison</italic> species based upon podial elements alone. Species designations in our dataset originated from whole collections of associated podial and cranial material that may not distinguish mixes of species at each location. For example, American Falls Reservoir in Idaho contains at least four co‐existing species of 
 <italic class="italic">Bison</italic> (Pinsof, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>). If we ignore species designations and analyze our data at the clade level, the slope of podial size with increasing temperatures becomes steeper; −63 kg/°C (±10; 
 <italic class="italic">z </italic>=
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>−6.11 
 <italic class="italic">p </italic>&lt;
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>.001) with an intercept at 648 ± 26 kg for 
 <italic class="italic">Bison</italic> spp., as compared to the −41 kg/°C for 
 <italic class="italic">Bison bison</italic> (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34019-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>). This slope may change regionally with latitudinal differences in body size of extant 
 <italic class="italic">Bison</italic>.
</p>
