<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data and Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observation and reanalysis data</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed Arctic sea ice concentration data at 1° longitude-latitude resolution for the period 1980 through present (2017) are obtained from HadISST.2 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst2/data/download.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst2/data/download.html</span> 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
   </span>. The observed SST prescribed in AGCM experiments consist of the NOAA Optimal Interpolation Sea Surface Temperature (OISST) data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The atmospheric reanalysis dataset used is NASA Modern-era Retrospective Analysis for Research and Applications, version 2 (MERRA–2)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
   </span> at 0.625° longitude × 0.5° latitude resolution. The primary variables used for this study consist of geopotential height, temperature, and wind at tropospheric pressure levels (850, 700, 500, and 250 mb)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
   </span>, cloud fraction, surface albedo, short and long wave fluxes at surface
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
   </span>, and turbulent fluxes (e.g., latent and sensible heat fluxes) at surface
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods (Numerical model and experimental design)</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NASA Goddard Earth Observing System model, version 5 (GEOS-5) is used for the model experiments. In order to explore large-scale atmospheric responses to idealized SST over the subtropical Pacific, we try uncoupled atmospheric GCM (AGCM). The model has 72 hybrid sigma-pressure vertical levels, extending to 0.01hPa, and 0.5° latitude/longitude horizontal grid spacing. The convection scheme is a modified version of the Relaxed Arakawa Schubert (RAS) scheme of
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
   </span>. It includes a stochastic Tokioka trigger function
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
   </span> that governs the lower limits on the allowable entrainment plumes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>
   </span>. The model has the option for a standard single-moment microphysics
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
   </span> or a two-moment cloud microphysics
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>
   </span> embedded within the RAS convective parameterization, and the simulations described here used the single moment option. Further details about the GEOS-5 AGCM can be found in
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We carried out AGCM experiments to identify the impact of the subtropical Pacific warming on the global atmospheric circulation. We first conducted climatological SST–forced runs as a control experiment (Exp CTL). The SSTs are prescribed to be climatological (SST are averaged over the period 1980–2015) everywhere. The main experiment (Exp SPW) (here SPW stands for “subtropical Pacific warming”) is forced by the same SST as Exp CTL, except over the STWCP region (130°–180°E, 0°–35°N) where the observed warming (SST averages over the years when the SST is warmer than climatological average) has been added to climatology to include the warming effect. Specifically, this warming is imposed only for spring (MAM) and fall (SON) seasons to explore their warming impact on the atmospheric responses in the following seasons of summer (JJA) and winter (DJF). Model is initialized in February and integrated through February next year. The 20 ensemble members are distinguished by having different atmospheric/land initial conditions taken from MERRA–2 during the 20-day period February 9 through February 28.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
