<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Boreal summer North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) indices
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> have tended to be in the negative phase in the last decade
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>, blue line, in this paper), as characterized by high surface pressure anomalies over Greenland and low anomalies over the North Atlantic. The negative phase of the NAO has relevance to conditions in the Arctic and for the Greenland Ice Sheet in particular, as it enhances the potential for ice mass loss. Recent, severe surface melt in Greenland such as in 2007, 2010, and 2012
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> occurred while the NAO was in its strong negative phase. An exceptionally strong positive phase of the NAO occurred in the summer of 2013, concurrent with a noticeable recovery of the Arctic sea ice cover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. The phase of the summer NAO has also been associated with Atlantic tropical cyclone activity on sub-seasonal time scales during the hurricane season
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. The focus of this paper is to explore whether a remote impact of sea surface temperatures (SSTs) over the subtropical Pacific on the Arctic climate as characterized in earlier studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> may explain the interannual variability of this index in summer, including the recent, frequent occurrence of the negative phase.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Time series of the SST anomaly over the subtropical western-central Pacific (130°E–180°E, 0°–35°N) (black), the Arctic sea ice concentration (SIC) anomaly over the Beaufort Sea (180°–120°W, 75°–90°N) (red), and the phase of the NAO (blue) over the period 1980–2016. The NAO and SIC anomalies are averages for June, July, and August (JJA), while the SST anomaly is an average for April, May, and June (AMJ), which is two months before JJA to present time-lagged impact of the SST that leads the variation of SIC and NAO phase. Two spatial patterns represent (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) simultaneous correlations between the NAO indices and SIC for JJA, and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) two month lag correlation between the northern hemispheric SST in AMJ and the NAO in JJA. Green dots are plotted, where correlations are statistically significant at 5 percent.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39896_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e342" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have explored forcing mechanisms from both local and remote sources to account for Arctic-subpolar climate variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Arctic lower-tropospheric temperatures have been suggested to be largely a response to variations in Arctic sea ice cover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Recent, enhanced Arctic warming has also been suggested to influence climate in the Northern Hemisphere mid-latitudes via changes in the jet stream and in the planetary-scale wave propagation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. But other studies have suggested that Arctic warming and the atmospheric response are largely explained as being forced remotely for example, by anomalous SST, and poleward heat and/or moisture fluxes in lower-latitude oceans
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. This remote SST forcing was found to not only warm the Arctic mid-troposphere, but also trigger surface-based Arctic amplification through enhanced sea ice melt
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These differing views on the relative roles of local and remote forcing mechanisms have also been applied to trends in the NAO index. Numerous studies have examined the potential for Arctic warming to force the negative phase of the NAO or its related Arctic Oscillation (AO) index
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, while other studies have suggested the positive phase of the NAO in association with lower-latitude forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. The identification of the dominant forcing mechanism is consequential, as the expected amplification of high latitude conditions in a warming climate may suggest an associated change in the character of the NAO. Several modeling studies found little relation of the NAO phase in response to climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, while another study found a limited response that was confined to the summer season
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Potential changes in the NAO may become amplified by the effects of the associated circulation on the sea ice cover. Earlier studies reported that an upward trend in the NAO index was conducive to reduced Arctic sea ice cover during 1980s and 1990s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. But the exceptional Arctic sea ice cover reduction over the last two decades occurred despite the reversal in the NAO trend
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>, indicating a change in the physical relationship before and after ~2000.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we hypothesize that the physical linkage between lower-latitude forcing and the atmospheric response in the Arctic-subpolar region may characterize the atmospheric anomalies extending to the Arctic Atlantic sector and the vicinity of Greenland, contributing to a determination of the phase of the recent summer NAO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. For this study, we analyze reanalysis variables and observed sea ice concentration data, and perform atmospheric general circulation model (AGCM) experiments to 1) explore if the relationship between SST changes over the subtropical Pacific, variations in Arctic sea ice concentrations, and the phase of the seasonal mean NAO has become enhanced in recent summers and 2) address causality between the Pacific SST, the NAO, Arctic sea ice (i.e., time sequence of their occurrence), and their response time scales (time-lag). We also discuss the extent to which the variation of Arctic sea ice concentration and phase of the NAO in recent summers is correlated with the subtropical Pacific SST variation. We also examine the tendency towards a certain phase of the NAO under continued remote SST warming conditions by comparing observational and model results for recent summers and winters.
 </p>
</sec>
