<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Changes in the range distribution of species are the most widely understood effect of climate change as most ectothermic species show a strong unimodal temperature preference (Parmesan &amp; Yohe, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0153" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). The majority of evidence of range retractions of subarctic fish is based on predicted rather than observed effects (Comte et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). For example, occurrence rates of walleye, cisco, and Arctic charr are predicted to decline by 22%, 26%, and 73%, respectively, across the subarctic by 2070–2100 in part due to temperature increases under modeled climate scenarios (Hein, Öhlund, &amp; Englund, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Van Zuiden et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0193" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). In conjunction with temperature, range retractions of sensitive cold‐water species, Arctic charr and burbot (
 <italic class="italic">Lota lota</italic>), are also influenced by increases in productivity (Hayden, Myllykangas, Rolls, &amp; Kahilainen, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Jacobson, Stefan, &amp; Pereira, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Lehtonen, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Tammi, Lappalainen, Mannio, Rask, &amp; Vuorenmaa, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0185" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). Vertical range retractions of cold‐climate species are linked with changes in isotherms causing extinctions at low elevations where water temperature and possibly dissolved oxygen pass physiological performance thresholds (Isaak &amp; Rieman, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Whitney et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>); such reductions in distribution are not consistently compensated for by vertical colonization of higher elevations due to dispersal limitations (e.g., Lindholm et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0133" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Range expansions and invasion of temperate fish species are also predicted to occur in the subarctic zone due to increased water temperature, further complicating impacts of climate change (described in detail below). For example, smallmouth bass are predicted to increase their range by 55%–422% by 2070 in Ontario, Canada, based on 126 climate scenarios (Van Zuiden et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0193" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Pike (
 <italic class="italic">Esox lucius</italic>), ruffe, European perch, yellow perch (
 <italic class="italic">Perca flavescens</italic>), smallmouth bass, largemouth bass, roach, and ide have either been observed or predicted to expand their range into subarctic regions due to temperature increases with climate change (Alofs &amp; Jackson, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015a</xref>; Byström et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Hayden et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Henriksson, Wardle, Trygg, Diehl, &amp; Englund, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016a</xref>; Henriksson, Yu, Wardle, Trygg, &amp; Englund, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016b</xref>; Reist et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0163" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Sepulveda, Rutz, Ivey, Dunker, &amp; Gross, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0170" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
