<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">By altering temperature and hydrological regimes, climate change affects the cohort‐specific survival within freshwater fish populations. Increases in streamflow discharge during early spring contribute to higher mortality of salmon larvae by increasing streambed scouring where eggs are deposited (Cunjak et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Goode et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Temperature increases stimulate earlier hatching and larval emergence of cool‐water species (e.g., Harper &amp; Peckarsky, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Thermal tolerances for newly hatched salmonids are lower than older juveniles, therefore suggesting that temperature increases will increase larval mortality (Elliott &amp; Elliott, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). However, increases in winter temperature by 1–2°C did not alter mortality of eggs and larvae of subarctic salmonids, whitefish, and vendace (Karjalainen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), suggesting that extreme events will have the strongest effects on recruitment dynamics. Increased heatwaves will also increase the frequency and extent of fish kills for cohorts of adult or large‐bodied cold‐water salmonids as water temperatures approach the upper lethal limit (Arctic charr and brown trout: 22–25°C; whitefish and Atlantic salmon: 25–28°C; Elliott &amp; Elliott, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Vielma, Koskela, &amp; Ruohonen, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0195" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). Salmonid (Arctic grayling, Atlantic salmon) population recruitment is also impacted by climate change due to reduced rearing habitat size during low summer discharge, therefore negating positive effects of temperature on individual body growth (Bryant, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Hedger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Hobbie et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>; Jonsson &amp; Jonsson, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). In contrast, year‐class strength of cool‐ and warm‐water species (e.g., European perch and roach) is associated with years of warmer temperatures during spawning and early growth (e.g., Jeppesen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Nunn, Frear, Lee, &amp; Cowx, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Tolonen, Lappalainen, &amp; Pulliainen, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0191" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). Extreme events are unlikely to cause extirpation of fish species in the subarctic and arctic regions (due to the availability of thermal refugia) but, however, may impose significant stress to local populations, such as Arctic charr and burbot, especially in small shallow lakes and streams (Guzzo, Blanchfield, Chapelsky, &amp; Cott, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Lehtonen, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>). In contrast, prolonged warm summers frequently cause mortality of cisco (
 <italic class="italic">Coregonus artedi</italic>) via oxygen depletion, especially in unstratified lakes in North American lakes (Jacobson, Jones, Rivers, &amp; Pereira, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>).
</p>
