<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For its fifth Assessment Report in 2014, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) developed four greenhouse gas concentration trajectories (Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs)) to facilitate future assessments of climate change, including emissions mitigation. RCPs are named according to the radiative forcing levels from 2.6 to 8.5 
 <italic class="italic">W</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> shown in 
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. These comprise the lowest forcing level scenario (RCP 2.6), two medium stabilization scenarios (RCP 4.5/RCP 6.0), and the high-end baseline emission scenario (RCP 8.5). The Korea Meteorological Administration (KMA) provides future climate data generated from RCP scenarios [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. We compare the dynamics of dengue prevalence between the four types of climate change scenario RCP 2.6, 4.5, 6.0, and 8.5 to investigate the effect of climate change on dengue outbreaks. Temperature and precipitation data for Jeju Island under the assumption of the RCP scenarios consist of the average values estimated for the four regions Jeju, Seoguipo, Sungsan, and Gosan, which are located in a warm temperate zone [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. While the climate zones of Jeju Island are divided into a warm temperate zone, grassland zone, and cool temperature zone according to the altitude, more than 98% of the population of Jeju Island lives in the warm temperate area, which is less than 200 
 <italic class="italic">m</italic> above sea level [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Thus, our model focuses on the warm temperate area using the climate data provided by KMA. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0199205.g003" class="xref">Fig 3(a)</xref> illustrates the average daily temperature for five year intervals from 2020 to 2099. According to the RCP 4.5 and RCP 8.5 scenarios, the average temperature on Jeju Island in Korea will increase by 2.02°
 <italic class="italic">C</italic> in RCP 4.5 and 4.13°
 <italic class="italic">C</italic> in RCP 8.5 over 80 years. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0199205.g003" class="xref">Fig 3(b)</xref> illustrates the average daily precipitation for five year intervals on Jeju Island from 2020 to 2099.
</p>
