<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Primary occurrence records for 
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">ricinus</italic> were obtained from diverse sources. Data were drawn from the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.gbif.org</ext-link>; ~2110 occurrence points), VectorMap (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vectormap.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.vectormap.org</ext-link>; ~1801 occurrence points), and the scientific literature [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] (~1195 points; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0189092.s001" class="xref">S1 File</xref>). Sampling was concentrated in Great Britain and Germany thanks to surveillance by the European Vector Map Program of the European Center for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ecdc.europa.eu/en/healthtopics/vector/vector-maps/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ecdc.europa.eu/en/healthtopics/vector/vector-maps/</ext-link>). The initial set of occurrence records was subjected to several data cleaning steps to reduce possible biases in calibrating ecological niche models (ENMs) [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. (1) We discarded all records with unknown geographic references, and removed all duplicate records. (2) The data were further filtered by distance, so that all redundant records occurring in a single 10’ cell (~20 km) were omitted. (3) Finally, we accounted for marked differences in sampling density across countries: data records were filtered by balancing the density of occurrences on a country-by-country basis. We chose Spain as a reasonable intermediate-density reference point (6 occurrence records /100,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) to overcome problems associated with oversampling or undersampling observed in some countries. Although we discarded large numbers of data points, this step removes large-scale spatial biases, and allows a better estimation of niche characteristics [
 <xref rid="pone.0189092.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>].
</p>
