<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">The YDB impact hypothesis posits that the hemisphere-wide debris field of a large, fragmenting asteroid/comet struck Earth and caused brief “impact winter” conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. In turn, this triggered major shifts in continental drainage patterns, dramatically changed oceanic circulation, and caused abrupt global climate changes (temperature and precipitation) marked by the Younger Dryas (YD) climatic episode in the Northern Hemisphere
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. The airburst/impacts are proposed to have caused significant environmental changes, including widespread biomass burning, anomalously abrupt shifts in plant and animal distributions, human cultural changes and population declines, and broad extinctions within the iconic late Pleistocene megafauna
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Studies of the Younger Dryas boundary (YDB) layer report peak abundances of a diverse suite of proposed cosmic impact-related proxies at more than 50 sites, located mostly within the Northern Hemisphere, but with two previous sites in the Southern Hemisphere (Venezuela
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup> and Antarctica
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>). These include peak abundances of high-temperature high-iron (Fe) spherules, glassy silica-rich spherules, high-temperature meltglass, nanodiamonds, platinum (Pt), iridium (Ir), osmium (Os), and/or other impact-related proxies (for references, cf. Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">A2</xref> in Wolbach 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>). The YDB layer is also often marked by abundance peaks in biomass-burning proxies, including charcoal, aciniform carbon/soot, carbon spherules, glasslike carbon and/or combustion aerosols
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. This entire suite of proxies at the YD onset is argued to represent one of the largest known biomass-burning peaks of the late Quaternary
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
