<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Abnormalities in CCA germlings were more frequent in spores exposed to high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> than those growing under control conditions, suggesting a role of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in altering the normal development of early stages of CCA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189122.g004" class="xref">Fig 4A</xref>). A similar finding was reported for the Mediterranean CCA 
 <italic class="italic">Phymatolithon lenormandii</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Cell enlargement, cell density reduction and cell wall thinning in adult CCA exposed to high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> have also been described [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. In our study, the abnormal germlings presented irregular and enlarged cells, especially among cells forming the germination disc (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189122.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>). Irradiance variability also modified the normal development of germlings in our study, with more abnormal germlings occurring at low irradiance intensity agreeing with the fact that low irradiance does not seem optimal for 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">onkodes</italic> development [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. The reasons why low irradiance causes abnormalities is unclear, but it is likely that abnormal development is related to reduced availability of resources for growth (e.g. light). Spores from other macroalgae are quite sensitive to environmental stressors such as elevated nutrients [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>] and high irradiance intensity [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. The implications of spore abnormalities for subsequent early development, spore viability, and life cycle of CCA are unknown, but abnormal early development may impact adult populations as shown in terrestrial plants [e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]].
</p>
