<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 3</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Large-scale reduction of genetic variation for seasonal plasticity across the transcriptome. 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>, 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold> An order of magnitude more genes show significant differential expression due to seasonal environment and genetic background than due to the interaction between environment and genetic background for abdomen (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>) and thorax (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>). Within each Venn diagram, numbers of differentially expressed genes (FDR &lt; 0.05) are indicated for seasonal environment (left), genetic background (right), and their interaction (top), as well as overlap in responses among genes. Small insets in 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> illustrate expression patterns for each gene group, showing mean normalised expression in wet and dry season for random genes in each group, with reaction norms for different full-sib families represented by different colours. 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>, 
   <bold class="bold">d</bold> Across all genes in the abdomen (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) and thorax (
   <bold class="bold">d</bold>) transcriptome, mean absolute expression changes (log
   <sub class="sub">2</sub> fold change) due to the interaction between environment and genetic background (i.e., transcriptional plasticity or GxE; right boxplot) are 43–51% smaller than those due to genetic background (i.e., genetic variation for average expression or G; middle boxplot; ***
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Only 120 and 88 transcripts (in abdomen and thorax, respectively) showed more than a twofold expression change as a result of inter-family differences in plasticity, compared to 1054 and 766 transcripts above that threshold for inter-family difference in average expression. 
   <bold class="bold">e</bold>, 
   <bold class="bold">f</bold> Families are more similar in how expression responds to the environment than in average expression levels, with reaction norms for expression of all genes showing on average 57 and 32% lower across-family variance in slope (right, black) than in intercept (left, blue) for abdomen (
   <bold class="bold">e</bold>) and thorax (
   <bold class="bold">f</bold>), respectively (***
   <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). 
   <italic class="italic">P</italic>-values are for two-sample Wilcoxon signed-rank tests (two-sided). Upper whiskers are at the upper quartile plus 1.5× the interquartile range or at the maximum value (whichever is lowest), whereas lower whiskers extend to the lower quartile minus 1.5× the interquartile range or to the minimum value (whichever is highest)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3384_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e688" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
