<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5008777</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27583363</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-16-14891</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Atmospheric Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Climatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Climate Change</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Materials by Attribute</subject><subj-group><subject>Contaminants</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Research and Analysis Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Research Facilities</subject><subj-group><subject>Mesocosms</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and Technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Environmental Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Pollution</subject><subj-group><subject>Water Pollution</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and Environmental Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Limnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Effluent</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Limnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Effluent</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Marine and Aquatic Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Water Quality</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Organisms</subject><subj-group><subject>Viruses</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hell and High Water: Diminished Septic System Performance in Coastal Regions Due to Climate Change</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Septic Systems and Climate Change</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>Jennifer A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001"><sup>&#x000a4;</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>George W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>Jose A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Soil Ecology and Microbiology, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, Rhode Island, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>New England Onsite Wastewater Training Center, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, Rhode Island, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>Andrew C</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Natural Environment Research Council, UNITED KINGDOM</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> JAC GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Data curation:</bold> JAC JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Formal analysis:</bold> JAC JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Funding acquisition:</bold> JAC GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Investigation:</bold> JAC GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Methodology:</bold> JAC GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Project administration:</bold> GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Resources:</bold> GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Software:</bold> JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Validation:</bold> JAC JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Visualization:</bold> JAC GWL JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing &#x02013; original draft:</bold> JAC JAA.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing:</bold> JAC GWL JAA.</p></list-item></list></p></fn><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001"><label>&#x000a4;</label><p>Current address: University of Florida Everglades Research and Education Center, Belle Glade, Florida, United States of America</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>jencooper@ufl.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0162104</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 Cooper et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cooper et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0162104.pdf"/><abstract><p>Climate change may affect the ability of soil-based onsite wastewater treatment systems (OWTS) to treat wastewater in coastal regions of the Northeastern United States. Higher temperatures and water tables can affect treatment by reducing the volume of unsaturated soil and oxygen available for treatment, which may result in greater transport of pathogens, nutrients, and biochemical oxygen demand (BOD<sub>5</sub>) to groundwater, jeopardizing public and aquatic ecosystem health. The soil treatment area (STA) of an OWTS removes contaminants as wastewater percolates through the soil. Conventional STAs receive wastewater from the septic tank, with infiltration occurring deeper in the soil profile. In contrast, shallow narrow STAs receive pre-treated wastewater that infiltrates higher in the soil profile, which may make them more resilient to climate change. We used intact soil mesocosms to quantify the water quality functions of a conventional and two types of shallow narrow STAs under present climate (PC; 20&#x000b0;C) and climate change (CC; 25&#x000b0;C, 30 cm elevation in water table). Significantly greater removal of BOD<sub>5</sub> was observed under CC for all STA types. Phosphorus removal decreased significantly from 75% (PC) to 66% (CC) in the conventional STA, and from 100% to 71&#x02013;72% in shallow narrow STAs. No fecal coliform bacteria (FCB) were released under PC, whereas up to 17 and 20 CFU 100 mL<sup>-1</sup> were released in conventional and shallow narrow STAs, respectively, under CC. Total N removal increased from 14% (PC) to 19% (CC) in the conventional STA, but decreased in shallow narrow STAs, from 6&#x02013;7% to less than 3.0%. Differences in removal of FCB and total N were not significant. Leaching of N in excess of inputs was also observed in shallow narrow STAs under CC. Our results indicate that climate change can affect contaminant removal from wastewater, with effects dependent on the contaminant and STA type.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award001"><funding-source><institution>Rhode Island Agricultural Experiment Station</institution></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>Jose A</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award002"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100005784</institution-id><institution>Rhode Island Sea Grant, University of Rhode Island</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>Jose A</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="award003"><funding-source><institution>University of Rhode Island Enhancement of Graduate Research Program</institution></funding-source><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>Jennifer Anne</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>This study was funded by grants from Rhode Island Sea Grant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://seagrant.gso.uri.edu/">http://seagrant.gso.uri.edu/</ext-link>), the Rhode Island Agricultural Experiment Station (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.uri.edu/riaes/">http://web.uri.edu/riaes/</ext-link>), by a grant from University of Rhode Island Enhancement of Graduate Research Program to J.A.C. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.uri.edu/graduate-school/enhancement-of-graduate-research-awards-egra/">http://web.uri.edu/graduate-school/enhancement-of-graduate-research-awards-egra/</ext-link>), and by personal funds of the authors. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="18"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The soil treatment area (STA; also known as a drainfield or leachfield) of an onsite wastewater treatment system (OWTS) is an important component for removal of contaminants from wastewater. Treatment takes place as wastewater percolates through the unsaturated portion of the soil profile, where low moisture and high oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) levels are conducive to removal of pathogens, and where chemical and microbial processes can reduce the concentration of other contaminants. The extent of treatment in the STA depends on soil texture, residence time, and the volume of unsaturated soil the wastewater passes through, represented by the vertical separation between the infiltrative surface of the STA and the water table [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Because wastewater renovation relies on hydrologic, microbial and chemical processes, treatment of wastewater in the STA is sensitive to changes in soil moisture and temperature.</p><p>Wastewater contains contaminants that affect human and environmental health. Pathogenic organisms (bacteria, viruses, protozoa and nematodes) can cause illness in humans from ingestion or contact with contaminated water [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Excessive nitrate concentration in drinking water disrupts O<sub>2</sub> binding to red blood cells, known as methemoglobinemia [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and may cause breathing difficulties in infants. Inputs of nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) from OWTS to aquatic ecosystems contribute to eutrophication [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] in marine and fresh waters, respectively. Release of biodegradable organic carbon, as biochemical oxygen demand (BOD<sub>5</sub>), promotes microbial consumption of available O<sub>2</sub>, resulting in hypoxia and death of aquatic organisms [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Climate change, through the combined effects of temperature and sea level rise, is expected to affect contaminant removal in the STA in the Northeastern United States. Sea level rise will reduce the volume of unsaturated soil available for wastewater treatment in coastal areas. The sea level in the Northeastern U.S. is projected to rise 90&#x02013;120 cm by 2100 [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], resulting in higher water tables in coastal regions as denser saltwater displaces lighter freshwater. The effect of sea level rise on water table elevation will diminish with distance from the coast, affect areas with shallow water tables, and depend on the hydrology of the region. A USGS study of Cape Cod found median water table elevation to increase 19&#x02013;63 cm for modeled sea level elevations between 60 and 180 cm, with 30 cm or greater elevations occurring within approximately 10 km of the coast [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Furthermore, precipitation events are expected to increase in number and severity over the same time period [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The effects of greater evapotranspiration experienced during warmer temperature [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] is likely to mitigate and often exceed increased precipitation rates on an annual basis, however, at shorter temporal and smaller spatial scales, precipitation may be very large when there is little evapotranspiration. Higher groundwater tables will result in a wetter conditions that enhance the survival and transport of bacterial and viral pathogens [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Wetter soils may also result in microbial metal reduction, leading to lower P removal capacity and increased mobilization of P retained on soil particles [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In contrast, removal of N by microbial reduction to N<sub>2</sub> may be enhanced by diminished O<sub>2</sub> diffusion in wetter soils [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Finally, decomposition of organic carbon may be hindered or enhanced by increased soil moisture [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], which will affect BOD<sub>5</sub> removal. Because 40% of the U.S. population resides in coastal communities [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], sea level rise will likely impact coastal communities that rely on OWTS for wastewater renovation.</p><p>Elevated temperatures due to climate change may also affect contaminant removal in the STA. Atmospheric temperature is expected to increase 3&#x02013;5 &#x000b0;C in the next 100 years in the Northeastern U.S, warming the soil profile [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and warmer conditions have been shown to increase bacterial and viral pathogen mortality [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Microbial activity increases with warmer temperatures, which may enhance removal of BOD<sub>5,</sub> however, lower levels of BOD<sub>5</sub> may limit heterotrophic processes such as N removal by denitrification. Higher temperatures will also reduce O<sub>2</sub> solubility and increase microbial O<sub>2</sub> consumption, resulting in less O<sub>2</sub> available for aerobic treatment processes. In addition, this reduction in available O<sub>2</sub> can lead to low redox conditions, resulting in metal reduction and a diminished P removal capacity of soil.</p><p>In a conventional OWTS, solids are removed from wastewater by sedimentation in the septic tank, and septic tank effluent (STE) is dispersed to the STA for final treatment. The STA in a conventional OWTS is located deep in the soil profile&#x02013;generally in the C horizon&#x02013;where infiltration of STE into coarser textured soil with larger pores reduces the likelihood of hydraulic failure due to clogging. Shallow narrow drainfields, an alternative type of STA used with advanced wastewater treatment systems (designed to reduce waste strength, not designed to remove N), may be more resilient to climate change effects than conventional STAs. A shallow narrow STA receives effluent that has undergone secondary treatment in an advanced treatment component, resulting in higher dissolved oxygen levels, and reduced levels of BOD<sub>5</sub> and particulates in effluent prior to STA dispersal. The secondary treatment lowers the probability of hydraulic failure due to clogging of soil pore spaces, and allows the infiltrative surface to be placed higher in the soil profile than in a conventional STA. Shallower dosing affords a greater volume of unsaturated soil for treatment, and may provide better oxygenation, as well as enhanced filtration of wastewater through finer soil particles in the upper portion of the soil profile. In addition, shallow narrow STA designs incorporate frequent timed-dosing of small volumes of wastewater, preventing prolonged periods of soil saturation, which are common in a conventional STA. Together, these factors may make shallow narrow STAs more resilient to climate change than conventional STAs.</p><p>In a previous study we compared the water quality functions of conventional and shallow narrow STAs [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. We observed complete removal of fecal coliform bacteria (FCB), bacteriophage (a human virus surrogate) and total P, and near complete removal of BOD<sub>5</sub> in conventional and shallow narrow STAs [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Although limited, removal of total N was higher in the conventional STA [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In the present study we tested the hypothesis that climate change (higher shallower water table and increased temperature) would diminish removal of FCB, viral surrogates, and total P in conventional and shallow narrow STAs, whereas removal of BOD<sub>5</sub> and total N would be marginally improved. We expected the shallow narrow STAs to have comparatively better contaminant removal than conventional STAs because the former have a larger volume of soil for treatment. We evaluated these hypotheses in a laboratory experiment using triplicate intact soil mesocosms representing a conventional STA and two types of shallow narrow STAs. We compared the water quality functions of the STAs under present climate (PC) (20&#x000b0;C; vertical separation distance representative of regulatory values), and moderate 100-year predicted climate change (CC) (25&#x000b0;C; vertical separation distance reduced by 30 cm by raising the water table elevation) conditions. These conditions are generally representative of the expected climate changes in the glaciated Northeastern U.S.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Description of mesocosms</title><p>Intact soil cores were collected in PVC pipes (152-cm tall x 15-cm-diam.), and excavated in October 2012 from a 5-m long trench containing Bridgehampton silt loam soil (Coarse-silty, mixed, active, mesic Typic Dystrudepts) in Kingston, Rhode Island, USA. Bottom edges of PVC pipes were sanded until sharp to minimize soil compaction and gradual pressure was applied to the top with an excavator until desired core depth was achieved. Intact cores were transported to the laboratory (&#x0003c; 1 mile) in a flat-bed truck and engineered to represent one of three drainfield types in the laboratory:(i) conventional pipe and stone (P&#x00026;S), (ii) shallow narrow drainfield (SND), and (iii) Geomat&#x000ae; (GEO), a SND variation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g001">Fig 1</xref>), in triplicate. The infiltrative area was established at 20 cm below the ground surface for SND (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g001">Fig 1</xref>), at 25 cm for GEO, and at 84 cm for P&#x00026;S. Briefly, dosers were designed to replicate technology designs with sheet flow inside an upside down, halved 10-cm-diam. PVC dome for SND, diffused flow from a 2.5-cm-diam. PVC pipe through fused plastic filament mesh and geotextile filter fabric for GEO, and massive flow from a 10-cm-diam. PVC pipe placed between layers of stone for P&#x00026;S. Mixed A and B horizon topsoil covered dosers to previous soil surface level as per in-field practices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g001">Fig 1</xref>). A detailed description of the experimental design, sampling, and analytical methods can be found in [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><p><bold>(A) Schematic diagram of soil mesocosms representing a shallow narrow drainfield (SND), GeoMat<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (GEO), and pipe and stone (P&#x00026;S) soil treatment areas (STAs).</bold> The wastewater input to SND and GEO was sand filter effluent (SFE), whereas the P&#x00026;S received septic tank effluent (STE). The approximate location of soil horizons, ports for gas sampling, and moisture and temperature probes are indicated. Water exits the mesocosms through a hanging water column device used to adjust the height of the water table. The atmosphere in the infiltrative area is connected to a 30-cm soil column. <bold>(B) Detailed schematic diagram of the SND, GEO and P&#x00026;S delivery devices.</bold> Diagrams are not to scale. Heating cables were wrapped around mesocosms, covered with insulation, and connected to a digital thermostat to control soil temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Moisture</title><p>The separation distance from the water table was controlled using a hanging water column (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g001">Fig 1</xref>) and, to represent present climate (PC) conditions, was set at 102 cm below the infiltrative surface for SND and GEO, and at 56 cm for P&#x00026;S to replicate technology regulations [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. To simulate climate change (CC), the water table was raised 30 cm, resulting in a separation distance of 72 cm for SND and GEO, and 26 cm for P&#x00026;S. Soil EC-5 moisture probes and Em5b data loggers (Decagon Devices, Pullman, WA) were used to measure soil moisture every 15 minutes at depths of 15, 30, 45, 60 and 75 cm below the infiltrative surface for SND and GEO, and at 15 and 30 cm below the infiltrative surface for P&#x00026;S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Temperature</title><p>The mesocosms were maintained at 20.0 &#x000b1; 0.7&#x000b0;C under PC conditions, and the temperature increased to 25.0 &#x000b1; 0.7&#x000b0;C to simulate CC. This was accomplished by covering the outside of the mesocosms with heavy-duty aluminum foil (to increase heat diffusion), wrapping 115V heating cables (Hydrokable, Sacramento, CA) around the mesocosms, and wrapping reflective double bubble foil insulation material around the mesocosms. A thermostat (NEMA 4X, Aqua Logic, Inc., San Diego, CA) was used to regulate the temperature, and soil temperature was measured using iButton sensors (DS1921G, Maxim Integrated, San Jose, CA) buried 5 cm below the soil surface. Ceramic-tipped probes (YSI, Yellow Springs, OH) were used to measure soil temperature at depths of 0, 15, 30, 45, 60 and 75 cm below the infiltrative surface for SND and GEO, and at 0 and 15 cm below the infiltrative surface for P&#x00026;S (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g001">Fig 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Wastewater dosing and characteristics</title><p>The P&#x00026;S was dosed with 200 mL of septic tank effluent (STE) every 12 h over 1.5 h, corresponding to 400 mL d<sup>-1</sup> (22.6 L m<sup>-2</sup> d<sup>-1</sup>). The SND and GEO received wastewater that had passed through a single-pass sand filter (SFE). They were dosed with 22.5 mL SFE every 30 min over 15 min, corresponding to 2000 mL d<sup>-1</sup> (113 L m<sup>-2</sup> d<sup>-1</sup>). Dosing rates were based on regulations governing OWTS design in the state of Rhode Island [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Septic tank effluent and SFE were collected weekly from the same treatment train at a residence in South Kingstown, RI, USA. Permission was provided by the homeowners to access and sample their septic system for the duration of this study. Wastewater was stored in sealed plastic containers at 4&#x000b0;C in the dark after collection before dispensing small volumes to chilled plastic holding containers maintained at 4&#x02013;16&#x000b0;C for dosing. The characteristics of wastewater inputs (<xref rid="pone.0162104.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) are within the range observed by others [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><table-wrap id="pone.0162104.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of septic tank effluent (STE) and sand filter effluent (SFE) used in our study under present climate (n = 8 samples) and climate change (n = 11 samples) scenarios.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0162104.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0162104.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Analyte</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">STE</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">SFE</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">climate</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">change</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">climate</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">change</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#x000b1; 0.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 &#x000b1; 0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dissolved O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 &#x000b1; 0.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0 &#x000b1; 0.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 &#x000b1; 1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BOD<sub>5</sub></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219 &#x000b1; 61</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 &#x000b1; 79</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 &#x000b1; 7.3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 &#x000b1; 8.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Electrical conductivity</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">786 &#x000b1; 47</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">620 &#x000b1; 146</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">615 &#x000b1; 85</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">422 &#x000b1; 120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal coliform bacteria</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1; 1.7 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1; 1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1; 6.7 &#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup></td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b1; 2.8 &#x000d7; 10<sup>1</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total N</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 &#x000b1; 8.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 &#x000b1; 15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 &#x000b1; 8.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 &#x000b1; 11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>4</sub>-N</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 &#x000b1; 7.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 &#x000b1; 15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 &#x000b1; 4.8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 &#x000b1; 2.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<sub>3</sub>-N</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 &#x000b1; 8.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 &#x000b1; 8.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total P</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4 &#x000b1; 2.1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 &#x000b1; 1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PO<sub>4</sub>-P</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.70 &#x000b1; 1.7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 &#x000b1;1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SO<sub>4</sub>-S</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 &#x000b1; 2.4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 &#x000b1; 2.8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 &#x000b1;3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Field collection temperature</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 &#x000b1; 2.0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 &#x000b1; 6.1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 &#x000b1; 2.2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 &#x000b1; 6.8</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Values are means &#x000b1; standard deviation. All units are mg L<sup>-1</sup> except for pH, electrical conductivity (&#x003bc;S), fecal coliform bacteria (CFU 100 mL<sup>-1</sup>), and collection temperature (&#x000b0;C).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Analyses</title><p>Output water was collected at the bottom of the mesocosms under both climate conditions, in N<sub>2</sub>-purged, autoclaved 1-L Nalgene bottles fitted with an airlock, and the water was analyzed for pH, dissolved O<sub>2</sub>, BOD<sub>5</sub>, electrical conductivity, FCB, total N, ammonium, nitrate, total P, phosphate, and sulfate, as described in [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Samples for Al, Fe and Mn were acidified to pH&#x0003c;2 with HCl, and analyzed at the Brown University Environmental Chemistry Facility with a JY2000 Ultrace ICP Atomic Emission Spectrometer (Horiba, Kyoto, Japan) equipped with a JY AS 421 autosampler and 2400 g mm<sup>-1</sup> holographic grating. Details of MS2 viral measurement of concentration can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0162104.s002">S1 File</xref>&#x02014;Supplemental Methods.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Timeline</title><p>Mesocosms were prepared by initially filling with tap water from the bottom, and dosed with tap water at steady flow rates for 75 days. They were allowed to drain by gravity for two days before introduction of wastewater. The mesocosms received wastewater for 24 months prior to this experiment. The data representing PC in this study was collected for four months (July&#x02013;Oct., 2014) prior to implementation of CC conditions. Climate change data was collected after the STAs had equilibrated, approximately four months after the change in climate conditions (Feb.&#x02013;July, 2015). We estimated the time required for equilibration of STAs based on the time for recovery of water quality functions following environmental disturbances reported in [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], as well as stabilization of variation in water quality functions following elevation of water table and temperature in our experiment.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Damk&#x000f6;hler number</title><p>We evaluated N removal in the STA using the Damk&#x000f6;hler number (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>) [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], which compares the timescales of transport and reaction rate. Values <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> &#x0003c; 1 indicate that elevated rates of transport limit denitrification, and <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> &#x0003e; 1 indicate that reactant (e.g. NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>) consumption limits denitrification [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This approach has been employed successfully by others to identify the extent to which transport and biochemical reactions control removal of N in groundwater and riparian zones [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The Damk&#x000f6;hler number was calculated using the equation:
<disp-formula id="pone.0162104.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.e001.jpg" id="pone.0162104.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>
where <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> = Damk&#x000f6;hler number (unitless), <italic>k</italic> = reaction constant, zero-order (mg L<sup>-1</sup> h<sup>-1</sup>), <italic>C</italic><sub><italic>0</italic></sub> = initial concentration of nitrate (mg L<sup>-1</sup>), n = reaction order (zero order), &#x003c4; = mean residence time = <italic>L/v</italic> (h), where <italic>L</italic> = distance between sample ports (cm) and <italic>v</italic> = velocity (cm h<sup>-1</sup>) [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Statistics</title><p>A non-parametric two-way ANOVA was used to evaluate differences in removal of BOD<sub>5</sub>, FCB, total P, and total N as a function of STA type and climate conditions using untransformed data, except for total P, which was transformed using a 1/(n) transform. Means separation was accomplished using the Holm-Sidak method. A t-test was used to evaluate differences in input wastewater characteristics for STE and SFE between climate conditions. All statistical tests were performed on averaged replicate data by sampling date collected over four months, and evaluated at p &#x02264; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec012"><title>Increased moisture and lower O<sub>2</sub> under climate change</title><p>Climate change was expected to result in wetter soils with lower O<sub>2</sub> relative to PC in all three STAs. Water-filled pore space (WFPS) increased under CC for conventional and shallow narrow STAs at all depths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Values of WFPS for P&#x00026;S ranged from 3%-11% under PC and increased to 10%-47% under CC, whereas WFPS increased from 5%-23% to 16%-29% in the shallow narrow STAs under CC. The concentration of O<sub>2</sub> in soil pores was lower under CC relative to PC at all depths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Less O<sub>2</sub> and higher WFPS in the STA can have a number of consequences for contaminant removal processes, discussed below.</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Water-filled pore space (WFPS) in conventional (P&#x00026;S) and shallow narrow (SND and GEO) soil treatment areas under present climate and climate change.</title><p>Values represent the average WFPS over 24 h at each depth.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone.0162104.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Soil pore O<sub>2</sub> concentration under present climate and climate change for shallow narrow (SND and GEO) and conventional soil treatment areas.</title><p>Values are means (n = 3); error bars represent one standard deviation for a single mesocosm over four months.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>More BOD<sub>5</sub> removal under climate change</title><p>Climate change resulted in a decrease in the median concentration of BOD<sub>5</sub> in output water from 0.3 to 0.0 mg L<sup>-1</sup> for P&#x00026;S and SND, and remained at 0.0 mg L<sup>-1</sup> for GEO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>). The concentration of BOD<sub>5</sub> in output water was significantly different between climate conditions (p = 0.011), but not among STA types (p = 0.699) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Pairwise comparisons of means between STA types were not significant under either climate condition. However, there was significantly less BOD<sub>5</sub> present in input wastewater to P&#x00026;S. Variability in the concentration of BOD<sub>5</sub> in output water was higher for GEO and P&#x00026;S under CC in comparison to PC, whereas variability in output BOD<sub>5</sub> concentration in SND was similar between climate conditions.</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><p><bold>Concentration of biochemical oxygen demand (BOD<sub>5</sub>) (top) and fecal coliform bacteria (FCB) (bottom) in output water under present climate and climate change for shallow narrow (SND and GEO) and conventional (P&#x00026;S) soil treatment areas.</bold> Values are means (n = 3) at each sampling date. Boxes represent the median and interquartile range, whiskers represent the 10<sup>th</sup> and 90<sup>th</sup> percentiles, and dots represent values outside the 10<sup>th</sup> and 90<sup>th</sup> percentiles for all sample dates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g004"/></fig><sec id="sec014"><title>Less BOD<sub>5</sub> can limit heterotrophic processes</title><p>Our results generally support the hypothesis that BOD<sub>5</sub> removal may increase under CC. Soil microbial communities are carbon limited [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and BOD<sub>5</sub> is expected to be well removed in the STA. Decomposition of organic carbon in soil is dependent on soil moisture content and temperature [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Because both soil moisture and temperature increased with CC, we cannot ascertain the contribution of each variable to increased BOD<sub>5</sub> removal. Greater removal of BOD<sub>5</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>) under CC in SND and GEO may have limited heterotrophic processes in the STA, such as denitrification, as discussed below.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Release of FCB increased under climate change</title><p>No FCB were detected in output water under PC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>). In contrast, FCB was detected in output water from all three STA types under CC, with maximum concentrations of 17, 6, and 20 CFU 100 mL<sup>-1</sup> for P&#x00026;S, SND and GEO, respectively. Median output water concentrations were 0.0 CFU 100 mL<sup>-1</sup> for P&#x00026;S and GEO, and 0.1 CFU 100 mL<sup>-1</sup> for SND. Differences were not statistically significant between climate conditions (p = 0.106) or among STA types (p = 0.696). The presence of FCB in output water was more variable under CC for all STA types, with greater variability observed in SND and GEO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>).</p><sec id="sec016"><title>Wetter soil likely reduced microbial attachment</title><p>Unsaturated conditions favor FCB removal in the STA [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] by increasing the opportunity for attachment to soil particles. Increased moisture content likely reduced bacterial attachment to soil, resulting in more FCB in output water under CC. Greater bacterial survival has also been observed in wetter soils [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Growth of FCB may also have taken place under CC, as indicated by higher numbers of FCB in output water from SND and GEO under CC relative to inputs from SFE on two out of 11 sampling events (data not shown). Others [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] have observed the survival and propagation of <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> in soil. Generally, bacterial pathogens in soil experience increased mortality with increased temperatures [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, our results suggest that the combination of warmer and wetter soils may have enhanced the transport, survival and/or growth of FCB in all STA types.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>Temperature likely less important than moisture for FCB removal</title><p>A study modeling <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> transport in the STA at 20&#x000b0;C and 23&#x000b0;C found greater attenuation at the higher temperature, but predicted lower <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> removal under simulated increases in rainfall leading to wetter soils [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. These two effects were not coupled in the model; since we observed lower FCB attenuation in our experiment, this would suggest that the degree of soil moisture plays a larger role in bacterial removal than temperature.</p><p>Our results suggest the possibility of greater presence of FCB&#x02013;and thus pathogenic bacteria&#x02014;in output water, particularly if bacterial growth takes place under CC. Many pathogenic microorganisms require relatively small doses to cause illness in humans. For example, <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> O157:H7, which produces shiga toxin and can cause kidney failure and death, requires fewer than 10 cells to cause illness [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], while an infected human will release 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02212;10<sup>8</sup> cells in feces [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Virus removal unlikely to be impacted by climate change</title><p>We determined the effects of CC on the fate and transport of viruses using MS2 bacteriophage, a surrogate for human viruses [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. MS2 was not detected in output water from any STA type under PC or CC (data not shown). Greater virus transport and survival has been observed in wetter soils [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; however, virus inactivation generally increases with increased temperature [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><sec id="sec019"><title>Acidic soils may be important for viral removal</title><p>The absence of differences in virus removal between climate conditions and among STA types suggests a common mechanism for viral removal and inactivation under all of these conditions. Viral particles develop a positive charge at pH values below their isoelectric point (pI). The pI of most bacteriophage and animal viruses is &#x0003c; 7.0 [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and the pH of the soil in the STAs was &#x0003c; 3.5 [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], suggesting that viruses are likely retained on the negatively-charged soil surfaces. This ionic interaction is probably more important than the effects of temperature or soil moisture on the fate and transport of viruses in these STA types.</p><p>The absence of viruses in output water regardless of climate conditions has positive consequences for public health. Enteric viruses can cause illness in humans from ingestion of a single viral particle [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and the feces of a human infected with rotavirus contains up to 10<sup>7</sup> viral particles [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Our results are encouraging for virus removal in the STA, however, soils with higher pH and greater buffering capacity may not have a comparable virus removal capacity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Effects of climate change on N removal dependent on STA type</title><p>The median total N removal was lower under CC for SND and GEO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g005">Fig 5</xref>), decreasing from 6% to -11% in SND and from 7% to 3% in GEO, resulting in a net increase in total N concentration in output water relative to PC conditions. In contrast, the median total N removal for P&#x00026;S increased, from 14% under PC to 19%, under CC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g005">Fig 5</xref>). The differences in total N removal between climate conditions were not significant (p = 0.171), although differences in removal among STA types were (p = 0.008). Pairwise comparisons of means between STA types indicated that P&#x00026;S was significantly different from SND or GEO; however, there was no significant difference in N removal between SND and GEO. Total N removal was more variable under CC for all STA types, which likely contributed to the absence of a statistically significant effect of climate conditions. There were more events of no net change in N concentration or net increase in total N concentration in output water under CC (data not shown). Under PC, 25% (SND) and 100% (GEO and P&#x00026;S) of the observations reflected net removal of total N. However, 27% (SND) and only 63% (GEO and P&#x00026;S) of CC observations resulted in net removal of total N. Although the frequency of total N leaching events in SND were similar between climate conditions, the concentration N in the output water was higher under CC.</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><p><bold>Total nitrogen (top) and total phosphorus (bottom) removal under present climate and climate change for shallow narrow (SND and GEO) and conventional (P&#x00026;S) soil treatment areas.</bold> Values are averages of three replicates by sampling date. Values are means (n = 3) at each sampling date. Boxes represent the median and interquartile range, whiskers represent the 10<sup>th</sup> and 90<sup>th</sup> percentiles, and dots represent values outside the 10<sup>th</sup> and 90<sup>th</sup> percentiles for all sample dates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g005"/></fig><p>Our results suggest that CC may increase inputs of N to ground water from shallow narrow STAs. Higher inputs of N to groundwater under CC increases the probability of affecting ecosystem and public health. Eutrophication from excessive inputs of N to saline water bodies may lead to hypoxia and anoxia when microorganisms decompose plant material after death, killing fish and other aerobic organisms. High levels of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> in ground water may also increase the risk of methemoglobinemia in infants.</p><sec id="sec021"><title>Heterotrophic N removal limited under climate change</title><p>Lower availability of organic carbon, measured as BOD<sub>5</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>), likely contributed to lower total N removal in SND and GEO under CC. Heterotrophic denitrification is considered to be the primary mechanism for N removal in the STA [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and requires organic carbon as an electron donor to produce N<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub>O from nitrate (NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>). The shallow narrow STAs receive SFE, which has a low initial concentration of BOD<sub>5</sub> as a result of passage through an aerobic sand filter (<xref rid="pone.0162104.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Greater removal of BOD<sub>5</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g004">Fig 4</xref>) under CC in SND and GEO may have limited heterotrophic denitrification in these STAs, particularly if BOD<sub>5</sub> removal takes place closer to the infiltrative surface. In contrast, the P&#x00026;S drainfield receives STE, which has a higher initial concentration of BOD<sub>5</sub> (<xref rid="pone.0162104.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), and organic carbon availability may not limit total N removal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g005">Fig 5</xref>).</p><p>The leaching of total N in excess of inputs may be due to an increase in the frequency of N cycling. In a previous study [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], we presented evidence of internal recycling of N through uptake and re-mineralization of microbial biomass N. Establishment of climate change conditions, and more frequent incidents of water table perching [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] in SND and GEO, may have caused the rate of internal N recycling to increase, increasing the probability that sampling occurred when net leaching of N to output water took place.</p><p>Microbial processes other than heterotrophic denitrification can contribute to N removal in the STA, including N<sub>2</sub>O production from nitrification [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], N<sub>2</sub> production from anaerobic ammonia oxidation [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and N<sub>2</sub> production from autotrophic denitrification [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. We have shown evidence for the occurrence of these processes in the STA [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Lower available O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g003">Fig 3</xref>) due to warmer and wetter conditions under CC would be expected to favor N removal by both autotrophic and heterotrophic processes in all three STAs. However CC may have impacted heterotrophic N removal negatively due to organic carbon limitations in shallow narrow STAs.</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>Rapid movement of wastewater in STA may limit N removal</title><p>We evaluated N removal in the STA using the Damk&#x000f6;hler number (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>) [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], which compares the timescales of transport and reaction rate. Our analysis shows that rapid movement of water through the STA limits N removal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g006">Fig 6</xref>), as indicated by values of <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> &#x0003c; 1 for all STA types (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0162104.s003">S1 Table</xref>). The residence time of the wastewater is 3&#x02013;4 times greater in P&#x00026;S than SND and GEO. Furthermore, the value of <italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub> is lower for SND and GEO, and higher for P&#x00026;S under CC relative to PC, reflecting differences in the reaction rates between climate conditions, since we assumed the velocity of water remains the same under both climate regimes. Our results suggest that the movement of water through the STA may be too rapid for substantial denitrification to take place, regardless of STA type and climate conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0162104.s003">S1 Table</xref>). Improvement of total N removal may be achieved through slower water movement, which would allow for higher rates of NO<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> consumption.</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Damk&#x000f6;hler number (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>) values under present climate (PC) and climate change (CC) for N removal in shallow narrow (SND and GEO) and conventional (P&#x00026;S) soil treatment areas.</title><p>Values are means of the range of possible values and error bars represent one standard deviation of the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>Models of N removal need more parameterization</title><p>In a model simulation of N removal in our STA mesocosms, Morales et al. [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] predicted increased N removal at 23&#x000b0;C (in comparison to 20&#x000b0;C) under PC depth to the water table, and higher N removal as the water table was elevated. The poor agreement between the modeled simulation and experimental results suggests that additional parameters affected by CC, such as higher consumption of organic C, need to be incorporated in the model.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec024"><title>Phosphorus removal diminished under climate change</title><p>Median total P removal under PC was close to 100% for SND and GEO, and declined to 71% for SND and 72% for GEO under CC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g005">Fig 5</xref>). Median total P removal in P&#x00026;S also declined, from 75% under PC to 66% under CC. The differences in total P removal between climate conditions were significant (p = &#x0003c;0.001), as were differences in removal among STA types (p = 0.004). Pairwise comparisons of means between STA types indicated that P&#x00026;S was significantly different from SND or GEO; however, SND and GEO did not have different removal. As was the case for removal of other wastewater constituents, we observed higher variability in total P removal under CC than under PC in all STA types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g005">Fig 5</xref>).</p><sec id="sec025"><title>Reduction of metal-P complexes mobilize P</title><p>Our results support the hypothesis that total P removal may diminish under CC for all STA types. The mechanism for this effect may involve lower availability of O<sub>2</sub> in the STA under climate change. Limited O<sub>2</sub> availability likely lead to microbial reduction and increased solubility of redox-active metals (Fe and Mn) in soil involved in forming insoluble precipitates with phosphate. Along with formation of precipitates with Al oxides, this is thought to be the primary mechanism for total P removal in the STA [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Reduction of Fe and Mn increases their solubility, which not only releases phosphate bound to Fe and Mn oxides into the dissolved phase, but also results in a decrease in the number of metal oxide sites available for reaction with&#x02013;and retention&#x02013;of phosphorus. Dissolution of Al at the acidic pH found in the STA (&#x0003c; 3.5) may have also contributed to P leaching [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], however, the pH of the output water, and likely STA soil (data not run), was similar under both climate conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec026"><title>Abiotic mechanisms appear more important for P retention</title><p>To differentiate between potential abiotic mechanisms affecting P removal, we plotted the concentration of dissolved Fe, Mn and Al in output water versus the concentration of total P for all three STA types under PC and CCe (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g007">Fig 7</xref>). The closer the slope of the line of metal concentration vs. P in solution is to 1 (indicating stronger coupling)&#x02013;which describes the stoichiometry of the metal-P complexes&#x02013;the more likely it is that P was released from complexes formed with that metal. Under PC, the slope of the line for all three metals is considerably less than 1, indicating that dissolution of metal-P complexes was not responsible for release of total P to output water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g007">Fig 7</xref>). In contrast, under CC the slope of the line for Fe and Mn is much closer to 1, suggesting that reduction of these metals became more important for total P release under CC. Because Al and total P in output water were not strongly coupled (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g007">Fig 7</xref>), it appears that climate change did not influence this mechanism.</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Concentrations of Fe, Al and Mn vs. total P (TP) in output water from all three STA types (n = 8).</title><p>Dashed line describes the stoichiometry of metal-P complexes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g007"/></fig><p>Our results suggest that the concentration of total P in output water from the STA may increase under CC. The resulting higher levels of total P in groundwater can eventually lead to increased eutrophication of freshwater bodies. In addition to the detrimental effects of eutrophication on aquatic organisms, it may also lead to public health concerns related to production of trihalomethanes (THM), carcinogenic compounds produced from chlorination of drinking water with a high concentration of dissolved organic carbon [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Algal blooms can also result in the production of human toxins that prevent use of surface water for drinking [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec027"><title>Whole system evaluation</title><p>To compare the performance of the treatment trains that include conventional and shallow narrow STAs under PC and CC, we estimated contaminant removal over the course of a year (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g008">8</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0162104.s001">S1</xref>). We used mean values for contaminant concentrations in input water (<xref rid="pone.0162104.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and, for treatment trains including SND and GEO, assumed that contaminant removal rates in the sand filter did not change with climate change. At the system scale, more BOD<sub>5</sub> was released from a treatment train with a conventional STA than from treatment trains with shallow narrow STAs under both climate conditions, likely due to sand filter pre-treatment. A greater number of FCB were present in output water from systems with a shallow narrow STAs than a system with a conventional STA under CC conditions, whereas complete FCB removal was observed under PC in all three systems. A higher mass of total P was released from treatment trains with a conventional STA than from treatment trains with shallow narrow STAs under both climate conditions. A greater mass of total N was present in output water from systems with a conventional STA under PC, however, more total N was present in output water from systems with shallow narrow STAs under CC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0162104.g008">Fig 8</xref>). Because the shallow narrow systems are not designed to enhance N removal, use of alternative OWTS with advanced N removal components should improve N removal rates regardless of climate conditions.</p><fig id="pone.0162104.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162104.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title>Yearly estimates of mass of BOD<sub>5</sub>, total P and total N, and number of fecal coliform bacteria released to groundwater from treatment trains that include P&#x00026;S and shallow narrow (SND &#x00026; GEO) soil treatment areas under present climate (dark bars) and climate change (light bars).</title><p>Error bars represent difference in removal between SND and GEO.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0162104.g008"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec028"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our results indicate that CC can affect contaminant removal, with effects dependent on the contaminant and STA type. Removal of FCB, total P and total N in shallow narrow STAs diminished under CC conditions. In contrast, total N removal in conventional STAs improved. Viral pathogens and BOD<sub>5</sub> were well removed under PC and CC, suggesting that OWTS were more resilient with respect to these contaminants.</p><p>Although conditions in the field may diverge from those in the laboratory, our experiment allowed us to make direct comparisons between PC and CC among different STA types. We recognize that systems installed under field conditions have more performance variability than systems evaluated under laboratory conditions [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Warming the entire STA, as opposed to only the near surface under field conditions, enabled us to make direct observations between the two temperature conditions at all depths in the soil profile. While the length of our study was relatively short, the limited duration prevented extreme temporal variation in the STA microbial communities between climate conditions.</p><p>The response of abiotic and biotic components in OWTS to differing temperature and moisture conditions may be different. For example, the rate of soil microbial processes is known to double with a 10&#x000b0;C increase in temperature [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In contrast, the rate of chemical reactions generally respond in a linear manner to increases in temperature over the range of temperatures experienced by soil [<xref rid="pone.0162104.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Nevertheless, our results demonstrate the potential effects of climate change on different types of OWTS. This study provides regulators with a starting point for future planning as well as providing an impetus for designing improvements for OWTS technologies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec029"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0162104.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Estimates of field-scale mass loading from septic tank, sand filter and soil-based treatment for an advanced system with a shallow narrow (SND) or GeoMat<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (GEO) soil treatment area, and for a conventional system with a pipe and stone (P&#x00026;S) soil treatment area.</title><p>Removal values (%) are for the previous step in the treatment train. Units are kg yr<sup>-1</sup> except for fecal coliform bacteria (FCB), which are CFU yr<sup>-1</sup>.</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0162104.s001.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0162104.s002"><label>S1 File</label><caption><title>Supplemental Methods.</title><p>Methodology for the propagation, addition and detection of MS2 bacteriophage in the pipe and stone (P&#x00026;S), shallow narrow (SND) and Geomat&#x000ae; soil treatment areas (STAs).</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0162104.s002.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0162104.s003"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Measured parameters used to calculate the Damk&#x000f6;hler Number (<italic>D</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub>) under present climate (PC) and climate change (CC) conditions for nitrate removal within shallow narrow (SND/GEO) and conventional (P&#x00026;S) soil treatment areas.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0162104.s003.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Alissa Becker, Rachel Naylor, Faith Anderson, Ivan Morales, David Kalen, Tom Boving and Dave Potts for technical and field assistance. We are especially grateful to the homeowners that provided us access to their onsite wastewater treatment system.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0162104.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cogger</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hajjar</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sobsey</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Septic system performance on a coastal barrier island</article-title>. <source>J Environ Qual</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>408</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Anderson DL, Otis RJ, McNeillie, Apfel RA. In-situ lysimeter investigation of pollutant attenuation in the vadose zone of a fine sand. In: On-Site Wastewater Treatment: Proceedings of the Seventh International Symposium on Individual and Small Community Sewage Systems. ASAE, St. Joseph, MI. 1994; pp. 209&#x02013;218.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Powelson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerba</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Virus removal from sewage effluents during saturated and unsaturated flow through soil columns</article-title>. <source>Water Resour</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>2175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2181</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stevik</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ausland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hassen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Retention and removal of pathogenic bacteria in wastewater percolating through porous media: A review</article-title>. <source>Water Resour</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1367</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">USEPA. United States Environmental Protection Agency. Onsite Wastewater Treatment Systems Manual. EPA/625/R-00/008. Office of Water, Washington D.C. 2002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shuval</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gruener</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Epidemiological and toxicological aspects of nitrates and nitrites in the environment</article-title>. <source>Am J Public Health</source>. <year>1972</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 5046442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5046442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Howarth</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrogen as the limiting nutrient for eutrophication in coastal marine ecosystems: evolving views over three decades</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>51</issue>): <fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mallin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ensign</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Factors contributing to hypoxia in rivers, lakes, and streams</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>51</issue>): <fpage>690</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>701</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IPCC. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</collab>. <chapter-title>Climate change 2013: the physical science basis</chapter-title>
<name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Platter</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tignor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boschung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (eds.). <source>Contributions of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the IPCC</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, U.K. and New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>
<year>2013</year>; pp. <fpage>1535</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Walter DA, McCobb TD, Masterson JP, Fienen MJ. Potential effects of sea-level rise on the depth to saturated sediments of the Sagamore and Monomoy flow lenses on Cape Cod, Massachusetts. US Geological Survey; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NRCC. Northeast Regional Climate Center. 2016. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nrcc.cornell.edu/regional/tables/tables.html">http://www.nrcc.cornell.edu/regional/tables/tables.html</ext-link> (Verified 8 August 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Biederbeck</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Soil bacterial changes as affected by growing season weather conditions: a field and laboratory study</article-title>. <source>Can J Soil Sci</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>310</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Quanrud</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerba</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Virus removal during simulated soil-aquifer treatment</article-title>. <source>Water Resour</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>762</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Enhanced attenuation of septic system phosphate in noncalcareous sediments</article-title>. <source>Groundwater</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>48</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Aerobic and anaerobic microbial populations in no-till and plowed soils</article-title>. <source>Soil Sci Soc Am J</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>794</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>799</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verchot</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Catt&#x000e2;nio</surname><given-names>J H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>I L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of soil water content on soil respiration in forests and cattle pastures of eastern Amazonia</article-title>. <source>Biogeochemistry</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NOAA. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. State of the coast: the U.S. population living at the coast; 2011. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://stateofthecoast.noaa.gov/population/welcome.html">http://stateofthecoast.noaa.gov/population/welcome.html</ext-link>. (Verified 14 March 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gerba</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melnick</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fate of wastewater bacteria and viruses in soil</article-title>. <source>J Irrig Drain Eng</source>.<year>1975</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glozman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nitzan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Contribution of microbial activity to virus reduction in saturated soil</article-title>. <source>Water Resour</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>2589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2595</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalen</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluation of water quality functions of conventional and advanced soil-based onsite wastewater treatment systems</article-title>. <source>J Environ Qual</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>962</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2014.06.0277</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26024275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26024275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">RIDEM. Rhode Island Department of Environmental Management. Rules Establishing Minimum Standards Relating to Location, Design, Construction and Maintenance of Onsite Wastewater Treatment Systems. 2010. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dem.ri.gov/pubs/regs/regs/water/owts10.pdf">http://www.dem.ri.gov/pubs/regs/regs/water/owts10.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 9 August 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">RIDEM. Rhode Island Department of Environmental Management. Guidelines for the design, use, and maintenance of pressurized drainfields. 2013. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dem.ri.gov/programs/benviron/water/permits/isds/pdfs/pdflds.pdf">http://www.dem.ri.gov/programs/benviron/water/permits/isds/pdfs/pdflds.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 9 August 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Siegrist RL. Advancing the science and engineering of onsite wastewater systems. In: On-Site Wastewater Treatment: Proceedings of the Ninth International Symposium on Individual and Small Community Sewage Systems. ASAE, St. Joseph, MI. 2001; pp. 1&#x02013;10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Loomis GW, Dow D, Stolt MH, Sykes AD, Gold AJ. Performance evaluation of innovative treatment technologies used to remediate failed septic systems. In: On-Site Wastewater Treatment: Proceedings of the Ninth International Symposium on Individual and Small Community Sewage Systems. ASAE, St. Joseph, MI. 2001; pp. 52&#x02013;61.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f6;rres</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicosia</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of aeration on water quality from septic system leachfields</article-title>. <source>J Environ Qual</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1838</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15356244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15356244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amador JA, Loomis GW, Kalen D, Patenaude EL, Gorres JH, Potts DA, et al. Evaluation of Leachfield Aeration Technology for Improvement of Water Quality and Hydraulic Functions in Onsite Wastewater Treatment Systems. The NOAA/UNH Cooperative Institute for Coastal and Estuarine Environmental Technology, Durham, NH. 2007; pp 12&#x02013;15.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fogler HS. Essentials of chemical reaction engineering. Pearson Education. 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ocampo</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oldham</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sivapalan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrate attenuation in agricultural catchments: Shifting balances between transport and reaction</article-title>. <source>Water Resour Res</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Domenico</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>The equations of mass transport</chapter-title> In: <source>Physical and chemical hydrogeology</source>. <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
<year>1998</year>; pp. <fpage>296</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schimel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaeffer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Microbial control over carbon cycling in soil</article-title>. <source>The causes and consequences of microbial community structure</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kirchhof</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Menzies</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Long-term flow rates and biomat zone hydrology in soil columns receiving septic tank effluent</article-title>. <source>Water Resour</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>40</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2338</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ksoll</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sadowsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Presence and growth of naturalized Escherichia coli in temperate soils from Lake Superior watersheds</article-title>. <source>Applied and environmental microbiology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>612</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16391098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Byappanahalli</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujioka</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence that tropical soil environment can support the growth of Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Water Science and Technology</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boving</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bacteria transport in a soil-based wastewater treatment system under simulated operational and climate change conditions</article-title>. <source>J Environ Qual</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2014.12.0547</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26436263?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26436263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">US Food and Drug Administration. Bad bug book: Foodborne pathogenic microorganisms and natural toxins handbook. Listeria monocytogenes. 1992.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Feachem</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garelick</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mara</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Health aspects of excreta and sullage management&#x02014;a state-of-the-art review</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>The World Bank</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington D.C.</publisher-loc>
<year>1980</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Cuyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegrist</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evaluating microbial purification during soil treatment of wastewater with multicomponent tracer and surrogate tests</article-title>. <source>J Environ Qual</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>316</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14964386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14964386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Michen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graule</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Isoelectric point of viruses</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Microbiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2010.04663.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20102425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20102425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Introduction to environmental virology</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
<year>1980</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Radcliffe</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrogen fate and transport in a conventional onsite wastewater treatment system installed in a clay soil: Experimental results</article-title>. <source>Vadose Zone J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bunnell</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zampella</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparison of nitrogen removal by subsurface pressure dosing and standard septic systems in sandy soils</article-title>. <source>J Environ Manage</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Crites</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tchobanoglous</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <source>Small and Decentralized Wastewater Treatment Systems</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston/London</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>WCB/McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>
<year>1998</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrogen transformations in different types of soil treatment areas receiving domestic wastewater</article-title>. <source>Ecol Eng</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>94</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wrage</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Velthof</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Beusichem</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oenema</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>Role of nitrifier denitrification in the production of nitrous oxide</article-title>. <source>Soil Biol Biochem</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1732</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spoelstra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elgood</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Natural attenuation of septic system nitrogen by anammox</article-title>. <source>Groundwater</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>553</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kanter RD, Tyler EJ, Converse JC. A denitrification system for domestic wastewater using sulfur oxidizing bacteria. In: Onsite Wastewater Treatment: Proceedings of the Eighth International Symposium on Individual and Small Community Sewage Systems. ASAE, St. Joseph, MI. 1998; p. 509&#x02013;510.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Robertson LA, Kuenen JG. Physiology of nitrifying and denitrifying bacteria. In: Rogers JE, Whitman WB, editors. Microbial production and consumption of greenhouse gases: methane, nitrogen oxides and halomethanes. Am Soc Microbiol, Washington, D.C. 1991; pp.189-199.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boving</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modeling nitrogen losses in conventional and advanced soil-based onsite wastewater treatment systems under current and changing climate conditions</article-title>. <source>PLOS ONE</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e0158292</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0158292</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27355369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27355369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Palmstrom</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Potential links between eutrophication and the formation of carcinogens in drinking water</article-title>. <source>Lake and Reservoir Management</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarver</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Toxic peptides from freshwater cyanobacteria (blue-green algae). I. Isolation, purification and characterization of peptides from Microcystis aeruginosa and Anabaena flos-aquae</article-title>. <source>Toxicon</source>. <year>1986</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>9</issue>): <fpage>865</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 3101230?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3101230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paerl</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moisander</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dyble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Harmful freshwater algal blooms, with an emphasis on cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>The Scientific World Journal</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12805693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oakley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oczkowski</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nitrogen control through decentralized wastewater treatment: Process performance and alternative management strategies</article-title>. <source>Ecol Eng</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1520</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Soil water content and temperature as independent or confounded factors controlling soil respiration in a temperate mixed hardwood forest</article-title>. <source>Global change biology</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0162104.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Silberberg</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Chemistry: The molecular nature of matter and change</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>; <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>