<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31" class="p">To represent the anticipated change in climate in the 11 sites (see Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref> for a detailed description of the site conditions), climate data for the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century were obtained from the Landscape Dynamics Unit at the Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research (WSL). Data were spatially interpolated at 1 km resolution. Three Regional Climate Models (RCMs) nested in the General Circulation Model ECHAM5 were used to derive climate data based on the IPCC
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup> AR4 SRES scenario A1B, providing us with the alternatives KNMI (
 <italic class="italic">Royal Netherlands Meteorological Institute KNMI RACMO2</italic>), SMHI (
 <italic class="italic">Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Inst. SMHI RCA30</italic>), and MPI (
 <italic class="italic">Max-Planck-Institute for Meteorology MPI CLM</italic>). To derive anomalies, we used the periods 1950-2000 for KNMI, 1961–2000 for SMHI and 1960–2000 for MPI from the WorldClim dataset
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> as baseline periods and the period 2090–2100 as representative for future conditions. Averaged changes in mean annual temperature and annual precipitation sums between the two periods are shown in Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S3</xref>. Note that we chose to use one SRES scenario but several RCMs because variability was greater between RCMs than between scenarios from IPCC
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly to Rasche 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>, we averaged the nine cells covering and surrounding each of our 11 locations.
</p>
