<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone.0204369.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0204369.g005</object-id>
 <label class="label">Fig 5</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">a. Behavioral patterns in the equal treatment based on average contribution during the evolution of the game</bold>. The value in each cell represents the average contribution normalized by the initial capital per round (i.e: 2 for participants starting with 20 €, 3 for participants starting with 30 €, and so on; 0.5 is the fair contribution) in a given stage of the game (depending on the accumulated contribution at that stage). 
   <bold class="bold">b. Proportion of individuals in the equal treatment groups</bold>. Cluster 1 is formed by generous subjects (61%) with average contribution above the fair while cluster 2 is formed by subjects (39%) that contribute around and below the fair contribution. Unequal treatment. 
   <bold class="bold">c. Behavioral patterns in the unequal treatment based on average contribution during the evolution of the game</bold>. The value in each cell represents the average contribution normalized by the initial capital per round in a given stage of the game (depending on the accumulated contribution at that stage). Cluster 1 consists of hyper-generous individuals (7.45%) that contribute very much above fair, cluster 2 is formed by generous individuals (43.48%) with average contribution above fair, and cluster 3 is formed by individuals (49.07%) that contribute around and below the fair contribution. 
   <bold class="bold">d. Proportion of individuals in the unequal treatment groups</bold>. Distribution of the different types among the participants as a function of their initial endowment.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0204369.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
