<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">The relevance of perceptual and socio-cognitive processes for climate change adaptation in agriculture are underlined by the fact that farmers’ adaptation decisions take place at local level and respond to perceived socio-environmental contexts including, for instance, social and institutional support, cultural values and norms, regional characteristics, and climate-related trigger events (Grothmann and Patt 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2005</xref>; Mitter et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2018</xref>). Against this background, perceptual and socio-cognitive processes have been investigated for farmers working in different cultural contexts and geographic regions, including major farming regions in North America (e.g. Arbuckle Jr et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2013</xref>; Doll et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2017</xref>; Haden et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2012</xref>; Mase et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2017</xref>; Nicholas and Durham 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2012</xref>), South America (e.g. Frank et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2011</xref>), Europe (Alcon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2014</xref>; Otto-Banaszak et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">2011</xref>; Woods et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">2017</xref>), Asia (Abid et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2015</xref>; Burnham and Ma 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2017</xref>; Dang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2014</xref>; Soriano et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" class="xref">2017</xref>), Africa (Mulenga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2017</xref>), and Australia and New Zealand (Niles et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">2016</xref>; Sanderson and Curtis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2016</xref>). The empirical results support the necessity to investigate and evaluate these processes within particular cultural and geographic contexts. For instance, Sanderson and Curtis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2016</xref> show that cultural factors influence farmers’ climate change risk perception, which inform their adaptation decisions. Such detailed analyses for specific cultures and regions also contribute to expand and extend the knowledge on climate change adaptation in agriculture and establish the basis for subsequent integrative research.
</p>
