<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We studied the responses of migratory caribou (
 <italic class="italic">Rangifer tarandus caribou</italic>) to trends in the availability of ice on lakes and rivers in an Arctic/subarctic region to assess potential mechanisms linking fine-scale individual behaviour to broad-scale climatic conditions. Predicting changes in caribou migration routes in response to climate change would aid conservation efforts for the species (notably regarding planning of human developments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>]) as well as ensure long-term sustainability of the Aboriginal hunt [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. Caribou perform one of the most impressive terrestrial long-distance migrations in the world [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. In Northern Québec (Canada), caribou travel distances up to 1 000 km from their calving grounds in the Ungava Peninsula to their wintering areas in the boreal forest. Along the way, they encounter many lakes and rivers, which are highly abundant in the region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>]. The potential consequences of crossing water bodies for caribou could depend on the availability of ice. Caribou are often observed swimming across open water bodies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>], but this type of locomotion is much less efficient and more energetically costly than walking [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Frozen water bodies are plane, wind-swept surfaces with packed snow and increased visibility that make them ideal substrates to move rapidly during travel. On the other hand, frozen lakes are entirely devoid of vegetation, and represent large open areas that may facilitate detection by predators [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>] and hunters [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. Thus, caribou encountering large water bodies may have to trade off energy maintenance (i.e., by crossing) with foraging opportunities (i.e., by going around), as well as mortality risk (including risks of drowning [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]).
</p>
