<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">All of these basins are exploited for hydropower, with an intake in each, either a single intake or a double pass intake, the first designed to settle out gravel and the second designed to settle out coarse sand, before abstracted water is transferred in tunnels to a storage lake, Lac de Dix. For regulatory reasons, each intake has to record precisely the volume of water (in m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>) that is abstracted. Thus, each has a broad-crested weir that has been calibrated to provide discharge data. However, once an intake is full of sediment, it has to be flushed, and this can be many times per day for the bigger basins with large glaciers (notably the Haut Glacier d’Arolla and Tsijiore Nouve, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). When the intake is flushed, the discharge falls rapidly and such drops can be seen clearly in discharge records (Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">M5.1</xref>). In almost all cases, flushing is related to the intake being full or nearly full with sediment and hence by counting the number of flushes per year, we can get an index of the level of activity in the upstream basins. There is an exception to this, for the Haut Glacier d’Arolla and Tsijiore Nouve, the operator introduced a different intake management system from 2008. For safety reasons, from this year, rather than waiting for when the intake was full, the intake was flushed at 23.30 each evening provided the intake was at least half full. This will increase the number of flushes recorded. Hence, from 2008 onwards, we calculate a range of total flush numbers, a maximum assuming that Haut Glacier d’Arolla and Tsijiore Nouve were full at evening flushing, and a minimum assuming they were only half full at night time flushing. The method used to identify flushes for the Haut Glacier d’Arolla, detailed in (29) is used for all other intakes except Tsijiore Nouve, where the method is detailed in (26). The data were used to determine total annual flushing rates for the six basins as an index of glacial sediment production. Work
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> has shown that flushing is primarily driven by glacial melt because of the importance of the latter for connecting subglacially eroded sediment to the basin outlet.
</p>
