<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relative amplitude of VWS due to climate change and AMV</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the future, AMV modulation of the tropical cyclone activity as seen during the historical period should continue and the relative amplitude of the anthropogenically forced change and the AMV could help determine the projections of future hurricane activity. This relative relationship is illustrated in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a> which shows the area averaged VWS for three geographical regions, the U.S. East Coast (25N–40N, 80W–60W), the Gulf Coast (20–30N, 95W–82W), and the MDR, for 1900 to 2100. The future anthropogenic emissions following both the rcp4.5 and rcp8.5 are included. The VWS associated with AMV is also indicated in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a> which illustrates the amplitude range of VWS due to AMV. While the magnitude of the MMM VWS associated with anthropogenic forcing is largely within the natural variability for the historical period, the decrease in the U.S. East Coast VWS (increase in the Gulf Coast) starts to dominate over the AMV VWS in the second half of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century. By the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century, the forced VWS in the coastal regions is almost twice as strong as that associated with the positive or negative phases of AMV, making possible for hurricanes to intensify faster along the U.S. East Coast (slower along the Gulf Coast). In the MDR, the VWS associated with AMV is rather large, and the increase in forced VWS only starts to dominate at the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> Century. The model spread of the VWS is fairly large, indicated by the light solid lines showing the 25th to 75th percentile of models’ values. But for the U.S. East Coast, the majority of the models indicate decreased VWS with magnitude ranging from +0.5 m/s to −2 m/s at the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> Century. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a> shows the VWS change in the CESM-LE. The ensemble spread in the single model is clearly much smaller than the multi-model spread in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>, with magnitude ranging from −1.5 m/s to −2.5 m/s at the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> Century. The VWS change in the CESM-LE is at the high end of the model spectrum as can be seen comparing Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a,c</a>. The MDR VWS changes show the largest multi-model spread and a relatively small amplitude. The large spread in this case is not surprising, as the spatial pattern in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> indicates a nodal point of VWS change in the MDR. The Gulf Coast shows an increase in VWS with the multi-model magnitude ranging from −0.5 m/s to +2 m/s. In the CESM-LE, both the MDR and the Gulf Coast show a similar magnitude increase in VWS with an ensemble range from +1 m/s to +2 m/s.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">a</span>) CMIP5 multi-model mean vertical wind shear for historical + rcp8.5 (thick solid lines), historical + rcp4.5 (thick dashed lines), and the 25% and 75% of the model spread using rcp8.5 (light solid lines) averaged over the U.S. East Coast (25N–40N, 80W–60W, blue), Gulf Coast (20N–30N, 95W–82W, red), and the Main Development Region (10N–20N, 80W–20W, green). (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) same as in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), but for CMIP5 MMM tropical cyclone potential intensity averaged over the same three regions. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) CESM-LE 42 ensemble member mean VWS (solid lines) and the 25% and 75% ensemble spread (light solid lines) averaged over the same three regions. Shadings in all three panels indicate the amplitude of the VWS or potential intensity associated with average AMV in the U.S. East Coast (light blue), Gulf Coast (purple) and MDR (light green).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44252_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e509" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the general increase in SST in the future scenario simulations, the hurricane PI increases across the North Atlantic domain
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a> shows the CMIP5 MMM PI time series averaged for the same three geographic regions. There is a monotonic increase in PI for all three regions, but the increase is much faster for both the U.S. East Coast and the Gulf Coast compared to the MDR, consistent with Ting 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. For the PI, the multi-model spread is not as large as for VWS, showing a more robust SST warming in all models – the main driver of the PI change. The fast increase in PI along the U.S. East Coast, coupled with the more favorable wind shear environment for hurricane intensification there, suggests that hurricanes tracking toward the U.S. East Coast will have a better chance of achieving its PI in the future, which may be much stronger than what we’ve experienced in the past. For the Gulf Coast, the two effects, warmer SST and stronger wind shear, oppose each other. How future hurricane intensity may change there will depend on the relative influence of the two factors, leaving future projections of hurricane intensity along the Gulf Coast less certain.
 </p>
</sec>
