<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species Distribution Models</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species distribution models were developed using boosted regression trees (BRTs) [
  <a rid="pone.0135350.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135350.ref027">27</a>]. BRT models aim to improve predictive performance of any single model by incorporating tree-based methods that iteratively fit nonlinear relationships and handle interactions between predictors automatically [
  <a rid="pone.0135350.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135350.ref028">28</a>]. We built separate distribution models for breeding and non-breeding seasons using BBS and CBC data, respectively. Our analyses of BBS and CBC data were similar in approach with small adjustments to account for differences in data sets and survey protocols. In addition to bioclimatic variables, for BBS analyses we used ordinal date (day of year) to account for variation in timing of surveys across the summer season. We used 25081 records collected along 3718 routes from 2000–2009 to train our models and 41959 records collected from 1980–1999 to test the predictive performance of our models. This approach allowed us to take advantage of increased geographic sampling in recent years to build models and availability of abundant historical data for assessing the predictive ability of our models outside the current time period and climate space. We had sufficient data to construct models for 475 North American species during the breeding season (see Supporting Information). For CBC analyses, we included the number of survey hours invested in each CBC circle as a predictor to account for uneven observer effort across circles, in addition to bioclimatic variables. The number of participating individuals and the duration of counts vary among CBC circles and through time, thus the number of party-hours has often been used as a covariate to account for this variation in analyses based on CBC data (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0135350.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135350.ref029">29</a>]). We used 19272 records collected at 2278 circles from 2000–2009 to train our models and 30630 records collected from 1980–1999 to assess the predictive ability of our models. We had sufficient data to construct models for 503 North American species during the non-breeding season (see Supporting Information).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We built models using the following parameters: (i) learning rate = 0.01, (ii) tree complexity = 5, (iii) family = Bernoulli. These settings resulted in models built with an average of 3100 and 2800 trees for winter and summer species, respectively, well beyond the suggested minimum of 1000 [
  <a rid="pone.0135350.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135350.ref028">28</a>]. All models were built using the gbm package [
  <a rid="pone.0135350.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135350.ref027">27</a>] in R and cross-validation was performed using 10 folds.
 </p>
</sec>
