<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Result 3: A variance reduction, safe-operating space tradeoff</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7</a> displays a powerful variance reduction, safe-operating space tradeoff associated with forager cycling. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a–7c</a> display three phase plots. Phase plots display the relationship between variables that change over time. For example, in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3a</a> the biomass of habitats one and two vary over time and are 180 degrees our of phase (i.e., when one peaks, the other troughs). An alternative way to plot this relationship is in phase space, plotting the biomass of habitat one on the x-axis, and the biomass of habitat two on the y-axis. In this example, the graph would display a perfect negative correlation. Imagine a movie of a pencil drawing this relationship on the graph. The pencil would start in the lower right corner (habitat one high biomass, habitat two low biomass) and, over time, move along a perfect linear trajectory toward the upper left corner of the graph and then back to the bottom right corner. The pencil will just oscillate along this trajectory over time. Displaying how variables in a dynamical system relate to each other in a phase plot is a powerful tool for studying the coevolution of those variables over time and identifying emergent changes in the qualitative structure of a system under different parameter values.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Phase plane analysis of spatial effort allocation.</div>
   <p>In all cases, 
    <span class="italic">α</span> = 1. graphs a-c are phase plots that illustrate changes in the proportion of time allocated to habitats one and two over time by groups one and two for different initial conditions. In graph (a) 
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub> for all i = 2.5; in graph (b) 
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub> for all i = 4.25; in graph (c) 
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub> for all i = 4.5. Graphs d-f illustrate total foraging effort (
    <span class="italic">e</span>
    <sub>11</sub> + 
    <span class="italic">e</span>
    <sub>12</sub>, orange curves) and the calorie harvest (
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>1</sub>-blue curve) for the forager in group one as the system converges to a perfectly mixed equilibrium, on average, of 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> = 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>2</sub> = 0.5. Graphs d-f illustrate the mean hours of work a forager from group one must put-in to gain food and the consistency of hitting the calorie target (
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">j</span>
    </sub> = 
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">m</span>
    </sub>) over time when foragers from both groups perfectly mix in space. The dynamics are analogous for the forager from group two.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The x-axis on each plot of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a—7c</a> displays the proportion of time that group one spends in habitat one, and the y-axis displays the proportion of time that group two spends in habitat two. On each plot we mark five regions. Regions 1 and 3 are analogous to each other. In these regions, both foragers spend near 100 % of their time in the same habitat (Region 1, everyone in habitat two, and Region 3, everyone in habitat one). Regions 2 and 4 are, again, analogous to each other. In these regions, the system displays partitioning. In Region 2 the group two forager spends near 100% of her time in habitat two, and the forager from group one near 100 % of her time in habitat one. Region 4 displays the opposite. Finally, Region 5 displays mixing in space and over time. At the very center of this region foragers spend, on average, 50 % of their time in each habitat.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The black curves that traverse 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a—7c</a> illustrate the relationship between the proportion of time spent in habitats one and two as the system changes over time. The arrows along the black curves illustrate the direction of change over time. For example, imagine a system that starts at an initial condition in Region 1 on plot 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a</a>. In this case, the system starts with the foragers from groups one and two spending almost 100 % of their time in habitat two. The arrow pointing toward the middle of the graph indicates that, over time, the mean proportion of time each forager spends in each habitat converges to a constant in the middle of the graph, after which the system oscillates with constant mean around 0.5 (a perfectly mixed system with a forager spending 50 % of her time in both habitats). To give some intuition in terms of foraging populations, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7</a> allows us to study how internal changes in the use of space, such as groups aggregating into habitat one for an important ceremony or groups completely partitioning to their associated ‘home-range’ affects the long-term evolution of the system under different population densities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a</a> illustrates that when population density is low, the system is globally robust to changes in the use of space, including highly aggregated populations (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.99, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 0.01) or highly partitioned populations (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 0.99). In the parlance of sustainable human-resource systems, the system has a complete safe-operating space. The safe-operating space includes all of the starting values of (
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a</a> from which the system will evolve to a state where foragers consistently meet their calorie target.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Again, thinking intuitively about real foragers, consider the low population density case illustrated by 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a</a>. Observing an important ceremony requires that forager populations temporarily concentrate in space (e.g., in Region 1 of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a</a>, foragers aggregate in habitat two). Due to this population concentration, foragers must work very hard to meet their energy target (i.e., effort is at 0.5 in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7d</a> at 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 0–the start of the ceremony). When the ceremony ends, foragers quickly move away from the extreme values in Region 1 toward Region 5, and foraging effort in habitats one and two quickly drop below the maximum tolerable work level and remain there. The orange curve on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7d</a> illustrates this dynamic for the forager from group one over time (the dynamic is analogous for the forager from group two). Initially, the orange curve is very high, then quickly drops and oscillates around a stable mean of 0.21 workdays/day, and the forager consistently meets her target harvest of calories (cyan line in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7d</a>) over time. In short, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a</a> illustrates a system in which forager cycling minimizes variation in the calorie intake of foragers (at multiple scales as demonstrated above) 
  <span class="italic">and</span> has a complete safe-operating space.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7b</a> illustrates the consequences of increases in population density to near carrying capacity (here, 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 4.25 &amp; 
  <span class="italic">α</span> = 1). This increase has two consequences. First, in a perfectly mixed system (rapid forager cycling), foragers continue to meet their calorie target at equilibrium (cyan line is constant at 0.1 in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7e</a>), but at a lower rate of return. The orange curve in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7e</a> illustrates changes in foraging effort over time as the system converges to an equilibrium at 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 0.5. Note the higher mean of the orange curve in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7e</a> (≈ 0.35) than in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7d</a>. This means that the group one forager works harder to maintain a constant intake of calories.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the increase in population density reduces the 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>–
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> space in which foragers can converge to meeting their calorie target. Another way to say this is that the constant cyan curve in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7e</a> only emerges when the system begins from a mixed state. If foragers too unevenly distribute on the landscape either due to aggregating (both foragers spend most of their time in one habitat, such as Regions 1 and 3) or partitioning (each forager spends most of their time in one habitat, such as Regions 2 and 4), the system will converge to one that is mixed, but foragers experience long-term variation in their mean intake of calories (a result analogous to 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7f</a> where the cyan curve oscillates). In this environment, the processes of aggregation or partitioning results in foragers not meeting their resource target. The safe-operating space of the system, the range of initial (
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) values from which the strategy of cycling between habitats leads to a consistent supply of calories over the long-term, declines in size. If foragers become too aggregated or too partitioned, the consequence is oscillating resource shortfalls; a sequence of: Good year, shortfall year, good year, shortfall year, etc.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For instance, when the system starts with everyone aggregated in habitat two (Region 1), foragers must, again, start by working as hard as they can to harvest food. This depresses the productivity of habitat two. Because the cost to migrate is zero (
  <span class="italic">q</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">ij</span>
  </sub> = 1 for all 
  <span class="italic">ij</span>), foragers head for habitat one, which depresses the resources in this habitat and causes foragers, again, to work as hard as they can. Over time, foragers converge back to a mixed system, but it is too late, in a sense, because the resource base in both habitats never has sufficient time to recover. Thus, foragers end up in a long-run equilibrium in which they can meet their resource needs every other year, but also experience a 10-20 % shortfall every other year. In sum, although forager cycling reduces variation in the calorie intake of individuals and raises the carrying capacity of many environments, the very success of the cycling strategy (leading to population growth until near carrying capacity) reduces the ability of foragers to aggregate and disperse without causing resources to vary unexpectedly as a consequence of their movements. This is a variance reduction, safe-operating space tradeoff. The very strategy used to reduce variation in the intake of calories leads to a decline in the size of the safe operating-space of the system. This is not something foragers could necessarily recognize unless they experienced the negative consequences.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7c</a> illustrates a population density above the carrying capacities identified in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g005" href="#pone.0218440.g005">Fig 5a</a> (
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>2</sub> = 4.55 &amp; 
  <span class="italic">α</span> = 1) and, in this case, there is no safe-operating space. All initial values of (
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) lead to a situation in which foragers do not meet their calorie target, regardless of whether they cycle or partition. In the long-run, effort is maxed out (
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) = 
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub>), and harvest is less than the preferred target (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) &lt; 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>) for some time intervals in the annual cycle (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7f</a>). This opens up a region in 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> space that cannot be reached from all initial conditions (i.e., generates habitat partitioning). In this setting, the long run mean proportion of time spent in a given habitat depends on initial conditions, creating a barrier between Regions 2 and 4 because the capacity of the internal dynamics of the system to reach well mixed states is limited, and only external forcing (e.g., climate variation beyond normal seasonality) can temporarily mix the system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bottom line: foragers have overshot carrying capacity and entered a “Malthusian Purgatory.” No matter whether they cycle or not, they cannot meet their desired energy target. Thus, initial conditions determine the degree of partitioning. More technically, when foragers work as hard as tolerable, their choices about foraging in different habitats decouple from productivity across habitats. Under conditions of relative abundance (
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) &lt; 
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub>) foragers adjust effort to create a match between their calorie uptake and desired calorie uptake (move 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) toward 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>). This decision impacts biomass (
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>) which, in turn, impacts foraging effort (
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>)), which starts the cycle anew. Thus, foraging effort (
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>)) depends on both the proportion of time in a given habitat (
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>) and biomass (
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>), coupling their dynamics in such a way as the average over an annual cycle of 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> become equal. However, when foraging effort equals the maximum tolerable effort (
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) = 
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub>), foraging effort 
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) no longer depends on the proportion of time in a habitat (
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>) and biomass (
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>), it is simply a constant. This weakens the coupling between the proportion of time in a habitat and the biomass of a habitat. Thus, a mixed distribution of foragers in space bifurcates into a potentially partitioned distribution, depending on initial conditions.
 </p>
</sec>
