<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results 1 and 2: The advantages of forager cycling in variable environments</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g004" href="#pone.0218440.g004">Fig 4</a> illustrates the benefits of cycling through habitats that boom and bust at different times. In this case, we force habitat partitioning. This means that we force the agent from group one to spend 100 % of her time in habitat one and the same for group two in habitat two. At a low population density (the blue line in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g004" href="#pone.0218440.g004">Fig 4</a>), resource harvest always meets a forager’s target of calories (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>). It is only when scarcity emerges that the incentive to cycle on a seasonal time-scale becomes clear (shift from blue-to-yellow-to-red curves). At 
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3.5 (the red curve), for example, during lean periods, foragers work at the max tolerable level (12 hours per day) while falling far short of their calorie target (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g004" href="#pone.0218440.g004">Fig 4b</a>). This situation is untenable. Foragers must shift between habitats to maintain a consistent intake of calories.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Foraging effort (a) and harvest (b) over a two-year period in habitat one for increasing population levels when foragers partition.</div>
   <p>Blue line–
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub> for all i = 1; yellow-green line–
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub> for all i = 2; Red line–
    <span class="italic">N</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub> for all i = 3.5. The dynamics in habitat 2 are identical. Note that the resource growth rate, 
    <span class="italic">r</span>, and the minimum harvest level 
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">m</span>
    </sub>, simply set the units for (or scale the) sustainable population size. Our choice to set 
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">m</span>
    </sub> = 0.1, sets the sustainable population size to order 1 (individuals, households, village clusters, depending on the spatial scale of the habitat implied in the units of 
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">i</span>
    </sub>, etc.) 
    <span class="italic">α</span> = 1.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g005" href="#pone.0218440.g005">Fig 5</a>, above a threshold of 
  <span class="italic">α</span> = 0.58 in seasonality–the degree of resource boom-bust between winter and summer–forager cycling maximizes the population density at which foragers consistently meet their calorie target (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>) over 50 years. Below this seasonality threshold, habitat partitioning maximizes the population density at which foragers can meet their calorie target. The parameter space above the two curves includes population densities at which the model transitions into a degraded resource state. In this range of population densities, foragers cannot consistently meet their resource target, no matter what strategy they use. The parameter space below the curves includes population densities at which both strategies, forager cycling or habitat partitioning, allow foragers to consistently meet their calorie target. The lower a realized population density is relative to the maximum values defined by the curves in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g005" href="#pone.0218440.g005">Fig 5</a>, the wider the range of initial conditions at which partitioning and forager cycling are equivalent.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Maximum population density at which foragers can maintain a consistent diet that meets the target of 
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">m</span>
    </sub> over 50 years when partitioned (
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> = 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>2</sub> = 1, solid magenta line) and when mixed (
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> = 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>2</sub> = 0.5, green-dashed-dot line).
   </div>
   <p>In high amplitude environments, migration between habitats has a higher maximum density than no migration, and in low amplitude environments, the opposite is true.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g006" href="#pone.0218440.g006">Fig 6a &amp; 6b</a> illustrate a tradeoff associated with partitioning. The recovery time of foragers when a perturbation hits habitat one (e.g., an extended dry period) increases among partitioned foragers. The results in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g006" href="#pone.0218440.g006">Fig 6a &amp; 6b</a> were generated by starting the initial biomass of habitat one at a very low level under two different population densities: One fourth the maximum density at which foragers meet their calorie target (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g006" href="#pone.0218440.g006">Fig 6a</a>) and one half of the maximum population density (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g006" href="#pone.0218440.g006">Fig 6b</a>). The x-axis records the initial degree of forager cycling (distribution of population in space), and the y-axis records the time (in years) that it takes foragers to recover from the perturbation to habitat one and converge to meeting their calorie target (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub> = 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>). At both levels of population density, higher forager cycling results in a much faster recovery than more partitioning.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The recovery time (y-axis) it takes a population of foragers to consistently meet their calorie target following a perturbation to habitat one (a drought) for different levels of initial cycling (x-axis).</div>
   <p>Graph (a) population density is 1/4 of the maximum population density recorded in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g005" href="#pone.0218440.g005">Fig 5</a> for a given level of resource oscillation (
    <span class="italic">α</span>). Graph (b) population density is 1/2 of the maximum recorded in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g005" href="#pone.0218440.g005">Fig 5</a>. In general, the graphics illustrate that full partitioning drastically increases recovery time from a perturbation.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, in a low population density and aseasonal environment (solid magenta line, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g006" href="#pone.0218440.g006">Fig 6a</a>), a population of foragers that spends 50% of their time in each habitat recovers 3/4 of a year faster than a partitioned population. It would not take a very high frequency of such perturbations, perhaps one per decade, to increase fitness for foragers who cycle relative to those who partition. In sum, at small time-scales and low population densities, rapid forager cycling and partitioning seem equivalent, in terms of the consistency of calorie intake, but at larger scales forager cycling has a clear advantage. Even at low population densities and in unrealistically aseasonal environments, forager cycling increases the consistency and mean of harvests over time. In short, we should expect well mixed distributions of foragers in space and time, even in unrealistically aseasonal environments.
 </p>
</sec>
