<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model structure and assumptions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We provide an intuitive description of the model’s assumptions here, and we present the formal equations in the 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec010" href="#sec010">Model and methods</a> section. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g002" href="#pone.0218440.g002">Fig 2</a> summaries the SPDm. In this model, a forager has the goal of obtaining a harvest of energy (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub>) equal to a baseline energy target (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>) necessary for reproducing social relationships, maintaining biological function and reproducing biologically. In order to achieve this goal, a forager chooses how much time to spend harvesting resources from either habitat one or habitat two, which are both affected by harvest pressure and an external driver of productivity (e.g., rainfall). The harvest of resources from habitats one and two, in turn, affects how much time foragers spend in a given habitat (i.e., whether a forager cycles between the two habitats). Choices about harvest and whether to cycle between habitats results in an output of resources, which foragers then assess against their baseline target and, again, make choices about harvesting and partitioning. This system captures three fundamental processes.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Basic block, feedback diagram of the SPDm.</div>
   <p>Equations defined in the 
    <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec010" href="#sec010">Model and methods</a> section. The diagram reads as follows: The goal is set outside the loop, and enters from the left. The feedback loop iterates as individuals assess whether the goal is met. Foragers adjust their effort and spatial partitioning, which affects biophysical dynamics and produces an output (harvest). Foragers then measure (do I feel hungry) and compare the harvest with their goal in the next time period.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, there are two habitats in which resources grow (
  <span class="italic">G</span>(
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>)) and deplete due to decay (
  <div id="pone.0218440.e001" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.e001.jpg" id="pone.0218440.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M1" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">d</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">x</span>
       <span class="mi">i</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>) and harvest pressure (
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>). Importantly, the resources in each habitat vary periodically due to external drivers (seasonality). Here we assume that variation in the productivity of the habitats remains out of phase. Resources in one habitat peak during the winter (e.g., the Texas Coast) and resources in the other habitat peak during the summer (e.g., inland gallery forests on the Texas Coastal Plain). 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3a</a> illustrates this dynamic. Note that the peaks of the red and blue curves are offset. The assumption that resources vary 180 degrees out of phase fits the resource structure of the Texas Coastal Plain. Please note that qualitatively our results hold for a system in which resources are 90 degrees out of phase as well.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">.</div>
   <p>Graph (a): Resource dynamics. Red curve (
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>1</sub>) illustrates resource variation of the TCP coast and the blue curve (
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>2</sub>) resource variation inland in riverine areas of the TCP. Graph (b): Harvest dynamics of a partitioned forager in the riverine area of the TCP (
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>2</sub>): Harvest (red curve) and foraging effort (black curve).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, two representative agents occupy the habitats. One agent represents the mean forager in group one, and the second agent represents group two. Group one has an association with habitat one and group two with habitat two. These associations follow the convention that mobile foragers form home-ranges. However, the association is fluid and does not represent a cost for other foragers who may move into the habitat (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0218440.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218440.ref030">30</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0218440.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218440.ref037">37</a>]), which contrasts with such costs generated by territoriality [
  <a rid="pone.0218440.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218440.ref038">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each forager makes two types of decisions: How much time to spend harvesting within a given habitat and whether to use multiple habitats (one or two?). The decision about how much to harvest now in habitat 
  <span class="italic">i</span> is defined by a satisfying process. Foragers simply ask: Have I met 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">m</span>
  </sub>? If the answer is yes, foragers use their excess time to bond socially, rest, etc. If the answer is no, foragers spend their time harvesting resources (see Eqs 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0218440.e007" href="#pone.0218440.e007">3</a>–
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0218440.e011" href="#pone.0218440.e011">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec010" href="#sec010">Model and methods</a> section). 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3b</a> illustrates how this dynamic works, in particular, when forcing a forager to remain in one habitat. The black curve represents time spent harvesting resources and the red curve harvest (
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub>) in habitat two (
  <span class="italic">x</span>
  <sub>2</sub>, the blue curve on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3a</a>). Note that as productivity increases (the blue curve on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3a</a> rises), work effort declines (the black curve on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3b</a>). The red curve in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g003" href="#pone.0218440.g003">Fig 3b</a> remains constant because, in this case, the partitioned forager maintains a constant level of harvest by adjusting her level of foraging effort up and down with the productivity of the habitat.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the benefits of residential cycling between habitats include the acquisition of information and a potentially more consistent supply of resources [
  <a rid="pone.0218440.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218440.ref039">39</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0218440.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218440.ref042">42</a>]; however, this comes with the opportunity cost of leaving known resources behind. We capture this tension between known and unknown resources by the equations that govern the degree of partitioning or how rapidly foragers mix in space and time (Eqs 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0218440.e013" href="#pone.0218440.e013">8</a>–
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0218440.e015" href="#pone.0218440.e015">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec010" href="#sec010">Model and methods</a> section). A forager changes the proportion of her time budget in a given habitat by taking into consideration her current proportion of time in a given habitat and the normalized difference in harvest per unit effort between the two possible habitats. This process captures the following heuristic: ‘Does changing my proportion of time in a habitat affect my harvest?’ If yes, then a forager is more willing to change the proportion of time they spend in a given habitat. Willingness to change, however, also depends on how well a forager knows the other habitat. If a forager spends 90% of her time in habitat one, then she does not know much about habitat two. This uncertainty reduces the willingness to change the proportion of time in habitat one. When the proportion of time in habitat one is 50%, foragers know both habitats well, and are more willing to change their location. In short, information about alternative habitats and the difference in harvest per unit effort between alternative habitats interact. When foragers cycle between habitats and completely mix in space, information remains abundant and the opportunity costs of leaving known resources low. Thus differences in harvest per unit effort more strongly influence decisions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In sum, we have a two habitat system described by four ordinary differential equations. In this system, the change in biomass, 
  <div id="pone.0218440.e002" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.e002.jpg" id="pone.0218440.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M2" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <span class="mi">x</span>
       <span class="mo">˙</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mi">i</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, effort devoted to foraging for resources, 
  <span class="italic">e</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">j</span>
  </sub> and the change in the proportion of time spent in a given habitat 
  <div id="pone.0218440.e003" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.e003.jpg" id="pone.0218440.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <div id="M3" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <span class="mi">p</span>
       <span class="mo">˙</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mi">j</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> co-evolve. These equations capture the interplay between uncertainty in the productivity of resources, decision making about how much time to spend collecting resources and how many habitats to use. The distribution of foragers in space emerges from the interplay of these processes.
 </p>
</sec>
