<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Territoriality</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A qualitative insight with important consequences emerges from the comparison of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7b and 7c</a>. In the environment illustrated by 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7b</a>, foragers are vulnerable to a cascade of oscillating resource failures. For example, if foragers respond to a drought in habitat one by aggregating in habitat two for a season, then in a system with free movement, this behavior generates a cascade of resource failures over the following years. But, the resource system still has enough stocked-up biomass that, if a bumper year hits in which productivity is above normal, the system could transition back into one in which individual foragers consistently meet their calorie target. Foragers can learn that their high cycling strategy is vulnerable and, thus, adjust their strategies to reduce the chances that they experience a sequence of resource shortfalls again.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the environment defined by 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7c</a>, foragers have crossed into a Malthusian Purgatory. Partitioning follows from overshooting the carrying capacity of the environment. The only way to deal with this is a massive migration or suffer prolonged negative fitness, until population is, again, well below carrying capacity and the resource base can recover. As Cowgill noted long ago, changes in strategy are unlikely in such a situation; rather depression and stagnation are likely because individuals lack adaptive capacity [
  <a rid="pone.0218440.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218440.ref043">43</a>]. Partitioning in real systems is not likely a simple consequence of changes in equilibirum resource abundance and competition among foragers in different habitats. Rather, partitioning results from a complex interaction of resource abundance, the perception of foragers and the dynamics of knowledge creation as foragers move on a landscape.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explore this dynamic further, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8a–8c</a> replicates 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7a–7c</a> except in two crucial respects. First, foragers occupy a one quarter less seasonal environment, and, second, in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8c</a> we keep population density equal to 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7b</a> and assume that there is a cost to enter another group’s home-range due to territorial norms. In particular, we assume that searching for resources within one’s home-range is free, but searching for resources outside of one’s own home-range has a cost (either avoiding attack or securing a ritual gift). In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8a and 8b</a>, we observe, again, that increasing population density reduces the 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>–
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> space in which foragers can converge to meeting their resource target. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8a</a>, again population density is low, and the safe-operating space of the system encompasses all potential values of (
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub>). Increasing population density to the level in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8b</a>, decreases the safe-operating space of the system. The red curves on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8b</a> illustrate the safe-operating space. If foragers aggregate too far, (e.g. beyond the red curves), they will experience cascades of resource short fall that oscillate over time.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218440.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218440.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Phase plane analysis of spatial effort allocation; red curves illustrate the initial conditions in the 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> − 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>2</sub> space in which foragers do not consistently meet their resource target 
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">m</span>
    </sub>, even though the system converges to a mixed state.
   </div>
   <p>As population density increases from (a) to (b), the initial conditions in 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> − 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>2</sub> space from which foragers can consistently meet their resource target 
    <span class="italic">h</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">m</span>
    </sub> declines. Graphs (c) illustrates the effect of territorial ownership. Territorial ownership enlarges the initial conditions in 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> − 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>2</sub> space from which foragers can meet their resource target. In graphs (a)–(c), the amplitude of variation in 
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>1</sub> &amp; 
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>2</sub> is held constant at 
    <span class="italic">α</span> = 0.75. To define the red curves in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g007" href="#pone.0218440.g007">Fig 7b</a>, we ran 50 numerical experiments varying 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> and 
    <span class="italic">p</span>
    <sub>1</sub> holding all parameters equal and the initial conditions of 
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>1</sub> = 0.3 and 
    <span class="italic">x</span>
    <sub>2</sub> = 0.8 in all experiments.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0218440.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this environment, territorial ownership has the consequence of enlarging the 
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>1</sub>-
  <span class="italic">p</span>
  <sub>2</sub> space in which foragers can converge to meeting their calorie target, though the system now always converges to a partitioned state. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218440.g008" href="#pone.0218440.g008">Fig 8c</a> introduces a cost for group one to access habitat two and for group two to access habitat one. This cost slows the flow of foragers between habitats in response to differences in harvest per unit effort. In turn, as foragers spend more time in their own habitat, they loose information on the other habitat and discount traveling there relative to harvesting resources from their own ‘home-range.’ This dynamic leads to the complete partitioning of groups in space and time. Such partitioning based on territorial ownership cannot happen when 
  <span class="italic">α</span> = 1 (very high seasonality) because partitioning creates too much concentrated harvest pressure on a given habitat. However, where 
  <span class="italic">α</span> = 0.75 ownership norms allow individuals to consistently meet their resource target, whether partitioned or highly aggregated. Foragers can partition because the resource base in each habitat can withstand more intense harvest and foragers can aggregate because territorial ownership prevents a massive swing of population from one habitat to another, slowing down the movement of foragers on a landscape. The adoption of territorial ownership, in an emergent way, stabilizes the harvests of individual foragers by reducing the risk of leaving a system’s safe-operating space.
 </p>
</sec>
