<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41" class="p">An important focus of the current work was to assess if low temperature affects dormancy establishment. During dormancy, callose containing DSC at all plasmodesmata lock the SAM in a dormant ‘offline’ state, in which the cell-cell communication that drives morphogenesis is abolished [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>). The molecular mechanism of chilling-induced dormancy release restores the symplasmic communication network involving plasmodesmata-associated 1,3-β-glucanases, which hydrolyse callose at the plasmodesmal DSCs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>], creating a ‘standby’ state that is inactive and eco-dormant. Developing AXBs and TBs can become dormant under short photoperiod, probably because as active sinks they are accessible to long-distance photoperiodic signals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Although lower temperatures than the one used here during pre-dormancy chilling (12 °C) are more effective in providing chilling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>], our findings show that this temperature reduced dormancy in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>). Despite being at the border of the chilling range [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>], this temperature had a cumulative effect like chilling-induced dormancy release at 5 °C [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>]. Importantly, our molecular analyses indicated that it also utilized the same mechanism as in chilling-induced dormancy release [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. Our results do not exclude that low temperature and other stresses, like drought, can induce growth cessation and even bud formation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>], but based on the present work these buds are likely to be eco-dormant.
</p>
