<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One factor likely linked to female breeding condition is the state of their reproductive system at arrival. The avian uterus largely regresses during nonbreeding for flight efficiency reasons and needs to regrow prior to breeding (Dawson, King, Bentley, &amp; Ball, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>), which may take substantial time and resources (Gwinner, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>; Williams, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Although overlaps between migration and development of the reproductive tract is a relatively unexplored area, there is some evidence that reproductive regrowth begins during migration (Ramenofsky &amp; Wingfield, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>) and that physiological breeding changes occur during migration for males (Covino, Jawor, Morris, &amp; Moore, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Because migration is energetically demanding and birds will pay a cost for carrying unnecessary weight (Alerstam, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Kullberg, Fransson, &amp; Jakobsson, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>), the pressure for early arrival is likely to invoke a trade‐off between early arrival and gonadal development (Crossin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Williams, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Thus, early‐arriving females may be less reproductively ready at arrival (Williams, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>) as they could be expected to encounter less favorable conditions during their migratory journey, potentially limiting their resource availability during migration and this preventing them from simultaneously arriving early and rapidly advancing the development of their reproductive tract. In contrast, late‐arriving individuals migrate during more favorable conditions, which could allow them to reach the breeding area with a highly developed breeding capacity and would explain their ability to rapidly initiate breeding after arrival with little between‐individual variation (but see Covino et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2018</xref> for data showing that female hypothalamic–pituitary–gonadal sensitivity was not higher for late migrating birds).
</p>
