<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">All regions in the contiguous United States are projected to cross the 2°C warming threshold about 10-20 years earlier than the global mean annual temperature. While there is a large spread in TCTs across all regions, 75% to 90% of the models reach 2°C warming by 2050 for every region in the US. We believe that our estimates of TCTs based on 5-year means of annual mean temperatures may be conservative since we require that all the subsequent 5-year means beyond the identified threshold crossing time exceed the selected temperature threshold. The unpredictable nature of internal climate variability could advance or delay TCTs by a few years to a couple of decades regionally as demonstrated using the initials conditions ensemble. But this uncertainty in regional TCTs is smaller than the spread arising from using different models and two different scenarios. The consequence of large climate variability at regional scales, however, suggests that it may prove difficult to distinguish between the consequences of global warming of 1.5°C and 2°C for regional changes. Note also that the selected temperature thresholds may be temporarily crossed earlier than the identified TCTs as a result of climate variability on seasonal and interannual timescales. In fact, regional warming of 2°C relative to the baseline has already been observed for some years for all regions in the US except for the South (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168697.s007" class="xref">S4 Fig</xref>). A cooling trend in the southeast US, the so called “warming hole”, in the second half of the twentieth century was not captured by CMIP5 models [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Although this cooling trend has disappeared since the 1990s [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], the CMIP5 models have overestimated warming in the region over the last two decades (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0168697.s007" class="xref">S4 Fig</xref>), which suggests that the actual TCTs for the South could be later than those presented here. On the other hand, the eastern US is projected to reach the 2°C target in the 2020s regardless of the scenarios. This result seems realistic given that the Paris Agreement will not come into force until 2020 [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] and that the model projections for the region match the current trends of regional warming well [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Importantly, the timescales associated with the eventual 1.5 and 2°C warming are long, requiring rapid development and deployment of efficient technologies throughout the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Consequently, we believe that the near-term regional projections discussed here may indeed be realized regardless of what greenhouse gas concentrations pathway the world takes to meet the COP21 temperature goals.
</p>
