<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are a number of caveats in the HS09 method [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] used to partition uncertainty in model projections such as the use of only two RCPs, and the constancy of internal variability estimates in time. The CMIP5 multi-model ensemble used in this study samples the structural diversity in model formulation, but was not designed for systematic exploration of uncertainties, and therefore may not span the full range of outcomes in climate projections [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Additionally, the use of one realization for every model is inadequate to capture the effect of internal variability that plays a significant role in driving regional changes from years to decades. While these shortcomings are not expected to affect the conclusions drawn in this work, we suggest that the uncertainty estimates be treated as reasonable guidelines. Overall, decomposing uncertainty in regional precipitation projections indicates the importance of internal variability in the short-term, model uncertainty in the long-term, and very little to no contribution of scenario uncertainty throughout the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century. In the absence of reliable constraints on future precipitation projections [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], assessment of regional impacts should be based on climate information obtained from a large number of models with diverse outcomes instead of putting too much emphasis on using different scenarios for a handful of models. Note that the uncertainty partitioning is relative in nature. If future generations of models reduce contributions from internal variability and model uncertainty substantially, studying precipitation response to different scenarios may become important. This, however, is unlikely given that the internal climate variations over CONUS remain large and highly unpredictable over the next 20-50 years [
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0168697.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>].
</p>
