<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig1" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>A framework for inferring phenotypic adaptive responses using three conditions. 
   <span class="bold">a</span> General framework. Arrows indicate hypothesized causal relationships, with dashed arrow indicating that we accounted for the effects associated with years when assessing the effect of climate on traits. 
   <span class="bold">b</span>–
   <span class="bold">f</span> demonstrate steps of the framework using as an example one study from our dataset—Wilson et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
   </span>. 
   <span class="bold">b</span> Condition 1 is assessed by 
   <span class="italic">β</span>
   <sub>Clim</sub>, the slope of a climatic variable on years, 
   <span class="bold">c</span> Condition 2 is assessed by 
   <span class="italic">β</span>
   <sub>Trait</sub>, the slope of the mean population trait values on climate. 
   <span class="bold">d</span> Interim step: assessing the linear selection differentials (
   <span class="italic">β</span>). Note that each dot here represents an individual measurement in the respective year and not a population mean; analyses of selection were not performed here but in original publications, except for a few studies, thus inset 
   <span class="bold">d</span> is a conceptual depiction and not based on real data. 
   <span class="bold">e</span> To assess condition 3, first the weighted mean annual selection differential (WMSD) is estimated. 
   <span class="bold">f</span> Condition 3 is then assessed by checking whether selection occurs in the same direction as the trait change over time, calculated as the product of the slopes from conditions 1 and 2. Red lines and font in 
   <span class="bold">b</span>–
   <span class="bold">f</span> illustrate the predictions from model fits. Grey lines and font illustrate the lack of effect in each condition. As an example, if temperature increased over years (as shown by the red line in 
   <span class="bold">b</span>), phenology advanced (depicted by the red line in 
   <span class="bold">c</span>) and WMSD was negative (as depicted by the red line in 
   <span class="bold">e</span>), then fitness benefits are associated with phenological advancement, reflecting an adaptive response (point falls in quadrant 3 in 
   <span class="bold">f</span>). Source data are provided as a Source Data file
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10924_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1691" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
