<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">International initiatives, particularly the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) and the Sustainable Development Goals, recognize that understanding the vulnerability and adaptation responses of local communities to climate change is critical to promote mechanisms for climate change-related planning. In the context of climate change, adaptation refers to adjustments in natural or human systems in response to actual or expected climatic stimuli or their effects, which moderates harm or exploits beneficial opportunities (IPCC 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">2014</xref>). It involves adjustments in lifestyle, behaviours and socio-economic structures (i.e. livelihood security-based responses) as well as in land use and management of biodiversity and ecological processes (i.e. ecosystem-based responses) (Smit et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">2000</xref>; Ojea 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2015</xref>; Vignola et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">2015</xref>). The social and institutional dimensions of vulnerability and adaptation to climate change have been increasingly addressed by scholars (Smit and Wandel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">2006</xref>; McLaughlin and Dietz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2008</xref>), specifically opening questions related to understanding matters of social differentiation, equity and power (Füssel and Klein 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2006</xref>). However, the multiple determinants that shape differentiated context-specific vulnerabilities and, particularly, adaptive capacity responses are still largely unexplored (Terry 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" class="xref">2009</xref>; Carr and Thompson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2014</xref>; Kaijser and Kronsell 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2014</xref>). Specifically, scholars recognize that such determinants are gendered and mediated by social, cultural, institutional and economic structures and processes (Morton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">2007</xref>; Kaijser and Kronsell 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2014</xref>; Sugden et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" class="xref">2014</xref>). In this sense, a significant body of literature on gender and climate change shows that women and men perceive and experience climate change differently, and usually women are more vulnerable due to their dependence on natural resources and structural inequity in their access and control of such resources (Dankelman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2010</xref>; FAO 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2011</xref>; Nellemann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2011</xref>; WEDO-IUCN 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, recent critiques from feminist political ecology perspectives question the validity of the conventional binary male–female view of gender in climate change studies as they can lack sufficient consideration of power relations determined by the social context (Demetriades and Esplen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2008</xref>; Rodenberg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2009</xref>; Arora-Jonsson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2011</xref>; Resurreccion 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">2011</xref>; Carr and Thompson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2014</xref>). Firstly, presenting women as a passive victim of change may misinterpret the causes of vulnerability and obscure the role of women as proactive agents of adaptation (Mitchell 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2007</xref>; Dankelman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2010</xref>). Secondly, climate change debates related to gender are shifting from a simple view of women as a homogenous group toward a more complex view of identities within gender categories (Tschakert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">2012</xref>). Indeed, multiple social, economic, and cultural characteristics interact with gender in influencing power inequities and explaining how and why people face and manage climate change in different ways (Carr 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">2008</xref>). Thirdly, several authors recognize that climate change occurs together with other concomitant direct and indirect drivers, which together affect local livelihoods, gender relations and management decisions (O’Brien et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">2004</xref>; Nielsen and Reenberg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2010</xref>; Sugden et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
