<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model configuration</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model used is the University of Victoria (UVic) Earth System Climate Model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span> in the configuration described by ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
   </span>. The ocean component is a fully three-dimensional primitive-equation model with nineteen levels in the vertical ranging from 50 m near the surface to 500 m in the deep. It contains a simple marine ecosystem model including the two major nutrients nitrate and phosphate and two phytoplankton classes, nitrogen fixers and other phytoplankton, the former being limited by phosphate only. As a caveat we note that the micronutrient iron is not explicitly included in the model, which nevertheless achieves a reasonable fit to observed biogeochemical tracer distributions for the tuned biological parameters and mixing parameterizations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. For the molar stoichiometry of C:N:P:−O
   <sub>2</sub> = 112:16:1:169.6 assumed in the model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>, organic matter is degraded by aerobic remineralisation (−O
   <sub>2</sub>:PO
   <sub>4</sub> = 169.6) as long as sufficient dissolved oxygen is available. In regions where oxygen concentrations are below a threshold of 5 mmol O
   <sub>2</sub> m
   <span class="sup">−3</span>, nitrate is used as electron acceptor (denitrification, −NO
   <sub>3</sub>:PO
   <sub>4</sub> = 119.68). No other electron acceptors are simulated and remineralisation stops whenever nitrate runs out, which happens only occasionally at very few grid points. A suite of idealised tracers is added comprising ideal age
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>, an abiotic oxygen tracer affected only by air-sea gas exchange and surface-water solubility
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>, and a tracer of preformed PO
   <sub>4</sub> that is, at every model time step, set identical to the model’s PO
   <sub>4</sub> tracer in the surface layer, but otherwise a passive tracer without sinks or sources
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. TOU is computed as the stoichiometric oxygen equivalent of regenerated PO
   <sub>4</sub>, i.e. total PO
   <sub>4</sub> minus preformed PO
   <sub>4</sub>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ocean component is coupled to a single-level energy-moisture balance model of the atmosphere and a dynamic-thermodynamic sea ice component and a terrestrial vegetation and carbon-cycle component
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>. All model components use a common horizontal resolution of 1.8° latitude times 3.6° longitude. The current model version does not consider any fluxes across the water-sediment interface and also does not account for fluxes related to weathering on land. Oceanic phosphorus is thus strictly conserved. Because the atmosphere contains about a hundred times as much oxygen as the ocean, any feedback of marine oxygen changes on atmospheric oxygen is neglected as in earlier studies (e.g. ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
   </span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global warming scenario</div>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After a spin-up of more than 10,000 years under pre-industrial atmospheric and astronomical boundary conditions, the model is run under historical conditions from year 1850 to 2000 using fossil-fuel and land-use carbon emissions as well as solar, volcanic and anthropogenic aerosol forcings. From year 2000 to 2100, the model is forced by CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions following the Special Report on Emissions A2 non-intervention scenario
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span> reaching maximum emissions of about 29 PgC/year in the year 2100. Thereafter, CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions decrease linearly to zero in year 2300. In this simulation, 2200 GtC are emitted until year 2100 and a total of 5100 GtC until year 2300. Model simulations are continued with zero CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions after year 2300 until year 8000.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
