<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Canada</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion of the area of managed forests varies among the ten provinces and three territories in Canada. Some provinces, including British Columbia, Alberta, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and Prince Edward Island consider all forest land as managed due to ongoing timber harvest, fire protection and conservation activities. In contrast, Saskatchewan, Manitoba, Ontario and Quebec delineate a northern border of managed forests based on the northern boundary of fire suppression. In these provinces, areas to the north of this boundary are considered unmanaged. The Province of Newfoundland and Labrador includes all forests on the island of Newfoundland as managed but limits managed forests in Labrador to those that are subject to ongoing or planned future timber harvest. Yukon and the Northwest Territories delineate managed forest as areas designated for timber harvesting and areas under fire protection surrounding communities. Nunavut does not contain any managed forest. The initial delineation of managed forests was based on GIS boundaries of forest management units used for timber supply planning, parks and fire protection zones.</p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Managed forest areas can occasionally change over time if management activities expand into areas currently considered unmanaged forests. Managed forest lands can only leave this category through land-use conversion. Once forests are considered managed, they remain in that reporting category. Unmanaged forests can become managed forests if forest road construction and timber extraction commence, or if they meet other managed forest criteria. Unmanaged forests are monitored through Canada’s comprehensive deforestation monitoring program to ensure that resource extraction (mining), road construction and reservoir flooding events, which cause conversion of forest to non-forest land uses, are identified and the resulting emissions reported in the National GHG Inventory [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The location and extent of cropland and grassland within a reporting unit is derived from remote sensing data [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Grassland is classified as managed within reporting units that have soil and climate conditions suitable for natural grassland and in which the Census of Agriculture identifies that agricultural activity is present [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. All other mapped grassland is considered unmanaged.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Atlas of Canada is used to determine the spatial extent of wetlands based on an inventory of wetlands, including those covered by forest at a national scale [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. The Canadian Sphagnum Peat Moss Association has provided a map showing the principal peat harvesting areas [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>] and an estimate of the wetland area managed for peat extraction in 2004 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Estimates of the area under peat extraction for previous and subsequent years are made by adjusting the 2004 value on the basis of peat production. Flooded lands are delineated based on (1) forest conversion mapping [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], (2) the Canadian Reservoir Database [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>], and (3) hydroelectric industry consultations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Emissions from reservoirs are reported only for the 10 years following impoundment, and all flooding events that have occurred since 1980 are considered managed wetlands.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Settlements are identified through remote sensing data and population density mapping using Census data. A combination of the two approaches is applied because remote sensing data may lead to misclassification of large areas of trees or grass within an urban boundary, while population density mapping may miss isolated areas of manufacturing, transportation or resource extraction. Delineation of the settlement area is accomplished using the boundaries of Statistics Canada’s ‘Populated Centers’ [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>] with populations over 30,000, which captures all major Canadian cities and represents 76% of Canada’s population. The total urban area for years prior to digital boundary availability was estimated using boundaries adjusted by manual editing of appropriate remote sensing data.
 </p>
</sec>
