<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Main text</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Use of managed land proxy</div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While most governments report net emissions from land use based on their national communications to the UNFCCC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>], only 19 countries have delineated managed and unmanaged land areas for their territory based on a review of the latest communications submitted by governments through 2015 and Common Reporting Format (CRF) tables submitted in 2018 (note: CRF tables are only submitted by Annex I parties to the convention) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). There are several reasons that may explain this situation. Approximately 85 out of the 195 member governments are developing economies and still use the Revised 1996 IPCC guidelines for reporting their emissions [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], which is in accordance with UNFCCC reporting requirements for developing countries. The revised 1996 IPCC guidelines pre-date the development of the managed land concept as a proxy to anthropogenic emissions and removals that was introduced in the 2003 IPCC Good Practice Guidance for Land Use, Land-Use Change and Forestry (LULUCF) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>], and incorporated into the 2006 IPCC Guidelines [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. The latter documents require full representation of land use in the country, with all land being subdivided into one of the following land-use categories: forest land, cropland, grassland, wetlands, settlements and other land. In addition, forest land, wetlands and grassland must be divided into managed and unmanaged sub-categories, and although there are no GHG reporting requirements for unmanaged lands, countries are encouraged to report their areas. As more developing countries adopt the 2006 IPCC guidelines or even start using the 2003 LULUCF guidance, a complete representation of land use will need to be developed, and countries will have to determine which portions of their territory meet their definition of managed land.
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Proportion of governments that use approach I, II or III methods for land representation, or have not included this information in their national communications (IPCC 2003, 2006) (
      <span class="bold">a</span>). The subset of governments reporting their approach for land representation that have delineated managed and unmanaged areas in their territories compared to the governments that consider all land as managed (
      <span class="bold">b</span>). Data extracted from the latest national communication to the UNFCCC as of 2015 and common reporting format tables submitted in 2018 (
      <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.unfccc.int" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.unfccc.int</span>)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2018_95_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another 97 countries have adopted the later guidance from the IPCC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>] that include a complete representation of land use, but have not provided information about their managed land base. It is not possible to determine the specific reasons for these decisions. Governments are not required to mention this concept in their national communication to the UNFCCC unless they have delineated a portion of the country as unmanaged, although application of the managed land proxy should be discussed based on IPCC Guidance [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Regardless, all governments using the later guidance from the IPCC are implicitly using the managed land proxy, and many of these governments may consider their entire territory as managed land.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Defining managed land</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the governments providing information about application of the managed land proxy to subdivide forest land, grassland and wetlands into managed and unmanaged land, several have classified managed land simply by considering some land uses as managed and others as unmanaged. For example, Australia and Belarus consider all forest land, grasslands and wetlands as managed, while land in the ‘other land’ category (e.g., rock outcrops, glaciers, barren areas) is considered unmanaged. New Zealand considers all grassland and forest land as managed, while wetlands are considered unmanaged. The Russian Federation, Ukraine and Peru use the same criteria as New Zealand, except that they have designated some forest land in reserves or natural forests as unmanaged.</p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some governments apply the managed land proxy with additional criteria, such as Canada, Brazil and the United States. Canada has subdivided grassland, forest land and wetlands into managed and unmanaged areas. Grassland is considered managed if used for grazing domestic livestock, designated as a national park or is used for an expressed purpose, such as a military base [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Canada considers wetlands in which human intervention has directly altered the water table level as managed, and there are two types: peatlands drained for peat extraction and flooded land associated with the creation of reservoirs. For reporting GHG emissions and removals, managed forests include all forest land that is subject to management for timber and non-timber resources as well as other ecological services. Therefore, managed land includes the timber harvest land base and other areas, including parks and reserved areas. Moreover, because fire suppression efforts in Canada also affect GHG emissions and removals, areas that are under intensive protection against natural disturbances, mostly fire, are considered managed forests even if there is no timber extraction or other non-timber forest use (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brazil defines all secondary forests and grasslands, planted forests, and forests subject to selective logging as managed land. Natural grasslands and natural forest land are considered unmanaged except in the following cases: [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>] legally created Conservation Unit areas in Federal and State Conservation Units (Except the Private Reserves of National Preservation, due to the lack of consistent information regarding management interventions), in accordance with the Ministry of the Environment and the National System of Nature Conservation Units; and [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>] legally demarcated Indigenous Lands, as per information from the National Indian Foundation (FUNAI). Managed wetlands include all reservoirs, which are created through human activity, while rivers and lakes are considered unmanaged. Other land is classified as unmanaged.
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The United States has taken yet another approach by focusing on direct intervention [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. The definition states “managed land occurs mostly in areas accessible to human activity and includes altering or maintaining the condition of the land to produce commercial or non-commercial products or services; to serve as transportation corridors or locations for buildings, landfills, or other developed areas for commercial or non-commercial purposes; to extract resources or facilitate acquisition of resources; or to provide social functions for personal, community or societal objectives where these areas are readily accessible to society” [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. The United States government has incorporated accessibility of the land as a criterion, and included specific functions in the definition.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implementation criteria and application to delineate managed land</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implementation criteria are specific rules that are used to delineate managed land. For most of the countries, the implementation criteria are based solely on the land use maps developed to support the national GHG inventory. Governments are typically considering a land-use category as completely managed or not managed based on these criteria. Brazil, Canada and the United States provide examples for delineating managed land that includes additional criteria, subdividing individual land uses into both managed and unmanaged areas. The sections below provide further detail on the criteria and implementation methods for each country.</p>
  <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Canada</div>
   <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion of the area of managed forests varies among the ten provinces and three territories in Canada. Some provinces, including British Columbia, Alberta, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and Prince Edward Island consider all forest land as managed due to ongoing timber harvest, fire protection and conservation activities. In contrast, Saskatchewan, Manitoba, Ontario and Quebec delineate a northern border of managed forests based on the northern boundary of fire suppression. In these provinces, areas to the north of this boundary are considered unmanaged. The Province of Newfoundland and Labrador includes all forests on the island of Newfoundland as managed but limits managed forests in Labrador to those that are subject to ongoing or planned future timber harvest. Yukon and the Northwest Territories delineate managed forest as areas designated for timber harvesting and areas under fire protection surrounding communities. Nunavut does not contain any managed forest. The initial delineation of managed forests was based on GIS boundaries of forest management units used for timber supply planning, parks and fire protection zones.</p>
   <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Managed forest areas can occasionally change over time if management activities expand into areas currently considered unmanaged forests. Managed forest lands can only leave this category through land-use conversion. Once forests are considered managed, they remain in that reporting category. Unmanaged forests can become managed forests if forest road construction and timber extraction commence, or if they meet other managed forest criteria. Unmanaged forests are monitored through Canada’s comprehensive deforestation monitoring program to ensure that resource extraction (mining), road construction and reservoir flooding events, which cause conversion of forest to non-forest land uses, are identified and the resulting emissions reported in the National GHG Inventory [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The location and extent of cropland and grassland within a reporting unit is derived from remote sensing data [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Grassland is classified as managed within reporting units that have soil and climate conditions suitable for natural grassland and in which the Census of Agriculture identifies that agricultural activity is present [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. All other mapped grassland is considered unmanaged.
   </p>
   <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Atlas of Canada is used to determine the spatial extent of wetlands based on an inventory of wetlands, including those covered by forest at a national scale [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. The Canadian Sphagnum Peat Moss Association has provided a map showing the principal peat harvesting areas [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>] and an estimate of the wetland area managed for peat extraction in 2004 [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Estimates of the area under peat extraction for previous and subsequent years are made by adjusting the 2004 value on the basis of peat production. Flooded lands are delineated based on (1) forest conversion mapping [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], (2) the Canadian Reservoir Database [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>], and (3) hydroelectric industry consultations [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Emissions from reservoirs are reported only for the 10 years following impoundment, and all flooding events that have occurred since 1980 are considered managed wetlands.
   </p>
   <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Settlements are identified through remote sensing data and population density mapping using Census data. A combination of the two approaches is applied because remote sensing data may lead to misclassification of large areas of trees or grass within an urban boundary, while population density mapping may miss isolated areas of manufacturing, transportation or resource extraction. Delineation of the settlement area is accomplished using the boundaries of Statistics Canada’s ‘Populated Centers’ [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>] with populations over 30,000, which captures all major Canadian cities and represents 76% of Canada’s population. The total urban area for years prior to digital boundary availability was estimated using boundaries adjusted by manual editing of appropriate remote sensing data.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brazil</div>
   <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brazil applies IPCC approach 3 methods for land representation, meaning that classification is spatially explicit (i.e., all land area is explicitly classified). The Brazilian government utilizes several criteria (i.e., information plans/layers) and datasets to determine the managed land base, including biome maps, municipal boundaries, native vegetation maps (phytophysiognomy), soil types and land use/cover maps from visual interpretation of Landsat-type satellite imagery. The integration of all these georeferenced layers generates uniquely defined polygons in a Geographic Information System (GIS) that cover the entire national territory. Specifically, each polygon belongs to a single biome, municipality, vegetation type, soil type, and land use/cover. The native forest land and native grassland that fall over legally created Conservation Units and/or demarcated Indigenous Land are included as part of the managed land database. From one inventory year to another, changes in land use/cover are identified, and a polygon in one inventory year may be split into several sub-polygons in the next inventory year, if the entire polygon does not remain in the same land use/cover category. All the native forest land and grassland that is part of the managed land base and is subject to land clearing during the period of inventory is re-classified as another land use category in the same period, even in the case that the land could be temporarily unstocked with trees in the case of forest land.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">United States</div>
   <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The United States has incorporated spatial data on specific anthropogenic functions to delineate the managed land base for the national GHG inventory [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. These functions are based on the following criteria. All forest lands with active fire protection and timber harvesting are considered managed. Other anthropogenic activities occur on forest lands, but are within areas already managed for timber harvest or fire protection, or are converted to another land use based on the activity or change in land cover. All grasslands are considered managed at a county scale if there are livestock in the county. Other grassland and forest land areas are considered managed if accessible based on the proximity to roads and other transportation corridors, and/or infrastructure. Wetlands are considered managed if the water level is artificially changed, or the wetlands are created by human activity. Protected lands maintained for recreational and conservation purposes are considered managed (managed by public and private organizations). Lands with active and/or past resource extraction are considered managed.
   </p>
   <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the implementation criteria provide a link between the definition and the specific data that are needed to delineate the managed land base. Criteria are implemented using remote sensing imagery that has been classified into land uses. Lands that are used for crop production or settlements are all assigned as managed using the National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) for the United States [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Active fire management is determined from maps of federal and state management plans from the National Atlas [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>] and Alaska Interagency Fire Management Council [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Forest lands managed for timber harvests are informed by county level estimates of timber products reported in the U.S. Forest Service Timber Products Output Reports database [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Lands maintained for recreational purposes are determined from analysis of the United States Protected Areas Database [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>] in which lands are classified as managed if there is suppression of natural disturbances or that are used for extractive or recreational purposes. Multiple data sources are used to delineate areas with active resource extraction, including the Alaska Oil and Gas Information System [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>], Alaska Resource Data File [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>], Active Mines and Mineral Processing Plants [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], and Coal Production and Preparation Report [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. A buffer of 3300 and 4000 m is applied around petroleum extraction and mine locations, respectively, to account for the footprint of operations and impacts of activities on the surrounding landscape. Accessibility is a criterion unique to the United States among these three countries, and is a key determinant of managed area in remote areas of Alaska. Accessibility is determined using a 10 km buffer surrounding road and train transportation networks with the ESRI Data and Maps product [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>], and a 10 km buffer surrounding settlements using the NLCD.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Managed land bases in Canada, Brazil and United States</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The managed forest land in Canada in 2015 includes 225.9 Mha (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and represents 81% of the total managed land base of the country [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. The total area of unmanaged forest in Canada is 118 Mha and all of this area is in northern regions of the country with limited or no access (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Canada also reported 45.1 Mha of cropland (16.1% of total managed land area) across 10 provinces and 6.6 Mha of managed grassland (2.4%) in Saskatchewan, Alberta and British Columbia. Settlements accounted for 0.9 Mha (0.3%) of the managed land base, and managed wetlands accounted for 0.5 Mha (0.02%). There are 512.4 Mha of unmanaged land in grasslands, wetlands and other lands, predominantly in northern Canada [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Managed and unmanaged land in Brazil, Canada and the United States (millions of hectares)</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Country</th>
       <th align="left">Managed land area</th>
       <th align="left">Unmanaged land area</th>
       <th align="left">Total land area</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Canada</td>
       <td align="left">279.0</td>
       <td align="left">630.4</td>
       <td align="left">909.4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Cropland</td>
       <td align="left">45.1</td>
       <td align="left">0.0</td>
       <td align="left">45.1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Grassland</td>
       <td align="left">6.6</td>
       <td align="left">Unknown
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left">Unknown
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Forest land</td>
       <td align="left">225.9</td>
       <td align="left">118.0</td>
       <td align="left">343.9</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Settlements</td>
       <td align="left">0.9</td>
       <td align="left">0.0</td>
       <td align="left">0.9</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Wetlands</td>
       <td align="left">0.5</td>
       <td align="left">Unknown
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left">Unknown
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Other lands</td>
       <td align="left">0.0</td>
       <td align="left">Unknown
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left">Unknown
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Brazil (observed)</td>
       <td align="left">499.4</td>
       <td align="left">316.1</td>
       <td align="left">815.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Cropland</td>
       <td align="left">68.5</td>
       <td align="left">0</td>
       <td align="left">68.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Grassland</td>
       <td align="left">188.3</td>
       <td align="left">41.1</td>
       <td align="left">229.4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Forest land</td>
       <td align="left">235.3</td>
       <td align="left">258.3</td>
       <td align="left">493.6</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Settlements</td>
       <td align="left">3.9</td>
       <td align="left">0</td>
       <td align="left">3.9</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Wetlands</td>
       <td align="left">3.4</td>
       <td align="left">16.1</td>
       <td align="left">19.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Other lands</td>
       <td align="left">0</td>
       <td align="left">0.6</td>
       <td align="left">0.6</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Cloud-covered areas</td>
       <td align="left" colspan="2"/>
       <td align="left">36.7</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">United States</td>
       <td align="left">890</td>
       <td align="left">46</td>
       <td align="left">936</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Cropland</td>
       <td align="left">159.2</td>
       <td align="left">0</td>
       <td align="left">159.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Grassland</td>
       <td align="left">320.6</td>
       <td align="left">25.8</td>
       <td align="left">346.4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Forest land</td>
       <td align="left">292.7</td>
       <td align="left">9.6</td>
       <td align="left">302.4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Settlements</td>
       <td align="left">50.6</td>
       <td align="left">0</td>
       <td align="left">50.6</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Wetlands</td>
       <td align="left">43.0</td>
       <td align="left">0</td>
       <td align="left">43.0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left"> Other lands</td>
       <td align="left">24.7</td>
       <td align="left">10.8</td>
       <td align="left">34.5</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>
      <span class="sup">a</span>The total area of unmanaged wetland, grassland and other land is 512.4 Mha, but these areas are not disaggregated into the individual categories
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Distribution of managed and unmanaged land in Canada. The light gray areas are unmanaged and the darker gray areas are managed</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2018_95_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brazil has approximately 500 million hectares of managed land and 316 million hectares of unmanaged land based on an analysis for 2010 (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. Brazil reports the net emissions for each one of its six biomes (Amazonia—AM; Cerrado—CE; Caatinga—CA; Mata Atlantica—MA; Pampa—PA; Pantanal—PT), with percent coverage of approximately 49, 24, 10, 13, 2 and 2% of the national territory (852, 187, 545 ha) respectively. In 2010, unmanaged native forest land corresponded to approximately 31% in AM; 30% in CE; 48% in CA; 16% in MA, 12% in PA and 54% in PT. Unmanaged native grassland corresponds to approximately 1, 13, 1, 2, 16 and 21% of the total territorial area of AM, CE, CA, MA, PA and PT, respectively. The percent coverage of other land (classified as unmanaged) in the total biome territorial area is near zero in all biomes except for PA, where it is approximately 1%.
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> shows the distribution of the Conservation Units and Indigenous lands (considered as part of the managed forest land) in the Brazilian territory, where their expansion from the periods 1994 to 2002 and 2002 to 2010 have been observed. The largest expansion occurs in the Amazonia biome, where most of the unmanaged forest land, grassland and wetlands also occurs (46.7%), followed by the Cerrado biome (27.9%). Approximately 36 million ha of land was cloud covered, corresponding to approximately 4% of the national territory [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>].
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Distribution of the Conservation Units and Indigenous Lands in the Brazilian territory, by biome, as represented in the Third National GHG Inventory for 2002 and 2010. Biomes include Amazonia (intermediate green), Caatinga (yellow), Cerrado (orange), Pantanal (brown), Mata Atlantica (darker green), and Pampa (light green). In black, managed areas in 1994; in medium grey (areas created between 1994 and 2002); and light grey (areas created between 2002 and 2010)</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2018_95_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total managed land base in the United States is 890 million hectares, and about 46 million hectares are unmanaged (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. Managed land includes the majority of the territory in the conterminous 48 states and Hawaii, where much of the land is actively managed for crop production, grazing livestock, timber production, or occurs within settlement areas. Moreover, the majority of the land in these regions is within a 10 km buffer of the road network, railroad corridors or settlements. There are large blocks of land in Alaska that are classified as unmanaged, which are grassland, forest land or wetland. These areas are largely inaccessible, which means that they are outside the 10 km buffer of road networks or other transportation corridors, and have no direct human management or function in which anthropogenic activities are influencing GHG emissions.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Distribution of managed and unmanaged land in the United States. The gray areas are unmanaged and the blue areas are managed</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13021_2018_95_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
