<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">United States</div>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The United States has incorporated spatial data on specific anthropogenic functions to delineate the managed land base for the national GHG inventory [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. These functions are based on the following criteria. All forest lands with active fire protection and timber harvesting are considered managed. Other anthropogenic activities occur on forest lands, but are within areas already managed for timber harvest or fire protection, or are converted to another land use based on the activity or change in land cover. All grasslands are considered managed at a county scale if there are livestock in the county. Other grassland and forest land areas are considered managed if accessible based on the proximity to roads and other transportation corridors, and/or infrastructure. Wetlands are considered managed if the water level is artificially changed, or the wetlands are created by human activity. Protected lands maintained for recreational and conservation purposes are considered managed (managed by public and private organizations). Lands with active and/or past resource extraction are considered managed.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the implementation criteria provide a link between the definition and the specific data that are needed to delineate the managed land base. Criteria are implemented using remote sensing imagery that has been classified into land uses. Lands that are used for crop production or settlements are all assigned as managed using the National Land Cover Dataset (NLCD) for the United States [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Active fire management is determined from maps of federal and state management plans from the National Atlas [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>] and Alaska Interagency Fire Management Council [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Forest lands managed for timber harvests are informed by county level estimates of timber products reported in the U.S. Forest Service Timber Products Output Reports database [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Lands maintained for recreational purposes are determined from analysis of the United States Protected Areas Database [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>] in which lands are classified as managed if there is suppression of natural disturbances or that are used for extractive or recreational purposes. Multiple data sources are used to delineate areas with active resource extraction, including the Alaska Oil and Gas Information System [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>], Alaska Resource Data File [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>], Active Mines and Mineral Processing Plants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], and Coal Production and Preparation Report [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. A buffer of 3300 and 4000 m is applied around petroleum extraction and mine locations, respectively, to account for the footprint of operations and impacts of activities on the surrounding landscape. Accessibility is a criterion unique to the United States among these three countries, and is a key determinant of managed area in remote areas of Alaska. Accessibility is determined using a 10 km buffer surrounding road and train transportation networks with the ESRI Data and Maps product [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>], and a 10 km buffer surrounding settlements using the NLCD.
 </p>
</sec>
