<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because isoprene is costly for leaves (20 ATP and 14 NADPH for each molecule of isoprene produced by CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fixation through photosynthesis) (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sharkey and Yeh, 2001</xref>) the great investment of leaves for Iso
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> under stressful conditions must have functional reasons (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sharkey and Monson, 2017</xref>). Isoprene may play multiple functions in countering the detrimental effects of supernumerary photons reaching the chloroplast, when the leaf ability to process radiant energy to carbon fixation is severely constrained by environmental stressors (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loreto and Schnitzler, 2010</xref>). Isoprene is effective in preserving the integrity of thylakoid membranes (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Velikova et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Populus × canescens</italic> lines where Iso
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> is suppressed displayed reduced photosynthetic electron transport rate (ETR) during heat stress, and did not recover photosynthesis at the level of the corresponding isoprene-emitting lines after relief from stress (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Behnke et al., 2007</xref>). The protective functions of isoprene on membrane-associated processes (also observed under ‘physiological’ conditions, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pollastri et al., 2014</xref>) may not depend simply on the hydrophobic interaction between isoprene and the lipid acyl chains of membranes (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Siwko et al., 2007</xref>), as isoprene concentration inside membranes is too low to effectively modulate their bulk lipid phase (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Harvey et al., 2015</xref>). Benefits for membrane stability associated to Iso
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> may also result from both the up-regulation of proteins associated with photosynthetic complexes (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Velikova et al., 2014</xref>) and the enhanced biosynthesis of relevant membrane components, such as mono- and di-galactosyl-diacyl glycerols and unsaturated fatty acids (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Velikova et al., 2015</xref>). In simpler terms, isoprene-induced improvement in the use of radiant energy to carbon fixation may reduce the risk of photo-oxidative stress in isoprene-emitting leaves. Protection of photosynthetic membranes may be induced by isoprene indirectly, as isoprene is also known to scavenge reactive oxygen species (ROS) (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loreto and Velikova, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Affek and Yakir, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Velikova et al., 2004</xref>). The antioxidant effect of isoprene is especially clear in the case of singlet oxygen (
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>), the most dangerous ROS in chloroplasts. This effect was empirically demonstrated by 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Velikova et al. (2004)</xref>, and has now been theoretically framed (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zeinali et al., 2016</xref>). ROS scavenging inside leaves explains the formation of isoprene oxidation products, mostly methyl-vinyl-ketone and methacrolein, in plants exposed to a wide range of stressors, especially heat, in both controlled (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jardine et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) and field conditions (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cappellin et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
