<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In many instances, Iso
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> increases under mild to moderate drought, but declines steeply when plants face severe drought (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brilli et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Centritto et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tattini et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Therefore, it has been hypothesized that isoprene plays a beneficial role only in response to mild stress, whereas non-volatile, more stable metabolites, produced through the same metabolic pathway of isoprene (the MEP pathway, i.e., carotenoids and abscisic acid), serve functions of greater significance when plants are challenged by severe stress. This is a revisited formulation of the “opportunistic hypothesis”, firstly postulated by 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Owen and Peñuelas (2005)</xref>. For example, in 
 <italic class="italic">Xerophyta humilis</italic>, Iso
 <sub class="sub">e</sub> ceased at 5% RWC, but zeaxanthin replaced isoprene to enhance membrane stability, thus allowing prompt chloroplast re-assembly upon re-watering of this resurrection plant (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beckett et al., 2012</xref>). Recent evidence suggests that isoprene may serve antioxidant functions (
 <italic class="italic">sensu lato</italic>) of increasing significance in plants concurrently challenged by drought and heat. Indeed, the activities of primary antioxidants, such as antioxidant enzymes, and the concentration of zeaxanthin may decrease in high light-exposed plants during the hottest hours of the day, whereas biosynthesis and emission of isoprene are promoted in the same conditions (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brunetti et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tattini et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
