<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The present study covered the entire coastal region of Bangladesh lying between 20°6′ N to 23°5′ N latitude and 88°5′ E to 92°6′ E longitude (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-04552-f002">Figure 2</xref>). It comprises 32% (47,201 km
 <sup>2</sup>) of the total geographical land area of Bangladesh [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and is home to about 40 million people in 19 administrative districts, where almost 80% of people are living in rural areas, and more than 70% of them are involved with agriculture-related activities [
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. This region is unique from ecological and economical points of view, containing a world heritage Sundarban mangrove forest (6017 sq. km), the world’s longest natural sea beach (120 km), coral islands, mountains, tidal estuaries, renewable and non-renewable energy resources, productive agricultural lands and marine resources [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The entire coastal region of Bangladesh is divided into three distinct zones: east coast, central coast, and west coast (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-04552-f002">Figure 2</xref>). The eastern coast is characterized by higher elevations and stable landmasses, and has experienced massive land-use changes; whereas the central coast is characterized by the Ganges-Brahmaputra floodplain, an active delta at a lower elevation, and has suffered massive erosion and accretion of sediments from the strong currents and tides. On the other hand, the west coast is a mature delta with large saline areas; it harbors a mangrove forest, yet experiences substantial anthropogenic pressures [
 <xref rid="B62-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The entire coastal region; however, is characterized by low-lying topography: 62% of the land is below 3 m elevation, and about 86% is below 5 m above average sea level [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
</p>
