<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Kappa statistic was used to measure agreement between the simulated and the observed frozen soil maps. The Kappa value of over 0.5, suggested that simulation in the baseline period agreed‒well with the frozen soil maps from Shi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> and Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. The area of simulated permafrost of 1.66 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> in the baseline period was larger than those from Shi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> and Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. Compared with the simulated permafrost area with result from Shi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>, differences primarily concentrated in the eastern QTP and the northern Gangdise and Himalaya mountains. There were differences in spatial distribution of permafrost between Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> and simulation in the baseline period, which could contribute to the discrepancy of permafrost area. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1c</xref> showed that the regions different from simulation were covered by seasonally frozen soil ground or non‒frozen soil ground. Therefore, the area of seasonally frozen soil ground or non‒frozen soil ground in Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> was significantly larger than those in the simulation. Moreover, these inconsistencies could be partly attributed to the relatively large grid size of the model and the climate data used as input in the baseline period. Climate data in the baseline period was interpolated to a resolution of 0.5° × 0.5° using a thin-plate smoothing spline algorithm with meteorological station data and latitude, longitude and elevation as independent variables. However, meteorological stations in the QTP are unevenly distributed with few observations in the northwestern QTP, which is a large permafrost region. Moreover, there are few representative observation stations in the eastern QTP because of its complex topography. The uneven distribution of meteorological stations may have affected the accuracy of the simulated results.
</p>
