<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The total area of simulated permafrost in the baseline period on the QTP is 1.66 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (including glaciers, lakes and rivers) which is larger than simulation (1.27 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) from Chang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> using the Surface Frozen Index model during the period 1986‒2005. Although the Surface Frozen Index model was used in the two studies, some differences still contributed to the area of inconsistency. Firstly, F
 <sub class="sub">+</sub> value of 0.58 was used by Chang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> to distinguish permafrost regions and seasonal frozen ground regions in order to match permafrost area with result from Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>, while 0.50 was used in this study. Based on Surface Frost Number model re‒drived from an explicit physical formula, Nan 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup> suggested that F value of 0.50 is more reasonable for distinguishing permafrost regions and seasonal frozen ground regions which should consider the effect of soil property on the freezing and thawing process. Secondly, different spatial resolution of permafrost distribution may contribute to the discrepancies. Moreover, the permafrost area in our study is also larger than the results from Guo 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> using the Community Land Model also over the period from 1981 to 2010. Differences may relate to the QTP boundaries, scale of the simulations and whether the simulation excludes glaciers and lakes. Further, Guo and Wang
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> used air temperature as input data and neglected the thermal conduction of snow cover. Studies by Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> and Zhang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup> resulted in areas of permafrost were 1.294 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> and 1.48 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, respectively. In both cases, an altitude model was used to predict permafrost distribution which only uses elevation as input data and this does not reflect the response of permafrost area to changes in temperature, snow, precipitation, solar radiation, and especially, the influence of snow cover. An altitude model cannot be used to predict future permafrost distribution. Furthermore, the resolution of the digital elevation model (DEM) was 30-second (latitude and longitude) in Li and Cheng
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> and 1 km in Zhang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>, which would also contribute to discrepancies with the results of the present study. Guo and Wang
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> indicated that a higher-resolution model might improve the simulation accuracy. As the objective of the present study was to produce projections of permafrost distribution and analyze the rate of change under different climate change scenarios, we used input data at a resolution of 0.5° × 0.5°. However, methods using higher-resolution climate data should be developed in the future to further improve simulation accuracies.
</p>
