<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0080" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we investigated whether among- and within-male variation in song production and performance characteristics in a subtropical population of white-browed sparrow weavers was predicted by their circulating levels of T, as would be predicted if natural variation in song production is achieved principally via variation in circulating T. Male song production and circulating T varied in a comparable way with timing in the breeding season, as has been reported for northern temperate species (
  <a rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0060">Foerster et al., 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0285">Van Duyse et al., 2003</a>), but in contrast to the seasonal decoupling of male dawn song and circulating T observed in an equatorial songbird (
  <a rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0225">Quispe et al., 2016</a>). However, dominant males were more likely to sing than subordinate males in all months of sampling and sang longer performances than their subordinates in paired within-group comparisons that rule out social environment and territory confounds, despite having comparable levels of circulating T to subordinates in both population-wide and again, in paired within-group comparisons. We also found no evidence that natural variation in the focal song performance characteristics of dominant males (performance duration, syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing) were predicted by their levels of circulating T in either among- or within-individual comparisons. Together these findings suggest that the natural variation in male song performance observed in this population is not achieved principally via variation in circulating T concentration.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results contrast with those from a previous study of a more northerly population of this subspecies in Zimbabwe, in which subordinates were never documented to sing and did show significantly lower levels of circulating T than dominants (
  <a rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0305">Voigt and Leitner, 2013</a>); though not in all studies (
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>). All of the findings to-date for this species are consistent with T playing a role in song 
  <span class="italic">acquisition</span> and 
  <span class="italic">seasonal onset</span> of song expression. First, circulating T concentrations and song production rise in tandem at the start of the breeding season (
  <a rid="f0015" ref-type="fig" href="#f0015">Fig. 3</a>, this paper). Second, experimentally-induced T elevations are sufficient to induce the production of male solo song by females (
  <a rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0305">Voigt and Leitner, 2013</a>). Third, subordinate males have lower circulating T levels than dominants in the population in which subordinates never produce song (the Zimbabwean population; 
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>) but comparable T levels to dominants in the population in which subordinates do produce song (our South African population; this study). However, our findings that (i) dominants exceeded subordinates in both the probability and duration of song despite having comparable levels of circulating T, and (ii) that natural variation in the circulating T levels of dominant males did not predict variation in any of the focal song metrics in either among- or within-male comparisons, are not consistent with the hypothesis that variation in circulating T concentration is the key regulator of 
  <span class="italic">within- and across-male variation</span> in song performance in this species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is conceivable, despite the weight of evidence from both among- and within-individual comparisons in the current study, that circulating T and song output actually are correlated in our study population and that this correlation was not detected because we could not catch males to sample circulating T actually while they were producing song. However, failure to detect such a correlation cannot be readily attributed to circadian variation in mean T levels between the time of song production and blood sampling, as we found no evidence of a systematic change in circulating T levels with sample timing while males were roosting overnight, and the circulating T levels of males sampled in the late evening were comparable to those of males sampled on the following dawn (prior to dawn song production). Consistent circadian variation in T was also not found in previous studies of this species (
  <a rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0325">Wingfield et al., 1991</a>, 
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>). Moreover, previous studies of other species have managed to identify positive correlations between circulating T and song production characteristics, despite time lags ranging from 24 h up to 14 days between song sampling and blood sampling (
  <a rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0060">Foerster et al., 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0075">Galeotti et al., 1997</a>, 
  <a rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0155">Johnsen, 1998</a>). Consequently, while it is difficult to rule out comprehensively a role for circulating T in regulating song output, our findings certainly suggest a need to consider additional and/or alternative mechanisms that may account for variation in song production.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is possible that the observed variation in male song production and performance characteristics in our population may be attributable to variation in other components of T-mediated endocrine pathways such as hormone receptor densities. There could be among-individual variation in the densities of T (and/or E2) receptors in relevant brain areas, leading to individual variation in sensitivity to circulating T and thus the effectiveness of circulating T in enhancing song production. For example, if dominant males had more numerous T receptors in the brain centres (HVC, RA) associated with song production this might account for their higher levels of song production despite comparable levels of circulating T. It is therefore notable that a previous study of the Zimbabwean population of this subspecies found that 
  <span class="italic">subordinate</span> males actually had higher mRNA expression levels for both androgen receptor (AR) and oestrogen receptor (ER) in their HVCs, than dominant males (despite no difference in HVC cell density between the classes), running counter to the rank-related pattern that might otherwise have been expected (
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>). Although, it is important to note that mRNA levels are not always strong predictors of final protein levels and receptor expression density (
  <a rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0105">Gygi et al., 1998</a>, 
  <a rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0225">Quispe et al., 2016</a>). Our within-male comparisons also failed to detect correlations between within-male changes in circulating T and within-male changes in song production characteristics over time, suggesting that reconciling our findings with a key role for circulating T would require one not only to invoke among-male differences in key components of endocrine pathways (such as T receptor levels), but also within-male changes in such components over time. Indeed, in equatorial silver-beaked tanagers (
  <span class="italic">Ramphocelus carbo</span>) seasonality in song expression appears to be associated with seasonality in androgen receptor expression in HVC, although within-individual changes in AR expression remain to be demonstrated (
  <a rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0225">Quispe et al., 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perhaps a more likely explanation for the absence of any relationship between circulating T and dominance status-related song production is that more complex mechanisms than a simple positive effect of circulating T underlie the regulation of male song behaviour in this species (
  <a rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0265">Soma et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0180">London et al., 2009</a>). Indeed, castration studies have demonstrated that a number of aspects of singing behaviour are not under control of circulating testosterone alone, for example in male European starlings non-courtship song does not appear to be regulated by testosterone while courtship song is (
  <a rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0215">Pinxten et al., 2002</a>). At least two key additional mechanisms could be at play. First, circulating T (and other circulating androgens) can be locally converted to oestrogen, by aromatase, which may then regulate the expression of song behaviour by binding to oestrogen receptors in the brain (
  <a rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0265">Soma et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0235">Remage-Healey et al., 2009</a>). Such an indirect mechanism of action by circulating T could explain our findings, if marked variation in aromatase expression and/or oestrogen reception existed both among and within males. Indeed, such a mechanism would also be consistent with the findings of the many experiments in which manipulating circulating T impacts song production in temperate birds (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>), because increasing circulating T would also be expected to alter local oestrogen concentrations within target cells if aromatase expression levels remained unchanged. Second, testosterone and other steroids are also locally synthesised in the brain, via neurosteroidogenesis, and so the actual concentration of a given steroid to which receptors are exposed may reflect a combination of steroids that originate both centrally and peripherally (
  <a rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0265">Soma et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0180">London et al., 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0230">Remage-Healey et al., 2010</a>). Together, a key role for these neuroendocrine mechanisms in the regulation of song production could readily account for the lack of an evident relationship between circulating T concentrations and song production in this and other studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As comparatively few studies (even of temperate species) have considered the role that these alternative neuroendocrine mechanisms may play in the regulation of song production (
  <a rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0260">Soma et al., 1999</a>, 
  <a rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0030">Cordes et al., 2014</a>), it is still too early to assess whether the endocrine or neuroendocrine basis for regulating the production of male song is conserved or divergent across songbird species worldwide. Nevertheless, it is notable that the experimental elevation of circulating T in non-temperate superb fairy wrens (
  <span class="italic">Malurus cyaneus</span>) did not result in greater song production relative to controls (
  <a rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0210">Peters, 2002</a>), a pattern that contrasts with the typical outcome of this manipulation in temperate birds (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). While both superb fairy wrens and white-browed sparrow weavers are cooperative breeders, it is more likely that the lack of response to circulating T manipulation in superb fairy wrens is due to latitudinal variation in the role of circulating T in relation to song production, given that white-browed sparrow weavers are cooperative breeders throughout their range, but circulating T varies with latitude in this species (see 
  <a rid="f0005" ref-type="fig" href="#f0005">Fig. 1</a>), providing a a potential system for more detailed latitudinal contrasts in future. However, on closer inspection, it is also notable that the evidence for relationships between natural song production and circulating T even in temperate species is mixed (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>), highlighting the possibility that the alternative neuroendocrine mechanisms outlined above could conceivably play a wider role in the regulation of song production even in temperate species than is currently widely appreciated. Future studies of song regulation in wild birds might therefore fruitfully combine both correlative analysis of the relationship between natural circulating T and song production with refined experimental manipulations, in an attempt to tease apart the relative contributions of central and peripheral sources of androgens and oestrogens to the regulation of male song production.
 </p>
</sec>
