<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0050" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does circulating T vary in relation to dominance status and timing during season?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A general linear mixed effects model (LMM) was used to investigate whether a male’s dominance status predicts his circulating T concentration. T values were square-root transformed for analysis. The time lag in minutes between capture onset and the end of blood sample collection was included as a possible covariate to control for any effect of this duration on T concentration (
  <a rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0055">Deviche et al., 2012</a>). The time elapsed between sunset on the day of sampling and the time of sample collection was also included as a covariate to account for the relative time of day of sample collection (exact times were not used due to the correlation between season day
  <span class="sup">2</span> and day length). The model included the fixed term ‘status’ (dominant/subordinate) and the random term ‘individual ID’ nested within ‘group ID’ as data in this model included repeated measures from dominant and subordinate males that were from the same group.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A paired within-group analysis was also conducted to examine whether dominance status predicts circulating T, using blood samples collected during the same night from the dominant and a subordinate male in each of 14 social groups (so as to control for variance in T levels arising from either the day or location of sampling).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A LMM was used to investigate whether subordinate male age predicts circulating T concentration. In most cases, male age (years) was assigned from known values of from the date of hatching to the date of sampling. In a sub-sample of cases, the hatching date was not known but the date of fledging was, therefore age was estimated by adding 30 days (the maximum duration for an individual to fledge) to the difference between fledging date and sampling date. Again, T values were square-root transformed for analysis and the significant effect of season day
  <span class="sup">2</span> was controlled for.
 </p>
</sec>
