<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0070" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does circulating T vary in relation to dominance status and timing during season?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was a significant quadratic relationship between season day and the circulating T concentrations of males (LMM: χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 22.30, n = 133 samples from 77 individuals, p &lt; 0.001; 
  <a rid="f0015" ref-type="fig" href="#f0015">Fig. 3</a>b); with circulating T concentration peaking halfway through the population-level breeding season. Across the population, there was no significant difference in the circulating T levels of dominant and subordinate males (χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.43, n = 133 samples (40 dominants and 38 subordinates), p = 0.51; 
  <a rid="f0015" ref-type="fig" href="#f0015">Fig. 3</a>b). None of the other terms included in the maximal model were statistically significant (dominance status × season day
  <span class="sup">2</span>: χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.11, p = 0.74; dominance status × season day: χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 1.08, p = 0.29; capture-collection lag: χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.12, p = 0.73; time of sample collection: χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 1.03, p = 0.31). The lack of significant difference in the circulating T levels of dominant and subordinate males still held when data collected during egg laying were excluded from the original dataset and the same model rerun with the reduced dataset (χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.81, n = 107 samples from 64 individuals, p = 0.36), while the significant quadratic relationship between season day and the circulating T concentrations also remained (χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 21.17, p &lt; 0.001). In addition, there was no significant difference between circulating T in relation to dominance status for the samples collected during egg laying (two sample 
  <span class="italic">t</span> test: t = 0.216, n = 26 samples (13 from 13 dominant individuals (mean = 1.18 ng/ml) and 13 from 12 subordinate individuals (mean = 1.13 ng/ml)), p = 0.83). Furthermore, a matched-pair comparison of dominant and subordinate males from the same social group sampled on the same day, outside of the within-group laying period, revealed no significant dominance-related difference in circulating T levels (paired 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test: t = −0.45, n = 14 pairs of males, p = 0.66, 
  <a rid="f0020" ref-type="fig" href="#f0020">Fig. 4</a>b).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was also no significant effect of subordinate male age (LMM: χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 0.0037, n = 61 samples from 38 individuals, p = 0.95) on circulating T concentration, while controlling for the significant quadratic effect of season day (χ
  <span class="sup">2</span>
  <sub>1</sub> = 12.18; p &lt; 0.001).
 </p>
</sec>
