<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="s0015" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This field study was conducted between October 2010 and April 2011 in the context of a long-term project monitoring a population of over 40 cooperatively breeding groups of white-browed sparrow weavers at the Tswalu Kalahari Reserve, South Africa (27°15′ S, 22°26′ E, elevation: 1195 m; see 
   <a rid="f0005" ref-type="fig" href="#f0005">Fig. 1</a> for species geographic range). All individuals in the population have unique colour-ring combinations for identification purposes (
   <a rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0110">Harrison et al., 2013a</a>, 
   <a rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0115">Harrison et al., 2013b</a>, 
   <a rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0345">York et al., 2014</a>). Males were identified during the dawn chorus using their ring combination and a black dye mark applied to feathers on the lower abdomens of dominant males during routine captures. Dye marks were used as an additional criterion to confirm individual identification, as the low light levels at dawn can reduce the reliability of colour-ring discrimination (
   <a rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0340">York, 2012</a>, 
   <a rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0345">York et al., 2014</a>). Male dominance status was assigned based on weekly assessments of behaviours following previous studies (
   <a rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0025">Collias and Collias, 1978</a>, 
   <a rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0120">Harrison et al., 2014</a>, 
   <a rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0040">Cram et al., 2015</a>) including the chasing and displacement of other males, and the duetting with and guarding of the dominant female (
   <a rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0110">Harrison et al., 2013a</a>, 
   <a rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0115">Harrison et al., 2013b</a>, 
   <a rid="b9000" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9000">York et al., 2016</a>, 
   <a rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0035">Cram et al., 2014</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0020" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male solo song observations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observation sessions began 2 h before sunrise, which is well before the earliest dawn song performance has been recorded to start in this population (
   <a rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0345">York et al., 2014</a>). The dawn solo song performance typically begins in the roost chamber and the male then emerges to continue singing around the territory from one or more song perches, until the performance ends shortly before sunrise. Performance “start time” was defined as the time at which the first notes of dawn song were produced, and performance “end time” as the time at which the last notes of dawn song were produced. Total “performance duration” was calculated as the difference between these times. Males were continuously observed from their performance start time (typically in the roost chamber) until they could be visually identified using their colour rings and feather dye mark and any occasions where male identity could not be confirmed were excluded from the analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0025" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Song file recordings and song analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recordings of pre-emergence song (song produced prior to the male’s emergence from his roost chamber) were made from within 10 m of the male, using a Sennheiser ME66 directional microphone with a K6 power module (2004 Sennheiser), and a Marantz PMD660 solid-state recorder (D&amp;M Holdings Inc.). Avisoft-SASLab Pro 5.1.16 (R. Specht, Berlin, Germany) was used to generate spectrograms (Hamming window, FFT of 1024 points, time resolution of 5.8 ms and 50% overlap). We focused our attention on song performance characteristics that previous studies have most commonly found to be impacted by the manipulation or blockade of circulating T (see 
   <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a> for examples). Male song has a variable structure that consists of syllables produced either alone or arranged in phrases (see 
   <a rid="f0010" ref-type="fig" href="#f0010">Fig. 2</a> for an example; 
   <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>). “Syllable rate” (number of syllables/min) and “proportion of time spent singing” (cumulative duration of syllables) were calculated for the 5-min sample period following the performance start time (during which time the male remained within his roost chamber). This sample period was selected as a standard time point during the song performance for contrasts within and between males, and because males were guaranteed to be stationary during this period, ensuring that the quality of recording files was consistent.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0030" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Capture and blood sampling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Captures were conducted at night, prior to the dawn chorus, whilst the males were in their roost chambers, by flushing them into a customised catching net (SAFRING license 1444). Males could not be caught at dawn as they were highly sensitive to disturbance immediately before and during song production. Therefore, to avoid effects of capture on our assessments of male song characteristics, males were captured for blood sampling on the night following their matched dawn song recording session. A blood sample was taken from the brachial vein with a 26 g needle (approx. 160 μl whole blood was collected). All samples were collected rapidly following capture (duration from initiation of capture to the end of sample collection: mean ± SD = 5.8 8 2.4 min) and the capture-to-bleed lag duration was never found to be significant in the analyses of circulating T (see Results), therefore it is unlikely that capture stress induced a rapid increase in testosterone that would influence our findings (
   <a rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0295">Van Hout et al., 2010</a>, 
   <a rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0055">Deviche et al., 2012</a>). Blood sample collection took place between 20:00 and 05:00; time of sampling (the time elapsed since sunset, to standardise for effects of seasonal variation in day length) was never found to be significant in the analyses of circulating T (see Results). Furthermore, there was no significant difference in T concentrations between a set of blood samples collected from dominant males on three evenings (21:00 – midnight; n = 9 males; T concentration mean ± SD = 0.90 8 0.64 ng/ml) and a set of samples collected on the three ensuing dawns before the dawn chorus (03:00–05:00, n = 10 males, T concentration mean ± SD 8 0.58 ± 0.28 ng/ml; Welch two sample 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-test: t = 1.35, p = 0.20). To allow paired comparisons of the T concentrations of dominant and subordinate males within the same group, blood samples were collected from both individuals on the same night. Whole blood samples were immediately separated in the field via centrifugation (12,000
   <span class="italic">g</span> for 3 min; Haematospin 1400; Hawksley Medical and Laboratory Equipment). The plasma was then drawn off and stored initially on ice (for 1–4 h), before being transferred to liquid nitrogen on return to the field base. The plasma samples were then shipped internationally on dry ice and stored at −80 °C until analysis five months later.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0035" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Testosterone analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">T was extracted from the plasma following a previously validated protocol (
   <a rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0090">Goerlich et al., 2009</a>). Briefly, the samples were extracted twice using diethyl-petroleum ether, 70:30 (vol/vol), snap-frozen, dried under a stream of nitrogen and then stored in a −20 °C freezer until a single assay was conducted for all samples. T concentration was then determined via a single coated tube competitive-binding radioimmunoassay (Orion Diagnostica, Spectria: 68628; detection limit: 0.02 ng/ml; cross-reactivity: 100% with testosterone, 4.5% with 5α-dihydrotestosterone, 0.007% with androstenedione). The average recovery rate (81.7%) for T was calculated by counts of tritiated T (20 μl), which was added to the initial plasma sample before the extraction step. All T values were adjusted for the recovery rate for the focal sample. Pooled samples were used to create dilution curves so that parallelism could be confirmed, all samples were analysed in a single assay, and the intra-assay coefficient of variation was 3.03%.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0040" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analyses were conducted using R 2.14.1 (R Development Core Team). Linear Mixed Models (
   <a rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0010">Bates et al., 2009</a>) started with a model including all of the fixed terms and interactions of interest (maximal model), followed by stepwise removal of each term in the order which resulted in the least significant change in deviance using a likelihood-ratio test for model comparison, until the minimal adequate model was found (when only significant terms remained; 
   <a rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0045">Crawley, 2007</a>). The significance of explanatory variables was determined by testing for the change in deviance in the fit of the model when the term was removed from the model. Repeated measures of groups and individuals were controlled for as required, by fitting group and individual identity as random terms, as detailed below. The residuals were checked for normality and homoscedasticity, and if they did not meet these assumptions the response terms were transformed to resolve this (see details below).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the five main models detailed below, each data point was attributed a ‘season day’, with season day 1 being October 1st 2010. Season day was fitted as both a quadratic (abbreviated to: season day
   <span class="sup">2</span>) and a linear (season day) term, to allow for the predicted curved relationship between the date during the season and the two response terms (circulating T and song production). Wherever season day
   <span class="sup">2</span> proved significant, both the quadratic and the linear term were retained in the model (
   <a rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0045">Crawley, 2007</a>).
  </p>
  <sec id="s0045" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.1</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does song production vary in relation to dominance status and timing during season?</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A generalised linear mixed model (GLMM) with binomial error was used to investigate the probability of dawn song production by dominant and subordinate males. On 216 mornings over the course of the breeding season (October to April), and at a total of 24 social groups that contained one or more adult subordinate males (&gt;1 year old) at the time of sampling, it was determined whether the dominant male sang (binomial response: 0 = did not sing; 1 = sang) and whether one or more subordinate males in the group sang (0 = did not sing; 1 = one or more sang). As such, the dataset for this analysis contained two lines per group per observation session, which were assigned a unique ‘session ID’ number; both ‘session ID’ and ‘group ID’ were included as random terms.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A paired analysis was also conducted to establish whether dominance status predicts dawn song performance duration. The performance durations of the dominant male and his singing subordinate male were calculated during the same dawn session (so as to control for variance in song production arising from either the day or location of sampling) for 10 social groups, where song performance duration was determined for both males.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s0050" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.2</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does circulating T vary in relation to dominance status and timing during season?</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A general linear mixed effects model (LMM) was used to investigate whether a male’s dominance status predicts his circulating T concentration. T values were square-root transformed for analysis. The time lag in minutes between capture onset and the end of blood sample collection was included as a possible covariate to control for any effect of this duration on T concentration (
    <a rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0055">Deviche et al., 2012</a>). The time elapsed between sunset on the day of sampling and the time of sample collection was also included as a covariate to account for the relative time of day of sample collection (exact times were not used due to the correlation between season day
    <span class="sup">2</span> and day length). The model included the fixed term ‘status’ (dominant/subordinate) and the random term ‘individual ID’ nested within ‘group ID’ as data in this model included repeated measures from dominant and subordinate males that were from the same group.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A paired within-group analysis was also conducted to examine whether dominance status predicts circulating T, using blood samples collected during the same night from the dominant and a subordinate male in each of 14 social groups (so as to control for variance in T levels arising from either the day or location of sampling).</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A LMM was used to investigate whether subordinate male age predicts circulating T concentration. In most cases, male age (years) was assigned from known values of from the date of hatching to the date of sampling. In a sub-sample of cases, the hatching date was not known but the date of fledging was, therefore age was estimated by adding 30 days (the maximum duration for an individual to fledge) to the difference between fledging date and sampling date. Again, T values were square-root transformed for analysis and the significant effect of season day
    <span class="sup">2</span> was controlled for.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s0055" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.3</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does circulating T predict song characteristics in dominant males?</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three LMMs were used to investigate whether a dominant male’s circulating T concentration predicts three performance characteristics of his solo song (performance duration, syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing). Syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing were square-root transformed prior to analysis. All measures of circulating T and dawn song performance characteristics were collected on the same day for a given male (dawn song in the morning, with capture for blood sampling on the ensuing night; see above). The models included the random term ‘individual ID’ to account for repeated measures of the same male.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above analyses were conducted to establish whether among-individual variation in T levels predicts among-individual variation in song performance characteristics. We therefore conducted a complementary set of analyses to establish specifically whether natural within-individual variation in circulating T predicts within-individual variation in song performance characteristics, using a sub-sample of nine dominant males for which two sessions of matched dawn song and T measures had been collected within a fortnight of each other in the at the mid-point of the population-level breeding season (the period between season day 100–150). We conducted two within-male analyses for each of the three song parameters (performance duration, syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing). First, we conducted a paired comparison to establish whether the focal song performance characteristic was significantly higher on the day when the male showed their higher T concentration (of the two T measures taken for that male on the different sampling days) than on the day when the male showed their lower T concentration. Second, we conducted a linear regression to investigate whether the within-male change in circulating T from their first to their second sampled day predicted the within-male change in the focal song performance characteristic from the first to the second day.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
