<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0040" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analyses were conducted using R 2.14.1 (R Development Core Team). Linear Mixed Models (
  <a rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0010">Bates et al., 2009</a>) started with a model including all of the fixed terms and interactions of interest (maximal model), followed by stepwise removal of each term in the order which resulted in the least significant change in deviance using a likelihood-ratio test for model comparison, until the minimal adequate model was found (when only significant terms remained; 
  <a rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0045">Crawley, 2007</a>). The significance of explanatory variables was determined by testing for the change in deviance in the fit of the model when the term was removed from the model. Repeated measures of groups and individuals were controlled for as required, by fitting group and individual identity as random terms, as detailed below. The residuals were checked for normality and homoscedasticity, and if they did not meet these assumptions the response terms were transformed to resolve this (see details below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the five main models detailed below, each data point was attributed a ‘season day’, with season day 1 being October 1st 2010. Season day was fitted as both a quadratic (abbreviated to: season day
  <span class="sup">2</span>) and a linear (season day) term, to allow for the predicted curved relationship between the date during the season and the two response terms (circulating T and song production). Wherever season day
  <span class="sup">2</span> proved significant, both the quadratic and the linear term were retained in the model (
  <a rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0045">Crawley, 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <sec id="s0045" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does song production vary in relation to dominance status and timing during season?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A generalised linear mixed model (GLMM) with binomial error was used to investigate the probability of dawn song production by dominant and subordinate males. On 216 mornings over the course of the breeding season (October to April), and at a total of 24 social groups that contained one or more adult subordinate males (&gt;1 year old) at the time of sampling, it was determined whether the dominant male sang (binomial response: 0 = did not sing; 1 = sang) and whether one or more subordinate males in the group sang (0 = did not sing; 1 = one or more sang). As such, the dataset for this analysis contained two lines per group per observation session, which were assigned a unique ‘session ID’ number; both ‘session ID’ and ‘group ID’ were included as random terms.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A paired analysis was also conducted to establish whether dominance status predicts dawn song performance duration. The performance durations of the dominant male and his singing subordinate male were calculated during the same dawn session (so as to control for variance in song production arising from either the day or location of sampling) for 10 social groups, where song performance duration was determined for both males.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0050" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does circulating T vary in relation to dominance status and timing during season?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A general linear mixed effects model (LMM) was used to investigate whether a male’s dominance status predicts his circulating T concentration. T values were square-root transformed for analysis. The time lag in minutes between capture onset and the end of blood sample collection was included as a possible covariate to control for any effect of this duration on T concentration (
   <a rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0055">Deviche et al., 2012</a>). The time elapsed between sunset on the day of sampling and the time of sample collection was also included as a covariate to account for the relative time of day of sample collection (exact times were not used due to the correlation between season day
   <span class="sup">2</span> and day length). The model included the fixed term ‘status’ (dominant/subordinate) and the random term ‘individual ID’ nested within ‘group ID’ as data in this model included repeated measures from dominant and subordinate males that were from the same group.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A paired within-group analysis was also conducted to examine whether dominance status predicts circulating T, using blood samples collected during the same night from the dominant and a subordinate male in each of 14 social groups (so as to control for variance in T levels arising from either the day or location of sampling).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A LMM was used to investigate whether subordinate male age predicts circulating T concentration. In most cases, male age (years) was assigned from known values of from the date of hatching to the date of sampling. In a sub-sample of cases, the hatching date was not known but the date of fledging was, therefore age was estimated by adding 30 days (the maximum duration for an individual to fledge) to the difference between fledging date and sampling date. Again, T values were square-root transformed for analysis and the significant effect of season day
   <span class="sup">2</span> was controlled for.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0055" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does circulating T predict song characteristics in dominant males?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three LMMs were used to investigate whether a dominant male’s circulating T concentration predicts three performance characteristics of his solo song (performance duration, syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing). Syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing were square-root transformed prior to analysis. All measures of circulating T and dawn song performance characteristics were collected on the same day for a given male (dawn song in the morning, with capture for blood sampling on the ensuing night; see above). The models included the random term ‘individual ID’ to account for repeated measures of the same male.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above analyses were conducted to establish whether among-individual variation in T levels predicts among-individual variation in song performance characteristics. We therefore conducted a complementary set of analyses to establish specifically whether natural within-individual variation in circulating T predicts within-individual variation in song performance characteristics, using a sub-sample of nine dominant males for which two sessions of matched dawn song and T measures had been collected within a fortnight of each other in the at the mid-point of the population-level breeding season (the period between season day 100–150). We conducted two within-male analyses for each of the three song parameters (performance duration, syllable rate and proportion of time spent singing). First, we conducted a paired comparison to establish whether the focal song performance characteristic was significantly higher on the day when the male showed their higher T concentration (of the two T measures taken for that male on the different sampling days) than on the day when the male showed their lower T concentration. Second, we conducted a linear regression to investigate whether the within-male change in circulating T from their first to their second sampled day predicted the within-male change in the focal song performance characteristic from the first to the second day.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
