<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male vertebrates produce a wide variety of sexually selected behaviours to repel rivals or attract mates and a central question in evolutionary endocrinology is whether the mechanisms that regulate the expression of such behaviours are conserved or divergent across species (
  <a rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0130">Hau, 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0135">Hau et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0140">Hau et al., 2010</a>). In particular, the circulating androgen testosterone (T) has been a key focus of research seeking to understand how male sexual signalling behaviours are regulated (
  <a rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0005">Ball, 1999</a>, 
  <a rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0065">Fusani, 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0085">Garamszegi et al., 2008</a>). While there is a weight of evidence supporting a fundamental role for circulating T in male sexual signalling behaviour, there has been a significant bias towards northern temperate zones in the species studied (
  <a rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0085">Garamszegi et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0095">Goymann et al., 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0135">Hau et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0335">Wingfield et al., 2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fundamental differences in life-history traits between temperate and tropical birds have long been recognised (
  <a rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0270">Stutchbury and Morton, 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b9005" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9005">Macedo and Machado, 2013</a>). Recent research also suggests that the underlying physiological mechanisms associated with life-history trade-offs exhibit similar latitudinal contrasts (
  <a rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0195">Martin et al., 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0080">Garamszegi et al., 2005</a>, 
  <a rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0205">Owen-Ashley et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0330">Wingfield et al., 2007</a>). Together, this evidence has led to the generalisation that birds in the tropics exhibit a slower ‘pace of life’ than their temperate counterparts (
  <a rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0315">Wikelski et al., 2003</a>) and indicates the importance of considering latitudinal contrasts when investigating the evolution of endocrine mechanisms in the context of life-history theory (
  <a rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0130">Hau, 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0140">Hau et al., 2010</a>). Despite their potential value, however, detailed empirical investigations of the role of circulating T in regulating investment in sexually selected behaviours remain rare for tropical species and rarer still from those inhabiting the subtropics (
  <a rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0135">Hau et al., 2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early studies of circulating T in tropical passerines revealed average circulating T concentrations an order of magnitude lower than those of temperate birds (
  <a rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0175">Levin and Wingfield, 1992</a>, 
  <a rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0130">Hau, 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0135">Hau et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0140">Hau et al., 2010</a>). Furthermore, circulating T levels remain low throughout the breeding season in many tropical species, whereas temperate species typically exhibit testosterone peaks during a brief breeding window (
  <a rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0175">Levin and Wingfield, 1992</a>, 
  <a rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0150">Hunt et al., 1995</a>, 
  <a rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0125">Hau et al., 2000</a>, 
  <a rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0315">Wikelski et al., 2003</a>); a limited number of within-species comparisons support this latitudinal pattern (
  <a rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0240">Rödl et al., 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0100">Goymann et al., 2006</a>, 
  <a rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0330">Wingfield et al., 2007</a>; but see: 
  <a rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0200">Moore et al., 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0245">Ryder et al., 2011</a>). While numerous potential ecological drivers of latitudinal patterns have been proposed (
  <a rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0020">Cardillo, 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0085">Garamszegi et al., 2008</a>), key among these with regard to circulating T may be the extent of seasonality in territorial behaviour and its implications for seasonal patterns of social instability (
  <a rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0150">Hunt et al., 1995</a>). Many temperate species are exposed to brief windows of intense intra-sexual conflict over access to mates and territory establishment, and circulating T is thought to play a key role in upregulating these behaviours (such as male song production and aggression) during these periods (
  <a rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0320">Wingfield, 2012</a>). By contrast, tropical and subtropical zones may include a higher proportion of year-round territorial species and this lifestyle may be associated with different seasonal patterns in circulating T (but see: 
  <a rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0245">Ryder et al., 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male bird song is one of the most extensively studied vertebrate sexual signalling systems, both in the laboratory and in ecologically relevant contexts, and therefore provides an excellent opportunity for latitudinal contrasts (
  <a rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0005">Ball, 1999</a>, 
  <a rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0015">Catchpole and Slater, 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0070">Gahr, 2014</a>). Correlative evidence from wild temperate birds indicates that population-level elevations in circulating T in spring are coincident with population-level elevated song expression (
  <a rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0060">Foerster et al., 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0285">Van Duyse et al., 2003</a>). Furthermore, experimental manipulations have revealed that artificially induced variation in circulating T levels can indeed influence the production of song by males in both laboratory and wild birds (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). Similarly, studies that experimentally inhibited T reception have largely shown the opposite effect of reducing song production (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). However, demonstrating that song production is altered by manipulating circulating T and/or T reception does not, in isolation, confirm that natural variation in song production is actually achieved in the wild through variation in the levels of circulating T, given that plausible alternative mechanisms exist (
  <a rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0265">Soma et al., 2008</a>). It is therefore important to also investigate whether natural within- and among-male variation in song production is predicted by natural variation in circulating T in wild populations. While rather fewer studies have investigated this association during breeding periods, there is some evidence of positive correlations between circulating T and song from wild populations of northern temperate birds (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>). There is, however, a conspicuous lack of similar studies investigating the link between circulating T and song production in wild populations of tropical and subtropical songbirds (
  <a rid="t0005" ref-type="table" href="#t0005">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigate whether natural variation in circulating T predicts natural variation in male solo song production in a subtropical population of wild white-browed sparrow weavers (
  <span class="italic">Plocepasser mahali)</span>; a year-round territorial songbird that is distributed across sub-Saharan Africa. White-browed sparrow weavers live in cooperatively breeding groups of 2–12 individuals, in which a dominant female entirely monopolises maternity, a dominant male largely monopolises paternity (12–18% of paternity is lost exclusively to extra-group dominant males), and subordinates of both sexes help to rear their young (
  <a rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0110">Harrison et al., 2013a</a>, 
  <a rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0115">Harrison et al., 2013b</a>). Males produce solo song at dawn during the breeding season almost exclusively at dawn (
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0340">York, 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0345">York et al., 2014</a>). Previous studies of this species suggest that the mean circulating T concentrations of males may vary in relation to latitude, as while very low mean circulating T concentrations were first reported in a tropical subspecies (
  <span class="italic">P. m. pectoralis</span>, Northern Zambia; 
  <a rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0325">Wingfield et al., 1991</a>), higher concentrations were found in a population of the more southerly subspecies (
  <span class="italic">P. m. mahali,</span> Southern Zimbabwe; 
  <a rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0305">Voigt and Leitner, 2013</a>). Studies of the latter sub-species suggest that circulating T does play a role in the development and initial expression of male solo song production, based on the stimulatory effect of experimentally induced T elevation in females (
  <a rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0305">Voigt and Leitner, 2013</a>), and have revealed pronounced dominance-related differences in male solo song production (subordinate males were not known to sing in the Zimbabwean population; 
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>). Whether these dominance-related differences in solo song production are associated with dominance-related differences in circulating T remains unclear, as dominance-related differences in T have been detected in the more northerly subspecies for which solo song studies are lacking (
  <a rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0325">Wingfield et al., 1991</a>) but were less clear in studies of the more southerly subspecies in which these song patterns were recorded (
  <a rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0305">Voigt and Leitner, 2013</a>, 
  <a rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0310">Voigt et al., 2007</a>). The matched sampling of T levels and solo song production is required to establish whether the marked among and within-individual variation in male song production in this species is indeed associated with natural variation in their circulating levels of T.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Specifically, we test three sets of predictions that would be made if male solo song production was regulated by variation in circulating T in a concentration-dependent manner. We do so using our subtropical South African study population of 
  <span class="italic">P. m. mahali</span>, which lies at a more southerly latitude than both the Zambian and Zimbabwean populations studied to date (see above). First, we investigate whether the circulating T levels and solo song production of dominant males show comparable patterns of temporal variation over the course of the breeding season (as has been reported in temperate birds; 
  <a rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#b0060">Foerster et al., 2002</a>). Second, we investigate whether dominant and subordinate males in this most-southerly population also differ in their solo song production characteristics and whether such differences are mirrored by dominance-related differences in circulating T. Third, we investigate whether natural variation in the circulating T levels of dominant males predicts natural variation in their solo song performance characteristics (performance duration, syllable rate and proportion time spent singing) using both among- and within-male contrasts.
 </p>
</sec>
