<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35" class="p">Digital geographic data for all PAs in the Atlantic Forest falling within IUCN categories I-IV
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122" class="xref">122</xref>
 </sup> were overlaid onto our grid cells. The 133 PAs comprised 711 cells entirely distributed in the biome. To assess the ability of PAs to effectively protect snake richness within the Atlantic Forest during climate change, we compared the current and future species distribution (given by our CONS model) with the disposition of the PAs. We did this performing two complementary analyses of PAs effectiveness based on null-modelling approach
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup>. The first one indicates how the spatial location of a given protected area determines if it will gain or lose species under different a climate change scenarios
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>. More specifically, we evaluated whether current locations of PAs are better than random allocations in protecting snake species under climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. For this, we generated a null model that considered the original size, form and orientation of protected areas but disregarded intrinsic effects (i.e. latitude and altitude) affecting their suitability in the face of climate change. The null model randomly allocated the protected areas in the Atlantic Forest and obtained species richness in the present and the future based on the projections of species distribution provided by the CONS model. Protected locations were randomized and repeated 1,000 times in order to obtain the average species richness for both climate scenarios. The second analysis demonstrated the effectiveness of the PAs network in protecting snakes by identifying the level of representativeness of species in the PAs at present and future times
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup>. For each species, the level of representativeness in the PAs network of Atlantic Forest was calculated as the mean percentage overlap (MPO), which corresponds to the mean percentage of spatial overlap between the units in which the species occurs in the studied area (10,359 grid cells in Atlantic Forest Hotspot) and the protected areas. For that, we firstly obtained the spatial overlap (%) of each cell of the study area with the polygons of PAs. So, we used null models to test if the level of MPO of each species was significantly different (lower or higher) than would be expected by chance, given its range size (e.g., the number of occupied cells in the Atlantic Forest Hotspot). The observed MPO value for a species was compared with MPO values obtained from 1,000 random species with an equivalent range size (i.e., the same number of cells in which the species occurs but extracted randomly from the entire study area). This comparison allowed us to identify if the representativeness of species within PAs given by MPO values is significantly higher and lower than would be expected by chance, considering a significance level of p &lt; 0.05. The two analyzes were developed in the R platform
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123" class="xref">123</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
